<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners Plenipotentiary,
                    Wednesday, February 19, 1919</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085246"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Occupied territory</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="american-revolutionary-war" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="american-revolutionary-war">American Revolution</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="15"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.00101/16</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners
                        Plenipotentiary, Wednesday, February 19, 1919</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-02-19">February 19, 1919</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Present: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">General Bliss</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. McNeir</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Herter</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>1. Mr. McNeir stated that yesterday Colonel Cloman representing the Financial
                    Section of the A. E. F. had come to him and had presented him with a bill of
                    over $500,000 for the service rendered by the Army in connection with the Peace
                    Commission. This bill covered every sort of expense from the complete cost of
                    the automobiles in use to the expense of the infirmary, and the commutation,
                    subsistence and salary of all officers including General Bliss. A letter was
                    attached to this bill from General Harts explaining its contents.</p>
                <p>General Bliss suggested that this bill be sent to Washington for the Secretary of
                    War to act on. All the Commissioners felt that it was a ridiculous charge to
                    make against the Commission …</p>
                <p>Mr. Lansing then suggested that Mr. McNeir should draft a telegram to the
                    Secretary of War which General Bliss agreed to sign, summarizing the items
                    included in the bill, and stating the great surprise which the Commissioners
                    felt at receiving such a bill sent to the Peace Commission. Mr. Lansing then
                    felt that a wireless message <pb facs="0090" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/> repeating
                    the above telegram should be sent to the President in order that he might take
                    up this matter with Secretary Baker upon his arrival in Washington. He noted
                    that the President was very anxious to keep down the expenses of the Peace
                    Commission, at least on paper.</p>
                <p>Mr. McNeir then asked whether special allotments for outside missions and
                    armistice expenses should be made in the mission’s funds. He stated that he had
                    before him a request for $15,000 for the American mission to Poland and one for
                    $10,000 for the armistice mission at Trèves. The Commissioners agreed to approve
                    $10,000 for the Commission to Poland, and to allot further funds to this
                    Commission if it was necessary at a later date. They also agreed that Mr. McNeir
                    should obtain further information from General Churchill regarding the necessity
                    of $10,000 for the armistice commission.</p>
                <p>Mr. McNeir stated that he had drawn $45,000 for Prof. Coolidge’s Commission to
                    Vienna on the understanding that it should come from the State Department
                    emergency fund and not from the Peace Commission’s allotment. Mr. Lansing stated
                    that Mr. McNeir’s understanding in this matter was correct, and that this matter
                    should be cleared up at once.</p>
                <p>Mr. McNeir left the meeting and Brigadier General Phillips (British) was then
                    called in. General Phillips declared that in a conversation with General Bliss
                    last night he had explained certain matters in regard to the Albania situation
                    which he desired to repeat to the Commissioners. General Wilson had agreed that
                    all information which he had should be put at the disposal of the American
                    Commissioners.</p>
                <p>General Phillips went on to explain that in his 7 years experience in Albania he
                    had had an opportunity of examining closely the question of the so called
                    Albania massacre by the Montenegrins and Serbians. Much literature had been
                    prepared on this subject but General Phillips was surprised to find that the
                    Albania claims which had been sent to the American Embassy at Rome had never
                    reached the Embassy.</p>
                <p>At the present time, the situation in Albania is extremely bad. It is not in need
                    of immediate food, but will shortly require organized <hi rend="italic"
                        >ravitaillement</hi>. In the mountains of Montenegro the people are
                    starving, but it is very difficult to feed them because of the great corruption
                    that exists and the hardships encountered in transporting the food. Both the
                    Montenegrins and the Serbians are doing all they can to hold the Buana, a purely
                    Albanian river, and to prevent the shipment of food supplies on this river.
                    General Phillips felt that it was extremely important that all ships going from
                    Scutari up this river should be made to pay a small tax in accordance with the
                    British toll system, and that in this way the shipping could be controlled.</p>
                <pb facs="0091" n="55" xml:id="pg_55"/>
                <p>When General Phillips was in command of the International forces in Albania in
                    1914 he had promised the Albanians autonomy. It was therefore with deep regret
                    that he learned of the pact of London of 1915 whereby Albania was split between
                    Serbia and Greece. He felt strongly that the Albanians, a people which were
                    purer than any others in Europe, with a higher sense of morality, a pure strain
                    and dauntless courage should be made autonomous, but should, until such a time
                    as they are able to establish a firm government, be under the protectorate of
                    some great power. General Phillips believed that Italy should be this power,
                    although he was conscious that the Albanians were hostile to the Italians
                    because they felt that Italy could not govern herself and could not successfully
                    withstand the Jugo-Slavs.</p>
                <p>General Phillips stated very strongly that in his opinion over half of the whole
                    Albanian question could be settled if only the Peace Conference would now
                    determine the boundaries of Albania, leaving to a later discussion the question
                    of the protecting power and their form of government.</p>
                <p>General Phillips then went into a short resume of Albanian history, explaining
                    how these people were made up of 5 great tribes whose history ran back 2500
                    years. They are Illyrians by heritage, speak Albanian only, and live by tribal
                    law. At different times 2 of these tribes had been given to Montenegro by
                    various of the great powers as a sop for favors rendered, and these gifts had
                    caused tremendous unrest and hatred in the souls of the Albanians.</p>
                <p>General Phillips declared that he was unable to understand the present policy of
                    France in Albania. The French Colonel in command was openly telling the people
                    that France was on the verge of war with Italy, whereas at the same time the
                    Italians were telling the Albania people the same story, likewise France had
                    told Albania that all her land would be restored to her which of course is a
                    statement most unfavorable to France’s Ally Serbia. Undoubtedly France wishes to
                    become the protector of Albania not because of any direct benefits to be derived
                    therefrom, but for the sake of weakening Italy’s prestige.</p>
                <p>In General Phillips’ opinion, if the Albania delegates who truly represent
                    Albania were allowed to come to Paris, much of the internal fighting would stop.
                    This has been the Albanians’ great weakness. Even in America where there are
                    200,000 Albanians, four distinct groups all opposed to each other have been
                    formed. Nevertheless, the people of Albania seem anxious to have a British or
                    preferably an American protectorate. Italy, however, both historically and
                    geographically is the most logical country for this purpose, and the Italians
                    would not encroach upon the Albanians because as settlers they never leave the
                    coast. If only Essad Pasha could be kept from Albania there is some chance of
                    unity being arrived at.</p>
                <pb facs="0092" n="56" xml:id="pg_56"/>
                <p>General Phillips felt very strongly that Albania had the right to know at once
                    what the future scope of her territories would be. He stated that he himself was
                    in a position to calm Albanians or to start them on a war-path against the
                    Montenegrins and Serbians by merely stating what the attitude of the Peace
                    Conference was in regard to their claims. The following districts, tribes or
                    towns of the north should be incorporated in the Albanian State: <table cols="3"
                        rend="width: 60%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="7">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Dulcino</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>(Town)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hoti-Gruda</cell>
                            <cell role="brace" rows="3">}</cell>
                            <cell rows="3">Tribes</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Gissinje</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Plava</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Ipec</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Djakova</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Prisrend</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>The most important was the district of Debra.</p>
                <p>Acting on the other questions in the Balkans, General Phillips explained that
                    Venizelos had included in his platform, which caused the exile of King
                    Constantine from Greece, the promise of the return of Constantinople to Greece.
                    He likewise stated that neither Montenegro or Serbia would ever be content until
                    they got Scutari, that likewise the Albanians would never rest quiet until the
                    flag which he had promised them in 1914 had been assured to them. Sixteen times
                    in all this country had been besieged.</p>
                <p>General Phillips ended his statement by declaring that the establishment of an
                    autonomous Albania would form a great bulwark between the Jugo-Slavs and the
                    East.</p>
                <p>2. Mr. Herter read a telegram received by Mr. Gompers from the Shipyard Workers
                    in the Northwest in regard to the spread of Bolshevism. The Commissioners
                    immediately asked whether this telegram had been sent to the President by Mr.
                    Gompers, and felt that if it had not it should be.</p>
                <p>3. Mr. Herter brought up the matter of loaning $60,000,000 to German-Austria, as
                    suggested to Mr. Grew by Mr. Strauss for the Commissioners’ consideration. The
                    Commissioners were unable to understand exactly how this loan would work out,
                    and therefore requested that they be allowed to speak to Mr. Strauss for about
                    five minutes during the meeting tomorrow morning.</p>
                <p>4. Mr. Herter translated a note to the Commissioners in regard to Mr.
                        Lasteyrie’s<note n="46" xml:id="d15fn46">Count Charles de Lasteyrie, French
                        financial expert and member of the secretariat of the Commission on
                        Reparation of Damage.</note> reply to Mr. Davis in respect to a mission into
                    Germany. The Commissioners felt that the excuse of the French in this matter was
                    very weak, and a letter should be immediately drafted to Mr. Loucheur to the
                    effect that no invitation had ever been received from the French to send
                    American representatives on the mission in <pb facs="0093" n="57" xml:id="pg_57"
                    /> question, and that further, the United States had never had an opportunity to
                    discuss with the other members of the associated governments a policy which, in
                    their opinion, resembles much the German policy of removing industrial machinery
                    from the occupied territory.</p>
                <p>Memorandum No. 88 was read regarding the belief of Messrs. McCormick, Baruch,
                    Davis, Lamont and Strauss that Messrs. Lamont and McFadden should go as Economic
                    representatives of the United States with the Permanent Armistice Commission at
                    Spa. The Commissioners were a little confused on this whole matter, and
                    requested that Mr. McCormick or Mr. Baruch come to one of their meetings to
                    explain it, bringing at the same time a copy of the resolutions of the Supreme
                    War Council authorizing the appointment of such Economic representatives to the
                    Armistice Commission.</p>
                <p>5. Memorandum No. 89 was read and it was decided that the Commissioners would be
                    glad to see the American Federation of Labor Mission on Saturday morning at 11
                    o’clock. They desired, however, that in the reply which was to be sent to Mr.
                    Gompers, it be stated that the Commissioners had other appointments at 11:30 and
                    would therefore be grateful if the Mission could arrive promptly.</p>
                <p>6. Memorandum No. 90 was brought up regarding the desire of the Sons of the
                    American Revolution to have the American Peace Mission present a wreath to be
                    placed on the monument of George Washington on February 22nd. The Commissioners
                    felt that they had hardly come to Paris for this purpose, and that as they would
                    have much business to do on Saturday morning, including the receiving of Mr.
                    Gompers and his party, they were afraid they would have to refuse. At the same
                    time they felt that this matter was one which came slightly within the
                    jurisdiction of the Embassy.</p>
                <p>7. Mr. Herter brought up the question of Lieut. Cobb’s assignment to the
                    Commission for duty with the American Delegates to the Reparation Commission.
                    The Commissioners were delighted at the thought that a good American interpreter
                    had been found, and approved highly the assignment of Lieut. Cobb to the
                    Commission.</p>
                <p>8. Memorandum No. 91 was read in regard to the President’s desire that rooms be
                    reserved in the Crillon for the personnel attached to him as indicated in that
                    memorandum. The Commissioners felt that at the time when these gentlemen
                    returned it would be well to have accommodations for them in the hotel, although
                    it was clearly stated that these accommodations need not be the same as those
                    which they occupied before their departure.</p>
                <p>The whole question of space in the hotel Crillon was discussed at some length,
                    and the Commissioners felt that aside from their own offices they would be glad
                    to have as many personnel living in the Crillon and as few offices as was
                    possible. They therefore hoped that Mr. Grew would maintain a very stiff
                    attitude in regard to requests <pb facs="0094" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/> for more
                    rooms that came from anyone except the Commissioners, and if possible to try and
                    persuade the technical advisors to have rooms elsewhere. They realize that it
                    would be very difficult to kick the technical advisors out at the present time,
                    but suggested that if any technical advisor asked for more space he should be
                    told that there is plenty of space available elsewhere in Paris and that the
                    Commissioners would be delighted if he go [<hi rend="italic">went?</hi>] out and
                    found it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Lansing inquired whether he might be informed as to Mr. Hoover’s status at
                    the present time. Whether it had been definitely agreed to allow Mr. Hoover [to]
                    keep his office in the Crillon. General Bliss observed that the Personnel
                    Committee would shortly begin its work of clearing out dead timber and that then
                    perhaps more space both for living quarters and for the absolutely necessary
                    office rooms would be found.</p>
                <p>9. Memorandum No. 92 was read containing the recommendation submitted by Mr. Beer
                    in regard to the treatment of Liberian [omission?] affairs was considered. These
                    recommendations were in general approved. The Commissioners felt that some of
                    them should [see?] Mr. Beer in order to have the whole matter explained, and it
                    was decided that Mr. White and General Bliss would do this.</p>
                <p>10. Memorandum No. 93 was considered in regard to the assignment of Captain
                    Lester W. Perrin to the Austro-Hungarian Commission. The Commissioners were
                    unable to see exactly how Captain Perrin’s previous experience fitted him for
                    work in regard to Austro-Hungarian affairs, but nevertheless were willing to
                    accept the recommendations of Dr. Mezes and Dr. Seymour in the premises. They
                    therefore approved of the assignment of Captain Perrin to the Commission.</p>
                <p>11. Memorandum No. 94 was read, requesting on behalf of Mr. Jerome D. Greene the
                    assignment of Lieut. Henry James to the Mission for duties in connection with
                    the Reparations Committee. The Commissioners approved the assignment of Lieut.
                    James for the purpose mentioned.</p>
                <p>12. Mr. Herter brought up the question of Mr. Jerome D. Greene’s acting as a head
                    of a Bureau or Department. The Commissioners approved that in his particular
                    case all would be well, and that they would trust him absolutely as far as the
                    organization of his Bureau went. At the same time they did not appear very
                    anxious to have him select assistants, secretaries, clerks, typists and
                    messengers who are to be put on the Commission pay-roll, without at least
                    putting through the formal request which even the Commissioners themselves have
                    to make. It was decided that Mr. Greene be informed that he will have complete
                    freedom in the ordering of supplies and matters of this sort, but that in the
                    matter of personnel, lie would have to conform to the regulations which every
                    other office has to follow.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
