<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners Plenipotentiary, Friday,
                    September 26th, at 10:30 a.m. and 3:30 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d155</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">155</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-09-26T04:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-09-26T09:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-09-26T09:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-09-26T04:30:00-05:00" n="155"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d155">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.00101/155</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners
                        Plenipotentiary, Friday, September 26th, at 10:30 a.m. and 3:30 p.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        from="1919-09-26T10:30:00+01:00" to="1919-09-26T15:30:00+01:00">September
                        26, 1919, 10:30 a.m. and 3:30 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Present: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">General Bliss</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Harrison</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I. General Bliss read a communication which he had received from the Military
                    Attaché at the Hague giving certain information <pb facs="0471" n="435"
                        xml:id="pg_435"/> obtained from a source not stated to the effect that
                    Germany was preparing to attack France in October, when a revolution was
                    expected to break out, and giving further detailed information regarding the
                    plot and the preparatory steps which had been and were now being taken by the
                    German military party to carry this out. <seg type="margin">German Attack on
                        France</seg>
                </p>
                <p>The Commissioners approved the suggestion that General Bliss should forward a
                    copy of the report in question to Major-General Allen commanding the U. S.
                    Forces of Occupation on the Rhine.</p>
                <p>II. General Bliss read a communication from Mr. Grew dated September 24th with
                    regard to the questions raised in the Department’s telegram No. 3184 of
                    September 20th, 4 p.m.,<note n="39" xml:id="d155fn39">
                        <ref target="frus1919Russia#pg_712">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1919, Russia, p.
                        712</ref>.</note> relative to the policy which should be followed by the
                    United States Government with regard to the further shipment of supplies and
                    food stuffs to Esthonia in view of the peace <hi rend="italic">pourparlers</hi>
                    now under way between representatives of the Esthonian Government and the
                    Bolsheviki. <seg type="margin">U. S. Attitude Toward Bolshevik-Esthonian Peace
                        Negotiations</seg>
                </p>
                <p>The Commissioners were not in a position to make reply to the inquiries contained
                    in the Department’s telegram under reference and were of the opinion that
                    inasmuch as the matter did not directly concern the Peace Conference it was a
                    matter for the attention of the Embassy.</p>
                <p>III. The Commissioners approved a further allotment to General Bandholtz<note
                        n="40" xml:id="d155fn40">Brigadier General Harry H. Bandholtz, American
                        member of the Interallied Military Mission to Hungary.</note> and directed
                    that he should be sent as soon as possible the sum of $6,000.00 to defray the
                    expenses of his Mission, any unexpended balance to be returned to Mr. McNeir.
                        <seg type="margin">Allotment for General Bandholtz</seg>
                </p>
                <p>IV. The Commissioners approved the release of Mr. Russell to be effective October
                    25th on the conditions stated in memorandum 571 of September 25th. <seg
                        type="margin">Release of Mr. Russell</seg>
                </p>
                <p>V. The Commissioners approved the recommendation as stated in Memorandum 572 of
                    September 25th that an additional allotment of $1000 be made to Lieutenant
                    Hynes. <seg type="margin">Allotment for Lieut. Hynes</seg>
                </p>
                <p>VI. In view of the contents of the Department’s telegram No. 3159 the
                    Commissioners approved in principle the discontinuance of the Press Bureau of
                    the Commission and authorized the Secretary General to wind up the Bureau unless
                    he should be satisfied that there were adequate reasons for its continuance.
                    Should the Bureau be closed, the Commissioners <pb facs="0472" n="436"
                        xml:id="pg_436"/> desired that a telegram be sent to the Department of State
                    requesting that the daily news telegram “For Grew from Emery” be enlarged. <seg
                        type="margin">Discontinuance of Press Bureau</seg>
                </p>
                <p>In this connection the Commissioners approved the recommendation contained in
                    Memorandum 573 dated September 26th regarding the release of Mr. Beryl and the
                    payment of his salary up to October 1st. It was understood that upon the
                    departure of Mr. Beryl the morning summaries of the French Press would be
                    prepared by Captain Gordon of Mr. Grew’s office.</p>
                <p>VII. The Secretary read an unnumbered dispatch dated September 13th from the
                    American Chargé d’Affaires at Sofia to the Commission regarding the systematic
                    violation of the armistice conditions with Bulgaria. (Memorandum 574 dated
                    September 24th.) <seg type="margin">Allied Violation of Bulgarian
                        Armistice</seg>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary also read a copy of dispatch No. 297 of August 27th from the
                    American Chargé d’Affaires at Sofia to the Secretary of State reporting the
                    departure of General Chrétien for Paris and also the attitude of his colleagues
                    and of the chiefs of the British, French and Italian military missions in Sofia
                    with regard to the policy heretofore pursued by the Conference vis-à-vis
                    Bulgaria.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
