<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-02-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-02-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="220" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d220">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Edward M. House Papers: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Commission to Negotiate
                                Peace</gloss> to President <persName type="to">Wilson</persName></hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-02-26">February 26, 1919</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>For President from House.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>George is desirous of arranging his engagements so that he can be in
                            Paris at a time most advantageous from your standpoint. He can either
                            come the later part of this week and remain here for about a week or can
                            be here on about March 14th and remain here for approximately ten days.
                            His Labor Committee is expected to report on March 20th but he can
                            probably put off receiving this report for five or six days at the most
                            provided he is engaged in Conference in Paris during that time. I
                            suggest that you authorize me to express to him your hope that he arrive
                            on March 14th and stay as long as practicable. Please cable me as soon
                            as possible respecting this matter.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Last Monday night Pichon and Klotz called on me. They were very much
                            disturbed over the French financial situation and stated that unless
                            England furnished France with some sterling exchange almost immediately
                            there would be a serious break in the price of the French franc with
                            disastrous results. They stated that the British Chancellor of the
                            Exchequer would come to Paris if he could see me <pb facs="0553" n="517" xml:id="pg_517"/> for a conference respecting this matter. I agreed
                            to see him at any time he came. On Thursday at noon Klotz, Tardieu and
                            other French Treasury officials called on me and asked me to intervene
                            at once with England so that France would be furnished immediately with
                            a few million pounds of sterling exchange to tide them over until the
                            Chancellor of the Exchequer could come to Paris for conference. I
                            promised to do what I could. I at once took steps to point out Lloyd
                            George the unfortunate effect which would be caused by French financial
                            difficulties at this time and I urged that some sterling exchange be
                            given the French to tide them over their difficulties. George directed
                            that this be done. Klotz expressed deep gratification of French Cabinet
                            for this assistance. British Chancellor of the Exchequer will come to
                            Paris early next week for conference.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Tardieu has submitted memorandum on French position respecting left
                            bank of Rhine. I will cable you about this fully when I have had an
                            opportunity of studying it.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer><hi rend="smallcaps">Am</hi>[<hi rend="smallcaps">erican</hi>] <hi rend="smallcaps">Mission</hi></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>