<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners Plenipotentiary, Monday,
                    February 3, 1919</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="3"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d3">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.00101/3</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners
                        Plenipotentiary, Monday, February 3, 1919</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-02-03">February 3, 1919</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Present: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">General Bliss</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Herter</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>1. Mr. Lansing asked General Bliss’ opinion at [<hi rend="italic">of?</hi>] the
                    advisability of requesting Mr. Polk to issue passports to the wives of such
                    officers attached to the Commission as the Secretary of War deemed it proper to
                    come to Paris at the present time. The cases of General Kernan <pb facs="0047"
                        n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/> and Major Scott as well as that of Admiral Benson
                    was discussed. General Bliss expressed the opinion that inasmuch as a ruling had
                    previously been made that the wives of officers in the A. E. F. in France should
                    not be allowed to come, it would be inadvisable to make an exception in the case
                    of those officers who were attached to the Commission because such action would
                    mitigate unfairly against the other officers who are now in France, and whose
                    work was just as hard and perhaps as important as those who are attached to the
                    Commission.</p>
                <p>Memorandum No. 8 dealing with this question was read and it was suggested that
                    perhaps General Bliss’ objections could be overcome by allowing those officers
                    attached to the Commission who wish to have their wives join them in Paris to
                    resign from the army and to remain attached to the Commission with the status of
                    volunteer civilians. This particular course of action was approved by Mr.
                    Lansing in the case of Major Scott because of the unusual circumstances
                    attending this case, but General Bliss believed that a general ruling in this
                    sense would be inadvisable as it would give an unfair advantage to those
                    officers who had independent means, and who would be able to resign their
                    commissions without suffering any material financial loss.</p>
                <p>It was decided that this whole question should not be settled at this moment but
                    that it should be taken under advisement by each of the Commissioners.</p>
                <p>2. Memorandum No. 20 regarding Mr. Whitlock’s<note n="13" xml:id="d3fn13">Brand
                        Whitlock, Minister to Belgium.</note> request for a reconsideration of the
                    decision that a military base of supplies should be established at Rotterdam,
                    rather than at Antwerp was read. Mr. Lansing was unable to see that there was
                    any political question involved, and that this was a military matter pure and
                    simple. Mr. White pointed out that there is considerable jealousy between
                    Holland and Belgium, and that undoubtedly either of the two countries would feel
                    slighted if the other had the American military base of supplies established
                    within its territories. He added that in Holland there was a feeling that
                    Belgium was being too much petted by America and that if the proposed change
                    were made this feeling would increase. Mr. Lansing stated that in his opinion,
                    if it were a question of favoring either Belgium or Holland in this particular
                    instance, he would prefer to favor Holland.</p>
                <p>General Bliss explained that the base of supplies was to be established at
                    Rotterdam for the purpose of feeding the American Army of Occupation in Germany,
                    that Rotterdam had been chosen not from any political motives but purely out of
                    expediency.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/>
                <p>It was decided that inasmuch as this matter was entirely one of expediency, no
                    change in the present plans of the American military authorities should be made,
                    and that Mr. Whitlock should be informed that the political considerations in
                    the premises were not of sufficient importance to justify a change of
                    policy.</p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>4. Mr. White stated that he had been asked to call this morning on the French
                    Minister of Commerce, and that he supposed that the question which the latter
                    wished to raise was that of the Chairmanship of the Committee to study the
                    nationalization of Ports, Waterways and Railways. Mr. White believed it possible
                    that the Minister of Commerce would wish to designate him as Chairman of this
                    Committee, and asked the opinion of the other Commissioners on this matter. He
                    was prepared, he stated, to do just as they thought best, but believed that
                    inasmuch as the United States had already been given the Chairmanship of several
                    other Committees, it might be advisable to refuse the offer in this case if it
                    were presented.</p>
                <p>Mr. Lansing observed that he had just been made Chairman on the Committee for the
                    responsibility of the war. General Bliss believed that representatives of the
                    United States were chosen to be the Chairmen of the various committees because
                    of the impartial attitude which the United States was able to maintain in most
                    of the questions dealt with. Mr. White asked whether the Commissioners would
                    approve of the nomination of Mr. Coromilas for the Chairmanship of the Committee
                    on Ports, Waterways and Railways. Mr. Lansing and General Bliss were afraid that
                    such a nomination might not be acceptable inasmuch as Greece had particular
                    interest in the questions which would be discussed. They both urged Mr. White
                    not to refuse the nomination if it were tendered to him.</p>
                <p>It was decided that Mr. White should accept the Chairmanship of the Committee to
                    study the nationalization of Ports, Waterways and Railways if it were tendered
                    to him.</p>
                <p>Mr. White observed that he had this morning discovered that Mr. Miller had been
                    assigned to his Committee as the second representative of the United States in
                    the place of Major Scott. Mr. Lansing explained that this change had been made
                    because Mr. Miller had been studying the question of the League of Nations, and
                    that the nationalization of Ports, Waterways and Railways was closely connected
                    with his other work.</p>
                <p>5. There was a brief discussion of the findings of the Committee appointed at
                    Saturday’s meeting to investigate the large personnel of the Peace Commission.
                    General Bliss expressed the opinion that the large number of military personnel
                    attached to the Commission should properly be detached, and if necessary,
                    continue its activities under the supervision of the War Department. Mr. Lansing
                    observed that the <pb facs="0049" n="13" xml:id="pg_13"/> whole question of
                    military intelligence did not interest him in the least.</p>
                <p>Mr. Lansing was called to a meeting at the Quai d’Orsay.</p>
                <p>6. Memorandum No. 22 recommending that Mr. Leon Dominian be attached to the
                    Commission for work on Turkish affairs was read. General Bliss requested that
                    this matter be left for later consideration by all the Commissioners. He
                    observed that as soon as the Committee on the investigation of the Commission
                    personnel had completed its work it would be better able to judge the merits of
                    requests for further assistance.</p>
                <p>7. Memorandum No. 23 was read and it was decided that Mr. Caldwell the American
                    Minister to Persia would be received by Mr. White as soon as an appointment
                    could be arranged.</p>
                <p>8. Mr. Herter read Memorandum No. 24 inquiring whether certain privileges could
                    be extended to Major Fling and Lieut. Yewdale who were engaged on behalf of the
                    War Department in writing a history of the war. The Commissioners present agreed
                    that these two officers should receive every facility from the personnel of the
                    Commission in collecting information, but that they should not be allowed to
                    occupy a room in the hotel or use the transportation facilities of the
                    Commission, nor have access to the plenary sessions of the Conference unless
                    they were admitted to the Press Section and unless their attendance at such
                    sessions did not preclude any one else from attending. The Commissioners present
                    however, requested that this matter be brought up again at a full meeting of the
                    Commissioners for final decision.</p>
                <p>9. Mr. Herter read Memorandum No. 25 regarding the expense of a mission
                    undertaken on behalf of General Churchill by Captain James Bruce and Mr. Ronald
                    Tree.</p>
                <p>The Commissioners decided to decline to pay the expense of Captain Bruce and his
                    party.</p>
                <p>10. Memorandum No. 27 was read inquiring whether the Commission should entitle
                    Mr. Baruch, Mr. McCormick and Mr. Davis to obtain supplies at the Commission’s
                    expense. It was decided that unless other appropriations were available to care
                    for the expense of the supplies of these three gentlemen they should be borne by
                    the Commission.</p>
                <p>11. Mr. Herter read Memorandum No. 28 inquiring whether the Commissioners would
                    approve the expenditure of 40 francs a day as subsistence allowance to the
                    officers of the Military Section of the American Commission to Negotiate
                    Peace.</p>
                <p>It was decided that the officers of the Military Section of the American Peace
                    Commission should not receive the subsistence allowance of 40 francs a day.</p>
                <p>12. Mr. Herter read Information Memorandum No. 29 containing report by Mr. Hugh
                    Gibson, who had just returned from the Hague, <pb facs="0050" n="14"
                        xml:id="pg_14"/> regarding the activities of Lieut. Voska and Mr.
                        Creel’s<note n="14" xml:id="d3fn14">George Creel, Chairman of the Committee
                        on Public Information.</note> utterances in Bohemia, Austria and Hungary.
                    The Commissioners took note of the information contained in the memorandum in
                    question, and expressed the desire to see Mr. Gibson as well as Major Schelling
                    at their meeting tomorrow. In the meanwhile, no action was to be taken in regard
                    to Lieut. Voska.</p>
                <p>13. Memorandum No. 4 of January 29, 1919 was read, regarding the assignment of
                    Mr. Joseph B. Umpleby to the Commission on behalf of the United States
                    Geological Survey.</p>
                <p>Mr. Umpleby’s assignment was approved, but General Bliss requested that for
                    personal reasons which he explained to Mr. White, he desired that in notifying
                    the Geological Survey of Mr. Umpleby’s assignment, it should be clearly stated
                    that until further advice no additional personnel from the Geological Survey
                    would be required by the Commission.</p>
                <p>14. Mr. Herter again brought up Memorandum No. 10 in regard to the assignment of
                    Lieut. Jefferson to assist Mr. Stratton, assistant to the cartographer, and
                    again the Commissioners requested that this question be postponed until the
                    investigation of the Committee upon which Mr. White and General Bliss were both
                    serving, had been completed.</p>
                <p>15. Memorandum No. 30 was read. The Commissioners present agreed that the members
                    of the Commission, other than the Commissioners, should not be allowed to charge
                    the expense of official guests to the Commission, but felt that this question
                    should be again brought up in the presence of all the Commissioners.</p>
                <p>16. Information Memorandum No. 31 was read and Mr. White made a note of the
                    opinions of the various factions in Russia in regard to the Prinkipo conference
                    in order to convey this information to the Press at this morning’s meeting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
