<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-04-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-04-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="44" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.00101/45</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners
                            Plenipotentiary, Thursday, April 3rd, 1919</hi></head>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1919-04-03">April 3, 1919</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <item>Present: <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">General Bliss</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Herter</hi></item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>1. Memorandum No. 203 was read with regard to the salary which should be
                        allowed to Lieut. Howe in payment for his services as the American
                        representative on the Inter-Allied Teschen Commission. The Commissioners
                        agreed that a salary of $3,000 per annum was not in the slightest degree
                        excessive. <seg type="margin">Salary of Lt. Howe</seg></p>
                    <p>2. Memorandum No. 204 was read with regard to certain measures which Col.
                        Olds, the Commissioner for Europe of the American Red Cross felt that it was
                        advisable to have taken with respect to the epidemic of Spotted Typhus which
                        is reported to be spreading in alarming proportions in certain districts of
                        Russia and Poland. The Commissioners believed that the President was not in
                        a position to make any transfer of medical supplies etc. from the Army to
                        the Red Cross, and thought that this could only be done either through
                        direct purchase by the Red Cross from the Liquidating Commission of the A.
                        E. F. or through some enactment of Congress. They request, however, that the
                        question be discussed with Mr. McNeir in order to ascertain the exact facts
                        in the premises. <seg type="margin">Typhus Epidemic in Russia and
                            Poland</seg></p>
                    <p>3. Memorandum No. 205 was read suggesting that four officers at present
                        attached to the Peace Commission be assigned to Messrs. King and Crane, whom
                        the President had appointed as the American representatives on an
                        Inter-Allied Committee to investigate conditions in those portions of Turkey
                        which are to be permanently separated from Turkey and put under the guidance
                        of Governments acting as Mandatories for the League of Nations. The
                        Commissioners agreed that it would undoubtedly be wise to assign the
                        officers in question to Messrs. King and Crane, but believed that the
                        Commission had no authority to do this unless the last named gentlemen
                        requested this extra assistance. It was therefore suggested that Messrs.
                        King and Crane be spoken to informally about this matter, and that if they
                        concurred in the advisability of being given expert assistance, they write a
                        letter to the Commissioners requesting it. <seg type="margin">Mission to
                            Turkey</seg></p>
                    <pb facs="0182" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/>
                    <p>Memorandum No. 190 was also considered in connection with the memorandum in
                        question, and the Commissioners agreed that if any party was to be assigned
                        to Messrs. King and Crane, it would be advisable to refrain from sending Mr.
                        Dominian as a member of this party. They thought that under these
                        circumstances, it would be best for Mr. Dominian to return to the State
                        Department at once where his services appear to be badly needed. They
                        likewise felt that the allotment of $18,500 which they had previously
                        approved should probably be put at the disposal of Messrs. King and
                        Crane.</p>
                    <p>4. Memorandum No. 206 was read to which was attached a suggested letter to
                        General Pershing in regard to the demobilization from the army of officers
                        attached to the Commission. The Commissioners were much pleased with the
                        letter in question, feeling that it exactly expressed their sentiments in
                        this matter. They suggested, however, that a clause be added to the letter
                        stating that because of their views as expressed therein, they were
                        enclosing the papers in the case of Major Thomas and Lieut. James without
                        comment, and for such action as General Pershing might see fit to take. <seg type="margin">Regarding Officers Being Demobilized in France</seg></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>