<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners Plenipotentiary, Thursday,
                    February 6, 1919</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d6</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">6</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-02-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-02-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="6"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d6">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.00101/6</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners
                        Plenipotentiary, Thursday, February 6, 1919</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-02-06">February 6, 1919</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Present: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Herter</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>1. Mr. Herter brought to the attention of the Commissioners the decision which
                    they had reached on February 4th,<note n="21" xml:id="d6fn21">See minute 8, <ref
                            target="#pg_16">p. 16</ref>.</note> in regard to the present
                    impossibility of rendering any assistance to Mr. Tredwell and Mr. Kalamatiano in
                    Russia, and then read a memorandum prepared by Dr. Lord suggesting that the
                    Bolsheviki be informed that <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The American Government demands the immediate restoration of Mr.
                            Tredwell;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>That it insists upon its demand of Dec. 7th with regard to Mr.
                            Kalamatiano;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>That its future attitude towards the Soviets, particularly in the
                            conference to which an invitation has been issued, must be materially
                            influenced by the reply made to the present demands. Failure to comply
                            with them could only be taken by us as an indication that the Soviets
                            were minded neither to maintain justice at home nor to respect the rules
                            of international law, and we should have to act accordingly.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Lansing observed that Dr. Lord’s suggestions were very good but that he did
                    not see how they could possibly be conveyed to the Bolsheviki. The invitation to
                    the Prinkipo conference had not been issued to the Bolsheviki alone, but to all
                    factions in Russia, and the government of the United States had never had any
                    official communications either directly or through a third power with the
                    Bolsheviki. Mr. Lansing observed, however, that it might be possible for the
                    American delegates to the Prinkipo conference to take up this question
                    informally with the representatives of the Soviet government, but that until
                    that moment nothing could be done.</p>
                <p>It was decided that no action should be taken at the present time in the cases of
                    Mr. Tredwell and Mr. Kalamatiano, but that this matter should be brought to the
                    attention of the American delegates who might be sent to the proposed Prinkipo
                    conference.</p>
                <pb facs="0057" n="21" xml:id="pg_21"/>
                <p>2. Memorandum No. 42 was read enclosing a draft of a telegram to the Department
                    of State at Washington regarding the granting of passports to the
                    representatives of the Department of Agriculture who desire to travel abroad,
                    and who may desire to enter the Central Empires before the final conclusion of
                    peace.</p>
                <p>The draft of telegram attached to Memorandum No. 42 was approved.</p>
                <p>3. Memorandum No. 43 was read, which again brought up the question of increasing
                    Mr. Sweetser’s salary as recommended in Memorandum No. 15 of January 31,
                        1919.<note n="22" xml:id="d6fn22">See meeting of February 1, minute 3, <ref
                            target="#pg_7">p. 7</ref>.</note> There was also read a note from Mr.
                    Ray Stannard Baker explaining in detail the necessity for increasing Mr.
                    Sweetser’s salary. Mr. Lansing observed that in view of the further explanations
                    which had been furnished in this matter he would be glad to see Mr. Sweetser’s
                    salary raised to a figure amounting to the equivalent of an army Captain’s
                    salary plus the 40 francs a day subsistence allowance which was allowed to
                    officers attached to the Commission. Mr. Herter undertook to determine the exact
                    figures involved.</p>
                <p>It was decided that Mr. Sweetser’s salary should be increased to the equivalent
                    of a Captain’s pay plus the equivalent of 40 francs per day.</p>
                <p>4. Mr. Herter read Information Memorandum No. 6 as well as several extracts from
                    the French press to indicate the attitude which that press was taking in regard
                    to the President’s speech in the Chamber of Deputies and the feelings of America
                    generally.</p>
                <p>Mr. Lansing and Mr. White while expressing their indignation at the comments of
                    the French press felt that it would be inadvisable to attempt any counteracting
                    influence at the present time, that it would be better merely to ignore the
                    whole question.</p>
                <p>5. Information Memorandum No. 7 was read indicating Mr. Horvath’s point of view
                    with regard to concluding an armistice with the Bolsheviks. Mr. Lansing stated
                    that he agreed heartily with the opinion expressed that the Bolsheviks would
                    undoubtedly violate the terms of any truce.</p>
                <p>6. Memorandum No. 8 was read in regard to the views expressed in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Nichi Nichi</hi> on Japanese claims. Mr. Lansing observed that
                    the attitude of the Japanese was extremely disquieting, particularly in its
                    relation to China, and that he felt that this was the time for us to have it out
                    once and for all with Japan. Mr. White added that the Japanese had undoubtedly
                    viewed with great apprehension our tremendous war preparations during the
                    present war and of course if it came to a direct issue between us Japan would be
                    in a greatly inferior position because of her relatively inferior economic and
                    financial strength. Mr. Lansing stated that this was absolutely true. He also
                    stated that it was America’s duty to support China.</p>
                <pb facs="0058" n="22" xml:id="pg_22"/>
                <p>7. Mr. Herter brought up again the question of Messrs. McCormick, Davis and
                    Baruch receiving the [minutes of the] secret meetings of the conferences at the
                    Quai d’Orsay, and stating that considerable ill feeling was being aroused at the
                    fact of their not being allowed to receive these minutes. Mr. Lansing stated
                    that the reason why the Commissioners had decided not to deliver a copy of these
                    minutes to the gentlemen in question was not because of any mistrust or because
                    of any desire that these gentlemen should not see them, but because it was
                    considered inadvisable to distribute more copies than was absolutely necessary.
                    He added however, that he had seen Mr. McCormick on this point last night. He
                    proposed that a compromise should be reached by allowing Messrs. McCormick,
                    Davis and Baruch to have one copy for their use, but that it should be specified
                    that this copy should not leave the hotel and should be definitely charged to
                    some responsible person in their office.</p>
                <p>It was decided that one copy of the [minutes of the] secret meetings of the
                    conference at the Quai d’Orsay should be distributed to one competent person in
                    the office of either Mr. Davis, Mr. Baruch or Mr. McCormick and that this one
                    copy should serve for the information of all three of these gentlemen.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
