<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-05-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-05-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="67" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.00101/68</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners
                            Plenipotentiary, Saturday, May 10, 1919</hi></head>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1919-05-10">May 10, 1919</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <item>Present: <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">General Bliss</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Herter</hi></item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Memorandum No. 269 was read in regard to the transportation to the
                            United States of members of the Commission. The Commissioners felt that
                            it would be inadvisable for the Commission to request any special favors
                            in this respect from the Army other than those which would permit of
                            members of the Commission sailing on transports when there happens to be
                            room available for them on such transports. They agreed, however, that
                            any arrangements which could be made with commercial liners to
                            facilitate the return of members of the Commission to the United States
                            would be most acceptable and absolutely permissible. <seg type="margin">Sailing Arrangements for Members of the Commission Returning to U.
                                S.</seg></item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Information Memorandum which stated that the President had no
                            authority to donate his funds to the American Red Cross to be used in
                            giving supplies of food and clothing to the Prisoners of War in Siberia
                            was noted by the Commissioners. <seg type="margin">Use of President’s
                                Fund by Red Cross</seg></item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Memorandum No. 271 in which Mr. Justin H. Moore, acting Chief of
                            Division of Foreign Relations and Government in the American
                            Expeditionary Force University inquired whether it would be possible for
                            certain members of the Commission to lecture at the A. E. F. University
                            was considered by the Commissioners. They approved highly of this being
                            done as an educational matter and requested that the Commission
                            facilitate this work as much as possible. <seg type="margin">Members of
                                Commission Lecturing at A. E. F. University</seg></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>