<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners Plenipotentiary, Saturday,
                    May 31, 1919</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.00101/78</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners
                        Plenipotentiary, Saturday, May 31, 1919</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-05-31">May 31, 1919</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Present: <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Lansing</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gen. Bliss</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Herter</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 309 regarding the release of Lieut. Allen, U. S. N. by the
                        Commission was read and approved. <seg type="margin">Release of Lt.
                            Allen</seg>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 310 was read regarding the assignment of Mr. W. W. Thayer
                        to the Commission to assist Mr. Vance McCormick in connection with the
                        blockade and other work of the Commission and particularly to handle some of
                        the work formerly cared for by Mr. J. F. Dulles. The Commissioners inquired,
                        whether, in view of recent information which had reached them to the effect
                        that Mr. Dulles was to remain with the Commission, Mr. McCormick would still
                        require the services of Mr. Thayer. Upon receiving this information they
                        stated their willingness to reconsider this memorandum. <seg type="margin"
                            >Assignment of Mr. W. W. Thayer</seg>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 311 was read inquiring whether the Commissioners desired to
                        take steps to have a passport issued to the wife and two children of Dr. J.
                        T. Shotwell, who at the moment is a member of the Commission and intends to
                        remain in Europe for the coming year. The Commissioners stated that they
                        were unable to take any action in this matter without the approval of the
                        President and requested, therefore, that a letter be drafted to the latter
                        putting the case in as strong a light as possible and adding that his
                        colleagues on the Commission were in favor of granting the necessary
                        permission. <seg type="margin">Request for Passport for Wife and Children of
                            Dr. J. T. Shotwell</seg>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 312 was read inquiring whether the Commissioners approved
                        of Mr. A. W. Dulles seeing Slatin Pasha of the Austrian Delegation who had
                        asked for such an interview. Mr. Lansing stated that he had already told Mr.
                        Dulles that in his opinion this would be inadvisable and the Commissioners
                        concurred in Mr. Lansing’s action in the matter. <seg type="margin">Request
                            for Permission for Mr. A. W. Dulles To Interview Slatin Pasha of
                            Austrian Peace Delegation</seg>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 313 was read with regard to the action which should be
                        taken in respect to an attack, that had appeared in a newspaper published in
                        Naples, on Miss Margaret Wilson. The Commissioners concurred in the action
                        suggested by Mr. Grew to the effect that a letter should be sent <pb
                            facs="0231" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/> to the American Consul General at
                        Genoa stating that the Commission felt that the case should be left to the
                        discretion of the American Ambassador at Rome. <seg type="margin">Italian
                            Newspaper Attack on Miss M. Wilson</seg>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 314 was read in which Dr. Lord recommended that an American
                        Mission of investigation should be sent to Poland and Roumania to
                        investigate the actual facts in connection with alleged Pogroms in those
                        countries. The Commissioners felt that it would be unnecessary to have a
                        special American Mission of Investigation sent out for this purpose, but
                        requested that complete instructions be sent to the American Ministers at
                        Bucharest and Prague to investigate and submit a report as soon as possible
                        to the Commission and State Department. <seg type="margin">Suggested Mission
                            To Investigate Programs Alleged To Have Taken Place in Poland and
                            Roumania</seg>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 315 was read submitting a report by the American
                        Vice-Consul at Geneva on the activities of Dr. Herron in Switzerland. The
                        Commissioners felt that a copy of this report should be sent to the
                        President for his information, and that instructions should be sent to the
                        Legation at Berne to issue such statements as might be necessary to
                        counter-act the belief that Dr. Herron is in any way connected with the
                        Peace Commission. Mr. White also offered to send a line to Mr. Balfour
                        notifying him that Dr. Herron has no connection with the Commission. <seg
                            type="margin">Activities of Dr. Herron in Switzerland</seg>
                    </item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 307 regarding the increase in salary of Sgt. Major Toren
                        and Pvt. Lambing and which had been taken up on May 29th was again
                        considered in connection with Memorandum No. 267 regarding increases to
                        other members of Mr. Crane’s and Dr. King’s Mission. The Commissioners felt
                        that they would be unable to approve of the increases suggested on behalf of
                        Sgt. Major Toren and Pvt. Lambing, but suggested that any extra expenses
                        that might have to be borne by these two men in connection with personal
                        outfit, etc., for their trip should be considered by the Commission as
                        necessary expenses of the Mission to be covered by the $10,000.00
                        appropriation previously granted. <seg type="margin">Increases in Salary for
                            Sgt. Major Toren and Pvt. Lambing</seg>
                    </item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Memorandum No. 308 regarding the assignment of Lieut. Linton B. Swift to
                        the Mission was reconsidered by the Commissioners and in view of the fact
                        that Mr. James Brown Scott had approved of the assignment in question the
                        Commissioners authorized it. <seg type="margin">Assignment of Lieut. Linton
                            B. Swift</seg>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
