<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>109. Memorandum From the Secretary of Defense (Wilson) to the Executive
                    Secretary of the National Security Council () to the Executive Secretary of the
                    National Security Council (Lay))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-02-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-02-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="rec626bb089a1004d2" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">Atomic
                        weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-policy" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-policy"
                        >National Security Policy</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="recMrVNgNJpQ8DjcR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037301"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deterrence</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-02-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-02-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="109"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d109">
                <head>109. Memorandum From the Secretary of Defense (<persName corresp="#p_WCE1"
                        type="from">Wilson</persName>) to the Executive Secretary of the National
                    Security Council (<persName corresp="#p_LJSJ1" type="to">Lay</persName>)<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d109fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss
                            target="#t_PPS1">PPS</gloss> Files: Lot 67 D 548, Military and Naval
                        Policy. Top Secret. Attached to a memorandum from <persName
                            corresp="#p_GSE1">Gleason</persName> to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss>, dated March 1, not printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1957-02-25">February 25, 1957</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Basic Military Planning Concept to Govern Planning and Development of the
                        Mobilization Base</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1503–b noted the President’s
                        request that the Secretary of Defense together with the Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff make a thorough analysis and report on the basic military planning
                        concept which should govern the planning and development of the mobilization
                            base.<note n="2" xml:id="d109fn2">Regarding <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss> Action No. 1503, see <ref target="#d52fn5">footnote 5,
                                Document 52</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I believe that the new strategic concept (Appendix A), prepared by the
                        Joint Chiefs of Staff and approved by me, provides the basic military
                        planning concept which should govern the planning and development of the
                        U.S. mobilization base. This strategic concept provides for two military
                        eventualities: (a) cold war or military conflict short of general war and
                        (b) general war, initiated with an atomic <pb facs="0444" n="420"
                            xml:id="pg_420"/> onslaught by the Soviets or as a result of hostilities
                        which were not initially intended to lead to general war. The U.S.
                        mobilization base must be fully responsive to these eventualities.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The introduction of atomic weapons into the military arsenal, and the
                        change which these weapons have made in our strategic concepts of war,
                        dictate a change in logistic planning. In the past, emphasis has been placed
                        on the capability of our industrial facilities to expand for support of our
                        forces in time of war. Our capability of expanding our industrial
                        capabilities was, in fact, an essential element in our U.S. mobilization
                        base. Our experience in past wars made it possible for us to forecast
                        military requirements over an extended period. We were able to economize in
                        times of peace by producing and stockpiling only those military supplies
                        which would be required in war before industrial production could meet the
                        demand. Our time and space advantages were the keys which permitted this
                        type of mobilization planning.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The present concept concerning the initiation of a general war by a
                        surprise atomic attack eliminates, for all practical purposes, the effect of
                        our previous time and space advantages from mobilization planning. Our
                        concept of the U.S. mobilization base, as related to potential industrial
                        expansion after war commences, must be brought into agreement with this
                        particular aspect of the strategic concept. Pre-D-day planning for
                        mobilization will improve our capabilities to conduct general war. Our U.S.
                        mobilization base should continue to provide for possible peripheral wars
                        both with and without direct participation by U.S. forces. We must develop
                        logistic objectives that are in consonance with our concepts of general war
                        which will restore to the maximum the advantage previously afforded by time
                        and space factors of our geography.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In consonance with our strategic concept (Appendix A) and Basic National
                        Security Policy, the U.S. mobilization base should at this time be so
                        planned and developed that for both general war and conflict short of
                        general war it will: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Maintain the active forces in a condition of optimum readiness to
                                execute initial wartime missions.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Maintain and support selected reserve forces in a condition of
                                high readiness.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Maintain and support the phased expansion to the M + 6 months
                                force levels.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Have the capacity to meet the combat requirements of all forces
                                which would be mobilized by M+6 months.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>Provide pre-D-day stocks of selected supplies and equipment
                                outside the United States reasonably protected to insure that those
                                forces surviving the enemy atomic attack will have a reasonable
                                capability of performing assigned initial tasks effectively despite
                                substantial interruption of resupply from the United States during
                                the initial phase of war.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="0445" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>In summary the U.S. mobilization base should be predicated on a military
                            planning concept for meeting two distinctively different mobilization
                            problems: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Conflict without damage to the U.S. production base.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Conflict characterized by atomic attack on the U.S.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Therefore, mobilization planning must be designed to
                            meet the different eventualities outlined above with emphasis on those
                            elements that will increase our D-day readiness and capability.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Your attention is invited to the fact that, for military planning
                        purposes, the strategic concept provides that in military operations short
                        of general war atomic weapons will be used when required in order to achieve
                        military objectives (Appendix A—para. 2–f, page 8). It is understood, of
                        course, that the actual use of these weapons in such a contingency is
                        dependent upon Presidential authorization as set forth in para. 11 of Basic
                        National Security Policy (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5602/1).<note
                            n="3" xml:id="d109fn3">
                            <ref target="#d66">Document 66</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>It is requested that this memorandum and Appendix A be given a special
                        limited distribution and that the contents be subject to special security
                        precautions with access limited to those individuals having a strict
                        “need-to-know”.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">C.E. Wilson</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d109fn4">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Appendix “A”</head>
                    <p rend="center">STRATEGIC CONCEPT</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">1. Strategic Concept for General War Beginning 1 July
                            1960</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>In the event of general war, a war in which the armed forces of the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and of the United States are
                            overtly engaged, the basic military objective of the U.S. Armed Forces
                            is the defeat of the Sino-Soviet Bloc to a degree which will assure the
                            accomplishment of the U.S. national objectives in order to preserve the
                            security of the United States and its fundamental values and
                            institutions. It is the policy of the United States that atomic weapons
                            will be integrated with other weapons in the arsenal of the United
                            States. [<hi rend="italic">1 sentence (18 words) not
                            declassified</hi>]</item>
                        <pb facs="0446" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>General war may be initiated either by the Soviets with an atomic
                            onslaught with little or no warning or may be the result of hostilities
                            short of general war which were not initially intended to lead to
                            general war.</item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>A general war would consist of two phases, an initial phase of
                            comparatively short duration, and a subsequent phase of indeterminate
                            duration. The initial phase would be characterized by an intensive
                            exchange of atomic blows and the initiation of operations and
                            deployments by Army, Naval and Air Force forces designed to achieve
                            strategic advantage. During this period, the U.S. atomic capability
                            would be exploited fully, to the end that enemy military losses and the
                            loss of the war-making capacity directly supporting enemy forces would
                            be such as to either (a) bring about his capitulation or (b) provide a
                            margin of relative advantage to the United States and its Allies
                            sufficient to assure victory in the subsequent phase of operations. This
                            subsequent phase would be a continuation of the initial phase
                            operations, probably at reduced atomic intensity, and follow-up
                            offensive operations to achieve victory and attain Allied war
                            objectives. The ultimate strategy adopted, as well as the duration and
                            outcome of this subsequent phase, will depend largely on the relative
                            advantage achieved in the initial phase and the remaining relative
                            capabilities.</item>
                        <label>d.</label>
                        <item>Prior to the outbreak of a general war which developed as an outgrowth
                            of a local or limited war the United States might achieve a significant
                            degree of mobilization, deployment and commitment of resources. Such
                            deployments might not improve our posture for general war. At any time
                            during hostilities short of general war the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                                >USSR</gloss> might initiate a large scale atomic attack, but the
                            alertness of the Allies, the defense preparations and the deployments
                            achieved might reduce casualties to civilian populations and to military
                            forces and establishments from the proportions to be expected in a
                            general war initiated by surprise Soviet atomic attack. However, once a
                            large-scale atomic exchange has taken place, the war situation would
                            probably develop along similar lines to a general war initiated by a
                            surprise atomic attack but with greater Allied capability remaining
                            after the atomic exchange.</item>
                        <label>e.</label>
                        <item>The United States, in collaboration with its Allies, will: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Defend the continental United States.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Defend vital areas in the Western hemisphere and
                                    overseas.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Destroy or reduce the military potential of the enemy by
                                    conducting offensive operations against the military forces of
                                    the enemy and the war-making capacity directly supporting those
                                    forces.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Conduct operations required to maintain control of essential
                                    sea areas and protect vital sea communications.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>During the initial phase, conduct a strategic defense in
                                    Europe, the Middle East and the Far East.</item>
                                <pb facs="0447" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>Subsequent to the initial phase, and as dictated by the
                                    military situation then existing, conduct such operations as may
                                    be required to achieve Allied war objectives. Consequently, only
                                    broad guidance in terms of military objectives can now be
                                    determined for the conduct of operations in the subsequent
                                    phase.</item>
                                <label>(7)</label>
                                <item>Accelerate the phased expansion of all U.S. military
                                    forces.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">2. Strategic Concept for Cold War or for Military Conflict
                            Short of General War Beginning 1 July 1960</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>The basic objective of U.S. national security policy is to preserve
                            the security of the United States and its fundamental values and
                            institutions. During a period of cold war or military conflict short of
                            general war, the Sino-Soviet Bloc regimes can be expected to continue to
                            prosecute through various means an expansionist policy detrimental to
                            the security of the United States and Allies. Military conflict short of
                            general war becomes more likely during this period because of the mutual
                            deterrence to general war resulting from the possession by both sides of
                            the capability to destroy each other even after a surprise attack.
                            Unstable areas of the world, disagreement among nations of the Free
                            World, and fear of atomic destruction will probably offer opportunities
                            for the Sino-Soviet Bloc regimes to exploit subversion and covert or
                            overt armed aggression.</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>The United States and its Allies reject the concept of preventive war
                            or acts intended to provoke war. A basic aim of U.S. military policy is
                            to deter the Sino-Soviet Bloc from using its military power. Hence,
                            during a period of cold war or military conflict short of general war,
                            it is the policy of the United States to affect the conduct of the
                            Sino-Soviet Bloc regimes, especially that of the <gloss
                                target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, in ways that further U.S. security
                            interest and encourage tendencies that lead them to abandon expansionist
                            policies.</item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>The military position of the United States for a period of cold war or
                            military conflict short of general war will be influenced by the support
                            and cooperation of appropriate major Allies and certain other Free World
                            countries. The United States must convince its Allies that U.S. strategy
                            and policy serve their security as well as that of the United States.
                            Military assistance will be provided by the United States as necessary
                            to insure the availability of strategic bases and key military
                            facilities and to enable other nations of the Free World to develop
                            forces capable of maintaining internal security, of conducting defensive
                            action against military aggression, and where practicable, of
                            contributing to the collective military power of the Free World. In
                            general this military assistance should be consonant with the economic
                            capability of each nation, except where political or military
                            considerations overrule and should include, wherever appropriate, new
                            weapons and advanced technology.</item>
                        <pb facs="0448" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/>
                        <label>d.</label>
                        <item>The United States with its Allies must defeat the shifting tactic of
                            the Sino-Soviet Bloc, and improve the relative strategic position of the
                            Free World. This will require military forces capable of: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Providing a position of strength from which to influence
                                    international negotiations for peaceful settlement of basic
                                    differences.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Reinforcing and exploiting U.S. political, economic,
                                    psychological and other actions in the Free World and
                                    elsewhere.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Demonstrating U.S. intent and readiness to discharge its
                                    mutual security and treaty obligations.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Deterring aggression.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Maintaining the security of the United States, and readiness
                                    for initial tasks in a general war.</item>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>Dealing swiftly and decisively with military aggression short
                                    of general war on a scale best calculated to achieve U.S.
                                    objectives and avoid the hostilities broadening into general
                                    war.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>e.</label>
                        <item>The United States military posture must provide: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>A forward deployment of U.S. ready military forces prepared to
                                    conduct operations immediately, from positions strategically
                                    selected both to counter local aggression and to carry out the
                                    initial tasks in a general war.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Mobile ready forces, principally based upon U.S. territory,
                                    which can be deployed rapidly to provide reinforcement to
                                    forward deployed forces and indigenous forces in defeating
                                    aggression, or to fight unassisted in the event forward deployed
                                    forces are not available and effective indigenous forces are
                                    lacking.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>An atomic retaliatory capability, adequately safeguarded and
                                    ready for immediate and effective action.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>A defense system, including the use of atomic weapons, which
                                    will provide an acceptable destruction probability against
                                    attacks which the Soviets are capable of launching against the
                                    North American continent, in order to protect the war-making
                                    capacity and resources of the Western Hemisphere.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Forces as necessary to provide the capability of maintaining
                                    essential land areas and sea and air communications.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>f.</label>
                        <item>[<hi rend="italic">remainder of paragraph (20 words) not
                                declassified</hi>]</item>
                        <label>g.</label>
                        <item>Although military operations short of general war are not intended to
                            provoke general war, military or political conditions might be created
                            which would precipitate the initiation of general war by the <gloss
                                target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Further, the United States, under
                            expanding military operations, might achieve a significant degree of
                            mobilization. Therefore, the deliberate initiation of general war by the
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> under these conditions is
                            considered to be unlikely. It would obviously be more advantageous to
                            the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to initiate general war by a
                            surprise atomic attack on the United States.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
