<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1908-11-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1908-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="263" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d263">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">5727/264–265.</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Danish Minister</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Denmark</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1908-11-23"><hi rend="italic">November 23,
                                        1908</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: By the note addressed to my
                                predecessor on September 4 last, 5727/248, serial No. 791, your
                                excellency was good enough to request of this legation a statement
                                concerning the organization and operation of the Committee of the
                                Wholesale Merchants’ Association of Copenhagen, “Kjöbenhavns
                                Grosserer Societets Komite,” in regard to the wish of my Government
                                to secure for the certificates of value issued by that body and
                                covering merchandise exported from Denmark into the United States
                                the recognition by American customs officers on the same footing as
                                like certificates issued by German chambers of commerce.</p>
                            <p>I have accordingly the honor to inform your excellency that the
                                above-mentioned Danish body was organized by a decree of April 23,
                                1817, by virtue of which it has to furnish reports and statements
                                which the Government, the authorities, or the courts of justice may
                                request of it. Through later dispositions the association was
                                invested with power for participating in the election of the members
                                of the Tribunal of Commerce and Navigation and in the operation of
                                determining the rate of exchange.</p>
                            <p>The said association being, according to a statement of the royal
                                ministry of interior, the only official Danish institution dealing
                                with questions pertaining to commerce and being frequently called
                                upon by the central Government for assistance in all matters
                                concerning such questions, it may, without any doubt, righteously be
                                described as a governmental or quasi-governmental organization.</p>
                            <p>In inclosing a printed statement (pp. 1–7) on the organization of the
                                said association I venture to express the hope that the above
                                information will enable your excellency to recommend the wishes set
                                forth in my predecessor’s note of August 20 last, for a favorable
                                consideration by the Department of the Treasury.</p>
                            <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">C. Moltke.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>