<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Russian Ambassador to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1908</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d274</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">274</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1907-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1907-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="274"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d274">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 5727/145.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Russian Ambassador</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Imperial Embassy of Russia</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-10-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 25, 1907</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: Under an agreement recently
                    concluded between the Federal Government and Germany, certain customs facilities
                    have been granted by the United States to the importation of goods from Germany.
                    They have mainly to do with the assessment of customs duties which, by virtue of
                    the agreement, are computed according to the value of the merchandise as
                    established by invoices certified by American consuls and also by special
                    certificates issued by the German chambers of commerce.</p>
                <pb facs="0450" n="348" xml:id="pg_348"/>
                <p>Desirous of having these commercial advantages extended to Russian imports into
                    the United States, I have the honor to ask, by order of my Government, that your
                    excellency will be so good as to inform me whether the Federal Government is
                    disposed to grant those facilities to Russian trade with the United States and,
                    particularly, that which consists in levying ad valorem customs duties on the
                    basis of the appraisement of Russian merchandise as determined by invoices duly
                    certified by consuls of the United States and by special certificates delivered,
                    in the absence of chambers of commerce, by committees of Russian exchanges
                    (general and special).</p>
                <p>The Imperial Government holds that the said committees, whose powers are set
                    forth in articles 591–598 of the Russian Commercial Code, and more specially in
                    the statutes of the St. Petersburg Exchange, after which the statutes of all the
                    other exchanges are patterned, and which are annexed to the aforesaid code, are
                    quite as competent in this respect as the chambers of commerce existing in
                    Europe, and that certificates issued by them will have the same value as those
                    delivered by the said chambers of commerce.</p>
                <p>Hoping that this request will be favorably received by the Federal Government, I
                    avail myself, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rosen.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
