<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1908-03-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1908-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="602" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d602">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 594/22–23.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Gummeré</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Tangier</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1908-03-05"><hi rend="italic">March 5,
                                1908</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of instruction No. 133, of February 6, 1908, regarding the wish
                            of the Gospel Union Mission to rent a house in the native quarter of
                            Mequinez, inclosing copy of a letter addressed by the department to the
                            Rev. George S. Fisher, president of the mission, and further directing
                            me to again address the shereefian government, inquiring as to the
                            nature of the shereefian orders given to the basha in November, 1906,
                            asking explanation of their nonenforcement and demanding assurances that
                            they will be carried out as soon as possible.</p>
                        <p>In pursuance with the said instruction I have addressed a letter to Sid
                            Abdelkrim Ben Sliman, the grand vizier, a copy of which is herewith
                            inclosed, setting forth the matter briefly and requesting that he will
                            inform me as to the nature of the shereefian orders given to the basha
                            of Mequinez in November, 1906, and an explanation of their
                            nonenforcement and also demanding assurances that they will be carried
                            out as soon as possible.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">S. R. Gummeré.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Gummeré</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Minister for
                                        Foreign Affairs</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Tangier</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1908-03-05"><hi rend="italic">March 5,
                                        1908</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 21.]</seg></opener>
                            <p>After compliments. I have the honor to inform your excellency that I
                                am instructed by my Government to again bring before you the matter
                                of the securing of a suitable house by the Americans residing in
                                Mequinez. Your excellency will recall that during my visit to the
                                court of his shereefian majesty, in the latter part of the year
                                1906, I brought this matter to the notice of his majesty and
                                yourself in an especial manner, and not only received the personal
                                assurances from his majesty that my request for such a house would
                                be granted, but also a written statement from yourself, dated
                                November 23, 1906 (Shoual 1324), in which it was expressly set forth
                                that a shereefian order had been issued by His Majesty the Sultan to
                                the governor of Mequinez “to be mindful of the said Americans, to
                                take care of their affairs, and treat them with favor and kindness
                                and not place obstacles in the way of their renting a residence in a
                                part of the town not objectionable, but to assist them in the
                                same.”</p>
                            <pb facs="0743" n="641" xml:id="pg_641"/>
                            <p>As I informed your excellency in a letter dated March 12, 1907
                                (Morarrem 27, 1325), when the said Americans presented themselves to
                                the said basha of Mequinez, instead of assisting them in securing a
                                house he raised foolish objections to those which they proposed, and
                                on their calling on him to assist them, as your excellency had
                                assured me His Majesty’s letter had directed, he replied that he
                                would look at the letter and that they could return the next day,
                                and on their so presenting themselves, he refused to see them, but
                                sent word that he could not find the letter of His Majesty. To this
                                your excellency replied that when the governor of Mequinez was
                                written to on the subject he had replied “that the Americans had
                                never applied to him nor informed him of any house, etc.” This reply
                                of the said governor was, as your excellency must have seen, after
                                reading my letters of March 12, 1907 (Moharrem 27, 1325), and June
                                11, 1907 (Rabe Thany 29, 1325), on the subject, an absolute
                                falsehood, and as I have previously informed your excellency, my
                                Government is exceedingly annoyed at the manner in which the solemn
                                assurances of His Majesty the Sultan and of yourself to me, when on
                                a special mission to His Majesty, have been entirely disregarded and
                                unfulfilled.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to inform your excellency that I have now received
                                instructions from my Government to request that you will inform me
                                exactly what were the shereefian orders given to the basha of
                                Mequinez in November, 1906, regarding the securing of a house for
                                American citizens and also an explanation as to why the said orders
                                were not enforced. At the same time I am instructed to demand from
                                the shereefian government assurances that the solemn pledges given
                                to me in this matter will be carried out at the very earliest
                                possible moment.</p>
                            <p>In peace,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">S. R.
                                Gummeré.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>