<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Secretary of Legation Neill to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1908</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d659</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">659</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1908-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1908-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1908-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1908-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="659"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d659">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 3742/28–30.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss type="from">Secretary of Legation Neill</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lima</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1908-07-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 29, 1908</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 148.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the regular
                    sessions of Congress were opened yesterday with the usual display, being the
                    eighty-seventh anniversary of the independence of Peru.</p>
                <p>The President read his message, of which I herewith transmit two official copies,
                    and the salient points in translation as inclosures.</p>
                <p>All the members of the diplomatic corps were present.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard R. Neill.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Résumé of President Pardo’s Message.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Foreign relations have been kept up on a footing of perfect cordiality
                        between Peru and other nations.</p>
                    <p>The arbitration of the question as to limits with Bolivia, subject to the
                        decision of the President of the Argentine Republic, is in an advanced
                        state.</p>
                    <p>The new arrangement as to traffic with Bolivia via Mollendo is now in force
                        and gives every possible facility to the Bolivian trade.</p>
                    <p>The modus vivendi agreed upon with Brazil as to a portion of the territory in
                        dispute still continues without having succeeded in arriving at a definite
                        solution. Both Governments have nevertheless come to an understanding that
                        the final settlement foreseen in the protocol of July 12, 1904, shall be
                        effected before May 31, 1909.</p>
                    <p>Conflicts between Colombians and Peruvians continue to occur in Putumayo
                        owing to the canceling by the Government of Colombia of the treaty of 1905.
                        These incidents are to be deplored, but our Loreto authorities have
                        interfered, reestablishing order and opening an official investigation to
                        prove who was to blame.</p>
                    <p>The question about limits with Ecuador awaits the decision of the arbitrator,
                        the King of Spain.</p>
                    <p>In February of this year Callao was visited by the powerful American Atlantic
                        Fleet, under the command of Admiral Evans. The sincere and friendly
                        reception which the inhabitants of Lima and Callao gave to the crews of the
                        American war vessels and the honors which in my person this squadron
                        tributed to Peru form an evident proof of the cordial relations which unite
                        the two Governments, and in which the people of one and the other country
                        fully share, as was shown likewise during the recent voyage of the cruiser
                            <hi rend="italic">Admiral Grau</hi> to San Francisco, Cal.</p>
                    <p>The question regarding the definite nationality of Tacna and Arica has not
                        yet been settled, and every day the bonds of nationality and patriotic
                        affection which unite us to those provinces are becoming closer and
                        stronger. During the diplomatic discussion our foreign office has had
                        occasion to show clearly once more to the Government of Chile and to those
                        of other friendly nations that the <pb facs="0786" n="684" xml:id="pg_684"/>
                        compliance on the part of Chile with the treaty of Ancon is the only method
                        to resolve with justice the pending question.</p>
                    <p>The recent revolution started by a group of rebels, and simply due to an
                        outburst of political passion, surprised the entire nation; but it was
                        promptly suppressed, as the whole population is opposed to revolution,
                        because they now comprehend that any revolution is more fatal to their
                        interests and to the country than it ever can be to the party or Government
                        in power.</p>
                    <p>The number of Government schools in the Republic is 2,410, with 156,011
                        pupils. During the past year 105 new schools have been opened. A North
                        American mistress has been brought out, under contract, for the inspection
                        and direction of the schools for girls.</p>
                    <p>The works of fortifying Lima and Callao are being carried on gradually
                        according to modern systems and mounted with Armstrong guns; two other
                        batteries are being constructed for the use of Schneider-Canet quick-firing
                        guns.</p>
                    <p>Several young naval officers are gaining practical knowledge by serving in
                        the navies of the United States, France, and Spain, and the Governments of
                        those countries have earned the gratitude of Peru by their kind
                        attention.</p>
                    <p>The bond stores in Callao customhouse continue giving excellent results. This
                        “warrant” system will soon be extended to others of the principal
                        customhouses.</p>
                    <p>The national mint has coined in the past year £214,000 in gold coin and
                        £104,000 in silver sols of 24d. each.</p>
                    <p>The budget for 1909 amounts to £301,194.</p>
                    <p>The value of importation in the past year was £5,514,787 and of the
                        exportation £5,747,732.</p>
                    <p>The value of the import and export trade in the first half year of 1908 was
                        £5,264,540; that is to say, £175,000 more than in the same period of
                        1907.</p>
                    <p>The Government could not be insensible to the want of facilities in the port
                        of Callao for the loading and discharging of vessels, and has arranged with
                        the dock company the extension of the present wharves and construction of
                        new ones, besides an increased number of lighters, winches, etc., and it
                        will not renew the privileges of the company on the expiration of the
                        contract in 1912.</p>
                    <p>The service of the public debt has been conducted with the greatest
                        punctuality.</p>
                    <p>The construction of different railways for the purpose of improving the means
                        of communication, cheapening freights, and extending trade with the most
                        important centers has continued without interruption.</p>
                    <p>By means of the wireless-telegraph system daily communication has been
                        established between Lima and Iquitos.</p>
                    <p>The Government continues devoting special attention to the problem of
                        immigration and during the past year has granted free passages to 566
                        European immigrants, of which 435 were of the male and 131 of the female
                        sex.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
