<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1908-07-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1908-07-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="752" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d752">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 4832/31–32.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Brazilian
                                    Ambassador</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1908-07-10"><hi rend="italic">July 10,
                                1908</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 61.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to inclose, with
                            the request that you will be good enough to transmit them to Mr. John
                            Brewer, who is acting as custodian of the archives of the American
                            Legation at Caracas, for the legation’s files, a copy of the note of
                            June 20, 1908, by which the Brazilian minister at Caracas informed the
                            Venezuelan Government that he would have charge of American interests in
                            Venezuela during the suspension of diplomatic relations between the
                            United States and Venezuela, and a copy of the Venezuelan Government’s
                            reply thereto under date of June 22, 1908.</p>
                        <p>I beg to request that you will inform Mr. Brewer that his consular
                            functions have been suspended, and that he will regard himself as merely
                            custodian of the archives under the friendly supervision of the
                            Brazilian representative.</p>
                        <p>I trust that there may be no inconvenience in displaying the Brazilian
                            flag over the American Legation building, if it should become necessary
                            or desirable to display a flag.</p>
                        <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Alvey A. Adee.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure
                                1.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Brazilian Chargé</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Venezuelan Minister for Foreign
                                        Affairs</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States of Brazil</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1908-06-20"><hi rend="italic">June 20, 1908</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: I have the honor to inform
                                your excellency that the chargé d’affaires of the United States of
                                America having advised me in a note dated <pb facs="0929" n="827" xml:id="pg_827"/> to-day that he has requested his passports
                                from the Government, I have this day assumed charge of American
                                interests during the rupture of friendly relations between the two
                                countries I have also been intrusted with the protection and care of
                                the archives and of the American Legation building which have been
                                placed until further orders under the charge of the American
                                consular agent, Mr. John Brewer, who will continue to reside in the
                                aforesaid building.</p>
                            <p>In the name of my Government I express to your excellency its great
                                regret at this event and its most ardent wish to see the present
                                difficulties amicably arranged in the briefest possible time.</p>
                            <p>I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to your excellency,
                                etc.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Luiz R. de Lorena
                                    Ferreira.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure
                                2.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Venezuelan Minister for
                                        Foreign Affairs</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Brazilian
                                        Chargé</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1908-06-22"><hi rend="italic">June 22, 1908</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 731.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your honor’s polite note of the 20th instant, and
                                referring to its contents, which have also been communicated to this
                                office by the Hon Jacob Sleeper, chargé d’affaires ad interim of the
                                United States of America, in a letter of the same date, my
                                Government takes note of the fact that the interests, property, and
                                archives of the American Legation in Caracas have been placed under
                                your honor’s charge I thank your honor in the name of the Government
                                of Venezuela for the wishes which you express in regard thereto.</p>
                            <p>I avail myself, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Jose de J.
                                Paul.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>