<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-05-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-05-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="110" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d110">
                    <head>110. After Action Report<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d110fn0">Source:
                            National Defense University, <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> Papers, Box 12, Cuba, Paramilitary Study. Secret;
                            Eyes Only. <persName>Robertson</persName> prepared the report for the
                                <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>
                        Committee.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-05-04">May 4,
                            1961</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p rend="center">MR. <persName>ROBERTSON</persName>ʼS REPORT OF ACTIVITIES ON
                        BARBARA J</p>
                    <p>The writer was Operations Officer on the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>.
                        The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>. is an <gloss target="#t_LCI1">LCI</gloss> fitted with eight .50 cal machine guns, three .30 machine
                        guns, a 75mm recoilless rifle, and a 57mm recoilless rifle, plus various
                        automatic <pb facs="0282" n="250" xml:id="pg_250"/> hand carried weapons.
                        The job for the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> during the operation was as
                        follows: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> was to escort the transport
                                ship <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> into Bahia Cochinos to Red
                                Beach. The <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> had aboard the 2nd and 5th
                                Battalions Reinforced.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> was to spot the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> offshore, while the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>ʼs beach reconnaissance team reconnoitered the
                                beach and set light markers at each flank of a suitable landing
                                site.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> was to provide gunfire
                                support when necessary and assist in the unloading of the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>ʼs men and supplies at Red
                                Beach.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>When the beach was considered in good shape, the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> was to escort the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>
                                out of Bahia Cochinos and proceed to patrol the beach from Green
                                Beach eastward for five miles, engaging any enemy sea or road
                                convoys heading toward Green Beach.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> was to engage in any
                                harassment operations which would confuse the enemy and help our own
                                forces.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The objective of the 2nd Battalion on Red Beach was to secure the beachhead,
                        proceed northward to Sopillar airstrip, link up with the paratroopers, and
                        proceed to Objective A on the railroad at 82.0-72.0 on the 1:50,000 map. The
                        objective of the 5th Battalion was to land behind the 2nd Battalion and take
                        over and safeguard the beachhead.</p>
                    <p>At 2330 on D-1 the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> separated from the major convoy on schedule. At 0115 on
                        D-Day the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> were on station opposite Red Beach. One <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> small boat with radio was dispatched to stand by with
                        the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>. The other small boat with the
                        reconnaissance team and the writer proceeded ashore to the right of Red
                        Beach and scouted and marked the right flank without being detected. Then
                        the team proceeded by water to the point which was to be the left flank of
                        Red Beach and discovered the point was occupied by enemy men. The 2nd
                        Battalion commander was asked to notify us when he was within ten minutes of
                        dispatching his first wave to the Beach. When the Battalion commander
                        signified he was ready, the recon team approached the point. At about 30
                        yards off the point four or five machine guns and submachine guns opened
                        fire on the recon boat. The recon boat returned fire and silenced these
                        guns. The recon boat backed up to approximately 100 yards off the point and
                        marked the left flank with a blinking flashlight towards sea. The first
                        forty soldiers landed without opposition, though sporadic fire started as
                        soon as they had landed ashore. This fire was their initial contact with the
                        50 militiamen in the village at the time of the landing.</p>
                    <p>Within twenty minutes of the reconnaissance teamʼs initial contact with the
                        enemy, six or seven trucks were seen entering the area from the left flank.
                        The writer called for supporting fire from the <hi rend="italic">Barbara
                            J.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>ʼs first shots hit the lead
                        truck and threw the convoy into darkness <pb facs="0283" n="251" xml:id="pg_251"/> and confusion and apparently helped delay the convoyʼs
                        arrival at Red Beach until later in the morning.</p>
                    <p>The reconnaissance group proceeded then to help in landing the troops. These
                        troops were landed with approximately two units of fire and a minimum of
                        equipment other than their personal weapons and the unit weapons. The unit
                        weapons we succeeded in getting ashore were four .30 cal light machine guns,
                        four 81mm mortars, and four 57mm recoilless rifles, plus 3.5 rocket
                        launchers. On the second trip to Red Beach, our boat was hit by machine gun
                        fire coming from about 200 yards left of the Red Beach left flank. One man
                        in the boat was killed. On arrival at the beach this second trip, the writer
                        sent for a representative of the 2nd Battalion command post, and between the
                        two, an airstrike plan was set up in the event that communication might be
                        out when the daylight airstrike arrived. In the plan, the aircraft would
                        take on any targets moving along the beach towards Red Beach or along the
                        road from the north towards Red Beach, and at first daylight the 2nd
                        Battalion commander would send a well-briefed officer to the beach carrying
                        a red flag for further conference with the writer. The commanding officer at
                        this conference requested that future landing craft be landed nearer the
                        right flank of the beach in as much as all enemy activity to date was being
                        encountered from the left. There were explosions within the beachhead at
                        this time which the writer took to be incoming mortar fire with some light
                        calibre.</p>
                    <p>During this period, some .50 cal machinegun fire was directed at the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>. The Barbara J was lying about 500 yards
                        offshore and the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> engaged this machine gun
                        and silenced it.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> reported that there were no small boats,
                        so our recon team tied onto one of the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>ʼs
                        rubber boats to the lee side of the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> where we
                        found seven or eight small aluminum boats huddled with no troop movement
                        going on. The writer climbed aboard and got a boat-load and a half of
                        soldiers off-loaded before being stopped by a Cuban believed to be the 5th
                        Battalion Commander. The writer believes that this manʼs intention was to
                        wait until first daylight before continuing off-loading the 5th Battalion.
                        At this point, 270 soldiers had been off-loaded. This was the 2nd Battalion
                        Reinforced and the weapons company from the 5th Battalion and the Assistant
                        Brigade Commander.</p>
                    <p>On the trip into shore, first daylight had arrived and at approximately 6
                        oʼclock a B-26 appeared low and machine-gunned our small boat without
                        success on this first run. When he came again we turned our small weapons
                        and the weapons of all the soldiers in the small boat and fired back at him.
                        On this pass the B-26 wounded one soldier with a freak shot that passed
                        through another manʼs weapon before hitting the soldier. On the third pass
                        of the B-26, he immediately, after passing over <pb facs="0284" n="252" xml:id="pg_252"/> head, started smoking and wobbling and soon went down
                        over land with one survivor parachuting out.</p>
                    <p>A second B-26 appeared and started after the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>
                        and <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>. He strafed and dropped two large bombs,
                        both misses. The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>ʼs skipper was circling the
                            <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> tightly and bringing all her firepower in
                        support of the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> during this action.</p>
                    <p>At this point, our cargo planes bearing paratroopers and accompanied by two
                        friendly B-26ʼs arrived in the area and the enemy aircraft departed. At the
                        departure of our aircraft, we were attacked by a fighter plane which I
                        believe was a Sea Fury. The skipper of the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>
                        decided to disperse until our air cover had better control and so moved the
                            <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>
                        away from Red Beach about five miles.</p>
                    <p>The writer suggests that the following is a likely account of the short
                        history of Red Beach. The account is compiled from observation and
                        interrogation of survivors. Very little action occurred at Red Beach before
                        daylight. Most of the shooting was our own. The air attack at daybreak,
                        which included bombing and strafing the beachhead, damaged nothing
                        important. At approximately 1000 a truck-mounted attack from the north
                        involving 500 or 600 militia was broken up by Red Beach forces. This was
                        accomplished with small losses to our forces and considerable loss to the
                        milita. Fifty to seventy of the militia were captured, most of which were
                        willing to join the Red Beach forces. The paratroopers were apparently
                        engaged immediately upon landing, and link between the paratroopers and Red
                        Beach forces was not accomplished. At 1400 on D-Day, another attack was made
                        from the north involving 1,500 militia. An unknown amount were destroyed en
                        route to this battle by a friendly B-26. Two of our own tanks which had been
                        sent up from Blue Beach assisted in stopping this attack. From all accounts,
                        this force was well handled by our forces, and we claimed 1,000 casualties
                        were inflicted. Seven tanks, which arrived after midnight were engaged by
                        our 57mm recoilless rifles and 3.5 rockets, and five were destroyed. On D+1
                        an orderly withdrawal to Blue Beach was effected, since Red Beach was out of
                        ammunition. Red Beach losses at this time were 25 dead, and an unknown
                        amount wounded. The wounded were carried to Blue Beach.</p>
                    <p>On arrival at Blue Beach, the 2nd Battalion was put into the Blue Beach
                        defense line which had been comparatively quiet till this point. In the
                        afternoon, a battle started which put 1,500 militiamen against the 2nd
                        Battalion. This battle lasted all night. The following morning an attempt
                        was made to regain Red Beach, but the 2nd Battalion encountered tanks,
                        trucks, troops, and artillery, and it is believed, did not reach Red Beach.
                        The heavy mortars supported the 2nd Battalion until out of ammunition. Two
                        tanks which were supporting the 2nd Battalion were returned to Blue Beach
                        damaged by this action. It is believed that the 2nd Battalion was lost with
                        Blue Beach.</p>
                    <pb facs="0285" n="253" xml:id="pg_253"/>
                    <p>At the time when the skipper of the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> ordered
                        the dispersal of the convoy, a B-26 arrived requesting targets for his bombs
                        at Red Beach. He was instructed to go to Objective A on the north road and
                        engage any mobile forces moving towards Red Beach. He located a convoy
                        moving into Red Beach with blue marked trucks and was refrained from
                        interfering with this convoy since it was known to be ours.</p>
                    <p>At this point the skipper of the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> turned the
                        convoy back towards Red Beach. The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> and the
                            <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> arrived off the point Carazones. When a
                        T-33 jet arrived and strafed and fired rockets, with near misses for the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> and hits on the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>, a welded seam on the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> was
                        split, causing the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> to take water at the
                        rate of four feet each two and a half hours. The <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> announced the loss of their steering capability, and was
                        at this time headed towards the beach. The skipper of the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> ordered the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> to reverse
                        engines and back away from the beach. The <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>
                        attempted to do this, but was observed to begin sinking rapidly by the
                        stern. At the same time another Sea Fury started attacking the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>. Gasoline was covering the water all around
                        both ships, and the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> reversed its engines
                        again and made straight into the shore, grounding about 100 yards off-shore.
                        As she struck shore, men were seen diving over the side in life jackets. The
                        Sea Fury continued its strafing runs against the ship and the men in the
                        water. From subsequent reports, we believe from seven to twenty men were
                        killed in the strafing, and ten drowned from inability to swim. The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> had no small boats; the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> didnʼt attempt to use its three small boats. There was
                        speculation as to whether we should attempt an evacuation, but this was
                        tempered by the idea that the occupants of the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> were scheduled to go ashore with the possibility that they
                        could make a tie-up at Red Beach. The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> was
                        ordered to move to the Blue Beach to provide protection for the unloading
                        operations there, the ships at Blue Beach being under air attack also.</p>
                    <p>From interrogation of survivors, it is learned that the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> group proceeded towards Red Beach, but the scouts observed
                        militiamen, and the entire group withdrew to the swamp. My last radio
                        contact with this group was an announcement by the 5th Battalion Commander
                        that he had successfully regrouped 1-1/2 miles west of the sunken ship.
                        Information on his position was requested for an intended air supply drop.
                        Within a half hour he was under attack. His request was for small boats so
                        that he could strip the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> of necessary
                        supplies. Arrangements were made for RB-12 rubber boats and paddles to be
                        dropped at first darkness. Within a half hour after this arrangement, the
                            <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> was under attack and apparently the enemy
                        was trying to split it up. I feel that our voice communication was being
                        monitored. The folowing night an enemy patrol craft approached the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> and landed five militiamen. These five were
                        attacked by the survivors of the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>. Two
                        militiamen <pb facs="0286" n="254" xml:id="pg_254"/> were killed and three
                        taken prisoners. The three prisoners were executed because of the logistical
                        problems they made for the survivors. On the 19th the skipper of the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>, the 5th Battalion Commander, five 5th
                        Battalion officers, the Chaplain, and three doctors left the beach in the
                        captured patrol craft, bidding their men to scatter and make out for
                        themselves. This might indicate a reason why the 5th Battalion seemed
                        reluctant to go ashore at Red Beach. Of the remaining men, a few immediately
                        made their way north through the swamps, and a few made their way south.
                        Those that were rescued on the southern islands had swum most of the way in
                        the swamps. The <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> skipper and the small boat
                        reportedly departed for Cayo Guano, but radio Cuba reported it landed at
                        Cayo Largo and the men were captured.</p>
                    <p>As the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> departed from Bahia Cochinos, a Sea
                        Fury was circling, but apparently was bluffed by two of our B-26ʼs which
                        were flying protection for <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>. A jet T-33 was
                        seen to attack one of the B-26ʼs, and the B-26 was seen to fly lower and to
                        either crash or make a crash landing on the airstrip at Blue Beach area. The
                        remaining B-26 hovered over the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>, reported
                        he was out of ammunition, and asked for instructions. I requested that he
                        stay as long as possible to bluff enemy aircraft, which he did, until he had
                        only fifteen minutes reserve gasoline supply. This manʼs name was Farrari
                        and should be commended for courageous work.</p>
                    <p>At the entrance of Bahia Cochinos we had observed the <hi rend="italic">Rio
                            Escondido</hi> catch fire and blow up.</p>
                    <p>On arrival in the Blue Beach area, all ships were ordered south. We departed
                        with the Atlantico and Caribe leading, and the <hi rend="italic">Barbara
                            J</hi> providing close support. The U-boats protected by the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> followed. The <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi>
                        requested all ships to merge for mutual self-protection. The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> joined the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi>
                        and U-boats, and the Caribe and Atlantico disappeared over the horizon. One
                        strafing and bombing pass was made on the right flank <gloss target="#t_LCU1">LCU</gloss>, with the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> and
                            <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> giving her support. What appeared to be
                        a salvo boat of shore-based artillery splashed five shells within the convoy
                        on the way out. This was possibly 1 oʼclock to 2 oʼclock in the afternoon of
                        D-Day.</p>
                    <p>At approximately 3:30, when the convoy was outside the continental limit, a
                        Sea Fury and a B-26 attacked. The Sea Fury circled high and the B-26 came
                        for a low strafing attack, lining up the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>
                        and the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi>. As the B-26 passed over the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi>, it exploded in a great ball of flame. It is
                        believed that hits from <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> guns had entered the
                        gas tanks, and that the pilot fired his rockets, causing the explosion. The
                        Sea Fury then circled for a few minutes and started a run on the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>, but peeled off early, probably because of
                        the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>ʼs gunfire. He scored 20mm hits on the
                            <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>. At this time we were ordered further
                        out to sea.</p>
                    <pb facs="0287" n="255" xml:id="pg_255"/>
                    <p>Preparations were made for a night run into Blue Beach. When the order
                        arrived, headquarters was notified that we were without the cargo ships, and
                        that it was felt that it was impossible to arrive at Blue Beach before
                        daylight. Air and/or sea support was requested, with the warning that we
                        felt we were sure to be sunk without this protection and thus be no good to
                        Blue Beach. During the night we were ordered to cancel this run. The
                        following evening the cargo ships had been reassembled, and the Caribe was
                        unloaded into <gloss target="#t_LCU1">LCU</gloss>s. The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> was unloaded into an <gloss target="#t_LCU1">LCU</gloss>
                        when the order came for the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> to make a
                        500-man pack supply run to Blue Beach. The <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi>
                        was leaking and one bank of engines was out and emptied of supplies and had
                        no small boats, so the responsibility was shifted to the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi>. The writer transferred to the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> to assist in this run and to assist the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> Operations Officer with communications functions. At
                        approximately midnight the run was started, with an additional warning to
                        headquarters that we were going to arrive in daylight. An air or sea support
                        was necessary. Sometime during the night this trip was cancelled.</p>
                    <p>The writer relieved the Operations Officer of the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> of communication duties at times during the night. The gist
                        of the communication can be summed up as follows: The Brigade Commander
                        continually reported he was out of anti-tank ammunition and surgical
                        supplies and had wounded to evacuate. All messages were forwarded to strike
                        base and U.S. Navy. From strike base and U.S. Navy we continually received
                        assurances that re-supplies and evacuation of wounded were being carried on
                        and that a close air support strike was arranged for first light. A tank
                        column had been located coming into Blue Beach from the north. Its exact
                        location was reported by the Brigade Commander. Arrangements were made for
                        strike base to take on these tanks at first light, and U.S. Navy jets were
                        “on the way.” The jets had not appeared when first light arrived and their
                        whereabouts was requested. We were told that they were still “on the
                        way.”</p>
                    <p>At 20 minutes daylight a request from headquarters came that either of the
                        two operations officers go on beach to evaluate the situation. A Cuban
                            <gloss target="#t_CW1">CW</gloss> operator was recruited to go with the
                        writer. No boat operator was found who would go. Subsequent activity negated
                        this operation.</p>
                    <p>At daylight the beach was under air, tank, and artillery attack. During the
                        night, two re-supply drops had been made, part of which went into the ocean,
                        part of which was received. A C-46 had landed on the airstrip, dumped its
                        supplies, and departed evacuating one wounded. The Brigade Commander began
                        talking in terms of his men standing in the water fighting, and “being
                        massacred” and “murdered.” At one point he could see four Navy jets high
                        overhead, and was being attacked simultaneously by three enemy Sea Furyʼs.
                        When he asked that the jets enter the <pb facs="0288" n="256" xml:id="pg_256"/> fight and was told that we were doing everything to
                        get permission, his comment was “God damn it, God damn you, God damn you. Do
                        not wait for permission.” He continually spotted tanks, artillery locations,
                        and continually asked when would they be attacked by our airplanes. About
                        midday the base announced that we were going in in full force, shooting, for
                        evacuation purposes. The Brigade Commander was told that within three hours
                        the Navy forces, air and sea, plus our cargo convoy would be there to pick
                        them up. He announced that an enemy tank was within 400 yards of his command
                        post firing at him and he had no ammunition with which to fight it. He said
                        he would not be there in three hours. In his next message he said he was
                        destroying his communications set and going into the woods. We were trying
                        to get him to hold on when communication abruptly broke. We have two
                        reports: (1) That the Brigade Commander was seen going to sea in a small
                        sailboat, and (2) That he had gone inland to Excambrey. The convoy started
                        out to sea.</p>
                    <p>On the morning of D+3 the operations officers of the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Barbara J</hi> were transferred
                        by rubber boat, along with six <gloss target="#t_UDT1">UDT</gloss> men and
                        personal weapons and radios, aboard the <gloss target="#t_USS1">USS</gloss>
                        Eaton. Subsequently we boarded the aircraft carrier Essex along with the
                        commander of the destroyer group, Captain Crutchfield, for the purpose of
                        conferring with <persName corresp="#p_CRAJE1">Admiral Clark</persName> and
                            <persName>Marine Colonel Mallard</persName> about effecting rescue
                        operations. It was generally thought among all concerned that the <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi> survivors could be sought only if the
                        information concerning them was recent, accurate, and reliable. The Eaton
                        was dispatched towards Bahia Cochinos with our operations officers and
                            <gloss target="#t_UDT1">UDT</gloss> men aboard with the understanding
                        that Mallard and <persName corresp="#p_CRAJE1">Clark</persName> would seek
                        information on the validity and accuracy of intelligence concerning
                        survivors on the beach, and would send authorization or cancellation of that
                        operation prior to the arrival of the Eaton on station. The operation was
                        cancelled by Admiral <persName corresp="#p_CRAJE1">Clark</persName> and we
                        spent the night sailing close to the beach for light signals. At daylight
                        movement was seen on Cayo Blanco del Sur. A rubber boat was dispatched and
                        contact made with four survivors, who were pulled aboard. A whaleboat was
                        dispatched from the Eaton with U-boat personnel aboard. The whaleboat would
                        carry the writer and three <gloss target="#t_UDT1">UDT</gloss> men to a
                        position 200 to 300 yards off the beach, from where we would make the
                        approach and contact with the survivors by rubber boat. Seventeen survivors
                        were removed in five separate operations by this group over a period of two
                        days. Predawn landings and reconnaissance were made each day to assure that
                        Castroʼs militiamen hadnʼt occupied the island during the night. Similar
                        activity was conducted by the <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> operations
                        officer and three <gloss target="#t_UDT1">UDT</gloss> men on other beaches.
                        The final day these two groups swept <persName>Cayao Miguel</persName> and
                            <persName>Cayao Blanco del Sur</persName> and the island of Carrario. We
                        carried loud speakers and searched in the mangrove swamps and tried to
                        reassure hidden refugees that the <pb facs="0289" n="257" xml:id="pg_257"/>
                        arms we carried were not against them, but against Castro. They were afraid
                        of our arms. For example, one man had been lying with only his face out of
                        the water, and when he saw the writer, he tried to sink under water. We
                        tried to assure him, but he thought that the writer was a Russian. He said
                        that there were no friends any more, and we were Russians. We broadcast that
                        if they would call to us, we would approach them without clothing and arms.
                        During this operation <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> had
                        helicopters calling as if they were saviors of the refugees and then
                        submachine gun those who would show themselves. I believe that we missed
                        many survivors because of the smallness of our patrol. We could not cover
                        every square foot of these islands, and the refugees were afraid to expose
                        themselves to us. All were in weakened condition and at times had to be
                        carried to the boat.</p>
                    <p>On this night, the militiamen moved onto the islands and set fire to the
                        brush and claimed to have driven out 166 survivors. I believe that this is
                        an exaggeration. On the following morning, the writer and four <gloss target="#t_UDT1">UDT</gloss> men and rubber boats and equipment boarded
                        the submarine <gloss target="#t_USS1">USS</gloss> Threadfin and started
                        towards Bahia Cochinos for an attempted rescue near the sunken <hi rend="italic">Houston</hi>. This operation was cancelled at 7 oʼclock in
                        the evening and the Threadfin returned to sea because of an occurence which
                        is U.S. Navy Top Secret and not to be recorded in this report. The writer
                        and men returned to the Eaton. The writer and the operations officer of the
                            <hi rend="italic">Blagar</hi> were air-lifted to the <hi rend="italic">Essex</hi> and subsequently to Guantanamo and to headquarters.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>