<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>228. Memorandum From Secretary of Defense McNamara to President to President
                    Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d228</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">228</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recjhAyAwrhStAWql" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Language training</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="228"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d228">
                <head>228. Memorandum From Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                        type="from">McNamara</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2"
                        type="to">Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d228fn0">Source: Washington National Records
                        Center, RG 330, <gloss target="#t_OASD1">OASD</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss>
                        64 A 2382, Cuba 1961 121-353. Confidential. Drafted by Mountain.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-06-08">June 8, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Service of Cuban Volunteers in U.S. Armed Forces</item>
                </list>
                <p>In response to your instruction at the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    meeting of 5 May 1961,<note n="1" xml:id="d228fn1">See <ref target="#d204"
                            >Document 204</ref>.</note> the Department of Defense has prepared the
                    attached program<note n="2" xml:id="d228fn2">Not printed.</note> to enable Cuban
                    volunteers to serve in the U.S. armed forces.</p>
                <p>There is at present no census of the Cuban exile population in the United States
                    which accurately reflects the number of males between the military ages of 17 to
                    26. However, from figures supplied by the Cuban Refugee Emergency Center in
                    Miami, out of a total of 25,000 of all ages registered at the center, 17,350 are
                    adults of whom approximately 75% fall within the 35-50 age group. On this basis
                    it appears likely that no more than 3,500 are of military age. If this figure
                    represents the upper limit, the number who would be interested in volunteering
                    for service with the U.S. armed forces will probably be considerably smaller. In
                    the absence of a census, the plan has assumed that the number of volunteers will
                    be not more than 2,000 and may be as few as 800.</p>
                <p>There are some legal barriers to the enlistment of aliens in the U.S. armed
                    forces. These barriers, however, do not prevent their voluntary induction if
                    they are between the ages of 18-26. It is therefore planned to make use of the
                    existing mechanisms of the U.S. Selective Service System to provide special
                    quotas for induction into the three services of Cuban volunteers in this age
                    group as they become identified and available. An exception in the law allows
                    the enlistment of aliens up to age 31 in the regular Navy and up to age 28 in
                    the regular Marine Corps. The plan makes use of this provision as well.</p>
                <p>Special measures for security screening have been stipulated.</p>
                <p>The Department of Health, Education and Welfare has agreed to provide and fund
                    any needed English language training prior to actual induction of volunteers.
                    The purpose of this arrangement is to avoid the necessity for assembling Cuban
                    personnel in one place for training under military auspices. With their English
                    language training completed before entry into the armed services, Cubans can be
                    processed and <pb facs="0604" n="572" xml:id="pg_572"/> trained as individuals
                    along with U.S. personnel. In addition, this arrangement assures the military
                    services of trainable people from the start, and will tend to cut down attrition
                    rates after induction.</p>
                <p>Although the Cuban volunteers will join the armed forces as individuals and will
                    be trained as such along with U.S. personnel, the military services will be
                    given informal instructions to make provisions for readily identifying and
                    locating each of these volunteers should it ever become necessary.</p>
                <p>The services will be required to give these volunteers the most advanced
                    individual training possible. However, assignment to training or duty requiring
                    access to classified information will be held to a minimum.</p>
                <p>No increase in manpower ceilings is proposed. Once language training has been
                    funded by the Department of Health, Education and Welfare, additional costs to
                    the military services for the processing of these volunteers can be handled
                    within present budgets.<note n="3" xml:id="d228fn3">On July 10 <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> sent a memorandum to the Joint
                        Chiefs of Staff and the Secretaries of the Army, Navy, and Air Force
                        indicating that the President had concurred in the program for the induction
                        of Cuban volunteers into the U.S. armed forces, outlined in thismemorandum.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> instructed that the
                        program be implemented by each of the services as quickly as possible.
                        (Washington National Records Center, RG 330, <gloss target="#t_OASD1"
                            >OASD</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: <gloss
                            target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 64 A 2382, Cuba 1961 121-353)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Robert S. McNamara</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d228fn4">Printed from a copy that indicates <persName
                                corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> signed the original.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
