<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-04-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-04-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="85" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                    <head>85. Memorandum From the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff (<persName corresp="#p_LGLL1" type="from">Lemnitzer</persName>) to the Commander in
                        Chief, Atlantic (<persName corresp="#p_DARL1" type="to">Dennison</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d85fn0">Source:
                                <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> Library, National
                            Security Files, Country Series, Cuba, Subjects, <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> Report. Top Secret. In a
                            memorandum for the record summarizing the changes in the rules of
                            engagement for the Bumpy Road operation, Commander Mitchell noted that
                            this memorandum was drafted in response to a memorandum sent from the
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> to <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW1">General Gray</persName> on April 7, modifying the U.S. naval
                            support requirements. The modifications called for destroyers to provide
                            area coverage, rather than convoying the <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss> ships, from 0600 on D-2 to the transport area. The
                            requirement for U.S. naval air cover was changed to provide an
                            additional day of air protection, from 0600 to sunset on D-2 and D-1.
                            D-Day was changed to April 17. Mitchell noted that CM-179-61 was
                            dispatched by special courier to Admiral <persName corresp="#p_DARL1">Dennison</persName> on April 8. He added that the naval task group
                            assigned to screen the Cuban Expeditionary Force was already at sea and
                            had made an anti-submarine sweep of the area off Nicaragua.
                            (Ibid.)</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">CM-179-61</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-04-07">April 7,
                            1961</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>“Bumpy Road”</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="references">
                        <head>REFERENCES</head>
                        <item>a. CM-152-61 Dated 24 March 1961, Subj: <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> Operation Crosspatch<note n="1" xml:id="d85fn1">Not
                                found.</note></item>
                        <item>b. <gloss target="#t_CINCLANT1">CINCLANT</gloss> Memo Serial Special
                            00029/61 Dated 28 March 1961<note n="2" xml:id="d85fn2"><ref target="#d73">Document 73</ref>.</note></item>
                        <item>c. SM-363-61 Dated 1 April 1961<note n="3" xml:id="d85fn3"><ref target="#d76">Document 76</ref>.</note></item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0225" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft">ENCLOSURES<note n="4" xml:id="d85fn4">A handwritten note in
                            the margin at this point reads: “Deleted from this copy, GAMitchell,
                            Cdr. <gloss target="#t_USN1">USN</gloss>” Mitchell drew a box around the
                            first five enclosures listed to indicate that they had been deleted from
                            the copy included in the <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>
                            Report. Another copy of CM-179-61, with all of the enclosures attached,
                            is in the Naval Historical Center, Area Files, Bumpy Road
                            Materials.</note></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>DD Support</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_LSD1">LSD</gloss> Support</item>
                        <label>C.</label>
                        <item>Combat Air Patrol</item>
                        <label>D.</label>
                        <item>Navigational Reference Points</item>
                        <label>E.</label>
                        <item>Individual Ship Movement Schedule (Code Name)</item>
                        <label>F.</label>
                        <item>Instructions for DD Escort and <gloss target="#t_CAP1">CAP</gloss>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Reference a requested certain naval support for the subject
                                    para-military operation. Due to required changes in concept of
                                    movement of surface units, the requirements for U.S. Naval
                                    support as set forth in reference a are superseded by those
                                    contained in Enclosures A, B, and C hereto.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Enclosures D and E contain the required navigational and
                                    individual ship movements information for the ships of the Cuban
                                    Volunteer Force.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>It is necessary to take precautions to assure that U.S.
                                    support of the Cuban Volunteer Force is not apparent and that
                                    support for this operation be undertaken so that the United
                                    States may plausibly deny participation. In order to achieve
                                    this goal, it is necessary to modify the instructions for the
                                    escorting destroyers and the combat air patrol. Accordingly, the
                                    specific “rules of engagement” as set forth in references b and
                                    c are superseded by the instructions contained in Enclosure F
                                    hereto.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>D-Day is now scheduled for 17 April 1961.</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_LGLL1"><hi rend="strong">L.L.
                                    Lemnitzer</hi></persName><note n="5" xml:id="d85fn5">Printed
                                from a copy that bears this typed
                        signature.</note></signed></closer>
                    <pb facs="0226" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>Enclosure F<note n="6" xml:id="d85fn6">Top Secret; Limited
                                Distribution.</note></head>
                        <p rend="center">INSTRUCTIONS FOR DESTROYER ESCORT AND COMBAT AIR
                                PATROL<note n="7" xml:id="d85fn7"><p>Commander Mitchell subsequently
                                    summarized the changes in the rules of engagement, outlined in
                                    Enclosure F, as follows:</p>
                                <p>“The changes to the rules pointed out the necessity for avoiding
                                    any sign of U.S. participation. The U.S. naval air cover was to
                                    be flown in such a manner that the planes did not appear to be
                                    covering the <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss> ships. During
                                    daylight hours the escorting destroyers were to maintain maximum
                                    practicable range ahead of the <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss> ships and to use courses and speeds so that
                                    they provided protection but didnʼt appear to be screening the
                                        <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss> ships. During the hours
                                    of darkness the destroyers could close the <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss> ships to provide adequate
                                    protection. The destroyers were not to approach within 20 miles
                                    (instead of the previous 3 miles) of Cuban territory and, as
                                    soon as the San Marcos (the <gloss target="#t_LSD1">LSD</gloss>)
                                    had withdrawn from the transfer area for the landing craft, the
                                    destroyers were to withdraw to join the U.S. naval task group
                                    (about 125 miles from Blue Beach). The rules of engagement were
                                    modified so that U.S. naval units would not open fire on Cuban
                                    ships or aircraft until they opened fire (or opened bomb bays
                                    and started a bombing run) (Note: Sea Furies and T-33ʼs do not
                                    have bomb bays) on the <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss>
                                    ships. In essence, the U.S. protecting forces could only open
                                    fire if the <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss> was attacked.
                                    (Instead of opening fire when a Cuban ship or aircraft made a
                                    threatening move.) If the U.S. forces intervened to protect the
                                        <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss> ships, the operation was
                                    automatically cancelled. U.S. forces were then to take all steps
                                    short of firing on the <gloss target="#t_CEF1">CEF</gloss> ships
                                    to cause them to withdraw to a port to be designated by the
                                        <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>.” (Memorandum for the
                                    Record, Rules of Engagement Operation “Bumpy Road”; <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> Library, National
                                    Security Files, Countries Series, Cuba, Subjects, <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> Report)</p></note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The US destroyers providing the area coverage of the Cuban
                                Volunteer Force ships will take the following precautions to avoid
                                overt association with ships of the Cuban Force: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>During daylight hours they will maintain maximum
                                        practicable range ahead of the ships of the Cuban Force and
                                        maintain a patrol using courses and speeds so as to provide
                                        protection but not appear to be screening the Cuban Force
                                        ships.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>During the hours of darkness the US destroyers are
                                        permitted to take station with respect to the Cuban Force
                                        ships to provide adequate protection.</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>US Naval support will not be used to support the landing
                                        operation. The US destroyers covering the transport ships of
                                        the Cuban Force will not close within 20 miles of the target
                                        area. After withdrawal of the San Marcos from Point
                                        Oldsmobile, the US destroyers will withdraw to Point Packard
                                        and rejoin the US Naval Task Group.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The surface and subsurface special rules of engagement are as
                                follows: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>Prior to the rendezvous of the Cuban Force ships: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>If intervention by US forces is required to
                                                protect the Cuban Force ships from att-ack or to
                                                prevent their capture, the US forces will intervene
                                                as necessary to protect the Cuban Force
                                                ship(s).</item>
                                            <pb facs="0227" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>This intervention will cancel the landing
                                                operation and the US destroyers will take measures
                                                short of firing on the Cuban Force ships, to cause
                                                them to withdraw to a port to be designated by the
                                                  <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> upon receipt
                                                of the report of intervention.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>Subsequent to the intervention and withdrawal, the
                                                US destroyers will maintain close escort of the
                                                Cuban Force to provide protection and witness
                                                compliance with the withdrawal order.</item>
                                            <label>(4)</label>
                                            <item>U.S. forces will open fire only if the Cuban Force
                                                ship(s) is attacked.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>After rendezvous of the Cuban Force ships at 1730 R, D-1
                                        Day and until convoy has moved to a point within 20 miles of
                                        the objective area, a DD commanding officer will: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Place his ship between the convoy and any
                                                suspicious or Cuban surface craft sighted.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>Warn the craft not to approach within gun range of
                                                the convoy.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>If the surface craft persists in closing the
                                                convoy, the DD will intervene as necessary to
                                                protect the Cuban Force ships, then follow
                                                instructions set forth in paragraph 2a(2) and (3)
                                                above.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>Intervention by US destroyers after Cuban Force convoy has
                                        moved to a point within 20 miles of the objective area will
                                        be limited to that required to assist the San Marcos at her
                                        request.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The combat air patrol mission pilots and air controllers will be
                                instructed as follows: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_CAP1">CAP</gloss> will take station
                                        so that it will not give the appearance of covering the
                                        ships of the Cuban Force.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>The “rules of engagement” are as follows: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Any unidentified aircraft approaching within radar
                                                range of the Cuban Force ships and closing will be
                                                investigated.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>If investigation reveals the aircraft to be Cuban,
                                                the investigating aircraft will make successive
                                                close passes ensuring that the Cuban aircraft is
                                                aware of his presence.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>If Cuban aircraft maintains course to close the
                                                Cuban Force ship(s)<gloss target="#t_CAP1">CAP</gloss> will continue to make close passes in
                                                an attempt to divert.</item>
                                            <label>(4)</label>
                                            <item>If Cuban aircraft insists in closing and attempts
                                                to take position to attack the Cuban Force ship(s),
                                                the <gloss target="#t_CAP1">CAP</gloss> aircraft
                                                will open fire if the Cuban aircraft commences to
                                                fire on the Cuban Force ship(s) or if it opens its
                                                bomb bays and commences its bomb run.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>