<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-09-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="92" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d92">
                    <head>92. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>According to summary notes on the meeting prepared by <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW1">General Gray</persName>, a meeting was held at the
                        White House at 5:45 p.m. on April 12, 1961, to consider final preparations
                        for the Zapata operation against Cuba. According to the Presidentʼs
                        appointment book the meeting lasted an hour and a quarter and was attended
                        by <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Robert
                            Kennedy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BRMJ1">Bissell</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BTPWD1">Barnes</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName>. (<persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> Library, Presidentʼs Appointment Book) Although
                            <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW1">Gray</persName> is not listed in the
                        appointment book, his notes indicate that he attended and it is probable
                        that some of the other responsible officials from the Department of State
                        attended as well. <persName corresp="#p_GMGDW1">Gray</persName>ʼs notes
                        summarized the meeting as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“At this meeting <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> presented a
                                paper which outlined the latest changes for the Zapata operation
                                including the defections and air strikes on D-2. Many questions were
                                discussed concerning training of additional forces, statements, if
                                any, on D-2 operations, how to prevent headlines, and acceleration
                                of internal troubles. The President stressed the necessity for
                                non-association with the US and directed that all training
                                activities being conducted within the US should stop. He was
                                informed that no-go time for preliminary operations would be 1200,
                                Friday, 14 April, and for the main landing 1200, Sunday, 16 April.”
                                (Summary notes prepared on May 9, 1961; ibid., National Security
                                Files, Countries Series, Cuba, Subjects, <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> Report. For the text of the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> paper, see <ref target="#d93">Document 93</ref>.)</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>The President did not give final approval to the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> plan at this meeting. (Memorandum No. 1 from the Cuba Study
                        Group to the President; <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName>
                        Library, National Security Files, Countries Series, Cuba, Subjects,
                            <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> Report)</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>