<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1894-01-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1894-01-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="169" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d169">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Gresham.</persName></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-01-26"><hi rend="italic">January 26,
                                1894</hi></date>. (Received March 15, 1894.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1796.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose a translation
                            of a communication received from the Tsung-li-Yamên on the subject of
                            the exhibition of passports by foreigners traveling in China, together
                            with a copy of my reply, as dean, thereto.</p>
                        <p>It will be seen that the Yamên has receded from its demand that travelers
                            should search out the local authorities en route and exhibit their
                            passports, and now proposes that passports shall be exhibited on demand
                            made by certain local officials.</p>
                        <p>It is now probable that the matter will be satisfactorily arranged.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                1796.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <persName type="from">Tsung-li-Yamên</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Denby</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-01-20"><hi rend="smallcaps">January</hi> 20,
                                        1894</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>The prince and ministers, on the 30th of December, had the honor to
                                receive a communication from the minister of the United States
                                acknowledging receipt of the Yamên’s communication setting forth
                                that foreigners traveling in China should be required, when applying
                                for passports, either at Peking or in the provinces, to report in
                                person to the local officials en route their arrival as well as
                                their intended movements.</p>
                            <p>In this communication it is stated that the foreign representatives,
                                disagreeing with the views of the Yamên, can not accede to the
                                proposition made, etc.</p>
                            <p>The prince and ministers would observe that the object of the viceroy
                                in having the question of the examination of passports considered
                                was to know of the movements of foreign travelers to the end that
                                the necessary measures could be taken to give them adequate
                                protection; and this is not at variance with existing treaty
                                stipulations.</p>
                            <p>The authority for traveling (in the interior) is the passport. If
                                there be no examination, how will it be possible to know whether the
                                foreign traveler is armed with a passport or not?</p>
                            <p>Hitherto there have been many passports applied for, the holders of
                                which, on arriving at a place, have secretly withheld them from
                                examination. There are also those who have recklessly gone into the
                                interior of China without passports and who have been unwilling to
                                be interrogated, and, as their intended movements can not be traced,
                                how is it possible for the local officials to know anything about
                                them?</p>
                            <p>It would in such cases be impossible for the local officials to take
                                timely action to guard against their being robbed or plundered, and
                                the offenders could only be arrested and punished after the offense
                                had been committed, and this would be too late.</p>
                            <p>In the communication of the minister of the United States it is
                                pointed out that for travelers to report to the officials would be
                                inconvenient. This there is no necessity of insisting on. And it is
                                not impracticable for the local officials to instruct their
                                subordinates, as suggested in the communication under
                                acknowledgment, to report the arrival of foreign travelers within
                                their jurisdiction. But it would be necessary for the foreign
                                travelers to show their passports to the subordinate officials <pb facs="0209" n="159" xml:id="pg_159"/> (village headmen and
                                elders) in order that they would have some authority for making a
                                report to the magistrates. If their passports are secretly withheld
                                then this would be the same as the traveler being without a
                                passport, and the local officials could not bear the responsibility
                                of providing protection.</p>
                            <p>It is further remarked in the communication under review that to
                                allow officials to plead absence or want of knowledge for not
                                performing their duty is not in accordance with Chinese law in
                                matters affecting Chinese subjects, and such excuses should not be
                                received in cases in which foreigners are concerned. To this the
                                prince and ministers would observe, How can the local officials know
                                beforehand that trouble is to occur between Chinese subjects? In
                                cases of murder it is only after the deed has been committed that
                                punishment is inflicted on the guilty according to the code, and in
                                cases where foreigners are concerned the local authorities naturally
                                could only take similar action according to law.</p>
                            <p>If passports are not examined, the local officials will not be in a
                                position to know and keep track of the foreign traveler’s movements,
                                and will not be able to guarantee that trouble may not occur, which
                                would be a matter to be regretted</p>
                            <p>As in duty bound, the prince and ministers send this communication in
                                reply for the information of the minister of the United States.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                1796.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to
                                    the <persName type="to">Tsung-li-Yamên</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-01-26"><hi rend="smallcaps">January</hi> 26,
                                        1894</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>The minister of the United States, as dean of the diplomatic body, on
                                the 20th instant had the honor to receive from the prince and
                                ministers a communication relating to the matter of foreigners when
                                traveling in China reporting in person to the local officials en
                                route their arrival as well as their intended movements.</p>
                            <p>This paper has been submitted to the foreign representatives, who
                                have requested the minister of the United States to return the
                                following answer:</p>
                            <p>The foreign representatives do not in anywise dispute the statement
                                made by the prince and ministers that their purpose is to furnish to
                                travelers adequate protection, nor do they dispute the proposition
                                that China has the right, in accordance with the treaties, to
                                require travelers to exhibit their passports when such exhibition is
                                demanded by an official thereto duly authorized.</p>
                            <p>If travelers have, as stated by the prince and ministers, secretly
                                withheld their passports from examination after having been applied
                                to to show them, such action is not approved by the foreign
                                representatives. If travelers have, as stated, recklessly gone into
                                the interior without passports, such conduct is also disapproved
                                of.</p>
                            <p>In the communication under acknowledgment the prince and ministers
                                distinctly concede that there is no necessity for travelers to
                                report to the officials, and that it is practicable for the local
                                officials to instruct their subordinates to report the arrival of
                                foreign travelers within their jurisdiction. As these were the exact
                                points of difference between the prince and ministers and the
                                foreign representatives, it would seem that there is no need for
                                further discussion thereof.</p>
                            <pb facs="0210" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/>
                            <p>The prince and ministers say, “but it would be necessary for the
                                foreign travelers to show their passports to the subordinate
                                officials (village headmen and elders) in order that they would have
                                some authority for making a report to the magistrates.”</p>
                            <p>The treaties provide that “passports, if demanded, must be produced
                                for examination in the localities passed through.” How or by what
                                official this demand shall be made is not distinctly stated.</p>
                            <p>It seems to the foreign representatives that the power or duty of
                                demanding the exhibition of passports for examination should not be
                                given to “village headmen and elders” or other numerous bodies of
                                men. Such a practice would, or might, lead to abuses and perhaps to
                                disturbances. It can serve no good purpose for foreigners to exhibit
                                their passports to the headmen of every village through which they
                                pass. On the other hand, it may be advantageous to exhibit passports
                                to the principal authorities on demand in district or prefectural
                                cities.</p>
                            <p>If it pleases the prince and ministers to adopt some regulation on
                                the subject, the foreign representatives will consider it carefully,
                                and, if it is approved, they will make it known to travelers through
                                the consuls and will enjoin compliance therewith.</p>
                            <p>The minister of the United States avails, etc.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Chas. Denby.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>