<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Baker to Mr.
                                    Gresham.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1894</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d436</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">436</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-11-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-11-18T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="alliances" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846" lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="asylum" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331" lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recbmmC3Qhr3E4JGh" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="refugees" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112309" lcsh-match="exact">Political refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recLrhH3r9BIhQsGe" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046582" lcsh-match="exact">Extradition</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-11-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-11-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="436" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d436">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Baker</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">San Salvador</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-11-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 18,
                                    1893</hi>
                        </date>. (Received December 12.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 148.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have advised you, under date of November
                            3, of impending troubles between Honduras and Nicaragua. I learn here
                            from reliable source that Salvador has been appealed to by Honduras to
                            intervene against Nicaragua, and that the Honduranean Government is
                            recruiting troops. The Government of Salvador has replied to Honduras by
                            wire, asking that hostilities be suspended until it may communicate by
                            mail.</p>
                <p>In this connection, I desire to call your attention to the treaty of
                            peace and arbitration, which was signed in this city on May 23, 1892, by
                            the commissioners from Guatemala, Salvador, Honduras, and Nicaragua, and
                            ratified since that time by the Governments of Salvador, Honduras, and
                            Nicaragua.</p>
                <p>Article 11 of that treaty provides that “it is not indispensable for the
                            validity of this treaty that it be ratified completely by all the
                            Republics who sign it. The one who may approve it shall communicate the
                            fact to the Government of Salvador, so that it may be communicated to
                            the other contracting powers. This procedure shall serve in lieu of
                            exchange of ratifications between the parties who may have approved
                            it.”</p>
                <p>And, therefore, the fact would be valid in so far as the Republics of
                            Salvador, Honduras, and Nicaragua are concerned, although the latter,
                            while it approved the treaty, never advised Salvador of the fact.</p>
                <p>The President of Salvador considers the treaty in force between the three
                            nations, and, in accordance with that view and in the interest of peace,
                            he has communicated by wire with the Governments of Honduras and
                            Nicaragua, asking them to send each a commissioner to La Union of
                            Salvador to meet there a commissioner from this country who will offer
                            the friendly offices of this Government in an effort to submit to
                            arbitration the questions at issue between Honduras and Nicaragua.</p>
                <p>To this Honduras has replied that, while the Government appreciates the
                            friendly intervention of Salvador in this matter, it desires to await
                            the reply of the other Central American Governments to its
                            communication, similar in tenor to that sent to Salvador, mention of
                            which was made above.</p>
                <p>Nicaragua has replied, thanking the Government of Salvador for its
                            intervention, and advising that a minister would be sent. I am informed
                            also by a private letter from Costa Rica that that Government has
                            offered its friendly offices to Honduras and Nicaragua in the interest
                            of <pb facs="0487" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/> a peaceful settlement of
                            the matters at issue between them. This was done, in all likelihood, in
                            reply to the communication of Honduras to the administration at San
                            Jose, of which I speak in the preceding paragraph.</p>
                <p>I beg, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lewis Baker.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No.
                                    148.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Treaty of peace and arbitration of San
                                    Salvador.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-05-23">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">May</hi> 23,
                                        1892</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Governments of Honduras, Nicaragua, Salvador, and Guatemala,
                                represented in the Central American peace congress, through their
                                respective plenipotentiaries, viz: Dr. Don Adolfo Zuñiga for
                                Honduras, General Isidro Urtecho for Nicaragua, Dr. Don Manuel
                                Gallardo for Salvador, and Dr. Cayetano Diaz Merida for Guatemala,
                                wishing to insure the benefits of peace between the Republics of
                                Central America and to strengthen at the same time the sentiments of
                                brotherhood which must serve as basis for the settlement of the
                                disputes which may arise between them, have agreed to enter into a
                                treaty covering these points, and to that end, after having
                                exhibited their respective full powers, and after conferences and
                                discussions on the subject, have agreed upon the following
                                stipulations:</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 1. The high contracting parties
                                recognize and guarantee to each other, as a basis of their
                                international public law, the following principles: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Nonintervention in the internal affairs of the respective
                                        Republics.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>The strictest neutrality in the questions or difficulties
                                        which may occur between two or more of the contracting
                                        Republics. Notwithstanding this, if any of these Republics
                                        shall permit, encourage, or protect the organization of
                                        factions within its territory, or shall invade another
                                        state, causing a “de facto” rupture, then the neutral
                                        Republics shall make common cause and shall constitute
                                        themselves into a defensive alliance with the state offended
                                        or invaded, until they shall obtain the reestablishment of
                                        peace; and</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>Arbitration as the sole method of settling or solving all
                                        questions or difficulties which may arise between the
                                        signatory Republics, whatever their cause, nature, or object
                                        may be.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. For the safeguard and application
                                of these fundamental principles a periodical delegation is
                                established, composed of five plenipotentiaries, one being named by
                                each of the Governments of Central America. This delegation shall be
                                called the “Central American Diet,” and it shall hold its inaugural
                                session on the 1st of January of the year 1893.</p>
                    <p>The sessions of the Central American Diet shall last ninety days,
                                which may be extended, at the will of said diet, when the affairs of
                                which it must take cognizance or the, public interest demand it; and
                                it may adjourn before the expiration of the term mentioned if it
                                should deem it expedient.</p>
                    <p>The meetings of the Central American Diet shall take place, in turn
                                each year, in the capitals of the contracting Republics, Guatemala,
                                Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua, and Costa Rica.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 3. The Central American Diet has the
                                following functions: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>To offer its pacific mediation when there is danger of any
                                        disagreement between the contracting Republics.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>To settle, as arbitrators, questions which may be
                                        submitted to it if pacific mediation should not suffice to
                                        end the dispute.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 4. The Central American Diet has
                                moreover the following functions: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>To draw up all the treaties involving private
                                        international law in criminal, civil, commercial, and
                                        judicial matters.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>To draw up treaties for the Central American customs,
                                        monetary, postal, and telegraphic union.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 5. When the signatory Republics wish
                                to submit their disagreements or questions to the arbitration of the
                                Central American Diet, the Republic believing itself menaced or
                                offended shall present to the diet, through its plenipotentiary, a
                                memorandum stating the grounds of complaint. The plenipotentiary of
                                the Republic against which the memorandum shall have been drawn up
                                shall present one of explanations. If in that one there should also
                                be complaints, the plenipotentiary who took the initiative shall
                                reply.</p>
                    <p>With these documents before them the plenipotentiaries of the
                                Republics not directly interested in the question shall deliberate
                                in regard to the means of conciliation which may appear the most
                                equitable and efficacious, and shall submit them to the
                                consideration of the plenipotentiaries of the differing Republics,
                                in order to try to reach an agreement.</p>
                    <pb facs="0488" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/>
                    <p>If such agreement can not he attained, the competent
                                plenipotentiaries shall name arbitrators to complete the diet from
                                among the ministers of the friendly nations, residing in Central
                                America.</p>
                    <p>The majority of votes shall constitute a decisive award.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 6. If when the Central American Diet
                                is not in session any question should arise between two or more of
                                the contracting Republics, the Governments having no interest in the
                                dispute shall, upon hearing thereof, interpose their friendly
                                offices to bring about a settlement. If this should not be possible,
                                they shall advise the contending parties to submit their
                                disagreements to the arbitral award of the diet or of any friendly
                                nation.</p>
                    <p>If the Governments concerned should express the desire that the diet
                                settle the pending question or disagreement, the latter shall be
                                called together, without any loss of time, by one or more of the
                                mediating or neutral Governments.</p>
                    <p>In this case the diet shall proceed in conformity with the provisions
                                of article 5.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 7. If the disagreeing Governments
                                should not wish to submit their disagreements to the arbitration of
                                the Central American Diet, the designation of the arbitrator, the
                                terms of the question, and the rules to be observed until the
                                rendering of the award, shall be the subjects of a special
                                treaty.</p>
                    <p>Such treaty shall be signed within the term of four months after the
                                grounds of disagreement shall have become known.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 8. Until the contracting Governments
                                shall agree upon special treaties regulating asylum and the
                                recognition of their public documents, it is provided that the
                                removal from the frontier of political refugees, stipulated in the
                                treaties, shall take place without any further proceedings than the
                                demand of the Government of the nation whence they come, to the
                                Government of the nation in which they took refuge.</p>
                    <p>And it is also stipulated that the verification of the authenticity
                                of public documents issued by any of the contracting Republics shall
                                be sufficient to establish the validity and force of such documents
                                and their effectiveness in securing in any of the Republics the
                                results inherent to their nature as if they had been issued by that
                                Republic itself.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 9. The treaties and conventions
                                entered into heretofore by and between the Republics of Guatemala,
                                Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua, and Costa Rica in matters relating to
                                peace, friendship, commerce, and extradition, and in any other
                                matters not in conflict with the present stipulations, are
                                considered valid and in force in conformity with the internal
                                constitutional law of these countries.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 10. The present treaty shall be
                                submitted to the Government of Costa Rica for its adhesion.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 11. It is not indispensable to the
                                validity of this treaty that, it be formally ratified by all the
                                Republics who sign it. The one who may approve it shall communicate
                                the fact to the Government of Salvador, so that it may be
                                communicated to the other contracting powers. This procedure shall
                                serve in lieu of exchange of ratifications between the parties who
                                may have approved it.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">In testimony whereof the respective
                                    plenipotentiaries sign this treaty in quadruplicate, at
                                        <placeName>San Salvador</placeName>, on <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-05-23">the 23d day of May,
                                        1892</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Adolfo Zuñiga</hi>,</item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Gallardo</hi>,</item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Isidro Urtecho</hi>,</item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cayetano Diaz Merida.</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
