<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-01-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="646" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d646">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Taylor</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-01-05"><hi rend="italic">January 5, 1895</hi></date>.
                                (Received January 18.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 283.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am happy to report that the demand
                            contained in your telegram of the 15th ultimo as to the reduction of
                            tariff dues imposed upon American products in Cuba and Puerto Rico has
                            produced the desired result sooner than I expected, although both the
                            ministers of state and ultramar had assured me that they would do all in
                            their power to comply with your wishes. I inclose herein an extract<note n="1" xml:id="d646fn1">Not printed.</note> (with translation) taken
                            from El Imparcial, of the 4th instant, which will explain to you what
                            took place in the council upon this subject on the day before. From this
                            you will see that the real pressure came from the Cuban deputies, and
                            that the slight advantage given to Cuban sugars by our present tariff
                            was taken as the ostensible reason for making the concession demanded.
                            Yesterday the subsecretary of state, who has a special knowledge of the
                            subject, was sent by his chief to the legation to express to me the
                            conclusion reached by the council on the day before. The interview and
                            its result I communicated to you in a telegram. From this you will see
                            that all you have asked has been conceded without any new concessions
                            from the United States. The subsecretary gave me to understand that
                            under the form of a modus vivendi the concession could be made to accord
                            at once with the requirements of the Spanish tariff and with the demands
                            of public opinion.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hannis Taylor.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>