<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1894-05-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1894-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="807" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d807">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bartleman</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-05-18"><hi rend="italic">May 18, 1894</hi></date>.
                                (Received May 28.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 150.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my Nos. 112 and 145, of the
                            3d ultimo and 9th instant, with regard to the question of navigation of
                            the bayous Macareo and Pedernales of the Orinoco River, and the
                            detention at Ciudad Bolivar of the American steamer <hi rend="italic">Bolivar</hi> for an alleged violation of the navigation laws
                            regarding these channels, I have the honor to inform you that up to this
                            time I have received no further communications from the consular agent
                            at that place.</p>
                        <p>I have called upon the minister of foreign affairs on several occasions
                            with the hope of obtaining a special permit for the steamer’s return
                            through the Macareo channel, but since she has changed her flag the
                            desired permission seems difficult to procure.</p>
                        <p>On the 14th instant I received two letters, dated Trinidad the 9th
                            instant, from the manager of the General Steamship Company, in which he
                            states that he is leaving that day for Ciudad Bolivar; that on his
                            arrival there he proposes to ask for a regular clearance, and if refused
                            he will bring the steamer away unless detained by force. Fearing that
                            further complications might arise from such action, I sent him a
                            telegram on the same day, advising him to act with discretion. Later the
                            same evening received a telegram from Mr. Carpenter, dated the 12th,
                            stating that the steamer was still illegally detained, and requesting me
                            to ask you for instructions to demand the release of the vessel, which I
                            thought was unnecessary, as she is not detained except by the agent, who
                            either can not or will not give the bond of 10,000 bolivars required,
                                <pb facs="0841" n="791" xml:id="pg_791"/> and who insists upon
                            returning through the channels. The steamer is at liberty to depart
                            through the “Boca Grande” when this is done.</p>
                        <p>I have refrained from any discussion with the minister of foreign affairs
                            as to the right of navigating these channels, having in mind the
                            Department’s No. 308, of November 4, 1892 (Mr. Foster to Mr. Scruggs),
                            in which is asked “whether the bayous of that river were open to the
                            flags of all nations, especially our own.”</p>
                        <p>I know that the public sentiment is against the decree of July 1, 1893,
                            closing these channels, and that such a regulation is most unjust to
                            ourselves; but in the absence of any instructions from you I have not
                            felt at liberty to protest against it.</p>
                        <p>Awaiting your instructions,</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">R. M. Bartleman.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                150.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Carpenter</persName>
                                    to Mr. <persName type="to">Bartleman</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port of Spain</hi></placeName>,<lb/><date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-05-09"><hi rend="italic">May
                                            9, 1894</hi></date>. (Received May
                                14.)</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Sir</hi>: The General Steamship
                                Company’s steamer <hi rend="italic">Bolivar</hi> is still being
                                detained at Ciudad Bolivar by the Venezuelan authorities; and by the
                                arrival at this port this a.m. of the Venezuelan gunboat <hi rend="italic">Gen. Rivas</hi>, direct from Ciudad Bolivar, I
                                received information that the telegraph wires between Ciudad Bolivar
                                and Caracas were broken and all communication cut off.</p>
                            <p>I am informed that a treaty exists between the United States of
                                America and Venezuela which grants to vessels of the United States
                                the free navigation of all Venezuelan rivers flowing into the
                                sea.</p>
                            <p>The steamship <hi rend="italic">Bolivar</hi> having been refused a
                                clearance by the collector of the port of Ciudad Bolivar, who claims
                                he is acting under instructions from Caracas, would it not be proper
                                to sail without a clearance, unless forcibly detained? Our case
                                seems to me to be similar to the case of the Red “D” steamship <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> was refused a clearance last year at La
                                Guayra for refusing to surrender a passenger, General Mjares, who
                                was a political refugee, and proceeded to New York without a
                                clearance.</p>
                            <p>This detention of the <hi rend="italic">Bolivar</hi> is causing
                                serious damage to our business, and if continued longer will result
                                in great pecuniary loss to the General Steamship Company, even
                                threatening tototally destroy the business which they have been
                                carrying on for sixteen years.</p>
                            <p>Hoping your efforts in our behalf may be successful, I remain,</p>
                            <p>Yours, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Geo. F. Carpenter</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Manager.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                150.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Carpenter</persName>
                                    to Mr. <persName type="to">Bartleman</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port of Spain</hi></placeName>,<lb/><date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-05-09"><hi rend="italic">May
                                            9, 1894</hi></date>. (Received May
                                14.)</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My dear Sir</hi>: After writing you this morning
                                I consulted Mr. William P. Pierce, United States consul, and acting
                                on his advice I have decided to go to Ciudad Bolivar myself by the
                                steamer leaving to-day. <pb facs="0842" n="792" xml:id="pg_792"/> On
                                my arrival there I propose to ask for a regular clearance from the
                                collector of customs, and if it is again refused, I intend to bring
                                the steamship <hi rend="italic">Bolivar</hi> away from Ciudad
                                Bolivar at once, unless detained by force by the authorities. Our
                                detention is illegal and without reason, and the line of procedure
                                at present marked out may bring matters to a crisis.</p>
                            <p>I write this to prepare you for anything you may hear from Ciudad
                                Bolivar.</p>
                            <p>Yours, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Geo. F.
                                Carpenter.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                                    150.—Telegram.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Carpenter</persName>
                                    to Mr. <persName type="to">Bartleman</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ciudad Bolivar</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-05-12"><hi rend="italic">May
                                            12, 1894</hi></date>. (Received May
                                14.)</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Bolivar</hi> still illegally detained. Full
                                particulars of the case already in possession of State Department,
                                Washington. If you can do nothing, ask for instructions from
                                Washington. Demand immediate release, Please wire answer here to me
                                at this place at once.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Geo. F. Carpenter</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Manager.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No.
                                    150.—Telegram.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bartleman</persName>
                                    to Mr. <persName type="to">Carpenter</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-05-14T10:00:00-04:27"><hi rend="italic">May 14,
                                            1894</hi>—(10 a.m.)</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>Your letter dated Trinidad May 9 received to-day. Read my telegrams
                                to your agent at Ciudad Bolivar. Act with discretion and do not
                                complicate matters.</p>
                            <p>You are in error as to treaty.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Richard M. Bartleman</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>