<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-08-20T16:42:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-08-20T16:42:00-05:00" n="219" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d219">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/1589: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Collier</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-08-20T17:00:00-04:42"><hi rend="italic">August 20,
                                        1925—5 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 10:02
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>77. Last week rumors reached me that more than a hundred natives of Tacna
                            were detained prisoners here in Santiago in various barracks. I
                            investigated immediately and requested information from Minister for
                            Foreign Affairs. He ordered inquiry and several days later informed me
                            that 120 men who had refused to report for military service had been
                            compelled to report and had been sent to various regiments here to
                            render the required service; that they were not detained, except that no
                            soldier can leave his regiment without being guilty of desertion, and
                            that a list of these men would be given Pershing through the Chilean
                            Commissioner and to you through Mathieu; they would be returned to Tacna
                            for the plebiscite whenever Pershing desires. Shall I communicate this
                            information to Pershing? Minister for Foreign Affairs asserted that he
                            and President Alessandri knew nothing of matter and that the military
                            authorities look upon it as a customary application of the rules of
                            military discipline; nevertheless, I doubt that without my intervention
                            these men would have been allowed to return to the provinces to
                            vote.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Collier</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>