<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Consul at Arica ( (Von Tresckow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1925v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1925-10-31T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1925-10-31T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-10-31T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-10-31T13:00:00-05:00" n="242"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/1663: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Consul at Arica</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Von Tresckow</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-10-31T13:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 31, 1925—1 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>For Pershing: Your telegram October 29, 8 p.m. See my telegram of Oct. 29, 5 p.m.
                    The following has just been received from Ambassador Collier dated October 30, 1
                    p.m.: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>This morning Minister for Foreign Affairs informed me that Chilean
                            Cabinet yesterday decided to make every sacrifice necessary <pb
                                facs="0535" n="409" xml:id="pg_409"/> to avoid rupture of
                            plebiscite; that wide divergence of views exists between Edwards and
                            Government; that Edwards will be summoned to Santiago at once; and that
                            if he does not then agree with Government’s policy he will be replaced.
                            Minister also informed me that, as General Pershing had expressed
                            opinion that Chile ought to have no officer in province of higher rank
                            than colonel, present commanding officer would be called to Santiago
                            very soon and would not be sent back to Tacna. Minister also said that
                            present <hi rend="italic">intendente</hi> would probably be replaced
                            this coming week and would probably be succeeded by former Minister for
                            Foreign Affairs, Jorge Matte. The Minister strongly requests that you
                            instruct General Pershing to postpone action on proposed resolutions for
                            week or so until Government of Chile can carry out foregoing program. In
                            deference to difficult situation of Government here and its manifest
                            desire to carry the award into effect honorably, and also in view of its
                            difficulties with jingoistic element and with extreme national sentiment
                            of population of Arica, I sincerely hope that you can grant Minister’s
                            request.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Today at noon I replied to Collier that you are on ground with full knowledge of
                    local conditions and with authority to carry out fair and free election as
                    provided in award; that you possess my full confidence and that of Arbitrator;
                    that it is impossible under the circumstances for me to give you instructions
                    and directions about details of manner in which award is to be carried out; and
                    that I will transmit for your information and careful consideration the request
                    of Chilean Minister for Foreign Affairs.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
