<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-11-12T14:42:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-11-12T14:42:00-05:00" n="246" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d246">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/1679: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Collier</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-11-12T15:00:00-04:42"><hi rend="italic">November 12,
                                        1925—3 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received November 13—9:50
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>118. Department’s No. 72, November 11, 11 a.m. I informed the Chilean
                            Foreign Office of Peruvian complaints made to me, and the Ministry sent
                            the Counselor to see me. He volunteered following information: Few of
                            those maintained by the Government are from Tacna, and these will all be
                            repatriated at expense of Government before date of plebiscite if they
                            desire to be. Greater part of those brought here from Tarapacá were
                            brought because of Government’s desire to protect them from popular
                            violence arising from suspicion that Peruvians had promoted disorders.
                            All are maintained at Government expense. Minister of Foreign Affairs
                            was not aware of this until Peruvians made complaints. He says this was
                            stupid use of funds and states that police and administrative
                            authorities were permitted to do it because no other funds were
                            available. All who wished would be sent back; but it was believed that,
                            being well cared for, they will prefer to stay here. Conclusion of
                            Counselor’s statement.</p>
                        <pb facs="0539" n="413" xml:id="pg_413"/>
                        <p>This version of Chilean Government’s action has since been confirmed by
                            Minister for Foreign Affairs, who expresses willingness to have
                            Government of the United States make inquiries, and asserts his desire
                            to give information on any complaint that may be brought to his
                            attention. Since first call at the Embassy, Peruvians have come here
                            daily to say that they were not molested by neighbors in the north and
                            needed no protection from them; that they are remaining here
                            involuntarily; but that since first complaint was made to me they have
                            been required to sign statements to contrary and upon refusal have been
                            threatened with repatriation, but without indemnification or the
                            opportunity to earn a living.</p>
                        <p>These cases I have not discussed with the Foreign Office. Writer of first
                            complaint to me said that he addressed me because numerous letters to
                            Plebiscitary Commission had apparently been intercepted.</p>
                        <p>I am convinced that practically all of these deportations were
                            unjustified and are related to the plebiscite, and that charges of
                            communistic activity are pretexts. …</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>I respectfully submit my view, in answer to your request. It is quite
                            apparent that our duty requires us not to ignore any fact which affects
                            the plebiscite, or any relevant statement if it is not inherently
                            improbable. Our diplomatic and consular officers in Chile should be free
                            to take statements from all who assert that rights granted them by award
                            are being violated or whose liberty appears to be abridged because of
                            their lawful activities in connection with the plebiscite. Diplomatic
                            and consular officers, at least under the present circumstances, should
                            avoid everything susceptible of being construed as espionage or police
                            investigation or interference with administrative action; but they
                            should be free to hear complaints and, after previously consulting with
                            the authorities, even to visit places of residence or detention, and
                            their interviews with complainants should be private to avoid fear of
                            later punishment by complainants. Impartiality, in my opinion, requires
                            that after complaint has been received, then Chilean authorities should
                            be fully informed and given opportunity to explain or to refute. …</p>
                        <p>I am confident that if I bring these complaints to the attention of the
                            present Minister for Foreign Affairs, he will accept and probably
                            suggest course of procedure I have just outlined. I believe it even
                            possible to obtain his promise to give complete list of all natives of
                            Tacna now in Chile with their present residence and changes of residence
                            in future and to acknowledge the right of unrestricted correspondence
                            and interview between them and American diplomatic, consular, or
                            plebiscitary representatives. Embassy and consulates should keep in
                            touch in order to ascertain reliability of statements made, and
                            especially to ascertain that the repatriated really get home.</p>
                        <pb facs="0540" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/>
                        <p>… I believe bitterness which Chileans feel against our observers in
                            Tacna, and in certain places against our consuls, arises from Chilean
                            belief that they conduct ex parte investigations, encourage Peruvian
                            complaints, and do not give Chile chance to explain or refute.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Collier</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>