<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the British Ambassador ( (Howard))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1925v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d436</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">436</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1925-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1925-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Domestic politics</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="436"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d436">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/6109</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Howard</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-04-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 2, 1925</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                    receipt of your note No. 309 of March 27, 1925, in which it is stated that the
                    British Government fears that civil war may again break out in the near future
                    in North China to the serious detriment of the country in general and to its
                    arteries of communication in particular. In view of these circumstances, you
                    state that the British Ambassador in <pb facs="0734" n="608" xml:id="pg_608"/>
                    Tokyo has been instructed to ascertain from the Japanese Government whether it
                    desires to make any proposals with a view to international consultation or the
                    use of diplomatic pressure upon the rival Chinese groups so as to prevent the
                    hostilities now threatened. You add that it appears to the British Government
                    that this is an opportune moment for Japan to submit constructive proposals
                    calling for joint pacific action and that you have been directed to solicit the
                    cooperation of the American Government in approaching Japan upon this important
                    matter.</p>
                <p>The seriousness of the present situation in China, with its menace of a further
                    outbreak of civil war, has not failed to cause this Government also the greatest
                    concern; and it has therefore given the most careful consideration to the
                    proposals of the British Government as stated in your note. As a result of a
                    thorough review of the matter, I venture to submit the following observations as
                    briefly summarizing the views of this Government: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The use of diplomatic pressure upon the rival Chinese groups so as to
                            prevent hostilities would in effect constitute a form of interference in
                            the domestic affairs of China. In the recent hostilities, it has been
                            the carefully observed policy of the principal Powers concerned,
                            including Japan, to abstain from such intervention, a policy which this
                            Government believes has had much to do with the comparative immunity of
                            foreign persons and property within the areas affected. It does not
                            appear that the hostilities now threatened are likely to be of a
                            character essentially different from such conflicts as have hitherto
                            occurred, and this Government is scarcely inclined to believe, in view
                            of the declared policy of the Japanese Government of non-interference in
                            such matters, that a suggestion to that Government that it initiate a
                                <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> of the character described, would
                            prove acceptable. In this connection, the speech of the Japanese
                            Minister for Foreign Affairs at the recent opening of the Diet appears
                            most pertinent,—particularly the statement that the Japanese Government
                            had no intention whatever of interfering in the domestic affairs of
                            China and that it had consistently conformed to that policy.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Irrespective, however, of the attitude of the Japanese Government
                            toward a proposal to apply diplomatic pressure with a view to the
                            prevention of hostilities, this Government is of the view that pressure
                            limited to joint pacific action would not prove effectual and would in
                            all probability be disregarded by whichever faction sought to profit by
                            taking the offensive.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Aside from the question of the doubtful efficacy of the course
                            proposed, this Government cannot escape the conviction that such an
                            effort to influence by external pressure the course of Chinese domestic
                            politics would almost certainly aggravate, and perhaps render critical,
                                <pb facs="0735" n="609" xml:id="pg_609"/> the present wide-spread
                            anti-foreign sentiment among certain classes of the Chinese people. As
                            the British Government is aware, the last few months have seen a
                            recrudescence of such sentiment, which has manifested itself acutely at
                            various places throughout China and has appeared in different forms,
                            opposing foreign capital, foreign education, and foreign Christian
                            missions. While this Government has no desire to exaggerate the dangers
                            of this situation, it is reluctant to assume the risk of exacerbating
                            such sentiment by adopting a course which seems likely at the same time
                            to prove ineffectual for the purposes in mind, and to afford a basis for
                            a possible charge of favoring one faction as against another.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>This Government, therefore, while viewing with the greatest sympathy the objects
                    which the British Government has in mind, and not wishing to close the door to a
                    consideration of any practical suggestion which may be evolved, regrets that it
                    cannot see its way to adopt the course of action proposed in your note of March
                    27.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
