<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State ( (Grew))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1925v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d504</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">504</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1925-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1925-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="504"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d504">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.5045/75</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Grew</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-06-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 6, 1925.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Situation at Shanghai</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Chinese Minister called on me and said that he had talked the other night at
                    the British Embassy with the Secretary who suggested that he come to the
                    Department if he had any concrete proposals to make. The Minister said that no
                    doubt we had much more information regarding the situation in Shanghai than he
                    had, but that nevertheless he desired to leave nothing undone to cooperate with
                    us with a view to bringing about the termination of the trouble. He said he had
                    sent one of his young secretaries who was a student last year to the meeting of
                    Chinese students in Washington the other night and had persuaded them materially
                    to modify the resolution which they were sending to the Chinese students in
                    Shanghai. Unfortunately, he had not had an opportunity to see the resolution in
                    its final form or he would have endeavored to secure the elimination of the term
                    “brutal assault”.</p>
                <pb facs="0784" n="658" xml:id="pg_658"/>
                <p>The Minister said that the purpose of his visit was to ask if we would not make
                    representations to the British Government to avoid extreme measures. I informed
                    him subsequently, through Mr. Lockhart, that we did not feel ourselves in a
                    position to make such representations at the present moment. (The Secretary had
                    told me that he desired to take no step which might in any way interfere with
                    the solidarity of the Powers.)</p>
                <p>I then told the Minister that our instructions to our authorities in Shanghai
                    were to the effect that they should take adequate measures for the protection of
                    American lives and property, but to do nothing more. The Minister said it would
                    have a very salutary effect if he could be authorized to let this be known in
                    Shanghai. After consulting with the Secretary I asked Mr. Lockhart to inform the
                    Minister, who was then in his office, that the Minister might telegraph to his
                    Government and let it be known in Shanghai that our naval forces and marines
                    were present in Shanghai only for the purpose of protecting American lives and
                    property and that no other action was contemplated at the present time.</p>
                <p>The Minister said that he considered it unfortunate that we had permitted the
                    publication of Mr. Cunningham’s despatch stating that the killing of the Chinese
                    students was justified. It would have been all right if we had added that the
                    killings were justified in order to protect American lives; that the Chinese
                    students here had jumped at the conclusion that the attitude of the Consul
                    General was that wholesale murders of Chinese were justified without giving
                    adequate reasons therefor. He said he had explained to the Chinese students the
                    meaning of the Consul General’s message.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">oseph</hi>] C. G[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >rew</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
