<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Great Britain (
                    (Houghton))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1925v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d545</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">545</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1925-08-21T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1925-08-21T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-08-21T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-08-21T16:00:00-05:00" n="545"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d545">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.5045/187: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Houghton</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-08-21T17:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 21, 1925—5 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>272. Your 257, August 15, 3 p.m. was communicated in substance to American
                    Legation at Peking. The American Minister replies that in his mind and in those
                    of several of his colleagues whose opinion he respects, there is no doubt that
                    McEuen’s resignation is necessary and that the proposal that he be “suspended
                    without prejudice” pending the inquiry would be regarded by the Chinese as a
                    mere device to let him have a holiday until the judicial inquiry has returned
                    the finding that it is not competent to review his exercise of the
                    administrative discretion confided to him.</p>
                <p>He points out that McEuen is an administrative officer whose continuance in the
                    office is the occasion for ill-will and distrust not only <pb facs="0825"
                        n="699" xml:id="pg_699"/> locally but throughout China. You are authorized
                    to communicate the above to the British Foreign Office and to state that we hope
                    that the British Government may find itself able to reconsider its position in
                    this connection in view of the desirability that early action of a conciliatory
                    nature should be taken in connection with the Shanghai matter. It is the
                    considered view of this Government that as much should be done as is possible to
                    make some advance toward a settlement of the Shanghai matter in order to get
                    that out of the way before the Special Conference on Tariffs meets in
                    October.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
