<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-09-08T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-09-08T22:00:00-05:00" n="597" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d597">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/6590: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-09-09T11:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">September 9,
                                        1925—11 a.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 2:10
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>384. My telegram No. 293, July 28, 9 p.m. [<hi rend="italic">a.m.</hi>]<note n="53" xml:id="d597fn53"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_799">p. 799</ref>.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>It appear that by a process so gradual that the phases of its
                                development have scarcely been discernible there has come about in
                                general an abatement of the tensity of Chinese feeling such as to
                                warrant the hope that the crisis has passed. The Chinese no longer
                                “see red”; the aggressive movement against foreign rights and
                                interests has slackened; strikes and boycotts continue apparently
                                out of sheer momentum but with no new impulse behind them.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>These generalizations are subject to local exceptions particularly
                                in the case of Canton which is now more than ever under Soviet
                                domination and to that extent abnormal to Chinese conditions. They
                                are moreover subject to the qualification that they are less
                                strictly applicable to conditions in proportion to the distance
                                south from Yangtze.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>To a large degree also a distinction must be made between British
                                and other interests. The Japanese originally grouped with the
                                British have from the beginning perceived psychological crux of the
                                problem and by an assiduously conciliatory attitude towards Chinese
                                sensibilities have succeeded almost completely in “getting out from
                                under” and putting themselves on virtually the same basis as those
                                who like ourselves have been merely incidentally affected by the
                                present outburst of ethnical self-consciousness on the part of the
                                Chinese. The British Chamber of Commerce and China Association of
                                Shanghai have recently adopted and communicated to the Chinese
                                Chamber of Commerce resolutions so ludicrously ingratiating in
                                contrast with the previous attitude of community which they
                                represent that the fact of their being received without adverse
                                comment is in itself an evidence of subsidence of Chinese feeling
                                even towards the British.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Although the aggressiveness of feeling may have passed its crisis
                                it would be a mistake to assume that the volcano has burnt itself
                                out, that the danger is over and that things in China have reverted
                                to what they were before. The passionate intensity of feeling has
                                been succeeded by a new sentiment that involves at once sullenly
                                suspicious attitude towards foreign nations and a rather
                                complacently self-conscious conviction that Chinese have scored once
                                and can do it again when they want to. Representative Chinese talk
                                in more or <pb facs="0865" n="739" xml:id="pg_739"/> less detached
                                fashion about the defects and possibilities of mass action, half
                                apologizing for the abatement in the movement of self-assertion and
                                half-threatening recrudescence of it if occasion should arise. I
                                believe there is still the possibility of a new movement which might
                                be set in train by affront to their pride even by some casual
                                accident as the situation is still explosive.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The recent after-developments of the situation seem to add
                                confirmation to the belief that the whole crisis through which the
                                Chinese Government have been passing is emotional rather than
                                logical and that it is less concerned with substraction [<hi rend="italic">abstract?</hi>] rights and obligations (which are
                                only vaguely understood by any but the exceptionally keen minds
                                among them who for the most part understand also the reasons for
                                abnormal state of things in China) than with appearances and
                                amenities of intercourse.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>There is of course a development here which, whatever the
                                crudities of its manifestations, is real and must be met. But it is
                                accompanied by much plausible assumption which has no basis whatever
                                in fact. Idealistic though term of about the [apparently garbled
                                groups] possibilities of the Chinese people and sympathetic towards
                                their somewhat elementary yearnings towards nationality, it is a
                                case [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] nevertheless incumbent upon those
                                who deal with China today to keep in mind that in relation to the
                                present problem China consists of two elements: first, the faction
                                recognized as the government which is in control in Peking and which
                                only wants money to go on with, and second, the articulate element
                                of China’s population which, most of it, holds the so-called
                                government in contempt but is momentarily willing to array itself
                                behind that effigy or [<hi rend="italic">of</hi>] sovereignty for
                                the sake of gaining “face” for the ethnic group which calls itself
                                the Chinese nation as opposed to the foreigner. It behoves us
                                therefore to be on our guard against the assumption that a
                                concession to be [<hi rend="italic">the?</hi>] government is <hi rend="italic">ipso facto</hi> concession to that growing
                                national sentiment with whose healthy development we would be
                                disposed to sympathize. It is in fact quite possible that any
                                concrete concession enabling the present governing faction to
                                consolidate its power over the country would incur the active
                                resentment of the very elements which are urging in the abstract the
                                necessity for such concessions. I venture this observation in view
                                of the considerable amount of American comment reprinted here which
                                advances upon the facile assumption that the problem is to decide
                                whether or not we are prepared to satisfy the legitimate aspirations
                                of the Chinese people.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Repeated by mail to Tokyo.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>