<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-07-10T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-07-10T09:00:00-05:00" n="648" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d648">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.00/76: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Mayer</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-07-10T22:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">July 10,
                                        1925—10 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received July 10—7:30
                                p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>270. Following from MacMurray. Your 142, July 9, 3 p.m.<note n="84" xml:id="d648fn84">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>My own conviction is that the present ebullition of national
                                self-consciousness on the part of the Chinese Government can be
                                diverted from actions and uncontrolled hostility to foreign rights
                                and interests only by consistent and scrupulous observation by the
                                powers of the obligations already undertaken by them at the
                                Washington Conference for the alleviation of what the Chinese regard
                                as anomalous inequalities imposed upon them by the treaty. I,
                                therefore, feel that we should resist any temptation to deviate from
                                the course laid down by the Washington treaty and resolutions, and
                                that we would be in a stronger position if the contemplated purposes
                                of those agreements were to fail through the fault of the Chinese
                                than if we were to deny the Chinese the opportunity for a
                                reconsideration by the treaty powers of the several problems which
                                the Washington Conference offered them the opportunity to discuss.
                                In the face of the present agitation against foreign treaty rights,
                                a strict adherence to the Washington Conference program seems to me
                                the only safe road.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I feel that British note No. 683, July 7th, presents
                                considerations which the powers strongly urged upon the
                                consideration of the Chinese, but that to make these considerations
                                a condition precedent to a fulfillment of our international
                                obligation would merely inflame a popular psychology already
                                abnormal and prone to seek occasions for the further embitterment of
                                feeling against all foreigners.</item>
                            <pb facs="0905" n="779" xml:id="pg_779"/>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>My recommendation is, therefore, that the Department should insist
                                upon literal fulfillment of obligations undertaken by the powers in
                                respect to Special Conference and the Commission on
                                Extraterritoriality.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Mayer</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>