<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-08-03T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-08-03T16:00:00-05:00" n="669" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d669">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.00/114: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-08-03T17:00:00-04:00"><hi rend="italic">August 3,
                                        1925—5 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>181. Your 306 August 1, 9 P.M. Department’s 180 of August 1, 3 P.M.
                            covers conversation which Japanese Ambassador had with me on July 31,
                            evidently in response to his Government’s instructions mentioned in
                            paragraph 2 of your telegram.</p>
                        <p>… In any case, the Japanese Government should have been prepared for this
                            Government’s views as Tokyo’s 118 of July 1, 4 P.M.<note n="13" xml:id="d669fn13"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_836">836</ref>.</note> indicates that you expressed the opinion that
                            “the present situation in China makes it necessary for the special
                            economic conference to assume a position a little beyond the scope of
                            the conference in order to reestablish Chinese confidence.” As stated to
                            you in Department’s 170, July 28, 2 P.M. the British Embassy here
                            communicated to the Department the text of a proposed declaration which
                            the British Government desired to use as the basis for an identic
                            expression on the part of the Powers of their attitude toward the
                            Chinese proposals, the opening sentences of which I now quote more
                            fully: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Washington Customs Treaty provided for the early convocation
                                    of a conference at which by the agreement between China and the
                                    Nine Powers certain economic measures should be adopted for the
                                    benefit of China as a whole. The spirit animating the Powers
                                    remains today what it was then. Various subsequent changes in
                                    the situation which have delayed the meeting of a conference
                                    have not affected the original intentions of the Powers; on the
                                    contrary, they have confirmed these intentions whilst the Powers
                                    themselves consider that the objects of the Washington
                                    Conference are to fulfill an agreement to be reached at the
                                    Tariff Conference which will require to be of a more
                                    far-reaching and comprehensive nature than was originally
                                    contemplated. The Powers further hope that the Tariff Conference
                                    will be but the first step in a comprehensive revision of the
                                    treaties which they express their willingness to undertake at
                                    the earliest opportunity.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>British viewpoint was adopted in preparing Department’s draft of proposed
                            reply as this Government was and is ready to extend the scope of the
                            conference beyond that originally intended by the treaty. You should
                            know that British Government submitted its views also to Japanese
                            Government and that Japanese amendment of British proposal omitted all
                            reference to extension of scope of conference. It would therefore seem
                            that Shidehara, finding British Government and this Government ready to
                            extend the scope of the Conference, is endeavoring as a last resort to
                            bring about a reconsideration <pb facs="0937" n="811" xml:id="pg_811"/>
                            of this matter on the part of this Government by referring to your
                            conversation in Tokyo expressing views held by the Department prior to
                            consideration of Chinese proposals of June 24.</p>
                        <p>I have just received a note from British Embassy<note n="14" xml:id="d669fn14">Note No. 723 of July 30, <ref target="#pg_805">p.
                                    805</ref>.</note> informing me of instructions which the British
                            Government have communicated to their Chargé in Peking for his guidance
                            in discussing with you American draft. The note states, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, that British Chargé has been
                            “informed that his Majesty’s Government disapprove the statement in the
                            American draft reply that the Extraterritorial Commission will be
                            instructed to make recommendations to enable the Powers to consider what
                            steps may be taken for relinquishing their extraterritorial rights,
                            inasmuch as my Government feel that the commission should be allowed to
                            make such recommendations as may appear to them desirable without any
                            lead from the Powers.” You should point out to British Chargé that
                            language of American draft states that this Government desires to
                            instruct its commissioner to include in his report recommendations based
                            upon the findings of the commission which will enable the Governments
                            concerned to consider “what, if any, steps may be taken” and not “what
                            steps may be taken.” The British note also objects to the use of the
                            term tariff autonomy. This objection will be met, it seems to me, by
                            alternate phraseology mentioned in Department’s 173 of July 30, 1 P.M.
                            British note also objects to the use of phrases such as “constant and
                            sympathetic interest” and “gratification at progress in the improvement
                            of the Chinese judicial system.” I have no objection to the omission
                            from the text of draft reply of the clauses “and has watched the growth
                            of that sentiment with constant and sympathetic interest,”
                            “sympathetically and hopefully [<hi rend="italic">helpfully?</hi>]” and
                            “it has been gratified to note the progress that has been made in this
                            connection.”</p>
                        <p>With reference to paragraph 10 of your telegram you should know that text
                            of Department’s draft reply has been communicated to all of the Powers
                            party to the Washington Conference and to those Powers who have
                            indicated their adherence to Resolution No. 5. They were told that this
                            draft was to be used by you as a basis for discussing the Powers’ reply
                            to Chinese Government’s policies of June 24.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>