<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-12-30T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-12-30T20:00:00-05:00" n="80" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d80">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51 W 89France/50a: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Herrick</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-12-30T20:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">December
                                            30, 1924—8 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>493. Extracts from statement of so-called “balance sheet of France”
                                issued by Finance Minister Clémentel<note n="21" xml:id="d80fn1"><hi rend="italic">Inventaire de la Situation Financière de la
                                        France au Début de la Treizième Législature, présenté par M.
                                        Clémentel, Ministre des Finances</hi> (Paris, Imprimerie
                                    Nationale, 1924).</note> has [<hi rend="italic">have</hi>] been
                                given wide publicity in press and have caused most unfavorable
                                impression. It would appear that Clémentel endorses a policy not in
                                accord with the statements heretofore made to you as reported in
                                your letter of December 12th,<note n="22" xml:id="d80fn2">Not
                                    printed; see the Ambassador’s telegram No. 550, Dec. 8, <ref target="#pg_132">p. 132</ref>.</note> or with the statements
                                made to the World War Foreign Debt Commission by M. Parmentier. For
                                instance, the report is said to contain the following:<note n="23" xml:id="d80fn3"><hi rend="italic">Inventaire</hi>, pp.
                                    72–74.</note>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“This technical exposition of the elements which constitute
                                        our debt to the United States and Britain doesn’t seem,
                                        however, sufficient to justify a brutal addition to our
                                        liabilities of the sums which it seems to represent.</p>
                                    <p>“The question of a settlement of our debts to Britain and
                                        America has just raised the general problem of interallied
                                        debts, an examination of which has not yet been seriously
                                        taken up because of the uncertainty existing from a lack of
                                        accord among the Allies on ways and means of the payment of
                                        reparations by Germany. …<note n="24" xml:id="d80fn4">Omission indicated in the original telegram.</note> If
                                        we abandon the juridical plane and look on the matter from
                                        the higher view of cooperation and fairness, strict justice
                                        would seem to demand a general pooling of war expenditures
                                        and their allotment among the allied States proportionately
                                        to the riches of each one, and without taking count of the
                                        particular engagements which the necessities of the moment
                                        imposed. …<note n="24" xml:id="d80fn5">Omission indicated in
                                            the original telegram.</note> at least France could hope
                                        that the rank she occupied on the long list of sorrows and
                                        devastations would give her the right to legitimate
                                        concessions in the domain of compensations.<note n="24a" xml:id="d80fn6">Omission which follows is indicated in
                                            the original telegram.</note></p>
                                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                                    <p>If the abstention of our principal debtor has not yet
                                        permitted us to undertake a settlement, for which we first
                                        hoped, nevertheless we cannot consider the possibility of
                                        assuming the burden of annual <pb facs="0261" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/> payments which may be fixed until we
                                        have first completed the work of reparation of the damages
                                        which our devasted regions suffered, and until the payments
                                        due us under the peace treaty have created for us the
                                        necessary resources.<note n="25" xml:id="d80fn7">Omission
                                            which follows is indicated in the original
                                            telegram.</note></p>
                                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                                    <p>France doesn’t intend to repudiate any contracts she has
                                        made, and her signature always will be held sacred. But she
                                        is convinced that an appeal to the sentiments of justice
                                        which grouped so many nations around her in the war will not
                                        be in vain, and she is convinced that her allies and friends
                                        will respond to the hopes she places in their conscience and
                                        their sentiments of justice and solidarity.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>M. Clémentel is also reported as advancing the argument that France
                                should receive due compensation for the fact that her soil was the
                                common battle ground; that inasmuch as the Governments of Britain
                                and the United States collected large sums in taxes by virtue of
                                expenditures which France made within their borders, the total of
                                these taxes should be deducted from the French debt; and that
                                advances made by France to her Allies of some fifteen billion francs
                                should be taken into consideration. France’s debts to Great Britain
                                and the United States are spoken of as so-called political
                                debts.</p>
                            <p>2) Senator Reed, of Pennsylvania, whose friendship for France is well
                                known, discussed the Clémentel statement in the Senate yesterday.
                                After stating the amount of the advances to France, Senator Reed
                                pointed out that in order to pay the current interest which French
                                tax payers should have paid, we have taken from our tax payers
                                approximately eight hundred million dollars in the last 6 years. He
                                said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“We have a full understanding of France’s difficulties. We
                                        understand how hard it is for her and for Italy and for
                                        Belgium and these other countries to collect what is coming
                                        to them from Germany, and that is why our people have not
                                        wished us to press unduly for the payment of these foreign
                                        debts; but the debtor nations have taken no steps toward
                                        refunding the debts, they have paid no interest upon it, and
                                        they have not even given authority to any of their official
                                        representatives to come to any terms with our country toward
                                        refunding.</p>
                                    <p>Mr. Parmentier came here in 1922 absolutely naked of
                                        authority to come to any settlement, or even to recommend
                                        any settlement to his own Government as far as we were able
                                        to learn. The French ambassador—Mr. Jusserand—has done the
                                        best that his great talent enables him to do, but he is
                                        without authority. He has done much to keep the situation
                                        placid. He deserves the gratitude of his country to an
                                        extent that I believe few of his own countrymen as yet
                                        understand, because his efforts have gone far toward
                                        preventing this question from becoming acute. But now, Mr.
                                        President, from France itself, and from Paris, and from the
                                        cabinet of the present administration, comes a step which
                                        our people can not fail to regard as being some evidence of
                                        an official intention to repudiate that war-time <pb facs="0262" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/> debt—the
                                        publication of a balance sheet, listing the obligations of
                                        the French Republic, that absolutely omits the debt to
                                        America or the debt to Great Britain incurred during the
                                        time of the war—and I do not believe that the United States
                                        Senate ought to take an adjournment after the publication of
                                        that balance sheet without some voice being raised in
                                        protest against it.</p>
                                    <p>I make no threats. I do not believe that anyone in the Senate
                                        desires to make any threats. I know that I speak wholly out
                                        of friendship for France, but with an acute realization of
                                        the fact that American taxpayers are paying every day a debt
                                        that France owes. France must be told by her friends that
                                        her inaction in this matter throughout the past 5 years has
                                        puzzled those of us who look toward her most affectionately,
                                        and she should be told that this publication of last week
                                        has alarmed her friends and alarmed them very gravely.
                                        France must be made to see—and when I speak of France I
                                        speak of her because this publication comes from the French
                                        ministry, although what I say applies as well to the other
                                        countries that are still in the same position—that her
                                        present course can result only in a chilling of that
                                        affection that she has found to exist here in America
                                        throughout the past decades. It can have only that result,
                                        Mr. President, and she must be told it by her friends, and
                                        she must be told that each day of delay in achieving a
                                        refunding of that debt makes it more difficult to grant her
                                        leniency in terms of payment. Her taxpayers deserve
                                        consideration. Their sufferings must be remembered, and the
                                        terms of payment must take into account the difficulties of
                                        payment on her part, but each day that she waits makes that
                                        more difficult of achievement. And, finally, she must be
                                        told by her friends that future French loans in America
                                        would be made impossible by a repudiation of the existing
                                        debt.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>3) In reply to an inquiry from one of the correspondents at the
                                morning press conference yesterday, I pointed out, not for
                                quotation, that <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“What Mr. Clémentel had said was not an official
                                        communication to this Government; that it had not been
                                        communicated to this Government directly or indirectly. So
                                        far as its communications to us were concerned the French
                                        Government had never suggested that it repudiated its
                                        obligations or asked for their cancellation. On the contrary
                                        the French Government had always stated to us that it
                                        expected to pay although it had stated its difficulties in
                                        arranging for payment and that it would like to have easy
                                        terms. Only recently the French Ambassador had stated that
                                        France did not ask for a cancellation of its debt and when
                                        the French Commission was here some time ago, headed by Mr.
                                        Parmentier, while they were not ready to make a funding
                                        proposition they did not ask that the debt should be
                                        cancelled or repudiate its obligations. So it is my
                                        understanding that France acknowledges her debt and intends
                                        to pay. While the United States does not wish to be
                                        oppressive, we recognize no grounds in law or equity, (there
                                        can of course be no question of our legal position), why the
                                        debt should be reduced or cancelled.</p>
                                    <p>The attitude of the American Government has been made clear
                                        again and again in official pronouncements. These statements
                                        had <pb facs="0263" n="137" xml:id="pg_137"/> been made by
                                        the President himself. This Government had always opposed
                                        the cancellation or an international conference which would
                                        bring our debt into discussion. An analysis of the manner in
                                        which the debt was incurred would show that our position was
                                        entirely equitable. After our army went to Europe there were
                                        vast purchases in France and large obligations incurred by
                                        our Government to France which were set off against the
                                        indebtedness owed by France to us. Besides enormous sums
                                        lent France during the war an additional billion dollars was
                                        lent her after the Armistice, exclusive of the $400,000,000
                                        for purchase of surplus army supplies after the war. It
                                        would be a very serious mistake not to recognize our debt
                                        and provide for its discharge as international credit should
                                        be maintained.</p>
                                    <p>The United States would not consent to any arrangement for
                                        the pooling of our debt. This Government regards the debt
                                        question as a matter for Congress, and a Commission was
                                        formed for funding the debts owed to the United States.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>[Paraphrase.] 4) While this Government has not received an official
                                communication of the Clémentel statement, it has nevertheless been
                                widely published and cannot, therefore, be ignored. In order to make
                                clear our position and to remove any misunderstanding in regard to a
                                proposal for partial or entire cancellation of the debt, you will
                                please find an early occasion to take up the matter informally with
                                the Premier and the Minister of Finance in the light of the
                                foregoing. They should understand that public opinion in this
                                country reacts promptly and definitely to statements such as those
                                of M. Clémentel which raise a question as to the French Government’s
                                intention to pay its debt or as to the equity of such payment, and
                                the United States Government must expect that the French Government
                                will take an early occasion to give evidence of its intention to pay
                                and make proper provision for refunding of its debt.</p>
                            <p>Results of your conversations should be cabled and please advise also
                                as to desirability of making formal written communication of our
                                views. [End paraphrase.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>