<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-02-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="121" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d121">
                    <head>No. 119.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Count <persName type="from">de
                                Rémusat</persName> to the <persName type="to">Marquis de
                                Noailles</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Versailles</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-02-13"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 13,
                            1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">[Received from <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Marquis de
                            Noailles</persName>, March 13, 1873.]</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Monsieur le Marquis</hi>: The Japanese ambassadors, who,
                        after their sojourn in the United States, visited England, finally came to
                        perform the mission in France which had been confided to them. They had not
                        been furnished with the necessary powers to enter into negotiations,
                        properly so called, at Paris any more than at London, and the discussion
                        concerning a revision of the treaties will not be opened until their return
                        to Japan. Although the conversations which I have had with the first
                        ambassador, Iwakura, only constitute an interchange of views upon the
                        various questions touching the relations between France and Japan, they
                        afforded me an opportunity to elicit statements from the envoy of the Mikado
                        which possess real interest for us.</p>
                    <p>I think it proper for me to send you inclosed, for your information, a report
                        of these conversations. One of the matters insisted upon by Iwakura, that of
                        the Simonosaki indemnity, is one in which the United States are interested
                        in common with us, and the Senate not yet having ratified the act releasing
                        Japan from all obligation toward the Washington Government, it is not
                        improper for you to be enabled to inform the Secretary of State, if anything
                        lead thereto, in what sense I have explained myself. The considerations
                        urged by the Japanese government in support of its desire to have what
                        remains due remitted, have not seemed to us to justify its request. I have
                        therefore maintained the right of the powers to expect payment in full,
                        without, however, formally refusing to admit the possibility, (which is
                        admitted by the London cabinet,) of a concession, the expediency of which we
                        shall appreciate after having come to an understanding with the other
                        Governments interested.</p>
                    <p>Receive, &amp;c.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>RÉMUSAT</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>