<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 121.Marquis de Noailles to Mr. Fish..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85019949"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Capital punishment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="123"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                <head>No. 121.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName type="from">Marquis de Noailles</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_HF1" type="to">Fish</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of France</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-06-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 9, 1873</date>. (Received June
                        12.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: Although temporarily absent
                    from Washington I do not wish to delay sending to your excellency the inclosed
                    copy of a dispatch which I have just received from my government.</p>
                <p>So far as I have been able to understand from the few words which I have heard
                    from the mouth of your excellency in relation to the treaty which has just been
                    proposed to the government of the Mikado by the minister of Italy in Japan, in
                    relation to the privileges to be granted to his countrymen traveling in the
                    interior of the empire, I think I may hope that the views of the Department of
                    State will coincide with those expressed in the dispatch of the minister of
                    foreign affairs of France. It is, indeed, a matter of great importance, as well
                    for the United States as for France, that the representatives of the principal
                    powers in Japan should act harmoniously, and your excellency has several times
                    been pleased to state to me how important you considered it that their
                    harmonious action should not be interrupted.</p>
                <p>Be pleased, &amp;c.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>MARQUIS DE NOAILLES</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Count <persName type="from">de Rémusat</persName> to the
                                <persName type="to">Marquis de Noailles</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Versailles</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-05-09">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 9, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marquis</hi>: Our chargé d’affaires informs me that the
                        minister of Italy is about to go to Rome on leave of absence, and that,
                        while there, he will submit to the approval of his government an
                        arrangement, the terms of which have been fixed by him, with the ministers
                        of the Mikado, with a view to making provision for the free travel of
                        Italians in the interior of the empire. I have the honor herewith to send
                        you the text of this draught of a convention as furnished to M. de Turenne
                        by the legation of Italy, and by the minister of foreign affairs of Japan.
                        The difference between the two versions does <pb facs="0356" n="270"
                            xml:id="pg_270"/> not change the purport of this document, the sole
                        interest of which for us lies in the provision, in virtue of which Italians,
                        when they have passed the limits assigned by the treaties now in force, as
                        those of the residence of foreigners, are to be subject to the jurisdiction
                        of the Japanese authorities.</p>
                    <p>The motive which has led the minister of Italy to seek to procure access to
                        the interior provinces for his countrymen is evident, and as long ago as
                        1868 we were witnesses of the impatience of his predecessor to secure to his
                        country new facilities for the obtainment of silk-worms’ eggs. Whatever may
                        be the importance of this product for Italian industry, the advantage
                        expected from the new convention does not seem to us to make amends for the
                        very serious objections which it presents. Such has been, according to the
                        information furnished me by our chargé d’affaires, the opinion of the
                        representatives of England, the United States, Russia, Germany, and Spain,
                        who have, like him, viewed with regret the agreement brought about by the
                        minister of Italy, and who have felt it their duty to write in this sense to
                        their governments, urging them to dissuade the government at Rome from
                        ratifying the arrangement submitted to it for approval. This is a step which
                        we on our part cannot hesitate to take, and which is justified by an
                        interest of the highest importance. The proposed convention would in effect
                        destroy in a capital matter that unity of action which constitutes the first
                        element of the success of foreign legations in Japan. It would create a
                        troublesome precedent, of which the Japanese government (which has already
                        declared that other nations shall enjoy similar privileges only on the same
                        conditions) would not fail to avail itself. The organization of justice in
                        Japan, and the laws in force there, do not furnish guarantees sufficient to
                        render it wise to renounce, for the present at least, the right of
                        exercising protection over our citizens, and of securing to them, on these
                        terms, access to the provinces of the interior, where we hope without doubt
                        to cause them to be admitted more freely, but without abandoning a
                        prerogative, the maintenance of which is still rendered necessary by the
                        state of the country. What we know of the intentions of the Washington
                        Cabinet does not permit us to doubt that it will share our view, and the
                        Secretary of State, whose attention I beg you to call to this matter, will
                        without doubt be disposed to instruct the representative of the United
                        States at Rome to endeavor, as Mr. Fournier will do, to induce the Italian
                        government not to sanction an arrangement whereby it only secures an
                        advantage which it might confidently expect to secure by co-operating with
                        the other powers in their efforts, and which it would then obtain without
                        making a dangerous sacrifice.</p>
                    <p>Receive, &amp;c.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>RÉMUSAT</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Draft of a provisional convention relative to the travel
                            of foreigners in the interior of Japan, presented by the minister of
                            Italy to the government of the Tenno</hi>.</head>
                    <p>1. Italians may travel freely in the interior of the empire, with the proviso
                        that, if they shall go beyond the limits of the jurisdiction of their
                        consuls, they shall be under the protection and jurisdiction of the
                        territorial authorities, according to the usages which prevail in the
                        countries of Europe and America.</p>
                    <p>2. To this effect Italians of good character and conduct shall obtain,
                        through the intervention of the authorities under whose jurisdiction they
                        are, a personal passport from the ministry of foreign affairs.</p>
                    <p>3. If an Italian subject, or his property, shall suffer injury, the Italian
                        government shall have the right to demand satisfaction, conformably to the
                        laws of Japan. It is understood, however, that the said government shall not
                        interfere in any matter of this kind so long as that one of its subjects who
                        shall have been injured in person or property shall not have used all the
                        means rendered available to him for the obtainment of justice before the
                        Japanese tribunals.</p>
                    <p>There shall be no exception to this rule, save in the case of an evident
                        denial of justice.</p>
                    <p>4. The Japanese government engages that foreigners condemned by its courts
                        shall not be subjected to cruel punishments.</p>
                    <p>Such persons shall only be liable to imprisonment, <hi rend="italic">with or
                            without compulsory labor</hi>. (Sic.)</p>
                    <p>5. If a crime shall be committed rendering the perpetrator liable to capital
                        punishment, the local authorities shall not execute the sentence without
                        having first referred the matter to the seat of the government of the Tokeï,
                        in order to conform to the usages adopted in this empire in the case of a
                        Japanese under a similar sentence.</p>
                    <p>[These two paragraphs are wanting in the text of the draft furnished by the
                        Japanese government to the French government.]</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
