<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 139.Mr. Fish to Mr. Bancroft</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d141</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">141</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-06-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-06-04T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274" lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907" lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619" lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558" lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-06-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-06-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="141" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d141">
                <head>No. 139.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GB1" type="to">Bancroft</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of
                                    State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-06-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 4, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 583.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your dispatches, 480 and 481,
                        and have read with great attention the reasons which you give in the latter
                        for not <pb facs="0379" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/> pressing at present for
                        the unification of the naturalization treaties with Germany.</p>
                <p>It is much to be regretted that the present government at Berlin is not
                        disposed to listen favorably to the suggestion which you were authorized to
                        make, that the naturalization treaty with the North German Union should be
                        extended over the empire.</p>
                <p>The circumstances under which the existing treaties were negotiated,
                        necessarily made them what they are. To have gained at that time the
                        recognition of the principle of the right of emigration was a triumph of
                        which everyone connected with it has good right to be proud. But the fact
                        that the negotiations were made with different and independent governments,
                        each with its own peculiar views, has been the cause of the divergencies
                        referred to in my No. 569. Notwithstanding what you say in your No. 480, I
                        still think it would be better to remove these differences, and to have but
                        one rule for all Germany. And I had thought that, as your name is identified
                        with the recognition of the great principle upon which the treaties were
                        founded, it was due to you that the complete structure which must inevitably
                        come should bear your signature. I regret to learn from you that there is no
                        present probability of such a result.</p>
                <p>A German can now come to America, obtain his naturalization papers through
                        the operation of our laws, return to Germany and reside there indefinitely
                        as an American citizen, provided he does not reside the requisite time for
                        renunciation in the territories under the jurisdiction of the particular
                        power of whom he was formerly a subject. It is true that such a course would
                        be a fraud upon the United States, and a fraud upon the German Empire. We
                        should be deprived of the resources of the naturalized citizen towards the
                        support of the state; Germany would be deprived of the right to call upon
                        him for her defense. It is for the interest of neither to perpetuate this.
                        We are ready on our side to remedy it by extending the provisions of the
                        treaty with North Germany over the empire, as I have already said; but if
                        our proposition will not be listened to, we must await the return of a
                        better reason. Meanwhile it is not wise to take any half-way measure as to
                        Alsace and Loraine.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HF1">Hamilton Fish</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
