<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-03-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="214" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d214">
                    <head>No. 211.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bassett</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of
                                    State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>,
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-03-26"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 26, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 137.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatch No. 181, of the 17th ultimo,
                        inclosing a copy of correspondence, marked “Non-official,” between yourself
                        and the secretary <pb facs="0546" n="460" xml:id="pg_460"/> of state of
                        Hayti in relation to the arrest on your premises of persons engaged in your
                        domestic service, has been received.</p>
                    <p>The statement made in your personal note to Mr. Ethéart, respecting the
                        inviolability of the domicile of a diplomatic agent, was substantially
                        correct; but the immunities of an embassador are not of a personal
                        character. They belong to the government of which he is the representative.
                        It is to be regretted, therefore, that you treated the invasion of your
                        house and the arrest therein of your servants as a personal offense, to be
                        atoned for by the simple release of the persons arrested, and a private note
                        expressive of regret.</p>
                    <p>This act, especially when regarded in connection with a recent invasion of
                        the commercial agency at St. Marc, and other acts of disrespect, and of
                        neglect of diplomatic and international courtesies, significant of an intent
                        which should have elicited from you a more emphatic protest than your
                        unofficial communication to the Secretary of State, and a demand for more
                        decided redress than that which you were content to accept.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName corresp="#p_HF1">Hamilton Fish</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>