<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 244Mr. De Long to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d247</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">247</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-11-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-11-06T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-11-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-11-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="247" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d247">
                <head>No. 244<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEDL1" type="from">De Long</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States
                                    Legation, Japan</hi>
                        </placeName>,<lb/>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-11-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 6, 1872</date>.
                            (Received December 7.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 302.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Upon learning, some time since, from the
                        minister of foreign affairs for this empire, that the kingdom of Lew Chew
                        had at last been formally incorporated into this empire, and the King
                        reduced to the condition of an ex-daimio and assigned a residence at Yedo,
                        which he had accepted, I felt called upon to call the attention of this
                        government to the compact between our Government and that of Lew Chew,
                        proclaimed by the President March 9, 1855, and to inquire if that would be
                        respected and observed by this government, as it, in its provisions, gave to
                        our people certain privileges not embodied in our treaty with Japan.
                        Accordingly, I addressed a note to this government making such inquiry,
                        (inclosure No. 1,) to which, on yesterday, I received an answer, (inclosure
                        No. 2,) by which these authorities agree to regard the same.</p>
                <p>Having learned that recently a junk’s crew of Lew Chew people, who had been
                        wrecked on Formosa, had been slain by the natives of that island, I inquired
                        verbally of his excellency to know if such report was true; and if so, what,
                        if anything, this government intended to do about it. I was informed, in
                        reply, that it was true, and an intimation was thrown out that steps would
                        soon be taken by the Japanese government to punish those people. The
                        minister then inquired of me very particularly about Formosa; the character,
                        purposes, and result of the expedition against those people led by our late
                        Admiral Bell, and expressed the wish that I would obtain for him from our
                        naval officers any copies of maps or charts possible.</p>
                <p>All this seemed to indicate an intention to fit out an armed expedition.</p>
                <p>At this juncture, which was about two weeks ago, General L. P. Le Gendre,
                        United States consul at Amoy, arrived here en route to Washington, having a
                        very full and complete set of maps, charts, photographs, &amp;c., of the
                        coast, main-land, and people of Formosa.</p>
                <p>From him I learned that he had, on several occasions, visited the people who
                        committed the atrocities, and established such relations with them as had
                        enabled him to obtain guarantees against such atrocities being committed in
                        the future upon Americans. that these people had observed their promises,
                        and in two subsequent cases cared for and protected the crews of two English
                        ships which were wrecked there; that diplomatic negotiations of some nature
                        were now pending between our Government and China relative to this island,
                        and that, in his opinion, <pb facs="0640" n="554" xml:id="pg_554"/> it was
                        feasible to undertake to obtain by peaceable means the same nature of
                        guarantees for the Japanese.</p>
                <p>Upon learning this, I thought I observed an opportunity, with the assistance
                        the general could and seemed willing to lend me, to furnish this government
                        with a mass of information most useful to it, thereby saving it from making
                        any ill-advised efforts, and at the same time to put our legation at Peking
                        and yourself in such rapport with the views and intentions of this
                        government as to be of substantial benefit to us and at the same time
                        advance my standing and intimacy with this government.</p>
                <p>Actuated by these views, I requested General Le Gendre to remain over here
                        for one steamer and assist me with this government by imparting to it such
                        information relative to his observations of Formosa and its inhabitants as
                        in his opinion and my own might, without impropriety, be given.</p>
                <p>The general kindly consented to do so, and an interview between us and the
                        minister of foreign affairs followed.</p>
                <p>The minister expressed himself as surprised and delighted at thus being
                        brought in contact with one so well informed on a subject so very
                        interesting to them, and yet about which they could learn so little. The
                        minister at once extended accommodations for the general in Yedo; invited my
                        participation in all deliberations with Mr. Smith, the general, and himself,
                        and has twice visited me and conferred upon the subject, being with me last
                        evening until nearly midnight. The plan of action has not yet been resolved
                        upon, but the minister assures me that his action shall be as open as the
                        day to me, and that he will frame it to coincide with the wishes of our
                        legation at Peking and of yourself.</p>
                <p>I will at once advise Mr. Low of these proceedings by sending him a copy of
                        this dispatch and writing him fully as often as anything develops of
                        interest.</p>
                <p>General Le Gendre will be compelled to remain over here at least one steamer
                        more; that is, two weeks.</p>
                <p>My obligations to him are very great. By his intelligence and courtesy, he
                        has enabled me to serve this government in a substantial manner, which will,
                        I am sure, materially strengthen my influence with them, and, as a
                        consequence, promote our Government’s interests. I think, also, that before
                        this matter is concluded we shall be able to arm Mr. Low with power and
                        information calculated to enable him to effect good results and improve his
                        influence with the Chinese government. I hope in all of this that I have
                        acted as you would have wished me to; if not, however, and you should
                        disapprove of what has been done, I beg you to let the whole blame rest on
                        me, as General Le Gendre has, in all matters, acted simply by my request,
                        although I am satisfied that such action has also been in accordance with
                        his own views and wishes.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CEDL1">C. E. DE LONG</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEDL1" type="from">De
                                    Long</persName> to <persName type="to">Soyeshmia
                                    Tane-omi</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Legation, Japan</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-10-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 20, 1872</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: Understanding you to advise me
                            a few days since that the King of the Lew Chew Islands had been called
                            upon by the Japanese government to resign his titles and estates, which
                            had been done, letters-patent of nobility issued to him <pb facs="0641" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> constituting him a member of the nobility
                            of your empire, ranking as do the former daimios, thus incorporating Lew
                            Chew as an integral portion of the Japanese Empire:</p>
                    <p>I feel called upon to call your attention to a contract entered into
                            between the former kingdom of Lew Chew and the United States of America,
                            on the 11th of July, 1854, (see bound volume of Treaties, page 4,) and
                            to ask if the same will be observed in all its provisions by your
                            government within the territorial limits of the former kingdom.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CEDL1">C. E. DE LONG</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName type="from">Soyeshmia Tane-omi</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEDL1" type="to">De Long</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                        Office, Tokei</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="japanese-nengō gregorian" when="1872-10-05">
                                <hi rend="italic">The</hi> 5<hi rend="italic">th of</hi> 10<hi rend="italic">th month of</hi> 5<hi rend="italic">th year of
                                        Meigi</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>In reply to your excellency’s note of October 20, 1872, regarding the Lew
                            Chew Islands, I beg to state as follows:</p>
                    <p>The Lew Chew Islands have been dependencies of this empire for hundreds
                            of years, and to them the title of Han was recently given.</p>
                    <p>As you say, the Lew Chew being an integral portion of the Japanese Empire
                            it is natural that the provisions of a compact entered into between the
                            Lew Chew and the United States on the 11th of July, 1854, will be
                            observed by this government.</p>
                    <p>With respect and consideration,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>SOYESHIMA TANE-OMI</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
