<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 300.Mr. Schuchardt to Mr. Hunter.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-01-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="recFe9iZmLH8fc4Ed" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103898"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Harvest</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85105939"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Poverty</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-01-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="303"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d303">
                <head>No. 300.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Schuchardt</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_WH1" type="to">Hunter</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Commercial Agency</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Piedras Negras, Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-01-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 10, 1872</date>. (Rec’d
                        Feb.16.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 63.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit, for the information
                    of the Department, the copy of a letter directed to me by Messrs. Harrison and
                    Bronaugh, both respectable citizens of the United States, residing in the
                    district of Monclova, about one hundred and fifty miles from here. The
                    Lieutenant Colonel Bueno mentioned in said letter is the same who is the second
                    in command of the force which now occupies this place, and what he has done to
                    the writers of said letter is only a small wrong in comparison with the outrages
                    he has committed since he occupied this place. Before this band arrived here all
                    the people fledto the Texas side, having received the news how these men had
                    depredated on the towns they came through. Like in other places through which
                    they came, all mercantile establishments of this place were forced open and the
                    goods disposed of to the benefit of the few commanders. Goods of all
                    descriptions, billiard-tables, house-furniture, and ornaments are sold at very
                    low prices; and I am sorry to say that citizens from the Texas side were the
                    buyers, knowing how all this property was obtained.</p>
                <p>By Bueno’s order, also, the house of an American citizen was broken into and a
                    quantity of corn and other things appropriated, and, although I wrote twice to
                    the commander, requesting the payment for the articles so taken, he never
                    answered to my request.</p>
                <p>When this plundering commenced several United States citizens themselves, and the
                    attorneys of others, made application at this office, in order to protect their
                    goods against this pillaging, to certify their property being that of United
                    States citizens, and seal the rooms where such property was stored. After having
                    scrupulously examined the claims establishing their citizenship, I proceeded to
                    render the service requested from me, sealed several doors and fastened to each
                    door so sealed a certified notice expressing the character of the goods
                    contained in the respective rooms.</p>
                <p>These seals were respected so long as there was any Mexican establishment left to
                    be sacked, but this source being exhausted, they did go so far in their
                    licentious practice as to break my official seals. One Jesus Cantee, who
                    undertook this act of violation, was warned by the man who guards the rooms, and
                    notified that if he had to enter the rooms he had to first call on me to remove
                    the seal, as only myself could remove it. This warning was insultingly
                    disregarded by Cantee, who stated he was ordered by Pedro A. Valdes to proceed
                    in the manner he did.</p>
                <p>I have reason to believe that, after such violation took place by breaking seals,
                    the next will be the breaking into the houses so sealed and sacking of the
                    American property stored therein; and I cannot see how I can protect the same
                    against a band of outlaws who are reigning now in this town in the name of the
                    legitimate government of Mexico. These men know well that their force is the
                    only so called government force left in the State, and know also well that they
                    cannot hold this place long, and it seems to be their intention to harvest while
                    they are in possession of it. They have made all preparations to go across the
                    river in the event this place is attacked by the revolutionists, but before may
                    destroy the town by fire, through the dangerous works they have made in defense
                    of the place.</p>
                <pb facs="0786" n="700" xml:id="pg_700"/>
                <p>A part of the cotton detained in Eagle Pass is crossing now below that place,
                    through the lines of the revolutionists, by consent of Valdes, who received, for
                    his permit to cross, one hundred and fifty bales, the sum of $240. Pedro A.
                    Valdes, the representative of the legitimate government, having thus been
                    satisfied, the collector of customs at Eagle Pass objected no longer to allow
                    this cotton to be exported outside of his port, although full duties must be
                    paid to revolutionists. These trains were detained on the Texas side over twenty
                    days, and their expenses amount to thousands of dollars.</p>
                <p>Colonel Falcon, the chief of the revolutionists, is three miles distant from this
                    place, and it is reported that his force is a very large one, and that his
                    intention is, in order to avoid bloodshed, not to attack, but besiege the town
                    until Valdes surrenders or goes to the Texas side. The men of Valdes being not
                    paid and very badly cared for, desert in great numbers to the Texas side. For
                    each impressed man it takes the vigilance of another to prevent his
                    desertion.</p>
                <p>By this unfortunate struggle, this and the adjoining districts are ruined for
                    many years to come; particularly this town, by the acts of Valdes, is reduced to
                    poverty. Men who were transacting a fair business are ruined entirely; not only
                    have they lost all they had, but also their credit, by not being able to pay
                    their debts, and not even the hope of a new starts remains to them. Many of
                    these men will probably engross the files of professional revolutionists, with
                    the intention to repay themselves in revolutions for what they have lost through
                    them.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>WM. SCHUCHARDT</persName>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States Commercial Agent</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Messrs. <persName type="from">Harrison and
                                Bronaugh</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to"
                            >Schuchardt</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Molino del Norte Hacienda de Sardinas</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Coabueld, Mexico</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-12-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 16, 1871</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Sir</hi>: The state of war which exists at
                        present in this State, between the government, or Juarez party, and a rival
                        faction, seems to be fraught with as much evil to citizens of the United
                        States, resident of or traveling in Mexico, as to citizens of Mexico taking
                        an active part in hostilities. Some of the chiefs seem to take great
                        pleasure not only in insulting the United States in the persons of her
                        citizens, but allow in robbing them of their property, thereby preventing
                        them from following the ordinary avocations by which they gain a living. It
                        is but just to say that the Diaz party have shown a much better disposition
                        toward Americans than the Juarez party.</p>
                    <p>A few days ago, December 12, at sunset, and on the Hacienda de Sardinas,
                        soldiers of the Juarez party, by order of one Lieut. Col. Bueno, commanding
                        the detachment, drove off the premises of J. H. Harrison &amp; Co., at
                        Molino del Norte, caught and appropriated three horses, one the property of
                        Mr. Harrison, the other two the property of Dr. Bronaugh, practicing
                        physician, located at San Buena Ventura.</p>
                    <p>The doctor and several friends remonstrated with Lieut. Col. Bueno, stating
                        that it was impossible for him to attend to his patients unless they left
                        him one horse. That officer replied that the constitution of Mexico not only
                        gave him authority to appropriate the property of citizen of the United
                        States, but also to impress them into the military service of Mexico, and
                        that he would take the doctor and friends along as soldiers if he did not
                        cease his remonstrances. The horse was an exceedingly fine and gentle one,
                        and the doctor had refused to take $500 for him. The lieutenant colonel
                        aforesaid had a drove of some forty loose horses good for service when this
                        was done, so there was no excuse for his high-handed act on the ground of
                        necessity. His manner was exceedingly insulting, and his whole bearing that
                        of a robber chief rather than an officer of the regular army of a friendly
                        power. Finally he refused to give a receipt showing that he had taken the
                        horses, promising to return within two days at farthest. It only remains for
                        us to send this statement of the facts to you, and through you to our
                        Government, <pb facs="0787" n="701" xml:id="pg_701"/> in order that we may
                        receive some indemnity for this wanton and uncalled-for insult and robbery.
                        In proof of which we also state that, late in the night, a number of the
                        lieutenant colonel’s band entered and searched the premises of J. H.
                        Harrison &amp; Co. for arms, saddles, bridles, &amp;c., but finding none,
                        offered to return the horse if the doctor would give him a pistol. It will
                        be well to bear in mind the fact that the doctor offered to make the
                        government of Mexico a present of Mr. Harrison’s and his other, a saddle
                        horse, valued at $150, if he would only return his riding-horse, so that he
                        might continue his practice. And also that the doctor, a short time before,
                        had attended this same lieutenant colonel in an attack of sickness, relieved
                        him, and refused to charge him for his services because he was a soldier.
                        The doctor does a practice worth from $50 to $60 per day when in the saddle.
                        Now he is placed on foot miles from his home, where he had come with a very
                        ill patient, without the means to purchase another horse, and where there
                        are none for sale, owing to the wholesale robbery of this model officer of
                        the regular army of the republic of Mexico.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Harrison values his horse at $100. We now lay these facts before you,
                        hoping that something may be done to protect the persons and property of
                        citizens of the United States, and that we may obtain some return for the
                        damages sustained and some guarantee for the future.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>J. H. HARRISEN</persName>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>FRANC’CO BRONAUGH</persName>.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">William Schuchardt</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">American Consul at Piedras Negras.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>We, the undersigned, were eye-witnesses of the above facts, as the whole
                            thing took place while we were enjoying the hospitality of Messrs. J. H.
                            Harrison &amp; Co., and must say that the gentlemen have represented the
                            action of Lieut. Col. Bueno without exaggeration.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <list>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName>CHARLES A. JAMES</persName>,<lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Texas Military Institute</hi>.</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName>C. T. COLLINS</persName>.</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName>J. H. FLY</persName>.</item>
                                </list>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
