<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-07-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-07-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="304" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d304">
                    <head>No. 301.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Schuchardt</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WH1" type="to">Hunter</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States
                                    Commercial Agency</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Piedras Negras,
                                    Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-07-15"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 15, 1872</date>.
                            (Rec’d Aug. 11.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 80.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The following report relative to the condition
                        of affairs in this district is respectfully submitted to the Department. The
                        resources of this district are:</p>
                    <p>Agriculture, mining, stock-raising, and, up to the outbreak of the present
                        revolution, the traffic in cattle and horses stolen from Texas, partly by
                        Indians, but mostly by professional Mexican cattle-thieves.</p>
                    <p>The crops principally consist of Indian corn, wheat, sugar-cane, and cotton;
                        besides, onions, red pepper, and beans are cultivated for export to Texas.
                        Most of the corn is exported to Texas, for consumption in the United States
                        military posts. Wheat also is exported, to some extent, to Texas and to the
                        more populated places in the States of Nuevo Leon and Tamaulipas. Cotton is
                        a well-paying crop, although the area planted is comparatively small. One
                        manufactory making unbleached domestic, established in Mocmova, consumes all
                        that is raised in this district, and, besides, imports Texas cotton. The
                        wheat-crop of this year is already harvested and very abundant, and a cargo
                        of three hundred and fifty pounds can be bought, at present, at the place
                        where it is raised, at $2.50. The area planted in corn is not equal to that
                        planted in former years, for the want of hands and for the depressed spirit
                        of the farmers on account of the revolution. They say, “We plant the corn,
                        but we do not know if we will harvest it.” Sugar-cane is cultivated where
                            <pb facs="0788" n="702" xml:id="pg_702"/> water to irrigate is
                        plentiful, and is worked up by a very primitive machinery in piloncillo, (a
                        small loaf not weighing over one pound.) The juice of the cane is boiled
                        down to the crystallization point, then stirred for some time with a stick
                        to produce granulation, and then it is emptied into small earthen moulds.
                        Molasses not being separated by this process, is rather an inferior
                        substitute for sugar, but generally used as such by the poorer class here,
                        and partly exported to Texas for consumption by the Mexican population of
                        that State. Mescal, an alcoholic liquor, peculiar to Mexico is also
                        manufactured in this district. The material for this liquor, the <hi rend="italic">Agave Americana</hi>, (maguey,) grows wild in the
                        tablelands, and is found in some places abundantly. When the plant attains
                        the age of eight years, it is ripe for manufacture into mescal; then the
                        plant is cut above the root and the leaves separated from the trunk. Stones
                        are heated then, and interred, interspersed with the trunks until these are
                        well cooked, through the heat of the stones, and when taken out of the
                        ground the juice is pressed from them and put for fermentation in raw hides,
                        hanged in a frame so as to form a vessel, and after the fermentation is
                        terminated the wine is distilled in a very primitive apparatus, consisting
                        generally in a big kettle covered with another, from which the vapor is
                        conducted by a reed to the receiving-vessel. These distilleries are mostly
                        established in deserts where the plants grow near by. Physicians attribute
                        to mescal officinal qualities, and recommend the use of it in many diseases.
                        In a few places grape-vines are cultivated extensively. Raisins, wine, and
                        brandy are made of the grapes. The wine is manufactured the same way as in
                        Spain or Portugal, and resembles very much the wines of those countries.
                        Very few people know how or take the trouble to make the wine so as to keep
                        good for any length of time, and this may be the reason why none is
                        exported.</p>
                    <p>Cattle-raising is not carried on extensively, since beeves for consumers are
                        procured very cheap from Texas. Fifty years ago this district was supplying
                        some parts of the interior with young horses and mules, but since the
                        continual revolutions commenced to desolate the country, and in consequence
                        of that the Indians could invade it without resistance, the results of
                        horse-raising are of little importance, and the horses raised now are hardly
                        enough to supply the home market, and very few are exported. In the
                        mountainous districts goats and sheep are raised. The castratos are
                        separated at a certain time in the year from the herds, fattened, and driven
                        slowly to the large cities of the interior, where they sell at good prices,
                        the hides and tallow entered into commerce, and the meat consumed there.
                        Most of the large fortunes in this district, I am informed, were accumulated
                        in this traffic.</p>
                    <p>In minerals this district is very rich; for a long distance along the Rio
                        Grande are abundant outcroppings of coal, indicating very extensive layers
                        of this valuable mineral. About one hundred and thirty miles from here are
                        several hot mineral-springs, but, no accommodations being provided there for
                        the invalid visitors, they are rarely frequented; but the few persons who
                        have used them, against rheumatism and similar sicknesses, left them
                        restored to health, and recommend these springs very much to the public
                        attention, and in particular to their fellow-sufferers. About one hundred
                        and twenty miles from here, right at some of the eastern outrunners of the
                        Sierra Madre, is the town of Santa Rosa situated. It was founded in 1737, by
                        miners who worked the admirably rich silver-mines in the vicinity. According
                        to the old town records, the production of silver of the Santa Rosa mines
                        was enormous, but since Mexico accomplished its independence from Spain the
                        mines fell in decadency, and were not worked in a noteworthy manner until
                        lately, when <pb facs="0789" n="703" xml:id="pg_703"/> several American
                        companies engaged in preparing to work them on a scale that attracts
                        attention and promises success, but at present they are kept back very much
                        in their operations. On account of the political situation of the country
                        most of their laborers are forced into military service. There are many rich
                        mines waiting to be worked again, but which can be done with success only by
                        Americans. Mexicans will not do it, and not many American capitalists will
                        risk their money in this country while the long-desired protectorate of or
                        the annexation to the United States is a fact which is considered as the
                        only means to afford protection to people coming here to develop the
                        resources of this country by investing their capital. Honest-working and
                        industrious Mexicans, which are the unprejudiced of the country, express
                        themselves as having arrived at the conclusion that a protectorate by the
                        United States is the only remedy to pacify their unhappy country, affording
                        them the guarantee which they never can expect from any of their own
                        governments.</p>
                    <p>The Kickapoo Indians, who emigrated to this district in 1864 from Kansas, are
                        living on an old plantation called El Nacimiento, thirty miles from Santa
                        Rosa, and are under the direct supervision and protection of the authorities
                        of that place. They make their living partly by cultivating the soil, and
                        making mats, baskets, &amp;c., and dressing deer-skins, and partly by
                        engaging in the traffic of horse-stealing from Texas, very profitable for
                        them and their Mexican protectors. Several years ago, a Mexican Congress
                        voted $10,000 to subsidize these Indians in buying agricultural implements
                        and cattle, but these funds were retained by the State government until a
                        year ago, when it became known that a delegation composed of United States
                        Indian agents and Kickapoos from Kansas was on its way to Santa Rosa to
                        induce the Kickapoos to return to their reservation in Kansas. Then the
                        government of this State (Coahuila) sent a commissioner to Santa Rosa with
                        $3,000 to divide among the Indians, but at the time the delegation arrived
                        in Santa Rosa said commissioner had only given them a little corn and a few
                        beeves, worth about three hundred dollars. The Indians, having knowledge of
                        the whole amount sent for them, became dissatisfied, listened to the
                        propositions of the Kansas delegation, and most of them agreed to leave
                        Mexico. When the Mexican agent saw this he commenced to bribe several of the
                        influential chiefs, and by that he obtained his object, which was to
                        frustrate that of the mission of the American delegation. So soon as the
                        Americans had left Santa Rosa, the Mexican agent being convinced of the
                        failure of that mission, not one more dollar was given to the Indians by
                        him.</p>
                    <p>The benefit the Mexicans derive from the staying of these Indians in Mexico,
                        besides the supply of cheap horses, is the protection they afford against
                        the invasion of their district by other savage tribes. The Mexican
                        government, which cannot any longer misapprehend the good faith of the
                        United States Government in its exertions made to stop the hostile
                        incursions of these Indians in its own territory by inducing them to leave
                        Mexico, expending thousands of dollars for that purpose, and the Mexican
                        government having done its best to counteract these sincere exertions of the
                        United States Government by its underhand dealing, it should be held
                        directly responsible for all the depredations committed by the Kickapoos on
                        our Texas frontier.</p>
                    <p>The Lipans and Mescaleros are also Indians of Mexico, and continually invade
                        Texas, committing depredations there. They do not live in a certain locality
                        of Mexico, but whenever they have made a successful raid into Texas they
                        return to this district and ask for peace, which always is conceded to them
                        by the Mexican authorities. Then the Mexicans buy <pb facs="0790" n="704" xml:id="pg_704"/> their Texas plunder, supplying them in exchange with
                        powder and lead, lance-blades, and arrow-points, &amp;c.; in fact they fit
                        them out for a new campaign against the citizens of their sister republic,
                        for which they always profess a great friendship in public. Two years ago
                        even the collector of the Piedras Negras custom-house sent his commandante
                        of inspectors, Pedro A. Valdes, to the camp of the Lipan Indians to trade
                        off for stolen horses some cart-covers he had confiscated from the carts of
                        some poor freighters, the covers being apparently new and bought in Texas.
                        Among the horses so obtained appeared one of Mr. Adams’s, who was murdered,
                        with two other men, a very short time before, near the Careza, about sixty
                        miles below Eagle Pass, Texas.</p>
                    <p>In the same spirit these Indian depredations in Texas were considered by the
                        Mexican government; the cattle-stealing by Mexicans was (that is to say)
                        protected by it, it seems, as the government thought to benefit by it its
                        own people; it did not concern it if so many innocent Texan families were
                        sacrificed by its winking at these crimes.</p>
                    <p>Although the cattle-stealing from Texas has ceased since the government bands
                        evacuated this frontier and became refugees on the Texas side, it had
                        reached before the outbreak of the present revolution such extension that it
                        has nearly ruined many of our frontier stock-raisers in Texas. To show that
                        the cattle-stealing could be carried on so extensively as it was only by
                        being, so to speak, officially protected, I mention one of many cases
                        reported to me, as an illustration. Senor Don José Maria Ramirez contracted
                        with Juan Manuel Ramos to deliver him (Ramirez) a drove of beeves, promising
                        Ramos for all he could bring eight dollars per head. Ramos crossed over to
                        Texas, stole the beeves, and on offering to turn them over to Ramirez the
                        latter refused to pay him the price as per contract, offering him only $5
                        per head, which Ramos declined to accept, declaring that he would take the
                        beeves to the market in the interior himself. Ramirez said this was all very
                        well, but he should get the documents from the Piedras Negras customhouse
                        necessary for his trip to the interior, if he could obtain them, and without
                        which he would see the beeves confiscated by the Mexican inspectors, and he
                        (Ramos) would lose all. Ramos seeing the truth of this well enough, and
                        knowing his inability to procure the documents, agreed to sell the beeves to
                        Ramirez for $8 per head, payable on the return of Ramirez from Saltillo with
                        the money for the beeves sold. When Ramirez returned from the trip, and
                        Ramos asked him for the money for the beeves, he was told by Ramirez that he
                        did not owe him anything, and if he was not satisfied he could sue him,
                        which Ramos knew he could not do without accusing himself as a cattle-thief.
                        In the association which carried on this contemptible traffic, Ramos
                        belonged to the class of the agents who did the stealing, while Ramirez was
                        one of the respectables of the ring, who procured from his associates in the
                        custom-house the necessary documents for the transit of the stolen cattle to
                        the interior, and, in case thieves were captured, he went to have them
                        released from prison by his influence. Ramirez is a man of a low education,
                        but partly by his activity, and partly by transactions similar to those
                        mentioned, realized some capital, and by giving occupation to some people,
                        and having others obliged to him through his knowledge of their crimes, he
                        created for himself a great influence over them, which he exercised in
                        elections to his own and the advantage of those who in recompense protected
                        him against the laws he violated at all times, and which he knew he could
                        defy with impunity, and so he became one of the prominent men of his
                        district, who could dictate to the local authorities what he thought proper
                        they should do. In the election just before the outbreak of the present
                        revolution, Ramirez was elected a member of the <pb facs="0791" n="705" xml:id="pg_705"/> legislature of the State of Coahuila, it is said, by
                        the instructions to the local authorities of this district by Governor
                        Cepeda.</p>
                    <p>There are many good and honest men living in this district, who, mortified
                        and ashamed to witness such things carried on nearly public, were opposed to
                        such management of public justice, and who attempted for the sake of the
                        honor of their country to put a stop to these outrages; but they very soon
                        found out that by this they were fighting the State government, and all they
                        earned for their good-will was persecution by the higher authorities of the
                        State through those of their residence, and being called unnatural sons of
                        their country (<hi rend="italic">hijos inatural de su patria</hi>) who to
                        the benefit of foreigners would disclose the misdeeds of their own
                        countrymen.</p>
                    <p>The military of the United States forts along the line are indefatigable in
                        their exertions to persecute the depredating Indians and Mexican
                        cattle-thieves, and deserve justly the thanks of the people of the frontier;
                        but their efforts will never be crowned by success of any importance so long
                        as the Rio Grande, constituting the line between the United States and
                        Mexico, serves as a safeguard for these marauders of Mexico. It is an
                        undeniable fact, that the best and most intelligent men in the present
                        political movement belong to the revolutionary party, for which, however,
                        they did not declare until they were beaten by the government party in the
                        late election for State officers through the forcible means and machinations
                        of the federal and municipal authorities. Although considering rebellion a
                        great wrong in itself, any man who honestly and impartially observed the
                        progression of affairs can excuse these people in some respect, who strive
                        that their nation’s honor shall not be stained any longer by the disgraceful
                        conduct of the worst men of their district and the protection offered to
                        them by the authorities.</p>
                    <p>However good the disposition of the federal government of Mexico relative to
                        the affairs on this frontier might have been, it seems it had not the power
                        to enforce its decrees in these remote States. This clearly appears, for
                        instance, in the irregularity of the custom-house laws, which are the same
                        all over Mexico, as executed on this line, where the duties are collected in
                        three different ways; on the lower Rio Grande up to Laredo the so-called
                            “<hi rend="italic">zona libre</hi>” exists, because it is the will of
                        the people of Tamaulipas that it should exist, being to their benefit, and
                        they at all times have threatened rebellion, should this privilege be taken
                        away from them. In the custom-house of this State (Coahuila) the duties
                        according to the tariff are collected, while in the custom-house in the
                        State of Chihuahua only the third part of these duties are collected, and by
                        this a great deal of traffic being attracted to that State, the governor of
                        it therefore sustains the custom-house officials of the federal government
                        to discharge their duties in this way.</p>
                    <p>Although the merchants of this district complained at different times in
                        Mexico against the privileges Tamaulipas and Chihuahua enjoyed to the
                        detriment of their own trade, it never could be remedied by the federal
                        government.</p>
                    <p>I have related so circumstantially matters contained in this report with the
                        intention to impart knowledge of the same as exact as possible to the
                        Department.</p>
                    <p>My insight in these affairs I have acquired through close observation by
                        myself during a long time, and through statements made to me by reliable
                        persons of the district.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>WM. SCHUCHARDT</persName>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United
                                States Commercial Agent.</hi></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>