<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-03-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="67" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                    <head>No. 65.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FFL1" type="from">Low</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="to">Fish</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the
                                    United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-03-22"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 22, 1873</date>.
                            (Received May 23.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 241.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Among the many duties devolving upon the
                        Emperor of China after he enters upon the active duties of his high office,
                        a visit to the tombs of his ancestors, to offer sacrifices according to
                        Confucian rites, is not the least important.</p>
                    <p>It is now announced that the present Emperor will make such a visit early in
                        April, starting on the 1st and returning on the 9th proximo. It is
                        understood that one of the objects of the visit is to select an appropriate
                        location for this sovereign’s tomb. He will be accompanied on the journey by
                        the princes and other high officers in the capital and vicinity, and the
                        cortege will be escorted by a large body of troops. The imperial tombs are
                        distant about one hundred miles from Peking.</p>
                    <p>An imperial decree issued a few days since names a prince, one grand
                        secretary, two presidents of boards, and one high military officer, who will
                        jointly have charge of all governmental affairs during the Emperor’s
                        absence. The proposed excursion is, in the estimation of the Chinese, an
                        important event in the history of the young Emperor; it will be the first
                        time His Majesty has ventured outside the walls of Peking since his return
                        here from Jehol in 1862.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName corresp="#p_FFL1">FREDERICK F. LOW</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>