<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-03-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="7" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d7">
                    <head>No. 5.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of
                                    State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>,
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-03-29"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 29, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">To the Diplomatic and Consular Officers of the United
                            States:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>A copy of a law of Congress approved by the President of the United States
                        March 3, 1873, is herewith inclosed for your information. You will observe
                        that it is stated that, in computations, the value of a pound sterling shall
                        be deemed equal to four dollars and eighty-six cents and six and one-half
                        mills; and this valuation shall be the par of exchange between Great Britain
                        and the United States. Heretofore the value of a pound sterling has been
                        deemed equal to $4.84; and this value has formed the basis upon which your
                        drafts and accounts have been adjusted. On and after the 1st day of April
                        you are required to regard the pound sterling as equal in value to four
                        dollars eighty-six cents six mills and one-half, and to employ this
                        valuation in the computation of your accounts.</p>
                    <p>I am, gentlemen, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName corresp="#p_HF1">Hamilton Fish</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <p rend="center">[<hi rend="smallcaps">General Nature</hi>—No. 96.]</p>
                        <p rend="center">AN ACT to establish the custom-house value of the sovereign
                            or pound sterling of Great Britain, and to fix the par of exchange.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Be it enacted by the Senate and House of
                                Representatives of the United States of America in Congress
                                assembled</hi>, That the value of foreign coin, as expressed in the
                            money of account of the United States, shall be that of the pure metal
                            of such coin of standard value and the values of the standard coins in
                            circulation of the various nations of the world shall be estimated
                            annually by the Director of the Mint, and be proclaimed on the first day
                            of January by the Secretary of the Treasury.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 2. That in all payments by or to the
                            Treasury, whether made here or in foreign countries, where it becomes
                            necessary to compute the value of the sovereign or pound sterling, it
                            shall be deemed equal to four dollars eighty-six cents and six and
                            one-half mills, and the same rule shall be applied in appraising
                            merchandise imported where the value is, by the invoice, in sovereigns
                            or pounds sterling, and in the construction of contracts payable in
                            sovereigns or pounds sterling; and this valuation shall be the par of
                            exchange between Great Britain and the United States; and all contracts
                            made after the first day of January, eighteen hundred and seventy-four,
                            based on an assumed par of exchange with Great Britain of fifty-four
                            pence to the dollar, or four dollars forty-four and four-ninths cents to
                            the sovereign or pound sterling, shall be null and void.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 3. That all acts and parts of acts
                            inconsistent with these provisions be, and the same are hereby,
                            repealed.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">Approved <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-03-03">March 3, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>