<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 83.Mr. Blair
                            to Mr. Fish..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856" lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-05-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="85" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                <head>No. 83.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blair</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="to">Fish</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the
                                    United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">San José, Costa
                                    Rica</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-05-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 12, 1873</date>.
                            (Received June 9.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 151.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The annual meeting of Congress took place on
                        the first instant.</p>
                <p>The President’s message was read by the secretary of foreign affairs.</p>
                <p>Its unusual length, I hope, will be deemed a sufficient excuse for not
                        inclosing a translation of the same.</p>
                <p>The leading points of the message are as follows:</p>
                <p>The President commences by stating that the nation is at peace with all
                        foreign powers. He then alludes to the boundary question between Nicaragua
                        and Costa Rica; would greatly prefer to have the question settled amicably,
                        but that Costa Rica cannot, in justice to itself, cede any part of its
                        territory to Nicaragua.</p>
                <p>He then refers to the boundary question between the United States of Colombia
                        and Costa Rica, and says that the difficulty has been amicably settled.</p>
                <p>He alludes to the arrival of a minister from Guatemala to obtain the
                        ratification of the treaty of December, 1871, and his recall, he not having
                        the necessary powers to act in the premises.</p>
                <p>He next refers to the peaceful state of the country; his visit to Europe;
                        expresses the hope that ere long Costa Rica will take a distinguished place
                        among the great nations he visited, and looks forward to the day when the
                        Central American States will be merged into one grand republic.</p>
                <p>He alludes to the stability of the national credit abroad, owing to the
                        punctuality with’ which the nation meets its obligations; states that the
                        revenue of the country has doubled itself in direct proportion to the
                        increase of commerce, and that the population is fast increasing. He
                        compares the net proceeds of the national revenue of 1869, seven hundred and
                        eighty-three thousand dollars, against those of the past <pb facs="0296" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/> year, viz, one million six hundred and
                        sixty-four thousand dollars, or more than double; that the total revenue in
                        1870 was two millions five hundred and eighteen thousand dollars, or eight
                        hundred and fifty thousand dollars more than the previous year, and one
                        million seven hundred and thirty-five thousand dollars more than in 1869,
                        and avers that, in the coming year, the revenue will exceed three millions
                        of dollars. The President then puts the question, if the revenue of the
                        country has increased so rapidly during the construction of the railroad,
                        what will it be when that work is accomplished?</p>
                <p>He then refers to what he terms the late “supposed” monetary crisis in this
                        country, attributes the cause to the suspending of credits in a private
                        bank; but states that it had been dispelled by the protective influence of
                        the government.</p>
                <p>The President then refers to the construction of the railway to the Atlantic,
                        and is sanguine of its completion; refers to the report of a commission
                        appointed by the government to examine it and report progress.</p>
                <p>Such, in brief, is the substance of the document that forms the subject of
                        this dispatch.</p>
                <p>I am inclined to the opinion that it will be more valued without than within
                        the country.</p>
                <p>Many statements of the President appear to me too highly colored—particularly
                        is this the case when he speaks of the credit of the nation abroad and its
                        present financial condition.</p>
                <p>I will reserve, for another occasion, to give the Department an accurate and
                        full statement of the political and financial condition of the country.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>JACOB B. BLAIR</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
