<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 84.Mr. Blair
                            to Mr. Fish..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-06-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-06-23T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664" lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871" lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130" lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699" lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-06-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-06-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="86" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d86">
                <head>No. 84.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blair</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="to">Fish</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the
                                    United States,<lb/>San José, Costa Rica</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-06-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi>
                                23, 1873</date>. (Rec’d July 26.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 153.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Inasmuch as the sands of my official existence
                        are fast running out, and this legation will soon cease to exist by
                        operation of law, I deem it appropriate to review, briefly, the political
                        and financial history of Costa Rica during the four years and eight months,
                        the period I have had the honor to represent the United States as minister
                        resident to this republic.</p>
                <p>I arrived here on the 2d day of October, 1868, and presented my credentials
                        on the 6th of the same month. I found the executive chair of the republic
                        occupied by Señor Doctor Don José Maria Castro, a gentleman of fine personal
                        appearance, agreeable manners, intelligent, and whose administration gave
                        the most conclusive proof that the President regarded the freedom of speech
                        and press as not only the essence, but necessary to the existence of a
                        republican governments</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the people were in the full enjoyment of these <pb facs="0297" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/> inestimable privileges, and the
                        country prospering to perhaps a greater extent than under any former
                        administration, within one month after my arrival a revolution occurred,
                        resulting in the removal of President Castro from office, and placing Jesus
                        Jimenez in the executive chair as provisional president. The constitution
                        being abrogated by reason of the revolution, President Jimenez continued to
                        act as provisional president, untrammeled by any constitutional
                        restrictions, until a new constitution was formed, and a President elected
                        under its provisions, which occurred in the month of March following, when
                        President Jimenez was duly elected President of the republic for the term of
                        three years from the 8th day of May, 1869, at which time he was duly
                        installed into office. In less than thirty days from his inauguration, the
                        President of the republic found arrayed against his administration, both in
                        and out of Congress, a most formidable party, and realizing that “power is a
                        heavy burden” he tendered his resignation, which Congress refused to accept.
                        He then asked Congress to clothe him with “full powers,” to which Congress
                        acceded. The granting of full powers simply means the folding up of the
                        constitution for a given period, until the President can rid himself of all
                        opposition to his administration by banishing his enemies from the
                        country.</p>
                <p>President Jimenez remained in office until 27th of April, 1871, when he was
                        relieved from the burden of official life by a second revolution, which made
                        Señor Dr. Don Bruno Carranzo provisional President of the republic.</p>
                <p>President Carranzo served his country faithfully for a period of a little
                        over ninety days, when, not taking a hopeful view of the situation, he laid
                        down his robes of office at the feet of Congress, and retired into private
                        life. Congress at once elected as provisional President General Thomas
                        Guardia, the hero of the last revolution. A convention was soon called to
                        form a new constitution, and under its provisions an election was held, and
                        General Thomas Guardia elected President of the republic. He was inaugurated
                        on the 8th of May, 1872. His term of office will constitutionally expire May
                        the 8th, 1876.</p>
                <p>Almost the first official act President Guardia performed was to enter into a
                        contract on behalf of the government with Mr. Henry Meiggs, a citizen of the
                        United States, but who now, and for several years has been, a resident of
                        Peru, to construct a railroad from Port Lemon, on the Atlantic, to the city
                        of Alagula, a point about fifty miles distant from the Pacific Ocean,
                        passing through the cities of Cartago, San José, and Heredia, the estimated
                        distance being one hundred and twenty-nine miles.</p>
                <p>By the terms of the contract the government agrees to pay Mr. Meiggs the sum
                        of eight millions six hundred thousand dollars to construct said road,
                        furnish it with all necessary rolling stock, and erect buildings for depots,
                        &amp;c. The road to be finished December, 1874.</p>
                <p>The work has been prosecuted with commendable energy; still there is little
                        hope of its being completed in contract time. At Port Lemon end about
                        fifteen miles are nearly completed. In the interior fifteen miles may be
                        said to be finished and twenty miles more graded. By far the most difficult
                        and expensive part of the line remains untouched.</p>
                <p>The question whether Mr. Meiggs will fully comply with his part of the
                        contract does not seem to be the problem the most thoughtful are trying to
                        solve. It is this: Will the government be able to negotiate a loan
                        sufficient to enable it to comply with its part of the contract? For it is
                        reasonable to suppose that if the government should fail to pay, Mr. Meiggs
                        will cease to work. I think it will. The government has <pb facs="0298" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/> already obtained loans to the amount of
                        seventeen millions of dollars, realizing therefrom about $9,000,000. This
                        sum would be sufficient to enable the government to meet its engagement with
                        Mr. Meiggs but for the fact that the government is compelled to draw from
                        this fund an amount necessary to cover the amount of the interest borrowed,
                        and two percent., which is set apart as a sinking fund.</p>
                <p>I feel confident a further loan of at least five millions of dollars will be
                        required to meet the demands upon the government during the construction of
                        the railway. The debt of the country will then stand as follows: <table cols="2" rows="7">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Amount of loans for railway purposes</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom" role="num">$22,000,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Domestic Loan</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom" role="num">300,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Debt to Peru</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #border-bottom" role="num">100,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Total</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #border-bottom" role="num">22,400,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>The estimated income of the country, as per official statement
                                    for the fiscal year 1873–’74, is</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom" role="num">$2,850,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Expenses, including interest on foreign loans</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #border-bottom" role="num">2,350,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Leaving a surplus of</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom" role="num">500,000</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>But it is proper that I should state that the estimate of the income of the
                        present fiscal year is greater than last year by $648,000, and greater than
                        the previous year by $1,034,000.</p>
                <p>It is difficult to see how a country embracing an area of only 5,700 square
                        miles, with a population not exceeding 170,000 inhabitants, the exports of
                        which are confined almost exclusively to one single article, coffee, can
                        liquidate such an enormous debt as Costa Rica is contracting. The thing at
                        my stand-point is utterly impossible, and in a few years more Costa Rica,
                        like Venezuela, Honduras, and other Central and South American States, will
                        be literally bankrupt.</p>
                <p>It is now-generally conceded that Mr. Meiggs will not be able to construct
                        the railway for the sum stipulated in his contract with the government by
                        over a million of dollars, and it is also clearly understood that he has by
                        some private arrangement with the government, been released from all
                        responsibility or loss in the event the sum stated in the contract proves
                        insufficient to construct the railway. Rumor has it that he performed this
                        diplomatic feat by assigning, with consent of this government, the contract
                        to Mr. Henry Meiggs Keith, a relative of Mr. Meiggs, but a man of no
                        responsibility whatever.</p>
                <p>Should this impression prove true, and I fear it will, Costa Rica will indeed
                        be in an unenviable condition. The country at present is tranquil, and the
                        indications are that peace, with its innumerable blessings, will be enjoyed
                        by the people of Costa Rica for years to come. But it is well to remember,
                        as it is peculiarly applicable to these Central American States, the
                        truthful saying, that no one can tell what a day may bring forth.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>JACOB B. BLAIR</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
