<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1988-03-23T20:10:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1988-03-23T14:30:00-05:00" n="139" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                    <head>139. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d139fn1">Source: Department of State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss> Records, Memoranda of Conversations
                            Pertaining to United States and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            Relations, 1981–1990, Lot 93D188, 3/88 Washington/<persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>—<persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>. Secret; Sensitive. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PM_1">Parris</persName>. The meeting took place in
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>’s outer office at the
                            Department of State. In an undated memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> reported to <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>: “In taking my leave of
                                <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>, I told him we
                            remained committed to making as much progress as we can across our full
                            agenda between now and May 30. He said the Soviet side is as well, and I
                            felt he was sincere in stressing the importance of doing everything
                            possible to ensure that your visit to Moscow is a success.” (Reagan
                            Library, <persName corresp="#p_LN_1">Ledsky</persName> Files, Soviet
                            Union (<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>)(1))</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1988-03-23T14:30:00-05:00" to="1988-03-23T20:10:00-05:00">March 23, 1988, 2:30–8:10 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECTS</head>
                        <item>Ministerial Dates, Iran-Iraq, Afghanistan, Other Regional Issues,
                            Working Group Reports, Joint Statement</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </head>
                                <item>THE SECRETARY</item>
                                <item>Gen. <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1">Armacost</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <gloss target="#t_EURSOV_1">EUR/SOV</gloss> Director <persName corresp="#p_PM_1">Parris</persName> (Notetaker)</item>
                                <item>Mr. Zarechnak (Interpreter)</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">U.S.S.R.</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </head>
                                <item>FOREIGN MINISTER <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> Aide
                                        <persName corresp="#p_ST_1">Stepanov</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> Aide
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TS_1">Tarasenko</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Soviet <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> Notetaker</item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Palazhchenko</persName>
                                    (Interpreter)</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0905" n="868" xml:id="pg_868"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Ministerial Dates</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said it had been a good
                        meeting with the President. It was good to have the question of a summit
                        date resolved.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY agreed. Having a date would allow work to begin on the
                        details—both in terms of arrangements and substance. Setting dates was a way
                        of saying we were serious. For the same reason, it might be a good idea in
                        the joint statement to be issued after the ministers met to give the dates
                        for their April meeting, and to indicate they would meet in May as well.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> agreed, noting that the
                        best time for him in April would be April 25. But he understood that was a
                        problem for the Secretary.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said he thought agreement had been reached on the dates April
                        21–22 for the Secretary’s discussions in Moscow, with some travel outside
                        Moscow the following weekend. The Secretary had to be back in Washington the
                        evening of April 25.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> agreed that the April
                        meeting should be April 21–25. As for May, the middle of the month would be
                        best for him. THE SECRETARY agreed that the statement would say “mid-May,”
                        with precise dates to be determined later.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> observed that the
                        ministers seemed to have said as much as was necessary on the Middle East
                        that morning. If their experts came up with something in the meantime, it
                        could be reflected in the joint statement. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued to believe that there ingredients of
                        a common approach. Perhaps these could be discussed in greater detail in
                        April, during the Secretary’s Moscow visit.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that the statement should say that the two sides had
                        discussed the Middle East and would continue to do so. But we would have to
                        say that our respective concepts of an international conference and how to
                        go about it were quite different.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Iran-Iraq</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that the ministers
                        needed to finish their discussion of Afghanistan.</p>
                    <p>The Foreign Minister had already dealt with the Iran-Iraq war. In the spirit
                        of the understanding the ministers had, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> could confirm that, after the Secretary General
                        had completed his consultations with the foreign ministers of Iran and Iraq,
                        the Soviet Union would be able to act in the Security Council.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY welcomed this. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        proposed to return to the U.K. draft without the modifications which the two
                        sides had considered in Moscow for a suspension period during which the
                        Secretary General could seek implementation of the first resolution.
                            <persName corresp="#p_DP_1">Perez de Cuellar</persName> was already, in
                        effect, doing this.</p>
                    <pb facs="0906" n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> was not sure about such
                        an approach. The Soviet Union had agreed in principle to work on the basis
                        of the U.K. draft, but since then many amendments had been attached to it.
                        The time before the Secretary General’s meeting with the Iranians and Iraqis
                        should be used to work on the text.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY asked <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> if
                        he would be willing to say publicly what he had said to him in private.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that, for public
                        consumption, it might be better to state simply that, if the Secretary
                        General’s consultations produced no results, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet Union would favor “strong action.” The two
                        sides had already decided that this meant voting for a second
                        resolution.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY agreed that the phrase “strong action” should be recorded in
                        the joint statement. If asked what this meant, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would say it referred to voting a second resolution. If
                        asked what about the Soviet view, we would suggest putting the question to
                        the Soviet Union. The Secretary remarked that the President’s comments at
                        the White House made clear how deeply he had been moved by recent reports of
                        chemical weapons use in the Iran-Iraq war.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said he understood. He
                        appreciated the need for a resolution, even though it would give him a “big
                        headache” with Iran after the vote.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY reemphasized that a decision was needed. If there were a
                        subsequent need for further follow-up, the two sides could consult.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> recalled that the
                        current <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> proposal called for the 30 day
                        suspense period the ministers had discussed in Moscow.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY repeated that the idea in February had been to enable the
                        Secretary General to use the suspense period to seek Iranian compliance with
                        Resolution 598. Time had passed since then, and the consultations which had
                        been foreseen were happening. This argued for going back to the original
                        U.K. draft.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said he felt the
                        suspense period should be retained. Implementation should be based on
                        whatever situation prevailed at the time.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that, if the modification were retained, the suspense
                        period should be very short.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Afghanistan</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked about
                        Afghanistan.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said it was hard. He asked to review the bidding to be sure he
                        understood the Soviet position, laying aside for the moment the question of
                        arms supplies.</p>
                    <pb facs="0907" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/>
                    <p>The Soviet side agreed, he recounted, that half its troops would leave in the
                        first three months. If the Geneva accords were signed, the withdrawal would
                        be over by the end of the year. The Soviet Union and the parties agreed that
                            <persName corresp="#p_CD_1">Cordovez</persName> could in a private
                        capacity mediate efforts to reach agreement on an Afghan interim government
                        acceptable to all parties. We assumed that was something the Soviet side
                        would be prepared to make public. (<persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> shook his head in the affirmative when the
                        Secretary asked, “Right?”).</p>
                    <p>The Secretary recalled that the Soviet side had suggested that, as far as it
                        was concerned, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> could say it would
                        continue to support those we had supported in the past. The Soviet Union
                        would reserve the right to complain about this, but would not claim that the
                        Geneva accords were being violated.</p>
                    <p>The most sensitive issue, the Secretary said, had to do with Pakistan,
                        because there was no other realistic route for transporting supplies to the
                        resistance. Any <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> statement of its right
                        to deliver arms, if it chose to do so, had to be credible. As a practical
                        matter, we hoped this would not be necessary. We would say we would observe
                        restraint if the Soviet Union did. If the Soviet side showed restraint, so
                        would we. We would say this publicly.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said he would like to have from <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> some indication as to how the Soviet Union
                        would comment on Pakistan’s position in light of such a statement by the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> If, for example, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> said it would continue arms supplies, and
                        Moscow said that Pakistan would be in violation of the accords if they
                        transited that country, that would be too contentious for us.</p>
                    <p>There were a number of factors to consider in this context, the Secretary
                        emphasized. One was an actual supply operation by the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> Then there was the question of what the
                        Soviet Union would say under those circumstances. We needed to understand
                        what kind of position Pakistan would be in if we accepted the Soviet
                        proposal. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would make a
                        statement—and be ready to act on it. But under the withdrawal timetable that
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had described of
                        seven months or so it was not at all clear that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would deliver any supplies. We would, however, reserve the
                        right to do so. These were the kinds of considerations the Secretary would
                        like to get <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s feel
                        for.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said it would not be
                        possible to just invent something here in Washington. The Soviets had no
                        desire to criticize the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>’s discharge of
                        its obligations to Pakistan. As for American military assistance to groups
                        opposing the Kabul government, that Moscow would criticize. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> frequently criticized Soviet military
                        assistance. The ministers could discuss this kind of thing. But to go beyond
                        that and decide what might happen if Pakistan supplies the resistance would
                        lead nowhere.</p>
                    <pb facs="0908" n="871" xml:id="pg_871"/>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said he had asked a different question. Pakistan would not
                        supply anything. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would provide any
                        assistance. But since it was most practical for <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> aid to go through Pakistan, questions would emerge in
                        response not to what the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        <hi rend="italic">did</hi>, but what it <hi rend="italic">said</hi>, if we
                        accepted the formula the Soviet side had proposed. It would be one thing for
                        Moscow to criticize the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> It would be
                        another if Pakistan were criticized. It would help for <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> to say the Soviet Union would
                        say nothing, at least not until an actual act of supply had occurred.</p>
                    <p>After a lengthy pause, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName>
                        said that if there were no actual act of supply, there would be no reason
                        for Moscow to invent one.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said, “Thank you.”</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> added, “If there is no
                        supply.” The document the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> were to sign made no reference to
                        arms supplies. The issue was simply not covered.</p>
                    <p>ARMACOST pointed out that the instrument of guarantee in Geneva committed the
                        guarantors to respect the undertakings of the high contracting parties. That
                        was why the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had to be concerned about
                        Pakistan’s position. A lawyer would argue that, to the degree the
                        contracting parties have undertaken not to supply, the guarantors were
                        involved. That was why the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was
                        suggesting a moratorium.</p>
                    <p>ADAMISHIN asked for a clarification. It was his understanding that the Soviet
                        side was being asked not to criticize not a statement, but only actual
                        provision of supplies. His question was: “Whose statement?”</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY asked what if the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> were to
                        say it would support “as needed” those it had supported.</p>
                    <p>ADAMISHIN said that would be a <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        statement, not the Pakistani statement.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY speculated that Pakistan might say that it had noted the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> statement, and supported the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> in that statement.</p>
                    <p>ADAMISHIN posed a second question: would the statements be made before or
                        after signing? And, in the second case, would the statements be seen as an
                        interpretation of the Geneva accords? Obviously, if the statements were made
                        before signing in Geneva, it would sound one way; if after, another.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY asked <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName> to
                        explain. ADAMISHIN said it would make a difference in how Moscow
                        responded.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY explained that if the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> did
                        what he had described, and it would be difficult for us to do so, we would
                        say that we intended to act as a guarantor of the Geneva accords. We would
                        say further that we felt that continuing support for those we had been <pb facs="0909" n="872" xml:id="pg_872"/> supporting was consistent with our
                        role as guarantor. So the question of a violation would not arise. If asked,
                        we would say that the people we supported were not covered by the accords’
                        definition of “mercenaries,” etc, since they were fighting for the freedom
                        of Afghanistan.</p>
                    <p>ADAMISHIN interrupted to comment that, from what the Secretary was saying, it
                        appeared that such a statement would be made before signature.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that, when the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> said
                        it would sign, it would make a statement about what it intended to do. We
                        had major problems on this issue with Congress. The Secretary had just
                        gotten off the phone with Sen. <persName corresp="#p_BRW_1">Byrd</persName>,
                        who had expressed concern that the Secretary was going to give away
                        Afghanistan. So we needed a posture we could defend. As he had said at the
                        outset, however, the Secretary was talking about how to present what was
                        taking place, not what would really be taking place.</p>
                    <p>POWELL observed that, if the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> signed and
                        the accords were in place, the first question from Congress would be, “Does
                        that mean we will stop aid?” We would say, “Only if the Soviet Union does.”
                        If the Soviet Union continued, we would continue. The Soviet side, <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName> speculated, would criticize the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> statement, but not allege a
                        violation of the Geneva accords.</p>
                    <p>The next questions would be, “If the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        continues arms supplies, or has to resume supplies, and if <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> aid can only go through Pakistan, what
                        will the Soviet reaction be if Pakistan agrees to allow such aid to transit
                        its territory?” It was <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>’s
                        understanding that the Soviet Union would not only criticize such a decision
                        by Pakistan, but would allege a violation.</p>
                    <p>BESSMERTNYKH clarified that the formula discussed by <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1">Armacost</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName> did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> provide for
                        symmetry between <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet
                        obligations. The concept was not appropriate, because the situations were
                        not analogous. To try to say that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        would supply the opposition if the Soviet Union supplied the government of
                        Afghanistan would be to add a new element to the formula. The Soviet formula
                        contained no linkage to supplies.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY pointed out that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was
                        talking about a unilateral statement. We would say we were prepared to
                        resume supplies, and that our readiness to take that step would be affected
                        by what the Soviet Union did. That implied no undertaking by the Soviet
                        side. It was a unilateral view.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that the
                        discussion had shown there were only two ways to resolve the problem.</p>
                    <p>The first was based on the fact that the Geneva accords imposed no
                        obligations on guarantors not to supply arms. There was thus no <pb facs="0910" n="873" xml:id="pg_873"/> need for the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet Union to discuss the matter. If
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> wanted to supply the resistance, it
                        should do it. The Soviet side would not be “consultants” as to how that
                        should be done. It was not in Soviet interests for the aid to continue. How
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> provided aid was its business. For
                        public opinion purposes, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> could
                        simply point out that Geneva did not deal with arms supplies by
                        guarantors.</p>
                    <p>A second option was for the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> to refrain
                        from signing in Geneva. This was a bad option, but could not be ruled out. A
                        document signed in Geneva on a three-way basis would involve the Soviet
                        Union only insofar as it addressed troop withdrawals. This was clearly a
                        less satisfactory approach. These were the two options. There was no other
                        way.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY recalled that <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had earlier seemed to suggest that there were
                        circumstances under which it would not allege that Pakistan had violated the
                        Geneva accords, if the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had stated its
                        intentions along the lines the Secretary had described, and Pakistan had
                        endorsed that statement. The Secretary asked if <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> could elaborate on that, emphasizing that he
                        was trying to distinguish between how the Soviets would react to statements
                        on one hand, and an actual flow of arms on the other.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> responded somewhat
                        testily that he wanted the Secretary to know Moscow was not tied to the
                        Geneva process. If an agreement were signed, that would be good. It not, it
                        would mean that the process of reaching a settlement in Afghanistan would
                        take a different path. But <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said he felt that the two sides had come very
                        close to a meeting of the minds. There were still a few days in which to
                        give legal force to something they had been discussing for many years.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said he had the
                        impression that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and Pakistan had
                        obtained what they had most wanted from this process—dates for the
                        withdrawal of Soviet forces from Afghanistan. Now the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was trying to get more. This tactic would
                        not work. Moscow could have not set dates and continued to bargain. Instead,
                        it had sought to convince the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and
                        Pakistan that it was serious, that it would withdraw. So dates had been
                        set.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> alleged, had not really believed that the
                        Soviet Union would get out of Afghanistan. As a result, it had not
                        adequately studied the drafts when they were being prepared in Geneva. It
                        was too late for second thoughts. To try now to nullify the accords would
                        lead nowhere. If the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> wanted to continue
                        to supply the resistance, it could go ahead, since this was not covered by
                        the Geneva documents. In practical terms, how the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> did this was its problem. The Soviets knew how to get
                        their troops out of Afghanistan. How the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> got arms in was up to it. But the question had to be
                        settled today, now. That was the direction <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> thought their conversation in Moscow—and
                        previous conversations—was leading.</p>
                    <pb facs="0911" n="874" xml:id="pg_874"/>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY acknowledged that there had been a lot of discussion on
                        Afghanistan. That discussion had included the need for a balanced outcome.
                        We welcomed the steps which had been taken thus far. We wanted to see the
                        Geneva process come to fruition. But we also wanted to be in a position to
                        avoid political turmoil here which would have an adverse impact on that
                        process. Were we to say that nothing in the accords prevented us from
                        continuing to support those we had supported, and that we intended to do so,
                        we would expect the Soviet Union to criticize that statement, but not to
                        charge that it violated the accords.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that the Soviet
                        Union would not invoke the accords under such a scenario.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that there also had to be clarity when the question was
                        asked as to how this affected Pakistan. If Pakistan were to state that they
                        supported our statement, and would cooperate with us if it were necessary to
                        resume aid, we understood that, to use <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s words, the Soviet Union wouldn’t have to
                        “invent” anything. In effect, Moscow would criticize Pakistan’s statement,
                        but not say Pakistan had violated the accords.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that Pakistan was
                        bound by the accords not to supply the opposition. That did not apply to the
                        guarantors. It was up to the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> to decide
                        what intermediaries it used to supply aid to the resistance. But it should
                        realize there would be efficient monitoring mechanisms, including <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> inspectors, to ensure Pakistan did not
                        supply arms. That, however, had no relation to the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> asked the Secretary to
                        recognize that the Soviet Union had already made very substantial
                        concessions. General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_GM_1">Gorbachev</persName> himself had said that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> should cut off supplies to the resistance once the Soviet
                        Union had made its decision to withdraw. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> did not want to dwell on the matter, but this
                        was an important statement by the leader of the Soviet Union. Now the Soviet
                        position was quite different: the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        <hi rend="italic">could</hi> supply the opposition, and the Soviet Union
                        would not claim a violation, although it would criticize such action.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY suggested a caucus. He moved to his private office, accompanied
                        by <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1">Armacost</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PM_1">Parris</persName>.</p>
                    <p>After a ten-minute break, the Secretary and his advisors returned. THE
                        SECRETARY outlined the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> position in
                        light of the previous discussion.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> welcomed, he said, the steps which
                        had been taken toward a settlement of situation in Afghanistan and the
                        withdrawal of Soviet forces from that country. We felt there was a clear
                        understanding that these objectives were close to being achieved. We also
                        believed, <pb facs="0912" n="875" xml:id="pg_875"/> however, that any
                        negotiated outcome must provide for a balance of obligations among its
                        signatories. It was also most important that conditions be created during
                        the withdrawal period and thereafter which would ensure the safe and
                        honorable return to Afghanistan of refugees. In this context, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> welcomed the agreement under which
                            <persName corresp="#p_CD_1">Cordovez</persName> would work in a private
                        capacity to mediate among the various Afghan parties on interim government
                        arrangements.</p>
                    <p>Under these circumstances, the Secretary continued, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> felt it important for all parties—the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>, Soviet Union, and others—to agree
                        to a moratorium on arms shipments. The moratorium would initially run for
                        the period during which Soviet forces would be withdrawn, and for three
                        months thereafter. It could be extended if, as all the Afghan parties had
                        called for, agreement could be reached on a neutral status for
                        Afghanistan.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side had proposed such a moratorium
                        during the course of the morning’s discussion. The Soviet side had said it
                        could not agree. Our proposal remained on the table. Under the circumstances
                        the Secretary had described, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was
                        prepared to assume the responsibility of guarantor of the Geneva accords. In
                        the absence of such arrangements, we would not be able to undertake those
                        obligations.</p>
                    <p>ARMACOST added that acceptance by either side of the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> moratorium proposal would be without prejudice to its
                        rights to supply arms to parties in Afghanistan.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said this was an important point. Acceptance of a moratorium
                        would be without prejudice to any rights held by either side. It would be an
                        act designed with the best interests of Afghanistan in mind.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said that, while he could not speak for Pakistan, he knew that
                        the Pakistanis, like ourselves, wanted to see Geneva signed.</p>
                    <p>After a lengthy pause, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName>
                        suggested that the ministers move on to the next regional issue. “On the
                        basis which you have indicated, it will not be possible to reach
                        agreement.”</p>
                    <p>After a further pause, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        asked what the consequences of such an arrangement would be. The
                        negotiations in Geneva were between Pakistan and Afghanistan. They could
                        continue. Everything that had to do with the Soviet Union had already been
                        stated, and declared acceptable by Pakistan and Afghanistan. If Pakistan was
                        prepared to sign, the accords could be concluded without guarantors. There
                        was nothing tragic about that. If there was no signature at all, that, too,
                        would not be so terrible.</p>
                    <pb facs="0913" n="876" xml:id="pg_876"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Central America</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY asked if <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        wished to take up Central America. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that the ministers had discussed the basic
                        elements of that issue Monday evening.<note n="2" xml:id="d139fn2">March 21;
                            see <ref target="#d132">Document 132</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY offered to describe the situation as the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> saw it. Over the previous seven or eight
                        years there had been steady movement toward more openness and democracy
                        among most of the governments of the region. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had welcomed this trend. All of the countries involved
                        were relatively poor. Their traditions were more feudal than
                        militaristic.</p>
                    <p>In Nicaragua, there was a different pattern, although we saw some prospect
                        for positive change. Nicaragua was like its neighbours in being a small,
                        poor country. It was unique in that its government was seeking to develop a
                        centralized, more totalitarian form. That government was putting into place
                        a military force triple the size of any other country in the region. The
                        ultimate scope of Nicaragua’s military plans had been revealed by a senior
                        defector and, incredibly, confirmed by Nicaragua’s Defense Minister. All of
                        this was taking place against a backdrop of massive Soviet military
                        support—support which remained at a level of a quarter billion dollars this
                        year, despite the conclusion of the Guatemala City agreement.<note n="3" xml:id="d139fn3">See <ref target="#d82fn10">footnote 10, Document
                                82</ref>.</note> This was a massive sum by Central American
                        standards, and there was no sign that the flow of supplies was
                        decreasing.</p>
                    <p>In the Guatemala City accords, Nicaragua had committed itself to a pattern of
                        internal development consistent with an open, democratic society. The
                        standards set in these accords were frankly higher than those prevailing in
                        the Soviet Union today, despite words like <hi rend="italic">glasnost</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Unfortunately, the trends in Nicaragua seemed to be retrogressing,
                        particularly in the wake of the House of Representatives’ cut-off of aid to
                        freedom fighters. Nicaragua had recently moved 1,500-2,000 troops into
                        Honduras in an apparent effort to wipe out the freedom fighters and their
                        supply sources. The attempt had failed, because the freedom fighters had
                        given a good account of themselves, because of the outrage the action had
                        provoked in the region, and because the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        had responded to Honduras’ request for a show of support. As the Secretary
                        had indicated on Monday, our forces would probably begin returning home over
                        the weekend.</p>
                    <p>It had not escaped our notice that the Soviet Union maintained an aircraft in
                        Nicaragua—ostensibly for mapping purposes. We knew, however, that that
                        aircraft was being used for aerial reconnaissance to <pb facs="0914" n="877" xml:id="pg_877"/> provide tactical intelligence for Sandinist
                        counterinsurgency operations. Such activities by the Soviet Union on the eve
                        of ceasefire talks between the freedom fighters and Managua was hardly in
                        keeping with Soviet calls for reduction of tension in the region and
                        implementation of the Guatemala City accords—one feature of which was the
                        ceasefire talks. Those talks were continuing, and the initial reports were
                        positive. But there was never an agreement until there was an agreement. We
                        would await the results.</p>
                    <p>The policy of the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was to support the
                        Guatemala City accords; to support the ceasefire negotiations; to join other
                        countries in insisting that Nicaragua meet its obligations under the
                        accords; and to be ready for direct talks with Managua in a regional
                        setting.</p>
                    <p>When <persName corresp="#p_GM_1">Gorbachev</persName> had been in Washington,
                        he had said that the Soviet Union also supported the Guatemala City accords.
                        He had also said something which apparently he had repeated to Senator Nunn
                        and others when they were in Moscow—that the Soviet Union was prepared to
                        reduce military assistance to Nicaragua to the level of police weapons if
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> did not supply arms to the freedom
                        fighters. If the Soviet side were really interested in such an undertaking,
                        we would welcome the opportunity to explore it. It was an observable fact
                        that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was not currently providing
                        assistance to the fighters.</p>
                    <p>In short, the Secretary concluded, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        wanted to see Central America removed from the list of trouble spots, an
                        area of greater stability, whose citizens would be free to get about the
                        business of improving their economic well-being. He could assure <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> that in the context of
                        implementation of the Guatemala City accords, and with the behaviour Moscow
                        had volunteered, we were prepared to talk to the Nicaraguans in a regional
                        setting, and to work with the nations of the region, including Nicaragua, to
                        improve economic conditions.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> recalled that the
                        Soviet delegation had made clear during the Washington summit its support
                        for the Contadora process, later the Contadora group and its support group,
                        and finally the Guatemala City agreement. Moscow felt that these efforts
                        provided the right basis for a settlement of the problems of Central
                        America.</p>
                    <p>Unfortunately, not everything resolved in Guatemala City had been
                        implemented. And this was not the fault of Nicaragua. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> recalled the steps already
                        taken by the Sandinist government: it had taken the initiative to engage in
                        negotiations on a ceasefire; it had been the first in the region to
                        establish a commission on national reconciliation. Looked at objectively,
                        much had been done to advance democratization in Nicaragua. The media had
                        been opened to the opposition on an equal basis. Nicaragua had taken the
                        initiative at the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> to ask for
                        monitoring/inspection of the Nicaragua–Honduras border.</p>
                    <pb facs="0915" n="878" xml:id="pg_878"/>
                    <p>Nicaragua’s “solid” military forces, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> explained, were a function of its needs. If a
                        country did not feel threatened, it would obviously prefer to devote scarce
                        resources to its economic development. The situation around Nicaragua was
                        such that it did not have this luxury, and this was largely the result of
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> policy. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> appeared to be “organically incompatible” with the
                        Sandinist regime. This was totally inappropriate. What did the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> have against Nicaragua’s government? How
                        were they a threat to the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>? Did
                        Nicaragua need Honduran territory? No. Were it not for the bands of
                        extremists fighting the current government, the countries of Central America
                        would have found a solution to these problems long ago.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> reminded the Secretary
                        that he had already said the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>’s despatch
                        of troops to Honduras was inappropriate. But the decision was America’s. It
                        was not for Moscow to order the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> about.
                        But the action was totally unjustified and had caused alarm not only in the
                        region, but around the world. But the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        appeared to think that this was its personal hemisphere and it could do what
                        it wanted.</p>
                    <p>But where was the solution?, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> asked. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        could not strangle the Nicaraguan revolution. It was the people’s struggle.
                        It was bigger than Nicaragua. The only way out was to engage in direct
                        dialogue with Nicaragua—and Cuba, too. Unfortunately, it appeared that some
                        Administration officials still hewed to the old, notorious policy of trying
                        to establish an order acceptable to the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        in every country and in every region of the world. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had complained about Soviet shipment of
                        arms to Nicaragua. On what basis did the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> ship arms to Pakistan? The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> did not even stop at shipping arms to governments close to
                        the Soviet Union’s borders. It aided groups fighting legitimate government
                        all over the globe. Why should the Soviet Union not supply a government
                        which was represented in the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> and was
                        universally recognized.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY asked to interject some comments on the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>’s relations with the government of Nicaragua. When the
                        Sandinist revolution took place, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        had supported it. We had welcomed Somoza’s ouster. We were quick to provide
                        economic assistance to the new regime, assistance which, on a per capita
                        basis, had been the highest of any of our aid programs. But the revolution
                        had gone sour. The proof of that was that many of the people who had made
                        the revolution left Nicaragua, or were forced to leave. So we had to shift
                        our policy.</p>
                    <p>Even then, some years later, in response to recommendations by many
                        countries, but notably Mexico, the President had authorized the Secretary to
                        go to Managua and talk to Ortega. Bilateral talks had been set up to support
                        the Contadora process. There were a series of meetings in Manzanilla. But we
                        soon found that Nicaragua was going to other governments and saying that it
                        would not deal with them because it <pb facs="0916" n="879" xml:id="pg_879"/> was working directly with the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> We had
                        been forced to break off talks, although we said we would resume them in a
                        regional context. We had reaffirmed that position with the conclusion of the
                        Guatemala City accords. We wanted to encourage the success of the accords,
                        and of the ceasefire, so that the region could focus on economic
                        development.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> agreed that that was
                        needed. But he felt the Secretary was ignoring one fundamental issue—neither
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> nor the Soviet Union could tell
                        Nicaragua or any other people how they should live. This was what the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was trying to do. It did not like the
                        Managua government, so it kept raising additional requirements. The
                        Nicaraguan people had established an order of their own.</p>
                    <p>As for Soviet arms supplies, the General Secretary had told the President
                        that both countries should refrain on a mutual basis from providing arms.
                        That offer remained on the table. If the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was prepared to stop supplying arms to all Central
                        American countries, so was the Soviet Union. The only exception would be
                        police-type arms, which could continue to be provided. If the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> were interested, the idea could be
                        explored further.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY pointed out that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had
                        long-standing relationships with the countries of Central America, some of
                        which involved the supply of military assistance for purposes of keeping
                        order. The most obvious case was El Salvador, where there was a guerrilla
                        movement supported by Nicaragua and Cuba. This forced the Salvadoran
                        government to maintain a larger military than they would like. We could not
                        cut off those who were simply seeking to maintain order in their country in
                        the face of a challenge from Nicaragua and Cuba.</p>
                    <p>As for Nicaragua, there was no <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        assistance flowing to those opposed to the government. Even over the past
                        few years, what aid had been provided was relatively little.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said the Secretary’s
                        logic was odd. The Secretary called those fighting against the Nicaraguan
                        government “freedom fighters.” He used the same term to describe those
                        opposed to the governments of Afghanistan and Angola. Those who opposed the
                        regimes he liked were bad people. There was an inconsistency here.</p>
                    <p>As for arms supplies, if <persName corresp="#p_GM_1">Gorbachev</persName>’s
                        proposal was acceptable, why not get down to discussions on that basis? If
                        it was not, the Soviet Union would meet the obligations it had to Nicaragua,
                        just as the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> met its obligations to many
                        of the Soviet Union’s neighbours. Moscow didn’t complain about that. Why
                        should the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had ringed the Soviet Union with bases—big bases, and lots
                        of them. <persName corresp="#p_YD_1">Yazov</persName> had shown <persName corresp="#p_CFC_1">Carlucci</persName> a map the week before. When
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had seen the map,
                        it had frightened him.</p>
                    <pb facs="0917" n="880" xml:id="pg_880"/>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that all our forces were for defensive purposes. Besides,
                        the Soviet Union was so big, it was hard not to surround it.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said it would cost the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> a lot to do so. But there were some
                        good trends that the two sides should try to take advantage of. That was why
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had raised the
                        question of limiting naval activities the day before.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said Moscow really had
                        no desire to arm Nicaragua if that country were not threatened. He proposed
                        the two sides discuss the matter and see whether some mutually acceptable
                        solution could not be found. He assured the Secretary that Moscow was not
                        getting rich by providing weapons to Managua. It would welcome the
                        opportunity to stop.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY noted that there was now a good rationale—the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was no longer sending arms to those we had
                        formerly supported in Nicaragua. That should remove the need for Soviet arms
                        supplies.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked what about
                        Honduras.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that was a different question. Honduras was not invading
                        Nicaragua.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked where the contras
                        were based. How were they armed, trained? Honduras was not rich enough to do
                        that. There was a need for mutuality.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY underscored that there was <hi rend="italic">no</hi> aid going
                        to the freedom fighters, wherever they were. Honduras was indeed in no shape
                        to supply anyone. It was a poor country.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that Honduran
                        weapons were good, modern. Some said they looked much like American weapons.
                        But there was no need to get specific.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Regional Dialogue</p>
                    <p>Recalling a point <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had
                        made on an earlier occasion, THE SECRETARY said he sometimes thought our
                        regional dialogue with the Soviet Union would be more productive if there
                        were a different approach. Some headway had been made as a result of experts
                        discussions on the Iran-Iraq war, southern Africa, and Afghanistan.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> interrupted to say with
                        some feeling that there had been no progress on Afghanistan. If asked at the
                        conclusion of their meeting what had been achieved on that subject,
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> would say that it
                        had been impossible to find common language, that no positive elements had
                        emerged from the discussion.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY replied that what he had in mind was to try to focus on what we
                        would like to see in certain regions in, e.g., 1995 or 2000. It would not be
                        too difficult to define emerging trends. It would <pb facs="0918" n="881" xml:id="pg_881"/> be interesting and potentially fruitful to discuss
                        their implications for <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet
                        relations.</p>
                    <p>Following further elaboration by the Secretary of this concept, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> agreed that such an approach
                        might have merit, but pointed out that certain problems had to be addressed
                        now. Otherwise any plans which might be developed would be in vain.</p>
                    <p>Apparently in this context, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said he was reminded of the relationship
                        between the problems of Afghanistan and the Iran-Iraq war. The Soviet Union
                        had been true to its word in both cases. The Soviets had said what they
                        would do, and had made clear they would follow through on any obligations
                        they had assumed, even where it would be difficult for them. But, on
                        Afghanistan, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had pulled back from
                        its commitments. It had not been as good as its word. This was not a
                        tragedy, but the point had to be made.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary in his comments on improving the regional dialogue had referred
                        to the Soviet Union’s providing missiles to Iraq. It was a fact that Moscow
                        provided arms to Iraq. No one complained about it because it was done on a
                        legal basis.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said he had not meant to complain about Soviet arms supplies to
                        Iraq. He only wanted to make the point that ballistic missile proliferation
                        was occurring.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that, even if the
                        Soviet Union voted for an embargo on arms to Iran, it was not certain the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would not itself arm Iran. That was
                        the way things were in the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> The
                        Secretary of State said one thing; other members of the Administration did
                        something else.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that the earlier <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        attempt to provide arms to Iran was a misguided enterprise. Its scale was
                        inconsequential. It would not be repeated.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said there was no
                        guarantee of this. The whole administration had been involved. This was not
                        just a private firm. One of <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>’s
                        predecessors had been intimately involved.<note n="4" xml:id="d139fn4">Presumably reference is to either <persName corresp="#p_MRB_1">McFarlane</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_PJM_1">Poindexter</persName>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that the discussion was going downhill. If the ministers
                        started down this path it would lead nowhere.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> protested that there
                        was a fundamental question involved. When the Soviet Union was considering
                        what to do about a second <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> resolution on
                        the Gulf war, one reason for its delay was uncertainty as to whether the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>, or some private firm sponsored by
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>, would not supply arms to Iran.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> was still not
                        sure.</p>
                    <pb facs="0919" n="882" xml:id="pg_882"/>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that, under the circumstances, he could not believe
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> was saying
                        this.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said he had believed
                        the Secretary until that afternoon, until they had discussed Afghanistan.
                        Now his confidence was shaken. There were certain norms in any business,
                        including “this one.” But <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> would drop the subject.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Afghanistan</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had played
                        it straight on Afghanistan. We had made known our concerns on what we called
                        “symmetry” for some time. This was not a new idea.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> replied that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> wanted the Soviet Union to abandon its
                        friends, friends to whom Moscow was linked by legitimate relations. The
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> wanted to equate the government of
                        Afghanistan to fundamentalist bands. “We can’t accept that. You have put
                        forward demands that are unacceptable.”</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had listened
                        carefully to the concerns the Soviet side had expressed, just as, we hoped,
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had listened to us.
                        We had tried to put out an idea which got to the Soviet problem. The
                        Secretary did not see why it would be so difficult for Moscow to supply
                        Kabul with what it needed before an agreement entered into force. We had
                        tried to respect the Soviet need to preserve the right to be able to supply
                        the Kabul regime. We had not challenged that. We had tried to come up with a
                        solution consistent with that. We had tried to work with <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName>’s formula. We had not been able
                        to find language which did the job. We were still ready to seek formulae
                        which could describe what both sides wanted to see happen.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said his conclusion was
                        that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would remain outside the
                        Afghan settlement process. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would
                        not be able to give orders to Pakistan. The Soviets knew the Pakistanis
                        would make their own decisions. It was up to the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> to say what it would do.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY confirmed that Pakistan would make its own decisions. The
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>, for its part, was ready to sign in
                        Geneva, but subject to finding a formula which would be workable. We had
                        tried to fit such a formula into <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName>’s proposal. We had tried out the idea of a
                        moratorium. The Soviet Union traditionally favored moratoria. What was wrong
                        with one in this case?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> replied that he could
                        give the Secretary a long list of Soviet moratorium proposals that the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had derided.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY suggested that <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> offer one on Afghanistan. Or perhaps the Kabul
                        government, which had stated its desire that Afghanistan be neutral, could,
                        with the comfort provided by Soviet weapons provided prior to entry into
                        force of the Geneva <pb facs="0920" n="883" xml:id="pg_883"/> accords, might
                        itself call for a moratorium. The Soviet Union and the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> could honor that appeal.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said he had come to
                        Washington well prepared to deal with this issue. He had had extensive
                        consultations with those dealing with Pakistan and Afghanistan on
                        Afghanistan questions. If he saw options other than those he had proposed,
                        he would have given them to the Secretary.</p>
                    <p>But there was no need to dwell on the question. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> understood that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would not act as a guarantor for the Geneva accords.
                        Accordingly, the Soviet Union would not either. The process would proceed on
                        a different basis. There was no need to add new language; it was simply a
                        matter of deleting. So, what was next, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> asked.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Cambodia/Korea</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY suggested Cambodia. Sihanouk was an asset with respect to a
                        settlement there, because he was someone the people could rally around. The
                        key, however, remained for Vietnam to leave Cambodia.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> agreed that there were
                        certain positive elements. The dialogue between Sihanouk and Hun Sen was
                        very important. Sihanouk certainly supplied a certain prestige. He was
                        occasionally ridden by doubts and hesitations, but who wasn’t? The situation
                        was complicated, but the issues of a political settlement and national
                        reconciliation were proceeding in a positive way in the context of the
                        Sihanouk-Hun Sen dialogue.</p>
                    <p>As for Vietnam, its course was clear. By 1990 it would have withdrawn its
                        troops. The process was already underway; a substantial number was already
                        out. The Vietnamese had their own plan. There was no reason for anyone else
                        to interfere. Sihanouk himself, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> speculated, might have an interest in seeing
                        certain issues resolved before the Vietnamese left. Among them: questions
                        relating to Cambodia’s governmental and national structure; relations
                        between the opposing parties; and China’s attitude. Until China’s attitude
                        were clear, one could not speak with confidence on prospects for a
                        settlement.</p>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss> was also playing an important role,
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said, particularly
                        Indonesia. The Vietnamese dialogue with Thailand was less fruitful, although
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had heard some
                        interesting things in his talks with the Thai foreign minister. Perhaps
                        there were prospects in this area as well.</p>
                    <p>So, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> concluded, there
                        were some positive trends. But much depended on how the Afghanistan problem
                        turned out. Afghanistan was the first time there was a real opportunity for
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet Union to resolve a major
                        regional issue. If national reconciliation <pb facs="0921" n="884" xml:id="pg_884"/> proved to be an effective basis for a settlement, it
                        would have a positive impact on prospects for solutions to the problems of
                        Cambodia, southern Africa and elsewhere. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> knew first-hand that the leaders of Afghanistan
                        and Cambodia considered the trends in their two countries to be related.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> emphasized that it was
                        the task of the great powers to encourage national reconciliation. This was
                        sometimes difficult. But the choice boiled down to encouraging national
                        reconciliation or encouraging civil wars. Afghanistan was the
                        touchstone.</p>
                    <p>As for Korea, the ministers in Moscow had talked about the proposals which
                        Kim Il Sung had asked <persName corresp="#p_GM_1">Gorbachev</persName> to
                        convey at the Washington summit. These were thoughtful proposals which
                        warranted serious consideration. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> did not rule out that South Korea might also
                        come forward with serious proposals. If this happened, they, too, could be
                        considered.</p>
                    <p>On a more general plane, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        called for a broader <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet dialogue on
                        Asia and the Pacific. The Secretary was aware of the Soviet Vladivostok
                        proposals. The Soviet side knew of the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        reaction to some of those proposals; some elements of the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> position were by no means unacceptable.
                        The Australian government had also had some good ideas. Could the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet Union not seek to harness
                        emerging trends and ideas in this vast area to formulate a mutually
                        acceptable platform—like they were already doing in the Middle East? This
                        was an area which should not be ignored. Perhaps there could be a reference
                        to this idea in the joint statement.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said it would be good to discuss Pacific issues.</p>
                    <p>On Korea, the Secretary noted that there was a new President in Seoul, whose
                        popular mandate gave him a stronger power base. He was still sorting out his
                        domestic program. Once national assembly elections were over, he would have
                        a freer hand for foreign affairs. He clearly had a bolder approach than his
                        predecessor to dealing with the North. Once South Korea’s political
                        transition was sorted out, he would be inclined to do things. Of course the
                        Olympic Games were currently claiming all of the South’s attention.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Southern Africa</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> suggested that
                            <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName> report on his Monday
                        discussion of southern Africa with Asst. Sec. Crocker.</p>
                    <p>ADAMISHIN said that his talks with Crocker had revealed broad agreement on
                        the theoretical plane, which, however broke down on questions of tactics.
                        Both sides, for example, were opposed to apartheid. But the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was not prepared to make a joint statement
                        on recent anti-democratic moves by South Africa. Both sides wanted South
                        Africa out of Angola, but disagreed over how this should be brought
                        about.</p>
                    <pb facs="0922" n="885" xml:id="pg_885"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName> said that the most
                        important segment of the experts’ talks had to do with the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>-Angolan-Cuban talks. <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName> had made clear that Moscow
                        supported the talks and was by no means opposed to <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> mediation efforts. But the Soviet Union strongly supported
                        the positions Angola had taken in the discussions thus far. <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName>’s impression was that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was seeking the maximum number of
                        concessions, particularly with respect to a Cuban troop withdrawal, without
                        offering anything in return. Specifically, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had made clear it would not end aid to <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>Both sides, <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName> concluded, felt
                        that the discussions were useful, and should continue.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY asked to comment. <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Adamishin</persName> was right: both the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet Union deplored apartheid. We wanted a different
                        situation in South Africa. We had made that plain. Our own relations with
                        South Africa were strained, although they existed.</p>
                    <p>We saw significant potential for movement on the complex of issues related to
                        Angola, Namibia and a Cuban troop withdrawal. So, apparently, did the South
                        Africans. Botha had recently asked to meet with Crocker; and a meeting had
                        taken place in Geneva. So hoped to keep that dialogue open.</p>
                    <p>There was greater fluidity in the situation. If national reconciliation could
                        get underway in Angola, it could contribute to the removal of both Cuban and
                        South African forces from that country. That, in turn, would open up the
                        Benguela railroad, which could have an enormous economic impact in the
                        region. <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Savimbi</persName> was a genuinely
                        popular leader, enjoying the support of 40% of Angola’s population. He did
                        not seek a military victory; he favored national reconciliation. Many
                        African leaders were also in favor of reconciliation in Angola. Perhaps
                        parallel demarches in African capitals to this effect would contribute to
                        the process.</p>
                    <p>As for a Cuban troop withdrawal and Resolution 435,<note n="5" xml:id="d139fn5">See <ref target="#d162fn6">footnote 6, Document
                                162</ref>.</note> what we were calling for was not unilateral
                        concessions, but putting together a package which would be credible enough
                        to engage South Africa’s attention. South Africa at least rhetorically was
                        committed to implementation of 235 under the right circumstances. And, of
                        course, once Namibia had gained its independence, Angola would be cut off
                        from South Africa.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary noted that, on the other side of the continent, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was supporting the Chissano government,
                        along with the Soviet Union. While some in the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> favored supporting RENAMO, that was not the Secretary’s
                        policy, or the President’s. We would welcome <pb facs="0923" n="886" xml:id="pg_886"/> reinvigoration of the Nkomate accords. If the
                        situation in Mozambique could be brought under control, the Beira corridor
                        could be reopened. In conjunction with the reopening of the Benguela
                        railroad, the economic impact of such a development would be important.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary noted that <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        had once commented on the potential importance of regional groupings to the
                        resolution of local conflicts. We agreed. Southern Africa was an area where
                        the concept could be given a chance to work. Setting local transportation
                        systems back on their feet could make a major contribution. So these were
                        some of the ideas we had on southern Africa. Some might be appropriate for
                        parallel or joint efforts.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that parallel
                        efforts were probably most appropriate. Our consultations on southern Africa
                        had nonetheless produced good results and should be continued.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> cautioned that national
                        reconciliation was at a different stage in southern Africa than in such
                        areas as Afghanistan or Cambodia. In those areas, conditions were ripe for
                        solutions. It was still early in Africa. It was not possible to force the
                        process. There were some ideas on the table which could be studied. The
                        African states, for example, had suggested a <gloss target="#t_UNSC_1">UNSC</gloss> meeting. Perhaps this could be supported, although
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> didn’t want to make
                        any commitments at this point. It might prove useful in focusing public
                        attention on the problem.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Cyprus</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> noted that he and the
                        Secretary had not in the past discussed Cyprus. But there had been requests
                        from both the current and previous Cypriot governments that the problem be
                        taken up in <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet bilateral
                        discussions. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> did not
                        want to get into details, but there were some interesting ideas, e.g. for an
                        international conference. Perhaps the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                        and Soviet Union could do something to revive the process of finding a
                        solution.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said he would think about it. It seemed to him that the most
                        interesting thing going on with respect to Cyprus was the developing
                        dialogue between Greece and Turkey. If their relations improved, it could
                        have an important impact on the situation in Cyprus.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> agreed. Intercommunal
                        differences on the island would no doubt continue, but there were some
                        positive factors: the Greek-Turkish dialogue; new leadership among the Greek
                        and Turkish Cypriot communities. Perhaps some way could be found to
                        engage.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Bilateral Issues</p>
                    <p>After determining that joint statements were not yet ready for the ministers’
                        review, THE SECRETARY touched briefly on bilateral issues. <pb facs="0924" n="887" xml:id="pg_887"/> He said he particularly wanted to endorse the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> proposal that cultural centers be
                        established in Moscow and Washington, and that an announcement be made at
                        the summit. We were prepared to move ahead in this area, and were ready for
                        detailed discussions if there were interest on the Soviet side.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> nodded in
                        acknowledgement.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Working Group Reports</p>
                    <p>The Ministers then decided that, as the joint statement was still being
                        prepared, they should hear from working groups. <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName>
                        were summoned, and <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> briefly
                        summarized the results of the Nuclear and Space group’s discussions.</p>
                    <p>The thrust of OBUKHOV’s opening remarks was that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had insisted on language which had nothing to do with the
                        Washington Summit statement, which ministers had agreed in Moscow should be
                        the basis for a new agreement on observance of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked if that meant that nothing had been
                        achieved in this area. OBUKHOV said that the issue had been discussed both
                        in the working group and by <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KV_1">Karpov</persName>.
                            <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> was not informed on the
                        outcome of their discussions.</p>
                    <p>NITZE challenged <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName>’s
                        presentation of the subject, noting that the real problem was that the
                        Washington Summit Statement language was never intended to be a
                        self-standing agreement. A formal agreement would require greater
                        specificity as to the meaning of “non-withdrawal.” It would also have to
                        deal with issues like the supreme national interest clause, and what should
                        happen at the end of the non-withdrawal period. So a number of questions
                        remained on which work had to be done.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY pointed out that there were also verification questions to be
                        addressed. There seemed to have been some headway, but more was needed. We
                        had some ideas on how to reduce ambiguity. NITZE said that our proposal on
                        space sensors was one such idea.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> what he meant by “sensors.”
                            <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> briefly explained the
                        concept.</p>
                    <p>OBUKHOV noted that the Soviet side had just received the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> proposal. It would require expert analysis
                        and assessment.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that the key was
                        to determine what would take place during the non-withdrawal period. The
                        Soviet side thought that should be compliance with the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. If the two sides could agree on
                        this, it would make open the field to progress across the board.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY noted that that was the virtue of trying to work from a joint
                        draft text. As had proven the case in other areas, such a device forced
                        negotiators to identify for ministers where the problems lay. This could be
                        done for the April meeting.</p>
                    <pb facs="0925" n="888" xml:id="pg_888"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said this could be
                        considered. But the important thing was not the text itself, but knowing
                        where the differences lay. The bottom line was that the present visit had
                        added nothing to what had been achieved during the Washington summit. If
                        anything, the situation was less clear. So, work should continue.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY agreed, but on the basis of a joint text. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that the Soviet
                        delegation didn’t consider that a useful idea. OBUKHOV explained that the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> text would “drown” the principles
                        which had been agreed to in Washington. Perhaps the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> could provide a revised text, which dropped the additional
                        points. NITZE noted that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> text
                        contained all of the elements of the Washington Statement,<note n="6" xml:id="d139fn6">See <ref target="#d125fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                125</ref>.</note> as well as other elements we considered
                        necessary.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said he disagreed with
                        something <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> had said
                        earlier—that the Washington statement was only “communique language.”
                        Rather, it should be seen as the basis for everything. THE SECRETARY pointed
                        out that <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> had said the
                        Washington Statement language was incorporated into the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> text, adding that it did not provide
                        adequate clarity. We had provided some ideas on how to achieve that.</p>
                    <p>“OK,” <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said, “let’s work
                        on a joint document.” But that was not the solution. It could not be
                        recorded that progress had been made. NITZE noted that agreement to work a
                        joint draft text <hi rend="italic">was</hi> progress. THE SECRETARY said
                        that, whether it was progress or not, it should be done. He agreed with
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> that, on the whole,
                        little had been achieved. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that the two sides had gotten nowhere, and
                        asked <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> to continue his
                        report.</p>
                    <p>When <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> had finished, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> asked him where, in the
                        Soviet working group’s view, there had been progress during the visit.
                        OBUKHOV said that there had been some movement on <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>’s, in that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had
                        revised upward its proposals for a counting rule. This did not solve the
                        problem, since, in the Soviet view, the only realistic rule was the maximum
                        number for which bombers could be configured, but the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> move suggested that this issue could
                        ultimately be resolved. While there had been no definitive progress on the
                            <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> question, the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had agreed to intensify experts
                        discussions on verification questions, and this, too, was a step
                        forward.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked if there had been
                        a discussion of the detailed proposals the Soviet side had made on <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> verification. OBUKHOV said that the
                        Soviet side had made a thorough presentation, that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had asked a number of questions, and that
                            <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> had <pb facs="0926" n="889" xml:id="pg_889"/> raised no objections. From this, <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> assumed that the Soviet ideas would
                        be studied. NITZE interjected that he had said the proposals would be
                        studied. He had made no commitments.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY asked if any brackets had been eliminated in the texts prepared
                        to date. NITZE said Hamner felt it would be possible to remove some
                        brackets. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that, as
                        best he could tell, there had been no serious movement on <gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss>. If the other groups had done no better,
                        it was not clear there would be anything for the ministers to review in
                        April.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> were then dismissed, and <persName corresp="#p_HHA_1">Holmes</persName> and Palenykh summoned to report on
                        the nuclear testing group’s discussion.</p>
                    <p>Following their statements, THE SECRETARY asked how long it would take to
                        complete a technical verification protocol after the <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss> had been conducted. HOLMES said that
                        remained to be seen, but that the <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss> was
                        being designed to minimize the gap. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked what there would be to sign in Moscow if
                        there were no <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss> results. Palenykh
                        admitted that, without such results, it would be premature to sign anything.
                        That was why the <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss> was necessary.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked Palenykh to
                        confirm his understanding that, without conducting the <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss>, there would be no documents to sign in
                        Moscow. Assuming ideal conditions, how much time would it take to prepare
                        the necessary documents once a <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss> had been
                        conducted?</p>
                    <p>PALENYKH said that the <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss> could be
                        conducted by the end of May. The results would be available perhaps a week
                        later. For more substantive analysis, more time would be required. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that this was an
                        important consideration for the ministers, because it bore on what could be
                        signed at a summit.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that Palenykh had provided a technically perfect answer.
                        If we conducted enough tests, eventually we would know all there was to know
                        about the subject. The question was, at what point would we know enough to
                        be able to establish something, knowing that the situation could shift as we
                        proceeded? We felt that it would be possible to develop a protocol without
                        first conducting a <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss>. We wouldn’t know
                        everything, but we would know enough.</p>
                    <p>HOLMES noted that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> felt that no
                            <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss> was necessary to complete a
                        protocol on the Peaceful Nuclear Explosions Treaty (<gloss target="#t_PNET_1">PNET</gloss>). The Soviets were considering this
                        idea. If they agreed, the protocol could be signed in Moscow, although its
                        submission for advice and consent would have to await agreement on a
                        satisfactory protocol for the Threshold Test Ban Treaty (<gloss target="#t_TTBT_1">TTBT</gloss>).</p>
                    <p>PALENYKH pointed out that the Soviet proposal was not to do many experiments.
                        One would be sufficient to provide the data they <pb facs="0927" n="890" xml:id="pg_890"/> considered necessary to familiarize themselves with
                        the CORRTEX method proposed by the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> But
                        even a single test would require some analysis.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said to the Secretary
                        that he (<persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>) had explored
                        after the ministers’ last meeting whether or not it would be possible to
                        prepare testing protocols without conducting a <gloss target="#t_JVE_1">JVE</gloss>. Most of the experts had said it was not.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said it was up to the Soviet side. He proposed that the
                        ministers conclude their discussion of testing. We would do it the Soviet
                        way, even though that meant there would probably be nothing to sign at the
                        summit.</p>
                    <p>Palenykh departed, to be replaced by Nazarkin. At the Secretary’s invitation,
                        HOLMES read a short agreed statement on the results of the <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> working group’s discussions. NAZARKIN then
                        read a much longer “personal” comment on the talks, one element of which
                        focused on the alleged <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> insistence on a
                        right to refuse challenge inspections of private facilities.</p>
                    <p>Asked by THE SECRETARY if this was correct, HOLMES indicated that the problem
                        was how to define what facilities were “relevant.” Privately owned
                        facilities, as such, were not the problem. THE SECRETARY noted that the
                        “relevant” problem would apply to government-owned, as well as to
                        privately-owned facilities.</p>
                    <p>A brief discussion of <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> verification
                        questions followed, after which Nazarkin and <persName corresp="#p_HHA_1">Holmes</persName> departed, to be replaced by Grinevskiy and <gloss target="#t_EURRPM_1">EUR/RPM</gloss> Deputy Director Moffitt.</p>
                    <p>Asked to proceed, GRINEVSKIY reported that it had not been possible to agree
                        on a joint report. He described objections raised by the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> to the Soviet proposal for an exchange of
                        data on conventional forces in Europe.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said he would like to comment on that. Every effort was being
                        made in Vienna to complete the mandate for conventional discussions. We were
                        also insisting upon a balanced outcome to the Vienna meeting. It was not
                        possible simply to leapfrog that process to, in effect, begin discussions of
                        conventional arms in Europe before Vienna had concluded. The Soviet proposal
                        would have that effect. Moreover, our experience in the <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> negotiations was that years could be
                        spent arguing about data. Ultimately, we had had to try a different approach
                        altogether. We would of course take up the Soviet proposal with our allies,
                        but saw little to comment it.</p>
                    <p>MOFFITT noted that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had reiterated in
                        the working group its opposition to a reference in any conventional mandate
                        to dual-capable systems. We had also expressed reservations with respect to
                        the proposal for discussions on naval activities which <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had made the previous
                        day.</p>
                    <pb facs="0928" n="891" xml:id="pg_891"/>
                    <p>Grinevskiy and Moffitt were replaced by <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Simons</persName> and Kutovoy, who reported on the results of the
                        bilateral working group.</p>
                    <p>SIMONS report focused on five sets of negotiations (fisheries,
                        transportation, basic sciences, maritime search and rescue, and cultural
                        exchanges) which could produce documents for signature in Moscow. He noted
                        that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had handed over draft texts on
                        transportation and basic sciences, and would soon be in a position to
                        provide drafts on exchanges, as well as a draft memorandum on the
                        establishment of cultural centers under the 1985 Exchanges agreement.</p>
                    <p>KUTOVOY’s response noted that there had also been discussion of cooperation
                        in what he termed the more “difficult” areas of <gloss target="#t_AIDS_1">AIDS</gloss> research, trade, energy, and the Arctic.</p>
                    <p>In response to <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName>’s request
                        for clarification as to what agreements might be ready for signature in
                        Moscow, SIMONS again went over the list. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> asked if this was a realistic assessment. Both
                        SIMONS and KUTOVOY said it was.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Joint Statement/Final Assessments</p>
                    <p>At this point, the ministers received copies of the draft joint statements
                        for their review.</p>
                    <p>After reading the texts, THE SECRETARY expressed regret that the Soviet side
                        had not, as <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had earlier
                        indicated, been willing to include a reference to “strong actions” which
                        would be undertaken in the event the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                        Secretary General’s early April consultations with Iran and Iraq produced no
                        results. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that such
                        language was not needed, as nothing was said about Afghanistan. THE
                        SECRETARY said, “OK.”</p>
                    <p>The ministers authorized release of the statements.</p>
                    <p>Reflecting on the results of his visit, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> reiterated that if progress continued at this
                        rate there would be no serious documents to sign at the Moscow summit. It
                        was of course possible to meet and talk without signing documents. But it
                        was discouraging that the two ministers and their delegations could meet for
                        two days without accomplishing anything substantive. The statement was a
                        good one, but it contained no specifics.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> suggested that this
                        pointed to the need for particularly thorough preparations before the
                        ministers’ next meeting. He would be in favor of removing as many brackets
                        and disagreements as possible.</p>
                    <p>What then, should be said to the press? Was a press conference really
                        necessary? How would the ministers assess their work?</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said that he agreed that the visit had not been very
                        productive. He had been asking himself why this should be. In <pb facs="0929" n="892" xml:id="pg_892"/> the past, the ministers had dealt
                        more successfully with some very difficult problems. That had not happened
                        this time.</p>
                    <p>The problems which remained were the hard ones. But the Secretary felt that,
                        with the right spirit on both sides, the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> issue could be resolved. The <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> discounting rule also seemed to be resolvable, even if,
                        thus far, it had not proved possible to identify conceptually common ground.
                        The <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss> issue remained tough, but we
                        would look at Soviet suggestions. We thought that a declaration was a
                        realistic way out of the problem; we were not optimistic about being able to
                        verify a limit.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> desire to limit strategic arms was
                        strong, the Secretary affirmed. The President shared this view. He wanted to
                        get the job done. And the prospect was tanatalizing when we looked at how
                        much had been accomplished since the Secretary and <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had first met in Helsinki.
                        The difference was like night and day. The two <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> protocols and <gloss target="#t_MOU_1">MOU</gloss> which
                        the ministers had commissioned in Moscow had been produced, albeit with lots
                        of brackets. Many of these had to do with technical issues which should
                        yield to further efforts. Others required resolution of broader
                        questions.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said he was as discouraged as anything by the failure to
                        accomplish anything in the regional area. He felt that the overall effort we
                        had been making in this area had been soured. Even at the most difficult
                        moments in their relationship, e.g. during the Daniloff affair,<note n="7" xml:id="d139fn7">See <ref target="#d35fn4">footnote 4, Document
                            35</ref>.</note> he had not felt such a sourness, even though the
                        discussions were tough.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said that he had gained the impression from his experience
                        going back to the Nixon administration that there were rhythms to the
                        relationship. One of the accomplishments of the past few years had been to
                        attenuate the swings of the pendulum, while keeping the trend line moving in
                        a generally positive direction. Perhaps the relationship was entering a
                        downward cycle; the Secretary hoped we could pull out of it.</p>
                    <p>POWELL said that, while both sides obviously would have liked to accomplish
                        more, they knew that they would be dealing with the most difficult
                        questions—particularly on arms control. <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName> agreed that we could work on <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss>’s; <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>’s would be harder, even with the new Soviet ideas.</p>
                    <p>For his part, <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName> had been most
                        disappointed over the failure to make progress on the question of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. We had felt after the Secretary’s
                        Moscow visit that there would be movement in this area. Since then, the
                        Soviet side had not engaged. <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>
                        emphasized <pb facs="0930" n="893" xml:id="pg_893"/> that steps <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be taken to eliminate the ambiguity in the
                        Washington Summit Statement. This was an essential political imperative for
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> After the Washington summit, our
                        negotiators had been instructed to use the Statement as the <hi rend="italic">basis</hi> for a treaty, not as the text of a treaty
                        itself. This ambiguity had to be resolved before we could take a possible
                        treaty to the Senate. That was why we had put forward our proposals on
                        sensors and verification procedures. Soviet acceptance of these would create
                        a common understanding of what had been intended in Washington.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY stressed that the approach <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName> had described was intended to get away from the
                        debate over the broad versus the narrow interpretation of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. It sought to put out information
                        on the nature of each side’s programs. This would provide greater
                        predictability and certainty, something which the Soviet side had sought, as
                        well as a clearer idea of what would happen during the non-withdrawal
                        period.</p>
                    <p>RIDGWAY said that she had been reminded by some of her colleagues that in
                        “off cycle” periods, bilateral progress could provide useful buoyancy. The
                        report of the bilateral working group had identified a number of areas where
                        constructive progress was being made.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY observed that, seen in the long term, there were clearly stages
                        in the development of our relationship, each with its own dynamics. The
                        Geneva summit had had a certain air. Reykjavik was a different sort of
                        meeting—highly charged, but, as summits went, the most productive ever. The
                        Washington summit was a magnificent event, crowned by the signing of the
                            <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> Treaty. We hoped that there would
                        be an even more important treaty to sign in Moscow.</p>
                    <p>But one could ask: “What about a 1989 summit?” If we concluded a <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> agreement for Moscow, what could be
                        done for an encore? This was by way of saying that, for the relationship to
                        become more normal, the time had to come when our leaders could meet, and,
                        while it would be a major event, it need not be marked by gigantic
                        achievements. This was a mark of maturity in the relationship. As people
                        thought about the management of the relationship over the next five to ten
                        years, that needed to be kept in mind.</p>
                    <p>So, the Secretary concluded, he felt a little disappointed with their
                        meetings. But the way one accomplished things in this area was to keep
                        plugging away. Our people would be working in Geneva. It would be even more
                        important that people in capitals do their homework. The work in Geneva
                        reflected what was being done in capitals.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said he did not think
                        that the meetings had been useless—particularly when he read the joint
                        statement. What disturbed him was that he had expected to be able to
                        identify some concept for the Moscow summit, even if only in general terms.
                        If he <pb facs="0931" n="894" xml:id="pg_894"/> were asked what that concept
                        might be at this point, he could not answer. This did not imply that the
                        ministers should set grandiose tasks for themselves, but they needed a clear
                        idea of where the process was leading. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed that it would be possible to have a
                        meeting which did not produce major results. There was plenty of precedent
                        for that in visits by other world leaders. But <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet relations were special.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said he agreed completely. He thought that something could be
                        accomplished in the time remaining. So did the President.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that the ministers
                        should try to move positions closer together during their April meeting.
                        They should try to identify more clearly a concept for the summit.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said he did not want to
                        return to all the problems the ministers had discussed. <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> was central. Unless some decisions were
                        taken, there could be no expectation of progress in other areas. <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>’s were another important area which the
                        Soviet side hoped the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would be ready to
                        address urgently. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        wanted to emphasize that if there were not understanding on the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty, there would be no agreement on 50%
                        strategic reductions. The same went for <gloss target="#t_SLCM_1">SLCM</gloss>’s.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet Union, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued, had a unique
                        chance to close off the main channels of the arms race. He did not know how
                        Moscow’s relations with the next administration would be. Perhaps they would
                        be better. But the Soviet leadership felt that there was a unique chance to
                        negotiate an agreement now. It should not be missed. Guided by this
                        principle, the two sides should act more vigorously in Geneva, Washington
                        and Moscow.</p>
                    <p>By way of a second general observation, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said he had known the Secretary now for some
                        time. The Secretary knew the Foreign Minister did not hide his feelings.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had been deeply
                        disappointed by the results of their discussion of Afghanistan. He did not
                        know how to continue the discussion. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had simply decided it didn’t want to help solve the
                        problem. A major chance had existed to do something together, to resolve
                        “the most acute problem of our time.” Moscow would resolve the problem. But
                        it would have been well to demonstrate to the world that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> could work together to solve such problems. This was
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s most acute
                        disappointment as he left Washington.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said he did not want to
                        overdramatize this. But he had believed the two sides could do better. There
                        was every reason to expect success.</p>
                    <p>So, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> summed up, he had
                        been very frank. No purpose would be served by going over the issue once
                        more. But success would <pb facs="0932" n="895" xml:id="pg_895"/> have
                        helped in the resolution of other problems, e.g. the Iran-Iraq war, the
                        Middle East. The two sides had to cooperate if these issues were to be
                        resolved. Moscow knew the mentality of the Arab world. Resolution of the
                        Afghanistan conflict on a negotiated basis would have been a good stimulus
                        in the Middle East.</p>
                    <p>But the meeting had been useful, despite the disappointments. There was a
                        clearer idea of our differences. That was progress. And the atmosphere, as
                        always, had been hospitable and constructive. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> asked that the Secretary convey his thanks to
                        the President for the time he had made available.</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY asked to respond on a few points.</p>
                    <p>On the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> question, he urged that Soviet
                        negotiators in Geneva be instructed to engage on a joint draft text. They
                        should try to eliminate the inconsequential problems, e.g. the supreme
                        national interests clause issue. We were surprised at the adverse reaction
                        to our proposal that the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty should
                        remain in effect at the end of the non-withdrawal period unless a side
                        exercised the six-month notice of withdrawal option, and hoped the Soviet
                        side would look again at that. We urged the Soviet side to look closely at
                        our sensors and verification proposals as a means of giving clarity to the
                        Washington Summit Statement. Our objective was to put the issue on an
                        operation basis, avoiding the question of broad versus narrow interpretation
                        of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty.</p>
                    <p>On Afghanistan, the Secretary expressed his own disappointment, for reasons
                        paralleling those <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had
                        expressed. The Secretary felt the two sides had come close to an
                        understanding. He hoped <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        had a better appreciation of the difficulties we had. Our moratorium
                        proposal was an attempt to find solutions consistent with the Soviet need to
                        maintain a certain posture, and with what, in practical terms, Moscow would
                        want to do. It would give us the necessary sense of balance and even
                        contribute to a solution to Afghanistan’s internal problems.</p>
                    <p>If asked, the Secretary would say that there had been a thorough discussion
                        of Afghanistan and that, from our standpoint, there were some positive
                        results. We would welcome acceptance of <persName corresp="#p_CD_1">Cordovez</persName>’s mediation efforts. We would describe where the
                        talks had ended up. We would not put it in a cataclysmic way, but would
                        express our disappointment.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that, if he were
                        asked by the press whether the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> and
                        Soviet Union would sign as guarantors in Geneva, he would say, “no.” Was
                        that correct?</p>
                    <p>THE SECRETARY said he would say the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> was
                        prepared to act as a guarantor, and that the arrangements which had been
                        agreed to <pb facs="0933" n="896" xml:id="pg_896"/> were close to what we
                        needed to do so. But he would indicate that an essential element—balance—was
                        missing. He would say we had tried to resolve this and were not successful.
                        We remained glad to be a guarantor if the issue could be resolved.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">SHEVARDNADZE</persName> said that, if he were
                        asked what the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> would do, he would say
                        the press should ask the Secretary.</p>
                    <p>The meeting concluded with a brief discussion of plans for press conferences
                        that evening.<note n="8" xml:id="d139fn8">For the text of the joint
                            statement, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, May
                            1988, pp. 42–43.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>