<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1988-05-11T10:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1988-05-11T07:55:00-05:00" n="149" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d149">
                    <head>149. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d149fn1">Source: Department of State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss> Records, Memoranda of Conversations
                            Pertaining to United States and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            Relations, 1981–1990, Lot 93D188, Untitled Folder. Secret; Sensitive.
                            Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Simons</persName> on May 12. The
                            meeting took place in the Ambassador’s Office at the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> Mission.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1988-05-11T14:55:00+02:00" to="1988-05-11T17:30:00+02:00">May
                                11, 1988, 2:55–5:30 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>The Secretary’s First Meeting with <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </head>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George P. Shultz</persName>,
                                    Secretary of State</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Colin Powell</persName>,
                                    President’s National Security Advisor</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MJF_1">Jack F. Matlock</persName>, <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> Ambassador to Moscow</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Rozanne L. Ridgway</persName>,
                                    Assistant Secretary of State (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>)</item>
                                <pb facs="1021" n="984" xml:id="pg_984"/>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Thomas W. Simons, Jr.</persName>,
                                    Deputy Assistant Secretary of State (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>) (notetaker)</item>
                                <item>Dimitri Zarechnak (interpreter)</item>
                                <item>Peter Afanasenko (interpreter)</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </head>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Eduard Shevardnadze</persName>,
                                    Minister of Foreign Affairs</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Aleksandr A.
                                    Bessmertnykh</persName>, Deputy Foreign Minister</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TS_1">Sergei Tarasenko</persName>, Chief
                                    of <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s
                                    Secretariat</item>
                                <item>Georgiy Mamedov, USA and Canada Department (notetaker)</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pavel Palazhchenko</persName>,
                                    (interpreter)</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>During the photo opportunity, <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he had been asked why he arrived in Geneva so early; the last
                        time he had been here he had been asked why he arrived so late. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> gave him a picture of him showing the
                        President a photo of the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> flag flower
                        display in Tbilisi. In response to press questions, both said they were
                        there to work; <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> told a Soviet questioner the atmosphere in the delegation was
                        workmanlike and positive.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> began by saying he had told the
                        President of the very warm reception he had received in Tbilisi, and of the
                        good time he had had there. It had been a pleasure to see <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s children and grandchildren,
                        although he had had a hard time making friends with the youngest. He then
                        suggested they get to work.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said we had to move forward. But he wished to say first he had had
                        calls from Tbilisi and Kiev, all wishing the Secretary the best. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he had had good visits to both
                        places. It was educational and worthwhile to travel to different parts of
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s country. We all
                        knew intellectually that big countries are diverse, but it did not register
                        until you saw them. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said there was no substitute for personal experience.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said they were working to make the
                        summit a success. They needed to get hold of the issues, to get them in good
                        order. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he saw no reason to be pessimistic. It was in the nature of man
                        to want the maximum possible. Maybe they would not obtain that in this case.
                        But the leaders should review what had been done in the last years. There
                        would be a lot to report on in Moscow. There had been a lot of results. The
                        meeting could be a truly impressive occasion to take stock and determine the
                        prospects for the future. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he
                        agreed totally.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said it was becoming a tradition for them to finish up summit
                        preparations in Geneva. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> recalled that
                        the first summit itself had taken place there.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the principal questions concerned disarmament, specifically
                        strategic offensive weapons and the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss>
                        Treaty. Perhaps they could return to these questions later. First he wanted
                        to discuss the very basic questions of what could be completed by the time
                        of the Moscow visit. They would be meeting in a small group to discuss
                        strategic offensive arms, but the ministers should probably discuss <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> matters first.</p>
                    <pb facs="1022" n="985" xml:id="pg_985"/>
                    <p>On <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> there were problems that needed
                        discussion, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued.
                        He failed to understand what had happened. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side had asked some questions which the Soviet side had
                        answered. Then there was a new set of questions. The Soviets had sent
                        answers. It was not clear what the problem was. They needed to discuss it.
                        He had met with his experts through part of the night, digesting the
                        material. The issues were mostly technical. Their experts could meet, and
                        they could listen to them the next day. They could have a general
                        discussion, and then take stock. It would be very desirable to complete this
                        work while they were in Geneva.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said it was essential to complete it
                        while they were there, perhaps even that very day. There were two types of
                        issues.</p>
                    <p>First, the Secretary said, they had to nail down what they had previously
                        discussed on the so-called futuristic-type weapons on range at
                        treaty-prohibited areas. He thought there was no disagreement there. We had
                        brought with us a paper to clarify it. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName> had it with him, and could meet
                        with whomever <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> would
                        designate to finish it off. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he thought they had basically finished that issue. If the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> needed clarification, that would be fine.
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> replied that that was exactly the
                        case; it could even be a problem of translation from the Russian. People in
                        the Senate had asked that it be further clarified, and we had brought along
                        some language that had been worked with the Senate.</p>
                    <p>The other set of issues, the Secretary continued, were those that had arisen
                        between the two teams responsible for on-site inspection. It was not
                        surprising that problems arose when two technical teams met. He thought
                        these ought to be fairly resolvable. The guide should be the text of the
                        treaty. The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> had a strong technical team
                        in Geneva. He had brought Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GMM_1">Glitman</persName>, who had negotiated the treaty and was coordinating
                        the information flows with the Senate. The sooner the ministers gave
                        instructions for the work to be done the better off they would be. He
                        proposed that <persName corresp="#p_GMM_1">Glitman</persName> and a team
                        meet with a Soviet team on the second set of issues, and that <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s designate meet on futuristics. He hoped they
                        could finish that afternoon and evening. He was prepared to try.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said with <persName corresp="#p_GMM_1">Glitman</persName> the Soviet
                        delegation would be General Chervov and many specialists, including many
                        participants in the talks. With <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName>, he asked <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName>, he supposed it should be <persName corresp="#p_KV_1">Karpov</persName>; <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName>
                        </hi> confirmed that it should.</p>
                    <p>On <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and DST, <hi rend="italic">the
                            Secretary</hi> suggested that they convene a working group, which could
                        then report to them.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> asked if this meant there would be no plenary. Would they simply
                        instruct the working group to begin? <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi>
                        said he did not feel they needed a human rights working group; perhaps the
                            <pb facs="1023" n="986" xml:id="pg_986"/> two of them could discuss
                        that. The same, he felt, held for regional issues; they should discuss this
                        area themselves. On bilateral issues, <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Simons</persName> was there for discussions, to the extent they were
                        needed, with <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName>. That left
                        arms control: <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and Defense and Space, chemical
                        weapons, conventional arms.</p>
                    <p>On conventional arms, the Secretary continued, the ministers should seek to
                        break things open in Vienna. We had not seen particular motion there, and
                        that was where the key was. We thought very positive results in Vienna could
                        be reflected at the summit. <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had made many interesting statements on
                        conventional arms, also from the standpoint of the expense of their
                        respective defense efforts, where conventional arms played a major role,
                        even though strategic arms took a tremendous burden when it came to
                        deterrence. Both sides, he thought, would like to take note of movement; the
                        key was Vienna.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> replied that the negotiations were in Vienna, but much depended on the
                        two ministers. If they could not decide on the mandate and actual
                        negotiations did not begin, there would be no movement to report. He was
                        ready for more detailed discussion.</p>
                    <p>(At this point Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GMM_1">Maynard
                            Glitman</persName>, General Nikolai Chervov of the Soviet General Staff,
                        and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KV_1">Viktor Karpov</persName>, Soviet
                            <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> Disarmament Department head
                        arrived.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> greeted <persName corresp="#p_GMM_1">Glitman</persName>, joking he was responsible for the
                        whole <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> mess. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Secretary</hi> informed the newcomers that he and <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had decided they should meet
                        briefly with the ministers and then with each other and their people, and
                        should work in a positive frame of mind to resolve the remaining issues,
                        largely related to on-site inspection. He hoped the work could be completed
                        that day, though that would of course depend on how much could be achieved.
                            <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KV_1">Karpov</persName> would meet on futuristics. The
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side thought it quite possible the
                        problem there was one of translation; it had brought some language which key
                        members of the Senate found satisfactory.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> asked if <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName> were in
                        Geneva. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> replied that he had come with
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> team, but had stopped by his
                        apartment to change. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he had reviewed all the questions relating to <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> missiles, and did not see any that could
                        not be resolved at this meeting. It was important for the experts to sit
                        down and get to work. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said that was
                        also our view; he suggested the ministers kick them out. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he thought <persName corresp="#p_KV_1">Karpov</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName> might finish first;
                        all should get to work. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> bid farewell to
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GMM_1">Glitman</persName>. (<persName corresp="#p_GMM_1">Glitman</persName> and Chervov left at 3:20.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he thought there should be some discussion of nuclear testing and
                        chemical weapons, even if there were no formal working group. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he had his full panoply of people
                            <pb facs="1024" n="987" xml:id="pg_987"/> with him. He suggested they
                        organize; on the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side this would be
                        under <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Paul Nitze</persName>’s chairmanship. We
                        were prepared to work in all areas. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName>’s partner would be
                        (Ambassador Alexei) <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName>.
                            (<persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Simons</persName> left to call them
                        in.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he understood they would be
                        meeting until 5:30 p.m., and would reconvene after a break at 8:00 p.m. The
                            <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side was thinking in terms of
                        finishing by 9:30 p.m., and meeting again at 9:00 a.m. the next day, and
                        again in the afternoon, when they could work until they finished.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the Soviets had the same schedule in mind; the only difference
                        was they had envisaged working till 6:00 p.m. the first day, but 5:30 was
                        alright. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> explained that he had just
                        arrived and needed time to consult with his Geneva delegation. He was sorry
                        he could not come earlier, but he had had to host a dinner the night before
                        and wait till all the guests cleared out. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he had met with his people. He thought they were not optimistic
                        about strategic offensive weapons and the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. They had done some good work in Geneva, but without
                        a push from the ministers there would not be agreement.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he saw two other items for
                        discussion. First, they should reflect on how to document the summit and the
                        work done since the Washington summit; it would also be desirable to reflect
                        on the progress made since the Geneva summit.</p>
                    <p>(At 3:30 p.m. <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Paul Nitze</persName>, Special Advisor to the
                        President on Arms Control, arrived.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said jokingly he had told <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> he had been too quiet recently, listening to <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> proposals.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> told the newcomers he had explained to
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> that <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName> would be in a position to
                        discuss language on futuristics, consistent with what had been agreed, that
                        was satisfactory to the Senate, with a view to finishing off the issue. The
                        ministers were asking <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_OA_1">Obukhov</persName> to organize the arms
                        control working group, for discussion of chemical weapons, conventional
                        arms, nuclear testing, strategic arms, and defense and space issues.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName>
                        </hi> asked if they should report at 9:00 a.m. the next day, or take more
                        time. He did not think his people would welcome working all night, as had
                        happened once before. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> replied that this
                        was not formalized: he and <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> would be discussing some issues, and the others
                        could think of making reports the next afternoon. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he agreed. The <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> people should
                        work through the rest of the day and then report; the others should work and
                        then report the next afternoon. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> added,
                        however, that if they had something urgent to report they should come and
                        tell the ministers. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said that in principle, therefore, everything was clear.</p>
                    <pb facs="1025" n="988" xml:id="pg_988"/>
                    <p>(<persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KV_1">Karpov</persName>
                        left at 3:35 p.m.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> suggested the ministers discuss what the summit meeting should be
                        like, what results it should have.</p>
                    <p>Realistically, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        continued, it would not be possible to reach a <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> agreement by the summit. Even if the ministers agreed on
                        all the basic issues that day, it would be physically impossible to put them
                        all on paper in time. But he would welcome, as the crown of the summit, an
                        impressive document that summarized the results of Geneva, Reykjavik,
                        Washington and the work prior to Moscow. What the document was called was
                        not important. What was important was to record the results achieved.</p>
                    <p>A conceptual approach was also needed here, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> went on, and a review of specific issues: where
                        we stood on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>, what had been
                        achieved, what ground had been prepared for the future. The ministers needed
                        to decide whether it should be one big document or two documents. His view
                        was that it should be one big impressive document, and that it should be
                        signed by their two leaders. It could also be without their signatures, but
                        that would be different. A document signed by the two would evoke more
                        response in the world, would be more impressive. He thought their
                        negotiators should work on such a document.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he agreed that they could find
                        something suitable, and if both leaders signed it, that would be a good
                        concept. We had suggested two documents. We had no hangup on whether there
                        should be one or two. There were advantages and disadvantages each way. If
                        there were two, that would single out some issues, and the disadvantage was
                        that other issues would look as if they were of lesser importance. But we
                        had gotten going because there had been a tremendous amount of forward
                        movement toward 50% cuts in strategic arms since Geneva, and it would
                        provide continuity with the <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> Treaty to
                        register that in some way. If there were one document, there would have to
                        be a section with that in. Perhaps <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s suggestion was a good one.</p>
                    <p>General <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>
                        </hi> said they should consider both possibilities.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the Soviet side had two drafts. He had looked them over the
                        previous evening. The sides should consider the question of how to unite
                        them. They should record everything that had been achieved between them. It
                        would be a rather big document, and that was a little worrisome to him. But,
                        he suggested, let the experts start on it. He asked <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName> to hand over the Soviet draft.
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> asked <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName> if the thick paper he had was the draft; <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName>
                        </hi> laughingly said it was only a part, and pointed to his briefcase.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the document would have great significance. The people had wanted
                        a <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> agreement. It was important to
                        have a <pb facs="1026" n="989" xml:id="pg_989"/> substantial appeal or
                        address to the people on what had been achieved, to make up for the fact
                        that there would be no <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>
                        agreement.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> recalled that when he had met with the
                        General Secretary in Moscow they had reflected on how progress on the broad
                        range of issues was important; nuclear arms was part of it, but not
                            everything.<note n="2" xml:id="d149fn2">See <ref target="#d147">Document
                                147</ref>.</note> There was a certain desirability to having that
                        perspective. Perhaps the second document could be made part of the
                        first.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName>
                        </hi> noted that this would require a conceptual change in the nature of the
                        joint statement. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said the two ministers
                        had a trustworthy working group in these two individuals (<persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName>). They should struggle to come up with a good
                        document. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName>
                        </hi> said it would help to have a piece of paper from the Soviet side. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said they had one, even translated into English, for the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> to consider. It could not be finished in
                        Geneva, so the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> could send someone to
                        Moscow, or the Soviets could send someone to Washington, to continue and
                        complete it. He would like <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> to complete it. They were people who did not argue
                        much, but just did their work.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said the sides should aspire to settle
                        on the structure of the document while they were in Geneva. They should make
                        up their minds, and agree to as much language as possible. Some things, for
                        instance the historical recitation, could be pretty well settled. Others
                        they would work on up to and even during the summit. But they should try to
                        have most of it worked out.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary continued that he thought they should have a process underway
                        working the document or documents that week and in the few days before the
                        summit. He would be arriving in Helsinki the early morning of May 26, and
                        would be there three days. They could work there if <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> wanted to send someone, or we
                        could send people to Moscow. They should agree on the process by the next
                        day.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said he had the idea that <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> and he should meet as needed during the summit.
                        This would keep the process going and understood. For instance, on the first
                        day there would be an arrival ceremony and then a ceremony and private
                        meeting of the two leaders at the Kremlin. Perhaps the ministers and their
                        associates could meet during that time to see what the problems were. If
                        there were a place always available for that, in or outside the Kremlin,
                        that would facilitate things if there were problems to be solved.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he agreed they should discuss whether there should be one
                        document or two documents. Looking at the matter the <pb facs="1027" n="990" xml:id="pg_990"/> day before, he had thought it would be a good thing if
                        there could be one document, with a general assessment and various sections,
                        for instance political-military, including strategic offensive arms and the
                            <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. In it they could record
                        things that had been done by the time of the summit. In Moscow they had
                        discussed whether chemical weapons should be treated in a separate document
                        or as part of a joint document. There should be a section on conventional
                        arms. There should be a big section on humanitarian issues. There should be
                        a big section on regional matters, where there were also steps, progress to
                        report. In the bilateral area they would be signing a very substantial
                        number of agreements, and could mention those signed over the previous two
                        years. If all these things were put together it would be very impressive.
                        But there could also be two documents. They could discuss this matter. The
                        day before he had been inclined toward one document. But those were just
                        thoughts.</p>
                    <p>But, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> went on, he thought
                        the main work should be done before the summit. The sides knew the assets,
                        the capital that had been accumulated. They could add to it during the
                        meetings of their leaders. Or the leaders could decide there should be no
                        document. But it would be useful to be prepared. He thought their people
                        should get together to put the documentation in as final a form as possible.
                        He would be giving the Secretary the Soviet suggestions on how they should
                        work.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said they would want to record what
                        they had done in the past, but in a way that looked to the future. They
                        should say what they had done since 1985, but they should also say this was
                        an ongoing process. They should say that they had the people in place to do
                        it, that they had not achieved everything, but that it was a good process.
                        On strategic offensive weapons and defense and space, they should record
                        results, but also give a sense of forward motion, so that people would have
                        confidence that no matter how difficult the remaining issues the process
                        would come to a conclusion.</p>
                    <p>A small question had arisen among the delegations, the Secretary continued,
                        concerning the recess. He gathered they had agreed to break on May 24 so
                        that our delegation could join the President in Helsinki. We had thought it
                        would be a good idea to reconvene in mid- or early July. We could understand
                        it would be desirable to reconvene at the end of June, since it was closer
                        than July. The ministers could perhaps privately pick a date to announce at
                        the summit, that would carry with it the notion of continuity.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary asked if General <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>
                        or Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> had anything
                        to add. They did not.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> suggested they return to these issues after the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side had looked at the Soviet ideas. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said that would be fine.</p>
                    <pb facs="1028" n="991" xml:id="pg_991"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said that, concerning matters related to the President’s visit, if the
                        Secretary agreed, it would be a good idea to provide for parallel meetings
                        of leaders and ministers and other members of the delegations. This had
                        happened at Geneva, at Reykjavik and at Washington. The Soviet side would
                        supply working areas. How many would be needed would depend on the
                        situation.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side had suggested simultaneous
                        interpretation, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> went
                        on. The Soviet side agreed that interpretation should be simultaneous
                        throughout the duration of the summit. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi>
                        said that would be good, subject of course to the proviso that either side
                        could ask interpreters to slow down and repeat, or switch back to
                        consecutive interpretation. That was a convention they had followed. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> agreed.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said they should also
                        think of some breakdown of questions to be discussed in each session. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he agreed. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said they could prepare a preliminary agenda.</p>
                    <p>—On May 29 there would be a private meeting of the General Secretary and the
                        President at 3:30 p.m.</p>
                    <p>—On May 30 he thought it would be useful to have a plenary session in the
                        same room where the Secretary met with the General Secretary, the Catherine
                        Hall. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> asked how big it would be. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said they were thinking of eight or nine on a side. For instance, on
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side, in addition to the President,
                        there could be the Secretary, <persName corresp="#p_CFC_1">Carlucci</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BHH_1">Baker</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MJF_1">Matlock</persName>, and the Soviet side would have a similar group.
                        This would be about the same as in Washington. On the Soviet side there
                        would be Defense Minister <persName corresp="#p_YD_1">Yazov</persName>
                        rather than <persName corresp="#p_AS_1">Akhromeyev</persName>, since
                            <persName corresp="#p_CFC_1">Carlucci</persName> would be there, but it
                        would be basically the same group. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said
                        he liked <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s idea. He
                        observed that as soon as the group got larger, it was hard to cut it below a
                        roomful, and the quality of the meeting declined. He did not know why, but
                        that was what happened. So he thought <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s idea was about right, with an interpreter and
                        a notetaker. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said there should be two notetakers on each side.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said that as to the
                        meetings of the leaders, they would decide whom they wanted with them. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said his sense was that this would
                        depend somewhat on the questions under discussion, but to the extent
                        possible <persName corresp="#p_BA_2">Bessmertnykh</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> should be there. They would have
                        to knead the material together, and should be present to hear what was
                        said.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said he saw the May 30 session as a general assessment of the status
                        and prospects of the Soviet-American relationship, and perhaps some
                        discussion of human rights. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he
                        thought that at the initial one-on-one session the President would want to
                        give an assessment of the outlook in a broad way. He commented that the <pb facs="1029" n="992" xml:id="pg_992"/> President also liked to say what
                        he had to say on human rights to the General Secretary, and not to the whole
                        world. So he expected the President would talk about human rights in the
                        one-on-one session. That did not mean other issues could not also be
                        discussed, or that the sides did not have a way of talking about human
                        rights in a systematic and orderly way. But he expected the topic would be
                        discussed there.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> reaffirmed that he expected the first meeting would touch on general
                        Soviet-American relations, and probably the second afternoon meeting on May
                        30 would deal with strategic offensive arms and the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty. Of course they could structure it otherwise. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said that sounded sensible to him.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> continued that on May 31 at 10:00 a.m. there would be a one-on-one in
                        the General Secretary’s office. He thought that should be a conceptual
                        meeting, on the future of Soviet-American relations, on continuity of
                        policies. The General Secretary would want to touch on perestroika, as well
                        as the future of our relations. But it would be a rather short meeting. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> joked that he had thought from the
                        subject matter that it would last a couple of days. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> joked back that it could last a month. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Secretary</hi> said he thought it would be useful to have some
                        continuity with the first day’s meeting. But he also understood it would be
                        a relatively short meeting, and then the two leaders would walk to the
                        general meeting. This would allow the President to see the inside of the
                        Kremlin building.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said that although they had been suggesting a broad approach, the
                        General Secretary might wish to pick up some specific topics. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said that with regard to new thinking,
                        the President had noticed the General Secretary’s comments on religion. He
                        had given this a lot of attention; it fascinated him. He would be interested
                        to hear on an expanded basis what the General Secretary had in mind. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the two leaders could pick and discuss what they wanted. They
                        could put religion on the list. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said
                        that would not be necessary; he had merely wanted to note that the President
                        would be interested. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the General Secretary would be ready. Then at the conclusion of
                        their private talk they would walk across the Kremlin.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that at the
                        session to which they would walk they could concentrate on regional and
                        bilateral issues.</p>
                    <p>Then at the concluding session in Catherine Hall on May 31, <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued, with the full
                        official delegations present, they could consider the concluding
                        documentation and consider the results of the summit.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said that in considering the question
                        of signing bilateral documents, or the <gloss target="#t_PNET_1">PNET</gloss> document—that level of material—we had been asking whether
                        this should be done as a prelude to the <pb facs="1030" n="993" xml:id="pg_993"/> leaders’ signature of the main documentation, or in
                        some other setting not involving the two leaders. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the Soviets had been envisaging signing of all the documents in
                        the presence of the two leaders. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> asked
                        if that meant the subsidiary <hi rend="italic">and</hi> the principal
                        documents. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said they saw signing of four or six documents by ministers or even
                        other officials, and then signing of the substantial document by the two
                        leaders.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said that would be a perfectly good way
                        to do it. We had no special objection to it. But perhaps the sides should
                        look at another option. There would be a huge press corps in Moscow. They
                        would be looking for something to report. One possible variant would be that
                        at the conclusion of the plenary session on regional and bilateral issues,
                        those agreements could be signed. That would be something to report, which
                        would be an advantage. Then the final major signing would not be diluted by
                        separate little ceremonies. He asked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> to comment.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName>
                        </hi> said we had given some thought to the image and perception of a new
                        kind of dialogue. It was a fair evaluation to say that it was not the
                        dialogue typical of previous leaders. The previous dialogue had been
                        associated with a grand final day, with many ministers and officials present
                        and signing. This suggested that agreements had been reached only because of
                        the summit, in haste, and had no value of their own. We had been careful
                        over the past two years not to let ceremony govern the preparation of our
                        summits. If we were successful in negotiating one, this format would also
                        take something away from the single document to be signed by the leaders. If
                        it were not possible to get a major document, there would be advantage to
                        gathering the various bilateral documents together for signature, but
                        assuming we would be successful we had been thinking it could be signed with
                        ministers present, and the others could be signed at other points during the
                        visit. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> interjected again the
                        possibility of doing this after the session on bilateral matters. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName>
                        </hi> said that was included in the idea of doing it earlier in the visit.
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said that of course that was not
                        the only option.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said they should think about these issues. The Soviet practice was to
                        have one signing ceremony. He did not think it would take too much time. It
                        usually took place in the Vladimir Hall, with 150–200 persons present, drawn
                        on the Soviet side from the leadership, from among intellectuals, from
                        Supreme Soviet deputies.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he assumed each leader would make
                        a statement, as had happened in the past. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> agreed; they would be short statements, of three to five minutes each.
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> recalled the successful experience
                        of Geneva in 1985, after they had persuaded the leaders to make them; short,
                        pithy statements were good.</p>
                    <pb facs="1031" n="994" xml:id="pg_994"/>
                    <p>Returning to the question of separating ceremonies, <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said it would have to be carefully weighed. It was one thing to sign
                        in the presence of the leaders; that was impressive. If they did not
                        participate, signing would be harder to understand. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Secretary</hi> said he wished merely to think aloud. At the conclusion
                        of the session on bilateral issues, the parties could go to another room,
                        and the appropriate people could sign documents in the presence of the
                        leaders, and each leader could make a brief statement. The statements could
                        register that our relationship is a broad one, and say they wished to call
                        attention that day to the bilateral elements, and the next day to the
                        relationship across the board. He was just trying out ideas, to see if it
                        would be desirable to break up the signing into something readily
                        reportable, after the arrival statements and before the end.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>
                        </hi> noted this would also be close to the model used in Washington.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> recalled that in Washington there had
                        been the arrival, which was an event; then the <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> signature and the statements; then the toasts, which there
                        would also be in Moscow; and then the finale. We were looking for a
                        counterpart to the <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> signing. He urged
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> to think about it.
                            <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the Soviet side would. He had no objection in principle to the
                        separation. But he had doubts about the two leaders’ attendance at a first
                        signing. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he saw some advantages to
                        their spending three minutes there. As <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had said, it would lend greater weight to the
                        event, and they could say things on the meeting and the relationship that
                        the press could report. It was something to think over. It was not something
                        the President was pushing for, but he had thought about it.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said they would think about it. The important thing was to have
                        something to sign. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said there would be
                        things to sign.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said the Soviets would officially announce the visit May 22. They
                        would provide the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> side with the text of
                        the official announcement. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> asked if
                        this were routinely done. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said it was Soviet practice to announce visits in a formal way. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> asked if this were to inform the
                        people. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said they all knew, but since some visits were not announced
                        officially, this one had to be too; otherwise people would not understand.
                        There would be an official photo published in the press on the day of
                        arrival, with a biographic note on the President. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Secretary</hi> said it was courteous of <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> to tell us about it. We did not have an
                        official press; only an inundation of press interest. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> noted that 5000 foreign journalists had already registered in
                        Moscow.</p>
                    <pb facs="1032" n="995" xml:id="pg_995"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said he had mentioned <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName> to his friend Katharine
                            <persName corresp="#p_GW_1">Graham</persName>,<note n="3" xml:id="d149fn3">Reference is to Katharine <persName corresp="#p_GW_1">Graham</persName>, editor of the <hi rend="italic">Washington
                                Post</hi>.</note> who wished to interview the General Secretary and
                        would also like to interview <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>. She had told him she would be spending some
                        time in Leningrad; he had told her she should go to Tbilisi. She and her
                        friend Meg Greenfield, editorial page editor of the <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, would be going. <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEA_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                        </hi> said it was on the program.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> suggested a break (at 4:30 p.m.).</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>