<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States High Commissioner for Germany ( (McCloy) ) to the Secretary
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-18T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-18T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-18T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-18T08:00:00-05:00" n="120"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d120">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762A.0221/10–1851: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="#p_MJJ1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d120fn1">Repeated, to Paris, London, and Frankfurt.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bonn</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-18T14:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 18, 1951—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>245. Chairman opened today’s<note n="2" xml:id="d120fn2">October 17.</note>
                    meeting between High Commissioners and Chancellor by explaining the status of
                    Canadian contingent attached to Brit occupation forces. Ger newspapers had
                    apparently published conflicting reports concerning basis for presence of these
                    forces in Ger and <persName corresp="#p_KSIA1">Kirkpatrick</persName> made it
                    clear that contingents of other allied nations participating in Eur defense will
                    be stationed as auxiliary components of occupation forces in Ger.</p>
                <p>Chancellor then gave brief report Bundestag session of Oct 16 and expressed
                    gratitude for allied note which had been generally welcomed throughout Ger.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d120fn3">Regarding the High Commissioners’ letter of October
                        15 concerning all-German elections, see the editorial note, <ref
                            target="#pg_1801">p. 1801</ref>.</note> He attached great significance
                    to speech of <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> spokesman, Lutkens, [which?]
                    chancellor interprets as endeavoring to lay basis for understanding with Sov
                    Union thus constituting reversal of previous <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss>
                    policy. Chancellor said speech undoubtedly had <persName corresp="#p_SK1"
                        >Schumacher</persName>’s approval but that other members of <gloss
                        target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> had disassociated themselves from such
                    expression of policy. He considers this indication that large section of <gloss
                        target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> would refuse to fol <persName corresp="#p_SK1"
                        >Schumacher</persName> if he endeavored for his own pol purposes to seek
                    closer ties with east (other reports of Lutkens speech in Bundestag indicate he
                    Stressed primarily the note that unification of Ger was incompatible with
                    western integration and that latter should not be permitted interfere with
                    unification). He also suggested that Chancellor was too much concerned <pb
                        facs="0276" n="1554" xml:id="pg_1554"/> over attaining eventual sovereignty
                    in matters of little importance vis-à-vis Allies. While he ignored the main
                    issue of unification, combination of these things produced strong disavowal of
                    entire speech by <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> leaders and led to
                    something of an uproar. My impression is that incident has less significance of
                        <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> defection than Chancellor indicates.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SK1">Schumacher</persName> will line them up on his
                    main policy in the end.</p>
                <p>He stated that general situation and these developments all pointed to necessity
                    of getting ahead immed with our agreements. We agreed but we all have feeling
                    that <persName corresp="#p_HW1">Hallstein</persName> is endeavoring slow things
                    up on lower levels as result of his rather timid approach on all points where he
                    feels any opposition would develop.</p>
                <p>Chairman then turned to question of maintenance of Allied rights in Ger as re
                    Berlin and Ger as a whole and stationing of troops. A long discussion ensued at
                    conclusion of which Chancellor agreed to recognize retention by Allies of their
                    existing rights both in respect of Berlin and as regards Ger as a whole, but
                    declared he could not accept Allied requirement that troops should be stationed
                    here and their security protected on basis of existing rights as such would mean
                    continuation of theory of occupation. He insisted that this would be in
                    contradiction to Allied assurances that in future troops would not be occupation
                    troops but troops stationed here for defense of Eur, including Ger. He renewed
                    his assurances, however, that all of the rights needed as regards stationing of
                    troops, their reinforcement, and protection of their security would be granted
                    by Fed Govt in new treaty: He insisted he would give by contract more than they
                    now had by right.</p>
                <p>I explained (1) present situation requires that we must have, irrespective of
                    will of Bundestag, full authority to reinforce and deal with all questions
                    affecting security of our troops; this might mean taking measures in Ger
                    politically difficult to secure by contract. (2) Our rights with respect to
                    these troops must be unequivocal vis-à-vis Sov Union, which would not
                    necessarily be case if derived from treaty with <gloss target="#t_FedRep1"
                        >FedRep</gloss>. (3) Contractual agreements with <gloss target="#t_FedRep1"
                        >FedRep</gloss> were contemplated which would establish certain rights and
                    privileges to be enjoyed by our forces and provide for fulfillment of their
                    requirements. Such contracts, together with general reservation of our right to
                    station them in Ger and protect their security would in my opinion seem to meet
                    the preoccupations of Chancellor and still enable us to preserve our fundamental
                    rights.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FPA1">Francois Poncet</persName> agreed and added that he
                    thought the presence of Allied troops here based solely on treaty with <gloss
                        target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> would be more provocative to Sov Union
                    than if they remain in Ger by virtue of rights which have already been
                    recognized. Chancellor dismissed idea that treaty governing presence of our
                    troops would be more provocative <pb facs="0277" n="1555" xml:id="pg_1555"/>
                    than maintenance of occupation rights, pointing out that if Sov Union were
                    looking for provocation such would be provided by large Ger forces in <gloss
                        target="#t_EDF1">EDF</gloss> and substantial reinforcements of Allied troops
                    in Ger.</p>
                <p>Chancellor then argued at considerable length that concept of Eur army was
                    inconsistent with retention of rights derived from occupation status.
                    Furthermore, since annexation had been precluded the purposes of assuming
                    supreme authority under declaration of June 1945 had been to restore order in
                    Ger and establish democratic institutions. These objectives had been fulfilled
                    and the need to retain troops was consequently no longer based on internal
                    situation in Ger but upon new situation created by threat from east. Declaration
                    of June 1945 could not however be utilized for this different purpose. He
                    reiterated that all of Allied requirements could be covered and covered
                    generously by treaty with Fed Govt which would take into account new
                    situation.</p>
                <p>Prior to adjournment we emphasized importance of getting ahead with supplementary
                    conventions since gen agreement alone would be inadequate and unacceptable.
                    Chancellor agreed to issue instructions so that work on other conventions could
                    proceed without delay on Ger side.</p>
                <p>It is apparent that question of our right to station troops here on basis of
                    supreme authority is becoming most difficult point in our negots and there does
                    not seem to be an immediate possibility of inducing Chancellor to abandon his
                    insistence upon treaty status for our troops despite fact it may be politically
                    difficult for him to include in treaty all safeguards we should require. I shall
                    discuss this matter further with UK and Fr <gloss target="#t_HICOM1"
                        >HICOM</gloss>S and hope to send further recommendations shortly.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
