<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-02-04T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-02-04T12:00:00-05:00" n="210" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d210">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">662A.62B/2–451: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_MJJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d210fn1">Repeated to London, Paris, Moscow,
                                Rome and Brussels.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfurt</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-02-04T18:00:00+01:00">February
                                    4, 1951—6 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>6447. <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss>. Comparison of <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>’s May 26 and October 9 letters to
                                <persName corresp="#p_C1">Chuikov</persName> (first of which
                            enclosed <gloss target="#t_FM1">FM</gloss>’s May 7, 1950 statement on
                            conditions of German unity), Bundestag’s resolutions of March 22 and
                            September 14, and Chancellor’s statement of January 15, on one hand,
                            with <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> letter of November
                            30 (Frankfort’s 5922, January 18) and Volkskammer resolution of January
                            30 (Berlin’s 995, January 31, sent Frankfort 1120), on other, discloses
                            these points of difference:<note n="2" xml:id="d210fn2">For
                                documentation on the letters of May 26 and October 9, the
                                resolutions of March 22 and September 14, and Grotewhol’s letter of
                                November 30, see <ref target="frus1950v04#pg_590">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 590</ref> ff. For the text of
                                the Foreign Ministers statement of May 7, see <ref target="frus1950v03#pg_1086">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 1086</ref>. For telegram 5922 see <ref target="#pg_1749">p. 1749</ref>; telegram 995, is not printed,
                                but see editorial note, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>1. Basic differences in approach re establishment of forum for
                                all-German talks, role of free elections, creation of provisional
                                government, and pattern of control of four powers over new
                                all-German government. Soviet/<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                                offer made in <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> letter
                                and renewed in Volkskammer resolution is that equal number <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> representatives convene in <hi rend="italic">ad
                                    hoc</hi> group to discuss ways and means of establishing an
                                all-German constituent council (<gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss>), that <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss> be
                                empowered to discuss “all questions which must be solved for
                                securing peace and for reunification Germany” and “prepare for
                                establishment of all-German sovereign, democratic and peace-loving
                                provisional government”, and that <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss> (apparently after establishment of provisional
                                government) submit proposals (apparently <pb facs="0475" n="1753" xml:id="pg_1753"/> intended to mean decisions reached by <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss>) to four powers “for joint
                                approval”. <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> letter
                                indicates <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss> might also discuss
                                elections to an undefined type of national assembly (thus borrowing
                                terminology from previous Bundestag resolutions and <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>’s letters to <persName corresp="#p_C1">Chuikov</persName>), but role latter left vague
                                and Volkskammer resolution seems to make it clear that negotiation
                                terms German unity and elections would be performed exclusively by
                                    <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss>. This position negates
                                    Allied-<gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> positions that
                                new all-German government should emerge as result new all-German
                                constitution (negotiated in freely-elected national constituent
                                assembly (<gloss target="#t_NCA1">NCA</gloss>) and ratified by
                                people) and that all-German government should be subject to four
                                power supervision pending conclusion of peace treaty. Whereas
                                    Allied-<gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> position
                                envisages free elections to <gloss target="#t_NCA1">NCA</gloss> as
                                first step (Bonn’s 497 and 498, February 1, sent Frankfort 581,
                                    582<note n="3" xml:id="d210fn3">Neither printed; they reported
                                    West German reactions to the Volkskammer resolution and outlined
                                    the tentative plans for responding to it. (762.00/2–151 and
                                    762A.5/2–151)</note>), Soviet/<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> position, though not specific on subject, would
                                almost certainly make them final step. Whereas Allied-<gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> position is that four powers
                                should preside over emergence new all-German government,
                                    Soviet/<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>, for propaganda and
                                other purposes, stand for proposition that four powers should
                                surrender competence over German affairs to Germans, that time has
                                come for Germans to take matters in hand, to become “fifth power”,
                                and to emerge as “fifth voice” which would more or less dictate
                                terms of peace settlement, withdrawal of occupation forces, and
                                course of Germany’s future. Four powers would not, therefore,
                                control negotiations or decisions within <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss>’s
                                “proposals” would merely be referred to four powers for “joint
                                approval.”</p>
                            <p>2. This formula, should we accept it and permit all-German talks on
                                terms proposed, would in fact hand control of Germany’s future over
                                to Soviets, rather than keep it within control of four powers and
                                freely elected representatives of German people, as contemplated in
                                    Allied-<gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> formula
                                proposed in <persName corresp="#p_C1">Chuikov</persName> letters.
                                Although the Soviet/<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> position is
                                that the four powers would not intervene in <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss> negotiations, we can of course assume that <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> dels would hew strictly to Soviet
                                line; under such circumstances and assuming Germans could agree,
                                only a provisional government suitable to Soviet purposes could
                                emerge. This provisional government would then submit proposals to
                                four powers, which could only be approved or disapproved by joint
                                (i.e. unanimous) decisions. The provisional government itself could
                                ostensibly remain in being unless it were dissolved by joint
                                decision of four powers. Thus, if a provisional government suitable
                                to Soviet purposes should emerge, Kremlin could under this formula
                                keep government in being while employing other tactics to dislodge
                                and isolate Allies from provisional government and German people. We
                                think full appreciation these hazards, plus loss of momentum in West
                                which could be caused by prolonged (even if fruitless) negotiations
                                in <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss>, forms basis <persName corresp="#p_SK1">Schumacher</persName>-<gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> position that, preliminary to any all-German talks,
                                four powers must arrange conditions under which free elections to
                                    <gloss target="#t_NCA1">NCA</gloss> can be held (Bonn’s 497,
                                February 1, sent Frankfort 581).</p>
                            <p>3. Allied-<gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> position has been
                                that certain enumerated conditions should be accepted, either in
                                fact or principle, as necessary <pb facs="0476" n="1754" xml:id="pg_1754"/> prerequisites to talks pointing toward
                                all-German elections and unity. Soviet/<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> meets this position only half way: None of
                                previously specified Allied-<gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> conditions are accepted, but <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> states that its delegation will be
                                authorized to “negotiate”, “discuss”, or “deal with” these
                                conditions in all-German talks with <gloss target="#t_AGCC1">AGCC</gloss>. Refusal to date of Soviets or <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> to accept Allied-<gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> conditions undoubtedly
                                accounts in large part for <persName corresp="#p_SK1">Schumacher</persName>-<gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss>
                                position that four powers, rather than Germans, must reach agreement
                                on these conditions and provide framework within which free
                                elections can be held and all-German talks proceed with some hope
                                success.</p>
                            <p>4. Volkskammer resolution purports to meet all three basic conditions
                                interposed by Chancellor in January 15 statement on <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> letter (Bonn’s 459,
                                January 13, sent Frankfort 518<note n="4" xml:id="d210fn4">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1747">p.
                                        1747</ref>.</note>), i.e., guarantees in Soviet Zone of
                                civil and personal liberties commensurate with state founded on law
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Rechtstaat</hi>), guarantees of political
                                freedom, and objections to “law for protection peace” and
                                Volkspolizei Bereitschaften. On latter points, <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> states willingness to discuss
                                extension applicability peace law to <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> and to negotiate parity between Volkspolizei and
                                    <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> police–para-military
                                formations or, if necessary to unity, to reduce Volkspolizei on
                                mutually agreed parity basis. Since intent Chancellor’s statement
                                was to suggest abrogation of law (as example employment “legal”
                                machinery to suppress civil and political freedoms), <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> meets these conditions only
                                obliquely (attitude re Bereitschaften, though it can be interpreted
                                as conciliatory, does not meet May 7 <gloss target="#t_FM1">FM</gloss> condition of “prohibition throughout Germany of
                                political secret police and police formations constituting military
                                force.”</p>
                            <p>5. Volkskammer resolution does not directly respond to four
                                conditions which <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>
                                quoted from Bundestag resolution of March 22, i.e., freedom of
                                action of political parties and guarantees of noninterference
                                political activities by four powers; guarantees by four powers
                                against reprisals following elections; freedom of press; and freedom
                                of movement, together with abolition interzonal passes.
                                Nevertheless, liberal interpretation of preamble and points 1 and 8
                                of resolution might be stretched to signify <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> willingness to discuss and negotiate on all
                                conditions interposed by Chancellor as requisite to German
                                unity.</p>
                            <p>6. With specific reference to May 7 conditions of <gloss target="#t_FM1">FM</gloss> and letters of <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>S to <persName corresp="#p_C1">Chuikov</persName>, Volkskammer resolution silent on (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) international control of free elections,
                                    (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) role of four powers, (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) independence of judiciary, (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) prohibition secret police and military
                                formations, (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) quadripartite agreement on
                                cessation reparations from current production and <gloss target="#t_PLI1">PLI</gloss> and (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)
                                surrender and disposal industrial enterprises acquired after May 8,
                                1945 by foreign powers unless confirmed by quadripartite approval
                                and subjected to German law.</p>
                            <p>7. Volkskammer resolution, additionally, advances all of Praha
                                    declaration<note n="5" xml:id="d210fn5">For the text of the
                                    Praha Declaration of the Foreign Ministers of the Soviet Union,
                                    Czechoslovakia, Poland, Hungary, Bulgaria, Romania, the “German
                                    Democratic Republic”, and the Albanian Minister at Moscow,
                                    October 21, 1950, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on German
                                        Unity</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 158–161 or
                                        <persName>Ruhm von Oppen</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Documents on Germany</hi>, pp. 522–527.</note> proposals
                                and thus interjects Soviet/<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                                conditions that (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) principle of German
                                demilitarization be reaffirmed and enforced, <pb facs="0477" n="1755" xml:id="pg_1755"/> (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) armament
                                industries be prohibited, and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) German
                                industrial potential be made available to Far East and to USSR and
                                its European orbit.</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>On balance, we think it dangerous and illusory to attribute sincere
                            conciliatory spirit to Volkskammer resolution or to interpret it as
                            making real concessions to Western position. Although it can be
                            interpreted as representing position more liberal than Praha
                            declaration, it sacrifices none of principles of Praha and binds <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> only to talk and to talk only in forum
                            established on parity basis as between <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>