<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-02-04T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-02-04T12:00:00-05:00" n="211" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d211">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">662A.62B/2–451: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_MJJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d211fn1">Repeated to London, Paris, Moscow,
                                Rome, and Brussels.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfurt</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-02-04T18:00:00+01:00">February
                                    4, 1951—6 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>6448. <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss>. Supplementing preceding
                            numbered telegram,<note n="2" xml:id="d211fn2">Telegram 6447, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> believe these are governing
                            points in assessing impact and purposes of <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> initiative and bearing thereof on Soviet
                            intentions: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> initiative
                                    should not be regarded solely as propaganda move and is not so
                                    considered by wide segment West German opinion. Though
                                    propaganda values are extensive in view fact that occupation
                                    reaching point of sharply diminishing returns, Volkskammer
                                    resolution follow-up and its conciliatory, non-polemic tone
                                    denotes initiative as genuine diplomatic move. It could not be
                                    dismissed and must be answered on merits if German people are to
                                    be convinced of unwisdom of all-German talks. Chancellor’s
                                    initial riposte (Frankfort’s 5922, January 18<note n="3" xml:id="d211fn3">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1749">p.
                                            1749</ref>.</note>) did not accomplish this purpose and
                                    thus left initiative With <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>,
                                    which Volkskammer resolution carries forward in singularly
                                    adroit document designed to exploit neutralist sentiment and
                                    restiveness of Germans to take things in their own hands.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> should not, because of
                                    impact on German people, make completely negative reply. Since
                                    one purpose of Volkskammer follow up is to appeal to people and
                                    to isolate Chancellor and coalition government, slamming of door
                                    would play into Soviet/<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                                    hands.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Allies, on other hand, could not permit all-German talks of
                                    scope proposed for variety reasons, most obvious, of which are
                                    that such talks would permit Germans (rather than four powers)
                                    to negotiate a complex of subjects affecting European and German
                                    future, and would delay and possibly disrupt completely present
                                        Allied-<gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>
                                    negotiations on contractual relationship<note n="4" xml:id="d211fn4">For documentation on the negotiations for a
                                        contractual relationship with the Federal Republic, see <ref target="#pg_1446">pp. 1446</ref> ff.</note> and
                                    rearmament. <pb facs="0478" n="1756" xml:id="pg_1756"/>
                                    Preceding tel has also noted how acceptance of present
                                        Soviet/<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> terms would in
                                    effect hand control of Germany’s future to Soviets. Soviets
                                    framed their strategy to accomplish these objectives. Our
                                    difficulty is that to deny these objectives we must stand on
                                    policy of no all-German talks. For purposes prestige, however,
                                    neither <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> nor Allies can
                                    admit this.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Seems obvious enough, therefore, that Allies cannot continue
                                    treat <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> initiative
                                    solely as German affair: it is mixed Allied-German affair and
                                    should be so treated.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>We are fortunate in having virtually unanimous government arid
                                    Bundestag disinclination to talk with <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and in having rapport between <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SK1">Schumacher</persName> on subject. This is
                                    remarkable circumstance in that unanimity in Bonn by no means
                                    reflected in constituencies or press. It should permit us to
                                    form common front with Bonn in effort place matter in proper
                                    perspective and influence German opinion away from <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> blandishments.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> initiative
                                    integral part of strategy pursued since “legitimation” <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> in October to neutralize
                                    Germany under demilitarization pact, disrupt unity of Allies,
                                    impede <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> defense plans,
                                    isolate Allied position in West Germany by fostering neutralist,
                                    defeatist and nationalistic sentiments among German people, and
                                    shift onus of any forthcoming armaments race to West. Praha
                                    declaration, Soviet bid for <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                                    arid Soviet “peace offensive”<note n="5" xml:id="d211fn5">For
                                        documentation on the Soviet peace offensive, see <ref target="frus1951v04p1">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>
                                        </ref>.</note> are additional components of this strategy.
                                    Tactics employed have been skillful in alternating club and
                                    carrot, of which <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName>
                                    address of January 30 to Volkskammer (Berlin’s 999, February 1,
                                    sent Frankfort 1127<note n="6" xml:id="d211fn6">Not printed, but
                                        see editorial note, <ref target="#pg_1751">p.
                                        1751</ref>.</note>) and subsequent Volkskammer resolution
                                    (Berlin’s 995, January 31, sent Frankfort 1120<note n="6" xml:id="d211fn7">Not printed, but see editorial note <ref target="#pg_1751">p. 1751</ref>.</note>) good example:
                                    thus <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> said “civil
                                    war and new world war” would be end result if all-German talks
                                    not undertaken, while Volkskammer rubber-stamped document was
                                    framed to impress West Germans with spirit reasonableness and
                                    willingness to make concessions to <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> position.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> initiative seems
                                    clearly to constitute pre-<gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                                    move to strengthen Soviet politico-psychological posture in West
                                    Germany and to probe our position and German opinion. It may
                                    thus furnish preview of Soviet tactics and reveal perspectives
                                    of extent Soviets may be willing to go to obtain demilitarized
                                    Germany within <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>, or, if
                                        <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> not held, by future
                                    overtures to Allies. Though Volkskammer resolution itself does
                                    not justify conclusion that Soviets will relinquish East
                                    Germany, disband Bereitschaften, or submit to free elections in
                                    order obtain demilitarized Germany, it may furnish clue that
                                    Soviet tactics in <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> will be to
                                    offer such concessions with expectation and knowledge that they
                                    will be refused by West if <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi>
                                    is demilitarization of Germany. In view fact that Praha
                                    declaration not popularly received in West Germany, somewhat
                                    more liberal position advanced in Volkskammer resolution marks
                                    disposition on part Soviets to make concessions to West German
                                    opinion in effort attain strategic aim of demilitarized West
                                    Germany. Hence, our own <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                                    strategy should be framed with full appreciation of flexibility
                                    of Soviet tactics in this field.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>To date, <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName>
                                    initiative only hints at Soviet time-table and does not show
                                    Soviet hand on possible intentions to precipitate general <pb facs="0479" n="1757" xml:id="pg_1757"/> war. Threats of
                                    civil or world war form part of psychological intimidation
                                    campaign and would probably be less vocal if West were stronger.
                                    In any event, they fit into standard Communist outbursts against
                                    any threat of encirclement. Most significant conclusion to be
                                    drawn is that Soviets have not yet exhausted their efforts to
                                    win control of Germany through political-propaganda cold war
                                    tactics and negotiation, and that present tactics of pressure,
                                    intimidation and negotiation will probably run their course
                                    before force is employed.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>With regard to Soviet intentions and <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> strategy, big and unanswered question emerging
                                    from <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> initiative
                                    is whether concessions to Western position in Volkskammer
                                    resolution are tactical only, whether they represent disposition
                                    to agree to West’s conditions, and whether, if so, they
                                    represent price Soviets would be willing pay to obtain
                                    demilitarized Germany. Since resolution pledges <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> only to discuss Western
                                    conditions, and in view tactical advantages to Soviets of
                                    spinning-out any all-German talks at this time, resolution
                                    offers very little, if any encouragement that Soviets or <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> ready do more at this time than
                                    offer concessions in bad faith and in contexts where they can
                                    safely assume we must refuse to accept concessions
                                    offered.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>With regard to <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>-Allied riposte
                            to <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName> initiative, (Bonn’s
                            502, February 2, sent Frankfort 588<note n="7" xml:id="d211fn8">Not
                                printed; it reported that <persName corresp="#p_WH1">Wehner</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TF1">Thedieck</persName> believed that the West German response to
                                the Volkskammer resolution “should be so phrased and handled that
                                    <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>, Volkskammer, <persName corresp="#p_GO1">Grotewohl</persName>, <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss> and Soviets would not be in position to address any
                                more unification proposals to <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> organs or officials without associating
                                themselves with Bundestag resolution.” (762A.5/2–251)</note>)
                            outlines <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> course of action with
                            which British, French, and ourselves are in general agreement. It has
                            also been tentatively agreed on <gloss target="#t_PolAd1">PolAd</gloss>’s level, subject to governmental approval, that it would
                            be desirable for <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> to follow-up
                            Bundestag resolution with tripartite statement which would endorse
                                <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> position and carry
                            initiative forward to Soviets in some fashion. Will advise further as
                            our thoughts crystallize.<note n="8" xml:id="d211fn9">In telegram 6512
                                on February 6, <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName>
                                reported that Liaison Bonn did not believe it would be advisable for
                                the United States “to adopt a policy of urging Federal Government or
                                Bundestag officials to consider conditional acceptance of talks”,
                                since the “Soviets masterminding <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                                delegation behind the scenes can be counted on to find a way to
                                prolong such talks for weeks in order to stall Fed Rep rearmament.,
                                (662A.62B/2–651)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>