<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Director of the Berlin Element of HICOG ( (Page) ) to the Office of the
                    United States High Commissioner for Germany, at Frankfurt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d298</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">298</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-02-20T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-02-20T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-02-20T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-02-20T07:00:00-05:00" n="298"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762A. 00/2–2051: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Director of the Berlin Element of <gloss
                            target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>
                    </hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PEJ1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Page</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Office of the <gloss type="to">United
                            States High Commissioner for Germany</gloss>, at Frankfurt</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d298fn1">Repeated to Washington and Bonn. The source text is
                        the copy in Department of State files.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-02-20T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >February 20, 1951—1 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1196. West-licensed press February 18 carried report that “leading
                    representatives of West German <gloss target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss>” intend
                    propose that Bundestag hold special session in Berlin “to take position before
                    entire German people” on contemplated Four Power Conference and reunification
                        Germany.<note n="2" xml:id="d298fn2">For documentation on U.S. policy on the
                        question of Germany unity, see <ref target="#pg_1747">pp. 1747</ref>
                        ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Informal inquiries of city officials indicate they have no specific information
                    re such meeting beyond fact that one had been proposed some time ago to be held
                    in June (which would probably be too late now for pre-<gloss target="#t_CFM1"
                        >CFM</gloss> meeting). It was discussed in Senate meeting February 19 but as
                    far as can be ascertained, discussion dealt mostly with technical aspects such
                    as transport from west and lodging here of Bundestag members and available
                    assembly hall. Titania Palast suggested as one possibility for latter for which,
                    they said, US permission would be needed just as US help would probably be
                    needed to provide air transport. <persName corresp="#p_SO1">Suhr</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_KVA1">Kielinger</persName> will be in Bonn this week
                    and will presumably discuss matter there. Berlin officials obviously keen to
                    have Bundestag meet here but as yet, at least not overly excited by it.</p>
                <p>French <gloss target="#t_PolAd1">PolAd</gloss> told us he was opposed any
                    Bundestag meeting Berlin as it would constitute recognition of Berlin as twelfth
                    land. British <gloss target="#t_PolAd1">PolAd</gloss> said preliminary British
                    reaction Berlin also against such meeting here, not because of twelfth land but
                    because it might well cause difficulties which could not be outweighed by
                    benefits. We inclined to agree with latter view to extent we believe latter is
                    probability that meeting could not be held without Allied, especially US, help
                    in providing transport and perhaps meeting hall).</p>
                <p>We urge, and British and French <gloss target="#t_PolAd1">PolAd</gloss>s are of
                    same opinion, that if <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss>s are going to ban
                    meeting here, it be done before proposal is formally introduced in Bundestag so
                    that ban gets least possible <pb facs="0619" n="1897" xml:id="pg_1897"/>
                    publicity. West press February 20 carries further items re meeting speculating
                    re choice of assembly hall and saying Bundestag <gloss target="#t_CDU1"
                        >CDU</gloss> faction advocate holding meeting here “in near future”.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d298fn3">On February 22 the Bundestag Committee on all-German
                        Affairs decided in favor of holding a Bundestag session in Berlin, but on
                        February 27, <persName corresp="#p_WH1">Herbert Wehner</persName>, its
                        chairman, told the Liaison Division in Bonn that <persName corresp="#p_AK1"
                            >Adenauer</persName> had approved the “idea of such meeting until <gloss
                            target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> only on condition that situation of ‘great
                        psychological necessity’ vis-à-vis Soviet Zone population arises.” (Telegram
                        570 from Bonn, February 27, G62A.62B/2–2751) On the following day <gloss
                            target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss> discussed the question and decided that
                        the disadvantages of holding a Bundestag session in Berlin outweighed the
                        advantages because of adamant French opposition, difficulties of transport,
                        and the dangers inherent in spotlighting Berlin during a Foreign Ministers
                        meeting. The Department of State concurred in <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1"
                            >PEPCO</gloss>’s views but expressed its belief that the “idea of
                        session may have considerable merit from propaganda standpoint and it might
                        at some later time be useful [to] carry it out.” (Telegrams 7073 from
                        Frankfurt, February 28, and 6085 to Frankfurt, March 8, 662A.62B/2–2851 and
                        3–851)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PEJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Page</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
