<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-05-28T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-28T13:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">800.4614/5–2851: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_MJJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d346fn1">Repeated to Paris, London, Moscow,
                                Rome, Vienna, Bern, Brussels, The Hague, Copenhagen, Oslo, and
                                Stockholm.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfurt</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-05-28T19:00:00+01:00">May 28,
                                    1951—7 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>9603. <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss>. Re <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 7882, May 24, rptd Berlin
                                379,<note n="2" xml:id="d346fn2">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> and Dept’s plan prepare
                            coordinated global campaign to counteract and discredit Communist World
                            Youth Festival (<gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss>) scheduled Berlin in
                            August, <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss> cables (<gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 9506, May 24<note n="3" xml:id="d346fn3">Not printed; it reported, <hi rend="italic">inter
                                    alia</hi>, that <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss> had
                                approved, at its 49th meeting on May 22, the background paper
                                transmitted earlier.</note>) and minutes have furnished general
                            lines of our thinking together with suggestions for main points to
                            emphasize in circular message instructing missions to expose event
                                (<gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 9508, May 24). Specific
                            info requested follows: <list>
                                <item>1. Status Berlin plans: Berlin counter measures to <gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss> not finalized by May 25 due to
                                    slowness of Gers in presenting coordinated program and unsolved
                                    question of extent financial support available from Senat,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Kaiser</persName> Min and
                                    commandants’ fund. However, in May 10 and subsequent meetings
                                    definite agreement achieved between Aug comite, Senat, and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Kaiser</persName> Min that basis
                                    of program will be subsidized hospitality activities by West
                                    Berlin youth organizations for estimated 200,000 <gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss> participants expected to visit
                                    Western sectors. West Berlin movie theater owners have offered
                                    free entrance to <gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss>
                                    participants during Aug period. Special guide to West Berlin
                                    will be printed. Centers will be established where East Eur
                                        <gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss> participants can come
                                    and converse in their own languages. Special cultural and
                                    sporting events are contemplated. EBP exhibit now touring
                                    Western Ger scheduled Berlin July 20–Sept 6. Europa Zug on
                                    display Berlin July 22–Aug 12. Endeavoring procure <gloss target="#t_UNESCO1">UNESCO</gloss> human rights exhibit.
                                    Financial limitations prevent any further activities at present
                                    although Bundesjugendring may sponsor radio lottery whose
                                    proceeds could be used expand program. Whole question of
                                    financing expected influx permanent refugees during <gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss> will be negotiated between
                                    Senat and <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>. In addition
                                    to Europa Zug and <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName> Plan exhibit at <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> pavillion, <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>
                                    will definitely: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Feature free films
                                    in <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">George C. Marshall</persName>
                                    House, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) distribute 200,000 copies each
                                    of satirical pamphlet (<hi rend="italic">Wir Brauchen Keinen
                                            <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>
                                        Plan</hi>) contrasting econ conditions in Sov Zone and
                                        <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> and of <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> pamphlet on Berlin (<hi rend="italic">Berlin Baut Auf</hi>) and, tentatively (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) sponsor television exhibit (see
                                    below).</item>
                                <item>2. Measures to restrict participation. In addition to exposure
                                    campaign <gloss target="#t_PolCom1">PolCom</gloss> now has
                                    tripartite position on travel restrictions which <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> will consider May 31 in
                                    conjunction with Berlin commandants. Measures include (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) harassment and slowdown of interzonal
                                    passes and of issuance of visas to transit <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) obtaining assurances from <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> that no extra transport
                                    facilities will be made available in connection with <gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_PolCom1">PolCom</gloss> agreed that before any extraordinary
                                    measures recommended to, or taken by, Western Govts, <pb facs="0728" n="2006" xml:id="pg_2006"/> to refuse passports
                                    to natls who desire attend festival, consideration should be
                                    given to effectiveness such measures via-á-vis propaganda
                                    ammunition such policy of refusal would supply to Commies. UK
                                    Element, pending <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> meeting
                                    May 31, has reserved position on whether <gloss target="#t_CTB1">CTB</gloss> should issue directives on passport and visa
                                    issuance. UK Element, in general, less inclined to support
                                    restrictive travel measures than US and French Elements and
                                    believes principal emphasis should be on discouragement of
                                    attendance through exposure. Definite tripartite policy should
                                    be formulated as of May 31.<note n="4" xml:id="d346fn4">At their
                                        meeting in Berlin on May 31 the Allied High Commissioners
                                        took note of the measures planned to counter the festival,
                                        and <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> stated
                                        that it would be well to take precautions against disorderly
                                        demonstrations. The Liaison Division at Bonn reported this
                                        in telegram 900, June 1 (762A.00/6–151).</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>3. <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> productivity fair.
                                    Productivity fair, as originally envisaged, now more or less
                                    abandoned. <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss> planning television exhibit
                                    in lieu thereof but this will not be finalized until project
                                    submitted to and approved by <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName>. Will keep Dept informed
                                    developments.</item>
                                <item>4. Radio Free Europe activity. <gloss target="#t_RFE1">RFE</gloss> contacted and in principle willing send
                                    prominent iron curtain refugees to Berlin for Aug period and to
                                    do some broadcasting on <gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss>.
                                        <gloss target="#t_RFE1">RFE</gloss> awaiting complete Ger
                                    program before making commitments.</item>
                                <item>5. European Union plebiscite. Mytel 9506 May 24 reported
                                    latest <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss> thinking and
                                    instructions to US member Aug comite on this subject. Continue
                                    feel plebiscite is excellent counter-attraction and perhaps
                                    financially justifiable if utilized as counter-attraction. Dept
                                    aware, however, that UK objects to plebiscite during <gloss target="#t_WYF1">WYF</gloss>, that both UK and French
                                    dragging heels on use of commandants’ fund to finance project,
                                    and that sincerity of Ger attitude still unprobed. Proposal will
                                    probably reluctantly be dropped unless Berlin Senat vigorously
                                    and promptly supports it, which seems unlikely due to split
                                    opinion in Senat heretofore.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>