<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Office of the United States High
                    Commissioner for Germany, at Frankfurt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-02-27T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-02-27T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-02-27T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-02-27T17:00:00-05:00" n="4"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d4">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">033.62A11/2–1751: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Office of the <gloss type="to">United States High Commissioner for
                            Germany</gloss>, at Frankfurt</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d4fn1">This telegram was drafted by
                            <persName>Jones</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_WLA1"
                            >Wiesner</persName>; cleared by the Economic Cooperation Administration,
                        the Bureau of German Affairs and the Offices of German Political and German
                        Economic Affairs.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-02-27T17:00:00-05:00"
                            >February 27, 1951—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5856. Re <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 6833, Feb 17 and <gloss
                        target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 5803, Feb 23.<note n="2" xml:id="d4fn2"
                        >Telegram 6833, not printed, but see footnote 2, <hi rend="italic"
                            >supra</hi>.</note> In informal joint conversations Dept and <gloss
                        target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> officials with Bundestag members question of
                    whether Ger ready now before end of occupation to declare its adherence Western
                    defense effort raised and relation this issue to justification next year Ger aid
                    before Congress was discussed. It was pointed out to Bundestag members that aid
                    program next year will be based to substantial extent on defense effort of
                        <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>’s and that affirmative evidence Ger
                    willingness to participate wld create more positive atmosphere for obtaining
                    appropriations for Ger aid. <persName corresp="#p_BHV1">Brentano</persName> was
                    queried separately on whether Gers had considered possibility of Bundestag
                    resolution offering Ger econ contribution to Western defense prior to mil
                    participation, which might furnish desired evidence Ger willingness to
                    participate. He thought idea had merit and stated wld raise with other members.
                    In later conversation with <persName corresp="#p_BHV1">Brentano</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_OE1">Ollenhauer</persName> they presented idea of
                    resolution expressing desire to contribute to Western defense and asking Govt
                    after agreement with <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> to bring in two
                    separate budget items of occupation costs, one of which wld be labeled defense
                    covering which voluntary appropriation cld be made. <persName corresp="#p_OE1"
                        >Ollenhauer</persName> pointed out that it wld be helpful to base such
                    resolution upon some outstanding event and he suggested that termination state
                    of war by US and other Allies might be appropriate event. We pointed out that
                    while this timing not out of question what wld be most helpful wld be simple
                    declaration Ger intent on their own initiative.</p>
                <p>It was also pointed out to Gers that Allied auths including armed forces wld not
                    agree to subj defense or other portions occupation cost budget to Bundestag
                    examination and debate. <persName corresp="#p_BHV1">Brentano</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_OE1">Ollenhauer</persName>
                    <pb facs="0049" n="1327" xml:id="pg_1327"/> brushed this aside by saying it wld
                    be Govt (not Bundestag) responsibility to negot with Allies on size of defense
                    and occupation cost components of budget.</p>
                <p>Pressed on whether Ger willing to make total contribution in same relative amt as
                    other Eur countries, <persName corresp="#p_BHV1">Brentano</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_OE1">Ollenhauer</persName> were agreed on this as
                    matter of principle but were evasive as to amt. Both called attn to special Ger
                    burdens arising out of last war, e.g. refugees and war damages. <persName
                        corresp="#p_OE1">Ollenhauer</persName> argued that Ger expenditures for
                    groups of population adversely affected by last war shld be considered
                    contribution on polit side to cold war since they made these groups less
                    vulnerable to Commie infiltration. To this we replied a Bundestag resolution
                    expressing Ger’s wish to assume fair share of Eur defense burden wld be most
                    useful if clear and unequivocal. It wld be more than useless however, if
                    accompanied by statements of why Ger’s contribution shld be small.</p>
                <p>We have impression that Bundestag members may carry above ideas further and that
                    some type of resolution cld result. It is difficult to conceive <gloss
                        target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> supporting resolution volunteering Ger defense
                    contribution in any form under present conditions of Ger inequality. It seems
                    questionable whether clear resolution volunteering econ contribution wld be
                    passed by coalition parties, although we believe all six delegates understand
                    problem of Congressional presentation of Ger aid program. However, they may
                    propose only split of budget item.</p>
                <p>Separation of budget item into occupation costs and defense contribution might
                    well lead to increasing attempt to negot latter as well as division of
                    categories of expenditures between the two. This perhaps is inevitable in long
                    run. Separation cld lead to increasing Ger criticism of occupation cost item
                    which wld then stand naked and alone. However, Ger offer to make contribution
                    wld probably have helpful overall effect even though separation of items were
                    troublesome.</p>
                <p>We impressed upon Bundestag members that any views expressed by Dept and <gloss
                        target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> officials shld not be considered as official
                    and that if any proposal is made on our side it will be through <gloss
                        target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WJE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
