<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Decision of the Allied High Commission for Germany</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d61</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">61</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recUInGVZ0Y3MeuOS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="61"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d61">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762A.00/3–150</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Decision of the Allied High Commission for Germany</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bonn</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-06">March 6,
                            1951</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Decision</hi> No. 10</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">program for the revision of occupation controls</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In implementation of the decisions taken by the Foreign Ministers of the United
                    States, the United Kingdom and France at their New York Meeting on 18 September,
                    1950, the Council of the Allied High Commission, having this day promulgated the
                    “First Instrument of Revision of the Occupation Statute”,<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d61fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> has decided to adopt the following
                    program for further relaxation of controls under the Occupation Statute: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The powers reserved by paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) relating
                            to deconcentration will be exercised only to ensure completion of Allied
                            programs relating to the steel, coal and motion picture industries, I.G.
                            Farben and the Grossbanken and actions which, as of December 31, 1950,
                            were called for under laws adopted by the Allied High Commission or have
                            been initiated through legal process taken under existing laws. Upon
                            completion of such programs and actions these powers will be
                            relinquished.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The powers reserved by paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                                    relating to decartelization will be relinquished upon the
                                    enactment by the Federal Republic of legislation satisfactory to
                                    the Occupation Authorities, including provisions to prevent new
                                    concentrations of economic power.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The powers reserved by paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)
                                    relating to displaced persons and the admission of refugees will
                                    be relinquished as soon as commitments and other action
                                    satisfactory to the Occupation Authorities have been taken by
                                    the Federal Government with respect to the admission, care, and
                                    protection of displaced persons and refugees, including
                                    safeguarding their civil rights, assuring the continued and
                                    effective operation of International and Allied agencies
                                    established for their care and resettlement, and compensating
                                    victims of Nazi persecution.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The powers reserved by paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)
                                    relating to respect for the Basic Law and the Land Constitutions
                                    will be relinquished as soon as the Federal Republic has
                                    established a judicial authority deemed by the Occupation
                                    Authorities to be capable of effectively upholding the civil
                                    rights of the individual as defined in the Basic Law.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Occupation Authorities will retain the powers necessary to ensure
                            that the Federal Government carries out commitments undertaken and
                            legislation enacted pursuant to paragraph 2 above and that the essential
                            features of such legislation are maintained.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The Council of the Allied High Commission will issue further
                            instruments of revision of the Occupation Statute from time to time as
                            the conditions prescribed by this Decision for the relinquishment of
                            powers are fulfilled.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>This Decision shall become effective on March 7, 1951.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
