<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Office of the United States High Commissioner
                    for Germany, at Frankfurt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-04-14T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-04-14T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recP1TxBSuFrpDZ2S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Interim agreement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-14T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-14T15:00:00-05:00" n="85"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762A.0221/4–1451: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Office of the United States High Commissioner for
                            Germany</gloss>, at Frankfurt</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d85fn1">Repeated to Paris and London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-14T15:00:00-05:00"
                            >April 14, 1951—3 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6943. For <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> from <persName
                        corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName>. You will have seen <gloss
                        target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 6922, Apr 13,<note n="2" xml:id="d85fn2"
                        >Not printed.</note> dealing with procedural problem in handling the
                    contractual arrangements papers. This message concerns the problem of substance
                    and timing in achieving the contemplated new political relationship between the
                    Occupying Powers and the Fed Rep.</p>
                <p>You will recall my ltr of Mar 19<note n="3" xml:id="d85fn3">Not found in
                        Department of State files.</note> which advanced for your consideration the
                    thesis of a much fuller “declaration of intentions” than had previously been
                    contemplated. Your response by ltr and cable to this tentative suggestion has
                    greatly encouraged us here.</p>
                <p>On reading the majority of the preliminary position papers<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d85fn4">None of the <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>
                        preliminary position papers, which <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1"
                            >McCloy</persName> had begun transmitting in March, is printed.</note>
                    we have received here on the subjects for contractual arrangements, am concerned
                    that even the proposed fuller declaration of intentions may not be sufficient or
                    the best way to handle the situation. I wld like to advance for your
                    consideration therefore the idea of concluding an interim agreement on
                    principles with the Fed Rep. Such an interim agreement wld presumably cover the
                    main principles which will be found to underlie the many points you are now
                    working on.</p>
                <p>Among other things, we have in mind the possibility that a quite liberal peace
                    treaty with Japan<note n="5" xml:id="d85fn5">For documentation on the Treaty of
                        Peace with Japan, see <ref target="frus1951v06p1#pg_777">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, Part 1, pp. 777</ref> ff.</note> will
                    materialize before long and that any arrangement with the Ger govt which is
                    markedly less favorable will not have the desired political effect in Ger.
                    (Documents on Japan being sent separately.) We fully appreciate that there are a
                    number of compelling reasons why we cannot at this time conclude an arrangement
                    with the Fed Rep which wld in fact be a final peace settlement. Not the least of
                    these reasons is the apparent fact that the Gers <pb facs="0196" n="1474"
                        xml:id="pg_1474"/> themselves do not want this now since it wld formally
                    recognize the permanent division of Germany. What we do want, however, is an
                    arrangement which will resolve all problems except those which cld only be
                    solved by a final peace settlement with a unified Germany. This wld seem
                    consistent with the language of the Brussels decisions, notwithstanding that the
                    obscure language of Brussels does not necessarily point to such a sweeping
                    settlement as we suggest.</p>
                <p>We are impressed by the industry and careful thought that has gone into
                    preparation of <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss> papers. Upon rapid
                    scrutiny of the recommendations first impression is that cumulatively they do
                    not sufficiently reflect the goal of eliminating Allied controls wherever
                    possible. As a whole they perhaps support too strongly the principle of
                    confirming controls in the form of contractual obligations by the Gers rather
                    than to completely eliminate the controls wherever possible. We recognize that
                    certain subjects must be covered by contractual agreements whereby the Gers
                    assume obligations and responsibilities. However, the commitments to be required
                    of the Germans in accordance with the <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>
                    recommendations seem numerous and complicated in nature. Their negotiation
                    tripartitely and with the Gers wld necessitate long discussions and by the time
                    they wld come into effect, their political value wld probably have been
                    seriously impaired (as in the case of the New York decisions). We hope the
                    number and complexity of the agreements can be kept to an absolute minimum
                    without relinquishing supreme authority entirely at this stage.</p>
                <p>If you consider the idea of an interim agreement on principles with the <gloss
                        target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> feasible, it might have certain
                    advantages over the procedure now contemplated. Securing tripartite and then Ger
                    agreement on the numerous and technical points covered in your papers will take
                    many months. During this period we will certainly at some stage find progress on
                    the whole approach being held up by a number of relatively unimportant technical
                    points, such as occurred in the implementation of the New York decisions. The
                    subjects for discussion during this protracted period are of such a nature that
                    German public opinion probably will not grasp the significance of the
                    contemplated package as a whole. The package, even when finally completed, will
                    probably not readily lend itself to simple public relations usage.</p>
                <p>Certain other considerations may have a bearing upon the wisest way of
                    proceeding. In the past, in order to finalize any tripartite agreement of
                    significance as regards Ger it has been necessary to hold a meeting of the three
                        <gloss target="#t_ForMin1">ForMin</gloss>s. However it is practically out of
                    the question to require personal discussion and approval by the Ministers of the
                    bulky and detailed package that will result from the consolidated papers on
                    contractual arrangements. You will recall the previous difficulties when the
                    Ministers had to act on the detailed <gloss target="#t_ISG1">ISG</gloss>
                    recommendations for the New York agreements.</p>
                <pb facs="0197" n="1475" xml:id="pg_1475"/>
                <p>The Ministers will probably be together for a considerable period of time this
                    summer at a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>. If we cld use this opportunity
                    to have them agree upon a relatively simple form of interim agreement which wld
                    contain the principles underlying the contractual arrangements, it may be that
                    the remainder of the work cld be completed with the Gers on a piece-meal basis
                    and without necessity for <gloss target="#t_ForMin1">ForMin</gloss>s
                    consideration.</p>
                <p>The question of Bundestag approval of new arrangements may be a factor in favor
                    of relatively simple agreement on principles. Believe we have always considered
                    next phase agreement shld have such approval yet submission entire contractual
                    package to Bundestag wld undoubtedly be time consuming, give unnecessary fodder
                    to opposition parties on details of such matters as civil affairs agreement,
                    etc., and perhaps give unnecessary rigidity to details which may require change
                    in future.</p>
                <p>These thoughts have brought us more and more to the conclusion that an agreed
                    statement of mutual objectives at a reasonably early date (perhaps after
                    Bundestag ratification of the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan
                        Treaty<note n="6" xml:id="d85fn6">For documentation on the negotiations
                        leading to the signing of the treaty setting up a European Coal and Steel
                        Community, April 18, at Paris, see <ref target="frus1951v04p1">volume <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>) wld be desirable in order to obtain the full political
                    benefit of the fundamental change in relations we contemplate. Have not as yet
                    attempted to draft terms of such an interim agreement. Such a document wld
                    emphasize the common nature (Allied and German) of the objectives and
                    obligations. It might not differ greatly from the terms of a full unilateral
                    declaration of intentions because in such a statement of policy it wld be
                    necessary to list certain things we wld expect the Gers to do on their part. The
                    agreed principles wld have to be treated as an indivisible whole and the manner
                    in which they wld come into effect wld have to be carefully worked out. A single
                    quadrilateral agreement wld seem most effective, but an alternative cld be to
                    negotiate in advance a declaration of intentions to which the Gers wld respond
                    with a statement of willingness of what they were prepared to do. Their answer
                    wld thus complete an agreement to which both sides wld be committed. We, of
                    course, wld expect a declaration of their willingness to join the defense effort
                    to be a major point. Such a document or documents shld put definitive seal of
                    recognition to <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>’s place in the Western
                    community.</p>
                <p>The timing of such an interim agreement in its relation to the <gloss
                        target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> and Paris <persName corresp="#p_PR3"
                        >Pleven</persName> Plan<note n="7" xml:id="d85fn7">For documentation on the
                        European Army talks (<persName corresp="#p_PR3">Pleven</persName> Plan) at
                        Paris, see <ref target="frus1951v03p1#pg_755">pp. 755</ref> ff.</note> talks
                    wld be difficult and probably wld be a major point with our Allies and perhaps
                    with the Gers. However, even if it became necessary to hold it up until after a
                        <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> it shld provide us with a procedure that
                    shld allow quick consummation subsequent to a <gloss target="#t_CFM1"
                        >CFM</gloss>.</p>
                <pb facs="0198" n="1476" xml:id="pg_1476"/>
                <p>Wld greatly appreciate your comments on the above and suggestions you might have
                    as to the form and content of such an agreement if you consider the idea has
                    merit. [<persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName>.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
