<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d127</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">127</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-07-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-07-05T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-07-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-07-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="127" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d127">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1227.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">London</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-07-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 5, 1866.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the reception of
                            despatches from the department numbered from 1782 to 1790 inclusive.</p>
                <p>The interregnum occasioned by the resignation of the ministry still
                            continues and business remains suspended. It is understood that Lord
                            Derby, having failed to obtain the co-operation of the section of the
                            liberal party which occationed the necessity of a change, has determined
                            upon attempting to go on with his own friends only. The list of his
                            cabinet circulating in the newspapers is believed to be substantially
                            correct. It is obvious that this structure can last merely by sufferance
                            of the majority in the commons, who stand without the pale. The course
                            of Mr. Lowe and his friends is plainly to attempt to control the
                            restoration of their own party under conditions rather than to identify
                            themselves with their opponents; but it will, I think, prove more
                            difficult to impose such conditions to bind the advanced section of the
                            liberal party, than to coalesce with the other side. Hence the question
                            may ultimately resolve itself into this: whether the conservatives will
                            consent 10 merge themselves under the lead of the moderate whigs, or the
                            latter will finally abandon their pretensions to the <pb facs="0220" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/> highest places and their ancient name.
                            Thus far it certainly does not seem as if the amount of ability and
                            character enlisted in this venturous enterprise could prove adequate to
                            the task undertaken.</p>
                <p>It is possible that by avoiding every topic of a disputed nature and
                            accelerating the day of adjournment of Parliament, this state of things
                            may last until the reassembly in February. Much will depend upon the
                            course of events on the continent. The Prussians now appear to be
                            gaining the ascendant in Germany so rapidly that the interposition of
                            the other great powers may be necessary to save Austria from sinking too
                            low for the general safety. In that event it will become difficult for
                            this country to adhere to its policy of isolation. Lord Stanley is
                            understood to be the type of that policy, and for this reason he has
                            been selected for his particular post. But it is well known that in this
                            he does not represent the true feeling of the party to which he
                            belongs.</p>
                <p>Just now there is a tendency in some quarters to draw closer to the
                            United States. It has been made visible in a few of the leading journals
                            that lean to the conservative side. I transmit to you a copy of the
                            Times of yesterday which contains a leader on the national anniversary
                            that may have significance in this connection.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
