<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to  to Mr.
                                Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d148</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">148</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-08-02T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004" lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-08-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="148" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d148">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">No.
                            1248.]</hi>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">London</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-08-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 2, 1866.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the reception of
                            despatches from the department numbered from 1801 to 1804, inclusive,
                            together with a printed copy of a bill to provide for the admission of
                            the British provinces into the Union.</p>
                <p>The Parliament is on the eve of prorogation. The ministers have fixed
                            Saturday for the customary dinner at Greenwich, and it is probable that
                            by, this day next week the annual dispersion from London of all official
                            persons will have taken place. It seems to be now definitively settled
                            that some sort of pacification will be made on the continent, which will
                            be a great relief to all parties, and not among the least to the new
                            ministry here, which may now perhaps hold over until next year.</p>
                <p>The cholera has at last broken out with great severity in the easterly
                            portion of this metropolis. As yet it does not appear to have reached
                            this section. But its progress up the line of the river is doubtless
                            only a question of time. Its simultaneous appearance at Liverpool, the
                            great port of the American trade will also render its spread over the
                            western continent likely. I do not know how far experience proves that
                            precautionary measures will avail to stop the progress of this
                            extraordinary malady, but in any event they will not be useless to
                            improve the health of the people in the long run.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hon. William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">, Washington,
                                    D.C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
