<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="2"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d2">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1093.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 22, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I now send you a copy of my note in reply to Lord
                    Russell’s of the 2d instant.</p>
                <p>The more I consider the subject, the more extraordinary seems to me the reckless
                    character of the assertion made by his lordship respecting the facts in the
                    Portuguese case. Having access only to the printed documents—though <pb
                        facs="0076" n="2" xml:id="pg_2"/> these seem to contain all the material
                    portions of the correspondence between the government and the Portuguese
                    representatives—I could not deal quite so confidently with him as, with your
                    ampler means of verification, you could have done. Yet I trust I have not
                    hazarded anything which the facts will not sustain. The attempt to shift the
                    responsibility for the feeble performance of an acknowledged duty by an appeal
                    to the precedent furnished by the United States, which is misrepresented to
                    sustain it, forms one of the memorable events of this extraordinary history. I
                    say nothing of the unusual course of discussing the transactions of a foreign
                    nation with an assumption of authority which breaks down at almost every
                    step.</p>
                <p>With this paper I gladly take leave of the controversy, so far as I may have
                    assumed the responsibility of any share in it. It has given me much satisfaction
                    to learn that, so far as you had been placed in possession of it at the time of
                    writing, you were disposed to view it with approbation.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hon. William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Earl
                            Clarendon</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-18">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 18, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        reception of a note from your predecessor, the Right Honorable Earl Russell,
                        dated the 2d instant, in reply to one which I addressed to him on the 18th
                        of September last, on certain important questions now under consideration
                        between her Majesty’s government and that which I have the honor to
                        represent. It is with the most profound regret that I am thus compelled to
                        open my relations with your lordship in a spirit of controversy. I can only
                        urge in extenuation of this proceeding, the great importance of the subject
                        under consideration, not simply as between two countries, but from their
                        wider bearing on the future relations of all the civilized nations on the
                        globe. Furthermore, I flatter myself that from the contraction necessarily
                        going on of the topics under treatment, we may before long arrive at some
                        sort of termination of a discussion already on my part, I fear, rather
                        tediously protracted. His lordship’s note appears to be substantially
                        confined to the consideration of two classes of facts, both of them bearing
                        upon the establishment of one general principle of the law of nations, to
                        wit: The obligation of a neutral country to belligerents to do everything
                        within its power to maintain its neutrality inviolate. This obligation his
                        lordship appears to maintain to be fully acquitted by the adoption of such
                        measures as the neutral itself may judge sufficient, without regard to any
                        remonstrances of the belligerents. And without entering into argument on the
                        abstract question, he contents himself with vouching the conduct of the
                        United States in past cases, in full justification of the course taken by
                        Great Britain, and complained of by the United States, in the progress of
                        the late war.</p>
                    <p>The chief of the cases relied upon by his lordship is that in regard to
                        certain claims for indemnity for injuries done to the commerce of Portugal
                        by vessels illegally fitted out in the United States. In order to define the
                        nature of the question thus raised, it would seem to be proper first to note
                        how far his lordship and I are agreed. After which it may be made more
                        clearly to appear wherein we are so unfortunate as to differ. By consenting
                        to cite the language and the action of the United States government in the
                        Portuguese case so freely as his lordship does, as a precedent to justify
                        the later course of her Majesty’s government now drawn into question, it is
                        obvious that he must have given to them the high sanction of his
                        approbation. On my side I have already in a preceding note expressed it as
                        my opinion that the grounds taken in that case by my government were
                        impregnable.</p>
                    <p>It necessarily follows that on this point we are fully agreed. Where there is
                        no difference it is obviously superfluous to continue an argument. Here I
                        would beg permission to observe that in all the previous examination of this
                        topic, I have carefully abstained from the task of affirming that a neutral
                        power is absolutely responsible for the injurious consequences of any and
                        every violation of neutrality that may originate within its territorial
                        limits, without regard to the circumstances attending each case. The
                        proposition which I have affirmed, and still do continue to insist upon, is,
                        that a neutral is responsible for all injuries which may so ensue to a
                        friendly nation, when it fails to exercise all the means in its power for
                        prevention, and constitutes itself the sole judge of the extent to which it
                        will refuse to resort to <pb facs="0077" n="3" xml:id="pg_3"/> stronger ones
                        within its reach, when the old ones are proved by the injured party to have
                        been wholly inadequate to the emergency.</p>
                    <p>With the light shed by this explanation, I now propose very briefly to set
                        forth those points in the respective action of the United States towards
                        Portugal, and of Great Britain towards the United States, wherein they
                        appear to me to differ so essentially and radically as to make it impossible
                        to bring them within a reasonable parallel.</p>
                    <p>1. The United States did not recognize the insurgents in South America as
                        abelligerent, until the fact of the presence of their armed vessels was made
                        patent to them on the ocean. But Great Britain did erect the insurgents in
                        the United States into a belligerent before they showed a vessel on the sea,
                        before they organized an army on land, and before they had done a thing but
                        declare an intention to do what they never subsequently executed.</p>
                    <p>2. Upon the first notice given to the government of the United States that
                        the neutrality of their ports was violated by South American insurgents,
                        making outfits in connection with their own citizens, they immediately put
                        in force the provisions of the existing law. Prosecutions were instituted
                        against the foreign agents as well as citizens, and decrees of restitution
                        were obtained from the judicial tribunals in the cases of captured property.
                        In other words, nothing was left undone that energy could do to bring to
                        bear existing preventive legislation against these offenders.</p>
                    <p>One particular instance of the desire to perform their obligations is worthy
                        to be presented to your notice more particularly, inasmuch as it
                        incidentally explains as well the public sense of the extent of the
                        obligation of a neutral power in similar cases, as of the responsibility
                        entailed from an insufficient performance of it. It appears that some of the
                        insurgent emissaries, in conjunction with desperate adventurers Of the
                        United States, went to the extent of seizing and occupying two different
                        spots on the American coast, neither of them within the recognized
                        jurisdiction of the Union, nor yet within that of any responsible power.
                        Here they made bases from which to conduct their hostile operations against
                        the commerce of Spain and Portugal, very much in the manner but not nearly
                        with so much success as Liverpool in this kingdom, and the port of Nassau,
                        were made bases of operations against the commerce of the United States by
                        insurgent emissaries during the late war. These proceedings soon attracted
                        the attention of the President, who dwelt upon the necessity of adopting
                        prompt measures of prevention in his annual recommendations to Congress in
                        the year 1817. The matter was referred in course to the consideration of a
                        committee of the House of Representatives, which made a report recommending
                        that these establishments should be at once suppressed, by force if
                        necessary.</p>
                    <p>Among the reasons given for resorting to this summary proceeding are the
                        following, to which I ask a moment of your lordship’s attention:</p>
                    <p>“The immediate tendency of suffering such armaments in defiance of our laws
                        would have been to embroil the United States with all the nations whose
                        commerce with our country was suffering under these depredations, and, <hi
                            rend="italic">if not checked by all the means in the power of the
                            government</hi>, would have authorized Claims from the subjects of
                        foreign governments for indemnities at the expense of this nation, for
                        captures by our people in vessels fitted out in our ports, and, as could not
                        fail of being alleged, countenanced by the very neglect of the necessary
                        means of suppressing them.”</p>
                    <p>It would be difficult to express in more forcible language the principle
                        established by the law of nations than is done in these sentences. The
                        action recommended was, moreover, performed so promptly, that soon after the
                        President, in a special message, was enabled to announce that the piratical
                        establishments at Amelia island and at Galveston had been suppressed. The
                        paramount necessity had been thought to justify the exercise of power, even
                        over territory not within the national jurisdiction.</p>
                    <p>But when I turn my attention to the proceedings of her Majesty’s government
                        as they are noted in the dreary list of my representations and complaints
                        contained in the printed memorandum furnished to me, with his lordship’s
                        note of the 2d instant; when I perceive real justice to have been so seldom
                        done and so often defeated, however good the intentions may have been; when
                        I note the omissions of all reference to the endless remonstrances made by
                        myself against the establishment of a naval bureau in Liverpool, conducted
                        by insurgents, mentioned and particularized by name, because not a single
                        step was ever taken either to prevent their action or to punish them, I
                        cannot but be sensible of a difference in the preventive action of the two
                        countries in similar circumstances, which would ever forbid me from classing
                        them together in one connection for a single moment.</p>
                    <p>3. It is not, however, denied that in the one case, as in the other, several
                        cases of illegal outfits took place which the existing laws proved
                        inefficient to prevent or punish.</p>
                    <p>In that of the United States, the representation of the aggrieved power made
                        at once a direct appeal to the government, stating the cause of the
                        difficulty and soliciting a new movement, for the purpose of obtaining from
                        the requisite source stronger powers of prevention; to which that government
                        immediately responded by recognizing the justice of the complaint and at
                        once adopting the suggestion.</p>
                    <p>If her Majesty’s government has at any time in this struggle followed that
                        example, it has escaped my observation. I should be glad to be corrected
                        when I affirm that it has done the directly opposite thing.</p>
                    <p>Here I may be permitted for a moment to refer to a passage of his lordship’s
                        note, which <pb facs="0078" n="4" xml:id="pg_4"/> appears to have been
                        called out by a hypothetical description I ventured to give of the
                        consequences that might ensue to the world, if neutral nations constituted
                        themselves the sole judges of the degree in which they had done their duty
                        under a code of their own making.</p>
                    <p>To this phrase his lordship is pleased to retort as follows:</p>
                    <p>“Yet, as far as I can judge, your Secretaries of State always maintained that
                        the United States, as a neutral power, were the sole judges of the degree in
                        which it had done its duty under a code of its own making.”</p>
                    <p>To which I would beg permission to observe that his lordship can scarcely
                        presume me to maintain that in the literal sense my country does not make
                        its own code of laws.</p>
                    <p>What I did mean to do was to distinguish by this term a country which was
                        ready to accept suggestions from foreign powers for an improvement of a code
                        designed to give the protection they are entitled to by treaties, as well as
                        international law, from one which determined to abide by its own system,
                        without regard to external representations. By keeping in mind this
                        distinction in connection with the facts already stated of the action of my
                        government, it will then appear that his lordship is in error when he
                        declares “that our Secretaries of State (meaning those of the United States)
                        made themselves the sole judges of the degree in which the country had done
                        its duty under a code of their own making.” So far was this from being true
                        that they admitted that the country had not done its full duty, and they
                        proceeded to amend the code, at the suggestion of a foreign power that
                        claimed to be aggrieved “Hence it is that the code, was not of their own
                        making.”</p>
                    <p>If there be a shadow of doubt left on this point, I will proceed to disperse
                        it by the following extracts:</p>
                    <p>On the 20th of December, 1816, Mr. Correa de Serra addresses these words to
                        the Secretary of State:</p>
                    <p>“I apply, therefore, to this government in the present instance, not to raise
                        altercations or to require satisfaction which the Constitution of the United
                        States has not, perhaps, enabled them to give, but because I know that the
                        supreme executive of this nation, all-powerful when supported by law, is
                        constitutionally inactive when unsupported by it. What I solicit of him is
                        the proposition to Congress of such provisions by law as will prevent such
                        attempts for the future.”</p>
                    <p>To which application Mr. Monroe, then Secretary of State, replies as follows
                        on the 27th of December, 1816:</p>
                    <p>“I have communicated your letter to the President, and have now the honor to
                        transmit to you a copy of a message which he has addressed to Congress on
                        the subject, with a view to obtain such an extension by law of the executive
                        power as will be necessary to preserve the strict neutrality of the United
                        States in the existing war between Spain and the Spanish colonies, and
                        effectually to guard against the danger in regard to the vessels of your
                        sovereign, which you have anticipated.”</p>
                    <p>And on the 13th of March Mr. Rush, then Acting Secretary, writes to him as
                        follows:</p>
                    <p>“The act of Congress, passed on the 3d of this month, to preserve more
                        effectually the neutral relations of the United States, <hi rend="italic"
                            >being upon the subject brought under consideration in your letter to
                            this department of the 20th of December last</hi>, I have the honor, by
                        direction of the President, to transmit for your information the enclosed
                        copy of it.</p>
                    <p>“The President feels sure that your sovereign will perceive in the spirit and
                        scope of its provisions a distinguished proof of the desire which animates
                        this nation to maintain with his dominions and subjects the most harmonious
                        relations.”</p>
                    <p>But when I turn to the other side of the picture, and view the action which
                        her Majesty’s government has thought it proper to take in answer to similar
                        representations made by me on behalf of my government; when I observe that
                        the appeals to the existing law have been almost uniformly of a kind to
                        prove its utter inefficacy; and when, upon my making representations as to
                        the expediency of further legislation to enlarge the powers of the
                        government to an extent adequate to the emergency, I find that proposal
                        positively declined, it seems to me that here again the parallel sought to
                        be made utterly fails.</p>
                    <p>I would respectfully ask whether, in the correspondence just laid before your
                        lordship, there be any language similar to that which his lordship, in one
                        of the notes which he did me the honor to address to me, used to me:</p>
                    <p>“Surely we are not bound to go on making new laws <hi rend="italic">ad
                            infinitum,</hi> because new occasions arise.”</p>
                    <p>Here I would respectfully submit that if his lordship be right in his
                        assertion, that new laws <hi rend="italic">ad infinitum</hi> are not
                        required by new occasions, it is difficult to explain the reason for the
                        existence of so many legislative bodies and such multiplied statute books.
                        Surely the government which I represent would not have so repeatedly acceded
                        to the solicitations of her Majesty’s government, as it has done, to “make
                        new laws for new occasions,” under any other plea.</p>
                    <p>But I am in candor bound to observe that even in this doctrine there has been
                        during the late struggle a singular variation in the practice of her
                        Majesty’s government which I ask your lordship’s permission to point out. At
                        a very early date the exposed nature of the frontier bordering upon Canada
                        became so much a subject of anxiety to my government that I was instructed
                        to bring the matter to the attention of his lordship, with a view to the
                        establishment of more effective preventive measures on the Canadian side
                        than were thought to be then <pb facs="0079" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/> within
                        reach. To that end, in the early part of December, in 1863, in a
                        conversation which I had the honor to hold with his lordship, after
                        explaining the reasons of my government for the danger apprehended in this
                        quarter, I proceeded to propose the adoption of a form of law, on the part
                        of Canada, resembling that which had been enacted on our part in 1838, to
                        meet a similar emergency then happening there. It is true that for a
                        considerable period I had no reason to presume that this proposal had been
                        more favorably received than any other of the same kind I had been called to
                        make; but when, one year later, information was received of the extreme
                        peril into which Canada had been thrown by the violent enterprise executed
                        by some of the insurgents established in that province upon the peaceful
                        town of St. Albans, I then had the satisfaction of learning from his
                        lordship that the suggestion had been adopted so far as that her Majesty’s
                        government had recommended to the authorities of Canada to procure the
                        enactment of the suggested law. In this case, then, it is clear that the
                        imminent danger of a rupture between the two countries had brought on an
                        acknowledgment of the necessity of going on to “make a new law to meet a new
                        occasion.” But surely her Majesty’s government would not be willing to give
                        even a color to an inference that nothing but a necessity to avoid a war
                        would be a sufficient motive to induce it to recognize an obligation to make
                        a new law. If the reasons for the suggestion were equally valid in all
                        cases, I fail to perceive upon what principle the nature of the answer
                        should be made to depend upon the merely accidental pressure of the
                        circumstances attending the moment when it was made.</p>
                    <p>Without pressing this topic further, I would then beg to observe that in any
                        event, however the facts attending the Portuguese claim as now explained may
                        be viewed, one thing is indisputable, and that is that there is a wide
                        divergency in the nature of the two cases sought to be brought together.</p>
                    <p>It is plain that neither in the commencement nor in the proceedings under the
                        existing laws, nor yet in the mode of treating the suggestion of new
                        legislation, was there any resemblance whatever in the tone or the action of
                        the respective governments. Hence I am constrained to arrive at the
                        conclusion that, whatever may be thought of the conduct of the government of
                        the United States in its relations towards Portugal, there is no parallel to
                        it in that of Great Britain towards the United States, by which the latter
                        may be tested by way of justification. Considered as a precedent, for which
                        alone the case seems to have been quoted by his lordship, I must insist that
                        the evidence entirely fails to establish its authority.</p>
                    <p>On a general review of these marked differences, considered in the light of
                        the rule of international law laid down at the outset of this letter, it may
                        now be said that one government appears to have done all that it was
                        reasonably asked to do, and that it could do to preserve its neutrality,
                        whilst the other certainly could have done more, but deliberately refused,
                        and accepted the responsibility for that refusal.</p>
                    <p>Hence, I must respectfully submit that, before his lordship concludes to
                        adopt the language used by the United States in answer to Portugal, he
                        should be prepared with proof to show that he has likewise adopted the
                        action on which they based it.</p>
                    <p>I should here gladly close my portion of this long controversy, if it were
                        not that his lordship has, in his note to which I now have the honor to
                        reply, thought fit to open a new matter which I cannot decline to notice. It
                        has happened in the course of this extended discussion that he has, on more
                        than one occasion, deigned to give me the fruits of his examination of
                        various points of history in my own country. In the first instance his
                        lordship was pleased to apprise me that Spain had never received any
                        compensation for the claims of her citizens against the United States. By
                        the aid of a little light I think I succeeded in dispersing that illusion,
                        so that it has not been made to appear again. Again, his lordship was
                        pleased to inform me that the enlistment acts of the respective countries
                        were, in their main provisions, similar and co-extensive. Here I
                        respectfully pointed out to his attention the fact that certain important
                        provisions were contained in the one that were not to be found in the
                        other—provisions which we at least regarded as having proved, in practice,
                        the most efficient in the whole law.</p>
                    <p>His lordship, in the note to which l am now replying, has been kind enough to
                        take notice of this difference, and goes on to describe the nature of the
                        provisions he had overlooked. But it appears to be only for the purpose of
                        trying to convince me that, in my statement of their superior efficacy, I am
                        utterly wrong. Hence, the argument appears to follow somewhat after this
                        fashion:</p>
                    <p>His lordship having proved to his satisfaction that those provisions of the
                        law which her Majesty’s government did not adopt were as susceptible of
                        evasion as all the others which it did adopt, it must necessarily follow
                        that her Majesty’s government were fully justified in declining a proposal
                        to make any amendment whatever of its existing statute.</p>
                    <p>To which I would respectfully venture to reply, that even had the result
                        proved to be as supposed, yet the position of her Majesty’s government, if
                        it had consented to make the experiment, would have been, at least to my
                        eye, infinitely stronger than it is now. It might then have replied to all
                        complaints, as the United States replied to Portugal—that everything in its
                        power had been done, even to the extent desired by the complaining party.
                        Whereas, by a refusal to recognize the justice of the request, it appears to
                        have placed itself in the attitude of a party deliberately assuming the
                        responsibility of declining to use those powers legitimately within its
                        reach, wherewith to fulfil its most imperative obligations.</p>
                    <p>But I am constrained to go further, and affirm that I can by no means
                        subscribe to the <pb facs="0080" n="6" xml:id="pg_6"/> opinion which his
                        lordship is pleased to express as to the ineffective nature of the
                        provisions of the law to which he has referred. It is not without extreme
                        surprise that I find him use the precise language respecting it, which I beg
                        permission here to quote:</p>
                    <p>“Now I contend, first, that for ten years these provisions proved utterly
                        inefficacious to prevent the fitting out of privateers at Baltimore, as
                        shown by the fact that the complaints of the Portuguese ministers of
                        captures and plundering by American privateers were more frequent and
                        extended to a larger amount of property after 1818, than they had done from
                        1816 to 1818.”</p>
                    <p>It is difficult for me to describe the high degree of astonishment with which
                        I have read these lines.</p>
                    <p>In opposition to this grave affirmation of fact, which, I must beg leave to
                        observe, no attempt is made to sustain by any distinct evidence, I am driven
                        to take the liberty to affirm, on my own side, first, that there is not a
                        tittle of specification to show that the fitting out of privateers
                        continued, in any appreciable sense, for ten years after the year 1818; and
                        secondly, that no pretence of that kind is to be found in any of the
                        official remonstrances of the representatives of Portugal, to which I have
                        had access, with one single exception, which I propose presently to
                        notice.</p>
                    <p>In relation to the point of the efficiency of the law, I shall venture, in
                        opposition to his lordship’s reasoning as to what it might be, to confront
                        that which, in the mind of Mr. Correa de Serra, the person through whom all
                        the transactions passed during much the largest part of the period in
                        question, and who had every opportunity to be familiar with them, it really
                        was.</p>
                    <p>On the 4th of February. 1819, about two years after it had gone into
                        operation, he deliberately used the following language:</p>
                    <p>“This law, so honorable to the spirit of justice of the government that
                        enacted it, <hi rend="italic">has also been found in practice the most
                            useful of the laws existing on this subject.</hi> Unhappily, the
                        continuance and aggravations of the evil it was intended to remedy seem to
                        render it necessary that this law may still continue in force for some
                        time.</p>
                    <p>“I apply, therefore, to this government in order to obtain the continuance of
                        this law, <hi rend="italic">so necessary to the peaceful trade of the
                            subjects of my sovereign, and so honorable to the character of the
                            United States,</hi> perfectly confident that my request is according to
                        the just and friendly intentions of the chief magistrate and legislators of
                        the Union, and conducive to the consolidation of good harmony between my
                        sovereign and the United States.”</p>
                    <p>On the 4th of June, 1820, he again writes to the Secretary of State as
                        follows, thanking him for still more effective legislation:</p>
                    <p>“Permit me, sir, to profit of this occasion to offer my thanks to this
                        government for the law that prohibits the entrance of privateers in the most
                        important ports of the Union, and for the other that declares piracy the
                        landing, and committing outrages ashore in foreign lands. I acknowledge the
                        salutary influence of the Executive in obtaining these ameliorations.”</p>
                    <p>Notwithstanding the very great deference with which it is my desire, as well
                        as my habit, to bow to the judgment of his lordship, if I find myself so
                        unfortunate as to be constrained to express an humble opinion in this case
                        of conflicting authority, I cannot, in candor, disguise my conviction that
                        the correct view is most likely to be that of Mr. Correa de Serra.</p>
                    <p>But, however efficient this law may have been proved to be by Mr. Correa de
                        Serra, at so late a date as the 4th June, 1820, it is now gravely affirmed
                        that it so wholly lost its efficacy for the ten years following, that more
                        property was captured after 1818 than before, and the complaints of the
                        Portuguese ministers for these captures and plunderings were more frequent
                        than ever.</p>
                    <p>The natural corollary, should this statement be sustained, would be that,
                        assuming the exertions of the government to have continued the same, instead
                        of improving the efficacy of the old law, the additions of the new
                        provisions must have only made it more worthless than it was before—upon
                        which logic might doubtless be based a very good justification to her
                        Majesty’s government for declining to try further legislation
                        altogether.</p>
                    <p>But, unfortunately, the whole argument falls to the ground when its base
                        disappears. It is not denied that some outfits escaped from Baltimore after
                        the year 1818, but it is denied that the complaints made for captures after
                        that time bore any fair proportion to those made before. It never has been
                        pretended that any law could be made so perfect, or any vigilance could be
                        so complete, as to put an end to the efforts of profligate and desperate
                        men. The grave error into which his lordship has fallen appears to have
                        originated in an <hi rend="italic">ex parte</hi> letter written by a
                        minister from Portugal at Washington, thirty years after the date of the
                        events, in which letter and the caption of a list embracing the names of
                        vessels captured, he includes them vaguely within two distant dates, of 1816
                        and 1828. It is, however, remarkable, that in the letter itself containing
                        his own recapitulation of the facts, no date of a capture is given later
                        than 1820. By turning to the original representations made by his
                        predecessors, the same fact distinctly appears.</p>
                    <p>I have carefully examined these representations to trace the dates of the
                        claims embraced in that list, and find much the greater proportion included
                        within the period of residence of Mr. Correa de Serra, ending in that year.
                        So also of the gross amount of value assigned in 1850 as an indemnity for
                        all the damage done during the entire period, which is less than three
                        hundred thousand pounds; I find a great proportion embraced in an early and
                        more trustworthy representation made by the same person.</p>
                    <pb facs="0081" n="7" xml:id="pg_7"/>
                    <p>Such being the facts, I submit whether with such small support as can be
                        given by this wholly <hi rend="italic">ex parte</hi> and vague averment, his
                        lordship has not a little crossed the verge of international courtesy, by
                        venturing, without any personal experience whatever of American legislation,
                        and in the face of the statement of M. Correa de Serra, which he must have
                        read, to hazard an assertion, still more give rise to an impression like
                        that necessarily produced by the languge already quoted. Standing, as I do,
                        the defender of the law of my country, it is with regret that I am compelled
                        to protest against it, as wholly unsubstantiated by any facts adduced, and
                        in every essential particular incorrect.</p>
                    <p>Neither were those the only cases in which the efficacy of these provisions
                        of law has been fully testified. It is not a very long time since I had the
                        honor of calling the attention of her Majesty’s government to an instance of
                        the remarkable promptness with which action was had under them upon a
                        request made by the representative of her Majesty’s government at
                        Washington. When Mr. Crampton, on the 11th of October, 1855, directed the
                        attention of my government to the character of a vessel in New York, then
                        believed by him to be fitting out as a privateer, it was by virtue of the
                        authority vested in it by one of the sections of this law that she was
                        seized on the 19th of the same month, and taken possession of by the
                        officers of the law in such a manner as to prevent all possibility of
                        escape. It required but four days to prosecute the investigation before her
                        Majesty’s representative was led to declare his satisfaction with the result
                        to which it had reached, and desired the process to be stopped. When I
                        compare the celerity of this effective proceeding with the feeble nature of
                        the process that ended in the escape of the Alabama, in defiance of the
                        British authority—whilst I give due credit to her Majesty’s government for
                        good intentions, it seems difficult to assent to the view which his lordship
                        has been pleased to take of the slight difference in the inefficacy of the
                        legislation of the respective nations. In any event, I cannot but think
                        their future harmony would have been much more certainly secured by a
                        consent to try the experiment in season, than by an endeavor, after great
                        injury has been done, to prove that it might not under circumstances have
                        been averted.</p>
                    <p>But it would appear superfluous to pursue this investigation further, in view
                        of the fact that, whether these provisions of the American law were or were
                        not effective, it never was any part of my instructions to urge their
                        adoption upon her Majesty’s government. I was instructed only to suggest the
                        expediency of having recourse to such additional measures as it might think
                        proper to choose, to the end of making the laws of Great Britain more
                        effective. And it was in that form only that her Majesty’s government
                        decided to decline the proposal. The decision was not against the adoption
                        of the law of the United States; it was against doing anything at all.</p>
                    <p>Neither in presenting the argument, which I have been called to do in the
                        course of my duty here, can I for a moment permit an implication that my
                        government has either “made a demand which aims at the diminution of British
                        freedom, or which assumes, without warrant from any previously recognized
                        authority or practice, the existence of an extent of obligation on the part
                        of neutrals towards belligerents, going beyond any which the government of a
                        free country could have power, though acting with entire good faith,
                        punctually to fulfil.”</p>
                    <p>I feel very sure that my country is quite as jealous of the preservation of
                        the true principles of freedom as Great Britain is, or ever has been; and
                        further, I fully believe that neither government would consent to give the
                        term that latitude which would encourage the power of doing wrong with
                        perfect impunity.</p>
                    <p>The suggestion which his lordship has been pleased to make towards the close
                        of his note of improvements in the statutes of both nations, to the end that
                        greater security may be given to the respective nations against those who
                        endeavor to evade its laws—though it appears to me to be in substance little
                        more than it has been the object of my government from the outset of the war
                        to obtain—is yet one which I cannot but receive with great respect, and
                        which I shall transmit to my government with pleasure. If the reasons for it
                        are sound now, I am at a loss to perceive why they did not avail during a
                        period when my country could have felt the benefit of them. I trust I need
                        not repeat how much pain it has given me heretofore to witness the evil
                        consequences that ensue from the alienation of sentiment that has grown out
                        of this struggle between people of the same race, and how cheerfully I
                        welcome every appearance of a desire to bring them back to harmony. Yet,
                        with regard to the proposition immediately before me, I cannot forbear to
                        observe that it is predicated upon an assumption that the legislation of the
                        two countries is now equally inefficacious, which I cannot entertain for a
                        moment. On the contrary, the necessity for some action in future seems to me
                        to be imperative, because that legislation, as it now stands, is not
                        coextensive.</p>
                    <p>For it is hardly possible for me to imagine that the people of the United
                        States, after the experience they have had of injuries from the imperfection
                        of British legislation, and a refusal to amend it, would be ready cheerfully
                        to respond to another appeal like that made in 1855, by her Majesty’s
                        representative, to the more stringent and effective protection extended by
                        their own. The great preservative of harmony between nations is the full
                        recognition of reciprocity in their obligations. So long as the heavy list
                        of depredations upon American commerce, consequent upon the issue of a
                        succession of hostile cruisers, built, fitted out, armed, manned, and
                        navigated from British ports, with perfect impunity, continues to weigh <pb
                            facs="0082" n="8" xml:id="pg_8"/> upon their minds, it would he the
                        height of assurance in me to hold out any encouragement to the acceptance of
                        proposals, the practical consequence of which might be to place Great
                        Britain in precisely the same degree of security in dangerous emergencies
                        which she herself, when applied to, had deliberately refused to accord to
                        them.</p>
                    <p>In regard to the parting words in his lordship’s note, I have already too
                        often had occasion to express the sentiments of my government to leave any
                        doubt of the sense in which I accept them.</p>
                    <p>In the performance of a duty which has been too often painful, whilst his
                        lordship has been officially the person to whom it has been my lot to
                        address my representations, I have been steadily cheered by the conviction
                        that he was substantially animated by the feeling that prompted those lines.
                        I have the greatest pleasure in believing that in assuming the duties of his
                        post under his auspices, my country may rest satisfied that the accession of
                        your lordship has brought about no unfavorable change.</p>
                    <p>I pray your lordship to accept the assurances of the highest consideration
                        with which I have the honor to be, my lord, your lordship’s most obedient
                        servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Right Hon. the <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl of Clarendon</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">.,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
