<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Adams..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-12-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85116821"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Salmon</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-12-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="21"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d21">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Adams</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1638.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Washington</hi>, </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-12-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 28, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I enclose to you a translation of a communication
                    of the 11th of November, addressed by Mr. S. Salnave, chief of the
                    revolutionists in Hayti, to the Hon. Salmon P. Chase, Chief Justice of the
                    United States, for the consideration of this government, from which it appears
                    that with a view to the overthrow of the revolutionary party on that island,
                    President Geffrard has, in order to obtain the co-operation of certain British
                    naval vessels there, made proposals to cede portions of that territory to the
                    British government.</p>
                <p>It is suggested that to counteract numerous designs prejudicial to general peace,
                    her Britannic Majesty’s government would cheerfully give assurances that they do
                    not intend or expect to acquire territory in Hayti.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic"
                            >&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Salnave</persName> to <persName type="to">Chief
                            Justice Chase</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Monte Christo,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-11-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 11, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The undersigned has the honor to address to
                        you this note to call your attention to <hi rend="italic">a</hi> question of
                        justice and of progress which cannot fail to interest you.</p>
                    <p>We have directed at the city of the Cape (Hayti) a liberal revolution, having
                        only for its object the overthrow of the despotism of Mr. Geffrard and to
                        establish in its place the democratic institutions which constitute the
                        honor and power of the United States.</p>
                    <pb facs="0110" n="36" xml:id="pg_36"/>
                    <p>The revolution has resisted for six months all the efforts of the tyrant, and
                        we were on the point of overthrowing him when he had recourse to English
                        intervention.</p>
                    <p>He pushed, by means unknown, the captain of the British war steamer Bulldog
                        into seeking a quarrel with us, without a plausible motive, and in
                        consequence to bombard our city. Seeing that we held out after this
                        bombardment, he caused two other English vessels of war to come from
                        Kingston—the Galope and the Lily. These two vessels presented themselves at
                        the cape, with Mr. St. John, chargé d’affaires of the British government,
                        and without choosing to listen to a single justification on our part, or to
                        accept any reparation for what they called an affront to their flag, they
                        demanded a dishonoring action—that of going on board their vessels to be
                        deported, and upon our refusal to abase ourselves, bombarded all our
                        fortifications, and thus favored the entrance of the army of Geffrard within
                        our walls. It need not be told that if the English could, in contempt of the
                        law of nations, intervene by force of arms with the policy of our country,
                        to destroy a revolution which was to give to Hayti liberty and prosperity,
                        it is because Geffrard has made them promises about certain portions of the
                        territory of our island. Such an engagement would be disastrous to the
                        country, and would break up the American policy of our country, as it has
                        established the Monroe system, which extends over all the American
                        nations.</p>
                    <p>We feel ourselves able to recommence the revolution, and end it in less than
                        a month, if we obtain from the government at Washington the succor we need
                        in arms, powder, and other munitions of war. We have in the country profound
                        sympathies. Our cause is that of liberty and progress. If your government
                        chooses to sustain us, we will make it triumphant for the happiness of our
                        country and the extension of friendly relations with the great American
                        republic. To obtain this aid, we offer to guarantee to the Cabinet of
                        Washington the port of Mole St. Nicolas as a maritime station. It is not the
                        policy of the United States to establish colonies, but a maritime arsenal in
                        a central position on the ocean cannot but be of great importance to them.
                        Without detaching the city of Mole St. Nicolas from the indivisible body of
                        the Haytian nationality, we would come under obligation to establish a
                        maritime station and arsenal for the government of the United States of
                        America, to which we would bind us more strictly still by a treaty of
                        friendship and commerce.</p>
                    <p>We would be very glad to receive your answer in this respect, if the proposal
                        attracts your attention. Presented by a man of your importance to the
                        Cabinet of Washington, it cannot fail of success. At all events, we ask of
                        you profound <hi rend="italic">secresy</hi> on this overture. If Geffrard
                        should get the least news of it, he would not neglect to invite the English
                        to the point in question. We hold out at Monte Christo, on Dominican
                        territory, waiting the honor of a reply, which we beg you to make as soon as
                        possible. Meantime we pray you to accept the assurances of our most
                        distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>S. SALNAVE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Salmon P. Chase</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chief
                                Justice of the United States.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
