<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Motley to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d477</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">477</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="477"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d477">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Motley</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 137.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-12-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 18, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have made a careful translation of the
                    Emperor’s speech on opening the Diet at Pesth, which you will find herewith. For
                    the first time in history, the royal discourse to the Hungarian parliament was
                    made in the Hungarian language, a fact which contributed much to the enthusiasm
                    with which it was received.</p>
                <p>My translation is from the German version published in the Vienna Gazette.</p>
                <p>There is no need of my offering any remarks as to the extreme importance of this
                    state paper in the present great historical crisis of the empire.</p>
                <p>Even in the midst of your severe labors at home to clear away the wrecks of the
                    secession war, and to re-establish the great republic on a more enduring basis
                    than perhaps can be hoped for by many European realms, you will doubtless find
                    time to observe the process by which the imperial government is seeking to
                    repair the damages of the civil war of seventeen years since, and to reconstruct
                    the empire.</p>
                <p>I shall endeavor in this correspondence to keep you accurately informed as to the
                    history and vital significance of events as they gradually unroll themselves,
                    and I shall be careful not to trespass more upon your patience than seems
                    necessary.</p>
                <p>To-day I shall simply draw your attention to the passage in the speech regarding
                    the necessity of the revision of a portion of the 1848 laws of Hungary,
                    observing that upon this point the most earnest debates will probably soon take
                    place, and the most divergent opinions manifest themselves. How to regulate the
                    public affairs common to the whole monarchy, when perhaps the most influential
                    party in Hungary will demand a resident palatine—in all but rank a king—with
                    independent ministers and departments of treasury and of war for that kingdom,
                    seems a most difficult problem. You will observe that the language of the
                    monarch, although conciliatory and benignant in general, does not lack firmness
                    upon this point. It is probable, therefore, that so soon as the first burst of
                    enthusiasm has passed away with which the speech has been greeted on all sides
                    in Pesth, grave demonstrations of dissent will be observed. Meantime the
                    suspension of a constitutional life is likely to continue for a considerable
                    period on both sides the Leitha, and this very fact must breed discontent
                    throughout the empire.</p>
                <p>Thus the organ at Pesth of the extreme party in Hungary (formerly called <pb
                        facs="0704" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/> the Beschlusz Partei, or resolution
                    party) observes in a late number that the 1848 laws contain nothing tending to
                    the ruin of the monarchy or detrimental to the rights of majesty, but that, on
                    the contrary, they are the foundation of constitutionalism and the prosperity of
                    the monarchy, and that it will be the grateful task of the Diet to make this
                    clear. It adds, that as the Hungarian and February constitution cannot exist
                    together, one of the two must always remain in suspense. “This suspension of the
                    entire State constitution simultaneously with the revision of the 1848 laws,” it
                    continues, “is, however, satisfactory to none of us, since the result is simply
                    that both constitutions are suspended, and that parliamentary government exists
                    neither in Pesth nor Vienna.”</p>
                <p>On the other hand, one of the most gifted and eloquent supporters of the February
                    constitution, Count Auersperg, known to all Germany as a popular and graceful
                    poet under the pseudonym of Anaslasius Gün, and recognized as one of the most
                    eminent debaters in the late Reichsrath, recently used this strong language in
                    the Diet of Carniola, speaking against the suspension manifesto of September:
                    “By this patent a new situation is created. A constitution over which the
                    Damocles sword of suspension is ever lifted is no longer a constitution, and
                    absolutism is preferable to such a system. The incomplete carrying out of the
                    February constitution was only a fault of persons, not of principle.</p>
                <p>* * * There is much that is enticing in the September patent, yet if twenty
                    creative diets are to bring about a chaos most certainly an absolute God
                    Almighty will cry out to them, <hi rend="italic">A quos ego</hi>.”</p>
                <p>You see by these extreme expressions in Germany and in Hungary how very grave the
                    situation may become, should the Hungarians, inspired by their present feelings
                    of exultation, push their claims to an unreasonable extent.</p>
                <p>Most certainly, if the various component parts of the Austrian monarchy cannot
                    agree upon some common constitution, the necessary result is a return to
                    absolutism—for otherwise the empire would cease to exist.</p>
                <p>I observed in my last despatch that it was possible that the diet of Bohemia
                    might pass a vote of censure or regret in regard to the September manifesto. The
                    party sustaining the present administration, however, uniting with the extreme
                    czech-federalist-aristocratic party, have obtained a small majority and voted an
                    address of approbation.</p>
                <p>The speech of the representative of government in the Bohemian Diet, Count
                    Lazausky, eminently federalist in tone, was considered by the German party so
                    bitter towards the Reichsrath that four members of that departed parliament,
                    Prince Carlos Auersberg and Counts Hartiz, Salm and Althau, members of the late
                    House of Peers, resigned their places as deputies in the Bohemian Diet. “The
                    government commissioner,” they say, “has declared, in the debate on the address,
                    that the Reichsrath has never legally existed, and has thus exposed the members
                    of the suspended Reichsrath to the laughter and the scorn of the diet party,
                    which abhors the Reichsrath. The undersigned, belonging to those members of the
                    Reichsrath thus exposed to contumely by the government representative, are
                    determined to prevent a recurrence of such scenes which have in view the
                    depreciation of a mission undertaken from a sense of duty, and they therefore
                    lay down their commission.”</p>
                <p>Prince Carlos Auersberg was presiding officer of the House of Peers—the other
                    gentlemen very eminent in rank, public service and general consideration; while
                    the extreme liberal and democratic organs in the German part of the empire are
                    still more vehement than the aristocratic party in their expressions of
                    feeling.</p>
                <p>Thus there are materials enough for a violent explosion, if the conflict of
                    nationalities is carried too far.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. LOTHROP MOTLEY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <pb facs="0705" n="631" xml:id="pg_631"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">
                            <hi rend="italic">Speech from the throne of his I. R. Apostolic Majesty
                                at the opening of the Hungarian Diet</hi>, <date
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1865-12-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 14, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>While we greet with sincere joy the estates and representatives of our
                        beloved kingdom of Hungary assembled in Diet, we at the same time make known
                        the purpose which has brought us here with that open frankness which can
                        alone establish the indispensable bond of confidence between a monarch and
                        his people.</p>
                    <p>We came to complete that which we had begun, penetrated with the feeling of
                        our duty as regent. Our object is, by our personal intervention, and
                        therefore the more successfully, to settle those doubts and to remove those
                        obstacles which hitherto have opposed the solution of pending questions of
                        state law.</p>
                    <p>Among these do we class in the first line the violent contradiction which
                        existed in the different starting-points towards the contemplated mutual
                        understanding. Legal forfeiture on the one side, and stiff legal continuity
                        on the other, could not lead to any agreement.</p>
                    <p>The obstacle we now remove in choosing a universally acknowledged ground for
                        our starting-point.</p>
                    <p>Whereas this fundamental state law has guaranteed the self-dependence of the
                        inner formation and administration of the kingdom of Hungary and the
                        adjoining provinces, it has at the same time preserved the constant
                        indissoluble and inseparable union between the kingdoms and provinces
                        standing under the government of our house, and therewith the position as a
                        great power of their entirety. Even as we therefore find in this entirety a
                        necessary and legal limitation of that independence, even so we recognize,
                        without reserve, justification thereof within these limits.</p>
                    <p>In the same manner do we wish to preserve unimpaired the conditions of the
                        pragmatic sanction which related to the integrity of the Hungarian crown,
                        and although we are obliged to pay regard to those facts upon record in the
                        last decade, we have at the same time directed our sovereign care to make
                        possible the representation of the provinces of our Hungarian crown at this
                        Diet.</p>
                    <p>For this purpose we have convoked the Diet of our principality of
                        Transylvania, in order that it may undertake an earnest and thorough
                        examination of the first law-article of the year 1848, relating to the union
                        between Hungary and Transylvania, and we require the estates and
                        representatives of our kingdom of Hungary assembled in Diet to take a
                        similar action in regard to the seventh law-article of the year 1847-8, in
                        order that this question, not, according to the dead letter of the law, a
                        fictitious and doubtful one, but, on the contrary, in harmony with all
                        vigorous factors, may find through their intimate conjunction a lasting and
                        complete solution.</p>
                    <p>In the same manner have we made known the summons to the assembled Diet of
                        Croatia and Sclavonia reasonably to provide that it should be represented at
                        this Diet; and while we communicate the resolution of the Croatian Diet,
                        passed in the year 1861, regarding the relation of Croatia to our kingdom of
                        Hungary, do we feel the confidence that the argument in regard to the legal
                        relations of brother races, united for centuries, will be firmly established
                        in the way of mutual yielding and in the spirit of that equitable conception
                        to which the estates and representatives of the kingdom of Hungary assembled
                        in Diet have lent an unequivocal expression in their address in this regard,
                        issued July 6, 1861.</p>
                    <p>As the first task of this Diet we must indicate the manner of negotiating
                        affairs common to all our kingdoms and provinces.</p>
                    <p>The existence of such affairs has its formation already in the spirit of the
                        pragmatic sanction, although, in regard to the manner of negotiating, the
                        essentially altered relations demand an essential change.</p>
                    <p>The transformation of the political, economical, and social factors which in
                        the meanwhile had gained ground, decided us, in the consciousness of our
                        high task, to confer constitutional rights also on our other kingdoms and
                        provinces, and therefore the affairs common to all provinces are only to be
                        conducted under the constitutional co-operation of those kingdoms and
                        provinces.</p>
                    <p>These were the motives which guided us when we issued our diploma of October
                        20, 1860, and we still firmly hold the conviction that a common
                        constitutional treatment of affairs, indicated in that diploma as universal,
                        forms an incontrovertible requisite of the united stability and position as
                        a power of our collected monarchy to which every other consideration must be
                        subordinate.</p>
                    <p>As regards the manner of negotiation, we have indicated a form in our patent
                        of February 26, 1861, which has, however, excited various and important
                        scruples. While we, therefore, cannot withhold the conviction that this
                        question cannot be determined definitely and lastingly with the weapons of
                        material or moral pressure, but, on the contrary, only in the way of general
                        compromise, and a recognition of necessity, we have temporarily, by our
                        manifests of September 20, suspended the efficacy of the statute of the
                        representation of the empire, and do now lay before the estates and
                        representatives of the kingdom of Hungary assembled in Diet our diploma of
                        October 20, 1860, as well as the patent of February 26, 1861, for mature
                        consideration, incisive criticism, and acceptance.</p>
                    <pb facs="0706" n="632" xml:id="pg_632"/>
                    <p>The well-understood interests of our kingdom of Hungary, as well as the
                        prosperity and safety of the whole empire, require the soonest possible
                        settlement of this affair, so that the constitutional rights of the single
                        kingdoms and provinces may, through the cordial annexation of our people, be
                        durably secured, may develop themselves on a firm basis, and may rejoice in
                        a vigorous bloom. We expect, therefore, of the estates and representatives
                        of our kingdom of Hungary assembled at this Diet, that they may in a spirit
                        of equity examine the state papers submitted to their judgment, and in case
                        of the existing objections appearing insurmountable, they may propose such
                        modifications only as can be brought into harmony with the vital conditions
                        of our entire monarchy. In close and inseparable conjunction with the
                        decision of this question stands the revision, and respectively the reform,
                        of that part of the 1848 laws which has reference to the efficacy of our
                        rights as sovereign, and the limitation of our attributes of government.</p>
                    <p>Things which stand in a close conjunction and exercise a mutual effect upon
                        each other cannot in practical realization be separated.</p>
                    <p>The unchanged coming into life of these laws does not lie within the region
                        of possibility when we take into consideration the position as a power of
                        our empire, the undiminished value of our sovereign rights, and the just
                        demands of the neighboring provinces. Although, therefore, the formal
                        legality of these laws cannot be questioned, yet our duties as a sovereign,
                        and the conscientious consideration of the care owed equally to all our
                        people, forbid us to confirm by our inaugural oath the vindication and
                        application of these laws, before the simultaneous fixation of the relation
                        of the mutual rights and duties. It is, therefore, necessary that the
                        motives of these laws which either circumscribe our sovereign rights or bear
                        reference to the alteration of the form of government, without bringing them
                        into harmony with the conditions of stability of the monarchy, or with the
                        inner institutions of the land that repose on a long-inherited basis, may be
                        carefully examined and judiciously altered. In this way it will be made
                        possible that we, too, may with a quiet conscience render our royal
                        inaugural oath to the suitably remodelled and, for late posterity, firmly
                        established constitution, and receive the consecration of coronation with
                        the diadem of the holy Stephen, our apostolic ancestor, with that holy crown
                        in which we are disposed to insert, as its most precious stone, the
                        prosperity of our kingdom of Hungary and the unbroken love of its
                        people.</p>
                    <p>As crowned king, we will not fail to impart to the assembled estates and
                        representatives, besides those state papers which we already submitted to
                        the Diet of 2d of April, 1861, also our royal propositions in regard to
                        numerous other affairs. These are objects which touch the spiritual and
                        material interests of the wisest circles, and whose successful regulation
                        cannot be postponed without detriment to the land.</p>
                    <p>The will of Divine Providence has imposed on us great and heavy tasks, and to
                        this land not less earnest ones, and charged with grave responsibility, by
                        reason of the suspension of constitutional life which has now taken place in
                        a great portion of our empire.</p>
                    <p>Insoluble, however, they are not, if the country, in union with its
                        sovereign, and following the traditions of the forefathers, undertakes them
                        with self-denial and willingness of sacrifice.</p>
                    <p>We hope this so much the more as the land, in imparting strength and weight,
                        gains strength and weight, in progressing to the lifting of these
                        difficulties elevates itself, in working for procuring the stability of the
                        whole secures its own stability; and if we are successful, after a long
                        pressing epoch, in leading our empire with the help of the country through
                        the doubtful turnings of a difficult situation to the wished-for term, we
                        shall bless the moment that ripened our resolution to revive and confirm the
                        confidence between the sovereign and the people.</p>
                    <p>With confident success do we look forward to the candid exposition of the
                        views of the assembled estates and representatives of this land, and while
                        we solemnly declare the Diet of our kingdom of Hungary as open, we close
                        with the earnest wish that it may be granted to us, with God’s help, to lead
                        to a happy issue the great work of mutual agreement.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
