<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d49</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">49</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-02-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-02-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="49"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1151.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">London</hi>, </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-02-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 15, 1866.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On a closer examination of the contents of the
                    parliamentary document containing the correspondence relative to the Shenandoah,
                    than I had been able to give at the moment when I transmitted copies to you last
                    week, I find, to my surprise, that Lord Clarendon, immediately after my
                    conversation with him of the 20th of December last, reported by me to you partly
                    in my despatch No. 1112, of the 21st of the same month, and partly in a
                    confidential letter, sent to Sir Frederick Bruce, in a despatch dated the 21st
                    of that month, instructions formally to submit to you the same proposition which
                    he had presented to me in that conference, and which I had then suggested to him
                    not to offer in that way. The objection to this course, as necessitating you at
                    the outset to bring forward the obstacle presented in the impossibility of
                    abandoning our claims, and in their absolute rejection of them, was so obvious
                    that I saw no method of reaching any useful result excepting through an informal
                    preliminary tentative process, absolutely committing neither party, by which
                    some notion might be reached of the precise extent to which each was willing
                    publicly to go in order to reach some common ground of negotiation. From a few
                    words that dropped from his lordship in our conversation, I rather inferred that
                    he had in his mind the possibility of making concessions of some sort from the
                    position taken by Lord Russell, provided they should not appear derogatory to
                    the national dignity. This was the only thing that gave me the smallest hope of
                    making something out of his overture. But that hope appears to be entirely
                    destroyed by the course now resorted to. The language of his letter to Sir F.
                    Bruce clearly implies that recurrence to the past makes no part of his plan. If
                    this be the true meaning, then the British government will have done nothing to
                    emerge from its former awkward position, of soliciting protection for itself in
                    certain future emergencies against the hazard of a retort of its own past
                    policy, without conceding that it had failed in any of its own obligations
                    heretofore. We are expected to abandon the whole ground of the justice of our
                    complaints at the same time that we shut ourselves off from all future chance of
                    profiting by their own policy, thus conceded to have been permissible under the
                    existing state of international law. The public presentation of such an
                    overture, if attended with no private explanation, would seem, therefore, only
                    like inviting a formal reply, which would more completely than ever block up the
                    last avenue to reconciliation.</p>
                <p>Of course, I write without knowledge of any instructions that may have
                    accompanied this letter to Sir Frederick Bruce. Hence, there may be something
                    unseen by me to soften the character of this transaction. But from my point of
                    view I am at a loss to explain the reasons for it excepting in one way. It may
                    be that the cabinet were unwilling to meet the new Parliament without having
                    something or other to show in qualification of the absolute and abrupt stopper
                    put upon the whole matter by Lord Russell. That step is very generally felt to
                    have been a mistake. It may be that this is the mode chosen by which to appear
                    to retract it, and at the same time to throw upon us an absolute necessity of
                    assuming the same position. It is scarcely possible to believe, after their
                    experience of the last four years, they could imagine us not in earnest in
                    maintaining the stand we had chosen to take, and not likely to abandon it from
                    the force of opposition. Hence the answer to a proposition publicly made in the
                    form chosen by Lord Clarendon could scarcely have been expected to be other than
                    an equally formal negative. Consequently, the end sought must have been, that
                    what odium might attach in this country to the fact of shutting off the last
                    avenue to a settlement of existing difficulties would be shifted from them to
                    us.</p>
                <pb facs="0142" n="68" xml:id="pg_68"/>
                <p>The idea is now started in private circles here, that, after all, the questions
                    raised in the late controversy are not susceptible of arrangement excepting
                    through a general conference of representatives of the maritime powers. Hence,
                    it is not impossible that some proposition of the kind may be started from other
                    quarters, but in the interest of this country, as the only remaining mode of
                    disposing of the matter.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
