<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Motley to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d491</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">491</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-05-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recfec047f5431758f" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="property-claims" subject="contraband-of-war">Contraband of war</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="reccab053b473a4a56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="world-war-i" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148236" lcsh-match="exact">Councils</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-05-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="491"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d491">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Motley</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 175<hi rend="italic">.</hi>]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Vienna,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-05-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 16, 1866.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your No. 178, of date 23d April, relative to German affairs.</p>
                <p>Referring to my No. 172, of date of 9th May, I have to state that the vote taken
                    on that day in the Diet at Frankfort resulted in a majority of ten to five for
                    the motion made by Saxony.</p>
                <p>The next step will probably be a declaration by the Bund that Prussia is guilty
                    of a breach of the Bund, (Bundesbruchig,) and a decree to enforce article XI
                    against her. This would naturally be followed by the occupation of Saxony by the
                    troops of the confederation unless Prussia herself should anticipate that
                    movement. In either case it would be the beginning of war.</p>
                <p>The accounts thus far in regard to the position of Hanover are conflicting. At
                    the above mentioned session of the Diet she voted with the majority against
                    Prussia. This is supposed to have somewhat surprised and offended that power.
                    Prussia, in consequence, addressed to Hanover a summons of a threatening nature.
                    Since then a statement needing confirmation has appeared that a treaty between
                    Hanover and Prussia has been made by which Hanover receives a guarantee of her
                    territory and promises assistance to Prussia in the coming war, or at least
                    neutrality.</p>
                <p>A glance at the map of Germany shows the great importance of Hanover by reason of
                    its geographical situation.</p>
                <p>Mecklenburg, Electoral Hesse and the Hanse Towns voted with the minority on the
                    9th.</p>
                <p>So far as concerns the German part of the impending struggle, much depends oh the
                    attitude of the southwestern powers, Wurtemberg, Baden, and Bavaria.</p>
                <p>I think that Austria relies with confidence on their support. They will, no
                    doubt, faithfully aid in carrying out the decrees of the Bund, so long as it can
                    be said to exist. But should Prussia in formal terms declare the Bund as no
                    longer existing, it would seem possible that the southwestern States might
                    content themselves with a position of armed neutrality in a war between Austria
                    and Prussia.</p>
                <p>I ascribe no very great importance to the suggestions of a congress and other
                    forms of pacific intervention.</p>
                <p>I suppose that the chief reason why hostilities have not begun is that the
                    military preparations are not fully made.</p>
                <p>Only those who have access to the military councils can tell how soon the war
                    will open.</p>
                <p>For some days placards have been posted in the streets of Vienna, signed by
                    Prince Colloredo, stadtholder of Lower Austria, and Dr. Zelinka, the burgomaster
                    of Vienna, calling for volunteers. The call is also published in the official
                    gazette. It is also officially announced that the government of Austria will
                    adhere to the declarations of the congress of Paris of 1856 and abstain <pb
                        facs="0738" n="664" xml:id="pg_664"/> from seizing merchant vessels of the
                    enemy and their cargoes at sea as good prize, in case of reciprocity on the part
                    of the enemy.</p>
                <p>This provision, however, has no relation to merchant men carrying contraband of
                    war, or endeavoring to break a lawful blockade.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to remain, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. LOTHROP MOTLEY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
