<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-03-15T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274" lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619" lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-03-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="62" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d62">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1172.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-03-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 15, 1866.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In compliance with a desire expressed in a
                            private note to me, I called to see Lord Clarendon on Tuesday, the 13th
                            instant, when he announced himself prepared to resume the conversation
                            held on the 5th instant, a report of which I made to you in my despatch
                            No. 1165.</p>
                <p>The substance of his observations, drawn from an examination of the
                            papers in the Home Office, was to the effect that the government, whilst
                            obliged to take every measure which the aggravated nature of the
                            circumstances demanded to secure the public safety in Ireland, was yet
                            ready to do whatever was possible not to make it press upon persons,
                            especially aliens, who might have become involved in suspicion, without
                            absolute proof. He referred to the claims made by Mr. West, the consul,
                            in behalf of certain individuals as native Americans, and expressed a
                            doubt from contrary evidence in their hands whether, at least in some of
                            the cases, the fact was made out. He spoke with some sensibility of the
                            very friendly manner in which the correspondence had been conducted, and
                            assured me that it would be fully met in the same spirit. With regard to
                            the claims made in behalf of naturalized Irishmen, he said that there
                            was here an opposition in the law between the two countries which was
                            not to be reconciled. He intimated that the process of naturalization
                            was susceptible <pb facs="0158" n="84" xml:id="pg_84"/> of abuse in
                            America, which might, if it were recognized as valid, have the effect of
                            paralyzing all their measures to suppress the disaffection. As it was,
                            what remained of it was clearly traceable to the support it got from
                            money and men sent from the other side. Hence, it would be very
                            difficult to make concessions in these cases.</p>
                <p>I replied to this by explaining to him the nature of the obstacles
                            existing in America to that facility of naturalization to which he had
                            alluded. There might be some abuse of the process and even some fraud,
                            but after all, the law required certain previous conditions of time from
                            the date of the preliminary declaration, which were generally fulfilled.
                            I did not, therefore, think that there was so much danger of abuse as he
                            imagined. For the rest, I had no disposition to encourage false claims.
                            To that end I had directed Mr. West to take every precaution in
                            verifying, so far as he could, the allegation of nativity by requiring
                            details of time, place, and circumstance. Furthermore, in regard to
                            naturalization, I had also required satisfactory evidence, which, as Mr.
                            West had written to me, had been furnished him only in a very small
                            number of cases. Hence, I infer that most of the persons arrested must
                            remain outside of my limit of interference. But even in all the admitted
                            cases, if the government had in its hands the proofs of complicity with
                            designs to overthrow the established law, I should feel myself obliged,
                            on the production of them to me, to desist from urgency in regard to
                            them. We had experienced so much annoyance from action of the same kind
                            by the subjects of foreign states, who sympathized with and aided the
                            rebellion, and whom we had been compelled to arrest and detain in the
                            same way, that I was not inclined to give any sanction to such conduct
                            anywhere. My efforts would be confined to those cases in which there was
                            mere suspicion, or at most feeble evidence, of actual evil intent.
                            Surely, in such instances it was no object for her Majesty’s government
                            to persevere in holding them, especially if the parties should prove
                            willing, in the event of liberation, to pass without the limits of the
                            jurisdiction. Of course, I could make no guarantee as to what they would
                            or would not do in that event. The choice might, however, be left to
                            them, if the case should seem to require it.</p>
                <p>His lordship, without absolutely committing himself in words, gave me
                            generally to understand that the government would cheerfully co-operate
                            in every effort to facilitate an arrangement of all such cases. He asked
                            me whether I desired to have the subject now put in writing between us,
                            or I should prefer to wait a little while, letting things go on as at
                            present. I replied that I was not yet quite prepared for the former
                            course. The consul was still busy getting up his evidence in the
                            respective cases Whenever the report I expected from him should arrive,
                            I would then make a representation in writing. To this his lordship
                            would probably consent to give me a reply. After the receipt of that I
                            should make the proper official report to my government, with a view to
                            obtaining full instructions as to the future. Thus far it was to be
                            understood that I had been acting upon the spur of the moment, without
                            being possessed of the views of my government. So soon as they should be
                            communicated to me I should take an early opportunity to let him know
                            what they were.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
