<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Adams..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d66</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">66</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1866-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1866-03-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-03-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="66"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Adams</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1717.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">State Department</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-03-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 22, 1866.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> A despatch, No. 145, has been received from
                    William B. West, esq., United States consul at Dublin, from which it appears
                    that he, on the 20th of February last, opened a correspondence with her
                    Majesty’s attorney general for Ireland. In that correspondence he set forth the
                    fact that a large number of the citizens of the United States have recently been
                    arrested and thrown into prison in Ireland, without any information against
                    them, or the slightest allegation of their guilt. That many alleged cases of
                    great hardship and unjustifiable harshness have been brought before the consul,
                    in the execution of the law by which the <hi rend="italic">habeas corpus</hi>
                    act was suddenly suspended in that country. That in other cases American
                    citizens may be imprisoned, who, although there may be some grounds of suspicion
                    against them, are nevertheless free from complicity in any designs against the
                    peace and safety of the realm.</p>
                <p>Upon these statements the consul would think it his duty to report to this
                    government all cases of arrest of American citizens, with a view that proper
                    proceedings might be taken for an inquiry into the causes of their arrest and
                    detention.</p>
                <p>In reply to this note, the secretary of the lord lieutenant informed the consul
                    that he would be expected by his excellency to furnish him with the names of
                    such American citizens as he had referred to, and to state any facts tending to
                    establish their innocence of the treasonable designs of which they are
                    suspected.</p>
                <p>It was further stated by the secretary that directions have been given by the
                    lord lieutenant for an investigation into the cases of all subjects or citizens
                    of foreign states who have been arrested, with a view to their liberation, if
                    the circumstances rendered it possible.</p>
                <p>On the 21st of February the consul replied to the under-secretary of the lord <pb
                        facs="0161" n="87" xml:id="pg_87"/> lieutenant that he had been refused
                    permission to visit certain prisoners, understood to be American citizens, who
                    were detained at Kilmainham, although he had been permitted to see others who
                    were charged with treason and felony.</p>
                <p>On the 22d of February the same under-secretary wrote to the consul that it was
                    impossible for the lord lieutenant to give to the consul a general permission to
                    visit the prisoners, but no impediment would be thrown in the way of their
                    communicating in writing.</p>
                <p>The secretary further stated that permission would be given to the consul to see
                    any prisoner who he had good reason to believe was a citizen of the United
                    States and not a subject of the Queen.</p>
                <p>On the 24th of February the consul wrote to the secretary that two gentlemen,
                    named John H. Gleason and Joseph Gleason, were then prisoners in the Neuagh
                    jail, who had documentary proof of their being citizens of the United States by
                    naturalization. In regard to these persons the consul asked to be furnished with
                    copies of any information that might have been sworn against them to justify
                    their arrest.</p>
                <p>In the same letter the consul asked of the lord lieutenant permission to visit
                    Bernard McDermott, who was a prisoner in Kilmainham jail, and who also was
                    citizen of the United States, as appeared by documents of naturalization.</p>
                <p>On the 27th of February the consul again wrote to the secretary, begging leave to
                    draw the attention of the lord lieutenant to the cases of Michael O’Brien and
                    Michael Duffy, who were confined in the Kilmainham jail, and whose evidence of
                    United States citizenship was then before the consul; and in their behalf the
                    consul asked permission to visit them, and also to be furnished with a copy of
                    the evidence or information upon which they were deprived of their liberty.</p>
                <p>On the 28th of February the secretary communicated to the consul the answer of
                    the lord lieutenant, which is this:</p>
                <p>“John H. and Joseph Gleason and Bernard McDermott are Irish-born subjects of her
                    Majesty the Queen, and, notwithstanding any course which they may have pursued
                    in the United States of America, they still in Ireland must be regarded as
                    ordinary subjects of her Majesty, bound by the allegiance which they owe to
                    their sovereign, and they must be dealt with accordingly. His excellency cannot
                    recognize any right on his part, or on the part of the consul, as consul of the
                    United States, to interfere in respect to the prisoners intrusted to his care,
                    on the ground of their being citizens of the United States.”</p>
                <p>It is well understood that there is a conflict between the laws of Great Britain,
                    as expounded by her legal authorities, and the laws of the United States, as
                    understood by this government, with regard to the effect of naturalization. It
                    is understood that the British government has not heretofore conceded that a
                    native subject of the British realm divests himself of his allegiance by
                    renouncing that allegiance, and transferring his allegiance under our laws to
                    the United States. On the other hand, there has been no reservation on the part
                    of the United States in regard to the principle that the process of
                    naturalization in this country completely absolves the person complying with it
                    from foreign allegiance, whoever may have been his sovereign, and invests him
                    with the right equally with native-born citizens to such protection and care of
                    the government of the United States as it can, in conformity with treaties and
                    the law of nations, extend over him, wherever he may sojourn, whether in the
                    land of his nativity or in any other foreign country. Of course the United
                    States do not claim or hold that any such naturalized citizen, when transiently
                    travelling or sojourning for a longer or shorter period in a foreign country,
                    can refuse submission to the sovereign authority and obedience to the laws in
                    the country of his temporary residence. All citizens of the United States, when
                    passing through or dwelling in foreign countries, owe obedience and submission
                    to the laws of those countries.</p>
                <p>Hitherto each party has adhered to its own position in this conflict of laws;
                    but, through what may be deemed to have been a fortunate <pb facs="0162" n="88"
                        xml:id="pg_88"/> and prudence, it has happened that occasions for collision
                    upon the question in debate have not arisen. Indeed, it has seemed to be passing
                    within the domain of those disputes which, in process of time, become harmless
                    abstractions.</p>
                <p>From the very nature of the conflict, however, it is one which, when once
                    practically raised, finds a friendly adjustment only by concession on one side
                    or the other, or both, in the form of a treaty, or of mutual legislation, or
                    through some form of arbitrament. The answer of the lord lieutenant to the
                    American consul, if it shall be adopted by her Majesty’s government, must bring
                    the question up for immediate solution. The lord lieutenant admits the right of
                    the consul of the United States to visit and lend good offices to the prisoner
                    under arrest upon a charge of treason, where he is a native-born citizen of the
                    United States. The lord lieutenant denies the same privileges to the consul in
                    the case of a native of Great Britain, who has been naturalized by the laws of
                    the United States. But he concedes to the consul the privilege of corresponding
                    with the accused in both cases.</p>
                <p>It will hardly be necessary to inform her Majesty’s government that among these
                    naturalized citizens of the United States, in whose behalf the good offices of
                    this government are thus discriminated against by the lord lieutenant, are some
                    who have borne arms in the defence of the United States in a war with public
                    enemies. Her Majesty’s government can conceive how impossible it would be for
                    the government of the United States to agree to a denial or abridgment of their
                    right to extend to them the same natural protection and care which the United
                    States extend to native-born citizens of the United States in similar cases.</p>
                <p>Practically there would seem to be no sufficient ground for the discrimination.
                    Why should not the consul be allowed to visit an accused party with whom he is
                    allowed to correspond? Why should not the United States consul be allowed to use
                    his good offices in having the claim of the offender, based upon his
                    naturalization in the United States, brought to the consideration of the
                    judiciary of Great Britain? What danger to her Britannic Majesty’s government
                    can be apprehended from allowing the right of visitation in the one case, and
                    not in the other? The government of the United States is in one case, equally
                    with the other, responsible for the good faith and loyal conduct of the
                    consul.</p>
                <p>Under the existing circumstances, the insisting, by the British government, upon
                    the discrimination mentioned, could not but be regarded as manifesting a
                    willingness to join issue with the government of the United States upon the main
                    question involved in the conflict. What advantage would result from this
                    precipitancy, and would it serve to disarm, or weaken, or disperse the class of
                    persons who are understood to be seeking to produce sedition and civil war in
                    Ireland, to have it known that a serious debate has arisen upon it between the
                    United States and Great Britain, without any good prospect of a peaceful and
                    friendly settlement? It is for her Majesty’s government to consider whether the
                    occasion which brings up the question is the most suitable one, and whether the
                    present time is the very conjuncture which ought to be chosen for joining that
                    issue; or whether some other occasion and time might not be more convenient for
                    treating the question, upon a good hope of its adjustment.</p>
                <p>You will submit these views to the Earl of Clarendon, and ask for the decision of
                    her Majesty’s government at as early a day as may be convenient. In doing so you
                    will, in a most respectful manner, give his lordship to understand that the
                    United States will find themselves entirely unable to acquiesce in the course
                    which is indicated by the lord lieutenant’s decision in the case of John H. and
                    Joseph Gleason and other British-born but naturalized citizens of the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>You may use this despatch either openly or confidentially, as you think best.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H SEWABD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic"
                            >&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
