<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1866p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d7</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">7</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="self-determination">National reconciliation</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619" lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-12-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="7" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d7">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1104.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">London</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-12-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 6, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In accordance with the desire expressed in
                            your despatch No. 1579, of the 4th of November, I presented a copy of
                            the same to Lord Clarendon, who freely expressed his approbation of it,
                            after which I concluded to give it publicity through the press. It
                            accordingly appeared simultaneously in all the London morning papers of
                            Saturday last, the 2d instant. I transmit a copy of the Times of that
                            day, and likewise a copy of the same paper of the 5th, containing <pb facs="0101" n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/> a leader on the subject. The
                            tone of this is conciliatory until towards the close, when allusions are
                            made of an ambiguous character.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">From the Times, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-12-05">December 5,
                                        1865</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>There are few Englishmen of any feeling who would not have a host of
                                once vivid impressions revived by the sight of Mr. Seward’s despatch
                                to the American minister in our Saturday’s columns. It is only seven
                                months since we heard the news of a crime which grows in magnitude
                                and in horror as we drift away from it down the swift stream of
                                time. The intervening period has not been uneventful or unexciting.
                                We too, like the Americans, have lost the political chief of our
                                government, and quietly accepted the next in authority. The United
                                States themselves have been pacified, reorganized, and reunited,
                                with a rapidity and ease that command our admiration. Our own
                                immense empire has never failed to produce, somewhere or other,
                                objects of anxious or agreeable interest. At home we are dividing
                                our time between domestic economies and organic reconstruction. Our
                                hands are never idle, but we can still feel the shock of the
                                frightful tragedy which only in the spring of this year threw into
                                the background every lesser or older misery, and might atone for any
                                number of errors. It so happened that Abraham Lincoln, by the
                                progress of or the amendment of truth, had righted himself in
                                English esteem, and then stood as well in our regards as any foreign
                                potentate could ever hope to stand. We admired the man, and were
                                beginning to like him, seeing in him the able and kind-hearted
                                administrator of the greatest work of social peace-making the world
                                had yet seen. So we felt his murder as we should have done that of a
                                leading British statesman at the hands of a political fanatic. There
                                was more, indeed, in his case than there would ever be in this
                                country, unless we could suppose half the realm making head against
                                the other half for several years. There was the grand ceremony of a
                                national reconciliation to be performed, and, as Heaven would have
                                it, there lay bleeding before us the victim to consecrate it. Other
                                victims were intended, and the assassins so far succeeded that one,
                                the foremost statesman on the federal side, and the man with whom we
                                had most to do, had to endure for months a living martyrdom. The
                                strong will, the active intellect, and the ready tongue lay
                                trembling between life and death when the most difficult stage of
                                his great task had only just begun. We could not but be deeply
                                impressed with a catastrophe that appealed to the chief qualities of
                                our race, and the national sympathy burst out at a thousand
                                openings, wherever many or few had been wont to come together and
                                make a common utterance. It was the same elsewhere. So mail after
                                mail took across the Atlantic such piles of condolence as had
                                probably never before been evoked by any national bereavement.
                                Answer could hardly be expected, for the man to answer was himself a
                                dying man, for the time as helpless as his chief. So we were all
                                content to wait; and now, after seven months, we find that we can
                                revert to that crisis with undiminished horror at the deed, and
                                larger and more certain knowledge of its place in the work of
                                American reconstruction.</p>
                    <p>The American Secretary of State has done all that could be done under
                                the circumstances. Any attempt to produce a form of words specially
                                appropriate to every address and every community would have been
                                only a ridiculous effort of literary clerkship. Even in this country
                                people are little aware of the pressure of work in the principal
                                departments on an extraordinary crisis or in a busy season. At
                                Washington there was a war to be brought to an end, a great empire
                                to be rebuilt, and a good many questions with other countries to be
                                settled, if possible, to the satisfaction alike of the American and
                                of the foreigner. Mr. Seward, who has recovered slowly from his
                                terrible succession of injuries, has only just been able to speak
                                for himself and his government. The British public will not have
                                failed to notice the modesty with which the Secretary alludes to the
                                cause of this delay. His department was indeed crippled when he lay,
                                as many thought, on his death-bed, with wound upon wound; for that
                                was “the peculiar calamity” which then impaired the efficiency of
                                the American foreign office. That a government simply constructed
                                for the transaction of necessary affairs in the ordinary course of
                                public business should have been able to do its share in the work of
                                the war was itself a wonder to this country. But when a new calamity
                                involved new “obligations”—the calamity a partial massacre of the
                                government, and the “obligations” the duty of answering
                                condolences—the worst foe of republican institutions could not but
                                do justice to the government which went on at all under such
                                circumstances. We all saw, and duly appreciated, that there was not
                                the least symptom of failure or collapse. Everything went on as
                                usual, as far as met the eye. Our own difficulties, indeed, are so
                                different in kind that it is not easy to make a just and
                                intelligible comparison; but after witnessing the confusion apt to
                                take place in other States upon the sudden withdrawing or the
                                disabling of those at the head of critical affairs, we seemed to
                                recognize a character like our own in a <pb facs="0102" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/> people whose chief rulers fell or were
                                prostrated in a day, at a time when they were more than ever wanted,
                                but which went on just as usual.</p>
                    <p>The simple but Very hearty acknowledgments of the American Secretary
                                seem to give us an opening for a word or two on the prevalent
                                feelings of this country towards the United States. It would be
                                quite idle to deny that there are points upon which this country is
                                jealous, or sore, or without the perfect sympathy that obtains
                                between two similar social systems. With long arrears of quarrels
                                upon one trifle or another, and a new one every year, and with a
                                very strong opinion on this side that our rights were often
                                sacrificed to political exigencies in the United States, we
                                certainly have found it difficult to appreciate the Americans as we
                                really wish to do. We can afford to make this confession when we
                                state what we believe to be the truth as to the great extent of our
                                good wishes for America. We have not the least objection to the
                                United States increasing to any extent, and annexing any amount of
                                territory or number of States, so long as it is all done honestly,
                                above-board, and by fair appeals to the sympathy and good sense of
                                the people. If the population, either of our own provinces or of
                                Mexico, freely and spontaneously declared that they thought this
                                their best chance of peace and prosperity, the British people would
                                only feel the most passing regret at the loss of a name, and the
                                proportionate aggrandizement of the United States. Of course the
                                case is altered if the object is to be obtained, by fraud, by force,
                                or by intimidation. In that case, not only is there actual wrong
                                done upon our own loyal fellow subjects, and others entitled to our
                                sympathy, but there is also established a prescription, a policy,
                                and a temper ruinous to the future peace and even progress of the
                                world. History contains some very colossal instances of continual
                                annexation by fraud and by violence; in fact, by policies
                                constructed with a special View to perpetual aggrandizement. But the
                                event yet condemns them; the moral sense is opposed to them; and
                                modern politics are mainly directed to prevent the recurrence of the
                                evil. It is from no special jealousy of the United States that we
                                dread their indefinite enlargement by the means too often employed,
                                and vainly denounced by American demoralists. It is our English
                                habit, our second nature, our historical teaching, our European law.
                                Even in Europe we are glad to see Italians or Germans achieve more
                                comprehensive unions than circumstances have hitherto allowed. Nor
                                should we object to any amount of aggregation in America by equally
                                allowable means. Only, as a great State we cannot bear to be ousted,
                                outwitted, and coerced, and to see our own people, suffer for their
                                loyalty.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
