<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-11-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-11-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                        <head>143. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of
                            State (<persName corresp="#p_TPR_1">Tarnoff</persName>) to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (Brzezinski)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d143fn1">Source: Carter Library,
                                National Security Affairs, Staff Material, Global Issues, Bloomfield
                                Subject File, Box 19, Indochinese, 7–12/79. No classification
                                marking.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-11-21">November 21, 1979</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Possible Use of a Pacific Island for Indochinese Refugees</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>There have been earlier proposals to use a South Pacific island (in the
                            Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands or elsewhere) as a transshipment
                            point or for resettlement of Indochina refugees. Although the idea of
                            using a tropical island for these purposes is appealing at first glance
                            there are a number of factors which make these proposals
                            impractical.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><gloss target="#t_TTPI_1">TTPI</gloss></p>
                        <p>Although the population of the Trust Territory is relatively small
                            (approx 120,000) the total land area is also very small as are the
                            individual islands. With a very weak resource base and declining U.S.
                            subsidies after the Trusteeship ends it will be difficult for the area
                            to support its own population which is growing very rapidly. Permanent
                            resettlement of any significant number of refugees would magnify these
                            problems. The use of one or more of the islands for temporary refuge at
                            international or U.S. expense would be more practical in principle but
                            would confront important political obstacles.</p>
                        <p>The United States administers the Trust Territory under the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Trusteeship Agreement.<note n="2" xml:id="d143fn2">See Chapter XII, Articles 75–85 of the United
                                Nations Charter. U.S. trusteeship of the <gloss target="#t_TTPI_1">TTPI</gloss> ended in 1986.</note> Our current negotiations
                            with the Micronesians have as their goal termination of the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Trusteeship by 1981. The principles
                            governing the negotiations call for a status of free association under
                            which the Micronesians will be fully self-governing and in control of
                            foreign policy subject only to their defense relationship with the U.S.
                            Meanwhile, any decision to use the territory of any of the four
                            Micronesian political entities for refugees (temporarily or permanently)
                            would require the approval of their elected legislatures. Such approval
                            would almost certainly not be granted for permanent resettlement and is
                            very unlikely for temporary refugee camps.</p>
                        <p>To act without such approval, or in the face of explicit disapproval,
                            would lay the United States open to the charge of acting contrary to <pb facs="0532" n="503" xml:id="pg_503"/> the terms of the Trusteeship
                            Agreement which includes an obligation for the United States to promote
                            the welfare of the native population and to promote self-determination.
                            It would also have an unfavorable impact on the political status
                            negotiations which would not be in keeping with our general strategic
                            interests in that area. In light of the seriousness of the refugee
                            situation, the Department of State will approach the Micronesian
                            governments through the High Commissioner to see if any of the four
                            political entities would be agreeable to providing an island site to be
                            used as a temporary refugee processing center.</p>
                        <p>We must of course recognize that if we accepted refugees into territory
                            under U.S. jurisdiction, even on a transient basis, many countries would
                            assume that these refugees would in the end be admitted into the United
                            States, and would not themselves accept them.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">The U.S. Territories</p>
                        <p>The U.S. territories in the Pacific (Guam and American Samoa) have
                            population problems and would also find it extremely difficult to absorb
                            permanent resettlement of refugees.</p>
                        <p>In recent years political discontent has grown because of what many
                            Guamanians feel is a high-handed attitude of the Federal Government in
                            making decisions which impact directly upon the Guamanians without prior
                            consultations or approval. Although Guam has been used as a temporary
                            holding center for Vietnamese refugees it is almost certain that the
                            Guam Government would reject any proposal to hold refugees on the island
                            for an extended period or to permanently resettle Indochinese refugees
                            on Guam. Because of the limited land available there has been
                            considerable pressure on the U.S. military to reduce land-use
                            requirements.</p>
                        <p>The geography of American Samoa (most of the land-area is mountainous)
                            has forced the concentration of the population onto the limited amount
                            of flat inhabitable land between the mountains and the sea. There is
                            little room available for an even moderately large refugee camp.</p>
                        <p>Again, if we accepted refugees even as transients in Guam or Samoa, other
                            governments would probably lose any interest in receiving them.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Independent Pacific Nations</p>
                        <p>The independent island nations of the South Pacific are developing
                            countries and require outside financial assistance in order to survive.
                            An exception is Nauru which is self-sufficient because of phosphate
                            mining. However, Nauru will in the future be forced to resettle its own
                            population as a result of extensive mining operations which are
                            rendering the island uninhabitable.</p>
                        <pb facs="0533" n="504" xml:id="pg_504"/>
                        <p>The smaller Pacific Island nations all have real development problems
                            (e.g., small land mass, inadequate infrastructure, subsistence
                            economies, and the threat of over-population, etc.). In the countries
                            with larger land areas (Fiji, <gloss target="#t_PNG_1">PNG</gloss>, New
                            Hebrides, Solomons, and New Caledonia) there is a delicate political
                            balance among ethnic groups, rival tribal and regional groups, white
                            settlers and indigenous population. The introduction into these
                            societies of a potentially destabilizing element in the form of another
                            ethnic group would be seen by the local governments as likely to upset
                            the fragile balance.</p>
                        <p>The Deputy Prime Minister of Papua New Guinea (<gloss target="#t_PNG_1">PNG</gloss>) voiced the concerns of many of the Pacific nations
                            when he discussed the refugee problem with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> on September 25.<note n="3" xml:id="d143fn3">A summary of the meeting between <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> and Foreign Minister
                                    <persName corresp="#p_OE_1">Olewale</persName> in New York
                                during the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> General Assembly
                                session is in telegram Secto 8018 to Port Moresby, October 1.
                                (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D790441–0448)</note> In explaining why <gloss target="#t_PNG_1">PNG</gloss> agreed to make a financial contribution but not to
                            accept any refugees, he explained that the Government of Papua New
                            Guinea did not want to create for itself a Fiji-like problem—that is, a
                            situation in which people (in this case Indians) whose skills were
                            greater than those of the local population were brought in from the
                            outside by Fiji’s then colonial rulers and took over the country’s
                            economy.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_TPR_1"><hi rend="strong">Peter
                                        Tarnoff</hi></persName>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Executive Secretary</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>