<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-11-09T09:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-11-09T09:00:00-05:00" n="248" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d248">
                        <head>248. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d248fn1">Source: Washington National Records Center, RG 330,
                                    <gloss target="#t_OSD_1">OSD</gloss> Files: FRC 330–80–0035, 26,
                                New Zealand 000.1–425.1, Jan 1977. Confidential. The meeting took
                                place at Blair House. Prepared by Hanson on November 14. <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Muldoon</persName> was in Washington November
                                8–11 for an official visit.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1977-11-09T09:00:00-05:00" to="1977-11-09T09:30:00-05:00">November 9, 1977, 9–9:30 a.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Meeting Between Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Robert
                                    D. Muldoon</persName> of New Zealand and Secretary of Defense
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold Brown</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">U.S.</hi></head>
                                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                                    <item>The Deputy Secretary</item>
                                    <item>U.S. Ambassador to New Zealand, Armistead Selden</item>
                                    <item>Dep Asst Secretary, East Asia &amp; Pacific Affairs,
                                            <persName corresp="#p_AMI_1">Morton I.
                                            Abramowitz</persName></item>
                                    <item>Deputy Asst Secretary of State, East Asia &amp; Pacific
                                        Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_ORB_1">Robert
                                            Oakley</persName></item>
                                    <item>RADM Thor Hanson, Mil Asst</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">New Zealand</hi></head>
                                    <item>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Muldoon</persName></item>
                                    <item>Secretary of Foreign Affairs, Frank Corner</item>
                                    <item>Permanent Head, Prime Minister’s Department, Bernard
                                        Galvin</item>
                                    <item>Director, Americas Division, Ministry of Foreign Affairs,
                                        William Plimmer</item>
                                    <item>Ambassador Lloyd White</item>
                                    <item>Defense Attache Harry Honor</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>1. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Muldoon</persName> opened
                            the meeting by stating his appreciation for the cooperation of the
                            United States in defense matters and emphasizing the importance of
                                <gloss target="#t_ANZUS_1">ANZUS</gloss> to New Zealand. He said New
                            Zealand wanted to play an even more active part in <gloss target="#t_ANZUS_1">ANZUS</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>2. <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> emphasized the importance
                            the U.S. attached to <gloss target="#t_ANZUS_1">ANZUS</gloss> and the
                            need for a close relationship among the United States, New Zealand, and
                            Australia. He also expressed the importance of the Pacific to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and our determination to remain a power
                            in East Asia.</p>
                        <p>3. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Muldoon</persName> said
                            that one important role New Zealand saw for herself was to help keep the
                            newly independent States of the South Pacific cooperative and “relaxed”
                            about great power rivalry. He thought the States of the area were doing
                            well.</p>
                        <p>4. The Prime Minister spoke of the resumption of <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> nuclear warship visits and urged the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> to increase their frequency—that it was
                            important in New Zealand to do so. The increase in <gloss target="#t_NPW_1">NPW</gloss> visits was necessary to accustom the
                            New Zealand public to them so they take such visits as a normal
                            occurrence. New Zealand would like a continuing combination of nuclear
                            powered and conventional warships. <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> expressed U.S. appreciation to <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Muldoon</persName> for allowing the resump<pb facs="0838" n="809" xml:id="pg_809"/>tion of <gloss target="#t_NPW_1">NPW</gloss> visits and said we would do what we
                            can to make them a more regular occurrence. The Prime Minister said that
                            the question of radiation monitoring for these visits had recently been
                            resolved.</p>
                        <p>5. Speaking of the New Zealand Army battalion now garrisoned in
                            Singapore, the Prime Minister said that <persName corresp="#p_LKY_1">Lee
                                Kuan-yew</persName> had told him privately that the battalion could
                            stay or could go—that he was not adverse to having it remain there. From
                            his point of view retaining the battalion in Singapore had the
                            advantages of giving the opportunity to train in a jungle area, offering
                            travel abroad for the soldiers, and also providing a good image for New
                            Zealand in South East Asia because of the large number of Maori troops
                            in the battalion. He went on to say that if the battalion did have to be
                            removed, New Zealand would be looking for <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> help in finding another training location. <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> responded that he thought the
                            present arrangement was helpful to stability in the area. If it were
                            necessary to withdraw the battalion we would be glad to look into joint
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>/New Zealand training
                            opportunities; he mentioned Guam as a possible spot. He hoped it would
                            not be necessary.</p>
                        <p>6. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Muldoon</persName> said
                            that New Zealand has a joint defense purchasing agreement with Australia
                            that has the aim of promoting standardization of equipment within the
                            two military forces. He said that the agreement is fine in theory but is
                            not producing much for New Zealand because the Australians want to
                            dictate all the purchases. The Prime Minister just offered this for
                            information—with no request for help.</p>
                        <p>7. The Prime Minister spoke of the proposed New Zealand-<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> fishing agreement, making the
                            economic arguments for the argument, and saying that New Zealand would
                            probably have to license some Soviet fishing trawlers. He asked whether
                            New Zealand should allow the Soviets any shore installations. <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> said our only concern was that
                            such installations could well result in intelligence collection and
                            urged New Zealand to be mindful of the problem. We had extensive
                            exchanges with New Zealand on intelligence and wanted to be sure these
                            would not be compromised. He also mentioned that many Soviet trawlers
                            are intelligence collectors. The Prime Minister responded that if the
                            licensing agreement included a condition allowing boarding of the
                            trawlers, it might discourage intelligence operations. He also spoke of
                            the problem of communications security and made the point that there was
                            no intention of giving the Soviets a base in New Zealand but rather just
                            the use of repair facilities and the opportunity to take on supplies.
                            Mr. Galvin emphasized that other types of Soviet ships are already
                            coming to New Zealand (merchants and liners) and that New Zealand
                            already has the capacity to deal with them and could easily handle the
                            fishing trawler from any security standpoint.</p>
                        <pb facs="0839" n="810" xml:id="pg_810"/>
                        <p>8. The Prime Minister mentioned that <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                            warships are warmly greeted in all Southern Pacific countries and made a
                            pitch for more visits to Fiji, Samoa, and Tonga. The <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> acknowledged the point and said
                            that we certainly do not intend to ignore the South-west Pacific.</p>
                        <p>9. The Prime Minister asked <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> if
                            he had any comments on the Indian Ocean. <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> responded that US/Soviet negotiations would probably
                            resume next month<note n="2" xml:id="d248fn2">The third round of
                                negotiations was held December 6–10 in Bern. See <ref target="frus1977-80v18#d117"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XVIII, Middle East Region;
                                    Arabian Peninsula, Document 117</ref>.</note> and that it is
                            possible that <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and Soviet interests
                            may be close enough to allow a modest agreement to stabilize the present
                            situation—that if neither want to expand their forces agreement may be
                            easy. He also emphasized that whether or not an arrangement was reached
                            the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> is not going to lose interest in
                            the area, given the importance of limiting Soviet expansion in the
                            Persian Gulf area to the North. He said that in the future we might be
                            able to negotiate a reduction of forces in the Indian Ocean but
                            certainly not now. He asked for the Prime Minister’s views.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister responded that New Zealand has a relaxed view as long
                            as a reasonable balance is maintained—that the Indian Ocean is important
                            to New Zealand and they want to see a continuing <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> interest. New Zealand is content to leave the details to
                            the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> commented that it is interesting to note that the
                            largest naval force in the Indian Ocean on a week-by-week basis is the
                            French but questioned how long that might continue.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister asked about Diego Garcia and <gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SecDef</gloss> responded that it is a modest
                            naval base limited to communications and fueling facilities—that we
                            certainly intend to continue our presence there but have no plans to
                            increase our activities.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Thor Hanson</hi></persName>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Rear Admiral, USN <lb/> Military Assistant to the
                                    Secretary of Defense</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>