<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-04-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="251" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d251">
                        <head>251. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> to New Zealand Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Muldoon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d251fn1">Source: Carter Library, Donated Historical
                                Material, Mondale Papers, Overseas Assignments—Trip Files,
                                1977–1980, Box 22, VP’s Visit to the Pacific, 4/29/78–5/11/78: New
                                Zealand (5/9/78–5/10/78)—President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s Letter to <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRD_1">Muldoon</persName>. No classification
                                marking.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-04-27">April 27, 1978</date></dateline>
                            <salute>Dear Mr. Prime Minister:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I set great store by the very close and fruitful relationship existing
                            between the United States and New Zealand. I have therefore asked Vice
                            President <persName corresp="#p_MWF_1">Mondale</persName> to visit
                            Wellington and to carry forward on my behalf the discussions we had with
                            you and your colleagues in Washington this past November.<note n="2" xml:id="d251fn2">See <ref target="#d248">Documents 248</ref> and
                                    <ref target="#d249">249</ref>.</note> I found your visit here at
                            that time extremely useful not only in furthering our bilateral ties but
                            in deepening my understanding of the cooperative steps our two countries
                            can take in the Pacific Basin and elsewhere.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President, who, as you know, has been playing a key role in
                            foreign policy, is looking forward to discussing a wide range of
                            political, economic, and trade issues. He will also be presenting our
                            thoughts on such key problems as food and energy, issues to which your
                            Government, I know has been devoting close attention.</p>
                        <p>I do hope to be able to make a trip to New Zealand at some time in the
                            future. In the meantime, I will be looking forward with great interest
                            to hearing the Vice President’s report of his visit.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"><hi rend="strong">Jimmy
                                    Carter</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>