<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-08-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="297" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d297">
                        <head>297. Memorandum From the Director of the Joint Staff of the Joint
                            Chiefs of Staff (Hannifin) to Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Brown</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d297fn1">Source: Washington National Records Center, RG 330,
                                    <gloss target="#t_OSD_1">OSD</gloss> Files: FRC 330–80–0017, 78,
                                Untitled. Secret. Copies were sent to the Directors of <gloss target="#t_DCA_1">DCA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_DIA_1">DIA</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <idno type="document-identifier">JCSM–348–77</idno></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-08-19">August 19, 1977</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Reductions in <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> Philippine
                                Military Presence (S)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>1. (S) Reference a memorandum by the Deputy Secretary of Defense, 27
                            April 1977,<note n="2" xml:id="d297fn2">Not found.</note> subject as
                            above, which requested that the Joint Chiefs of Staff review plans<note n="3" xml:id="d297fn3">(1) Memorandum by the Secretary of the Navy,
                                13 June 1977, “Reductions in Our Philippine Military Presence
                                (S)—INFORMATION MEMORANDUM.” (2) Memorandum by the Secretary of the
                                Air Force, 1 July 1977, “Reductions in our Philippine Military
                                Presence—INFORMATION MEMORANDUM (U).” [Footnote in the
                                original.]</note> of the Secretary of the Navy and Secretary of the
                            Air Force concerning reductions in <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                            military presence in the Philippines for their impact on the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> military posture in the Pacific.</p>
                        <p>2. (S) The <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> Naval Base complex at Subic
                            Bay and the airbase at <persName corresp="#p_CRC_1">Clark</persName> are
                            essential for support of the <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC_1">CINCPAC</gloss> mission in the Western Pacific and Indian Ocean.
                            These bases, and the forces they support, are very important elements of
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> forward strategy and serve as
                            visible reminders to <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> allies of <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> national commitment.</p>
                        <p>3. (S) Implementation of the personnel reduction plans provided by the
                            Secretary of the Navy would have a severe impact on <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> naval capabilities in the Pacific.
                            Forward bases permit more efficient operations and a higher level of
                            operations with the given level of mobile logistic support. A 10-percent
                            reduction would cause substantial loss in the capability to maintain
                            Seventh Fleet readiness, responsiveness, and flexibility. A 30-percent
                            reduction, with contracting alternatives, would degrade the support
                            capabilities at Subic Bay to the point where expansion at other bases in
                            the Western Pacific would be necessary. Appendix A<note n="4" xml:id="d297fn4">Appendix A, an undated paper entitled “Impact of
                                Personnel Reductions at Subic Naval Base/Cubi Point,” is attached
                                but not printed.</note> contains further details of the impact on
                            the Navy of the reduction plan provided by the Secretary of the
                            Navy.</p>
                        <p>4. (S) The Secretary of the Air Force plans identify management
                            initiatives already programmed equating to an approximate 10-percent cut
                            in Air Force presence. Other relocation actions which would not <pb facs="1012" n="983" xml:id="pg_983"/> reduce the Air Force’s combat
                            capabilities and support to other Services in the Western Pacific would
                            enable the Air Force to make additional personnel reductions of
                            approximately 20 percent. These actions, however, would increase <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> presence in the <gloss target="#t_ROK_1">ROK</gloss> and Japan. Further details on the impact of Air Force
                            personnel reductions and relocation are contained in Appendix B.<note n="5" xml:id="d297fn5">Appendix B, an undated paper entitled “Impact
                                of Personnel Reductions/Relocations at <persName corresp="#p_CRC_1">Clark</persName> Air Base,” is attached but not
                            printed.</note></p>
                        <p>5. (S) The Navy and the Air Force have already completed transfer of
                            those functions and operations which can be performed by the Philippines
                            without having a detrimental effect on <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> operations and base negotiations. Except in a few
                            limited instances, additional contracting is neither feasible nor
                            desirable because of strike potential, reduced flexibility, operational
                            difficulties, and possible impact on the Military Bases Agreement
                            negotiations (see Appendix C).<note n="6" xml:id="d297fn6">Not
                                attached.</note></p>
                        <p>6. (S) It is important that any reduction in <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> presence in the Philippines be considered in the context
                            of its potential effect on future <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-Philippine base negotiations. Further, any reductions should
                            be considered in conjunction with other ongoing personnel/facility
                            reductions elsewhere in Asia, particularly since the nearly simultaneous
                            and appreciable reductions in the <gloss target="#t_ROK_1">ROK</gloss>,
                            Taiwan, and the Philippines would probably have a distinct, negative
                            effect on Asian perceptions of <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                            resolve throughout the region. In this regard, any relocation and
                            reduction of major <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> headquarters at
                            this time could have a particularly unfavorable impact. Accordingly, a
                            decision on relocation of Headquarters, 13th Air Force, should be
                            deferred until its impact on <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-Philippine base negotiations and, in conjunction with other
                            ongoing reductions, its effect on perception of <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> resolve and staying power in the region can be
                            reassessed.</p>
                        <p>For the Joint Chiefs of Staff:</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Patrick J. Hannifin</hi></persName>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vice Admiral, USN <lb/> Director, Joint Staff</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>