<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>300. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Indonesia, the
                    White House, Department of Defense, and Commander in Chief, Pacific</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d300</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">300</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-09-22T10:44:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-09-22T10:44:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recHKBrLbO74DsZpb" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136190"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Torture</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-09-22T10:44:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-09-22T10:44:00-05:00" n="300"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d300">
                <head>300. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Indonesia, the
                    White House, Department of Defense, and Commander in Chief, Pacific<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d300fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Cables File, Far East, Box 11, 9–11/77.
                        Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Printed from
                        the copy received in the White House Situation Room.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-09-22T15:44:00+00:00">September 22, 1977, 1544Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>227946. Military addee handle as Specat Exclusive, Fol tel sent action SecState
                    from Manila dtd 22 Sep 1977 DTG Z221239Z.</p>
                <p>Qte White House for Brzezinski and <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1"
                        >Armacost</persName>, Jakarta for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1"
                        >Newsom</persName>, <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss>/<gloss
                        target="#t_ISA_1">ISA</gloss> for <persName corresp="#p_AMI_1"
                        >Abramowitz</persName> Eyes Only and <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC_1"
                        >CINCPAC</gloss> for Admiral Weisner Eyes Only. Secret Manila 15019. <gloss
                        target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. For the Secretary from <persName
                        corresp="#p_HRC_1">Holbrooke</persName>. Please pass to Jakarta for
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1">Newsom</persName> only. Please pass to
                        <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1">Armacost</persName>/<gloss target="#t_NSC_1"
                        >NSC</gloss>; <persName corresp="#p_AMI_1">Abramowitz</persName>/<gloss
                        target="#t_ISA_1">ISA</gloss>; <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC_1">CINCPAC</gloss>
                    for Weisner. Subject: <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1"
                        >Holbrooke</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName>
                    Meeting.</p>
                <p>1. In six hours of discussions today with <persName corresp="#p_MF_1"
                        >Marcos</persName> we covered wide range of issues, reached few conclusions.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> indicated considerable
                    flexibility on the timing of the conclusion of any agreements on the bases,
                    although he seemed to prefer the idea of a resumption of the negotiations this
                    year. He says he needs to finish the base issue before “normalization”. That is,
                    before he holds elections. This would be sometime next year. Other hand, he
                    questioned whether we should begin negotiations this year if congressional
                    calendar precludes consideration until 1978. I explained our intention to
                    consult closely with Congress and pointed out that content of agreement would
                    affect timing.</p>
                <p>2. He has not yet committed himself in any way on the question of size and
                    composition of compensation package. Although we stated clearly that last year’s
                    offer would be hard to match, I identified compensation package as most
                    important item from <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> point of view. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> focused on the twin issues of
                    sovereignty and legal jurisdiction over American servicemen under certain
                    circumstances. I stressed that we had already accepted concept of Philippine
                    sovereignty but that we had to retain for ourselves the right to determine
                    whether or not an American serviceman alleged to have committed a crime was on
                    official status or not—a key factor in Philippine eyes.</p>
                <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> and Defense Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_EJP_1">Enrile</persName> stressed theme that under the War
                    Powers Act,<note n="2" xml:id="d300fn2">See <ref target="#d296fn4">footnote 4,
                            Document 296</ref>.</note> the value of American treaty commitment was
                    either sharply reduced or eliminated. I said that this was simply not <pb
                        facs="1020" n="991" xml:id="pg_991"/> the case, and that the War Powers Act
                    did not affect the validity of the treaty.</p>
                <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> reacted with predictable anger
                    at my raising of human rights issue, saying that he was fully committed to human
                    rights and that, as a result of my raising the issue again, he was wondering if
                    there was not a serious misunderstanding even in the State Department of all
                    that he had done to promote human rights in the Philippines. I said that I did
                    not come to Manila to tell him how to run his country, but that he must
                    understand that the human rights situation would be an important ingredient in
                    the American reaction to any package for the bases when submitted to Congress.
                    In <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName>’ eyes, the only possible
                    victims of any torture or unfair confinement have been Communists, and he
                    professes not to know what all the shouting is about. Suggested <gloss
                        target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> is being “blackmailed” by subversive elements
                    appealing for external sympathy. <persName corresp="#p_EJP_1">Enrile</persName>
                    said that it was clear that the Americans believed anything negative that
                    opponents of the regime told us, while we did not believe them. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> at one point termed questioning <gloss
                        target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> compliance “offensive,” and questioned the
                    very value of trying to find a basis for new agreements at this time if there
                    was such misunderstanding in the U.S. but later backed off this posture.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> concluded that <gloss
                        target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> still has major human rights PR requirement in
                    U.S.</p>
                <p>5. We will conclude tomorrow. We did not expect any specific agreements to come
                    out of today’s session, and none did. But with the notable and deliberate
                    exception of compensation, we did hear their preliminary views on the entire
                    range of issues that might come up between us during a negotiation, and we got a
                    better sense of what <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> wants. A
                    recurrent theme was the lack of satisfaction with the existing consultative
                    arrangements regarding our defense relationship. This was included in <persName
                        corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName>’ concerns about: the perceived
                    vulnerability of the Philippines to attack due to our presence [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>], the need for a
                    self-reliant defense posture, and characterization of the <gloss
                        target="#t_MDT_1">MDT</gloss> as “useless” in resolving operational
                    issues.</p>
                <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> clearly expressed preference for
                    informal discussions at a “political level” to resolve policy issues first,
                    rather than a resumption of the unwieldy and unproductive formal talks. I agree
                    with this preference, and believe that <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1">Dave
                        Newsom</persName> will be the appropriate person to handle these. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> also showed a pronounced interest in
                    moving in <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss>-Embassy channel to settle several
                    secondary issues immediately. This I believe would be helpful in order to remove
                    some highly visible irritants from the situation, as long as it can be done in
                    full cooperation with our military. It was interesting to note that his own
                    Cabinet members were clearly more resistant than he was to this approach.</p>
                <p>7. The mood and tone of the meetings was extremely friendly, except during the
                    human rights discussion. <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> has
                    clearly lowered <pb facs="1021" n="992" xml:id="pg_992"/> his sights from what
                    they were a year ago, and wants to make a deal more than he did in the past. In
                    this sense our strategy over last eight months has had some beneficial
                    effects.</p>
                <p>8. In reference to the idea of inviting <persName corresp="#p_RCF_1"
                        >Romulo</persName> to meet with the President during <gloss
                        target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss>, I think that to make such an invitation
                    tomorrow would be premature.</p>
                <p>9. I advised <persName corresp="#p_MF_1">Marcos</persName> of U.S. decision to
                    make available to <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> an additional $30 million
                        <gloss target="#t_FMS_1">FMS</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss>
                    77 program as one-time exception and made all the points agreed to in our
                    discussions prior to departure. Stull Unqte</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Vance</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
