<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>32. Paper Prepared in the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-11-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="association-of-southeast-asian-nations" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="association-of-southeast-asian-nations">ASEAN</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-11-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="32"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                <head>32. Paper Prepared in the Department of State<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d32fn1">Source: Department of State, Vietnam General Files for 1978,
                        Lot 80D307, Box 6590, Briefing Papers (General) 1978. Secret. Drafted by
                        Thomas P. Hamilton (<gloss target="#t_INRREA_1">INR/REA</gloss>/SA).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-11-16">November 16, 1978</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">VIETNAM-KAMPUCHEA BORDER CONFLICT</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Background</p>
                <p>When Phnom Penh fell to the communists in 1975 the new Kampuchean leaders ordered
                    Vietnamese troops based in northeastern Kampuchea out of the country. By June of
                    that year the two nations were clashing over disputed border claims and offshore
                    islands. Periodic clashes continued in 1976 and 1977.</p>
                <p>In December 1977 major fighting developed in the Parrot’s Beak, a border area
                    only 30 kilometers from Ho Chi Minh City. This was followed by a new surge of
                    fighting on December 31 in the same area. Although the combatants pulled back
                    from their furthest advances by mid-January, fierce fighting involving
                    artillery, air strikes, and helicopter gun ships broke out again in June. It has
                    continued since and armed clashes and casualties occur regularly on both sides
                    of the border.</p>
                <pb facs="0136" n="107" xml:id="pg_107"/>
                <p>The outbreak of serious fighting between Hanoi and Phnom Penh in December 1977
                    helped to catalyze the falling out between Hanoi and Peking and brought about
                    increased Chinese military assistance to Kampuchea and greater tensions along
                    the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_SRV_1">SRV</gloss>
                    border. Sino-Vietnamese tensions have increased during October and November with
                    almost daily charges by Hanoi of Chinese encroachment on Vietnamese territory.
                    Hanoi’s most recent spate of accusations cannot be confirmed but they are
                    symptomatic of escalating tensions between China and Vietnam as a result of the
                    border conflict between Hanoi and Phnom Penh.</p>
                <p>The international implications of the dispute took on added significance in early
                    November with the conclusion of a Soviet-Vietnamese Treaty of Friendship and
                    Cooperation, followed immediately by a hastily arranged visit of a high-level
                    Chinese delegation to Phnom Penh. Vietnam, aware of the increased political
                    complexity of the dispute, will carefully calculate its future moves.
                    Nevertheless, the Vietnamese are likely to take strong military action in the
                    current dry season.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Military Build Up</p>
                <p>While we do not have full and precise information concerning the military
                    situation in the Vietnam-Kampuchea border area, refugee reports and other
                    sources, strongly suggesting the likelihood of increased fighting include:</p>
                <p>—Armed clashes on both sides of the border have continued for well over a year
                    with both sides taking heavy casualties. Reports of clashes dropped off somewhat
                    in August and September, but picked up considerably in October and the first two
                    weeks of November.</p>
                <p>—In June and July 1978 the Vietnamese sharply escalated the level of fighting by
                    conducting numerous air strikes some up to forty kilometers inside Kampuchean
                    territory. During this period the Vietnamese apparently took and held the towns
                    of Snoul and Mimot in eastern Cambodia. In recent weeks, the Vietnamese have
                    moved aircraft from central Vietnam to bases closer to the major troop
                    concentrations along the border.</p>
                <p>—The prepositioning of supplies and equipment along with movement of additional
                    troops to the border by both sides has continued throughout the summer and fall.
                    We now estimate that Kampuchea has some 60,000 troops (14 understrength
                    divisions) in place, while the Vietnamese have at least ten divisions totaling
                    over 100,000 troops.</p>
                <p>—Military recruitment of Vietnamese and Kampuchean youth has been stepped up
                    including females 18–25 years of age. (Monthly draft calls are reportedly at
                    their highest in years.)</p>
                <p>—Reports from visitors to the border area indicate the Vietnamese and Kampucheans
                    now regularly exchange artillery fire into each oth<pb facs="0137" n="108"
                        xml:id="pg_108"/>er’s territory. Kampuchean forces are reportedly employing
                    130 mm guns.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Current Military Situation</p>
                <p>Battlefield activity has increased considerably during October and early
                    November. Kampuchea has launched a number of attacks in the central highlands
                    region of Vietnam in an apparent effort to keep Vietnamese forces off balance
                    and forestall Vietnam’s offensive. Kampuchean units planted mines, destroyed
                    roads, and shelled Vietnamese forces in border areas along route 19 during the
                    month. They have also initiated attacks further south in the Duc Minh area
                    penetrating some ten kilometers into Vietnamese territory.</p>
                <p>In mid-October Kampuchean forces were instructed to try to take advantage of
                    Vietnamese weaknesses on all fronts stemming from disorganization caused by
                    heavy flooding. Interestingly, several sources indicate that the Vietnamese plan
                    to use a Kampuchean attack as an excuse to launch “counterattacks” in
                    retaliation. Presumably an offensive in the guise of a “counterattack” would be
                    calculated by the Vietnamese to be less alarming to neighboring <gloss
                        target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss> countries.</p>
                <p>The most intense fighting over the past month has been in the Parrot’s Beak
                    portion of Kampuchea and adjoining portions of Vietnam’s Southwestern Tay Ninh
                    province. Vietnam claimed in early October that forces from two Kampuchean
                    divisions were defeated near Ben Cau. During the first part of October the
                    Vietnamese attacks along route one inside Kampuchea were supported by
                    airstrikes.</p>
                <p>Fighting in the Mekong Delta area has been restricted by flooding for much of the
                    summer and early fall but gradually increased during late October. Hanoi claimed
                    to have killed or wounded 400 Kampucheans in clashes along and near the Mekong
                    in mid-October. Late last month the Kampucheans apparently again began shelling
                    Vietnamese border towns provoking the first Vietnamese airstrikes in the Delta
                    in over two months.</p>
                <p>In addition to military preparations, recent Vietnamese propaganda has
                    increasingly referred to uprisings in Kampuchea led by insurgents opposed to the
                        <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName> regime. We have no evidence
                    to support such wide scale activity, but reports of isolated incidents involving
                    insurgents have increased. Hanoi is known to be training Khmer insurgents who
                    will presumably be reinserted into Kampuchea in connection with stepped up
                    military efforts by Vietnamese forces in the border area.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Vietnam-China</p>
                <p>Since mid-October Hanoi has repeatedly charged that Peking has sent troops to
                    violate Vietnamese territory. Hanoi claims that major <pb facs="0138" n="109"
                        xml:id="pg_109"/> incidents occurred on October 13 and November 1. These
                    accusations which include charges of “1000” Chinese troops entering Vietnamese
                    territory are almost certainly exaggerated and were probably designed to set the
                    stage for the November 3 Soviet-Vietnamese Friendship treaty and help Hanoi
                    project the image of a smaller country forced to prepare for the contingency of
                    a Chinese attack. Nevertheless, as the Vietnamese continue to prepare for an
                    offensive in Kampuchea the risks of more serious incidents on the
                    Sino-Vietnamese border increase. Peking has indicated on numerous occasions that
                    it will send material support to Phnom Penh but does not intend to send troops
                    to bail out the <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName> regime. For this
                    reason China may feel compelled to initiate incidents along the Sino-Vietnamese
                    border in order to warn Hanoi against precipitous action against Kampuchea.
                    Despite some minor skirmishes by border guards, until recently neither Hanoi nor
                    Peking had moved main force units to the border area. This week however, Hanoi
                    reportedly has moved elements of a division formerly engaged in economic tasks
                    in central Vietnam to positions close to the border. In addition Vietnam has
                    reportedly fortified air defense positions near the China border further
                    demonstrating its concern over Peking’s intentions.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
