<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-21T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-21T17:00:00-05:00" n="83" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                        <head>83. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d83fn1">Source: Washington National Records Center, RG 330,
                                    <gloss target="#t_OSD_1">OSD</gloss> Files: FRC 330–82–0217, Box
                                4, C, 1980. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>.
                                Drafted by Lyne on February 22. The meeting took place in the
                                Sheraton Carlton Hotel. “<gloss target="#t_SecDef_1">SECDEF</gloss>
                                has seen” is stamped at the top of the page. A notation in an
                                unknown hand in the top right-hand corner of the page reads,
                                    “<persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold Brown</persName> eyes only,”
                                and <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Brown</persName> wrote, “2/27 <gloss target="#t_HB_1">HB</gloss>.” An unknown hand wrote adjacent to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Brown</persName>’s notation, “Show
                                this to <persName corresp="#p_PN_1">Nick
                            Platt</persName>.”</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-02-21T17:00:00-05:00">February 21, 1980, 5
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Situation in Kampuchea</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Prince <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Norodom
                                Sihanouk</persName></item>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Richard Holbrooke</persName>,
                                Assistant Secretary of State for <gloss target="#t_EA_1">EA</gloss></item>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_NJD_1">John D. Negroponte</persName>, Deputy
                                Assistant Secretary, <gloss target="#t_EA_1">EA</gloss></item>
                            <item>Stephen R. Lyne, Director, <gloss target="#t_EAVLC_1">EA/VLC</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Thank you for your warm
                            generous hospitality.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: I want to tell you
                            that it is at the personal instructions of Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Please convey to him my
                            personal gratitude and salutations.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: The Secretary and I
                            believe you are a great historic figure who has played an important role
                            in the past and has an important role to play in the present. He wanted
                            to demonstrate his regard for you.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I am deeply grateful and
                            honored to be considered a friend of the U.S. Please also transmit my
                            very affectionate salutations to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MMJM_1">Mansfield</persName>.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Last week I was in the
                            refugee camps along the Thai-Kampuchean border. I asked the people about
                            the future of Cambodia. I asked them: What about <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng Samrin</persName>? Everyone talked about Prince <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName>. All of them loved you; all of
                            them remembered you.<note n="2" xml:id="d83fn2"><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName> lived in exile following
                                the <persName corresp="#p_LN_1">Lon Nol</persName> coup in 1970.
                                After the Khmer Rouge takeover in 1975, <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName> returned to Kampuchea, where he lived under
                                house arrest. <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName> was
                                released in January 1979 and disassociated himself from the Khmer
                                Rouge.</note> They wanted to know where you were. They did not know
                            you were in Europe. You need to let your people know where you are.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I have many contacts
                            with my supporters along the frontier. Delegates come to me from my
                            sympathizers. I have sent them <pb facs="0313" n="284" xml:id="pg_284"/>
                            messages and tape recordings. In many of the Thai refugee camps and in
                            parts of Cambodia they have received my messages. I do not know why the
                            others don’t know where I am.</p>
                        <p>I have to explain that I have been unable to go to Cambodia despite my
                            great desire. I cannot achieve my great dream. The government of
                            Thailand will not let me go. I cannot reach them because of the
                            government of Thailand. I am anxious to meet with my people. I want to
                            go visit them.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: I am disappointed that
                            you did not go to Singapore. I know your explanation. We agree with you
                            that there can be no support for <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol
                                Pot</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_IS_1">Ieng Sary</persName>.
                            I would have thought that it would have been to your advantage to go to
                            Singapore to talk with <persName corresp="#p_LKY_1">Lee Kuan
                                Yew</persName> and to discuss the issues directly. It would have
                            been a way to improve relations between you and the Thai. Let us hope
                            that you can go to Singapore.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Maybe I can go in June.
                            I have to go to <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il Sung</persName>’s
                            birthday and he wants me to stay for one to two months after that. I
                            can’t travel until after that. I will go to Australia, and I can stop in
                            Singapore.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: May I ask you some
                            things about <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il Sung</persName>? You
                            know him, and we do not. What does <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il
                                Sung</persName> think about the Soviet-Chinese rivalry?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: He is clearly hostile to
                            the Soviet Union. He is very clearly sympathetic to China. He condemns
                            Vietnam and he criticizes the invasion of Kampuchea by Vietnam.
                            Officially he does not dare let the world and the Soviet Union know his
                            views. With me he made his position clear. He condemns Vietnam. He
                            condemns the Soviet Union. He likes China. He is very independent
                            vis-a-vis China but he likes the Chinese.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: What does he think
                            about the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan?<note n="3" xml:id="d83fn3">The
                                Soviet invasion of Afghanistan began on December 24, 1979. See <ref target="frus1977-80v06#d244"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. VI, Soviet Union, Documents
                                    244</ref>–<ref target="frus1977-80v06#d246">246</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I left before the
                            invasion. I am sure he must be very angry toward the Soviet Union. He
                            used to criticize the Soviet Union and very violently condemn
                            Vietnam.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: What do you think his
                            objectives are regarding South Korea? You know he has just sent letters
                            to individuals in the government in South Korea using their government
                            titles. This is a first.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: He may hide his ideas
                            and his thinking from me. It seems to me, however, that he was sincere
                            when he assured me that <pb facs="0314" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/> he
                            didn’t want any war, that he wanted South Korea to remain non-communist
                            if that is what the people of South Korea wanted. He wanted the South
                            and the North united as equal states in a federation which he called
                            Koryo.</p>
                        <p>He pointed out he does not want any war. I believe he is sincere. He has
                            done a lot for the development of his country; he has built schools,
                            hospitals, cultural centers, and other facilities for his people and
                            youth. This shows he does not want war. For himself he has built
                            beautiful palaces in the mountains and at sea resorts. He has many
                            luxury houses. He likes expensive cars, Mercedes, Lincolns. I think that
                            since he likes luxuries so much he will not wage war.</p>
                        <p>He is a lot like <persName corresp="#p_TJB_1">Tito</persName>. There are
                            three “imperial communist” heads of state: <persName corresp="#p_TJB_1">Tito</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il Sung</persName>. They are very
                            imperialistic; very luxurious; they do not want war. They would lose
                            their imperial style of life.</p>
                        <p>On the question of reunification of Korea. I remember that it is true
                            that North Vietnam said it would accept a non-communist South Vietnam if
                            that is what the people wanted. In fact North Vietnam communized South
                            Vietnam without delay. I cannot give you any guarantee about <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il Sung</persName>’s intentions toward South
                            Korea. He is intelligent. He realizes he can’t fight a war. If he
                            achieves his dream of a federation he may respect South Korea as a
                            nationalist state for many years. He knows he cannot fight against you,
                            the U.S. He knows he cannot rely on the Soviet Union. He does not want
                            to rely on the Chinese.</p>
                        <p>That is <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il Sung</persName>. I know him
                            very well. He is not in good health. He has a growth on his neck which
                            increases in size. It is very visible. It may be cancerous. He is the
                            guarantor of stability and peace in North Korea, and his people fear
                            that he may not have much life left. I guarantee you that if he lives he
                            will not fight a war.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: What is his attitude
                            toward the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName>?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: He condemns them but
                            allows them to have an embassy in Pyongyang.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Does he pressure you
                            to form a united front with <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol
                                Pot</persName>, as China does?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: China pressures me all
                            the time. <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il Sung</persName> never
                            pressures me. That is one reason I went to Pyongyang. He tells me: I
                            support you. He says I believe you should cooperate with the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss>, but I follow and support you. That is
                            all he says.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Has this issue
                            strained relations between China and North Korea?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il Sung</persName> said that North Korea and
                            China will remain good friends even if they do not share the same
                            opinions about <pb facs="0315" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/> Cambodia. He
                            said they have decided not to speak about it. He said North
                            Korean-Chinese relations are based on bilateral issues and they put the
                            others aside.</p>
                        <p>In Pyongyang the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss> has tried to contact
                            me through the Romanians and the Swedes but not the North Koreans. The
                            Romanians support the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss>. The Khmer
                            Rouge asked the Swedes to arrange a meeting for them with me. I rejected
                            this appointment with the Swedish Chargé to meet the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss>. He has since refrained from pushing
                            this idea. I have made it clear to him that when I meet with him the
                            condition is that we will not discuss the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss>. Each time I saw the Romanians they tried to press me on
                            behalf of President <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> to
                            accept the post of president of the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss>.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: I want to assure you
                            that we are totally opposed to the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss>,
                            to <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName>, to <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Khieu Samphan</persName>, to <persName corresp="#p_IS_1">Ieng Sary</persName>. We see no differences among
                            them. Do you agree?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Yes. Fully. <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Khieu Samphan</persName> is not less cruel. He is
                            the thinker, <hi rend="italic">le penseur</hi>, of the team. He said
                            that to create a revolutionary society one must physically liquidate the
                            people.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: I want to be sure that
                            you understand our vote for the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss> at
                            the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>.<note n="4" xml:id="d83fn4">See
                                    <ref target="#d60fn4">footnote 4, Document 60</ref>.</note> We
                            believed that it was the best tactical way to avoid legitimitizing the
                            Vietnamese takeover. <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>, our
                            European allies, and other non-aligned countries all agreed. When we
                            voted we stressed that we opposed all that <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName> stood for and would not recognize or help him.
                            Mr. Burchett says in a recent article in THE NATION<note n="5" xml:id="d83fn5">Not further identified.</note> that Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_WLF_1">Woodcock</persName> urged you to join
                            the Khmer Rouge.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: No. He did not ask me to
                            join the Khmer Rouge. He did explain that the Khmer Rouge were the only
                            armed force that could fight the Vietnamese in Kampuchea. He did not
                            urge me to join the Khmer Rouge.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: This is a simple
                            statement of fact. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WLF_1">Woodcock</persName> did not mean that we supported the Khmer Rouge
                            or that we wanted you to support them. Burchett must have misrepresented
                            what you said.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Mr. Burchett is not
                            honest. He did not quote me accurately. He misquoted me for the benefit
                            of the Vietnamese and the Soviets, he is one of their sympathizers.</p>
                        <pb facs="0316" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: I hope you will
                            clarify this in your interviews in the United States. I hope you will
                            clarify that we have never pressured you to join the Khmer Rouge.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I never said it.
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WLF_1">Woodcock</persName> never said
                            anything like that. The thing he did say was that on the battlefield
                            only the Khmer Rouge were capable of resisting the Vietnamese.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: That’s a fact at this
                            time.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: That’s a fact.</p>
                        <p>I want to let the world know I have a large army. I have officers in
                            France and the United States who have been trained in French and
                            American schools. They are ready to serve me. From Thailand and
                            Kampuchea I have received many letters from young Cambodians who are
                            ready to serve under me in a national army to fight for the liberation
                            of Kampuchea. But China does not want me to fight unless I am with the
                            Khmer Rouge. Thailand does not allow me to enter Cambodia through
                            Thailand. I met with your Embassy officers in Paris. I presented to them
                            an expose of my position and of my army.<note n="6" xml:id="d83fn6"><persName corresp="#p_ORB_1">Oakley</persName> met with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName> in Paris on
                                December 13, 1979. Telegram 39040 from Paris, December 13,
                                transmitted a memorandum of conversation of the discussion.
                                (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D790573–0911)</note> I beg your help to persuade Thailand to give me
                            sympathy and cooperation and to help me struggle for the national
                            liberation of Cambodia. Also I ask you to persuade China to help me. We
                            have many men. We have no weapons and no arms. King <persName corresp="#p_HSN_1">Hassan</persName> of Morocco told me: You will
                            not be successful in your political objectives to liberate your country,
                            to call an international conference, and to give your people the right
                            to determine their own future unless you have an army, unless you lead
                            an army to fight the Vietnamese and to weaken the government of
                                <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng Samrin</persName>. He said: You
                            must return to let the world know clearly that you are a valid
                            alternative to <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng Samrin</persName> and
                            the Khmer Rouge. The world must have a reason to support you and to
                            recognize you as the leader of Cambodia. You must fight on the
                            battlefield.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: There are some things
                            I don’t completely understand. The Chinese saved your life and brought
                            you out of Phnom Penh in 1979. You came to New York. We thought you were
                            going to stay here or in France. Then you had dinner with <persName corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName> Tsiao Ping. The next morning you
                            had breakfast with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ORB_1">Oakley</persName>
                            and you told him that you were going back to China.<note n="7" xml:id="d83fn7"><persName corresp="#p_ORB_1">Oakley</persName> met
                                with <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName> on February 1,
                                1979. Telegram 30886 to Tokyo and Beijing, February 5, reported on
                                the meeting. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D790055–1143)</note> Why?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Because China could not
                            let me go to Paris to fight the <gloss target="#t_DK_1">DK</gloss> in
                            the political field. I had promised <persName corresp="#p_MT_1">Mao Tse
                                Tung</persName> and Chou <pb facs="0317" n="288" xml:id="pg_288"/>
                            En Lai that if I was ever not in Cambodia, I would stay in China.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName> reminded me of my
                            promises. I made it clear that I would go to China only if <persName corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName> promised not to try to persuade me
                            to join the Khmer Rouge.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Is there any
                            difference between Chou En Lai and <persName corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName>?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: During the 1970–1975 war
                            the situation in Cambodia was different than it is now. I cannot say
                            whether if Chou En Lai were alive today he would behave differently than
                                <persName corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName> because the situation is
                            different.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: In regard to Thailand,
                            what is the problem between you? Are the Thai feelings based on the
                            difficulties between your two countries in the 1950s and 1960s. Your
                            problems with Thailand seriously limit your future, and we should
                            discuss them frankly to see what can be done.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: The key issue is Preah
                                Vihear.<note n="8" xml:id="d83fn8">See <ref target="#d60fn5">footnote 5, Document 60</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: You won. Dean Acheson
                            was your lawyer. You had the best lawyer in the U.S.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: We had the best lawyer
                            in the world. And we did win. But the Thai have never pardoned us. Also
                            now, Thailand, with China, protects the Khmer Rouge and <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName>. I am totally against the
                            Khmer Rouge. <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> is not with
                            me. The Thai are well aware that I cannot accept that part of Cambodia
                            become a protectorate of Thailand. Thailand, like Vietnam, wants to
                            swallow Cambodia and wants to establish at least a part of Cambodia as a
                            protectorate.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NJD_1">NEGROPONTE</persName>: You mentioned
                                <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> in the same way as
                            the Khmer Rouge. What are your feelings about <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName>?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> and his group, Dien Del, are
                            not sympathetic to me. They are very ambitious. They want to gain power.
                            They want to be the leaders of the people. They tell the people that
                                <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName> does not want to
                            serve the people, that he wants to lead the good life in Korea and
                            France. <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> does not like
                            me. He tries to discredit me and work against me with my people.</p>
                        <p>I want my people to be united, not disunited. I am ready to be friends
                            with all Khmer. Ninety per cent of the Cambodians here in the United
                            States fought against me. Now we are friends. <hi rend="italic">My duty
                                is not to be a leader of my own group but to represent the
                                nation</hi>. I want to unite not divide the nation. I am aware we
                            are weak. Each day we are weaker and weaker. We cannot have disunity. As
                            chairman of the Federation of all patriotic groups I cannot beg
                                <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> to accept me as his
                            servant. <pb facs="0318" n="289" xml:id="pg_289"/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> and his group should
                            join our Confederation. I should not join <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName>; he should join me.</p>
                        <p>I am not here for your support for me. I have been invited by my
                            compatriots. You said you wanted to see me. I have no personal
                            ambitions. I am happy in Korea. I am unhappy when I see my people facing
                            misery. I don’t seek help from foreign countries for myself. I don’t
                            plan to be the leader of my nation. Once the Cambodian people are
                            liberated, they can elect their leaders. Cambodia and the Cambodian
                            people have the right to determine their own future.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Yes, we agree, but how
                            do we get there? How do we get the Vietnamese to agree to a neutral
                            non-aligned Cambodia?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: King <persName corresp="#p_HSN_1">Hassan</persName> said I cannot achieve this goal
                            of liberation of Cambodia by peaceful means. He said: You must go to the
                            battlefield. How can I go if no one helps?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Do you want to go to
                            fight in order to drive out the Vietnamese or to force the Vietnamese to
                            negotiate?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: We cannot defeat the
                            invincible army of Vietnam. We want to give credibility to our efforts
                            to liberate our country. If I oppose <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng
                                Samrin</persName>, Vietnam will always be weak psychologically and
                            politically in Cambodia.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Do you believe the
                            Vietnamese would accept a political solution involving your return to
                            Cambodia?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Vietnam says it is in
                            Cambodia to protect the Cambodian people from the genocidal policies of
                                <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_IS_1">Ieng Sary</persName>. Therefore, to support
                                <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_IS_1">Ieng Sary</persName> is to strengthen the
                            Vietnamese pretext for being in Cambodia as a protector of the Cambodian
                            people against the Khmer Rouge. If I lead a movement of liberation
                            without the Khmer Rouge, the Vietnamese will no longer have a pretext to
                            remain.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: How do you propose to
                            fight the Vietnamese who have 200,000 troops and twenty divisions in
                            Cambodia who are destroying the country? When I was in the border camps
                            I asked: Who was worse, <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName>
                            or <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng Samrin</persName>? The Cambodians
                            said they were equally bad; <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol
                                Pot</persName> killed us and <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng
                                Samrin</persName> is starving us.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: According to <persName corresp="#p_MT_1">Mao Tse Tung</persName> if one cannot get the
                            support of the people, one can never win. The Vietnamese 200,000 troops
                            do not have the support of the people. You see that the Khmer Rouge are
                            still fighting and cannot be crushed. <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son
                                Sann</persName> is still alive. My own army would be much bigger
                            than theirs.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NJD_1">NEGROPONTE</persName>: Back to an earlier
                            question, with some armed resistance would you be willing to enter into
                            negotiations?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Yes. Also we would
                            continue to fight.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Will the Vietnamese
                            agree to a political settlement which will take their troops out and
                            yours back in?</p>
                        <pb facs="0319" n="290" xml:id="pg_290"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: What would happen would
                            be that <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng Samrin</persName> would
                            collapse internally and internationally.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng Samrin</persName> doesn’t exist as an
                            important factor. He is the creation of 200,000 Vietnamese troops.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: If my proposal is not
                            interesting, how can you and the Chinese believe that the Khmer Rouge
                            and <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> will be able to get
                            back Kampuchea? You will simply be creating further Thai instability. We
                            have to fight to weaken <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng
                                Samrin</persName> and to harm the Vietnamese. If we do nothing, if
                            we accept the Vietnamese, we will have no answer to recovering Cambodia.
                            We will remain under Vietnamese colonialism. We will have to accept the
                                <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> as in Afghanistan.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: I agree with your view
                            that Vietnam is the cause of the problem and we must get them out of
                            Cambodia. We see three problems: One is the refusal of many Khmer Serei
                            elements to work with you.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Many of the Khmer Serei
                            groups are pro-<persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName>. That is
                            why the Thai will not give them humanitarian relief.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: The second is the
                            attitude of the Thai government toward you. You have explained this. The
                            third is the attitude of the Chinese who want to create a united front
                            between you and the Khmer Rouge.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: This is impossible.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: We have to concern
                            ourselves with your relations with <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son
                                Sann</persName> and others.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> only.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NJD_1">NEGROPONTE</persName>: You said if the Khmer
                            Rouge came to join your federation you would not accept them. If
                                <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> came to join your
                            federation, would you accept him?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Yes. There is no reason
                            to refuse. But my compatriots in France and the U.S. tell me they will
                            abandon me if I accept the Khmer Rouge.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: We understand and
                            share your view about the Khmer Rouge. The difficulties between you and
                                <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> are crucial. It is
                            important to resolve the differences. The public appearance of
                            disagreement is very damaging. The Khmer Serei groups are fighting each
                            other at the refugee camps.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: But the Khmer Rouge have
                            attacked some nationalist camps too.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Yes.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: They were not battles
                            between nationalists. The Khmer Rouge attacked nationalist camps.</p>
                        <pb facs="0320" n="291" xml:id="pg_291"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: What about the
                            Vietnamese? You know <persName corresp="#p_PVD_1">Pham Van
                                Dong</persName> and the other leaders very well. Do you think the
                            Vietnamese leadership would ever accept you?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: The Vietnamese are
                            Vietnamese. We cannot change them. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry
                                Kissinger</persName> told me in Peking that no one should ever rely
                            on the Vietnamese. They are immoral. I cannot speculate about the
                            future. It all depends on their situation in the international arena,
                            the situation inside Vietnam, Indochina events, and the changing
                            attitudes of the U.S. and other great powers. Vietnam will make its
                            policy in conformity with its interests and capabilities. They are not
                            sentimental. They are without morality. They are intelligent and
                            opportunistic. They can understand where their interests lie.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NJD_1">NEGROPONTE</persName>: You will meet with
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> in a few days.
                            Could you and I meet informally during the next few days? Perhaps
                                Saturday,<note n="9" xml:id="d83fn9">February 23. See <ref target="#d85">Document 85</ref> and <ref target="#d85fn2">footnote 2</ref> thereto.</note> in order to prepare the best
                            possible meeting with the Secretary. You and I could meet on Saturday
                            and try to prepare what you want to discuss with the Secretary.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: You should know
                            clearly what we want. We want an independent Cambodia, neutral and
                            non-aligned, free of foreign troops, able to choose its own leaders. If
                            my experience on the border is any indication, the people want you.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: It’s up to them.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Yes, it’s up to
                            them.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Yes, I will never
                            propose myself. I simply wait for the chance to have my party compete
                            with the Khmer Rouge and <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Heng
                                Samrin</persName>. Please convey to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WLF_1">Woodcock</persName> my apologies. I apologize for
                            any misunderstanding. I understood him very well. He said nothing like
                            what Burchett has written. I mentioned only that he acknowledged that
                            the Khmer Rouge possessed the only effective armed force against
                            Vietnam. That is all he said.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Burchett twisted what
                            you said. The issue here is your relationship with the Thai government,
                            your relationship with <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName>,
                            your relationship with China, and your relationship with the Vietnamese.
                            We should talk more about it. I propose that when you meet with John you
                            focus on what you want to discuss with the Secretary.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName> is no problem. I am anxious to
                            get his friendship, and that of his group. If he decides to join
                                <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sihanouk</persName> and the federation
                            we will all welcome him.</p>
                        <pb facs="0321" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Are there any
                            conditions under which Vietnam would accept you, and remove its
                            troops?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: We have to wait for
                            Vietnam to determine its political, diplomatic, and military position. I
                            can’t guess. Vietnam might shift its position vis-a-vis <persName corresp="#p_SS_2">Son Sann</persName>, the Khmer Rouge, and
                                <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">Pol Pot</persName>.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: You were writing
                                <persName corresp="#p_PVD_1">Pham Van Dong</persName> a series of
                            letters. Have you received any response?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Yes, I wrote three
                            letters. There was no reply to either the first or the second. The third
                            letter was returned unopened. They are not very polite. When they have
                            the Cambodian cake in their mouth, they want to swallow it.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: You are still thinking
                            of going to Singapore in June?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I am going to Australia
                            in June. I can combine the two trips as they are in the same area.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: The Foreign Ministers
                            of Australia and New Zealand will be here next week.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I am going to Australia;
                            I am invited by my countrymen.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: What about China? Are
                            they keeping in contact with you?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Yes, I keep friendly
                            contacts with them.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Will you see
                            Ambassador Chai while you are here?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Yes, I think he will ask
                            to meet with me. In Paris I kept close contact with the Chinese
                            Embassy.</p>
                        <p>I have a message to deliver to you on behalf of President <persName corresp="#p_KI_1">Kim Il Sung</persName>. He wants to improve his
                            relations with you. I hope that the day will come when the U.S. will be
                            able to establish commercial relations with Pyongyang.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: I hope so too. But
                            North Korea has proposed direct talks with us. We can’t do that unless
                            South Korea comes too.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: But France and other
                            western countries have established commercial relations. You could do
                            the same.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: We can’t do that
                            without weakening our friends in South Korea.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I am not coming here to
                            promote my personal ambitions.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: We understand that. I
                            have always admired you. As I told Lacouture, I have always regarded you
                            like DeGaulle, a man who personifies his country and is above party or
                            faction.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I do not pretend to be a
                            DeGaulle. I just want to fulfill my duty as a Cambodian citizen.</p>
                        <pb facs="0322" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: I understand. We have
                            to resolve the internal rivalries and your problems with Thailand.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I have told the Chinese
                            I will not attack the Khmer Rouge on the battlefield. They don’t have to
                            worry. I won’t cooperate with them but I won’t attack them. China should
                            be satisfied with such behavior on my part.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Is China still
                            pressing you?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Yes. China still presses
                            me. Some westerners also advise me to become the Chief of State of
                            Democratic Kampuchea and to reshuffle the government in order to prove
                            that it is a humane one. I say I am ready to do it if the Khmer people
                            want me to, but they do not want me to.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Whatever you do you
                            mustn’t form a government in exile.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I will never form a
                            government in exile.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: Good. You are above
                            parties.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Some of my supporters
                            have urged a government-in-exile but I will never do it.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NJD_1">NEGROPONTE</persName>: It will reduce the
                            possibilities of any settlement.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: Rest assured I will
                            never do such a thing.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">HOLBROOKE</persName>: We are devoted to
                            peace in Cambodia. Tomorrow Ambassador Palmieri will explain what we are
                            doing to save the Khmer people. We are spending hundreds of millions of
                            dollars. We are working night and day. Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_CR_1">Carter</persName> herself visited Thailand in an important
                            gesture.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SN_1">SIHANOUK</persName>: I express my profound
                            gratitude to the U.S. Government, to the American people, to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>. I appreciate your
                            efforts.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>