<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v02p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="132" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>As indicated in circular telegram 225, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, President
                        <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Eisenhower</persName> delivered his
                    “Atoms for Peace” speech—as press accounts quickly named it—before the General
                    Assembly of the United Nations late on the afternoon of December 8, 1953.</p>
                <p>Work on the speech had proceeded nearly to the moment of delivery. A draft had
                    been transmitted from the Bermuda Conference to Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName> on the evening of December 7 in
                    telegram <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">Gadel</gloss> 121 (600.0012/12–753), but
                    according to <persName corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1">Lewis L. Strauss</persName>, the
                    President made major revisions in it on the Presidential airplane <hi
                        rend="italic">Columbine</hi> en route from Bermuda to New York. (<persName
                        corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1">Strauss</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Men and
                        Decisions,</hi> page 359) <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>, without going into details, merely stated: “Finally,
                    only minutes before delivery of the speech, the work was done.” (<persName
                        corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Eisenhower</persName>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mandate for Change,</hi> page 253) President <persName
                        corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s “Address Before the
                    General Assembly of the United Nations on Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy, New
                    York City, December 8, 1953,” is printed in <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of
                        the Presidents of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1"
                            >Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName>, 1953,</hi> pages 813–822.</p>
                <p>The President’s speech generated a significant amount of comment and reaction. In
                    telegram 2223 from Paris, December 9, Minister <persName>Achilles</persName>
                    reported that he had sought to impress upon French officials, including
                        <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>, the “importance of
                    France’s quickly picking up President’s initiative on atomic energy.” French
                    reaction was favorable, “<persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>
                    mentioning that he had already commented favorably to press on getting off plane
                    and that he still had time to get ahead of <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1"
                        >Churchill</persName> before latter’s return. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>’s comment to press, however, was
                    largely lost among his other remarks on Bermuda.” (600.0012/12–953) In telegram
                        <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 393 from New York, December 9,
                        <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName> reported that Indian
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MENONVKK1">V. K. Krishna Menon</persName>
                    “called on me late last night urging desirability of a resolution following up
                    President’s speech. I sought to discourage him in view need for reflection by
                    various powers concerned. Today before plenary meeting he informed me that he
                    had asked <persName corresp="#p_MALIKYA1">Malik</persName> (USSR) whether latter
                    had any objections. <persName corresp="#p_MALIKYA1">Malik</persName> said he had
                    no objection but that his delegation was without instructions.”
                    (600.0012/12–953). In priority telegram 691 from Moscow, December 10, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BOHLENCE1">Bohlen</persName> reported, eyes only for the
                    Secretary, that only a factual <pb facs="0478" n="1292" xml:id="pg_1292"/>
                    summary of the President’s speech had so far appeared in the Soviet press. “It
                    is possible that <persName corresp="#p_MOLOTOVVM1">Molotov</persName> may send
                    for me in next day or so to give privately Soviet reaction to President’s
                    speech. If there are any particular points you would like stressed in event
                    adverse Soviet reaction, this might be good opportunity. I would appreciate your
                    advice.” (600.0012/12–1053) <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    replied personally to <persName corresp="#p_BOHLENCE1">Bohlen</persName> in
                    priority telegram 362, December 10, that “if you have not gotten any official
                    reaction from <persName corresp="#p_MOLOTOVVM1">Molotov</persName> within 10
                    days’ time, you should approach him and inquire further. We will send you
                    further instructions at that time but would like your suggestions. In reference
                    to your question as to what points you might stress, I believe that the
                    principal point to underscore is that this is an entirely sincere and serious
                    proposal which we should like to develop as soon as possible.”
                    (600.0012/12–1053) <persName corresp="#p_BOHLENCE1">Bohlen</persName>
                    acknowledged <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName>’ comments with
                    thanks in priority telegram 693 from Moscow, December 11, adding: “I would
                    imagine <persName corresp="#p_MOLOTOVVM1">Molotov</persName> will send for me
                    before too long since failure to do so would in effect be equivalent to blanket
                    rejection without attempt to justify such action. Soviet press this morning by
                    selecting excerpts from foreign press, especially Communist, continues to
                    reflect cool and skeptical attitude towards President’s proposal.”
                    (600.0012/12–1153) The telegrams to the Department commenting upon foreign
                    reaction to the President’s “Atoms for Peace” proposal are in file 600.0012.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
