<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-01-19T20:03:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-01-19T20:03:00-05:00" n="161" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d161">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">600.0012/1–1954: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Embassy in the Soviet Union</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d161fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-01-19T20:03:00-05:00">January 19, 1954—8:03
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>487. Eyes only Ambassador from the Secretary. Reference <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 456 January 11.<note n="2" xml:id="d161fn2">See footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_1335">p.
                            1335</ref>.</note> Soviet Ambassador called on me January 19 at his
                            request.<note n="3" xml:id="d161fn3">According to a memorandum for the
                            record, prepared by <persName corresp="#p_BONBRIGHTJCHJ1">James C. H.
                                Bonbright</persName> on Jan. 19, the Secretary of State suggested at
                            his morning staff meeting that <persName corresp="#p_BONBRIGHTJCHJ1">Bonbright</persName> call the Soviet Embassy to remind Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_ZARUBINGN1">Zarubin</persName> that a promised
                            early Soviet reaction to the meeting of Jan. 11 had not been forthcoming
                            and that the Secretary was leaving for the Berlin Conference in 2 days’
                            time. <persName corresp="#p_BONBRIGHTJCHJ1">Bonbright</persName> reached
                            Counselor <persName>Vladykin</persName> who soon phoned back that the
                            Ambassador did indeed wish to see the Secretary and a meeting was
                            arranged for 5 p.m. that day. “In my conversation with Mr.
                                <persName>Vladykin</persName>, I made it quite clear that the
                            Secretary was not asking for the appointment and the initiative rested
                            clearly with the Soviet Ambassador.” (600.0012/1–1954)</note> He opened
                        by stating he had received answers from <pb facs="0532" n="1346" xml:id="pg_1346"/> Soviet Government which were embodied in memorandum
                        then read in translation.<note n="4" xml:id="d161fn4">For the text in
                            translation, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                            Oct. 4, 1954, pp. 478–479. The memorandum was among the documents
                            released as the result of Soviet-American agreement in September 1954,
                            to make public the correspondence between the two governments concerning
                            the question of an “atomic pool”.</note></p>
                    <p>In brief, Soviets accepted suggestions contained in numbered paragraphs 1, 2,
                        and 6, of memorandum I had given him January 11<note n="5" xml:id="d161fn5"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1339">p.
                            1339</ref>.</note> and repeated verbatim to you in reference cable.</p>
                    <p>On numbered paragraph 3 Soviet Government expressed consent bearing in mind
                        necessity at certain stage of negotiations of inviting all powers bearing
                        main responsibility for maintenance world peace and international security.
                        (Later in conversation I said that if this meant reaching present agreement
                        to bring Chinese Communists at some point into discussions, I could not give
                        any such agreement and that this should be made clear right away. <persName corresp="#p_ZARUBINGN1">Zarubin</persName> said it was very difficult
                        for him to indicate now who those nations are and he made no effort to
                        identify them.) On numbered paragraph 4 Soviet memorandum stated that it was
                        necessary to recall Soviet Governments declaration of December 21 pointing
                        out that in course of negotiations there should be simultaneously examined
                        the matter of agreement unconditionally to ban the use of atomic or hydrogen
                        or other weapons of mass destruction.</p>
                    <p>On numbered paragraph 5 the Soviet Government agreed to participate in
                        discussion of President <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s proposal of December 8 but at same time
                        believed agreement must be reached on plan of “rotation” under which Soviet
                        proposal of December 21 would be discussed in alternating meetings with
                        President’s proposal.</p>
                    <p>I told Ambassador I felt general tenor of reply marked some advance but that
                        I would want to study it more carefully before commenting. I asked whether
                        there was any preference on the part of his government for channel of
                        communication (i.e., through Soviet Embassy here or through you in Moscow)
                        if I had any questions to put to <persName corresp="#p_MOLOTOVVM1">Molotov</persName> before Berlin. <persName corresp="#p_ZARUBINGN1">Zarubin</persName> replied that either would do, whatever was most
                        convenient. He then confirmed that he was leaving Washington tomorrow and in
                        reply to my question as to whether his destination was Moscow or Berlin he
                        said he was going directly to Berlin.</p>
                    <pb facs="0533" n="1347" xml:id="pg_1347"/>
                    <p>I asked him when <persName corresp="#p_MOLOTOVVM1">Molotov</persName> would
                        arrive in Berlin and when he replied on 23, I remarked it might be possible
                        to talk to him before opening of conference on January 25.</p>
                    <p>In closing I thanked Ambassador for prompt reply of his government and we
                        quickly agreed upon a brief statement to press which said that, in agreement
                        with <persName corresp="#p_MOLOTOVVM1">Molotov</persName>, I would continue
                        these discussions in Berlin.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>