<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-08-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="242" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Atomic Energy files, lot 57 D 668, “<gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> Policies”</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Consultant to the
                            Secretary of State for Atomic Energy Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName>)</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d242fn1">Of the participants listed below, <persName>Edward R.
                                Trapnell</persName> was Special Assistant to the General Manager,
                            U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-08-24">August 24,
                                1954</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <item>Subject:</item>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> briefing of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Cole</persName> on Planning for the
                            Implementation of the President’s Pool Proposal</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <item>Participants:</item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Sterling Cole</persName>, Chairman,
                            Joint Committee on Atomic Energy</item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_HALLJA1">John Hall</persName>, Atomic Energy
                            Commission</item>
                        <item><persName>Ned Trapnell</persName>, Atomic Energy Commission</item>
                        <item><persName>Walter Hamilton</persName>, <gloss target="#t_JCAE1">JCAE</gloss> Staff</item>
                        <item><persName>Wayne Brobeck</persName>, <gloss target="#t_JCAE1">JCAE</gloss> Staff</item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Gerard C. Smith</persName>, <gloss target="#t_SAE1">S/AE</gloss>, Department of State</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HALLJA1">Hall</persName> had asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> to go along with him when he
                        briefed Mr. <persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Cole</persName> on planning for
                        the implementation of the President’s pool proposal. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HALLJA1">Hall</persName> had originally asked if Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> was going to brief Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Cole</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> advised him that he thought the
                        Joint Committee should be briefed by the Atomic Energy Commission.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HALLJA1">Hall</persName> outlined the present
                        planning to set up an international agency with the other nations
                        principally involved in atomic energy matters: to set up a reactor training
                        school, perhaps at Brookhaven; to declassify a certain amount of reactor
                        information; and to renew power reactor negotiations with the Belgians.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> pointed out to Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Cole</persName> that it was not intended
                        at this time that the international agency would hold any fissionable
                        material but that it would act, at least in the early stages, primarily <pb facs="0691" n="1505" xml:id="pg_1505"/> as an information exchange
                        mechanism. However, we hope that its charter would be broad enough to permit
                        it to evolve into an operating agency and perhaps in time into an
                        international control mechanism.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Cole</persName> was interested in the
                        relationship of this agency to the United Nations and urged that it have
                        only a tenuous relationship. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> pointed out that this question of relationship to the
                        UN was under study now. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Cole</persName>
                        suggested that the problems of Congressional ratification of United States
                        participation in any international agency would be easiest if done under
                        section 124 of the Atomic Energy Act since Congress, by passing this
                        provision, had shown a preference for this procedure. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Cole</persName> stated that the reason section 124
                        had been put in was so that the Congress would know in advance who the
                        members of the international agency would be. He felt that the United States
                        should also be able to control who subsequently joined the international
                        agency. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> pointed out the
                        difficulties that such a veto power would raise and pointed out that a power
                        to withdraw from the agency might be a sufficient protection. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_COLERWS1">Cole</persName> stated that he was glad that we
                        were getting on with planning for the international agency and said that he
                        thought Congressional ratification would not be very time consuming.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>