<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the United Nations (Lodge) to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v02p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d263</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">263</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-10-15T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-10-15T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-10-15T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-10-15T13:00:00-05:00" n="263"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d263">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">600.0012/10–1554: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations
                            (<persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1" type="from">Lodge</persName>) to the
                            <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-10-15T13:00:00-05:00"
                            >October 15, 1954—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 108. For the Secretary from <persName
                        corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName>. Re: Peaceful uses of atomic
                    energy.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>As has previously been reported there is continuing and widespread
                        interest in our plans for establishing an Atomic Energy Agency with a more
                        than nominal relationship to the UN. Extent of enthusiasm for our program as
                        presented in forthcoming debate may well depend on how far we are able to go
                        with respect to UN relationship. Secretary’s memo of Sept 24<note n="1"
                            xml:id="d263fn1">Not further identified.</note> indicated importance
                        working out this relationship and suggested that a “specialized” agency
                        might be the answer. However, it seems clear that the Agency will not be set
                        up before <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> debate and therefore no
                        relationship will be worked out during this session of <gloss
                            target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>For this reason I suggest consideration be given to the advantages of
                        recommending to the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> the establishment of a
                        UN comite comprising some or all of govts with whom we are now negotiating
                        as prospective members of <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss>. Comite wld
                        be asked to continue present negotiations for establishment of agency.
                            <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                        <pb facs="0719" n="1533" xml:id="pg_1533"/> might establish such a comite
                        without, in my opinion, any real interference in the actual negotiations and
                        this wld, from the start, provide adequate semblance of UN tie-up. Comite
                        cld report to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> upon creation of agency and
                        might, if it then seemed desirable, submit treaty creating agency to <gloss
                            target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> before ratification by national legislatures
                        (see <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 91 Oct 12).<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d263fn2">See footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_1530">p.
                            1530</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Seriously doubt whether the calling of a so-called “scientific” conf in
                        and of itself adequately meets the positive and affirmative leadership
                        requirements inherent in the program announced by the President last Dec. 3
                            [<hi rend="italic">8</hi>]. At some stage in the development of this
                        program such a conf might prove to be a useful thing, but it is vital that
                        it be properly organized and managed. As so far envisaged, however, I think
                        it wld be very difficult, if not impossible, for us to maintain our
                        leadership and control. Unwieldly and theoretical nature of debate carried
                        on by large body of scientists not responsible to govts wld do more harm
                        than good at this stage. Giving the opportunity of a world forum such as
                        this to “scientists” such as
                            <persName>Joliot</persName>-<persName>Curie</persName>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d263fn3">Dr. <persName>Frédéric Joliot-Curie</persName>,
                            French scientist; High Commissioner for Atomic Energy, 1946–1950; and a
                            Communist.</note> and a miscellaneous crew from Russia, Czechoslovakia
                        and Hungary would scarcely advance the President’s program. Similarly, a
                        conference of scientists could produce a situation conflicting with plans of
                        govts negotiating for creation of agency.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Therefore, in the first instance, it might be desirable to have UN comite
                        as suggested above undertake arrangements for the conf, leaving to this
                        comite the question of timing and terms of reference. This comite wld
                        provide desirable and necessary link between Agency as we develop it and
                        conf.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In addition to the foregoing, while I do not think we should make rash
                        promises of miracles to be accomplished overnight, nevertheless I feel that
                        we shld offer some very definite and tangible inducement, particularly to
                        the smaller, underdeveloped countries. This might be accomplished by
                        authorizing the UN comite to receive and respond to comments, requests for
                        information and requests for assistance from UN member govts.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>I also have considerable doubt whether it is wise to give as much power as
                        seems to be contemplated in our present draft resolution to UNSYG. I think
                        that all of these arrangements should be within effective control of USG and
                        the govts most closely associated with US.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lodge</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
