<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Consultant to the Secretary of State for
                    Atomic Energy Affairs (Smith)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v02p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d275</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">275</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="275"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d275">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Atomic Energy files, lot 57 D 688, “<gloss
                        target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> Policies”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Consultant to the Secretary
                        of State for Atomic Energy Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1"
                            >Smith</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d275fn1">
                        <p>A separate record of this meeting prepared by <persName
                                corresp="#p_WAINHOUSEDW1">Wainhouse</persName> of <gloss
                                target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> is in Secretary’s Memoranda of
                            Conversation, lot 64 D 199.</p>
                        <p>Of the participants listed below, <persName>James W. Barco</persName> was
                            Senior Adviser for Political Affairs, U.S. Mission at the United
                            Nations.</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1954-11-03">November 3, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject:</item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss>—Discussion at Luncheon Meeting</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Participants:</item>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName>Morehead Patterson</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KEYDMK1">Key</persName>—<gloss target="#t_IO1"
                            >IO</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WAINHOUSEDW1">Wainhouse</persName>—<gloss
                            target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1">Strauss</persName>—<gloss
                            target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Barco</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName>—<gloss
                            target="#t_SAE1">S/AE</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName> opened the discussion by
                    saying that he had brought us together since there had been some evidence of
                    need for coordinating <pb facs="0736" n="1550" xml:id="pg_1550"/> the various
                    groups working on different facets of the International Agency problem.</p>
                <p>The question was raised as to whether or not Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1"
                        >Lodge</persName> could state in his speech that the United States will hold
                    available “x” kilograms of enriched material for projects sponsored by the
                        Agency.<note n="2" xml:id="d275fn2">See telegram <gloss target="#t_Delga1"
                            >Delga</gloss> 158 from New York, Oct. 29, <ref target="#pg_1545">p.
                            1545</ref>.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1"
                        >Strauss</persName> pointed out the difficulty was that Presidential
                    approval was necessary—it had not yet been obtained—and in addition he would
                    like to consult with the Joint Committee on this matter in advance of their
                    hearing about it in a public speech. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1"
                        >Strauss</persName> indicated that he thought the necessary clearance would
                    be obtained, and it was agreed that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1"
                        >Lodge</persName> might make the reference in a subsequent speech.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> pointed out that this still
                    left the question of whether Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1"
                        >Lodge</persName> could say that the United States would hold this material
                    for disposal by the Agency or for disposal by the United States Government. This
                    depends upon whether we should seek United States participation in the work of
                    the Agency by a treaty and rely on section 121 of the Act, or by an
                    international arrangement and rely on section 124 and 123 of the Act. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> pointed out the
                    restrictions which would obtain if the latter course was pursued. There was
                    discussion as to whether or not the necessity for a finding under section 123
                    that any specific cooperation by the United States must promote its defense,
                    would prevent effective cooperation with neutral nations, for example. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1">Strauss</persName> pointed out his belief
                    that the Congress would be very anxious about the security aspects of any
                    international plan and it would be well to make a very cautious start. If the
                    limitations of section 123 prove too burdensome, the new legislative authority
                    could then be sought. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName>
                    suggested that proceeding under section 124 and 123 might be tantamount to a
                    United States position that it would only cooperate in the International Agency
                    with nations friendly to it. He pointed out that section 123 was a very
                    restrictive channel and had been made so in the light of its possible use for
                    transmitting military information to foreign countries and regional defense
                    associations. He pointed out that <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5431 had
                    directed the Department of State and the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> to
                    proceed along two lines: (1) bilateral cooperation, and (2) multilateral
                    cooperation, and that apparently we were losing sight of the second
                        direction.<note n="3" xml:id="d275fn3">Reference is to <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5431/1, Aug. 13; for text, see <ref
                            target="#pg_1488">p. 1488</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1">Strauss</persName> pointed out that even in
                    the case of research reactors there was a physical danger since they had
                    produced quantities of isotopes which, if improperly handled, could constitute
                    an international hazard. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1"
                        >Strauss</persName> pointed out that in his judgment <pb facs="0737"
                        n="1551" xml:id="pg_1551"/> true multilateral cooperation was contingent on
                    substantial Russian participation in the Agency. Absent that, he felt that at
                    least in the beginning we should keep close control.</p>
                <p>On the matter of the conference, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STRAUSSLL1"
                        >Strauss</persName> pointed out how it had been proposed by him in a speech
                    last April after he had obtained the approval of the President. If it was to be
                    UN sponsored, the world would lose sight of its original <persName
                        corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Eisenhower</persName> sponsorship and we would
                    lose a measure of credit to which the United States was entitled. It seemed
                    generally agreed that this decision was beyond recall.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHGC1">Smith</persName> pointed out that a
                    resolution concerning the conference, if joined to a resolution concerning the
                    Agency, would tend to confuse the fact that the Agency was to be separate from
                    the United Nations as opposed to the conference which is to be a creature of the
                    United Nations. [The Agency (although planned to be a specialized agency of the
                    UN) was to be separate from the UN as opposed to the conference which was to be
                    a creature of the UN.]<note n="4" xml:id="d275fn4">Brackets in the source
                        text.</note> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName>
                    agreed and suggested that there only be a reference to the negotiations looking
                    to the Agency in the resolution on the conference and that the UN not sponsor a
                    resolution concerning the Agency.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
