<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Administration
                    (Scott) to the Administrator of the United States International Information
                    Administration (Compton)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v02p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d301</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">301</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-09-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="301"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_CON1">CON</gloss> files, lot 53 D 233, “Investigations,
                    1952”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Administration (<persName corresp="#p_SCOTTWK1" type="from"
                        >Scott</persName>) to the Administrator of the United States International
                        Information Administration (<persName corresp="#p_COMPTONWS1" type="to"
                            >Compton</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d301fn1">Drafted by <persName>John W. Ford</persName>,
                        Assistant Chief of the Division of Security, Bureau of
                        Administration.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">eyes only</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-09-12">September 12,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject:</item>
                    <item>Investigation at Voice of America, New York City</item>
                </list>
                <p>Our Security people have reported the results obtained so far by the Federal
                    Bureau of Investigation and <gloss target="#t_SY1">SY</gloss>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d301fn2">Division of Security, Bureau of
                        Administration.</note> on certain charges and allegations made by employees
                    of <gloss target="#t_IBS1">IBS</gloss>.<note n="3" xml:id="d301fn3"
                        >International Broadcasting Service, U.S. International Information
                        Administration.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Since the <gloss target="#t_IBS1">IBS</gloss> employees against whom allegations
                    have been made were originally investigated by the <gloss target="#t_FBI1"
                        >FBI</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> was called in to make
                    the appropriate inquiry. The <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> has reported on
                    the basis of an <hi rend="italic">initial</hi> investigation that most of the
                    allegations concern administrative practices, with fewer charges bordering on
                    disloyalty or suitability. The charges concerning disloyalty are, in <pb
                        facs="0825" n="1639" xml:id="pg_1639"/> most part, allegations of deliberate
                    tone-down and sabotage of Voice program content. Deliberate, skillful countering
                    of U.S. objectives by choice of material and emphasis is alleged.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> representative at New York stated that
                    since their initial inquiry had indicated the greater percentage of the
                    information was primarily State’s responsibility to investigate, it was the
                        <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss>’s desire that <gloss target="#t_SY1"
                        >SY</gloss> develop all information possessed by informants, and refer to
                    the <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> only such data as would form the basis
                    for an <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> investigation on loyalty.</p>
                <p>As a result of Mr. <persName>Ford</persName>’s recent visit to New York, and from
                    the results of <gloss target="#t_SY1">SY</gloss>’s inquiry to-date, it does
                    appear that the greater percentage of the charges will concern administrative
                    practices. However, there are a considerable number of allegations pertaining to
                    moral deviation, security or loyalty. Some of the allegations on moral deviation
                    have been proved true and the individuals involved have been dismissed. Other
                    moral deviation allegations are currently under investigation.</p>
                <p>For the purpose of conducting an investigation into the situation, four <gloss
                        target="#t_SY1">SY</gloss> Agents have been assigned to New York to carry
                    out the required interviews. The Agents are obtaining insofar as possible full
                    signed statements from the persons interviewed. Information developed by <gloss
                        target="#t_SY1">SY</gloss> during the investigation will be segregated into
                    the following categories: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>loyalty information to be furnished <gloss target="#t_FBI1"
                                >FBI</gloss> for investigation.</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>information requiring further <gloss target="#t_SY1">SY</gloss>
                            inquiry on security or suitability grounds.</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>information requiring administrative inquiry on policy or program
                            questions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I suggest you may wish to approach the investigation of these allegations of an
                    administrative or policy nature by undertaking a thorough review of the content
                    of questioned broadcast material, checking the selection of material, emphasis,
                    et cetera. A study of this sort would have to cover a sufficient number of
                    broadcasts to establish a clear case, which I realize would impose a
                    considerable burden.</p>
                <p>I suggest, therefore, that you designate Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KIMBALLAA1"
                        >Art Kimball</persName> to consult immediately with Mr.
                        <persName>Ford</persName> concerning the findings of an administrative or
                    policy nature which have been obtained so far, in order that Mr.
                        <persName>Ford</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KIMBALLAA1"
                        >Kimball</persName> may jointly recommend action to be taken in light of the
                    investigation now in progress.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
