<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic Posts</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v02p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d323</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">323</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-03-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-03-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="323"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d323">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> files, lot 56 D 581, “Info Guide Bulletin
                    303”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to Certain
                            <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Posts</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d323fn1">This message was transmitted as circular telegram
                        961, Mar. 17. The central file copy of this circular telegram
                        (511.00/3–1753) was removed in July 1953. A notation on the source text
                        reads: “Copied from carbon tissue, March 18, 1953.” The source text also
                        indicates this message was drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CONNORSWB1">W.
                            Bradley Connors</persName> of the Office of Policy and Plans, U.S.
                        International Information Administration, and by Assistant Secretary of
                        State for Public Affairs <persName corresp="#p_MCCARDLECW1">Carl W.
                            McCardle</persName>, and was approved for transmission by <gloss
                            target="#t_IIA1">IIA</gloss> Administrator <persName
                            corresp="#p_JOHNSONRL1">Robert L. Johnson</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-03-17">March 17,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Following is Infoguide Bulletin 303:</p>
                <p>Department circular telegram 889 (Infoguide Bulletin 272)<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d323fn2">See footnote 5, <ref target="#pg_1679">p.
                        1679</ref>.</note> of February 19 is herewith canceled. Following effective
                    immediately: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Material produced by Communists or their agents or sympathizers should
                            be used only with great care and when responsible persons judge them to
                            be an effective way—and the uniquely effective way—to confound
                            international Communism with its own words, to expose its fallacies and
                            refute its doctrines. Responsibility for this judgment rests with
                            directors of media services, <gloss target="#t_PAO1">PAO</gloss>s and
                            their designated alternates.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Our policy is not to identify by name any living international
                            Communist unless absolutely necessary. This must not be carried to the
                            point of absurdity in treatment of straight news but even here a
                            conscious effort not to build up our living opponents by naming them
                            should be made. As often as possible, writings or statements of living
                            persons can be ascribed to some such anonymity as “a leading
                            international Communist or Stalinist”. Skillful use of this treatment in
                            commentary and in our own anti-Communist publications can be especially
                            effective.</item>
                        <label/>
                        <item>Our own press and radio have in the past built up Soviet personalities
                            to such an extent that whatever they do or say commands <pb facs="0873"
                                n="1687" xml:id="pg_1687"/> widespread attention. We should replace
                            individual buildups with anonymity to those hostile to us.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Reputable, responsible US periodicals of program value may be included
                            in <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> overseas libraries. However,
                            the Mission should withdraw any individual issues containing any
                            material detrimental to US objectives. Periodicals, which repeatedly
                            publish international Communist propaganda, have no place in the program
                            and cannot be used.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Works of Communist authors are banned from all <gloss
                                target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> public libraries and information
                            centers.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_PAO1">PAO</gloss> in each country mission has responsibility
                    for taking all reasonable efforts for removal of individual issues of
                    periodicals “containing material detrimental to US objectives”. <gloss
                        target="#t_PAO1">PAO</gloss> must immediately carry out the ban against use
                    of periodicals “which repeatedly publish international Communist propaganda” and
                    the “works of Communist authors” by removing all material known to him or his
                    staff to be within these categories. (For the purposes of this instruction
                    authors who obviously follow the Communist line or participate in Communist
                    front organizations will be considered Communists and their works banned.)</p>
                <p>Realizing that the <gloss target="#t_PAO1">PAO</gloss> and his staff may not be
                    aware of all Communist authors or publications which repeatedly publish
                    international Communist propaganda, the Department will attempt as promptly as
                    possible to furnish specific guidance on individual periodicals and books to be
                    banned. To facilitate review of material acquired locally, all posts which have
                    not already done so, should provide Department with list of these
                    acquisitions.</p>
                <p>This directive also cancels any previous directives or sections thereof that may
                    conflict with the instructions herein.<note n="3" xml:id="d323fn3">Infoguide
                        Bulletin 303 was supplemented by two further instructions. Circular telegram
                        1065 of Apr. 28 reads as follows: “Ref. Depcirc. 961 (Infoguide Bulletin
                        303) dated March 17, 1953 books of persons taking refuge behind the Fifth
                        Amendment in refusing to testify as to their political affiliations before a
                        Congressional Committee should be removed from the shelves of Information
                        Centers. <gloss target="#t_IIA1">IIA</gloss> hearing Wireless File FS
                        section since March 16, 1953 contains names of persons seeking such refuge
                        before <persName corresp="#p_MCCARTHYSJR1">McCarthy</persName> subcommittee.
                        Further information will be furnished by <gloss target="#t_IIA1">IIA</gloss>
                        as secured from records of previous hearings and other Congressional
                        committees.” (511.0021/4–2853) For documentation on the foreign policy
                        aspects of Congressional loyalty and security investigations and concern
                        over declining prestige abroad, see <ref target="frus1952-54v01p2#pg_1379"
                            >vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, Part 2, pp. 1379</ref> ff. On June
                        18, certain diplomatic posts were told in circular telegram 1213 that, in
                        reference to Infoguide Bulletin 303, “pending further instructions names,
                        authors or titles books removed should not be made public.”
                        (511.0021/6–1853)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
