<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-08T18:42:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-08T18:42:00-05:00" n="360" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d360">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">511.00/12–853: Circular telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Acting Director of the United States Information
                            Agency (<persName corresp="#p_WASHBURNAM1" type="from">Washburn</persName>) to Certain <gloss type="to">Diplomatic
                                Posts</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d360fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BERDINGAH1">Berding</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PHILLIPSJB1">Phillips</persName>, and Colonel
                                <persName>Hirsch</persName> of <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss>;
                            cleared by <persName corresp="#p_HADENA1">Allen Haden</persName> of
                                <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_SANGERRH1">Sanger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MONTGOMERYEP1">Montgomery</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MURPHYRD1">Robert Murphy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RAINEP1">Raine</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MEYERSH1">Meyers</persName>,
                                <persName>Stegmeier</persName>, <persName>Godel</persName>, and
                                <persName corresp="#p_ARNESONRG1">Gordon Arneson</persName> of
                                <gloss target="#t_SAE1">S/AE</gloss>; and sent to 69
                        posts.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-12-08T18:42:00-05:00">December 8, 1953—6:42
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_Usito1">Usito</gloss> 164. InfoGuide: President’s UN
                            Speech.<note n="2" xml:id="d360fn2">Reference is to President <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s “Atoms for
                            Peace” address before the UN General Assembly on Dec. 8. The speech is
                            printed in <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the
                                United States: <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Dwight D.
                                    Eisenhower</persName>, 1953,</hi> pp. 813–822. For documentation
                            on this speech, see <ref target="#pg_845">pp. 845</ref> ff.</note> This
                        is Joint State–Defense–<gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> message.</p>
                    <pb facs="0945" n="1759" xml:id="pg_1759"/>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Essential that all recipients make maximum effort to insure that
                            President’s historic offer of sharing the benefits of peaceful use of
                            atomic energy with the entire world achieves the sharpest and most
                            lasting impact.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>While premature to speculate on nature of any detailed plan, essential
                            for all media to carry and cross-report the wide variety of comment,
                            both in US and abroad, which will be generated as result this offer. In
                            so doing media should strive to serve as international forum, of
                            balanced comment, aiming at widest possible coverage.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Speech makes clear humanity now shares present danger but has also
                            capability changing situation to one of hope. Do not minimize grim
                            picture delineated first part of speech. Important that sense of urgency
                            aroused by the President be accurately reflected, yet be offset by offer
                            to take tangible first step towards international use of <gloss target="#t_AE1">AE</gloss> for peaceful purposes which will strike
                            massive blow against root causes of war and international
                            tension.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Stress that atom-sharing concept is product of maturing plans,
                            reflects continuity of dynamic policy stemming from April 16
                                speech,<note n="3" xml:id="d360fn3">See the unnumbered circular
                                airgram, Apr. 22, <ref target="#pg_1669">p. 1669</ref>.</note> and
                            is aimed at breaking international log jam on disarmament
                            proposals.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>While the bid to the Soviet Union to join in “private conversations”
                            must be underscored, the speech under no circumstances should be
                            interpreted as “psychological warfare”. Nor do we commit Soviet Union to
                            an early reply, keeping in mind the delicacy and difficulty of any
                            ensuing negotiations. To avert the pitfall that the issue of global war
                            or peace depends on the immediate fate of the proposal, we continue to
                            present it as a step forward in steady long range effort in UN and
                            elsewhere as appropriate, to establish a basis for eventual disarmament,
                            including prohibition of atomic weapons, when settlement of other issues
                            and consequent relaxation of world tension permits. The proposal
                            demonstrates the sincerity of our purpose but we avoid committing
                            ourselves or others to achieve an early agreement at the expense of a
                            fully dependable disarmament plan.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>In line with foregoing our objectives are: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>To impress upon world opinion, seriousness with which the US
                                    seeks world security through reduction of the arms
                                    burden.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>To follow up 16 April impact by making another breach in the
                                    Soviet’s near monopoly of “peace” propaganda. Hitherto Soviets
                                    have benefitted by simple, though spurious, approach while West
                                    has been handicapped in explaining rather complex proposals.
                                    Speech fills this latter gap, and by stress on Atomic Energy
                                    Authority <pb facs="0946" n="1760" xml:id="pg_1760"/> and A-Bank
                                    proposal will help combat previous Soviet atomic
                                    propaganda.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>To give to the peoples of Russia dramatic evidence of US
                                    peaceful intentions, while making clear at same time US resolve
                                    to resist aggression by all means at its disposal.</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>To seek to persuade the enslaved peoples of satellite Europe
                                    that their best interests will be served through international
                                    cooperation and understanding, which can be enhanced by
                                    international acceptance of the President’s proposals.</item>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item>To convince our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                                    partners, and other friends that we are ready to take positive,
                                    vigorous steps to achieve world peace and security by the
                                    sharing of peaceful benefits of atomic energy and by eventual
                                    disarmament.</item>
                                <label>f.</label>
                                <item>To convince neutrals less directly involved in the cold war
                                    that we aim to achieve a peaceful world in which the threat of
                                    global atomic war is removed and that our offer provides a new
                                    approach to the economic development which many of them so
                                    desperately seek.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Of equal importance with foregoing is exercise of appropriate
                            safeguards to avoid in our output: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Any stimulation of false optimism regarding immediately
                                    realizable substantive disarmament.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Any impression that the proposals are “cold war” maneuvers and
                                    are purely propagandistics.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>Any impression that we are offering a final proposal whose
                                    rejection would increase the danger of global [war].</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>Any indication that we have abandoned UN atomic energy control
                                    plans. Commentary might refer (1) to the US position supporting
                                    the UN plan or any other equally effective plan, (2) to
                                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName>’
                                    September 17 statement at <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                                    that our joint proposals are not immutable, but any proposal
                                    must meet essential tests of adequate safeguards.</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WASHBURNAM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Washburn</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>