<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The President to the President of the Senate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v02p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d365</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">365</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="365"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d365">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">511.00/7–2354</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">President</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">President of the Senate</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d365fn1">A notation on the source text reads: “Estimate No.
                        82 83rd Congress–2nd Session”.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-27">July 27,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith for the
                    consideration of the Congress a proposed supplemental appropriation for the
                    fiscal year 1955 in the amount of $5,000,000 for Funds Appropriated to the
                    President, as follows:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Funds Appropriated to the President</hi>
                </p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>For expenses necessary to enable the President to take such measures as he
                        deems appropriate to meet extraordinary or unusual circumstances arising in
                        the international affairs of the Government, $5,000,000 to remain available
                        until expended for use in the President’s discretion and without regard to
                        such provisions of law as he may specify: <hi rend="italic">Provided,</hi>
                        That the President shall transmit to the Committees on Appropriations of the
                        Senate and of the House of Representatives, not less often than quarterly, a
                        full report of expenditures under this appropriation.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>No existing program or appropriation is available to meet the numerous unforeseen
                    and unexpected contingencies, both great and small, which arise constantly in
                    the day-to-day conduct of the international affairs of the Government. The small
                    emergency fund which has been provided for the President in connection with
                    national interest, security or defense is inappropriate for dealing with many
                    situations which, although highly important, do not come within the purview of
                    this fund.</p>
                <p>An example is the participation in international trade fairs. Frequently a need
                    arises for coordination by the Federal Government to insure that the exhibits of
                    American business firms do not lose their national identification through
                    association only with local distributors and agents. In 1954 there will be about
                    75 international trade fairs of particular significance and size. We would not
                    expect to take part in all of these, but during the next twelve months the
                    really important hard core of about 30 do constitute a valuable spring board for
                    promoting a wider understanding of American products and our private enterprise
                    system.</p>
                <p>In the cultural and artistic fields as well we need greater resources to assist
                    and encourage private musical, dramatic and other cultural groups to go forth
                    and demonstrate that America too can lay claim to high cultural and artistic
                    accomplishments. The enthusiasm with which this type of cultural offering is
                    received abroad is demonstrated by the fabulous success of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Porgy and Bess,</hi>
                    <pb facs="0963" n="1777" xml:id="pg_1777"/> playing to capacity houses in an
                    extended tour of the free countries of Europe. The contribution which such
                    presentations make toward a better understanding of America can scarcely be
                    exaggerated. I consider it essential that we take immediate and vigorous action
                    to demonstrate the superiority of the products and cultural values of our system
                    of free enterprise.</p>
                <p>Just as it is impossible to anticipate the precise purposes for which the
                    proposed appropriation would be used, so it is impossible to make an accurate
                    estimate of the exact amount necessary to carry out those purposes. For this
                    reason, the amount herein requested is not limited to a particular period, but
                    would remain available so long as necessary to meet unforeseen and unanticipated
                    needs. The Congress could, of course, at any time rescind any portion of the
                    appropriation which remained unused.</p>
                <p>In requesting the Congress to provide broad authority of this nature, I believe
                    that the Congress will want to be kept informed of the precise uses to which
                    these funds will be put. Accordingly, the proposed appropriation language would
                    provide that full reports of expenditures be made quarterly to the respective
                    committees on appropriations of the two Houses.</p>
                <p>I trust that the Congress will give most careful consideration to the proposed
                    appropriation.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dwight D. Eisenhower</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
