<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum for the File, by the Special Assistant to the Secretary of State
                    for Atomic Energy Affairs (Arneson)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v02p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-10-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-10-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="59"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d59">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_GPM1">G/PM</gloss> files, lot 68 D 349, “Ivy”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum for the File, by the <gloss type="from">Special
                            Assistant</gloss> to the Secretary of State for Atomic Energy Affairs
                            (<persName corresp="#p_ARNESONRG1" type="to">Arneson</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-10-27">October 27,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject:</item>
                    <item>Advance Notification to the United Kingdom and Canada of United States
                        Atomic Tests</item>
                </list>
                <p>By memorandum of October 13, 1952<note n="1" xml:id="d59fn1">Not printed. (<gloss
                            target="#t_GPM1">G/PM</gloss> files, lot 68 D 349, “Ivy”)</note> I
                    requested the views of the Department of Defense and the Atomic Energy
                    Commission on the question whether the United Kingdom and Canada should be given
                    advance notification of the forthcoming Ivy series along the lines of
                    notification previously given for earlier test series. By memorandum dated
                    October 15<note n="1" xml:id="d59fn2">Not printed. (<gloss target="#t_GPM1"
                            >G/PM</gloss> files, lot 68 D 349, “Ivy”)</note> from Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LEBARONR1">LeBaron</persName> I was informed that the Secretary
                    of Defense concurred in the proposed advance notification. On October 22 I met
                    with Acting Chairman <persName corresp="#p_SMYTHHD1">Smyth</persName> and
                    Commissioners <persName corresp="#p_MURRAYTE1">Murray</persName> and
                        <persName>Glennan</persName> to discuss in detail the <pb facs="0223"
                        n="1037" xml:id="pg_1037"/> various problems presented by the proposal. It
                    was the consensus of the meeting, after some discussion, that I should proceed
                    with the advance notification on the Ivy series as in the past. I pointed out
                    that my general advance notification to the British and the Canadians would be
                    followed at a later date by more precise notification through AFOAT channels of
                    the exact time of the shots and of the meteorological conditions existing at the
                    time in order to facilitate British and Canadian interception of the clouds. No
                    objection was raised in the meeting to this follow-up procedure, it being
                    recognized that such information was operationally necessary in carrying out
                    technical cooperation in Area 5 under the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi.</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d59fn3">For text of the <hi rend="italic">modus
                        vivendi</hi>, see the minutes of the meeting of the Combined Policy
                        Committee, Jan. 7, 1948, in <ref target="frus1948v01p2#pg_679">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 679</ref>.</note> By memorandum dated
                    October 23 from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HALLJA1">Hall</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d59fn4">Not found in Department of State files.</note> I was
                    informed that the Commission concurred in the proposal for advance notification
                    with “the suggestion that the United Kingdom could be informed in the near
                    future that the Ivy test is planned for the early part of November.”</p>
                <p>Following on these concurrences I informed Mr. <persName>Eddie
                    Tomkins</persName>, British Secretary of the <gloss target="#t_CPC1"
                    >CPC</gloss>, and Mr. <persName>George Ignatieff</persName>, Canadian Secretary
                    of the <gloss target="#t_CPC1">CPC</gloss>, of the forthcoming Ivy tests along
                    the following lines: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The forthcoming tests would be two in number.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The test series was scheduled to begin early in November. The exact
                            time would be in large measure dependent on weather conditions which
                            tended to be quite uncertain at this time of the year in the Eniwetok
                            area.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The procedure followed in the past, namely notification as to exact
                            time and attendant meteorological conditions, would be forthcoming in
                            due course through AFOAT channels.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>No inkling was given, or asked, as to the nature of either
                            shot.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The notification as set forth above was given to the two named individuals orally
                    on the afternoon of Friday, October 24, 1952.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
