<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-08-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="111" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Adams</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 2032.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-08-07"><hi rend="italic">
                                        August</hi> 7, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I transmit a copy of a communication of
                            the 23d ultimo, from Henry Liebenau, esq., corresponding secretary of
                            the Constitutional Union Association, concerning the cases of Colonel
                            William J. Nagle and Colonel J. Warren, who have been arrested and
                            detained in Ireland on charges of complicity in recent Fenian movements.
                            You are well informed of the views of this government in regard to such
                            cases, and those referred to in the enclosed have, it is believed, been
                            already brought to your notice, that of Colonel Nagle being the subject
                            of my instruction of the 9th ultimo, No. 2016. You need not be informed
                            that faithful service in the armies or navy of the United States during
                            the rebellion constitutes an enhanced claim of persons so serving to the
                            consideration of the government which they have helped to perpetuate;
                            and the instances now before us are of that class.</p>
                        <p>In presenting such cases to her Majesty’s government, it is not expected
                            that you will submit to the perusal of the authorities any expressions
                            which could give just cause of offence to that government. This
                            circumspection should be practiced as well for its favorable influence
                            on the interests of the parties whose release is sought as upon grounds
                            of international courtesy.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Charles Francis Adams, Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c.,
                                    &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Liebenau</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>No. 4 <hi rend="smallcaps">Hamilton Place, West</hi>
                                            51<hi rend="smallcaps">st Street</hi>,<hi rend="italic">
                                            New York,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-07-23"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 23, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have been directed, as you will
                                observe by the proceedings of a meeting of the general committee of
                                “The Constitutional Union Association,” hereunto attached, to
                                address you in behalf of the liberation of Colonel William J. Nagle,
                                a native of our State, having been born at Syracuse; and Colonel J.
                                Warren, a native of Massachusetts, having been born at Boston; the
                                former, (Nagle,) of the 88th regiment New York volunteers; and the
                                latter, (Warren,) of the 63d regiment Massachusetts volunteers; and
                                who are now incarcerated in Kilmainham prison, Dublin, Ireland;
                                without having committed any overt act to justify or palliate such
                                an unwarrantable act of oppression, and in direct violation of that
                                comity of nations so essential to the harmonious and friendly
                                understanding of a Christian people.</p>
                            <p>With one of these gentlemen, William J. Nagle, I have the honor of a
                                personal acquaintance, and it gives me pleasure to state that I have
                                always known him as a highly honorable and law-abiding citizen, one
                                whom I am confident would not render himself amenable to any
                                violations of British law. You are, I believe, personally acquainted
                                with the family, and, therefore, it is perhaps superfluous for me to
                                dwell upon their character and conduct, except so far as to remind
                                you that <hi rend="italic">five</hi> of their brothers rendered
                                essential service in the Union army during the rebellion, while <hi rend="italic">three</hi> of them were killed in the service.</p>
                            <p>Colonel Warren, the travelling companion of our worthy
                                fellow-citizen, Nagle, I have not the pleasure of knowing
                                personally, but he is very highly spoken of by those who are
                                familiar with his general reputation.</p>
                            <p>As American citizens, they are entitled to the protection of our
                                government, while the services they have both rendered in the army
                                of our Union claim, as I am convinced they will receive from you,
                                the earnest and decisive action of the government they have both so
                                faithfully served in its hour of peril.</p>
                            <p>Permit me, in behalf of the organization I have the honor of
                                representing, to urge most respectfully your immediate intercession
                                in behalf of a speedy release of the aforesaid Colonel Nagle and
                                Colonel Warren.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your obedient and humble
                                servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>HENRY LEIBENAU, <hi rend="italic">Corresponding Secretary C.
                                        U. A.</hi></signed>
                            </closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                            <pb facs="0189" n="121" xml:id="pg_121"/>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#center">[From the <placeName>New
                                            York</placeName> Sun, Tuesday morning, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-07-16">July 16,
                                            1867</date>,]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <head>The Fenian prisoners–Meeting of Constitutional Union
                                    Committee–Resolutions demanding their release.</head>
                                <p>A special meeting of the Constitutional Union general committee
                                    was held last evening at Masonic Hall to take into consideration
                                    the unwarrantable imprisonment by the British government, of
                                    Colonel William Nagle, of this city, and Colonel J. Warren, of
                                    Massachusetts. After a short and earnest deliberation the
                                    following resolutions were passed:</p>
                                <p>We have heard with surprise and indignation of the unwarrantable
                                    imprisonment of American citizens in Ireland, arrested on the
                                    abject and pitiful pretence of suspicion of being Fenians, and
                                    their incarceration in a loathsome prison, subject to the
                                    indignities and manacles of convicted felons, in direct
                                    violation of every principle of international law and the comity
                                    of nations, in consequence of the cowardly fear of danger which
                                    the <hi rend="italic">guilty</hi> only feel from the
                                    consciousness of their own transgressions; and</p>
                                <p>Whereas Colonel William J. Nagle, a native of New York State, and
                                    Colonel J. Warren, a native of Massachusetts, both gallant
                                    soldiers of our Union army during our late domestic straggle,
                                    have been arrested without the slightest overt act on their part
                                    while on a visit to their relatives in their fatherland, for no
                                    other offence to them known than the expressing here on their
                                    native soil a sympathy for the down-trodden country of their
                                    parents f and</p>
                                <p>Whereas the noble act of Commdoroe Ingraham in demanding of
                                    Austria the instant release of Koszta, an adopted citizen of
                                    America, met the hearty approval of our undivided nation, and
                                    the case of Colonel Nagle and Colonel Warren being entited to no
                                    less a consideration, because of their being natives of the
                                    United States: Therefore, be it</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Resolved,</hi> That steps be taken to effect
                                    their immediate release, considering the violation of
                                    international law in the case as just and proper cause for
                                    demanding indemnification and retribution: be it therefore</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Resolved,</hi> That our corresponding secretary
                                    be directed to address the Hon. William H. Seward on behalf of
                                    the organization and in favor of our fellow-citizens, whom we
                                    believe are not amenable to British law by any overt act nor by
                                    any connection with Fenian movements in Ireland, and urge the
                                    honorable Secretary to make a speedy and resolute demand or
                                    their immediate release.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Resolved,</hi> That a petition be prepared and
                                    circulated for signatures by our fellow-citizens under the
                                    patronage of our organization.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>DANIEL B. NORTHRUP, <hi rend="italic">President.</hi></signed>
                                </closer>
                                <postscript>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">H. J. Banker</hi>,</p>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Liebenau</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretaries.</hi></p>
                                </postscript>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>