<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-09-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="142" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Adams</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 2054.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-09-14"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 14, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your despatch of the 23d ultimo, No. 1428,
                            in relation to the cases of Colonels Nagle and Warren, has been
                            received, and a copy of the paper which accompanied it has been
                            submitted to the collector of customs at New York, with a view to an
                            inquiry as to the truth of the statements made therein. I transmit a
                            copy of the collector’s reply, the tendency of which is to throw
                            discredit upon those statements.</p>
                        <pb facs="0211" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/>
                        <p>Special interest is felt in these cases by a large number of highly
                            respectable and influential citizens, as an illustration of which you
                            are informed that the President has recently received and referred to
                            this department, petitions in the form of one which has already been
                            forwarded to you, containing upwards of a thousand signatures, embracing
                            those of the mayor of Brooklyn, judges and other judicial and civil
                            officers, and many persons of eminence.</p>
                        <p>The communications which have been addressed to you render it unnecessary
                            for me to assure you of the gratification which would be afforded by an
                            early release of these officers.</p>
                        <p>There is probably little doubt that Colonel Warren is a naturalized
                            citizen of the United States; but I have pointed out to the applicants
                            in his behalf the importance of positive proof of the fact of
                            citizenship.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>