<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-12-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="280" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d280">
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">M. Berthemy</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-12-28"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 28, 1866.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to state that, in
                                accordance with a proposition made by his Majesty’s government,
                                through the Marquis de Montholon, to the government of the United
                                States, the President has this day issued a proclamation, to take
                                effect on the 1st day of January, 1867, removing the imposition of
                                discriminating tonnage dues upon French vessels coming into ports of
                                the United States.</p>
                            <p>Accept, sir, a renewed assurance of my very high consideration.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                            </closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">M. Berthemy,</hi> &amp;<hi rend="italic">c</hi>., &amp;<hi rend="italic">c</hi>., &amp;<hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</p>
                            </postscript>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>By the President of the United States of America.</head>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="italic">A Proclamation.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Whereas satisfactory evidence has been received by me from his
                                    Imperial Majesty the Emperor of France, through the Marquis de
                                    Montholon, his envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary,
                                    that vessels belonging to citizens of the United States entering
                                    any port of France or of its dependencies, on or after the first
                                    day of January, one thousand eight hundred and sixty-seven, will
                                    not be subjected to the payment of higher duties on tonnage than
                                    are levied upon vessels belonging to citizens of France entering
                                    the said ports—</p>
                                <p>Now, therefore, I, Andrew Johnson, President of the United States
                                    of America, by virtue of the authority vested in me by an act of
                                    Congress of the seventh day of January, one thousand eight
                                    hundred and twenty-four, entitled, “An act concerning
                                    discriminating duties of tonnage and impost,” and by an act in
                                    addition thereto of the twenty-fourth day of May, one thousand
                                    eight hundred and twenty-eight, do hereby declare and proclaim
                                    that on and after the said first day of January, one thousand
                                    eight hundred and sixty-seven, so long as vessels of the United
                                    States shall be admitted to French ports on the terms aforesaid,
                                    French vessels entering ports of the United States will be
                                    subject to no higher rates of duty on tonnage than are levied
                                    upon vessels of the United States in the ports thereof.</p>
                                <p>In testimony whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and caused the
                                    seal of the United States to be affixed.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <dateline rendition="#left">Done at the city of
                                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian us-republic" when="1866-12-28">this
                                            twenty-eighth day of December, in the year of our Lord
                                            one thousand eight hundred and sixty-six, and of the
                                            independence of the United States of America the
                                            ninety-first</date>.</dateline>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi> ANDREW
                                        JOHNSON.</signed>
                                </closer>
                                <postscript>
                                    <p>By the President:</p>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi></p>
                                </postscript>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>