<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>M. Berthemy to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1867p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1867-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1867-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="293"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d293">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">M. Berthemy</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of France to the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-05-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 27, 1867.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of State:</hi> On communicating to you, under
                    date of 4th January last, the text of the monetary convention recently concluded
                    between France, Belgium, Italy, and Switzerland, I had, at the same time, the
                    honor to call your attention to the opportunity for submitting to an
                    international conference which should be held at Paris the study of the more
                    general question of uniformity of coinage.</p>
                <p>In view of the reception given to these overtures, as well by the cabinet of the
                    United States as by those of other countries to which they were addressed, the
                    government of the Emperor has thought that the time has arrived for following
                    out the project, the realization of which it was their aim to prepare. In
                    consequence, a formal proposition has been transmitted through the diplomatic
                    medium to divers governments in order that they might cause themselves to be
                    represented in a commission which should meet at Paris on Monday, the 17th June
                    next, at the hotel of the department for foreign affairs. This conference would
                    be presided over conjointly by the minister for foreign affairs and the minister
                    of finance. The vice-presidency would be devolved on Mr. de Parieu,
                    vice-president of the council of state, who, with Mr. Herbet, minister
                    plenipotentiary, director of consulates and commercial affairs, would thereat
                    represent the department for foreign affairs. The delegates from the department
                    of finance would be Mr. Pelouze, member of the institute, president of the
                    commission on coinage, and Mr. de Lavenay, president of the section of finance
                    in the council of state. His excellency the Marquis de Moustier charges me, in
                    placing these notices before the government of the United States, to convey to
                    it, at the same time, the invitation to participate in the international
                    monetary conference. It would attach even, in consequence of the early time at
                    which the labors should commence, very special value to the information as soon
                    as possible of the name of the delegate by whom the cabinet of Washington shall
                    deem fit to be represented, and I would be very thankful to your excellency if
                    you would, as soon as possible, inform me on this point.</p>
                <p>There is no need to add that the commissioners will assemble without any
                    programme arranged in anticipation. They will thus be able to look more freely
                    for a solution of the difficulties which would oppose an assimilation between
                    the systems actually in operation. This mode of proceeding, which has already
                        <pb facs="0367" n="299" xml:id="pg_299"/> received so happy an application
                    at the conferences of 1865, appears at this time of greater utility, inasmuch as
                    different countries, while appreciating the importance of the object to be
                    attained, would have the means of recurring to divergent opinions. The
                    conference proposed has not otherwise any immediate object than to call out an
                    interchange of views and discussion of principles; in a word, to seek for the
                    bases of ulterior negotiations.</p>
                <p>Accept, Mr. Secretary of State, the assurances of my high consideration,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>BERTHEMY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi> &amp;<hi rend="italic"
                            >c</hi>., &amp;<hi rend="italic">c</hi>., &amp;<hi rend="italic"
                        >c</hi>.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
