<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-01-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="30" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d30">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1307]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">London,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-01-25"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 25, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In accordance with the suggestions made in
                            your despatch No. 1903, of the 4th instant, and under the authority
                            given by the letter of the Assistant Secretary of the Treasury, which
                            accompanied it, I have named Mr. Dudley as the person to take charge of
                            the unfinished business pertaining to the authorization of Mr. Morse,
                            which has been now revoked.</p>
                        <p>There are some reasons which would have weighed on my mind against this
                            selection had I been able, among the few American residents in this
                            kingdom, to think of a person thoroughly suited for the duty. These have
                            no reference, however, either to the competency or the fidelity of the
                            nominee. They are rather connected with the personal relations of the
                            various parties concerned who have been brought, heretofore, more or
                            less either into rivalry or conflict with each other during and since
                            the war. Whatever difficulties might be apprehended from this cause,
                            will, I think, be removed by the presence of the agent specially
                            appointed to superintend this business when he shall appear.</p>
                        <p>I shall not communicate this proceeding to Mr. Dudley, presuming that the
                            appointment will be made directly from the Treasury Department.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William. H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>