<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1867p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1867-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1867-02-06T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692" lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421" lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846" lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recBTfVgprHsl1J9K" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85047074" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Famine</term>
                    <term ref="recFe9iZmLH8fc4Ed" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103898" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Harvest</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236" lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662" lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004" lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579" lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recdTuobyjHNvXKhT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011601" lcsh-match="exact">Bankruptcy</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-02-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="33" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d33">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1315.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-02-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 6, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have to acknowledge the reception of
                            despatches from the department, numbered from 1910 to 1924 inclusive,
                            and likewise a box containing a gold watch intended for Captain
                            Furney.</p>
                <p>Parliament was opened yesterday in form by the Queen, and her speech was
                            read, a copy of which is herewith transmitted. I also have the honor to
                            send a copy of the London Times, containing a report of the speeches
                            made in both houses on the address.</p>
                <p>The most interesting topic to us is of course that of the relations
                            between the two countries. On this point the remarks of Lord Russell and
                            of the first minister of the Crown are the most material. It is plain
                            that the former acquiesces in having that done through another which he
                            had managed to preclude any possibility of his doing with any grace
                            himself. Hence it may be assumed that there is now only one opinion in
                            Great Britain as to the propriety of bringing the whole matter to some
                            peaceful issue. I heartily congratulate you upon this result.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William. H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <pb facs="0129" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">
                            <hi rend="italic">Her Majesty’s most gracious speech to both
                                            <placeName>houses of Parliament</placeName> on Tuesday,
                                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-02-05">February 5,
                                            1867</date>.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lords and Gentlemen:</hi> In again recurring
                                to your advice and assistance, I am happy to inform you that my
                                relations with foreign powers are on a friendly and satisfactory
                                footing.</p>
                    <p>I hope that the termination of the war in which Prussia, Austria, and
                                Italy have been engaged may lead to the establishment of a durable
                                peace in Europe.</p>
                    <p>I have suggested to the government of the United States a mode by
                                which questions pending between the two countries, arising out of
                                the late civil war, may receive amicable solution, and which, if
                                met, as I trust it will be, in a corresponding spirit, will remove
                                all grounds of possible misunderstanding and promote relations of
                                cordial friendship.</p>
                    <p>The war between Spain and the republics of Chili and Peru still
                                continues, the good offices of my government, in conjunction with
                                that of the Emperor of the French, having failed to effect a
                                reconciliation. If, either by agreement between the parties
                                themselves or by the mediation of any other friendly power, peace
                                shall be restored, the object which I have had in view will equally
                                be attained.</p>
                    <p>Discontent prevailing in some provinces of the Turkish empire has
                                broken out in actual insurrection in Crete. In common with my
                                allies, the Emperor of the French and the Emperor of Russia, I have
                                abstained from any interference in these internal disturbances, but
                                our joint efforts have been directed to bringing about improved
                                relations between the Porte and its Christian subjects not
                                inconsistent with the sovereign rights of the Sultan.</p>
                    <p>The protracted negotiations which arose out of the acceptance by
                                Prince Charles of Hohenzollern of the government of the Danubian
                                principalities have been happily terminated by an arrangement to
                                which the Porte has given its ready adhesion, and which has been
                                sanctioned by the concurrence of all the powers, signataries of the
                                treaty of 1856.</p>
                    <p>Resolutions in favor of a more intimate union of the provinces of
                                Canada, Nova Scotia, and New Brunswick have been passed by their
                                several legislatures, and delegates duly authorized and representing
                                all classes of colonial party and opinion have concurred in the
                                conditions upon which such an union may be best effected. In
                                accordance with their wishes, a bill will be submitted to you which
                                by the consolidation of colonial interests and resources will give
                                strength to the several provinces as members of the same empire and
                                animated by feelings of loyalty to the same sovereign.</p>
                    <p>I have heard with deep sorrow that the calamity of famine has pressed
                                heavily on my subjects in some parts of India. Instructions were
                                issued to my government in that country to make the utmost exertions
                                to mitigate the distress which prevailed during the autumn of last
                                year. The blessing of an abundant harvest has since that time
                                materially improved the condition of the suffering districts.</p>
                    <p>The pressing efforts and unscrupulous assertions of treasonable
                                conspirators abroad have during the last autumn excited the hopes of
                                some disaffected persons in Ireland, and the apprehensions of the
                                loyal population; but the firm yet temperate exercise of the powers
                                intrusted to the executive, and the hostility manifested against the
                                conspiracy by men of all classes and creeds, have greatly tended to
                                restore public confidence, and have rendered hopeless any attempt to
                                disturb the general tranquillity; I trust that you may consequently
                                be enabled to dispense with the continuance of any exceptional
                                legislation for that part of my dominions.</p>
                    <p>I acknowledge, with deep thankfulness to Almighty God, the great
                                decrease that has taken place in the cholera and in the pestilence
                                which has attacked our cattle; but the continued prevalence of the
                                latter in some foreign countries, and its occasional reappearance in
                                this, will still render necessary some special measures of
                                precaution, and I trust that the visitation of the former will lead
                                to increased attention to those sanitary measures which experience
                                has shown to be the best preventive.</p>
                    <p>Estimating as of the highest importance an adequate supply of pure
                                and wholesome water, I have directed the issue of a commission to
                                inquire into the best means of permanently securing such a supply
                                for the metropolis, and for the principal towns in densely peopled
                                districts of the kingdom.</p>
                    <p>Gentlemen of the House of Commons, I have directed the estimates for
                                the ensuing year to be laid before you. They have been prepared with
                                a due regard to economy and to the requirements of the public
                                service.</p>
                    <p>You will, I am assured, give your ready assent to a moderate
                                expenditure calculated to improve the condition of my soldiers, and
                                to lay the foundation of an efficient army of reserve.</p>
                    <p>My lords and gentlemen, your attention will again be called to the
                                state of the representation of the people in Parliament; and I trust
                                that your deliberations, conducted in a spirit of moderation and
                                mutual forbearance, may lead to the adoption of measures which, with
                                out unduly disturbing the balance of political power, shall freely
                                extend the elective franchise.</p>
                    <p>The frequent occurrence of disagreements between employers of labor
                                and their workmen, causing much private suffering and public loss,
                                and occasionally leading as is alleged to acts <pb facs="0130" n="62" xml:id="pg_62"/> of outrage and violence, has induced me
                                to issue a commission to inquire into and report upon the
                                organization of trades unions and other associations, whether of
                                workmen or employers, with power to suggest any improvement of the
                                law for their mutual benefit. Application will be made to you for
                                parliamentary powers, which will be necessary to make this inquiry
                                effective.</p>
                    <p>I have directed bills to be laid before you for the extension of the
                                beneficial provisions of the factory acts to other trades specially
                                reported on by the royal commission on the employment of children,
                                and for the better regulation, according to the principle of those
                                acts, of workshops where women and children are largely
                                employed.</p>
                    <p>The condition of the mercantile marine has attracted my serious
                                attention. Complaints are made that the supply of seamen is
                                deficient, and that the provisions for their health and discipline
                                on board ship are imperfect. Measures will be submitted to you with
                                a view to increase the efficiency of this important service.</p>
                    <p>I have observed with satisfaction the relaxations recently introduced
                                into the navigation laws of France. I have expressed to the Emperor
                                of the French my readiness to submit to Parliament a proposal for
                                the extinction, on equitable terms, of the exemptions from local
                                charges on shipping which are still enjoyed by a limited number of
                                individuals in British ports; and his imperial Majesty has, in
                                anticipation of this step, already admitted British ships to the
                                advantage of the new law. A bill upon this subject will forthwith be
                                laid before you.</p>
                    <p>A bill will also be submitted to you for making better provision for
                                the arrangement of the affairs of railway companies which are unable
                                to meet their engagements.</p>
                    <p>Measures will be submitted to you for improving the management of
                                sick and other poor in the metropolis, and for a redistribution of
                                some of the charges for relief therein.</p>
                    <p>Your attention will also be called to the amendment of the law of
                                bankruptcy, to the consolidation of the courts of probate and
                                divorce and admiralty, and to the means of disposing with greater
                                despatch and frequency of the increasing business in the superior
                                courts of common law and at the assizes.</p>
                    <p>The relations between landlord and tenant in Ireland have engaged my
                                anxious attention, and a bill will be laid before you, which,
                                without interfering with the rights of property, will offer direct
                                encouragement to occupiers of land to improve their holdings and
                                provide a simple mode of obtaining compensation for permanent
                                improvements. I commend to your careful consideration these and
                                other measures which will be brought before you, and I pray that
                                your labors may, under the blessing of Providence, conduce to the
                                prosperity of the country and the happiness of my people.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
