<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1867p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1867-03-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1867-03-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-03-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-03-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="39"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d39">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1330.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-03-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 2, 1867</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to transmit herewith a copy of
                    the Times of yesterday containing a legal opinion given by Sir Robert P.
                    Collier, the late solicitor general, and the same person who was employed in
                    behalf of the United States in the case of the Alabama on the claims of the
                    holders of the rebel loan in this country.</p>
                <p>If the advancement of any such claim as that indicated could be made a means of
                    opening up the secret history of that extraordinary transaction, it would not be
                    without its uses in estimating the value of the neutrality of Great Britain in
                    the struggle for our national existence.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">[From the <placeName>London</placeName> Times,
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-03-01">March 1,
                            1867</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Subjoined is a question of considerable importance in its bearing on the
                        confederate cotton loan, with the opinion thereof of Sir R. P. Collier, the
                        late solicitor general:</p>
                    <p rend="center">“QUESTION.</p>
                    <p>“Whether or not merchants and others, on being sued in England by the
                        government of the United States for property or money held by them at the
                        termination of the war belonging to the southern States, may not
                        successfully plead the confederate 7 per cent, cotton bonds as a set-off, to
                        the extent of the amount that each defendant may hold of them.</p>
                    <p rend="center">“OPINION.</p>
                    <p>“In the event of the United States government suing in the courts of the
                        country for debts due on property belonging the late confederate government,
                        I am of opinion that defendants, who may be holders of confederate cotton
                        bonds, are entitled to set up a counter claim against the United States
                        government in respect of these bonds.</p>
                    <p>“This counter claim will be founded on the principle, that if the United
                        States government assert in our courts claims accruing to them through their
                        succession to the property and rights of the late confederate government,
                        they are bound by the liabilities of that government.</p>
                    <p>“Should the United States government bring action of debt, I think that the
                        holders of cotton bonds may plead them as a set-off. Should they proceed for
                        a tortious conversion of property, a technical difficulty will stand in the
                        way of this defence, and it may be necessary to resort to an acquitable
                        plea, or possibly to the protection of a court of equity.</p>
                    <p>“The equitable case of the bondholders will be strengthened by the facts that
                        the United States government have possessed themselves of the cotton set
                        apart as the security for the payment of the bonds.</p>
                    <p>“The form, however, in which the defence I have indicated may be raised will
                        be matter of subsequent consideration when the mode of proceeding adopted by
                        the United States government is known.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>“R. P. COLLIER.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Temple</hi>, <hi rend="italic">February</hi>
                            28.”</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
