<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1866-10-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1866-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="397" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d397">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. G. F. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">the Tantai</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 658.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate
                                    General</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Shanghai</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1866-10-13"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 13, 1866</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your despatch of the 8th
                            instant.</p>
                        <p>I am afraid that you have mistaken the object of my negotiation with
                            you.</p>
                        <p>I was instructed by my superior officer at Peking, to whom I had referred
                            our correspondence touching the north-bank question, to investigate the
                            matter.</p>
                        <p>Having proceeded to your port and satisfied myself of the justice of the
                            position taken by the merchants, I urged, with a view to save further
                            trouble, that you should recognize this right to remain on the north
                            side; and, when I found that you would not do this, I told you how you
                            might compromise with the merchants, so far as lands already acquired
                            were concerned, viz., by paying them for their outlays. I proposed this
                            with the sanction of the merchants, who, while they would vastly prefer
                            to retain their lands, were not desirous of standing in a position of
                            hostility to yourself,</p>
                        <pb facs="0533" n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/>
                        <p>As to the question of the treaty right, that would rest for discussion at
                            Peking.</p>
                        <p>I did not go up to your port to urge a pecuniary indemnity, and I am not
                            disposed to do so now. The question stands at the moment in this wise:
                            if you think that the arguments which I adduced at our interview were
                            just, you may either pat the merchants in quiet possession of their
                            several properties or pay them for their outlays. If you do not, then
                            the only course is to submit the whole question to arbitrament of higher
                            authorities.</p>
                        <p>Touching the points raised in your despatch, I have to remark as
                            follows:</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The treaty right to purchase land on the north
                                bank.</hi> This point has already been fully discussed by us.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Absence of seals on deeds.</hi> I do not know that
                            it is necessary to have any seal. In the American treaty the <hi rend="italic">legal fees</hi> for seals are mentioned, but there is
                            no stipulation that deeds must be sealed. In the appropriate article of
                            the British treaty, the word seal does not occur.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Names of foreign merchants do not appear in
                                deeds.</hi> The Chinese names of the mercantile houses are given, I
                            believe, although it is true that they are not described as foreign <hi rend="italic">hongs.</hi> That such were meant, however, every one
                            familiar with trade at the ports would, I think, understand.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Land clandestinely rented.</hi> I do not know why
                            you should say this, for that these lands had been rented has been a
                            matter of common notoriety, and could not well have been concealed, had
                            there been any object for it.</p>
                        <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Proposition for pardal payment.</hi> The merchants
                            are unwilling to claim possession of the. north bank, or of anything on
                            account thereof, if they have not a just claim based on the
                            treaty-right, or if by informalities their titles to the land are not
                            good. They believe that they would be put in a wrong position should
                            they consent to do so.</p>
                        <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Proposition that the original renters should make
                                this partial payment.</hi> The merchants consider that their
                            transactions with the renters were complete when they made payment for
                            and received possession of the lands in question, and that it would be
                            bad faith to claim against them.</p>
                        <p>7. <hi rend="italic">The requirements of justice.</hi> It appears from
                            the governor general’s despatches, copies of which you allowed me to
                            take, that the object of having the Chinese and foreigners removed from
                            the north bank, was to give room for the great salt station which has
                            been recently established there. Now, the salt commissioners ought not
                            to take up lands belonging to foreigners without their consent, and
                            without paying them their price. Perhaps the governor general upon
                            further investigation would agree in this view, and not ask the present
                            renters to give up their lands, whether or not they are willing, and the
                            lessors, who seem to be innocent, to pay them all indemnity.</p>
                        <p>Having thus answered the points raised by you, in order that it may not
                            appear that I acknowledge that they have force, I may say, in
                            conclusion, that it is not desirable to spin out our discussion.</p>
                        <p>The merchants will positively not agree to different terms than those
                            offered by them, and if you cannot come up to this standard, it is
                            better to say so, and to refer the matter to Peking at once.</p>
                        <p>I am your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>GEO. F. SEWARD.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p> His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Ting</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tantai, &amp;c., Chinkiang.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>