<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Bancroft to to Mr. Seward.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1867p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d545</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">545</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1867-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1867-11-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005935"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Migration</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-11-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="545"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d545">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Bancroft</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward.</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 21.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-11-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 20, 1867.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I send to you to-day the laws enacted at the late
                    session of the North German parliament.</p>
                <p>The fourth law relates to the nationality of merchant ships and their right to
                    use the union flag. That flag, by the 55th article of the constitution, is
                    black, white, and red, and is, from the 1st day of April, 1868, to cover the
                    mercantile marine of North Germany; on and after that day it will be seen in all
                    our considerable ports. By the second article of the law you will perceive that
                    the character of a North German ship is acquired by ownership alone, without any
                    regard to the country in which the ship may have been built. I have already, in
                    my No. 17, called your attention to the fact that this new flag will cover a
                    larger amount of tonnage than the flag of any European nation except Great
                    Britain.</p>
                <p>The eighth law relates to free migration, (Freizugigkeit.) This law, although at
                    present it is confined to the citizens of the North German States, is not
                    without interest for us. An attempt will be made at the first meeting of the
                    German zoll parliament to extend this law to the South German States. Should
                    that take place, perhaps we might claim the benefit of it under that clause of
                    our commercial treaty with Prussia which places us on the footing of the most
                    favored nations. The eleventh law, relating to the organization of the consular
                    department, enacts that a <hi rend="italic">consulmissus</hi> shall not engage
                    in mercantile pursuits.</p>
                <p>The collection which I send you contains the bills as presented by the president
                    of the North German United States—that is, the King of Prussia—and the laws as
                    they were finally adopted. The official publication of the laws I have not as
                    yet been able to obtain.</p>
                <pb facs="0669" n="601" xml:id="pg_601"/>
                <p>I take this occasion to explain the relation which, according to my understanding
                    of the case, the American minister at Berlin holds to this government. The King
                    of Prussia, as King of Prussia, is the hereditary President of the North German
                    United States, and the president of the collective German customs and commerce
                    union, which last now embraces all Germany, except the Austrian provinces. Some
                    of the European powers regard with dissatisfaction the tendency of Germany
                    towards union, are reluctant to acknowledge that union as far as it has been
                    brought about, and would gladly exercise an adverse influence upon its further
                    progress. The United States of America have always held that every people has an
                    undoubted right to improve its institutions undisturbed by the jealousy of its
                    neighbors. Apart from this general principle, the United States have an especial
                    reason to be pleased with the progress of the German union, because it brings
                    with it an increase of liberty to the German people, and a greater analogy to
                    our own system. I therefore attended officially the opening of the North German
                    parliament, as well as the opening of the Prussian parliament, and intend in
                    like manner to be present officially at the opening of the German customs
                    parliament. In recognizing these several bodies, and assuming to be accredited
                    to the King of Prussia as their head, I act in harmony with the interests of the
                    United States, and, as I feel sure, with the wishes of the government and
                    people. I should be glad to learn from you the views of the President on the
                    points here referred to.</p>
                <p>I remain, sir, yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEO. BANCROFT.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
