<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-05-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-05-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="594" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d594">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Yeaman</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward.</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 70.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Copenhagen</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-05-28"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 28, 1867,</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have no official or reliable
                            information, nothing but telegraphic and editorial notices, of a
                            reported resolution of Congress touching the use of an <pb facs="0726" n="658" xml:id="pg_658"/> official dress or uniform by diplomatic
                            representatives of the United States. I am not in a condition to state
                            authoritatively that.any such resolution has passed, and taking the fact
                            as true, I would yet not know whether a future day was fixed for the act
                            to go into effect, nor whether Congress had presented any uniform more
                            acceptable than those now used.</p>
                        <p>I beg you to believe that I am not disposed to attribute more importance
                            to the matter than it really deserves, but, if it has been of sufficient
                            importance to demand the action of Congress, it is appropriate that
                            those whom it immediately concerns should know just what that action has
                            been. I receive scarcely half the numbers of the National Intelligencer,
                            in which the laws of the United States are published by authority, which
                            will account for my not having seen the resolution (if any such) in that
                            paper.</p>
                        <p>Desiring to comply with whatever may be the requirements of law on the
                            subject, and having, like many other representatives of the United
                            States abroad, expressed a preference for the simple dress of an
                            American citizen where it is at all permissible, I yet find in our
                            “personal instructions,” prepared by the department, this very proper
                            direction: “In performing the ceremonies connected with his official
                            reception, as well as on other formal occasions, the diplomatic
                            representative will be governed by the established usage of the country
                            in which he is to reside, and the rules prescribed for representatives
                            of his rank.” Any other course than this, pursued without the authority
                            and. direction of his government, would put a representative to a
                            manifest and useless disadvantage. I have, therefore, supposed that any
                            such resolution as the one in question ought to be officially brought to
                            the notice of the proper department or officer of the government to
                            which a representative is accredited. For most of the formal, official,
                            and semi-official occasions upon which uniforms are now worn, the
                            invitation or note granting an audience is so expressed that a
                            representative, by disregarding the established custom, would, without
                            some sufficient and authoritative reason, be thought lacking in
                            courtesy, or committing an eccentricity, neither of which would benefit
                            his government or his own standing with the government to which he is
                            accredited. I have, therefore, respectfully to request that the
                            department will furnish me with a copy of any law or resolution upon
                            this subject by Congress with an opinion whether it is deemed necessary
                            to communicate it to the proper officials of this government.</p>
                        <p>Another matter may arise for consideration upon which I would be much
                            obliged for your opinion. You will remember that at least two
                            distinguished members of the British Parliament have deemed it proper
                            and necessary for them to stay away from the official receptions and
                            dinners of the Speaker of the House of Commons, because they did not
                            approve of going in court dress, and could go in no other. When a
                            resolution of Congress, such as the one in question, is definitively
                            made known to the diplomatic representatives of the United States, and
                            by them to the governments or courts to which they are severally
                            accredited, if the courts near which they reside should not express
                            themselves entirely satisfied with the course prescribed for American
                            ministers, or should make no exception in their favor in the form of
                            invitation or grant of audience, and should continue to extend to them
                            invitations to appear on certain occasions in “gala,” can they do
                            otherwise than politely decline such invitations, giving the proper and
                            true reason for their course?</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>GEORGE H. YEAMAN.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>