<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1867-07-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1867-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="635" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d635">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. King</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward.</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 98]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1867-07-02"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 2, 1867.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: * * * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>The grand celebration of the centenary of St. Peter’s day passed off most
                            successfully. Notwithstanding the vast multitude gathered together in
                            Rome to witness the unwonted spectacle, no accident occurred, nor the
                            slightest disorder or disturbance to mar the festivities. I had never
                            seen so large or so orderly a crowd as that which assembled on the
                            Piazza del Popolo the evening of the 29th of June to enjoy the brilliant
                            display of fireworks from the Pincian hill.</p>
                        <p>Among the numerous Catholic ecclesiastics now present in Rome, there are
                            no less than 25 archbishops and bishops from the United States. They
                            called in a body to pay their respects to the Holy Father last week, and
                            the Pope embraced the occasion to speak kindly and candidly of our
                            country and of its representative at the papal court.</p>
                        <p>His Holiness has given notice of his intention to call a general council
                            of the church, to be held, as he intimated, in the fall of 1868. Great
                            importance is attached to the assembling and the action of the
                            council.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, with great respect, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>RUFUS KING.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>