<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            American Mission in Korea</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v07p2</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d221</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">221</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-04-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-04-15T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-04-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-04-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="221" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d221">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.952/4–1549: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">American Mission in Korea</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-15">April 15,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                    </gloss>
                </p>
                <p>246. Reurtel 389 Apr 14. For <gloss target="#t_urinfo1">urinfo</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> has in past taken position provisions of
                    Treaty of 1882 (Proclaimed 1883) were rendered inapplicable by series agreements
                    entered into by Korean Govt with Jap Govt during period 1904 to 1910 and that
                    Treaty therefore no longer in effect. Assuming this to be case, revival of
                    Treaty wld require Senate action. Admission that Treaty had continued in effect
                    might raise question of our failure take action under Art I thereof against
                    “unjust” and “oppressive” conduct of Japs during period annexation.</p>
                <p>If you feel Pres Rhee wld at this juncture react unfavorably to foregoing view,
                    you may consider it preferable to say that inasmuch as many details of Treaty
                    obviously been rendered inapplicable by passage of time and changed
                    circumstances this Govt believes it wld be appropriate consider negotiation new
                    treaty of friendship and commerce. You may also in your discretion inform him
                    that US adheres to principles enunciated in Art I (amity clause) of Treaty of
                    1882; in view fact Japs succeeded annexing Korea despite existence Treaty
                    however, public ref by Rhee to that provision or to Treaty in general wld appear
                    be undesirable. Altho <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> not anxious take
                    such action at this time, you may if circumstances require advise Rhee this Govt
                    prepared issue appropriate statement this subj here.<note n="1" xml:id="d221fn1">
                        <p>Mr. Muccio replied to this telegram in telegram 403, April 16, from
                            Seoul, the pertinent portion of which read as follows:</p>
                        <p>“I have just pointed out to President Rhee that inasmuch as many details
                            of the treaty of 1882 obviously inapplicable today, the US believes it
                            would be appropriate consider negotiation of new treaty of friendship
                            and commerce. I added that US adheres to principles enunciated in
                            Article I thereof but urged him not to make any public reference
                            thereto. He agreed any public reference here undesirable.…”
                            (711.952/4–1649)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
