<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="29" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d29">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 PW/2–1849</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for
                                    Occupied Areas</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Saltzman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the United
                                    States Representative on the Far Eastern Commission</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">McCoy</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-18">February 18,
                                        1949</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Trial of Japanese War Criminals (<gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>–314 Series)</p>
                            <p>In further reference to my memorandum of January 12, 1949 on the
                                above subject, you are now requested to withdraw the U.S. suggestion
                                authorized therein, and formally proposed by the U.S. Representative
                                at the meeting of Committee #5 on the same day, to the effect that
                                the entire paper <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>–314/4 be recast
                                in the form of a policy decision. You are hereby authorized to
                                support the Indian suggestion made at the same meeting, that the
                                first half of the paper only be adopted as a policy decision, the
                                second half to be left on the agenda of Committee #5 for future
                                consideration at the request of any government.</p>
                            <p>You should continue to oppose the complete withdrawal of the
                                paper.</p>
                            <p>If a question is raised again as to the nature of the Eighth Army
                                tribunals in Japan, you should reply that, since your Government has
                                withdrawn its support for the inclusion of Part 2 of the paper in
                                the policy decision, you are without final instructions as to your
                                Government’s position in the matter.</p>
                            <p>In reply to the questions raised by the New Zealand member of
                                Committee #5 on January 12, you are authorized to make the following
                                statement:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“As of February 4, 1949 Class A trials have been terminated,
                                    there being no other Class A suspects in custody, nor any whose
                                    apprehension is contemplated. The release of the former A
                                    suspects in December <pb facs="0073" n="659" xml:id="pg_659"/>
                                    was unconditional. The <gloss target="#t_IMTFE1">IMTFE</gloss>
                                    has not been formally dissolved. The action of <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> in releasing the A suspects
                                    does not of course preclude the theoretical possibility of
                                    initiating future trials if further evidence is uncovered.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>If the question is raised again as to whether a policy decision
                                terminating B and C trials in Japan would bar requests for the
                                extradition of B and C war criminals, you may state the view of your
                                Government that it would not have such an effect.</p>
                            <p>You may state, if the occasion arises, that <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> has practically completed investigation activity
                                in respect to war criminals, and that it is anticipated that all
                                trials in Japan will be terminated by April 30, 1949, except for the
                                apprehension of some of the 18 B suspects still being sought.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Saltzman</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>