<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d143</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">143</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-02-04T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-02-04T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recd8LWcmLbIIZh8o" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85116821"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Salmon</term>
                    <term ref="recdDEAik5EmT8luP" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-american-states"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007400"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Coast Guard</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recItilmdY8wKocmo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005329"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Conservation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-02-04T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-02-04T18:00:00-05:00" n="143"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.008 North Pacific/282a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-02-04T18:00:00-05:00"
                            >February 4, 1938—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>39. There are given below excerpts from accounts in the <hi rend="italic">New
                        York Times</hi> of February 2 and 3 in regard to hearing on the Dimond
                        bill,<note n="11" xml:id="d143fn11">Bill (H. R. 8982) introduced on January
                        15, 1938, by Delegate Anthony J. Dimond, of Alaska; <hi rend="italic"
                            >Congressional Record</hi>, vol. 83, pt. 1, p. 608.</note> which
                    indicate the nature of the testimony given by leading witnesses. You may
                    informally make use of this material in any manner that you think might be
                    effective: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Anthony J. Dimond, Alaska’s delegate to Congress, has introduced a bill
                            which would give this country jurisdiction over the fishing grounds
                            hundreds of miles at sea and would provide for the confiscation of
                            Japanese fishing boats taking salmon from these waters.</p>
                        <pb facs="0180" n="172" xml:id="pg_172"/>
                        <p>With other Alaskans he presented evidence to show that the Japanese, in
                            spite of official denials, had last year started taking the salmon,
                            returning to spawn in Alaskan rivers, in tremendous quantities.</p>
                        <p>Frank T. Bell, commissioner of the Bureau of Fisheries, testified to
                            receiving reports from the Coast Guard of the appearance of one of the
                            floating Japanese canneries 25 miles off shore, another 14 miles off the
                            Alaskan shore, and another 130 miles out.</p>
                        <p>This last vessel was licensed by the Japanese Government to fish in
                            Siberian waters, he said.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Bell testified that through conservation the fisheries had been built
                            up to a stable, dependable business, but that if foreign vessels did not
                            keep the conservation laws, Americans would certainly seek to violate
                            them and the fisheries would be destroyed.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Dimond placed the life of the famous Bristol Bay red salmon
                            fisheries, now yielding $12,000,000 a year, at 5 years unless the
                            Japanese were curbed.</p>
                        <p>‘I am gravely apprehensive that unless suitable legislation is passed
                            there will be armed conflict in the Bering Sea,’ he said.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Dimond warned that a private war of this type would endanger the
                            foreign relations of the United States a thousand times more than by the
                            enactment and enforcement of the legislation he proposed.</p>
                        <p>The Japanese entrance upon Alaskan salmon fisheries was assailed by H. B.
                            Friele, Alaskan salmon packer, who declared that the Japanese ‘wield a
                            two-edged sword over us’.</p>
                        <p>‘They take our fish and then, exporting to England, they take our
                            customer,’ he explained.</p>
                        <p>He said the Japanese consumed none of the red salmon, exporting it for
                            the most part to Great Britain, one of the most important customers of
                            the salmon fisheries and canneries of Alaska.</p>
                        <p>The witness presented evidence to show that in the last season the
                            Japanese had caught and packed 250,000 cases of red salmon in Bristol
                            Bay.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>For your information, the Department did not instigate the bill and has not
                    expressed views to the committee conducting the hearings and does not expect to
                    appear at the hearings unless urged by the committee to do so.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
