<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-03-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="147" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d147">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.008 North Pacific/298</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Adviser on Political
                                Relations</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Counselor of
                                the Department of State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Moore</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-03-05">March 5, 1938</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Moore</hi>: In my opinion this proposed
                            instruction to Grew<note n="12" xml:id="d147fn12"><hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi></note> represents the action which should be
                            taken.</p>
                        <p>The Department’s general plan and the substance of the proposed release
                            were assented to by Senator Schwellenbach and Mr. Dimond in the course
                            of the conference, at which I was present, in your office on February
                            14. It is my understanding that you subsequently explained the matter to
                            Senator Bone and evoked an assent by him.<note n="13" xml:id="d147fn13">Both Senators represented Washington.</note></p>
                        <p>It is also my understanding that day before yesterday Mr. McIntyre<note n="14" xml:id="d147fn14">Marvin H. McIntyre, assistant secretary to
                                President Roosevelt.</note> informed the Secretary orally that the
                            President had given an oral approval.</p>
                        <p>My greatest misgiving in regard to sending this instruction now arises
                            out of the fact of the delay which has taken place and unfortunate
                            publicity which has occurred both in Tokyo and in Washington during the
                            period of delay: the chances of acceptance by the Japanese Government of
                            the proposal which we make have been diminished.</p>
                        <p>I realize that pursuance of the course which the Department is advocating
                            is attended with certain risks from point of view of criticism within
                            administrative and political circles. I can conceive, however, of no
                            course which might possibly be taken in connection with this very thorny
                            problem which would not be attended with risks. Whatever action is taken
                            will be action on the basis of choosing among courses no one of which is
                            ideal. I know of no way in which the Department could achieve assurance
                            that the action which it takes will not later be subjected to criticism
                            and recrimination from some and perhaps several quarters.</p>
                        <pb facs="0184" n="176" xml:id="pg_176"/>
                        <p>Mr. Sturgeon and I have done our best in the making of our contribution
                            to the formulating of a line of procedure and drafting an instruction
                            the purport of which is action on that line. It is impossible for us to
                            give guarantees that the proposed course of action will not be made the
                            object of attack later by some individuals or interests. I personally
                            would not feel that I could give any such guarantees under any
                            circumstances, and I would not feel that there was absolute assurance in
                            that connection short of having approval in writing by and from all
                            important persons whose opinions with regard to the matter are
                            involved.</p>
                        <p>Frankly, it seems to me that the problem of gaining assurances, if
                            assurances must be had, can be handled only by officials between and
                            among whom the assurances would be effective.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion, I must urge that the situation as between this Government
                            and the Japanese Government in regard to this matter has become such
                            that the factor of time is becoming, in relation to the lack of value of
                            line of action which the Department has advocated, an exceedingly
                            important and perhaps even a determining factor.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanusy</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ornbeck</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>