<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-01-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.008 North Pacific/444</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Leo D. Sturgeon
                                of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-01-19">January 19, 1939</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Delegate Dimond</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Moore<note n="41" xml:id="d172fn41">R. Walton Moore, Counselor of the Department of
                                        State.</note></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Sturgeon</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>After obtaining the concurrence of Mr. Bland, Chairman of the House
                            Committee on Merchant Marine and Fisheries, Mr. Moore asked Mr. Dimond
                            to come to the Department in order that he might be given certain
                            information assembled in the Department with regard to the problem of
                            protecting coastal fisheries.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Moore mentioned that the Department had received from Mr. Bland a
                                letter<note n="42" xml:id="d172fn42">Not printed.</note> in which a
                            report on Mr. Dimond’s bill (H. R. 883, a Bill to Protect and Preserve
                            the Salmon Fisheries of Alaska, etc.) was requested and that he had
                            obtained Mr. Bland’s consent to discuss the matter orally and informally
                            with Mr. Dimond; that Mr. Bland had further assured, him that this
                            procedure would satisfactorily take the place of a written reply.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Moore stated that he was familiar with the purport and scope of Mr.
                            Dimond’s bill and had noted that it was identical with H. R. 8344,
                            introduced by Mr. Dimond during the last Congress. He then briefly
                            referred to the understanding concluded with Japan on March 25, 1938,
                            mentioned that the Japanese had thus far honored the assurances given to
                            this Government with regard to the salmon fishing activities of Japanese
                            nationals in Alaskan waters, and stated that by the terms of the
                            understanding it continued in effect.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Moore then informed Mr. Dimond that the Department has continued to
                            give study to the problem of coastal fisheries, and that the Department
                            of Commerce had been asked to prepare data showing the extent of
                            American interests in the offshore waters of other countries. He said
                            that he thought it important that we give careful attention to this
                            phase of the fishery question, in order to determine how American
                            fishing interests would be affected should we afford other countries a
                            precedent for the extension of their territorial jurisdiction. Mr. Moore
                            then asked Mr. Dimond to glance over the data supplied by the Department
                            of Commerce.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Dimond said that the data shown to him clearly indicated that
                            American fishing interests in foreign coastal waters were extensive and
                            that he realized that the Department must give consideration to <pb facs="0217" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/> this phase of the problem. He
                            thought, however, that it had been established that the situation of
                            salmon fisheries was in fact different from that of the general run of
                            fisheries, and that his bill could be defended on that ground. Mr. Moore
                            said that we were agreed that the Alaska salmon fishery could be
                            distinguished from most other fisheries but that there was the question
                            whether other countries would accept the distinction as material. He
                            said that the point with which we were especially concerned was that
                            there might be serious repercussions from unilateral action. Mr. Moore
                            also mentioned that certain existing fishery treaties might be
                            jeopardized—especially the Bering Sea fur seal treaty.<note n="43" xml:id="d172fn43">Signed at Washington, July 7, 1911, between the
                                United States, Great Britain, Japan, and Russia; <ref target="frus1911#pg_260"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1911, p. 260</ref>.</note> Mr. Dimond was
                            informed that the American share of the fur seal catch for 1938 totaled
                            $293,512 net.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Dimond said that he understood the reasons for our concern, and that
                            he appreciated the Department’s position, but that the preoccupation of
                            Japan in China caused him to believe that now; would be an admirable
                            time to enact legislation. He said that if the Department did not oppose
                            his bill he believed that Congress would pass it, and cited in support
                            of this statement the fact that Senator Copeland’s bill, of a more
                            drastic nature, easily passed in the Senate during the last
                                Congress.<note n="44" xml:id="d172fn44">Senator Royal S. Copeland,
                                Democrat, New York, introduced S. 3744, “To assert the jurisdiction
                                of the United States over certain portions of the Bering Sea and the
                                submerged land thereunder”, which passed the Senate on May 5, 1938;
                                    <hi rend="italic">Congressional Record</hi>, vol. 83, pt. 6, p.
                                6297.</note> Mr. Dimond stated, however, that he was thinking of
                            revising his bill to eliminate a “loop hole” in it which had been called
                            to his attention; that in view of this it would suit his convenience if
                            the Department refrained from making a report until it had been
                            submitted in revised form. Mr. Moore stated that we would be glad to
                            keep in touch with Mr. Dimond’s efforts.</p>
                        <p>The question of the Canadian attitude toward the proposed legislation was
                            briefly discussed. Mr. Dimond said that he was doubtful about what that
                            would be. Mr. Moore stated that the Department had kept the Canadian
                            Legation generally informed of our efforts in the fishery matter, and
                            that we should continue to do that. Mr. Sturgeon suggested that the
                            views of Canada with regard to ways and means of protecting coastal
                            fisheries may not be entirely in line with some of the views held here,
                            and that therefore it might be well to consider how we could assure
                            ourselves of Canadian cooperation toward our general objectives. Mr.
                            Moore suggested that we might at an early date have a general talk with
                            some one from the Canadian Legation.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>