<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-05-10T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-05-10T19:00:00-05:00" n="208" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d208">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24 Raw Materials/120:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-05-10T20:00:00-04:00">May 10, 1939—8
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>349. The price basis for the rubber–tin, cotton–wheat deal must be a
                                fair one, otherwise all the good results hoped for from this
                                agreement will be jeopardized. I certainly hope that the British
                                authorities will not try to burden us, in determining the terms of
                                exchange, with tie extremely high prices that the tin control in
                                particular has created during the past few months by its excessively
                                severe limitation of production. The same is true only to a lesser
                                degree in the case of rubber. In marked contrast is the fact that
                                the prices of cotton and wheat during the same period have been
                                abnormally low and quite below the costs of production. General
                                recognition of the fact that prevailing prices for cotton and wheat
                                have been unjustifiably low is indicated by the universal
                                expectation, in consuming countries as well as elsewhere, that the
                                fair price ranges to be sought in connection with international
                                control agreements affecting cotton and wheat, if they can be
                                established, would be substantially higher than recently prevailing
                                prices.</p>
                            <p>Disappointment will result if the quantities exchanged are not
                                substantially greater than those that would result from the exchange
                                of only 500,000 bales of cotton and corresponding amounts of rubber
                                and tin. If and as the British Government substantially enlarges its
                                ideas on the acquisition of cotton, consideration may be given to
                                adjustments in the basis of exchange.</p>
                            <pb facs="0253" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/>
                            <p>Many completely reliable indications have come to the Department that
                                various private interests, particularly rubber traders in London,
                                are busily at work criticizing the contemplated exchange and also
                                conjuring up false fears as to its effect upon ordinary trade in the
                                commodities concerned. They are actually busily contacting the press
                                in this country. Whether their moving motive is the thought that
                                they might lose a certain amount of commission business, or whether
                                their interest is in speculative price movements I will not attempt
                                to judge. However, if you find it useful, you may mention to the
                                British Government the unpleasant impression produced by the
                                evidences of their activity.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>