<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-09-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-09-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="222" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24 Raw Materials/308:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-09-06">September 6, 1939</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>811. Your 1424, September 4, 1 p.m.,<note n="50" xml:id="d222fn50"><ref target="frus1939v01#pg_928">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 928</ref>.</note> and 1442, September 4, 11
                                p.m. Reporters here claim to have rumors that the British Government
                                does not wish to proceed with the rubber–cotton agreement. We have
                                expressed the opinion strongly that there can be no foundation for
                                this report, and have pointed out that both Governments will now be
                                even more anxious than before to build up stocks.</p>
                            <p>There is of course concern in the markets as to whether the stocks
                                acquired will now be held as reserves. You can assure the Ministry
                                of Supply that this Government has every intention of holding the
                                stocks acquired in reserve. So far as we can see, the only situation
                                which would counsel release of these stocks would be a cutting off
                                or drastic reduction of current supplies of rubber from the East. It
                                might be useful for us to have some indication from the British
                                Government as to its intentions with respect to the stocks of cotton
                                to be acquired under the agreement.</p>
                            <p>The Maritime Commission is of the opinion that sufficient United
                                States shipping could be made available to carry the normal supplies
                                of rubber and tin from the East to this country as well as all the
                                rubber supplied under the agreement, provided these commodities are
                                available in reasonable quantities at reasonable intervals, and
                                subject always of course to the possibility that unforeseen
                                situations may develop requiring prior allocation of available
                                tonnage. Before definite commitments could be made for such
                                movements, it would be essential to have information specifying
                                amounts, ports of shipment, destinations, and loading dates. Word
                                from Singapore indicates that a temporary shortage of bottoms is
                                likely, despite precautionary British measures, but that American
                                and Netherland vessels now plying between Singapore and the United
                                States afford sufficient space for all normal tin and rubber
                                shipments.</p>
                            <p>Regarding cases, this Government will accept no. 9 cases to the
                                extent necessary, although it strongly prefers no. 10’s for storage
                                and rotation purposes. Further communication from the British
                                Government will be appreciated if it eventually appears necessary to
                                ship in bales.</p>
                            <p>Also, this Government is prepared to accept some no. 1 rubber if it
                                is considered unwise to limit purchases to no. 1–X at present. This
                                Government requests, however, that the amount of no. 1 be limited to
                                20 percent of the total, the rest to be no. 1–X, for shipment during
                                the <pb facs="0272" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/> first month or two,
                                and that the situation be reexamined before further purchases of no.
                                1 are made. In this regard, you should secure confirmation of the
                                understanding set forth in our no. 759, September 2, 1939,<note n="51" xml:id="d222fn51">Not printed.</note> before agreeing to
                                the modification requested. It will also be appreciated if the
                                British will supply us with information from time to time as to
                                actual or prospective market reactions.</p>
                            <p>United States consuls in the East will be instructed to issue a
                                certificate accepting responsibility for war risk when they receive
                                copies of bills of lading and weight notes. Inquiry is being made
                                regarding the form used by the National City Bank in Singapore.</p>
                            <p>For your information, Singapore advised, on August 30,<note n="52" xml:id="d222fn52">Telegram of August 30, 5 p.m., not
                                    printed.</note> that rubber interests anticipate and favor
                                continuing restriction during war conditions, with at least 10
                                percent increase of quota on outbreak of war. They expect no
                                shortage of supplies for the United States unless English reserves
                                necessitate requisition, which they consider improbable. They report
                                that tin smelting interests expect abandonment of quota control
                                during war but that traders anticipate the maintenance of
                                restriction with an immediate 10 percent quota increase on outbreak
                                of hostilities. All agree that mine head stocks equivalent to 10,000
                                tons will be permitted to move freely and will be adequate for
                                several months.</p>
                            <p>Batavia advised, on August 31,<note n="53" xml:id="d222fn53">Telegram
                                    of August 31, 11 a.m., not printed.</note> of the general belief
                                there that the international rubber agreement will be suspended if
                                actual hostilities occur. Some rubber producers believe that quotas
                                will be increased from 60 to 70 percent in the last quarter of this
                                year and to 80 percent in the first quarter of 1940.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>