<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Belgium ( (Wilson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d390</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">390</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="390"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d390">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5531/921</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Belgium</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 570</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Brussels</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-12-21">December 21,
                            1939</date>.<lb/>[Received January 11, 1940.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Adverting to my telegram No. 221, of December 19,
                    1939, 1 p.m.,<note n="16" xml:id="d390fn16">Not printed.</note> I have the honor
                    to inform the Department that Mr. de Fontaine of the Foreign Office called at
                    the Embassy on December 19 in order to tell me that his Government has now
                    completed the list of Belgian products, additional to those enumerated by the
                    Government of the United States, on which it plans to request concessions during
                    the contemplated negotiations for the revision of the trade agreement of 1935.
                    He assured me that this list will be forwarded this week by air-mail to the
                    Belgian Embassy at Washington for the perusal of the Belgian Ambassador and of
                    Mr. Grenade, the Commercial Attaché, and expressed the opinion that before
                    transmitting this list officially to the Department of State the Belgian Embassy
                        <pb facs="0446" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/> may desire to discuss it
                    informally with the appropriate officials of the Department. It was possible,
                    added Mr. de Fontaine, that during this period the Belgian Government might
                    desire to make minor alterations in the list by adding or withdrawing one or two
                    products. He believed, however, that this could be done if necessary by cable
                    without difficulty. It would appear, therefore, in the light of the above
                    information that the supplementary list will reach Washington about the first of
                    January.</p>
                <p>With reference to the place where the negotiations will be held, Mr. de Fontaine
                    expressed to me again the hope that they would take place in Brussels, as in the
                    present difficult circumstances it would be almost impossible for the Belgian
                    Government to send representatives to Washington. He was of the opinion that if
                    the American counter-proposals for the general provisions of the revised treaty
                    and the list of requests for tariff concessions should arrive at an early date,
                    they could receive the consideration of the Belgian authorities simultaneously
                    with the completion of the necessary formalities incidental to the submission of
                    the Belgian supplementary list of products to the United States Government. This
                    would tend to expedite the commencement of the negotiations.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Orme Wilson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[Preparations for the negotiation of a new trade agreement continued into
                        1940 until, on April 17, 1940, the Trade Agreements Committee met and
                        concluded (1) that a comprehensive agreement should not be attempted, but
                        only a revision of the existing instrument with concentration on a
                        relatively small number of items of first-rank trade importance; and (2)
                        that a formula should be worked out whereby the agreement could be more
                        rapidly adjusted to war and post-war conditions (611.5531/943). The invasion
                        of Belgium by Germany put an end to these trade agreement discussions.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
