<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d450</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">450</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-03-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-03-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="450"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d450">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.248/159½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-03-11">March 11,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The French Ambassador called to see me this morning at my request. I told the
                    Ambassador that I had asked him to come in in order to deliver to him a message
                    from the President, but that in order that the Ambassador could understand fully
                    the question regarding which I wanted to speak to him, I wished to give him a
                    brief résumé of the incidents involved in the project of Mr. Wertheimer and
                    Senator de la Grange. I then informed the Ambassador that I had heard Wertheimer
                    named some six weeks ago at the time of the visit to the United States of the
                    French aviation mission and that I had at that time inquired of the Ambassador
                    whether he had any connection with that mission. I reminded the Ambassador that
                    he had told me there was no connection whatever. The Ambassador replied that he
                    remembered the incident perfectly and confirmed what he had then told me. I then
                    informed the Ambassador of Mr. Bullitt’s recent telegrams on the subject and of
                    the nature of the Department’s replies to those telegrams.</p>
                <p>I told the Ambassador that the specific reason for my seeing him, since I
                    understood that Senator de la Grange was coming to Washington immediately after
                    his arrival in New York with a letter addressed to the Ambassador explaining the
                    purpose of his mission, was to ask the Ambassador to tell him that the
                    President, although Senator de la Grange had been a personal friend of the
                    President’s for more than twenty-five years, did not feel able to receive him so
                    long as he was in the United States on this particular errand. The President, I
                    said, would always be glad to receive him as a personal friend but not <pb
                        facs="0515" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/> when he came to the United States in
                    furtherance of this particular project. I emphasized to the Ambassador the
                    various points contained in the Department’s telegraphic instruction No. 150 of
                    March 10, 6 p.m. to Ambassador Bullitt<note n="46a" xml:id="d450fn46a">Not
                        printed.</note> and the Ambassador said that he understood the situation
                    fully and concurred emphatically in the position taken by this Government. The
                    Ambassador said that it happened that Senator de la Grange had for long been a
                    personal friend of himself and of his family and that it would be very easy for
                    him to explain to him personally the situation and the reasons for the
                    President’s request. I expressed to the Ambassador my appreciation of his
                    interest in the matter and of his willingness to transmit this message.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador spoke at some length on the European situation and on the Far
                    Eastern situation but gave me no information which we had not received with the
                    exception of one item of interest. The Ambassador told me that he had just had a
                    report from his Foreign Office transmitting a communication from the French
                    Consul General in Munich,<note n="47" xml:id="d450fn47">Louis Jousset.</note>
                    whom the Ambassador considered to be one of the ablest French representatives in
                    Germany, and in this communication the Consul General had stated that at a
                    recent private meeting which Hitler had had with some high German officials and
                    with some army generals Hitler had stated that in view of the conditions in
                    Germany and the general European situation, Germany would unquestionably have to
                    resort to war and he pled for the devotion and loyal support of those present.
                    The Ambassador remarked that this kind of information was very different from
                    the optimistic impressions being given to his Government by the British
                        Ambassador<note n="48" xml:id="d450fn48">Sir Nevile Henderson.</note> in
                    Berlin and that it also seemed to be entirely counter to the desires and
                    policies of Marshal Goering.<note n="49" xml:id="d450fn49">Hermann Göring,
                        German Reich Air Minister.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
