<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-04-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-04-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="525" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d525">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">611.623/396</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Deputy
                                    Commissioner of Customs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">W. R.
                                    Johnson</hi>)<note n="28" xml:id="d525fn28">Copy transmitted to
                                    the Department of State by the Treasury Department on May
                                    3.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-04-21">April 21,
                                    1939</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Dr. Tannenberg, First Secretary of the German Embassy, called at my
                                office this morning to discuss the outstanding countervailing duty
                                order against German imports. He stated that he was fully authorized
                                by his government in all that he would say.</p>
                            <p>He first asked whether it would be possible to clear importations
                                without the additional 25 per cent deposit if they were financed
                                solely in dollars or free reichsmarks. I advised him that this had
                                been thoroughly considered but no practical procedure had been
                                devised.</p>
                            <p>Tannenberg then said that his government is convinced that it will
                                have virtually no trade with the United States if the order stands
                                without modification, and that Germany does not want this result.
                                His careful study of the order, the Attorney General’s opinion, and
                                the practices which occasioned the order has satisfied him that
                                there remains no practical way for Germany to assist her exports to
                                the United States without incurring countervailing duties. He stated
                                that if shipments to which their formal assurances made through the
                                Department of State clearly applied could be cleared through customs
                                without the 25 per cent additional deposit, Germany is prepared to
                                repeal and prohibit completely, “today, if necessary”, all decrees,
                                regulations, and practices under which the “barter” procedures have
                                been carried on; to prohibit effectively any practice or procedure
                                for offsetting the disadvantages to German exports resulting from
                                our dollar devaluation; and to prevent exports to the United States
                                unless the transactions are financed solely in free exchange and
                                without price <pb facs="0580" n="572" xml:id="pg_572"/> manipulation
                                of any kind. He did not make it clear, but I understood these
                                proposals to relate to dutiable merchandise, since free goods are
                                not subject to countervailing duties.</p>
                            <p>Tannenberg seemed anxious for an early response to his proposals but
                                stated that he, of course, did not expect any reply from me today. I
                                made it clear that, in my opinion, complete revocation of the order
                                could not be considered since Germany could not now stop or recall
                                subsidies applying to goods beyond its control.</p>
                            <p>Several times during the conversation Dr. Tannenberg remarked that
                                unless we would assume that his government proposes to act in entire
                                good faith his visit could have no purpose.</p>
                            <p>In reply to my inquiries Tannenberg estimated the volume of dutiable
                                German imports into the United States recently financed without
                                subsidies at 40 per cent of the total. He estimated that this
                                volume, plus a third of the remainder, or a total of 60 per cent of
                                the past volume of trade, could be continued on a no-subsidy basis
                                if the 25 per cent deposit were eliminated. The remaining 40 per
                                cent, he said, is lost beyond recovery, since it cannot be carried
                                on without some assistance.</p>
                            <closer><signed>W. R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>