<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-06-22T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-06-22T10:00:00-05:00" n="539" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d539">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">862.4016/2118: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Germany</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-06-22T16:00:00+01:00">June 22, 1939—4
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received June 22—1:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>537. This morning’s Berlin papers carry brief summaries of an order
                                issued yesterday in Prague by the Reich protector which is designed
                                to “Aryanize” the economic life of the protectorate of Bohemia and
                                Moravia and which it is stated will replace miscellaneous
                                provisional measures hitherto taken to eliminate Jewish influence in
                                that region.</p>
                            <p>This order which enters into effect today provides that Jews, Jewish
                                undertakings or Jewish associations require the express written
                                Approval of the Reich protector to have the right of disposal over
                                real property, business partnerships, stocks and bonds and leased
                                properties irrespective of the legal nature of Jewish interests in
                                such matters. For the administration of Jewish businesses the Reich
                                protector may appoint special trustees who shall be responsible to
                                the Reich protector himself and may recall agents or administrators
                                who have already been named for this purpose. In the case of
                                enterprises employing less than one hundred workers or having an
                                annual turnover of less than 3 million crowns, with the exception of
                                banks and insurance companies, the powers of the Reich protector in
                                the above respects may be entrusted to the Oberlandraete.</p>
                            <p>Jews are required to register with the National Bank by July 31, 1939
                                their holdings of precious metals and stones, it being stated
                                however that a surrender of these valuables is not envisaged.</p>
                            <p>Transfers of property made by Jews subsequent of March 17, 1939 are
                                declared to be legally invalid unless approved by the Reich
                                protector or the competent authorities.</p>
                            <p>Attempts to circumvent the order may be punished by imprisonment up
                                to 10 years as well as by confiscation of the property in <pb facs="0596" n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/> question. Cases of this
                                nature will be dealt with by the German Courts in the protectorate
                                on the basis of the general provision of German law and the German
                                penal code.</p>
                            <p>The definition of Jews under the order is substantially the same as
                                that set forth in the Nuremburg Racial legislation of 1935, that is
                                “Jews” are persons with three or more full blooded Jewish
                                grandparents or persons with two Jewish grandparents who belong to
                                the Jewish religion or are married to full blooded Jews.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to London for Pell.<note n="56" xml:id="d539fn56">Robert
                                    Pell, Assistant to Director of the Intergovernmental Committee
                                    for Refugees.</note></p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>