<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-08-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="756" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d756">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">352.0022/83</note>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under
                                        Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-08-07">August 7,
                                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>The Spanish Chargé d’Affaires called to see me this afternoon by
                                    instruction of his Government. He said that his Government had
                                    been <pb facs="0791" n="783" xml:id="pg_783"/> informed that the
                                    Government of Chile was once more taking steps in order to
                                    obtain the active support of all of the American Republics in
                                    behalf of the contention of Chile that under the rules of
                                    diplomatic asylum which should be accorded political refugees
                                    the present Government of Spain had no right to demand of the
                                    Chilean Chargé d’Affaires in Madrid the surrender to the
                                    judicial authorities of Spain of the eighteen political refugees
                                    now sheltered in the Chilean Embassy. The Spanish Government had
                                    likewise heard that the Chilean Government was endeavoring to
                                    obtain the consent of the United States Government to mediate in
                                    the dispute which had arisen between the Spanish Government and
                                    the Chilean Government, and it desired this Government to be
                                    informed in the most friendly manner that the Spanish Government
                                    would not find it possible to accept mediation in this question
                                    on the part of any other Government since it believed that it
                                    was entirely a question involving the national sovereignty of
                                    Spain.</p>
                                <p>I told the Chargé d’Affaires that I had discussed this question
                                    with the Spanish Ambassador some six weeks prior to the
                                    departure of the latter from the United States, and I had
                                    explained to him at that time that the United States Government
                                    had made it clear at the Inter-American Conferences of 1928 and
                                    of 1933 that it could not subscribe to inter-American
                                    conventions providing for the right of diplomatic asylum since
                                    this Government did not acknowledge such right within the United
                                    States and since this Government had further refused to
                                    authorize its diplomatic representatives in foreign countries to
                                    extend the right of asylum to refugees who sought shelter within
                                    American embassies and legations. I said that in consequence of
                                    this traditional practice on the part of the United States, this
                                    Government had stated, when it had been approached by the
                                    Government of Chile some two months ago on this subject, that it
                                    could not support the position of the Government of Chile and
                                    that, for the same reason, it would find it impossible to make
                                    any representations to the Spanish Government in the matter.</p>
                                <p>I stated that I was somewhat surprised by this message delivered
                                    to me today by the Spanish Chargé d’Affaires as I had taken it
                                    for granted, since I had heard nothing further on the matter
                                    from the Chilean Government for at least six weeks, that the
                                    question had been amicably settled through direct negotiations
                                    between Chile and Spain. The Chargé d’Affaires replied that he
                                    was equally surprised upon receiving this message from his
                                    Government since he likewise had taken it for granted that the
                                    situation had been adjusted.</p>
                                <p>Señor de Silva said that the Spanish Under Secretary of State,
                                    Señor Barcenas, had spoken to him about the matter before the
                                    Chargé’s departure from Spain and had given him to understand
                                        <pb facs="0792" n="784" xml:id="pg_784"/> that while some of
                                    the refugees in the Chilean Embassy were writers and
                                    intellectuals against whom the present Spanish Government had
                                    nothing, there were one or two of the individuals who had taken
                                    refuge who were accused of criminal acts and that it was these
                                    latter that the Spanish Government felt it necessary to submit
                                    to the courts of trial. I told the Spanish Chargé that as he
                                    undoubtedly knew, the repercussions of this incident had been
                                    very considerable throughout the American continent and that I
                                    regretted, therefore, the fact that the matter had not been
                                    settled in a satisfactory way.</p>
                                <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed></closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>