<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d761</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">761</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-01-02T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-01-02T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recZPVvCSdB8G01JR" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-01-02T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-01-02T12:00:00-05:00" n="761"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d761">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.48/364: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-01-02T17:00:00+00:00"
                            >January [<hi rend="italic">February</hi>] 2, 1939—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 6:12 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>190. Your 63, February 1, 7 p.m. We are informed by the Foreign Office that while
                    the Franco-Spanish frontier is closed to refugees in <pb facs="0796" n="788"
                        xml:id="pg_788"/> practice it is wide open and since the fall of Barcelona
                    upwards of 60,000 refugees have been permitted to enter France from Catalonia.
                    The frontier is closed because France does not wish to encourage the entrance of
                    a large number of Spanish refugees who could be provided for in Spain. For
                    obvious reasons with the presence in France of some 3,500,000 foreigners
                    including almost 100,000 refugees from Central Europe the French authorities do
                    not wish to further complicate a difficult problem. Of the 60,000 admitted it is
                    estimated that from 45,000 to 50,000 are women and children. In addition to the
                    latter old and wounded men have been and are being admitted together with a
                    certain number of male refugees of military age whose lives are considered
                    menaced because of political reasons. An undetermined number have entered
                    clandestinely.</p>
                <p>It is also estimated that there remain on the Spanish side of the frontier
                    approximately 500,000 persons who would cross to France if permitted. During the
                    past 3 days about 8,000 persons daily have crossed into France. The French are
                    exerting themselves to stem the tide and to cooperate with the Figueras
                    authorities in persuading the population to remain in Spain.</p>
                <p>The French also plan to cooperate with the Spanish authorities in feeding the
                    destitute in the frontier area.</p>
                <p>Frontier control is in the hands of the Ministry of the Interior and the military
                    authorities and General Falgade, the commanding officer of the
                    Pyrenees-Orientales district who has charge of 50,000 troops, has detailed
                    approximately 10,000 men to assist in the reception of the refugees and also in
                    preventing a disorderly influx. The transport of the refugees to various French
                    departments removed from the frontier is organized and we understand that there
                    is no important congestion on the French side of the line. The bulk of the
                    refugees are being housed in available public buildings of one sort or another
                    such as schools and colleges and in private properties placed at the disposal of
                    the government or requisitioned for the purpose, monasteries convents, et
                    cetera.</p>
                <p>The problem is one of course which carries with it a burden of expense to the
                    French Government. For that reason we are informed the Government would welcome
                    contributions of foodstuffs for use in the nourishment of the refugees. We are
                    informed by the Acting Agricultural Attaché that he has received a telegraphic
                    inquiry from his department desiring to know whether the French Government would
                    welcome donations of foodstuffs. That question is answered in the affirmative
                    and it is also understood from our conversations with the responsible officer of
                    the Foreign Office that there should be no difficulty concerning the free entry
                    of such material into France.</p>
                <pb facs="0797" n="789" xml:id="pg_789"/>
                <p>The French authorities are exercising great care in respect of sanitation and the
                    necessary steps are being taken to prevent the spread of contagion.</p>
                <p>The utter confusion and panic which have existed in eastern Catalonia over a
                    period of days has brought to hundreds of innocent people particularly women,
                    children, and the infirm untold privation and suffering. Children have been
                    frozen to death and many have died of hardship and want. Still others have gone
                    insane and have fallen ill from the terrors and the fatigue of the exodus. I am
                    informed by the representative of the American Friends Service Committee which
                    is active in the distribution of foodstuffs that the work of organizing the
                    lodging and feeding of refugees in France is progressing very satisfactorily and
                    that the Government is assisted by a number of private relief organizations.
                    France, of course, is making an important contribution to alleviate their
                    suffering and extend them hospitality. I feel strongly that the situation is one
                    which should appeal to American charity and that any contribution which we may
                    be able to make to relieve these unfortunates will be fully justified.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
