<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in France ( (Leahy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d113</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">113</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-04-03T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-04-03T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ioEdqM9tjA4Dt" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85012460"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bauxite</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="minerals-and-metals" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85012460" lcsh-match="exact">Bauxite</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-04-03T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-04-03T17:00:00-05:00" n="113"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d113">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/9562a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Leahy</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-04-03T17:00:00-05:00"
                            >April 3, 1941—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>291. This morning’s cable (my 290 of April 3, 2 p.m.) has given deep cause for
                    reflection and I wish in the first conversation you may have alone with Marshal
                    Petain you would express to him that since early February there have been
                    developments in French foreign policy which seem to indicate that certain
                    elements of the Government are willing to collaborate much further with Germany
                    than the terms of the armistice demand. While General Huntziger’s activities are
                    less obvious to the foreigner the policy of Admiral Darlan with his openly
                    spoken anti-British bias and particularly his personal animosity against the
                    British Navy has caused us to analyze each of his actions in the light of his
                    association with the Maréchal. Our information indicates that the French
                    factories both in occupied and unoccupied France are under urgent orders to
                    produce not only for French military establishments but to a greater extent for
                    German delivery airplanes and/or airplane parts. We understand furthermore that
                    to facilitate this agreement, fully known to Admiral Darlan, executives of
                    French aviation factories have been released from prison.</p>
                <p>We understand undertakings for the delivery of French bauxite production to
                    Germany are to be increased.</p>
                <p>We understand by agreement of Admiral Darlan there are deliveries due to Italy of
                    some 20,000 tons of gasoline.</p>
                <p>The American press has carried generally Admiral Darlan’s repeated declarations
                    to convoy French shipping if necessary even should this entail resistance
                    against the British Navy. Our information leads us to believe that the sums
                    being expended on the French Navy far exceed those which are called for either
                    by needs of a peaceful France or the present needs of the French Government.</p>
                <p>While there exists every desire in this country to believe the Maréchal in his
                    direction of the French Government has no desire to go beyond the minimum
                    collaboration imposed by the terms of the armistice, we are inclined to doubt
                    that he may be aware of certain acts on the part of his associates in the
                    Government and of the adverse impression which these acts are creating in this
                    country.</p>
                <pb facs="0155" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/>
                <p>You will note that other incidents which might be cited in this connection such
                    as German infiltration into French Morocco and other questions which have formed
                    the subject of recent instructions to you are not touched upon here, but I must
                    re-emphasize this Government can only serve the cause of France and the French
                    people if the French Government keeps within the limitations and obligations of
                    the Armistice terms.</p>
                <p>Your telegrams seem to confirm our opinion of the Maréchal and we trust that this
                    will make it possible for you to raise very freely in your discussions with
                    Petain our doubts as to the real purpose of Admiral Darlan’s policy and the
                    significance of his actions.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
