<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-06-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="194" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d194">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War
                                1939/2815½</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The French Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Henry-Haye</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-06-03">June 3,
                                    1941</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: Referring to the
                                memorandum initialed at Algiers February 26, 1941, by General
                                Weygand and Mr. Robert Murphy, as well as to the letter sent by
                                Admiral Darlan on March 10, 1941, to Admiral Leahy, I have the honor
                                to confirm to Your Excellency that the guarantees formulated in
                                those documents will apply to the goods listed in the attached
                                    program,<note n="49a" xml:id="d194fn49a">Not attached to file
                                    copy.</note> which concerns the needs of French North Africa in
                                import products of first urgency.</p>
                            <p>Accordingly, the French Government undertakes not to build up
                                excessive stocks of the said goods in French North Africa and to
                                take all pertinent measures with a view to assuring that these
                                products and like products will be consumed in French North Africa
                                and will not be reexported therefrom in any form.</p>
                            <p>The performance of these undertakings will be checked upon by the
                                representatives that the American Government shall have designated
                                for this purpose. The latter will receive all facilities with a view
                                to the carrying out of their mission, the practical forms of the <pb facs="0252" n="240" xml:id="pg_240"/> control could, moreover
                                form the subject of a subsequent understanding, if such is
                                necessary, between our two Governments.</p>
                            <p>French vessels, stationed in ports of America, which are or shall be
                                assigned to transportation of goods as a result of this agreement,
                                shall be returned to their port of departure in America in case they
                                should cease to be used for such transportation. The return voyage
                                of each vessel to America must be made within the shortest possible
                                space of time after the discharging of its cargo in North African
                                ports.</p>
                            <p>Moreover, it is understood that the United States is disposed to give
                                all possible facilities for the continuance of this traffic and that
                                it will use its good offices to obtain from the British Government
                                the assurance that no vessel actually employed in this traffic will
                                be seized or held by the action of the British authorities.</p>
                            <p>Failing such guarantee, the French Government would find itself in
                                the impossibility of carrying out the obligations contracted in
                                these agreements.</p>
                            <p>The French vessels used for direct transportation of goods between
                                the United States and French North Africa shall not take on board
                                any passenger except with the previous approval of the American
                                Government. They shall not transport any letter or correspondence,
                                of any nature whatever.</p>
                            <p>A complete list of the cargo of each vessel leaving a North African
                                port shall be communicated, three days before its sailing, to the
                                representative of the United States nearest to the port of
                                departure. Vessels sailing for ports of the United States or other
                                territories of America shall go directly to their destination and
                                they may take on only natural or manufactured products of French
                                North Africa, unless it be with the approval of the American
                                Government, which has been sought in the course of numerous recent
                                conversations.</p>
                            <p>The settlement for the sums due by American importers shall be made
                                to the credit of the special N. A. account opened in the name of the
                                French Government by the French American Banking Corporation in New
                                York. This account may not be used except in conformity with
                                agreements entered into or to be entered into by the United States
                                Treasury and this Embassy.</p>
                            <p>The requests made by the Department of State concerning, on the one
                                hand the exportation of a certain quantity of olive oil from North
                                Africa to the United States, and on the other the undertaking not to
                                export ores of cobalt and Molybdenum from Morocco, are now the
                                subject of careful examination on the part of the French Government.
                                I hope to be in a position soon to communicate to Your Excellency my
                                Government’s reply on these two points.</p>
                            <p>In conclusion, I think I must call your attention to the fact that
                                the attached program applies only to the most urgent needs of French
                                    <pb facs="0253" n="241" xml:id="pg_241"/> North Africa. It would
                                be highly desirable that a definitive agreement be entered into as
                                soon as possible between our two Governments in order to give to the
                                supply of French North Africa the indispensable scope and regularity
                                and all the value which is attributed to it by the French
                                Government.</p>
                            <p>I should be grateful if Your Excellency would be good enough to
                                confirm to me your agreement with the terms of this letter.</p>
                            <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry-Haye</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>