<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Leahy) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-09-25T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-09-25T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="reclnawDbQgAFDvnc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85101098"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Phosphates</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recebl4V1INuqlVGh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090254" lcsh-match="exact">Palm oil</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="food" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Foodstuffs</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recfrz0b94d87k9th" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-engineering" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092968" lcsh-match="exact">Engineering</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-assistance-and-sales" lcsh-match="no_match">Munitions</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-25T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-25T09:00:00-05:00" n="377"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d377">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War 1939/3519: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Leahy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vichy</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-25T16:00:00+02:00"
                            >September 25, 1941—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received September 26—6:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1225. Department’s telegram 704, September 18, 7 p.m. Careful consideration has
                    been given to the highly important question of policy presented in the
                    Department’s telegram under reference. I may wish to supplement this telegram
                    after receipt of Murphy’s views and after further conversations with high
                    officials of the French Government. Meanwhile, since the problem presented
                    appears to be of urgency the following is submitted:</p>
                <p>As to the five specific points of criticism:</p>
                <p>1. As the Department is aware from previous telegrams (for instance, Embassy’s
                    telegram 251, February 28, 8 p.m.<note n="77" xml:id="d377fn77">Not
                        printed.</note>) under specific agreement with Germany certain percentages
                    of colonial products ranging from 12½ percent to 50 percent arriving at
                    Marseille are to be delivered to Germany. The French Government has not
                    concealed the general terms of this agreement from us. Actual deliveries of such
                    products as palm oil, peanut oil, and phosphates, we understand, have fallen far
                    under the original estimates owing to transport and other difficulties in
                    getting the products to Marseille. (The Department will recall that in return
                    Germany was to furnish France with certain quantities of potatoes and sugar
                    which have likewise been far below the amounts promised.) In addition, however,
                    there seems little doubt that in practice substantial percentages of foodstuffs
                    arriving from overseas eventually find their way from Marseille to Germany. This
                    seems particularly true of Algerian wine and mutton. The same applies to such
                    raw materials as crude rubber (some 1,700 tons which arrived at Marseille, as
                    the Embassy has previously reported) and probably Algerian wool. The Germans
                    apparently operate largely through purchase made by private French
                    intermediaries rather than through official direct requisitions so that reliable
                    estimates are difficult to obtain.</p>
                <p>I feel that there is probably some exaggeration as to the quantities of colonial
                    products obtained by the Germans at Marseille, but there is no doubt that there
                    is considerable leakage.</p>
                <p>2. Of the reports of deliveries of trucks and other materials to German military
                    authorities in North Africa, Murphy is in a better position to furnish the exact
                    figures than I can ascertain in Vichy. His previous telegrams have indicated
                    that trucks in quantity have been <pb facs="0449" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/>
                    delivered from North Africa. Weygand seems to resist such deliveries to the best
                    of his ability.</p>
                <p>3. The stories which the Department states emanate “from Vichy sources” as to a
                    wholesale shift of personnel in North Africa are, as far as I can learn, grossly
                    exaggerated. (It would be helpful in my search for information to know just who
                    these sources are if the Department is in a position to inform me.) Careful
                    investigation leads me to believe that, while there have been and necessarily
                    will be changes in personnel, they are not on the scale reported, nor are key
                    posts being filled by “100 percent collaborationists”. For instance, General
                    Koeltz, who was personally known to a member of my staff and who left Vichy
                    recently to take command in Algiers, was not considered to be pro-German; in
                    fact, his direct contact with Armistice Commission decisions could hardly have
                    led him to have much faith in the possibilities of any real Franco-German
                    collaboration under present conditions. Similarly, reports on General de Lattre
                    de Tassigny, who took over yesterday as Commandant in Tunis, indicate that he is
                    anything but a collaborationist. The reports, as the Department will recall, on
                    General Juin are contradictory though since his arrival to take command in
                    Morocco he does not appear to have shown any collaborationist tendencies and his
                    earlier reported advocacy of views in that direction may have been merely with
                    the object of obtaining his release from a German prison camp.</p>
                <p>As against this of course there is the ousting of Monick for whom the Germans
                    have long been gunning and which unquestionably represents a concession to their
                    demands.</p>
                <p>4. As the Department is aware, during the period last May and early June when
                    German pressure was at its height, there was much insistence that the French
                    undertake a military operation to retake dissident colonies in Africa. As the
                    Department is also aware, Weygand (and in this he appears to have had Darlan’s
                    support) effectively resisted the German demands, or at least succeeded in
                    postponing action thereon, by showing conclusively that any such operation was
                    unfeasible, owing to climatic conditions, prior to October. Investigation here
                    leads me to believe that there is strong opposition, not only from Weygand but
                    also from General Huntziger,<note n="78" xml:id="d377fn78">Gen. Charles Léon
                        Huntzíger, French Minister of War.</note> to any such movement now. In fact
                    there is considerable reluctance shown here to any plan, inevitably unpopular,
                    which would involve taking the initiative in sending Frenchmen to fight
                    Frenchmen, and it will be remembered that this fratricidal aspect was the
                    principal source of Vichy bitterness over the British move against Syria. (This
                    does not of course in any sense imply that the forces loyal to the Vichy
                    Government will not resist to the full any further Gaullist attack against
                    French West Africa.) In addition to private investigation showing the lack of
                    any such plans for an attack on Africa, my Military Attaché has received an
                    official denial of any such plans at the War Ministry and Rochat has given us a
                    similar denial at the Foreign Office.</p>
                <p>5. There is no doubt that the French have for some time, as the Department points
                    out, been strengthening their defenses in West Africa; but official sources,
                    even friendly ones, are of course reluctant <pb facs="0450" n="438"
                        xml:id="pg_438"/> to talk. We are told by a reliable source that two
                    battalions of the French Foreign Legion have recently arrived at Dakar and that
                    plans are being made to send a Senegalese infantry regiment and a Madagascan
                    engineering battalion by the end of this month. Two antitank corps are reported
                    to be in process of formation and are slated to be sent to Dakar as soon as they
                    are completely equipped. Apparently quantities of munitions, aviation bombs and
                    gasoline, as well as bridging materials, have been sent from metropolitan France
                    to Dakar, and the air army units there have also been reinforced. Similarly,
                    work is reported to be progressing on a number of air fields in North Africa,
                    although we have received no official confirmation of this. There is little
                    doubt, in my opinion, that the primary purpose in this military reinforcement of
                    Dakar is to defend that portion of the French Empire from any further De Gaulle
                    or British attack, or if need be, against a similar move by the United States.
                    This seems obvious since a German move would not come from the sea, in view of
                    the distance of Senegal from any present German-occupied base, and would
                    probably not take place until North Africa had been occupied by Axis forces.</p>
                <p>It is assumed that America’s present attitude toward the African colonies was
                    taken with a thought that when he is faced with a decision, Weygand either with
                    or without the Marshal’s orders might determine to resist by force of arms a
                    German move to North Africa; whether this premise proves to be right or
                    wrong—and only time and future events can tell—presumably the quantities of
                    supplies which we are now furnishing French Africa or may furnish in the future
                    are not sufficient to make any appreciable difference in the success or failure
                    of a German attack on that area. To halt or to reverse our North African policy
                    at the present time might have the effect of throwing France completely into
                    German hands.</p>
                <p>This moment would, in my opinion, be singularly ill-chosen for such a change
                    which, insofar as we can see from here, promises no advantage to America. Since
                    early June, as I have reported, Vichy has shown some resistance to German
                    demands with respect to North Africa and this resistance seems to be as firm
                    today as it ever was—as German interruption of collaboration negotiations would
                    seem to show. It is due almost entirely to two facts: The strength of Russian
                    resistance and a growing realization not only of the magnitude of our defense
                    effort but of our determination to see a Nazi defeat. For these reasons there
                    has been a considerable evolution of opinion here. As I have reported, the
                    eagerness of the “collaborationists” to hedge has at times been very
                    apparent.</p>
                <p>I do not wish in any sense to imply that this change is necessarily permanent.
                    German successes in the Ukraine in the past few days have already given signs of
                    reversing this trend, and Vichy, which began by having no faith in Russian
                    resistance then changed to believing <pb facs="0451" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/>
                    that country invulnerable, is once more beginning to visualize complete German
                    occupation of the vital Caucasus oil area and all its implications. It is the
                    growing feeling here that within the next month, possibly the next fortnight,
                    German demands for facilities in Africa will be renewed to the accompaniment of
                    dire threats, if not an ultimatum, with probably some proposals for modifying
                    the “severity” of the Armistice Convention terms. What the attitude of the Vichy
                    Government will be at that time depends, to some extent, on the military
                    situation. If there then should be sufficient evidence that Vichy is prepared to
                    grant facilities to Germany in Africa, that Weygand will not resist such a grant
                    with force, a change in our policy would seem necessary, including an immediate
                    stoppage of all shipments and a recall of the Ambassador “for consultation;” and
                    the reasons therefor should be publicly and widely stated. In the meantime,
                    however, pending some evidence or indication that either Marshal Pétain or
                    General Weygand is not prepared at least to refuse <hi rend="italic">to agree
                        to</hi> German infiltration into Africa or the passage of supplies to the
                    German forces in Libya through Tunis, I feel that we should continue our present
                    program, including Red Cross supplies for children in Free France and hold out
                    hope for its extension.</p>
                <p>With reference to the specific question of Bizerta or Tunis, the Department will
                    recall (Embassy’s telegram 1170, September 12, 2 p.m.) the intimations of
                    Admiral Darlan, in the Marshal’s presence, that the French Government may be
                    compelled to agree to the passage of German “foodstuffs” to Libya. Weygand, we
                    are told by Monick who has just arrived at Vichy, will oppose any such
                    concession, recognizing it for the entering wedge. I feel that it might be well
                    for the Department to instruct me to make it clear beyond the shadow of a doubt
                    that agreement to the extension such facilities will definitely mean the end of
                    all cooperation with French Africa, even if more serious steps are not under
                    consideration. It has been unfortunately, but understandably, in the past the
                    policy of the Vichy Government to yield when the pressure is greatest and in the
                    face of the greatest immediate dangers. In the long run, only through the
                    exercise of strong counter-pressure on our part will the Marshal and his
                    Government be persuaded to resist. As indicated in telegram No. 1150, September
                    8, 1 p.m., they may even welcome a strong statement of what we can and will do,
                    and use such a statement in the renewal negotiations with the Germans which,
                    according to current reports, will not now be long delayed.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Algiers.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Leahy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
