<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-11-24T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-11-24T12:00:00-05:00" n="408" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d408">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">881.00/2060: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Childs</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-11-24T18:00:00+01:00">November 24, 1941—6 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received November 24—3:07 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>361. My 356, November 22 [<hi rend="italic">21</hi>], 8 [<hi rend="italic">4</hi>] p.m. In view of the importance to us of
                                Morocco it is believed that despite the setback occasioned <pb facs="0487" n="475" xml:id="pg_475"/> our position by the events
                                of the past few days everything possible should be done to salvage
                                as much as can be preserved of the economic aid program. It is
                                suggested that at least we endeavor to maintain our contact with
                                Morocco through perhaps a modified program applicable to the French
                                Protectorate or if need be a more restricted and hand to mouth
                                basis.</p>
                            <p>Russell<note n="24" xml:id="d408fn24">Harry Earle Russell, Consul
                                    General at Casablanca.</note> and King<note n="25" xml:id="d408fn25">David W. King, Vice Consul at
                                    Casablanca.</note> have been spending the weekend in Tangier and
                                we and all of our officers in Morocco feel that there is much to be
                                gained by continuing our program as long as possible.</p>
                            <p>It is true that it has been said of General Noguès<note n="26" xml:id="d408fn26">Gen. Albert Noguès, Resident General in the
                                    French Zone of Morocco.</note> that he is an opportunist and
                                time server who sacrifices his subordinates to maintain his own
                                position and that he is a man without any strong fixed principles.
                                It must be remembered, however, that Noguès took a very advanced
                                position in favor of a continuance of French resistance from the
                                French colonial empire in June 1940, a fact which does not appear to
                                have been reported adequately to the Department at the time.</p>
                            <p>In all my talks with him since my arrival in Morocco I have never
                                found the least suggestion of any anti-Allied sentiment. In these
                                conversations Noguès has shown himself always discreet but also
                                unmistakably friendly disposed toward the democratic cause. If he
                                has shown himself an opportunist it can only be said that faced with
                                the necessity of composing the conflicting interests confronting him
                                he has shown himself skillful and dexterous in maintaining himself
                                for 18 months in his position, as any man would have had to do in
                                his place.</p>
                            <p>It has been charged that he is both a politician and a soldier but no
                                one who was not a consummate politician could have survived the
                                storms of the past year as he has. Noguès is an old Moroccan who is
                                passionately devoted to this country if he can be said to have any
                                passion. He was trained by Lyautey<note n="27" xml:id="d408fn27">Marshal Louis Hubert Gonsalve Lyautey, Resident General in the
                                    French Zone of Morocco, 1912–25.</note> and the disintegration
                                of Morocco would mean the loss of his life work. He retains the
                                great respect of the Sultan and the natives as possibly no French
                                administrator has since Lyautey and it is this strong bond with the
                                native population which has preserved his situation so long with
                                Vichy. I obviously do not know what his feelings are at present but
                                I believe it may be safely said that he would be willing to take any
                                reasonable risks to safeguard France’s position in Morocco.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Vichy, Algiers and Casablanca.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Childs</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>