<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-11-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-11-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="414" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d414">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">851.00/2169½</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi></persName>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily at Algiers, to the Under Secretary of
                                    State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-11-27">November 27,
                                        1941</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Welles</hi>: You might be interested
                                to know that among others Louis Rollin, formerly of Havas,<note n="38" xml:id="d414fn38">Official French news agency.</note> has
                                been living in Algiers where he is part of a small group who have
                                given much thought to the direction in which France has been going
                                during the months since the Armistice, and who have been busy lately
                                with the formulation of a plan of action. I might mention also that
                                Metral, formerly under-secretary for Air, is associated in the study
                                which is being made.</p>
                            <p>General Weygand’s departure, I believe, is crystallizing this study
                                into a practical movement which has the advantage of being limited
                                to a very small group. In essence, their purpose is the
                                establishment in French Africa of a provisional government operating
                                independently of metropolitan France. They are searching and hope to
                                find shortly a military leader (General Delattre de Tassigny,
                                commanding in Tunisia, is the man they have in view now). They feel
                                that he is sufficiently ambitious, ruthless and able to lead such a
                                movement. They also have in mind that Yves Chatel, who succeeded
                                General Weygand as Governor General of Algeria, will fill the top
                                civilian role in such a provisional setup. The control would be in
                                the hands of four or five men at the most. Their immediate action
                                would consist of cutting off all communication with metropolitan
                                France, at which time they will require both economic and military
                                support from the United States. By military support they mean
                                matériel and munitions.</p>
                            <p>Another phase of their current study is a formula under which a
                                bridge could be constructed between themselves and the De
                                    Gaulle<note n="38a" xml:id="d414fn38a">Gen. Charles de Gaulle,
                                    leader of the Free French.</note> organization. Their conviction
                                is that a large number of desirable military and civilian officials
                                otherwise available, because of an undoubted antipathy which exists
                                among them, would shrink from the idea of forming part of the De
                                Gaulle organization.</p>
                            <p>They are also studying the question of the role which the French
                                Admiralty would play in such an undertaking. They say that they are
                                reasonably certain of the army and the air force, and that while the
                                navy would play a secondary part, it nevertheless is a factor to be
                                considered.</p>
                            <p>I thought that you would want me to mention this to you quite
                                informally as a factor in the present situation which may or may not
                                    <pb facs="0496" n="484" xml:id="pg_484"/> develop. As to our
                                interest, I have contented myself with references to the public
                                statements made by the President, the Secretary and yourself
                                regarding the American desire to support any group which is offering
                                resistance to axis aggression, and I have also underscored as much
                                as possible my notion regarding the considerable volume of aid, both
                                economic and matériel, which should be available in the United
                                States during the coming months.</p>
                            <p>Louis Rollin feels that there is a strong possibility that this
                                movement may materialize during the coming weeks.</p>
                            <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi> D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>