<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-12-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="423" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d423">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War
                                1939/20095</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi></persName>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily at Algiers, to the Under Secretary of
                                    State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-12-07">December 7,
                                        1941</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I enclose as of
                                possible interest and to show the trend of thought of many
                                representative Frenchmen who are interested in French Africa, a
                                memorandum of a conversation with M. J. Lemaigre-Dubreuil, owner of
                                    <hi rend="italic">Le Jour</hi> and a prominent French business
                                man having important interests in French West Africa.</p>
                            <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi> D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Counselor of Embassy in
                                        France</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily at Algiers</hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-12-05">December 5,
                                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>I received the visit this afternoon on my return from Casablanca
                                    of Mr. J. Lemaigre-Dubreuil, who arrived on Thursday from Dakar
                                        <pb facs="0507" n="495" xml:id="pg_495"/> en route to
                                    France. M. Lemaigre-Dubreuil is the owner of the newspaper <hi rend="italic">Le Jour</hi> and has important interests in
                                    the edible oil industry, particularly West African peanut oil.
                                    He tells me that his invested capital in French West Africa is
                                    in the neighborhood of 60 to 70 million francs. He has
                                    industrial interests in the occupied zone. He is the proprietor
                                    of the Lesieur edible oil plant at Dunkirk which was bombed by
                                    the Royal Air Force a few days ago, causing damage, he says, to
                                    the extent of four million francs.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Lemaigre-Dubreuil has always professed the friendliest
                                    sentiments in respect of the United States, and ever since
                                    General Weygand’s arrival in French Africa, has evinced a desire
                                    to support his administration. He claims to be, and I believe he
                                    is, anti-German, for sentimental reasons and because he is
                                    convinced that German domination of France will in the end cause
                                    him to lose his own business, as it will lose to most Frenchmen
                                    the direction of their own affairs. He has said repeatedly that
                                    we should understand that some French business men still believe
                                    their interests would be best served by a German victory, and
                                    that a British victory would only mean the bolshevization of
                                    France.</p>
                                <p>The purpose of M. Lemaigre-Dubreuil’s visit was to tell me that
                                    he considered General Weygand’s dismissal in the nature of a
                                    major catastrophe which might well lead to France’s loss of her
                                    African empire. Therefore, he said he proposed to work for the
                                    establishment of a French African provisional government which
                                    would be independent of Vichy. He declared that he is in contact
                                    with leading French officials and military authorities in French
                                    West and North Africa whose names he will disclose to me at a
                                    later date. I know that he has important connections. He said,
                                    however, that his plan is dependent on American support. He
                                    believes that nothing can be accomplished unless the United
                                    States would be prepared to consider the following program: <list>
                                        <label>1</label>
                                        <item>—Recognize such a provisional government immediately
                                            it is established;</item>
                                        <label>2</label>
                                        <item>—Provide transport ships to carry French effectives
                                            and military equipment now at Dakar to French North
                                            Africa;</item>
                                        <label>3</label>
                                        <item>—Arrange for the immediate shipment of arms and
                                            ammunition to North Africa <hi rend="italic">against
                                                payment to be made by the provisional government
                                                with gold now stored in French Africa;</hi>
                                        </item>
                                        <label>4</label>
                                        <item>—Be prepared to send an expeditionary force of at
                                            least three divisions to French North Africa;</item>
                                        <label>5</label>
                                        <item>—Guarantee the complete restoration of <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the French Empire to France
                                            after the termination of hostilities;</item>
                                        <label>6</label>
                                        <item>—Accept French command of military forces in French
                                            Africa;</item>
                                        <label>7</label>
                                        <item>—When French Africa proclaims its independence the
                                            United States should send at least four warships to
                                            Bizerta as a demonstration <pb facs="0508" n="496" xml:id="pg_496"/> of its sympathy with the purpose
                                            of the French African provisional government to resist
                                            axis aggression.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>Mr. Lemaigre-Dubreuil insisted that under such plan it must be
                                    demonstrated that the French are acting independently of the
                                    United States and that we must be careful to avoid any
                                    appearance of collusion.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Lemaigre-Dubreuil also recommended that in any dealings with
                                    French Africa, the United States must use the greatest
                                    discretion as the Germans today are maintaining a most active
                                    surveillance of everything which concerns this area. He said
                                    that after all there were only two ways of defeating the
                                    Germans: (1) by force or (2) by duplicity. He said that thus far
                                    the French position is that not having any means to resist by
                                    force, of necessity they must resort to ruse. In his own case,
                                    for example, as his business requires him to go from the
                                    occupied French zone to Africa, since his interests lie in both
                                    places, he is even going to the extent of having a police record
                                    carefully prepared which will be shown to the Germans indicating
                                    that he is a collaborationist and pro-nazi.</p>
                                <p>I told Lemaigre-Dubreuil, whom I have known for a long time, that
                                    his ideas are most interesting; that at the moment I could give
                                    him no indication of the policy of my government with respect to
                                    French Africa, because as I understand it, that policy is at
                                    present under discussion at Washington. I could only tell him
                                    that as he already knows, our general policy is to assist all
                                    those who offer resistance to axis aggression.</p>
                                <p>M. Lemaigre-Dubreuil, who is now en route to Paris, and who, of
                                    course, runs a grave risk should his actual plans become known
                                    to the German authorities, promised that he would keep me
                                    informed of future developments. He expects to return to French
                                    West Africa on December 22.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>R[<hi rend="smallcaps">obert</hi>] D. M[<hi rend="smallcaps">urphy</hi>]</signed>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>