<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Greece ( (MacVeagh) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d622</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">622</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-03-03T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-03-03T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-03-03T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-03-03T11:00:00-05:00" n="622"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d622">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/8761: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-03-03T18:00:00+02:00"
                            >March 3, 1941—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received March 4—10:10 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>113. Mr. Eden arrived here yesterday accompanied by Air Vice Marshal Elmhurst
                        [<hi rend="italic">Elmhirst?</hi>] and General Mallabry [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Mallaby?</hi>] of the War Office and was immediately received by the King.
                    I saw him this morning at his invitation and afterwards talked to the Under
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs and my Yugoslav colleague.</p>
                <p>Mr. Eden said he thinks the immediate German aim is to “subdue” Greece either by
                    threats or by invasion with the idea of taking over her territory for the
                    establishment of air bases but that even if she is successful in this it will
                    not affect the war seriously since Great Britain is rapidly cleaning up in the
                    Middle East and will be “sitting pretty in Africa.”</p>
                <p>He is satisfied that Greece will hold firm and indicated that Britain will give
                    her all the support possible, adding that he believes it will take about a month
                    for military action to develop on the Greek frontier on account of the state of
                    Balkan roads. To my remark “you are sending reenforcements”, he said “I am not
                    saying anything about that to anybody, not even to the United States or to the
                    British <pb facs="0666" n="654" xml:id="pg_654"/> Minister in Athens. We are
                    treating the matter as reenforcements to the air force.” (See my telegram 106 of
                    February 27, 3 p.m.)</p>
                <p>He expressed himself as delighted with his reception in Turkey and stated that
                    the Turks are both loyal and fully aware of the German menace to themselves but
                    said they have neither the force nor the equipment to undertake offensive
                    action. If Greece is attacked he thinks that they may possibly declare war and
                    give the British the use of their air fields and other facilities but stated
                    that Germany’s main effort in the Balkans will be directed against them and a
                    drive to Salonika will be only a flank affair. He himself does not concur in
                    this view but said it is a possible one and must be taken into account in
                    judging the Turkish attitude. He said Sir Stafford Cripps reported Russia
                    unlikely to make any move at present.</p>
                <p>I communicated to Mr. Eden the substance of Mr. Lane’s<note n="30"
                        xml:id="d622fn30">Arthur Bliss Lane, American Minister in Yugoslavia.</note>
                    number 134, March l,<note n="31" xml:id="d622fn31">Not printed.</note> and he
                    said he had run across the same situation in Ankara and that Saraçoğlu<note
                        n="32" xml:id="d622fn32">Sükrü Saraçoğlu, Turkish Minister for Foreign
                        Affairs.</note> had laughingly remarked “Every time I see the Yugoslav these
                    days there seems to be a <hi rend="italic">malentendu;</hi> the next time will
                    be <hi rend="italic">malentendu</hi> number 4.” Mr. Eden said he believes the
                    trouble is that the Yugoslavs have not made up their minds what to do in the
                    case of an attack on Salonika. He called in the British Minister to Yugoslavia,
                    now in Athens, and they agreed that an attempt should be made to get the Turks
                    and the Yugoslavs together through the good offices of the British
                    representatives in Ankara and Belgrade. In conclusion he remarked, “I believe
                    that Greece, Turkey and Yugoslavia will all eventually come into the fight but
                    there will be a lot of slipping and slipping before that happens.”</p>
                <p>I found Mavroudis very depressed. Without knowing that I had just seen the
                    British Foreign Minister he volunteered that he could tell me nothing about him
                    except that despite his cheerful optimism his trip to Turkey had actually
                    established only one new fact, and that a bad one for Greece, namely that the
                    latter can expect no military aid from the Turks. Later the Yugoslav
                        Minister<note n="33" xml:id="d622fn33">Alexandre Vouktchevitch.</note> also
                    told me that he believed Mr. Eden’s trip had not been a success and showed
                    himself even more defeatist than ever, saying that it is now too late to do
                    anything against the Germans whose domination of Europe has been certain ever
                    since the collapse of France.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
