<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of State (
                    (Berle))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d649</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">649</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-01-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-01-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="649"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d649">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.248/116</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-01-10">January 10,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The British Chargé came in to see me at his request. He had received instructions
                    from his Government regarding Greek planes. In his interview with Mr. Welles,
                    His Majesty’s Government had made three conditions as part of the integral
                    proposal: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>They would deliver 30 planes to Greece;</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>These planes would be replaced by the same or better planes
                            later;</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Such planes were to be transported to Basrah in American ships.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Following my suggestion to him that there might be legal difficulties in
                    transporting by American ships, he had cabled his Government. His Government
                    continued to believe that transport by American ships was essential. They did
                    not consider that transport by Greek ships would suffice. They considered that
                    transport by American ships was the American implementation of the President’s
                    pledge to Greece. He thought, likewise, that transport by American ships,
                    irrespective of our laws (which he thought could be interpreted to permit
                    transport to Basrah) was indicated in the President’s pledge of “all aid” to
                    Britain.</p>
                <pb facs="0684" n="672" xml:id="pg_672"/>
                <p>I said that I noted his point. As to the legal point—transport by American
                    ships—this was a case of laws, and we had to abide by them. I personally hoped
                    that the interpretation he put on the laws would be adopted by our Department of
                    Justice, but when the Department of Justice ruled on a point, we were, of
                    course, bound by it. I added that I had had the opportunity of chatting at
                    dinner the previous night with the Greek Minister, who had indicated that if
                    they had sufficient notice, it probably would be possible to supply Greek
                    shipping.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. A. B[<hi rend="smallcaps">erle</hi>], <hi rend="smallcaps">Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Note</hi>: I understand from Wallace Murray that the
                        British are now handing over the planes to the Greek Government. The
                        transport question will not arise until the new planes shall have reached
                        the assembly line next June. I believe the matter could profitably be left
                        for a little time, since the situation is certain to change between now and
                        when the transport is needed. The important point is that the Greeks are
                        immediately getting the planes and we shall have additional planes to
                        deliver.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
