<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Italian Ambassador ( (Colonna))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d790</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">790</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Consular offices</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="790"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d790">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">702.6511/1353</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Italian Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonna</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <p>The Secretary of State presents his compliments to His Excellency the Royal
                    Italian Ambassador and has the honor to refer to the latter’s memorandum of
                    March 6, 1941, raising certain questions in connection with the request of this
                    Government that the Italian officials in the United States confine their
                    movements to those areas in which they exercise recognized duties of their
                    respective offices.</p>
                <p>The request of this Government would not, of course, preclude the Italian
                    Ambassador calling to Washington Italian officials to confer with him as it is
                    recognized that such would be part of his and their duties.</p>
                <p>Special couriers carrying official mail to and from Italian consular offices in
                    the United States may proceed in the discharge of their duties provided their
                    names as well as the offices between which they travel are communicated to the
                    Department of State.</p>
                <p>The Department’s request is not intended to include the wives, children and
                    servants of Italian officials in the United States.</p>
                <p>The request of the Department of State applies to employees of the Embassy and
                    Italian consular offices in the exercise of their duties regardless of
                    nationality.</p>
                <p>It is anticipated that Italian officers shall obtain permission in case of need
                    to leave the areas in which they exercise their duties in the same manner as
                    prescribed with regard to the limitation imposed upon American consular officers
                    in Italy by the Ministry of Foreign Affairs’ note of February 11, 1941.<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d790fn5">Text of note quoted in telegram No. 208, February 13,
                        7 p.m., from the Ambassador in Italy, not printed.</note> This note states
                    that the Ministry <pb facs="0811" n="799" xml:id="pg_799"/> of Foreign Affairs
                    will facilitate the trips to be made by the personnel of the missions or of
                    consular officers which are notified to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs by the
                    Chief of the diplomatic mission concerned. In other words, the Department of
                    State will be glad to take into consideration any requests from the Italian
                    Ambassador relating to such necessary trips.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-03-14">March 14,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
