<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Louis J. Halle, Jr., of the Division of the American
                    Republics</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d829</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">829</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-12-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Good Neighbor Policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-12-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="829"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d829">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">856A.20/135</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Louis J. Halle, Jr., of the Division of the
                        American Republics</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-12-05">December 5,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Attitude of the Other American Republics to the Joint
                        Action of Brazil and the United States for the Protection of Surinam</hi>
                </p>
                <p>News of the recent Brazilian-American joint action in Surinam has been received
                    with calm realism throughout Latin America, in official circles and in the press
                    alike. It may, perhaps, be viewed as an indication of the success achieved by
                    our Good Neighbor Policy that our motives in taking this action have been almost
                    universally accepted on the basis of our own avowal. The step has not met with
                    the fear and suspicion that it might have aroused a few years ago.</p>
                <p>In governmental circles, the responses that have not been explicitly favorable
                    have been merely non-committal, and only the pro-Axis press has found fault. The
                    general view has been that the action was a logical, almost an expected forward
                    step, in keeping with the progressive development of hemisphere defense since
                    the autumn of 1939, and thus to be regarded as a matter of course. It has been
                    viewed as stemming from the Act of Habana (in spirit at least) and leading
                    toward an anticipated occupation of French Guiana at some appropriate future
                    moment; and also as a gratifying indication of our determination to defend the
                    Western Hemisphere. While definitely unfavorable comments are not to be found
                    outside the pro-Axis press, notices expressing outright jubilation have appeared
                    only in Cuba, Nicaragua, and Brazil (where pride is aroused by Brazilian
                    participation together with some disappointment at the limited nature of that
                    participation). However, Colombia’s <hi rend="italic">El Liberal</hi> (not
                    considered pro-Nazi) published an ambiguous comment that might be construed as
                    an expression of alarm.</p>
                <p>The responses of government officials have ranged from silence (Mexico,
                    Venezuela, Bolivia, Ecuador) through non-committal comment (Colombia, Peru) to
                    unqualified concurrence in the action (Dominican Republic, Haiti, Honduras [<hi
                        rend="italic">New York Times</hi>],<note n="19a" xml:id="d829fn19a">Brackets
                        appear in the original.</note> El Salvador, Costa Rica, Nicaragua, Panama,
                    Brazil, Uruguay, Argentina, Chile).</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister of Argentina,<note n="20" xml:id="d829fn20">Julio
                        Roca.</note> in a note handed to our Ambassador, stated that his Ministry
                    considered that “the measure mentioned assures continental defense within the
                    spirit of American <pb facs="0846" n="834" xml:id="pg_834"/> solidarity and of
                    the pacts signed, which are its practical manifestation.” The Associated Press
                    reported him as stating, also, that the move was “a normal thing,” analogous to
                    our occupation of Iceland.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister of Paraguay<note n="21" xml:id="d829fn21">Luis
                        Argana.</note> said that the action appears logical for hemisphere defense.
                    The Chilean Foreign Minister<note n="22" xml:id="d829fn22">Bianchi
                        Gundian.</note> expressed himself as being personally in accord. The Foreign
                    Minister of Panama<note n="23" xml:id="d829fn23">Raúl de Roux.</note> said that
                    the action is greatly in the interest of all the American Republics, adding that
                    the statement that the contingent will be withdrawn at the conclusion of
                    hostilities should obviate any possible criticism which might have arisen.</p>
                <p>For the most part, the Latin American press has confined itself to reporting the
                    news without editorial comment. The press has been explicitly favorable in Cuba,
                    Nicaragua, Brazil, Uruguay, and Argentina.</p>
                <p>Cuba’s <hi rend="italic">El Mundo</hi> stated that no one in the Americas would
                    disapprove of the occupation of Surinam but would, rather, view it as evidence
                    of the firm determination of the United States to maintain its rights and those
                    of the other republics of the Western Hemisphere by force of arms. The only
                    editorial comment in Guatemala and in Venezuela accepted the step as a natural
                    development to be regarded as a matter of course.</p>
                <p>The only comment in the Colombian press (that of <hi rend="italic">El
                        Liberal</hi> referred to above) foretold, as a result of the step, imminent
                    economic complications and a radical alteration in international affairs, for
                    which Colombia must be prepared. The only exception to the favorable reaction of
                    the Uruguayan press has been that of the Herrerista <hi rend="italic"
                        >Debate</hi>, which referred to the action as “an outrage against the rights
                    of others.” In Argentina, only <hi rend="italic">El Pampero</hi> has viewed the
                    step with alarm; its tone, according to Ambassador Armour, was one of
                    discouragement. The Ecuadoran press, while refraining from editorial comment,
                    has published some news-reports of German statements that the United States has
                    “invaded” South America.</p>
                <p>It may be said that on the whole the Latin Americans were not shocked by our
                    action and, except at the prompting of malice from abroad, did not misconstrue
                    our motives.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
