<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Rumania ( (Gunther) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d864</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">864</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-11-14T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-11-14T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9yKWGNvCFmqmdD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="recVMjpePTbXrmHOO" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037040"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Deportation</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-11-14T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-11-14T09:00:00-05:00" n="864"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d864">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">871.4016/284: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Rumania</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gunther</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bucharest</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-11-14T16:00:00+02:00"
                            >November 14, 1941—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 15—2:48 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>956. With reference to my 866, October 3, 10 a.m.; and to the Department’s 458,
                    October 23, 11 p.m., regarding the deaths of Joseph Hirsch, Jacob Nimovitz and
                    Nathan Spitzer, I have received a note dated November 12 from the Foreign Office
                    requesting the Legation to give the necessary assurances before further
                    investigations are continued that the aforenamed persons “actually had at the
                    time of their deaths the right to American citizenship since naturalized
                    American citizens who have returned to their native country lose this status
                    after a certain time”.</p>
                <p>Inasmuch as the Foreign Office will undoubtedly discontinue its investigations
                    if, in reply to the note in question the answer called for by the citizenship
                    regulations is given; namely, that these individuals were citizens but not
                    entitled to protection or passports for residence in Rumania, I shall withhold
                    my answer pending instructions from the Department.</p>
                <p>In this connection I also refer to my 938, November 5, 5 p.m.,<note n="17"
                        xml:id="d864fn17">Not printed.</note> concerning the deportation of certain
                    American citizens to Mhilev in the Ukraine the release and safety of whom has
                    not been confirmed! by the Foreign Office in spite of reported representations,
                    the mass; deportations of Rumanian and <hi rend="italic">heimatlose</hi> Jews to
                    the Ukraine principally from the reconquered provinces where, according to
                    reports, they are living under the most primitive conditions without sufficient
                    food and shelter is continuing. If naturalized citizens against whom <pb
                        facs="0889" n="877" xml:id="pg_877"/> the presumption of having ceased to be
                    American citizens has arisen and native Americans for whom passports have been
                    approved for immediate return only are unable to identify themselves with
                    American passports as required by Rumanian regulations there are no means of
                    preventing their deportation to the Ukraine where their continued existence is
                    uncertain to say the least.</p>
                <p>I should therefore appreciate an early expression of the Department’s views as to
                    whether, in view of the exceptional circumstances outlined above and the recent
                    decision of Congress to grant naturalized citizens residing abroad until October
                    14, 1942 (Department’s circular telegraphic instruction October 14 to Bern<note
                        n="18" xml:id="d864fn18">Not printed.</note>) to complete arrangements for
                    their repatriation, the Legation should continue to deny passports and
                    protection to citizens in the two categories mentioned in the last paragraph who
                    number approximately 100.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunther</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
