<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Spain ( (Weddell) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d868</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">868</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-03-01T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-03-01T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recbHz5atbbO3GlrY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85063084"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hunger</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-03-01T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-03-01T07:00:00-05:00" n="868"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d868">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00118 European War 1939/142: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-03-01T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >March 1, 1941—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received March 3—2 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>162. I yesterday accompanied Colonel Donovan<note n="3" xml:id="d868fn3">William
                        J. Donovan, personal representative of the Secretary of the Navy on special
                        mission in Europe.</note> to the Ministry for Foreign Affairs where we spent
                    more than 2 hours with the Foreign Minister.<note n="4" xml:id="d868fn4">Ramón
                        Serrano Suñer.</note> At my request an interpreter was present and a double
                    check was thus had on what was said.</p>
                <p>Presenting Colonel Donovan I said that as the Minister was doubtless aware he had
                    recently visited a number of Mediterranean and contiguous countries where he had
                    talked to heads of governments, <pb facs="0894" n="882" xml:id="pg_882"/>
                    Foreign Ministers, and other authorized spokesmen; that he was now nearing the
                    conclusion of his European visit and was desirous of discussing matters with the
                    Minister with a view to making an appropriate report on his return to the United
                    States. I added that this distinguished visitor was familiar in general also
                    with our relations with Spain and the desire of our country to learn more fully
                    what its situation and needs were.</p>
                <p>Prior to responding to specific questions from Colonel Donovan, the Minister gave
                    a background of the recent civil war, emphasizing the point that in this
                    conflict the democracies of the world had been in opposition to Spain, and that
                    his country had been delivered from a period of disorder and violence (under
                    which democratic principles were nullified), by so-called totalitarian countries
                    and that naturally and as a result the gratitude of Spain flowed toward those
                    countries. The arch enemies of Spain in this conflict, he continued, had been
                    France and England whose Governments had entirely failed to recognize the basic
                    principles involved and had encouraged in every way in their power the so-called
                    Republican Government. The Minister then recalled with indignation and
                    bitterness the failure of Ambassadors and other Chiefs of Mission during the
                    civil war to mitigate by their physical presence and effort the reign of blood
                    and terror which had existed in the capital and elsewhere, recalling cases where
                    asylum had been refused to people who shortly thereafter were assassinated.</p>
                <p>Colonel Donovan in pointing out that he had visited the Franco<note n="4a"
                        xml:id="d868fn4a">Gen. Francisco Franco, Spanish Chief of State.</note>
                    troops at the front, and was himself a Catholic, emphasized that there were 20
                    million and more of the same creed in the United States, equally made clear that
                    the Franco leaders had entirely ignored the rise of propaganda as a result of
                    which that public opinion in the United States which would have been favorable
                    to the cause was left bewildered through lack of information—all this in sharp
                    contrast to the activities of Republican representatives.</p>
                <p>The most significant statement made by the Minister was a textual declaration
                    that “we hope for and believe in the victory of Germany in the present
                    conflict”. He added this was the opinion of his Government as well as of the
                    youth of Spain, the latter feeling convinced that a German victory would be to
                    the best interests of the country. (The Minister under cross-examination here
                    said that by the word “youth” he meant those who were young in their attitude
                    toward the object of the present situation!)</p>
                <p>The Minister was then asked why he desired a German victory. He replied that
                    first of all it was because of gratitude arising from its contribution to
                    Spain’s present independence referred to above and equally in resentment of
                    England’s and France’s attitude in the Spanish Civil War and further that he
                    felt that Spain’s legitimate <pb facs="0895" n="883" xml:id="pg_883"/>
                    aspirations based on her “natural rights” would be safeguarded if the hoped for
                    event became a fact.</p>
                <p>Colonel Donovan inquired what would become of the other countries of Europe under
                    a dominate [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] Germany. The Minister replied that
                    France and Belgium would receive special consideration and that there would be a
                    general control of other countries in accordance with German ideas. He could not
                    see any danger to the United States or to other American countries arising out
                    of this situation. It was British propaganda that provoked uneasiness. He also
                    remarked here that a nation of 80 million Germans was sufficiently large to
                    impose its will on all Europe as well as to protect greater component states
                    from the horrors of communism coming from the East. Being further queried along
                    this same line as to what Spain would gain, he said it would surely receive
                    Gibraltar together with a further recognition of Spain’s “natural rights” in
                    Africa.</p>
                <p>Colonel Donovan then asked what he thought would happen in the event of a British
                    victory. The Minister answered that in such a contingency it was out of the
                    question to expect a country of the limited population of the British Isles to
                    “impose a bourgeois government” on the rest of Europe. Furthermore in such a
                    case Europe would be an impoverished congeries of peoples too weak to resist the
                    Red attack referred to.</p>
                <p>Pressing the matter further Colonel Donovan inquired how Britain’s defeat was to
                    be brought about. The Minister declared that the issue would be settled in
                    British waters and within the British Isles. Admitting the apparent success in
                    Great Britain and Greece, in Albania and in Africa he said that only “prestige”
                    was affected thereby; that were conditions reversed the final result would not
                    be altered. While admitting the wonderful spirit shown by the British people,
                    the Minister added there was a limit to this form of human endurance and that
                    hunger plus incessant bombing would effectively end all resistance. (The
                    Minister seemed to leave Japan entirely out of the picture as he did equally the
                    United States!)</p>
                <p>Pursuing his examination Colonel Donovan asked the flat question whether Spain
                    intended to remain out of the conflict. The reply to this was that it would
                    remain aloof until Spain’s “honor or interests or dignity” were in question.</p>
                <p>Asked concerning activities of foreign governments in Spain, the Minister
                    declared that England and France had always intervened in the affairs of the
                    country and that England is intervening today. He followed this with the
                    astonishing declaration that stories of German infiltration and intervention in
                    Spain were part of British propaganda; that there was nothing of the kind nor
                    was any diplomatic pressure being applied against Spain by the German
                    Government. Colonel Donovan countered this vigorously, declaring that while he
                        <pb facs="0896" n="884" xml:id="pg_884"/> did not pretend to speak of Spain
                    he was thoroughly informed regarding German propaganda and pressure of various
                    kinds in the United States and in every country he had visited, and that it was
                    only reasonable to suppose that something of the same kind went on here. This,
                    together with other information which he had acquired confirmed his belief,
                    Colonel Donovan said, that the instinct of the American people had led them
                    aright in causing them to envisage a German victory not alone as a menace to
                    them but to their liberties. Colonel Donovan continued by remarking that
                    undoubtedly the Minister had read the speeches of President Roosevelt, and
                    emphasized that these speeches not alone represented the views of the President
                    and the Administration but were also the expression of the conviction of the
                    great majority of the American people.</p>
                <p>Colonel Donovan then spoke at some length of the gigantic material program now
                    going on in the United States which would soon be well into its stride, of the
                    huge army thoroughly armed and equipped now being molded, with other significant
                    points emphasizing what this meant in the scales of victory for Britain.</p>
                <p>Colonel Donovan also told the Minister that he had learned from his own
                    observation and otherwise of the general economic needs of Spain; that he was
                    aware that I had made these generally known to our Government; that he was
                    desirous of contributing in any way he could to a sympathetic consideration of
                    these necessities; that he proposed discussing this subject with the British
                    Ambassador here and perhaps with the British Government in London; and that on
                    his return to the United States, now fixed for an early date, he would equally
                    make these needs known. This gave the Minister the opportunity to speak of the
                    terrific destruction in field and forest and factory, in transportation, et
                    cetera, in Spain pointing out that other countries which had engaged only in
                    wars beyond their boundaries had secured loans for their rehabilitation while
                    Spain of today was not alone suffering from the destruction of the past but on
                    every frontier was feeling the repercussion of the present conflict.</p>
                <p>In conclusion Colonel Donovan told the Minister of his satisfaction in having
                    been able to see him and to have this frank discussion, having delayed his visit
                    to Portugal to confer with a high personality there in order to do so. The
                    Minister interrupted him here to express his pleasure in the visit. Continuing,
                    the Colonel said that he was disappointed, however, that despite my efforts it
                    has not been found possible to secure an interview with the Caudillo<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d868fn5">Gen. Francisco Franco.</note> whom he desired to see,
                    having in mind the interest of Spain and nothing involving him personally. The
                    Minister mumbled something intended to be consolatory but which was entirely
                    indefinite.</p>
                <pb facs="0897" n="885" xml:id="pg_885"/>
                <p>As a postscript to the foregoing it should be stated that I telephoned to the
                    Minister about 8 o’clock in the evening, recalled my two notes and our
                    conversation relative to the desire of Colonel Donovan to be received by the
                    Caudillo, and inquired if this could be arranged: The Minister replied that he
                    feared this would be impossible since the Caudillo was “very busy”.</p>
                <p>While nothing that is reported above is startlingly new, and certainly it is not
                    at variance with reports submitted by this Mission in recent months, perhaps at
                    no time have the views of the Spanish Government in the matter of the present
                    conflict, expressed through its official spokesman been stated with such clarity
                    and directness. However, it does not alter the opinions which I expressed in my
                    telegram No. 76, January 29, 5 p.m. (more especially the recommendations in the
                    four last paragraphs), and I would reiterate that our policy in dealing with
                    this Government should be one of bald realism dictated by a careful
                    determination of what Spanish neutrality is worth to the general cause and how
                    it should be secured.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Weddell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
