<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-12-13T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-12-13T19:00:00-05:00" n="918" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d918">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 (D) Regulations/5316:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-12-13T19:00:00-05:00">December
                                    13, 1941—7 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>662. Your 974, November 21, 7 p.m.,<note n="46" xml:id="d918fn46">Not
                                printed.</note> and 1024, December 8, 8 p.m. The Embassy is under a
                            misapprehension in assuming that the Department has been conducting
                            negotiations with the Spanish Government through Ambassador Cárdenas.
                            There have been no negotiations at this end thus far and the Embassy may
                            rest assured that it will be informed of any negotiations undertaken
                            hereafter.</p>
                        <p>No embargo has been applied on exports to Spain and it is understood that
                            some commodities are being licensed in the ordinary routine. On the
                            other hand, it is true that certain licenses are being rejected or held
                            in abeyance pending settlement of the basic question of the petroleum
                            supply.</p>
                        <p>In this connection a study of the figures in the hands of the Department,
                            which are understood to be CAMPSA’s figures, has revealed apparent
                            discrepancies and created serious doubts as to their accuracy. The
                            tankers now off Port Arthur applied for gas oil, whereas our figures
                            indicate that Spain’s gas oil inventory including Canary Islands is
                            already at a relatively high level.</p>
                        <p>If the situation with regard to any specific product is acute
                            consideration may be given to an adequately supported request, upon
                            receiving assurance that our proposed plan of control will be agreed to
                            and without awaiting the fully detailed information on all products.
                            Meanwhile it is understood that the Spanish Embassy has requested its
                            Government to furnish the preliminary data outlined in paragraphs 5 and
                            6 of the Department’s telegram 618 of November 26, 3 p.m.,<note n="46" xml:id="d918fn47">Not printed.</note> and the Department is awaiting
                            these data, which the Embassy states have not yet been received.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>