<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-03-15T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-03-15T15:00:00-05:00" n="944" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d944">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/9075a:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Yugoslavia</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Lane</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-03-15T15:00:00-05:00">March 15,
                                    1941—3 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>39. Last evening the Secretary of the Treasury<note n="47" xml:id="d944fn47">Henry Morgenthau, Jr.</note> was considerably
                            disturbed by a request from the National Bank of Yugoslavia to convert
                            its gold here to the value of $22,000,000 into dollar account and
                            immediately transfer approximately one half of the dollars to its
                            account in the Bank of Brazil.</p>
                        <p>We can see no reason for such large transfers of funds out of this
                            country, particularly as within the previous few days transfers to
                            Switzerland and Turkey had been requested to an amount approximating
                            some $3,000,000. We asked the Minister of Yugoslavia here to send a
                            message to his Government last night in the following sense:</p>
                        <p>That we were not contemplating any freezing measure against Yugoslavian
                            funds in general; that, however, Treasury was disturbed about this
                            request for transfers of large amounts of funds out of the United
                            States. We asked that the orders for these transfers be canceled and
                            would be glad to have any explanation of legitimate financial
                            transactions. We further asked the Minister to add that Yugoslavian
                            interests here are in friendly hands and that we desire to give every
                            consideration to their requirements. (End sense of message)</p>
                        <p>We wish to support in any way that we can the maintenance of the
                            independence and integrity of Yugoslavia. In the face of an overwhelming
                            of the Government or country by force we would, of course, desire to
                            have the Yugoslav financial assets in this country protected against
                            seizure or control by alien forces which could be accomplished by
                            freezing the funds now here. Further until the situation is clarified,
                            we would not wish these funds to get out of reach of our control. We
                            would therefore want you to keep us closely informed of your opinion of
                            the developing situation.</p>
                        <p>The gold conversion above referred to will not, because of technical
                            impediments, come before the Treasury for action before Monday morning.
                            If the report we receive from Fotitch is not satisfactory, however, we
                            feel that in order to protect Yugoslav interests it may be necessary to
                            consider a freezing order.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>