<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in France ( (Leahy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-03-15T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-03-15T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-03-15T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-03-15T15:00:00-05:00" n="98"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.48/227: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Leahy</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-03-15T15:00:00-05:00"
                            >March 15, 1941—3 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>229. Your telegram 251, February 28, 8 p.m.<note n="37" xml:id="d98fn37">Not
                        printed.</note> giving French food requirements for unoccupied zone.</p>
                <p>The French Ambassador came in this morning at his request.<note n="37a"
                        xml:id="d98fn37a">See <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> I took occasion
                    to inform him again that we have been giving all our attention to this situation
                    on the basis of your telegram and a similar memorandum presented by him, that we
                    have had several conversations with the British Government on the subject and
                    that the latter was giving all possible consideration to the various aspects of
                    the <pb facs="0137" n="125" xml:id="pg_125"/> proposals. On March 7, I had told
                    the French Ambassador that some real progress in the discussions had already
                    been made. Then de Brinon’s<note n="38" xml:id="d98fn38">Fernand de Brinon,
                        Delegate General of the French Government for occupied territories.</note>
                    statement and Admiral Darlan’s interview with the press threatening the use of
                    French naval convoys introduced a new element and came as a surprise to this
                    Government.</p>
                <p>I again recalled to the Ambassador our earnest desire to be helpful to France in
                    its present difficulties and our readiness to continue to devote our best
                    efforts toward obtaining some solution. In our approach to the problem we
                    recognized that France, under the armistice, is laboring under certain
                    restrictions with regard to its independence of movement but we must also bear
                    in mind that on the other hand France is not required to take any action which
                    inures to the benefit of the occupying power. Should the French Government take
                    any action against Great Britain, particularly if it were of a military nature,
                    France would lose before the world any claim to having acted within the limits
                    of the obligations imposed by the armistice terms and would place itself in the
                    position of a belligerent acting in concert with Germany.</p>
                <p>I pointed out that we will go ahead with our endeavors to be helpful to France
                    but, of course, it must be clear to the French Government that our efforts will
                    be made of no avail if by their acts they make it impossible for us to continue
                    discussions with regard to these problems by interposing indications or threats
                    of drastic military measures.</p>
                <p>I can assure you that we have not ceased to discuss with the British the
                    possibilities of sending some shipments of wheat into unoccupied France and we
                    feel that we are justified in believing that a definite amount will be permitted
                    to go forward within a very short time, provided that the present controversial
                    atmosphere can be clarified.</p>
                <p>Please seek an early opportunity to see Marshal Pétain and point out to him the
                    difficulties which are being put in the way of our efforts to be helpful in this
                    situation and tell him that we would be very grateful for any action he could
                    take which would help to smooth out the present difficulties.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
