<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-01-01T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-01-01T13:00:00-05:00" n="181" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                        <head>181. Telegram From <gloss type="from">the Department of State</gloss>
                            to <gloss type="to">the Embassy in the Republic of China</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d181fn1">Source: National Archives,
                                    <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73,
                                    <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>/<persName corresp="#p_NRM1">NIXON</persName>.
                                Secret; Priority; <gloss target="#t_EXDIS1">Exdis</gloss>. Text
                                received from the White House on December 15.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-01-01T18:00:00+00:00">January 1, 1972,
                                1800Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>27. For Ambassador. Please deliver soonest following letter from
                            President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>. Signed
                            original follows by pouch. <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> does not
                            intend make text public and requests <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                            respect confidentiality of message. <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                            may, however, announce receipt of letter of assurance from President.
                            Further, Department will consider possibility of authorizing release
                            certain extracts from letter if <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                            <pb facs="0690" n="635" xml:id="pg_635"/> wishes to do so. These
                            extracts should be cabled back for clearance prior to release. Signed
                            original is dated Dec 31.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Begin message</hi>. Dear Mr. President: As I prepare
                            for my forthcoming trip to meet and talk with leaders in Peking and
                            Moscow, I would like to share with you some thoughts concerning the
                            conversations I expect to have there.</p>
                        <p>It is my earnest hope that the visit to Peking will contribute to the
                            development of a more stable and peaceful situation in East Asia and in
                            the Pacific area. I recognize, of course, that the principles which move
                            the leaders in Peking are in many cases diametrically opposite to our
                            own. I hope, however, that my conversations with them will be a step
                            toward relaxing the longstanding tensions between Peking and
                            Washington.</p>
                        <p>Gradually and over a longer period, such discussion can result in a
                            reduction of tensions in Asia, which would benefit all nations in that
                            area.</p>
                        <p>You may be absolutely certain, Mr. President, that in taking steps toward
                            the goal of a peaceful Asia, the United States will not overlook the
                            interest of its allies and friends nor seek any accommodations at their
                            expense. I have very much in mind the interests of your government. We
                            intend to honor all of our treaty commitments, including that with the
                            Republic of China. As I said in assuming office, and have frequently
                            repeated since, the United States has no intention of disengaging from
                            Asia.</p>
                        <p>The talks in Peking will focus on bilateral questions affecting that
                            government and ourselves, of which there are many. Given the existence
                            of the deep and complex differences which exist in our relationship, the
                            question of establishing formal diplomatic relations between our two
                            governments most assuredly will not arise.</p>
                        <p>The events which are now taking place in East Asia will have a profound
                            effect on the nations of the Pacific for the remainder of this century.
                            I look to your continued understanding of our purposes, Mr. President,
                            to help ensure that these events will move us all in the direction of a
                            stable and enduring international order.</p>
                        <p>It is my hope that my visit to Moscow in May 1972 will also contribute to
                            greater international stability. In Moscow, as in Peking, the United
                            States will not deal over the heads of its friends and allies in any
                            matter where their security interests might be involved. For example,
                            there have been no, and there will be no, bilateral United States–Soviet
                            negotiations on mutual withdrawal of forces from Europe. I hope,
                            however, that some concrete progress might be made, either before or
                            during my Moscow visit, in such bilateral areas as arms control and
                            economic relations.</p>
                        <pb facs="0691" n="636" xml:id="pg_636"/>
                        <p>May I assure you, as always, of my highest personal regards and warm good
                            wishes for your continued excellent health.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard Nixon</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">End message</hi>.<note n="2" xml:id="d181fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_MCWPJ1">McConaughy</persName> delivered the
                                message to Acting Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YH1">H. K.
                                    Yang</persName> on January 3. (Telegram 5 from Taipei, January
                                3: ibid.) On January 9 <persName corresp="#p_LY1">Yang</persName>
                                gav. <persName corresp="#p_MCWPJ1">McConaughy</persName> a copy of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CCG1">Chiang</persName>’s January 6 reply,
                                which reads in part: “I am confident that, with your wisdom, rich
                                political experience, and your thorough understanding of the true
                                nature of the Chinese Communist regime, you would certainly have
                                full cognizance of Peiping’s treacherous tactics and intrigues in
                                its international activities, and would not be beguiled. I am also
                                confident that in all decisions vis-à-vis the Chinese Communists you
                                will not only take into account both the traditional friendship and
                                common interests of our two countries, but also bear in mind the
                                long-term national interest of the United States and her position in
                                world history.” (Telegram 132 from Taipei, January 10; ibid.) The
                                signed original was delivered by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SJCH1">Shen</persName> on January11. (Ibid.,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 751,
                                Presidential Correspondence File, Republic of China, Corres. Pres.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>) <persName corresp="#p_SJCH1">Shen</persName> apparently delivered the
                                letter in his meeting with <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>, where they discussed the summit in San
                                Clemente between <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and
                                Japanese Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_SE1">Sato</persName>.
                                (Telegram 7012 to Taipei, January 12; ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>/<persName corresp="#p_NRM1">NIXON</persName>) <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> of the contents of <persName corresp="#p_CCG1">Chiang</persName>’s response on January 11. (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 38, President’s
                                Daily Briefs)</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>