<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>193. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="193"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                <head>193. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d193fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 847, President’s File—China
                        Trip, China Visit—Readings on <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao
                            Tse-tung</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CE1">Chou
                            En-lai</persName>, Book IV, The President. Top Secret; Sensitive;
                        Exclusively Eyes Only. Sent for information. Much of this document was
                        underlined by <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>. On February 15
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> forwarded to the
                        President a 21-page paper “prepared by my staff” that “distills some of
                            <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName>’s major philosophic and
                        political themes drawn from his writings, statements, and actions throughout
                        his life.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s covering
                        memorandum and the report are in the Library of Congress, Manuscript
                        Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers,
                        Geopolitical Files, China, Trips, February 1972, Briefing Book. See also
                            <ref target="frus1969-76ve13#d86">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. E–13, Document
                            86</ref>. Other briefing materials or reports on the trip include: 1)
                        Detailed Schedule (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 <gloss
                            target="#t_US1">US</gloss>/<persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >NIXON</persName>); 2) Record of Previous Visits Arranged by Subject Matter
                        (ibid., <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 846, President’s
                        File—China Trip, Book I—<gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss>’s 1971 Visits by
                        Subject Matter and Book II [part I]); 3) Record of Previous Visits (ibid.,
                        Box 847, China Trip—Record of previous visits, Book III); 4) Readings on
                            <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao Tse-tung</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName> (ibid., China Visit— Readings on
                            <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao Tse-tung</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName>, Book IV); 5) Briefing Books
                        (ibid., Briefing papers for the China trip, The President, Books V and V–a);
                        6) Reading Materials (ibid., China Trip—Reading materials, Book IV); and
                        Department of State reading materials (ibid., Box 848, General reading
                        material, State Department Briefing Book, Book I [Parts I–III]). The
                        President’s Daily Diary also contains detailed information on the trip.
                        (ibid., White House Central Files) as does the Weekly Compilation of
                        Presidential Documents, February 28, 1972, pp. 461–499; <hi rend="italic"
                            >Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        </hi>, 1972, pp. 367–384; Foreign Broadcast Information Service, Daily
                        Report, People’s Republic of China, Special Report: President <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s Visit to China, March 9, 1972, no.
                        48, supp. 7; and Department of State Bulletin, March 20, 1972, pp. 419–440.
                        The <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> also prepared Special National
                        Intelligence Estimate 13–72, “Security Conditions in the <gloss
                            target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>,” for the President’s visit. (Central
                        Intelligence Agency, Job 79–R1012, <gloss target="#t_NIC1">NIC</gloss>
                        Files)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1972-02-19">February 19, 1972</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Mao, Chou and the Chinese Litmus Test</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0728" n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Litmus Test</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Over the long term, the intangibles of your China visit will prove more important
                    than the tangible results. We should be able to leave the People’s Republic of
                    China with a creditable public outcome—because of the advance work, the careful
                    scaling down of expectations, and the needs of both sides for various audiences.
                    The crucial factor, however, will be the Chinese judgment of our seriousness and
                    reliability: this litmus test will determine their future policy. If we fail it,
                    the immediate results will be less satisfactory than we expect, but more
                    importantly, they could turn sharply away from us in subsequent months.</p>
                <p>In that case, they could easily resort to the tempting levers of public opinion.
                    They could then deal with us like the North Vietnamese do—inviting in opposition
                    politicians, dealing with unfriendly private groups, appealing to hostile
                    journalists, lambasting us in the United Nations, and generally turning popular
                    pressures on us while being tough on the state-to-state level. We can be certain
                    that they would be especially skillful at this game; we would pay a double price
                    at home and abroad for our alleged naivete at trying to deal with these people
                    in the first place.</p>
                <p>Thus, the Chinese will be concentrating on your strategic concepts as they
                    discuss the various tactical issues. They will want to know if you understand
                    their perspectives, how we chart the future, and whether we can be counted upon
                    to move ahead surely and steadily. This does not mean that we shouldn’t be firm
                    with them. On the contrary, they will only respect strength and resoluteness.
                    Nor does it mean that we shouldn’t demand reciprocal treatment from them. On the
                    contrary, they must be made fully aware of our own international and domestic
                    imperatives.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>When one refers to the Chinese one is in effect discussing <persName
                        corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> and Chou, they are the premier exhibits, the
                    two clearly dominant figures on the Chinese scene today, and your only real
                    interlocutors during your visit.</p>
                <p>A convenient distinction between <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> and
                    Chou—and one that is generally valid today—is to cite the Chairman as the
                    philosopher and Chou as the practitioner. Thus we can think of <persName
                        corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> as the philosopher, the poet, the grand
                    strategist, the inspirer, the romantic. He sets the direction and the framework
                    and leaves the implementation to his trusted lieutenant. He can be counted on to
                    speak in broad, philosophic, historic terms and leave the negotiations to Chou.
                    He will want to talk about the long view, the basic tides running in the world,
                    where China and the U.S. are heading, with each other and with others.</p>
                <pb facs="0729" n="674" xml:id="pg_674"/>
                <p>Chou is the tactician, the administrator, the negotiator, the master of details
                    and thrust and parry. His emphasis will be on the concrete substantive issues,
                    and he will invoke the Chairman’s authority and prescience with what seems total
                    sincerity.</p>
                <p>However, this distinction between the two men can be misleading. Chou is
                    perfectly at home on the philosophic plane, and he couches his tactical
                    arguments in historical and conceptual terms. No man could have endured and
                    accomplished what he has without a strategic vision.</p>
                <p>More importantly, Mao can be as ruthlessly pragmatic as he is ideologically
                    fanatic. Now in his final years, he envisions himself as a man above practical
                    details, but his writings and his actions have shown hard-nosed adaptability as
                    well as philosophic insight. After all, in the past half-dozen years a whole
                    string of his closest associates have been declared guilty of the most serious
                    crimes and whisked out of sight—including two hand-picked heirs apparent and his
                    personal secretary.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName>’s style then, includes audacity and
                    the activist impulse with a skillful sense of political tactics. He has
                    repeatedly shown a unique capacity to judge when to press, when to retreat and
                    adopt a humble posture, how to build a broad coalition of support, and also an
                    unflinching willingness to attack his opposition when his own position is
                    strong.</p>
                <p>His pragmatism and tactical adaptability is reflected in what was clearly his
                    decision to use one barbarian (the United States) to control another (the Soviet
                    Union) and invite you to the Middle Kingdom. He is reported to have
                    remarked:</p>
                <p>“Bad things can change into good things, and bad persons can become good persons.
                    I like a person such as <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, but I do
                    not like Social Democrats or Revisionists. These kinds of people say one thing
                    and do another. Although <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> has his
                    cunning side, he is not as bad as the others, for his policy is more open.”</p>
                <p>Pointing out <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName>’s tactical agility should
                    not, however, obscure his basic philosophic trait. His stature as one of the
                    20th century’s outstanding political figures derives from his visionary side—a
                    combination of personal assertiveness, charismatic self-confidence, and a
                    creative native intelligence. This man knows where he wants China to go, and has
                    been pushing his country’s social revolution for more than fifty years. He has
                    torn China apart twice in a decade—in the Great Leap Forward and in the Cultural
                    Revolution—to meet what he considered ideological requirements.</p>
                <p>When he started his revolutionary road back in the 1920s there was absolutely no
                    prospect of success. Since then, again and again, he has faced one towering
                    crisis after another—the annihilation campaigns of Chiang, Long March, Japanese
                    invasion, civil war with the Nationalists, Korean War, Great Leap Forward, split
                    with Moscow, <pb facs="0730" n="675" xml:id="pg_675"/> Cultural Revolution,
                    progressive Soviet encirclement. Surmounting such challenges requires vision as
                    well as tactics.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName>’s peasant background is evident in his
                    direct and earthy humor, which he often used to ridicule or disarm opponents. At
                    the same time, he has the sensitivity to write appealing poetry, displays a good
                    working knowledge of Chinese history, and has a capacity for insight and
                    abstract social analysis which has produced a number of philosophical writings
                    and a clear (if not necessarily attainable) concept of his country’s future.</p>
                <p>And he has made this vision real to others, like <persName corresp="#p_YCM1"
                        >Marshal Yeh</persName> who told me in July of <persName corresp="#p_MT1"
                        >Mao</persName>’s romantic appeal to him. Yeh was a general in Chiang’s army
                    in the 1920s when he heard of <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> in the
                    mountains and what he was doing for the peasants and for China. The Marshal
                    decided that his place was alongside this man, and he has been with him ever
                    since. Countless others followed his example.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Chou</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Chou is clearly running China. He is the dominant figure in both the party and
                    government, and he steers both foreign and domestic policy. He refers to
                        <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> for major issues of principle but
                    clearly has great latitude in carrying out policies and decision-making.</p>
                <p>He is charming, articulate and tough. You will enjoy the give-and-take with Chou
                    on several planes, on all of which he is equally at home—historical discussion,
                    philosophic dissertation, tactical jousting, hard bargaining, light
                    repartee.</p>
                <p>You can be sure that he had done his homework, not only on the issues but also on
                    America and you personally. He has a good command of American politics and
                    society, although his picture must be distorted.</p>
                <p>His negotiating style is extremely effective and requires finesse to counter. If
                    he states a position in absolute terms, he will stick by it at least for a
                    while. He is not to be pressed if he is not ready to be pressed.</p>
                <p>If, however, he is at all evasive or ambiguous—which is the usual case—this
                    suggests room for exploration. In this case it is better to go at the issue
                    circuitously rather than frontally. Either later in a meeting, or on an informal
                    occasion, you could pick up the subject again and suggest another approach. He
                    might then absorb this and come back subsequently with a new statement
                    incorporating elements of what you said but presenting it as the Chinese
                    view.</p>
                <p>The indirect approach, the use of analogy, is typical of the Chinese in general
                    and Chou in particular. Almost everything he says, no matter how far it seems to
                    stray from the subject at hand, is making a relevant point. This oblique style
                    is not at all inconsistent with candor. Indeed, frankness was one of the
                    dominant elements in our talks with Chou, and frankness would serve you well in
                    your conversations.</p>
                <pb facs="0731" n="676" xml:id="pg_676"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HBGAMJ1">Haig</persName> and I have been treated to
                    withering blasts, although Chou has never been vituperative or harsh in personal
                    terms. In dealing at your level, he may round a few edges, but you can assume
                    that you will get some very hard speeches, spoken with a simple eloquence and
                    perhaps just after some cordial small talk.</p>
                <p>You should not let such statements stand but rather respond very firmly, though
                    non-abusively. If you start pulling back he will stay on the offensive. If his
                    thrust is philosophic, you should counter with your own viewpoint without
                    attacking his. If he makes a frontal assault on a specific issue, however, you
                    should retort directly.</p>
                <p>Chou’s firmness, however, is not the kind of brutalizing toughness which we have
                    come to expect from the Russians, but rather a hardness and consistency of
                    purpose derived from fifty years of revolutionary experiences. To these people
                    “struggle” is a way of life, without which they never would have gotten to where
                    they are. Peace in the abstract is not a virtue; without justice it can serve to
                    ratify oppression.</p>
                <p>Thus if Chou (or <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName>) makes hard
                    statements, your response must be different than what you would use with the
                    Russians. The latter can be met with tough language as well as tough substance.
                    With the Chinese it is important to counter strongly with one’s own viewpoint,
                    but in a way that reflects comprehension of their point of view. My own
                    experience is that if you remain firm on principles but express yourself with
                    restraint, they are likely to modify their rhetoric and address points of
                    contention in a relatively realistic way. They may actually try to test you by
                    firing some “empty cannon” of rhetoric at you, but a polite, though firm,
                    rebuttal should get them to drop this tactic.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In sum, these people are both fanatic and pragmatic. They are tough ideologues
                    who totally disagree with us on where the world is going, or should be going. At
                    the same time, they are hard realists who calculate they need us because of a
                    threatening Soviet Union, a resurgent Japan, and a potentially independent
                    Taiwan.</p>
                <p>The Chinese leaders are deadly serious people who will not be swayed from their
                    convictions by anything that in their view smacks of opportunism or convenience.
                    They take a very principled approach, but within that framework they are willing
                    to be realistic. This reflects the tension between their sense of history and
                    their imperative for movement.</p>
                <p>On the one hand, they have been surmounting towering internal and external
                    obstacles for some fifty years. They take a long view. They see history on their
                    side.</p>
                <pb facs="0732" n="677" xml:id="pg_677"/>
                <p>On the other hand, these leaders are in their seventies, and they surely want to
                    reach certain goals before they depart the scene. Assuring the security of their
                    country and their system for their successors must preoccupy them. In addition,
                    the mysterious events last fall and the alleged <persName corresp="#p_LP1">Lin
                        Piao</persName> challenge underline the great gamble <persName
                        corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> and Chou have taken in dealing with us and
                    inviting you. Thus they will need to show some immediate results for their
                    domestic audience.</p>
                <p>Our essential requirement is to demonstrate that we are serious enough to
                    understand the basic forces at work in the world and reliable enough to deliver
                    on the commitments we make. If in our formal and informal talks we can impress
                    the Chinese with these intangibles, we will have truly made your visit an
                    historic success. If we fail to do so, we can expect the Chinese to be an
                    increasingly thorny adversary, and history could record your visit as a gallant
                    but stillborn venture.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
