<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-02-25T05:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-02-25T04:45:00-05:00" n="200" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d200">
                        <head>200. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d200fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White
                                House Special Files, President’s Office Files, Box 87, Memoranda for
                                the President. Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. The
                                meeting was held at the President’s Guest House.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Beijing</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1972-02-25T17:45:00+08:00" to="1972-02-25T18:45:00+08:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">February 25, 1972, 5:45–6:45
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>The President</item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>,
                                Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">John H. Holdridge</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LW1">Winston Lord</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff</item>
                            <item>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CCK1">Ch’iao Kuan-hua</persName>, Vice
                                Minister of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CW1">Chang Wen-chin</persName>, Director of
                                Western Europe, North American, and Australasian Affairs, Ministry
                                of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>Cha Chi-hua, Ministry of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>Chi Chao-chu, Interpreter</item>
                            <item>T’ang Wen-sheng, Interpreter</item>
                            <item>Two Notetakers</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>(The conversation began with a brief exchange of pleasantries between
                            Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName> and the
                            President concerning the President’s trip to the Great Wall and weather
                            conditions in Peking.)</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: I understand
                            that the weather will be clear between here and Hangchow tomorrow, and
                            there will be no trouble in your flight there.</p>
                        <p>We don’t have too much time left tonight, so if we don’t finish we can go
                            on in Hangchow and Shanghai. We can also let the two negotiators (Dr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CCK1">Ch’iao Kuan-hua</persName>) work later on tonight
                            after the banquet.</p>
                        <p>The President: We should tell them to get finished!</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Then we can
                            meet for about 15 minutes to hold a plenary at the airport tomorrow
                            before your departure (for Hangchow).</p>
                        <pb facs="0841" n="786" xml:id="pg_786"/>
                        <p>The President: I think that a half-hour would be better. It would make
                            some of our people who have not had a chance to sit in on the private
                            sessions feel that they have had a part to play, too. We could also have
                            some photos taken.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Yes, photos
                            would be all right with me. And, if we go for a half-hour, you can say
                            more.</p>
                        <p>The President: No. I’m through talking. We will let the negotiators have
                            a chance to speak. They haven’t talked enough.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: We can also
                            ask Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and
                            Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_CP1">Chi P’eng-fei</persName> to
                            say more. They can talk about what went on in their meetings.</p>
                        <p>The President: That’s a good idea. They haven’t had a chance to talk to
                            us, and we should hear them.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Now I have
                            two questions which I haven’t discussed yesterday.</p>
                        <p>One is the question of Sino–Soviet relations. I have spoken very clearly
                            about that question in the meeting of the 23rd in this very room. That
                            was a recall of history. Now, we face a situation of great tension
                            between China and the Soviet Union, but it won’t be difficult to solve
                            if there is truly an intention to solve it. There is only a further
                            question, and therefore we are willing to solve the boundary question if
                            it is not done under the threat of force. Then, we have always striven
                                (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>) to reach a provisional agreement.
                            That’s what the question is all about. We have neither territorial
                            claims against the Soviet Union nor the wish to impose our will on
                            them.</p>
                        <p>As for other disputes on principle between the two centers, they are
                            bound to continue. As Mr. President said, ideological disputes are of a
                            long-term nature. But this should not prevent countries and states from
                            improving their relations—their good neighborly relations—and reaching a
                            state of harmony. That is what Chairman <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> told the deputy head of their negotiating delegation
                            on May Day 1970. This was at a period when the head of the Soviet
                            delegation, <persName corresp="#p_KVV1">Kuznetsov</persName>, was back
                            in the Soviet Union ill. We heard he was ill. Since 1964 and 1965, we
                            have conveyed our opinions to the Soviet Union through the former
                            Pakistan Head of State <persName corresp="#p_KMA1">Ayub Khan</persName>.
                            This was, first, we would not make provocations. At that time we
                            conveyed this message to two heads of state, the Soviet head of state
                            and President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B. Johnson</persName>,
                            that we would not make provocations. The second point was that if you
                            did attack us and came into our country, we would defend ourselves.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Just as the
                            President mentioned yesterday, the Great Wall was for the purpose of
                            defending, not dividing people.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: And our
                            digging underground air raid shelters is becoming known. Every family is
                            digging underground shelters <pb facs="0842" n="787" xml:id="pg_787"/>
                            and linking them together. I believe soon that Americans will find out
                            about that.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> didn’t know about it?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I didn’t know
                            this.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: I don’t think
                            he mentioned it. He knows about it.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: President
                                <persName corresp="#p_KAMY1">Yahya</persName> told me.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Our Soviet
                            friends also know because some also tried to see them.</p>
                        <p>A third point we made was that what we say counts.</p>
                        <p>The fourth point was that if your country from the air launches attacks
                            against us, we would also consider that war; you should not think that
                            you could get away with that.</p>
                        <p>Our attitude toward the Soviet Union at the present time still consists
                            of these four points.</p>
                        <p>As for relations between our two countries, since Mr. President initiated
                            contacts between our two countries, some changes have occurred in the
                            tension that existed between our two countries. And Chairman <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> also mentioned to Mr. President when
                            they met on the first day that the question of aggression by the United
                            States against China or the question of aggression by China against the
                            United States was not a major problem.</p>
                        <p>But another question exists, that is the question of the Soviet Union
                            which has not yet been solved. But we are still maintaining a position
                            of defense. We also maintain our position of willingness to improve
                            state relations with the Soviet Union.</p>
                        <p>But it is absolutely impossible for us to enter into negotiations under
                            the threat of force. Our request to the Soviet Union is not for them to
                            withdraw troops, because we do not interfere in their internal affairs.
                            Our request is only to disengage in areas that are disputed and this is
                            a most fair position. That is what we mentioned the day before
                            yesterday. Three points I mentioned on that day were: one, to maintain
                            the status quo on the border; two, to refrain from military threats; and
                            third, to disengage from disputed areas.</p>
                        <p>Yet from reports which we have received from various quarters, the Soviet
                            Union is engaged in major military maneuvers in this part of the world
                            or in others, and from what <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_FT1">Fukuda</persName>, within the next five years there will be greater
                            conflict between China and the Soviet Union than there was at
                                <persName>Chen Pao</persName>. Perhaps they want to do as they did
                            in Bangladesh, and maybe they will try to create a Republic of
                            Turkestan, or something.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: We won’t
                            recognize it.</p>
                        <pb facs="0843" n="788" xml:id="pg_788"/>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: But such
                            words can not intimidate persons. We will resist. It is not so easy for
                            them to enter the Sinkiang Province, and even if they come in it will be
                            hard for them to get out. No matter what, we will not make provocations.
                            At the same time our attitude toward contacts and negotiations between
                            the United States and the Soviet Union is not one of opposition, but
                            rather an attitude of viewing these things as a normal phenomenon. And
                            therefore we wish that the negotiations you are going to hold in May
                            will be able to make progress and also be successful. We also have to
                            admit that that will not be easy.</p>
                        <p>And we can’t understand why we, who are much weaker than they, have
                            greater confidence; while they, who are much stronger than we, show such
                            great fear. This is something we cannot understand. Mr. President, you
                            will understand their mentality.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: They are
                            pathological on the subject. The only major nation attacking this trip
                            is the Soviet Union. I am sure the Prime Minister has noted that
                            European nations, Latin American nations, all favor this trip. The press
                            is very good in Europe.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Japan and India are
                            not ecstatic.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Yes, but they
                            can’t do anything about it.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: They’ll have
                            to wait and see.</p>
                        <p>Our attitude toward Japan is also one of willingness to promote good
                            relations. And in the Communiqué we wish to issue, it may be written
                            that neither of our sides seeks hegemony in the Pacific Ocean region and
                            doesn’t want other powers to do so, and that also includes them. And
                            this is also our attitude towards the Soviet Union. If the Soviet Union
                            asks the President about our attitude toward them, you may tell them
                            that. Otherwise it may appear that we two here are colluding against
                            them and are up to some tricks; for example, they may think that we’re
                            trying to subvert them.</p>
                        <p>The question for their own country is their business to solve. We don’t
                            meddle in their affairs.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: And I’m glad to
                            get this information from the Prime Minister, because when I go to the
                            Soviet Union, under no circumstances will I negotiate about or discuss
                            our relations with the People’s Republic of China without his approval
                            or knowledge. We are not going there for that purpose. And it will be
                            our purpose as I indicated…<note n="2" xml:id="d200fn2">All ellipses are
                                in the source text.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: I said that
                            because they might ask you about that subject.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Would you prefer
                            that I not raise it?</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: There is no
                            need for you to raise it, but they will probably ask about that. This
                            should be your response.</p>
                        <pb facs="0844" n="789" xml:id="pg_789"/>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: (to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>) That is something we will
                            do. We will meet seven days and we will need topics in order to meet
                            every day; we will also have to find the topics. They have already asked
                            Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> three times about
                            what was discussed when he was here in the People’s Republic.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I expect a phone
                            call from the Soviet Ambassador 9:00 o’clock Tuesday morning, February
                            28. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: I also
                            heard that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> told the
                            President to use the name People’s Republic of China in a toast to
                            Ceausecu, and the Soviet Ambassador immediately called attention to
                            that, and when you also mentioned the title properly in the World
                            Report.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Rather than
                            “Communist China.”</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: That is a
                            very strange thing. Since they have been calling us by the People’s
                            Republic of China for so many years, why should they be unhappy when you
                            call us the same thing? We find it very difficult to understand them. It
                            is truly a kind of pathology.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I think they
                            apparently welcomed an antagonistic relationship between the United
                            States and the People’s Republic of China. That is why they react when
                            we showed we had changed our attitude. They did not want us to have more
                            normal relations.</p>
                        <p>I would not try to judge motives, but based on their conduct they
                            apparently want the People’s Republic and the United States to be at
                            odds. However, our policy is not, as I said to the Prime Minister, to
                            have the People’s Republic and the Soviet Union at odds. As I told the
                            Prime Minister, I reject the proposition that it is in the interest of
                            the United States to have the Soviet Union and China in a state of
                            belligerency.</p>
                        <p>In a sentence, we want good relations with the People’s Republic and we
                            want good relations with the Soviet Union. And we would welcome better
                            relations between the Soviet Union and People’s Republic of China. That,
                            however, is something the Soviet Union and the People’s Republic will
                            have to work out.</p>
                        <p>As I said when I was in Romania and Yugoslavia, my principle is any
                            nation can be a friend of the United States without being someone else’s
                            enemy. That is my view.</p>
                        <p>I realize that is sometimes very difficult to achieve, because there is a
                            tendency for some nations to gang up against other nations. But in the
                            very delicate power balances in the world we in the United States would
                            not gain in the long run by trying to stir up trouble between other
                            nations. We, the United States, would not gain by trying to stimulate
                            conflict between the Soviet Union and the People’s Republic. The
                            People’s Republic would not gain, the Soviet Union would not gain, and
                            we would not gain by trying to stimulate conflict between the
                            others.</p>
                        <pb facs="0845" n="790" xml:id="pg_790"/>
                        <p>That is the idea, but in practicality we realize that the real world is
                            very different than the ideal, and that is what we are concerned about,
                            the real world.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Because we
                            are speaking about practical questions, I would like to mention the
                            question of the Middle East. Why is it not possible for Israel to return
                            to the Arab nations the lands that it occupies? Wouldn’t that be
                            beneficial to the relaxing of tensions?</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: The return of
                            territory is, of course, the key to the problem. But Israel feels that
                            it cannot return territory unless there is a better balance—so that it
                            is better able to defend itself against an attack should one occur. But
                            the subject of returning territory is one we are constantly discussing
                            in these very intricate negotiations.</p>
                        <p>May I say to the Prime Minister that while this subject is not on our
                            agenda, I can understand the Prime Minister’s interest in it and his
                            interest in some of the other countries on Israel’s borders. I would
                            like to authorize Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                            when he comes in June to discuss this with the Prime Minister. It must
                            be kept totally confidential, however, because otherwise it will blow.
                            We may not get a settlement anyway, but Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> can inform the Prime Minister as it occurs.
                            What is happening in this arena is like the tip of the iceberg.</p>
                        <p>No confidential talks have yet begun but we are considering, just the two
                            of us, the possibilities here. That is why [<hi rend="italic">what</hi>]
                            I am referring to. One of the problems is that I don’t think I can sneak
                            Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> into Cairo, as I
                            did into Peking.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: That would be
                            rather difficult. But actually it originally was possible for you to
                            have contacts with the Arab countries.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Our policy, as
                            Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> can tell you, since
                            the day I took office has been to develop better contacts with the Arab
                            countries. I haven’t visited most of the countries. I knew Nasser and,
                            of course, several other leaders in the area, so that is a goal, but the
                            Israeli problem, I confess, makes more difficult the attainment of that
                            goal. But we are working toward it.</p>
                        <p>They in effect say, for example, that they cannot resume relations with
                            us in a formal sense until they settle the problems of the Israeli–Arab
                            dispute. But we have a number of informal contacts, and we are expanding
                            those. It makes no sense, looking at the Middle East situation in terms
                            of Israel, which as I pointed out is not the real problem in the Middle
                            East, but in terms of the geopolitical forces there, to leave the Soviet
                            Union as the only major power to whom the Arab countries can turn to for
                            assistance.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: After you
                            have withdrawn from Libya, do you still help the Libyans exploit their
                            oil?</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Yes, we still have
                            oil companies in Libya. The percentage being paid to Libya is being
                            increased compared to what it was <pb facs="0846" n="791" xml:id="pg_791"/> previously. Actually, the Libyans are becoming a
                            foreign policy power because they have an enormous amount of dollars and
                            a very small population. They have offered a subsidy to Malta, for
                            example. (<gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: That is also
                            an abnormal development since the Second World War.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It’s an indirect
                            program of American aid. American economic aid goes through Libya to
                            other countries. (<gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: They also say
                            that you have taken away their natural resources, and therefore you
                            should give them a percentage of the profits.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: They have a good
                            deal, a better percentage than any other nations are given by other
                            companies.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Therefore
                            they’re not only opposing your colonialism, but also Soviet colonialism.
                            That is one of their advantages. You probably already know they do not
                            have relations with us.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I did not know
                            that.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: You withdrew
                            your largest airbase from Libya.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Yes, Wheelus.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: You made it
                            impossible for the British naval base to stay on there. The Soviet Union
                            cast eyes on that base, but Libya resisted that. So there are some good
                            things in your oil profits.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Libya is one of
                            the artificial countries the Prime Minister referred to, primarily in
                            Central Africa; this is northern Africa. And I am not referring to
                            boundary problems.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: It is the
                            only country in north Africa that I have not been to.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: It is an
                            artificial country which should never have been created. It has never
                            been a country; that is my view. I don’t tell the Libyans that, however.
                            Morocco, Tunisia, Algeria, the UAR—all have a certain identity but Libya
                            just has oil.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: I believe in
                            the past it had closer relations with Egypt than with the Maghreb
                            countries.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Oil.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: It is one of
                            the few places where <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang
                                Kai-shek</persName> maintains one of his Ambassadors. That is a very
                            particular place. You, of course, also understand our policy towards
                            that. We understand their policy and don’t want to impose anything on
                            them.</p>
                        <p>I would like to go on to another question, that of the Portuguese
                            colonies in Africa. I’m just putting forward this question for
                            discussion in an informal way. Why is it you don’t persuade Portugal to
                            give up its two big colonies in Africa, because those are places where
                            the black people are subjected to the most oppressive policies.</p>
                        <pb facs="0847" n="792" xml:id="pg_792"/>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: The influence I
                            think we can assert on Portugal would be very minimal. The Portugal
                            Government has a totally negative reaction towards providing
                            independence for these countries.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: They consider them
                            technically part of Portugal. They are not treated as colonies, but they
                            are treated as part of Portugal.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Just as France
                            used to treat some of its colonies, like Algeria, as part of France.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: France could
                            say that, but Portugal is so tiny and yet has such great colonies
                            abroad. It even has a very small piece of our territory, a very small
                            place called Macau, and call it part of Portugal. It was acquired 400
                            years ago. Many of our comrades say that with a brush of one’s finger we
                            could get that territory back, but we have always maintained a very
                            restrained attitude and want to wait awhile.</p>
                        <p>India showed her courage and reconvened [<hi rend="italic">recovered</hi>] Goa, which is as small as Macau. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName><note n="3" xml:id="d200fn3"/>
                            once boasted to me about that, and asked why didn’t we take back Macau?
                            I said we were not in such a hurry because the major question was the
                            national independence of Angola, Mozambique, and Portuguese Guinea in
                            the south. Besides them, what is Macau in comparison?</p>
                        <p>We believe that this is the question most unequal toward Europe, and also
                            toward Africa and Asia. There are two things. First, the Portuguese
                            colonies. Second, there is the white rule in South Africa, also in
                            Southern Rhodesia and South West Africa. This is something too unequal,
                            too unjust. Recently in the U.N. our Vice Foreign Minister spoke about
                            that, and also mentioned that in the Security Council meeting held in
                            Addis Ababa, Ethiopia. And on these matters even the Emperor of
                            Ethiopia, Haile Selassie II, and also the very conservative President of
                            Kenya, were the most indignant ones when the issue was brought up.</p>
                        <p>And so, entirely based on the coming-closer relations (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>) which are happening between our two countries, I want to
                            say that this is a question worth saying something about, because the
                            U.S. could say something in this regard. Because the policy adopted by
                            the governments of South Africa, Portugal and Rhodesia they impose on
                            other countries to accept.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: We have, of
                            course, stated our position in the U.N. on many occasions on these
                            points. The question is not really one of goals, or of ideals. We
                            believe in majority rule; we don’t believe in racism. We said that and
                            we mean that. On the other hand, the <pb facs="0848" n="793" xml:id="pg_793"/> military resolution of the problem in South Africa
                            and Rhodesia would be a great tragedy, not so much for the whites as the
                            blacks. That’s our view. While other nations like the People’s Republic
                            may take a strong position, and may take a more immediate approach while
                            we have a more restrained position, I think our goals are the same.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: But the
                            Portuguese Government is adopting an attitude of even greater military
                            repression and suppression of those places according to what we have
                            learned. And the white rule in Southern Rhodesia also is supported by
                            the British, who support Smith.<note n="4" xml:id="d200fn4">Ian Douglas
                                Smith, Prime Minister of Rhodesia.</note> Of course, this is a very
                            informal exchange of opinions. There is no major difference in our
                            stands.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: I hope the Prime
                            Minister understands that we are not always going to vote the same way
                            on resolutions in the United Nations. But he also understands that each
                            of us must make the best judgment as to our best approach. We are, of
                            course, vitally interested in the problems of the black people of
                            Africa. There we are also allies of the British and of Portugal, and it
                            is very difficult for us to take a position which goes as far as the
                            Prime Minister goes on this. I think we can perhaps influence more
                            effectively by more of a restrained course of action so that we can have
                            some influence with our allies. (<gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>I wonder if the Prime Minister and I would have a chance to talk
                            informally on the plane.</p>
                        <p>There is one personal matter which I would like to submit for the Prime
                            Minister’s consideration. That is the problem of Downey that Dr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> discussed with him
                            in October.<note n="5" xml:id="d200fn5">See <ref target="#d164fn15">footnote 15, Document 164</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Downey?</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: The American
                            prisoner. We know that Downey was guilty. We know also the Prime
                            Minister’s government has shown compassion in commuting his sentence to
                            five years.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Mr.
                                <persName>Fecteau</persName> has already been returned. President
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Fecteau’s and
                            Harbort’s release had a very good impact on our country.</p>
                        <p>Incidentally, we know, too, that there are two flyers involved in Vietnam
                            about whom no action can be taken until the Vietnam problem is solved.
                            Naturally we would appreciate that those two be treated as well as
                            possible until we are able to work out the prisoner of war matter with
                            North Vietnam.</p>
                        <pb facs="0849" n="794" xml:id="pg_794"/>
                        <p>What I now present to the Prime Minister for consideration is not a
                            request—there is no legal basis—and he has no obligation to act, but
                            Downey’s mother wrote me before I came. She is now 76 years old. She is
                            not well. After five years she will be 81 and the possibility that she
                            will not be alive when her son returns is quite obvious. I told her I
                            would raise the subject with the Prime Minister. You must make this
                            judgment. It would be a very compassionate act, especially since the
                            mother is old and not well. It would have an enormously good impression
                            in the United States, as you know when you were there (looking at
                            Ch’iao) the story Harbort and Fecteau did.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chou</persName>: Last year we
                            already commuted his sentence to five years. And it seems he has behaved
                            rather well recently. And therefore it is possible for us to take
                            further measures when we have the opportunity. Of course, that will take
                            some time. It is a complicated process for us because there are no
                            relations between our two countries and there exists no legal
                            precedent.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>: Exactly.</p>
                        <p>I must get to the banquet before the Prime Minister.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>