<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>276. Telegram From the Embassy in India to to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d276</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">276</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-04-08T09:27:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-04-08T09:27:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-04-08T09:27:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-04-08T09:27:00-05:00" n="276"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d276">
                <head>276. Telegram From <gloss type="from">the Embassy in India</gloss> to <gloss
                        type="to">the Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d276fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 30 TIBET. Secret; <gloss target="#t_EXDIS1"
                            >Exdis</gloss>. Also sent for the White House.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New Delhi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-04-08T14:27:00+00:00">April 8, 1970, 1427Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4018. Subject: Dalai Lama Visit to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Ref: State
                        050041.<note n="2" xml:id="d276fn2">See <ref target="#d275fn4">footnote 4,
                            Document 275</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>I am aware that <gloss target="#t_REFTEL1">reftel</gloss> had been cleared
                        at White House level and I appreciate Washington’s concern over possibility
                        that the Dalai Lama’s visit might become additional point of friction with
                        Peking with whom we are attempting to develop useful dialogue. But there are
                        other factors which in my view strongly militate against a flat rejection of
                        the trip this year: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>The Department should be aware that historically for past several
                                years [<hi rend="italic">1 line of source text not
                                declassified</hi>] actively encouraged the Dalai Lama to make a trip
                                to the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Given the operating style
                                of the Dalai Lama’s brother, Gyalo Thondup, it is possible that
                                certain offices of the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> are aware
                                of this background, although we have no such evidence.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>CAS is currently reducing its contribution to certain sensitive
                                Tibetan programs [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>].<note n="3" xml:id="d276fn3">See <ref
                                        target="#d273">Documents 273</ref> and <ref target="#d274"
                                        >274</ref>.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>There is a strong likelihood, therefore, that taken together with
                                our recent gestures toward Peking a total rejection of even a
                                private visit at this juncture would be interpreted by the Tibetan
                                leadership and the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> not only as
                                an insult to the Dalai Lama but also evidence that Washington has
                                really gone soft on the <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">Chicom</gloss>
                                issue to the point of “appeasing” Peking. As suggested by <gloss
                                    target="#t_FONSEC1">FonSec</gloss> T.N. Kaul’s remarks during
                                last year’s Indo-<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> bilaterals,<note
                                    n="4" xml:id="d276fn4">See <ref target="frus1969-76ve07#d29">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol.
                                        E–7, Documents 29</ref> and <ref
                                        target="frus1969-76ve07#d30">30</ref>.</note> there are
                                those in the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> who are
                                increasingly prone to ask where shifting <gloss target="#t_US1"
                                    >US</gloss> position on China leaves India. I do not wish to
                                dramatize this point, but as Indians examine the <persName
                                    corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine it is a problem
                                which we must handle with extreme care. (This, of course, is not to
                                suggest that the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> wants the Dalai
                                Lama to make the trip. Indians have their own sensitivities re
                                keeping the door open for dialogue with Peking.)</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>I realize that our free press and what might be characterized as a
                                Tibetan lobby in the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> would make it
                                difficult to avoid <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> attention to
                                the Dalai Lama during his visit. Nevertheless, I believe that this
                                problem can be resolved tactfully yet firmly, without unduly <pb
                                    facs="1199" n="1144" xml:id="pg_1144"/> upsetting Peking
                                (certainly not as much as recent revelations of <gloss
                                    target="#t_US1">US</gloss> arms supply to Taiwan).</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Therefore, I urge that: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>The Department revise its position to permit at least a private
                                visit this year.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>Both Department and Embassy make it clear to Tibetans that while
                                    <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> will quietly provide
                                appropriate security protection, we wish the visit be kept private
                                with courtesy calls on <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> officials
                                limited to level stated <gloss target="#t_REFTEL1">reftel</gloss>,
                                and that we would expect the Dalai Lama and his entourage to refrain
                                from using <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> as a forum for
                                attacking Peking or generally engaging in politicking.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Pending reply this message, I am deferring approach to Tibetans.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KKB1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Keating</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
