<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>6. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d6</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">6</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        withdrawal</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006005376"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Extremist</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="east-asia-and-pacific" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="east-asia-and-pacific">East Asia</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="recH8UKNUTXoDXkax" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Bandung Conference</term>
                    <term ref="rec43c89ba39282f56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="vietnam-conflict" subject="peace-talks">Peace talks</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="6"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d6">
                <head>6. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d6fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 700, Country Files, Europe,
                        Poland, Vol. I Warsaw Talks up to 1/31/70. Top Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_EXDIS1">Exdis</gloss>. This memorandum and the options
                        described in Tab A were taken from a February 11 memorandum from <persName
                            corresp="#p_SRL1">Sneider</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>. (Ibid.) In September and November of 1968, the
                        United States proposed renewing ambassadorial talks between the United
                        States and the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> that had commenced in
                        Geneva in 1955 and moved to Warsaw in 1957. Talks had been suspended since
                        the 134th meeting on January 8, 1968, and U.S. attempts to restart talks
                        during the spring of 1968 had failed. See <ref target="frus1964-68v30#d311">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. XXX, Documents
                            311</ref>, <ref target="frus1964-68v30#d331">331</ref>, and <ref
                            target="frus1964-68v30#d332">332</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-02-12">February 12, 1969</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>U.S. Policy Toward Peking and Instructions for the February 20 Warsaw
                        Meeting</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Secretary of State has sent you a recommended position and proposed
                    instructions for the February 20 Warsaw meeting with the Chinese
                        Communists.<note n="2" xml:id="d6fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> forwarded the draft
                        instructions for the February 20 meeting under cover of an undated
                        memorandum and a cable written by <persName corresp="#p_KPH1"
                            >Kreisberg</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Platt</persName>
                            (<gloss target="#t_EAACA1">EA/ACA</gloss>) on February 3. The
                        instructions had been cleared by <persName corresp="#p_BWP1"
                            >Bundy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BWG1">Brown</persName>, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_BRW1">Barnett</persName> (<gloss target="#t_EA1"
                            >EA</gloss>). <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>’ covering
                        memorandum and its attachments are also attached but not printed. The
                        Department of State copies of these documents are in National Archives,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files, 1967–69, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">CHICOM</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss>.</note> I have edited these instructions slightly to remove
                    polemics and in one case to eliminate an implication that we might be prepared
                    to remove our presence from Formosa. The instructions cover a number of
                    continuing problems with Peking, such as the question of Americans held prisoner
                    by the Communists and our desire for an understanding with Peking on assistance
                    and return of astronauts. They also cover a broad range of contingencies that
                    might arise during the Warsaw talks.</p>
                <p>The principal issue facing us is the basic posture we should adopt at Warsaw. The
                    attached memorandum (Tab A) discusses the four broad options open to us. As
                    edited, the State Department instructions (Tab B) fall basically within the
                    third option, namely to indicate our willingness to enter into serious
                    negotiations with Peking, make proposals on scientific exchanges, and invite
                    specific proposals from the Chinese.<note n="3" xml:id="d6fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d6fn2">footnote 2 above</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Right now, the third option has several advantages: (1) it would cause less
                    concern to the Republic of China, presently very sensitive because Canada and
                    Italy are moving to recognition of Peking; (2) it <pb facs="0066" n="11"
                        xml:id="pg_11"/> would reduce the risk that other countries might
                    misinterpret any initiative on our part as marking a fundamental change in China
                    policy in response to, or in connection with, Canadian recognition of Peking;
                    and (3) it avoids prejudging U.S. China policy before the National Security
                    Council undertakes its full dress review in late March.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That you approve the instructions at Tab B.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Approve<note n="4" xml:id="d6fn4">President <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> initialed this option. On February 13
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRM1">Richard Moose</persName> sent a memorandum
                        to the Department of State Executive Secretariat detailing several slight
                        changes to the draft cable. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">CHICOM</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss>) The instructions were sent on February 15 to Warsaw as telegram
                        24916. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Disapprove</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Amended</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Tab A<note n="5" xml:id="d6fn5">Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1969-02-11">February 11, 1969</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="strong">Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>) to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Warsaw Talks</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Background</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On November 15, the U.S. proposed deferring the next Warsaw meeting until
                        next February after being unable to obtain any answer from the Chinese
                        Communists on their intentions with respect to the scheduled November 20
                        meeting. The Chinese responded on November 25, much more promptly than
                        usual, with a letter and subsequent press release proposing the talks for
                        February 20. In contrast to communications over recent years, the Chinese
                        reply was less abusive and revived an old Chinese proposal for a joint
                        declaration of adherence to the Bandung Conference five principles of
                        “peaceful co-existence.” This proposal was loosely linked to the usual
                        Chinese Communist demand for U.S. military withdrawal from Taiwan. There
                        have been other <pb facs="0067" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/> indications of a
                        Chinese interest in returning to a “softer foreign policy” emphasizing state
                        relations rather than being revolution-oriented. While there is no evidence
                        Peking is seeking a détente with us, it is clear that Peking wishes to
                        resume some form of dialogue with us at Warsaw.</p>
                    <p>Speculation as to possible Chinese Communist motivations focusses on five
                        possibilities: <list>
                            <label>(a)</label>
                            <item>Internal difficulties, which continue, may increase the desire for
                                an easing of external relations;</item>
                            <label>(b)</label>
                            <item>The continuing Paris peace talks coupled with the declining
                                military fortunes of the North Vietnamese;</item>
                            <label>(c)</label>
                            <item>As a reaction to increased Sino-Soviet tensions;</item>
                            <label>(d)</label>
                            <item>As an effort to explore the views of the new Administration of
                                President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>;</item>
                            <label>(e)</label>
                            <item>As an effort to probe for softness in U.S. positions, particularly
                                in our relations with the Republic of China on Taiwan.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>An additional factor to take into account is that there may be divided
                        counsel in Peking on relations with the United States—although there is no
                        evidence of a fundamental shift of attitude towards the U.S. in the Warsaw
                        talks proposals or in subsequent propaganda. At a minimum, we have a retreat
                        from extremist positions taken during the height of the Great Cultural
                        Revolution.</p>
                    <p>As a first step to test Chinese Communist intentions, we have proposed that
                        the locus of the talks be shifted from a building provided by the Poles to
                        either the U.S. or Chinese Embassy where Soviet/Polish eavesdropping will
                        not be possible. Any serious talks with the Chinese are foreclosed by the
                        present building. The Chinese have rejected this proposal but left the door
                        open for discussion of it at the February 20 Warsaw meeting. In addition, we
                        have been informed that the Chinese Communists will be represented by their
                        Chargé in Poland, in the continued absence of Ambassador Wang. (Almost all
                        Chinese Ambassadors were called back to Peking many months ago for
                        “re-education” during the height of the cultural revolution. They have not
                        been returned.)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. China Policy</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In the past, the debate on China policy has focussed on the questions of
                        recognition and <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> representation, and U.S.
                        tactics were built around proposals to expand contacts with the mainland.
                        The debate on recognition and <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                        representation is essentially, in my view, a fruitless exercise given the
                        opposition of both Chinas to any two-China policy—although we will
                        constantly be faced with the problems in preventing an erosion of the
                        Republic of China position. Similarly, efforts to expand contacts with the
                        mainland have brought no response although they have the value of signalling
                        our interest in a broader relationship <pb facs="0068" n="13" xml:id="pg_13"
                        /> with Peking. We have one more major play to make in this string—the offer
                        to resume non-strategic trade with the mainland.</p>
                    <p>The Warsaw talks offer an opportunity to shift the focus of our policy: to
                        seeking a modus vivendi with the Communist Chinese which provides greater
                        stability for East Asia, (a) without abandoning our commitment to Taiwan or
                        undermining its position, or (b) damaging the interests of our Asian allies,
                        principally Japan. More specifically, our policy would be directed towards
                        seeking specific, self-enforceable arrangements with Peking which give some
                        substance, and not lip service, to “peaceful co-existence.”</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Alternative U.S. Positions at Warsaw</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>At Warsaw, four broad options are open to us.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Option 1</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>At the one extreme, we could indicate that we are prepared to negotiate a
                        normalization of relations with Peking based on an agreement for peaceful
                        relations between the U.S. and Communist China and noninterference in the
                        affairs of other countries. The proposal might be sweetened by an offer to
                        resume non-strategic trade. The Chinese Communists would, however, be
                        informed that our proposal is without prejudice to our relations with and
                        commitment to the Republic of China. This approach, explicitly emphasizing
                        normalization, would represent a basic change in U.S. policy—although we
                        have been implicitly moving in this direction.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>A normalization of relations on this basis, accepted by Peking, would
                            accomplish a shift in relations with the U.S. from an ideological
                            confrontation to state relations and a shift in Peking’s policy away
                            from political warfare directed against other Asian and less developed
                            nations.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The proposal, even if not accepted, would encourage elements within
                            the Peking leadership who may be arguing that the U.S. is not a hostile
                            force and that serious efforts should therefore be made to reach an
                            understanding with it.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>If not preceded by a probing of the mainland position, the Chinese
                            Communists might interpret the proposal as “softness” on our
                            part.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The proposal, even if not accepted, could cause a crisis of confidence
                            in Taiwan and seriously upset the Japanese Government which is trying to
                            hold the line against both conservative and left-wing pressures for a
                            more conciliatory policy towards Peking.</item>
                        <pb facs="0069" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>The proposal is likely to lead Japan and other countries to try to get
                            out in front of the U.S., with some countries quickly recognizing
                            Communist China and others moving to change their position on <gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> representation.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">To sum up</hi>: Given the low probability of an
                        affirmative Peking response, this alternative involves considerable risks
                        without prospect of <hi rend="italic">immediate</hi> gains.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Option 2</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The U.S. could indicate that we are prepared to enter into serious
                        discussions or negotiations with respect to our policies with the exception
                        of our commitment to Taiwan. This proposal might be combined with a specific
                        offer or hint of our willingness to review our military presence in the
                        Taiwan area if the Chinese renounce the use of force to settle this
                        dispute.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>This proposal would represent a move to greater flexibility on our
                            part and a positive invitation to the Chinese Communists. It would also
                            demonstrate that President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName>’s Administration is prepared to take a more
                            conciliatory approach to Peking in response to the shift in Peking’s
                            line on the Warsaw talks as set forth in its November 25 note.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>It would likewise encourage whatever more conciliatory elements may
                            exist within the Peking leadership.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>If this approach were not combined with an offer of strong military
                            presence in Taiwan, it would provide time to consider U.S. China policy
                            within the U.S. Government and to consult with other countries on
                            specific steps to implement it.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>This approach is likely to leave Japan and other interested Asian
                            countries jittery about a possible change in U.S. policy without
                            eliciting an immediate positive response from Peking.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>It may not go far enough to force any serious reconsideration of
                            policy in Peking.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>The specific offer on Taiwan would bring a quick and negative response
                            from the Republic of China, already agitated by Canadian and Italian
                            initiatives to recognize Peking. In addition it raises the issue of
                            whether we are prepared to withdraw from our bases in Taiwan given the
                            possibility of negotiations with respect to our Okinawan bases.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Option 3</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>We could pick up the Chinese reference to peaceful coexistence and ask
                        whether they have any specific proposals to make. We would <pb facs="0070"
                            n="15" xml:id="pg_15"/> not, however, take any specific or generalized
                        initiatives beyond indicating our willingness to hear out the Chinese.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>This approach would emphasize our interest in developing a stable,
                            peaceful environment in East Asia without committing us to any new
                            actions at this time.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>It would cause the least concern with our allies of Asia and in fact
                            would probably be welcome.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>It would permit a probe of Peking intentions and emphasize that the
                            monkey is on its back for specific initiatives.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>This approach is less likely to elicit a positive response from
                            Peking, either immediately or in the longer term.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>It is likely to be construed by Peking and others as a holding action
                            rather than a new initiative on our part.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Option 4</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>We could take the initiative and clobber the Chinese for past transgressions.
                        This approach would signal a very tough stance and would probably close the
                        door to any meaningful exchanges for some time— assuming that there is any
                        possibility under the present circumstances.<note n="6" xml:id="d6fn6">The
                                <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> cancelled the meeting on
                            February 18, ostensibly due to the defection of Chinese Chargé
                            d’Affaires Liao Ho-shu (Liao Heshu) in the Netherlands on January 24.
                            See “Spokesman of Chinese Foreign Ministry Information Department Issues
                            Statement,” <hi rend="italic">Beijing Review</hi>, February 21, 1969, p.
                            4. The Department of State documentation on Liao’s defection is in
                            National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                            1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 30 <gloss
                                target="#t_CHICOMS1">CHICOM</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1"
                                >Stoessel</persName> reported these developments in telegram 427
                            from Warsaw, February 18. (Ibid.) <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1"
                                >Stoessel</persName>’s report was forwarded to <persName
                                corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> in the President’s February 18
                            daily briefing memorandum. (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                                >Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss> Files, Box 2, President’s Daily Briefs) <gloss
                                target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> attributed the cancellation to <gloss
                                target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> internal politics rather than the
                            diplomat’s defection: “We regard Peking’s abrupt decision to postpone
                            the 135th meeting as the latest and most striking evidence of
                            disagreement and indecision at the highest levels of the Chinese
                            leadership.” (<gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> Intelligence Note 102,
                            February 18; ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                            1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">CHICOM</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_US1"
                                >US</gloss>) The <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> had reported
                            that “it is unlikely that there will be any change in Chinese Communist
                            position or softening of attitude toward the United States in the
                            upcoming 20 February Warsaw meeting.” (Intelligence Information Cable
                                TDCS–<gloss target="#t_K1">K</gloss>–314/01387–69, February 10;
                            ibid., <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                            Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 518, Country
                            Files, Far East, China, Vol. I) The United States responded to the
                            cancellation on March 12 with a letter to the <gloss target="#t_PRC1"
                                >PRC</gloss> Embassy in Warsaw, rejecting claims that the United
                            States “engineered” the defection of Liao, and adding that “I am
                            instructed to inform your Government that the United States Government
                            remains ready at an early date to continue the series of
                            Ambassadorial-level meetings between our two governments, either here in
                            Warsaw or elsewhere at a mutually agreeable location.” (Telegram 37867
                            to Warsaw, March 12; ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59,
                            Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">CHICOM</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_US1"
                                >US</gloss>)</note>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
