<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-01-20T11:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-01-20T11:45:00-05:00" n="62" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d62">
                        <head>62. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Poland</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d62fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">CHICOM</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_NODIS1">Nodis</gloss>. Received at 2 p.m. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> forwarded the cable to the President on
                                January 21 in his daily briefing memorandum. (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 16, President’s
                                Daily Briefs) The Embassy sent the full record of the meeting to the
                                Department of State on January 24 in Airgram A–25 from Warsaw.
                                (Ibid.) See <ref target="frus1969-76ve13#d3">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. E–13,
                                    Document 3</ref>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Stoessel</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KPH1">Kreisberg</persName> (Advisor),
                                    <persName>Donald M. Anderson</persName> (Interpreter),
                                    <persName>Thomas W. Simons</persName> (Scribe), <persName corresp="#p_LY1">Lei Yang</persName> (Chargé d’Affaires),
                                    <persName>Li Ch-ching</persName> (Advisor), <persName>Ch’ien
                                    Yung-nien</persName> (Interpreter), and <persName>Yeh
                                    Wei-lan</persName> (Scribe) attended both the January 20 and
                                February 20 meetings.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Warsaw</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-01-20T16:45:00+00:00">January 20, 1970,
                                1645Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>143. <gloss target="#t_SUBJ1">Subj</gloss>: Sino-<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Talks: 135th Meeting. Ref: (A) State 8061;<note n="2" xml:id="d62fn2">See <ref target="#d61fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                    61</ref>.</note> (B) Warsaw 141.<note n="3" xml:id="d62fn3">Telegram 141 from Warsaw, January 20, relayed the contents of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Stoessel</persName>’s public
                                statement following the meeting. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">CHICOM</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>In relatively brief (one hour) meeting, I opened with text
                                provided ref (A). Chinese statement which followed started with
                                assertion that basis of <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">ChiCom</gloss>
                                foreign policy was peaceful coexistence on basis of five principles.
                                From this <persName corresp="#p_LY1">Lei Yang</persName> moved to
                                note that these principles were not consistent with interference by
                                one country in internal affairs of another or forcible occupation by
                                one country of territory of another. He observed that my statement
                                to him on January 8 had spoken of widening communication and
                                political dialogue with <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> but had
                                omitted any mention of Taiwan.<note n="4" xml:id="d62fn4">See <ref target="#d59fn2">footnote 2, Document 59</ref>.</note> He
                                then devoted bulk of his remaining opening statement to Taiwan
                                issue.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>He emphasized Taiwan was crux of long-standing Sino-<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> disputes. Reviewing history of issue
                                beginning with Cairo and Potsdam Declarations, <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> interposition of 7th Fleet in Taiwan
                                Strait at beginning of Korean War, and <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> Treaty following
                                conclusion of Korean War, he said <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                had attempted to legalize forcible occupation of Taiwan, to plan to
                                bring about “Two Chinas” or “One China, One Taiwan” situation, and
                                to separate Taiwan from China. He said <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> had carried out war threats and provocations against
                                Mainland from Taiwan and has provided military aircraft to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> in the name of our treaty
                                responsibilities. All this was intervention and aggression against
                                the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>He emphasized that the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> would
                                    certainly liberate Taiwan and would never allow another country
                                    to occupy China’s territory.</p>
                                <pb facs="0223" n="168" xml:id="pg_168"/>
                                <p>Any expectation that Peking’s position on this would change was
                                    fruitless. He emphasized that it had been the fault of the
                                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> that no progress had been
                                    made in the Sino-<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> talks thus
                                    far because the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> continued to
                                    talk about subsidiary issues, rather than the key issue of
                                    Taiwan. It was up to the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>, he
                                    said, to consider how to deal with this basic issue if it wished
                                    to improve relations with the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>China, Lei said, was consistently in favor of the use of
                                negotiations and peaceful means to resolve disputes between the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> and were prepared on this basis to
                                explore and consider how to resolve the basic problems existing
                                between the two countries. <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> was
                                willing to consider and discuss any thoughts and proposals
                                consistent with the principles of peaceful coexistence which the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> wished to put forward.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Concluding, Lei said that such proposals could be put forward
                                either through the Ambassadorial-level talks or through higher-level
                                discussions or any other channel which both sides might agree
                                    upon.<note n="5" xml:id="d62fn5">The full record of the meeting
                                    (see <ref target="#d62fn1">footnote 1</ref> above) shows that,
                                    following the instructions from the Department of State,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Stoessel</persName> offered that
                                    “If as these talks progress it would seem to be useful and your
                                    Government would so desire, my Government would be prepared to
                                    consider sending a representative to Peking for direct
                                    discussions with your officials or receiving a representative of
                                    your Government in Washington for more thorough exploration of
                                    any of the subjects I have mentioned in my remarks today or
                                    other matters on which we might agree.”</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The general flavor of Lei’s remarks was non-polemical. His
                                restatement of the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>’s Taiwan
                                position did not explicitly call for any specific action by the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. He did not refer to any
                                specific incidents, to the 7th Fleet (except in the context of his
                                recitation of the history of the Taiwan issue), to “<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–Soviet collusion”, to Viet-Nam, or to
                                any other multilateral or ideological issues. Likewise, Lei did not
                                comment on <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> trade or travel moves.
                                His sole focus was on Taiwan as a bilateral, political,
                                non-ideological issue between us, and upon Peking’s willingness to
                                resolve disputes with the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> through
                                peaceful negotiations.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>I replied only briefly to <persName corresp="#p_LY1">Lei
                                    Yang</persName>’s remarks, reiterating in accordance with
                                Department’s guidance that the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                position relating to Taiwan was clear, that it was without prejudice
                                to any peaceful settlement which might be arrived at between Peking
                                and Taipei, and observed that it was my feeling that there was much
                                similarity between the positions he and I had set forth so far as
                                our desire to resolve any disputes in the area, including Taiwan, by
                                peaceful means. I then asked whether he could elaborate on the
                                meaning of “other channels” as a means of continuing our
                                discussions.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Lei on his part repeated that Peking’s position on Taiwan was
                                clear, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> treaty was not recognized by the people of China,
                                    <pb facs="0224" n="169" xml:id="pg_169"/> and that Taiwan was
                                not a state but a part of China. Lei specifically noted that he
                                would refer to Peking our proposal on sending a representative to
                                Peking or having a Chinese representative visit Washington. He
                                declined to elaborate on the meaning of meetings at “higher level”
                                or through “other channels,” and suggested <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> would consider <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                specific proposal on this subject or could work out proposal at
                                ambassadorial meeting. He then suggested that rather than setting a
                                specific date for the next meeting, liaison officers of our two
                                Embassies be in touch soon.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Our over-all impression of the meeting was that the Chinese wished
                                it to be considered as a serious opening negotiating session in
                                which direct bilateral issues could be set forth and general
                                ideological issues set aside. The atmosphere was straightforward and
                                businesslike with the Chinese moving the actual meeting from a large
                                formal hall (where newsmen were allowed to take photographs) to a
                                small, informal conference room. (We assume this was for security
                                reasons as well as for greater ease of dialogue and strongly
                                recommend that no public mention be made of fact talks did not
                                actually take place where newsmen were admitted.) It is somewhat
                                ambiguous at this point who will take the initiative in proposing
                                the next meeting. I suspect the Chinese intentionally left it
                                so.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>In briefing friendly governments on meeting, I recommend that
                                Chinese statement be characterized as generally dealing with problem
                                of Taiwan, restating essence of <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">ChiCom</gloss> position on historical character of this
                                dispute. General non-polemical, non-ideological character of <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">ChiCom</gloss> presentation might also be
                                noted. Recommend, however, that <gloss target="#t_CHICOMS1">ChiCom</gloss> proposal on higher-level meetings and
                                willingness discuss peaceful resolution of outstanding disputes with
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> might be held to ourselves for
                                present. Chinese we believe have gone to considerable efforts to
                                maintain security of present meeting and any leak of relatively
                                relaxed Chinese comments or optimistic characterization of
                                atmosphere of meeting could embarrass our future contacts with
                                Chinese and force defensive hardening of their posture.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Stoessel</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>