<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>77. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <head>77. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d77fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 913,
                        VIP Visits, Vol. I Visit of Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_CCG1">Chiang
                            Ching-Kuo</persName> of China, April 21–23, 1970. Secret; Sensitive.
                        According to a covering memorandum drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HJH1"
                            >Holdridge</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        approved this memorandum of conversation on June 2. It was to have “in-house
                        distribution only.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1970-04-22">April 22,
                            1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">John H. Holdridge</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Senior Staff Member</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName>William Codus</persName>, Office of Protocol, Department of
                        State</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CCG1">Chiang Ching-Kuo</persName>, Vice Premier,
                        Republic of China</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJCH1">James Shen</persName>, Vice Foreign Minister,
                        Republic of China</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chow Shu-kai</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> Vice Premier’s Conversation with Dr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The Vice Premier said he was glad to be received by Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> at a time when he, Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, was so busy. Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> said he had been looking forward to
                    seeing the Vice Premier. An <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting on
                    Cambodia was being held, so he had been obliged to cancel all of his afternoon
                    appointments. Nevertheless, he didn’t want to miss the opportunity to see the
                    Vice Premier briefly. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                    mentioned that he knew Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CCS1">Chow</persName>
                    very well, and regarded him as a very effective representative.</p>
                <pb facs="0258" n="203" xml:id="pg_203"/>
                <p>The Vice Premier declared that he wanted to express his sincere appreciation for
                    what Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> was doing in providing
                    an important link between our two countries. He had been very pleased to be able
                    to meet with <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> leaders from the President on
                    down, and found his discussions with them most rewarding. Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> commented that the President had been
                    most impressed by his meeting with the Vice Premier and had said that there was
                    no substitute for face-to-face contacts of this nature. The Vice Premier agreed
                    that there was no better way to get ideas across than to have views exchanged.
                    He liked to think that the relations between our two countries were not of an
                    ordinary sort, since they had been in existence for a long time. It was in this
                    light that he approached the opportunity to have a few days here and engage in
                    face-to-face discussions.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> declared that we believe
                    very strongly in standing by our friends. Sometimes we engaged in tactical moves
                    which looked confusing, but we knew how to separate strategy and tactics. A
                    newsman had said to him the other day that he had finally worked out the
                    President’s approach—the President was always four moves ahead of the game. His
                    reply had been that the newsman was half right, and that the first thing to
                    figure out was what game the President was playing.</p>
                <p>The Vice Premier said that his President had known the President for more than
                    twenty years, and liked to think that he understood him and knew what he
                    thought. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> remarked that he
                    had worked with the President since he had assumed office, had seen him make big
                    decisions, and had always seen him make the big choice. He had always supported
                    his friends, and had never yielded to the Communists on any issue. Speaking
                    frankly, we would go through lots of maneuvering before we acted because there
                    was no sense in tipping our hand. In this respect, the North Vietnamese
                    offensive on Laos hadn’t stopped because we were using kind words. Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> added that the President is not good
                    for the nerves of some of his subordinates in the bureaucracy, who are of a more
                    cautious frame of mind.</p>
                <p>The Vice Premier said he would like to know the consensus in the Administration
                    on Cambodia—is this part of the whole Communist strategy (which would include
                    Laos), or an issue by itself? Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> said, first, that our Administration policy with
                    respect to the bureaucracy was to “let 100 flowers bloom” but that our friends
                    should watch what we do and not what they in the bureaucracy say. Continuing, he
                    explained that we looked at Cambodia as part of the entire Indo-China problem
                    and of the total Communist movement there. He added that if they thought they
                    could move in Cambodia for nothing, they would know better soon.</p>
                <p>The Vice Premier said that the Chinese hoped that the new government in Phnom
                    Penh could hold out, but were apprehensive that <pb facs="0259" n="204"
                        xml:id="pg_204"/> the North Vietnamese would not stop where they were and
                    would try to put <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> back in power.
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> agreed that they would try,
                    and remarked that we couldn’t be too optimistic. The Cambodian army did not
                        have<note n="2" xml:id="d77fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> corrected this sentence,
                        changing “did not have” to “had.”</note> the same quality as the Laotian
                    army, and had not yet distinguished itself in combat. Singapore Prime Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_LKY1">Lee Kuan Yew</persName> had once said that the
                    only people who could fight in Asia were the Chinese or the people under Chinese
                    cultural influence. The Cambodians were definitely not the latter. We couldn’t
                    guarantee the outcome but would do what we could. The Communists would not have
                    a free ride. They had had more problems with us than with our predecessors. We
                    didn’t talk so much and would not ignore events in Cambodia, which we did not
                    consider a separate war. He hoped that the Cambodians could hold out for a few
                    more weeks. He asked what the Vice Premier thought.</p>
                <p>The Vice Premier agreed that Cambodia was not an isolated case but part of the
                    whole Indo-China question. The Chinese felt the same with respect to Laos. Their
                    intelligence indicated that the Chinese Communists were intensifying a training
                    program for Cambodian and Lao cadres in Kunming, which is right on the border.
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted that the Chinese
                    Communists had also given strong support to <persName corresp="#p_SPN1"
                        >Sihanouk</persName>. The Vice Premier went on to say that he doubted they
                    would use their own forces in the situation.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> asked the Vice Premier for
                    his estimate of the quality of the Chinese Communist army. In response, the Vice
                    Premier said that there had not been much change in the combat quality of the
                    ground forces, but there had been noteworthy improvements in the capability of
                    the air force and the navy. Army morale accounted for 50% of the Communist
                    capability under fire in the past, but he knew for a fact that this morale was
                    now not what it had been. Nevertheless, we should not ignore the fact that they
                    were stronger in the air and on the sea. He surmised that the emphasis in the
                    training being given Cambodians and Lao in Kunming was on guerrilla warfare.</p>
                <p>The Vice President then asked Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> for his estimate of the significance of <persName
                        corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName>’s visit to Pyongyang. Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> replied that he didn’t have a clear
                    opinion on this. The Chinese Communists were trying to mend relations with many
                    neighbors, and to prevent excessive Soviet influence, but he felt that the Vice
                    Premier’s views would be more interesting than his own.</p>
                <p>The Vice Premier said that there was one theory to the effect that North Korea
                    had come to resent the tight control which the Soviets had exercised in
                    restraining North Korean adventures against South Korea <pb facs="0260" n="205"
                        xml:id="pg_205"/> which might involve the Soviets themselves. This
                    resentment had reached such proportions as to make it desirable for North Korea
                    to break away a bit and to establish closer relations with Peking instead. Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> observed that the North
                    Koreans would be in tough shape if they attacked—they could not count on making
                    a move against the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> again and getting away with
                    it.</p>
                <p>The Vice Premier wondered if the Chinese Communists’ purpose was to keep the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> busy on more than one front at a time by
                    keeping up the pressures on Taiwan, South Korea and Vietnam. Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> thought that this might be true.
                    There was something odd, he said, about a situation where the greatest country
                    in the world had to worry about what a whole lot of fifth rate countries were
                    doing to us. It would be unwise, though, for the Communists to hit us again.
                    This President had a great advantage over his predecessors in that there were 13
                    million votes on the right which he had not yet tapped, and it would be
                    dangerous to push us too hard. We engaged in a lot of tactics because we didn’t
                    believe in taking part in needless domestic battles which might involve our
                    political capital, but we would spend this capital when necessary. This
                    President didn’t get where he is today by yielding. There were many members of
                    the bureaucracy who didn’t realize this point.</p>
                <p>The Vice Premier said that he appreciated the fact that Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> was very busy, and would not take up
                    any more of his time. He simply wanted to make one last remark—people often
                    tended to apply normal standards in assessing <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao
                        Tse-tung</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName>’s thoughts
                    and actions. This was a mistake. <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao</persName> was
                    not a normal man, and his reflexes didn’t operate in ways in which they might be
                    expected to operate. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> agreed
                    that it would be a mistake to analyze other countries on the basis of our
                    standards.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
