<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>124. Telegram 202479 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                    Portugal</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve15p2Ed2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-10-12T10:09:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-10-12T10:09:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-10-12T10:09:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-10-12T10:09:00-05:00" n="124"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                <head>124. Telegram 202479 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                        Portugal<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d124fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: The Department instructed the Embassy to
                                inform Portuguese officials of the U.S. desire to use the Lajes Base
                                as a refueling stop for defense matériel-laden aircraft on the way
                                to Israel.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy Files, 1973, [no film number]. Secret; Flash; Exdis; Eyes
                                Only. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PT_1">Pickering</persName>;
                                cleared by <persName corresp="#p_SW_4">Stabler</persName>, <persName
                                    corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName> (in substance), Atherton,
                                and <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> (informed); and approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PT_1">Pickering</persName>. In telegram
                                3779 from Lisbon, October 13, the Embassy reported <persName
                                    corresp="#p_PRE_1">Patricio</persName>’s suggestion that
                                Portuguese compliance with the U.S. request would depend on U.S.
                                willingness to “provide <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> with
                                surface-to-air missiles for use against expected air threat in
                                Portuguese Guinea,” as well as “provide <gloss target="#t_GOP_1"
                                    >GOP</gloss> with general political support, treat <gloss
                                    target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> in a non-discriminatory manner.”
                                (Ibid., Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1"
                                    >NSC</gloss> Files, Box 701, Country Files, Europe, Portugal,
                                Vol. II (1972–1974) (1 of 2))</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-10-12T15:09:00+00:00">October 12, 1973,
                        1509Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Subject: Lajes Flights. Eyes Only for Chargé.</p>
                <p>1. You should seek an immediate appointment with the Foreign Minister, or if he
                    is not available with a senior official who has his trust and confidence.</p>
                <p>2. You should inform the Foreign Minister that you have been asked to see him to
                    explain that over the next several weeks we will wish to use the Lajes Base for
                    the flight of chartered civilian aircraft to Israel. The aircraft are chartered
                    by the United States Defense Department. The flights will be carrying urgently
                    needed military assistance equipment to Israel. We will average 10 to 20 flights
                    a day. They will stop in Lajes for crew change and refueling. They will touch
                    down nowhere else on their way to or from Israel. We will want to begin flights
                    tonight.</p>
                <p>3. We believe the Portuguese Government should be frankly informed of our
                    intentions. We would hope that at the bare minimum they would receive this
                    information without further comment as to the use of the base. We wish of course
                    to avoid their refusing to permit us to use this base.</p>
                <p>4. You may tell the Foreign Minister that we consider this a very important part
                    of our efforts to maintain the balance in the Middle East and to seek a
                    negotiated solution which will bring a durable peace to the region. We will not
                    forget Portuguese help and cooperation in this effort.</p>
                <p>5. You should inform the Portuguese that this activity is being carried on
                    against the backdrop of a large Soviet aerial resupply effort in Egypt, Syria
                    and Iraq which has been going on for the last several days.</p>
                <p>6. We hope and trust the Portuguese will respect our confidence in this matter.
                    We intend no publicity. We of course cannot guarantee that <pb facs="0487"
                        n="445" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_445"/> over time the flights will escape
                    public notice. If they come to public notice we intend to say only that our
                    ongoing supply relationship to Israel is of course well known; we neither
                    confirm nor deny specific information relating to that relationship.</p>
                <p>7. We are also calling in Portuguese Ambassador today to inform him of your
                    approach to <persName corresp="#p_PRE_1">Patricio</persName> and to request his
                    support for our démarche.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_KH_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
