<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>202. Key Judgments of National Intelligence Analytical Memorandum
                    27.1–1–75</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve15p2Ed2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d202</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">202</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-05-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recdZke2uFUGdGg1d" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-05-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="202"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d202">
                <head>202. Key Judgments of National Intelligence Analytical Memorandum
                        27.1–1–75<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d202fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: The memorandum analyzed problems of the
                                Spanish succession.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, History Staff
                                Files. Secret. On March 28, <persName corresp="#p_RN_1"
                                    >Rockefeller</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_FG_1"
                                    >Ford</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KH_1"
                                    >Kissinger</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_SB_1"
                                    >Scowcroft</persName>: “I met with the Acting Foreign Minister
                                of Spain. He is worried that the Communists are infiltrating all
                                over the world. They are worried about their own transition. In the
                                old days we would be planning how to have <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                                    >CIA</gloss> help this transition.” <persName corresp="#p_FG_1"
                                    >Ford</persName> asked, “Is the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                                    >CIA</gloss> or 40 Committee doing nothing on Spain?” <persName
                                    corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName> replied, “In your speech,
                                you should say the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> arrangements
                                with Congress must be changed. So long as you must report to 60
                                Congressmen, we can do nothing. We don’t need money right now—we
                                need planning. I agree with Nelson—the Communists are on the march.”
                                After <persName corresp="#p_RN_1">Rockefeller</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName> discussed Latin
                                America and various forms of U.S. assistance, <persName
                                    corresp="#p_FG_1">Ford</persName> said, “I think we should do
                                whatever we need to in Spain.” (Memorandum of conversation, March
                                28; Ford Library, National Security Adviser, Memoranda of
                                Conversation, Box 10)</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1975-05-15">May 15, 1975</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">SPAIN: PROBLEMS OF THE SUCCESSION</p>
                <p rend="center">Key Judgments</p>
                <p>1. The approaching end of the <persName corresp="#p_FGF_1">Franco</persName> era
                    carries many uncertainties for Spain—both as to short-term succession and
                    longer-term lines of development. The essential political dilemma is that the
                    regime must change in order to survive but any real change carries threats to
                    its existence.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">As for the short term</hi>, our best estimate is:</p>
                <p>—The odds are against a radical upheaval in Spanish political life during the
                    twilight and succession periods.</p>
                <p>—The most likely course is for a more or less controlled opening up of politics
                    to accommodate the more moderate political groups previously suppressed.</p>
                <p>—Chances are better than even that <persName corresp="#p_JCI_1">Juan
                        Carlos</persName> and Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_ANC_1"
                        >Arias</persName> (or someone like him), aided by common fears of the
                    alternatives, including civil turmoil, can keep a fairly broad base of support
                    while deterring all-out bids for control by any one faction.</p>
                <p>—Chances of such a modus vivendi are greater if <persName corresp="#p_FGF_1"
                        >Franco</persName> departs soon. The Spaniards need time for building
                    institutions and evolving new practices. The present period, with <persName
                        corresp="#p_FGF_1">Franco</persName> hanging on, is not conducive to more
                    than tentative efforts in this respect.</p>
                <p>3. This estimate relies heavily on the deterrent role of the Spanish military,
                    which appears united and disposed to accept political change and has generally
                    wanted to stay out of politics, but would be disposed to intervene if a serious
                    threat to law and order developed or if a radical left-wing regime seemed about
                    to come to power.</p>
                <pb facs="0686" n="644" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_644"/>
                <p>4. This estimate also relies heavily on a non-alarmist short-term economic
                    forecast, i.e., that the rapid growth of the past decade is not in the cards,
                    but the economy will stay healthy enough to avoid a major increase in labor
                    unrest. Failure in this area could alter the odds significantly, and the
                    magnitude of Spanish economic difficulties should not be minimized. Moreover,
                    the decisions are not entirely in Spanish hands but also involve Europe’s
                    economic course.</p>
                <p>5. Even in the short term, a radical polarization of Spanish politics, such as
                    has happened in Portugal, cannot entirely be ruled out. Among the possible
                    contingencies:</p>
                <p>—A late bid for power by <persName corresp="#p_FGF_1">Franco</persName>’s family
                    or the conservative coterie around him. This would challenge the left and the
                    moderates, whom the government might be unable to repress fully.</p>
                <p>—A bid for power by the more radical left with support from elements of organized
                    labor. Such a bid would invite vigorous response from the right and some of the
                    center, and the military.</p>
                <p>—In a direct contest in the short term, the odds would favor the right/military
                    side over the less organized left.</p>
                <p>6. Spain has significantly greater political and economic strengths than Portugal
                    and Spanish leaders know this. Nevertheless, the turbulent developments there
                    have heightened tensions in Spain: conservatives point to Portugal as an object
                    lesson in the dangers of lifting the lid through liberalization; reformers argue
                    that Portugal demonstrates the dangers of not liberalizing early enough.
                    Whatever the merits of these arguments, the effect of Portuguese developments
                    has been to harden attitudes on left and right and probably to compress the time
                    Spain has to resolve its problems.</p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Spain’s longer-term outlook</hi> is necessarily more
                    problematical, but essentially involves the same dilemma—whether even a
                    broadened establishment can, over time, gain adequately wide support without
                    letting things get out of control. Opening up political life will easily,
                    perhaps inevitably, give rise to escalating political demands stemming from
                    labor-management differences, conflicts between different classes and age
                    groups, and dissident regional loyalties. Resultant tensions will lead some in
                    authority to advocate increased or recurrent repression, but it is questionable
                    whether the government would have the will or capacity to carry it out.</p>
                <p>—Economic conditions will play a major, not necessarily controlling, part in
                    intensifying or ameliorating political strains.</p>
                <p>—The armed forces will continue to be of central importance both as a deterrent
                    against overt challenges from extremists and as arbiter or ultimate resort if
                    turmoil does develop.</p>
                <p>—The attitudes and policies of Western Europe and the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> will be a factor in influencing Spain’s political orientation
                    over the long haul.</p>
                <pb facs="0687" n="645" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_645"/>
                <p>—Over the longer term, assuming increasing liberalization, there would be a
                    growth of leftist and moderate strength. This would lead to increased turbulence
                    in the Spanish political process, but the odds appear against the assumption of
                    full power by either the extreme left or right.</p>
                <p>8. Meanwhile, certain themes of Spanish foreign policy will continue—certainly in
                    the short run, probably in the longer term as well. These include:</p>
                <p>—Cautious efforts to develop closer relations with Western Europe, limited by
                    fears of rebuff and some skepticism over where Europe is headed. The more
                    liberal Spain becomes, the more a push-pull dynamic will bring it closer to
                    Europe, but it has a long way to go in Europe’s eyes and there are limits on how
                    high a price Spain will pay.</p>
                <p>—A wary concern about trends in Portugal compounded of intense concern over left
                    radicalism there and a strong disinclination to interfere. Should Portugal leave
                    the Western camp, Spain would look to its defenses and seek to strengthen its
                    ties with Europe, but would not openly intervene in Portugal.</p>
                <p>—Policy toward the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> will depend on a number of
                    variables. In general, the more isolated Spain remains in Europe, the more it
                    will want to emphasize a special relationship with the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>. A perceived threat from Portugal would have similar effects. As
                    a practical matter, Spain has no alternative but to look to the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> for most of its armament needs.</p>
                <p>—Nevertheless, Spanish reservations about the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    tie persist. Many Spaniards view <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> base rights
                    in Spain as more important to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> than Spain,
                    and some see them as an embarrassing symbol of <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> support for <persName corresp="#p_FGF_1">Franco</persName>.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is the remainder of the 14-page memorandum.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
