<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-06-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="347" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d347">
                        <head>347. Briefing Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of
                            State-Designate for Economic and Business Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_ET_1">Enders</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d347fn1"><p><seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_ET_1">Enders</persName> discussed Italy’s
                                        financial difficulties.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Records of
                                        the Office of the <gloss target="#t_Coun_1">Counselor</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Helmut
                                            C. Sonnenfeldt</persName>, 1955–1977, Entry 5339, Box 5,
                                        Germany 1974. Confidential; Exdis. Concurred in by <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_ET_1">Enders</persName> did not initial the
                                        memorandum. Under cover of a June 7 memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName> forwarded to
                                            <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName> a
                                        letter in which <persName corresp="#p_SH_1">Schmidt</persName> urged the need to mobilize <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> gold reserves and for
                                            <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName> “to
                                        weigh in with <persName corresp="#p_SW_3">Simon</persName>
                                        on the political necessity of the ‘gold solution.’” (Ibid.)
                                        On June 11, <gloss target="#t_G10_1">G–10</gloss> Finance
                                        Ministers and central bankers meeting in Washington agreed
                                        that a country could borrow against its gold reserves valued
                                        at a price determined by itself and the lending country,
                                        that is, above the official price of gold, which remained
                                        $42.22 per ounce. See <ref target="frus1969-76v31#d69"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976,
                                            vol. XXXI, Foreign Economic Policy, 1973–1976, Document
                                            69</ref>.</seg></p></note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-06-08">June 8, 1974</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Italy’s Financial Difficulties; Gold;
                                Eurodollar Shakiness</hi></p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">1.</hi> Italy’s Financial
                            Difficulties</p>
                        <p>Italy’s balance-of-payment deficit is running at an annual rate of $10
                            billion. Having borrowed heavily for more than a year from the
                            Eurodollar market, Italy’s credit is rapidly worsening. Unless a package
                                <pb facs="1104" n="1062" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1062"/> of
                            internal and external stabilization measures can be put together
                            shortly, there is a risk of a financial collapse.</p>
                        <p>The payments deficit stems from uncontrolled deficit financing and
                            exorbitant domestic wage increases; it is aggravated by high energy
                            prices; the decay of confidence in Italy’s economic and political future
                            is playing an increasing role. Financial Minister <persName corresp="#p_CE_1">Colombo</persName> is in Washington June 10 for a
                            round of talks with <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and foreign
                            finance ministers and bankers. <persName corresp="#p_SW_3">Simon</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BA_1">Burns</persName> and
                            I have a working dinner with him Monday night.</p>
                        <p>To succeed, a stabilization package must include not only large scale new
                            credit, but some further devaluation, and above all action to increase
                            revenues and reduce the budget deficit.</p>
                        <p>So far the Europeans have taken little lead to organize assistance for
                            the Italians; they must be encouraged to do so now. Available sources of
                            finance are: the new <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> oil facility
                            to be established at the C–20 meeting (perhaps $900 million), a major
                            medium term bilateral loan from Germany (perhaps a billion dollars), new
                            borrowings on the Eurodollar market with <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> guarantees ($2 to $3 billion), additional help from the
                            Belgians, Dutch, Swiss drawings on existing $3 billion Federal Reserve
                            swap rolled over so as to constitute medium term assistance. If
                            necessary, Italy could under our new gold proposal use its gold as
                            collateral for new bilateral loans at prices somewhere between the
                            official return and the present market.</p>
                        <p>Action by Italy this week to devalue the “green lira” (accounting
                            currency used for intra-<gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> agricultural
                            trade) discriminates against us and will have to be offset as we
                            participate in a rescue operation.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">2.</hi> Gold</p>
                        <p>Our new position on gold was put to the Germans, French, and Dutch
                            (latter as the conduit to the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>) on
                            June 4 at Under Secretary level.</p>
                        <p>On June 6, the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> finance ministers met,
                            noted <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> position is evolving, and
                            decided not to take up gold formally at the June 12–13 C–20 meeting in
                            Washington.</p>
                        <p>Our position envisages gold collateral loans at market-related prices
                            which could be used to provide immediate relief for Italy. We thus
                            cannot be accused of being in a position of obstructing the solution to
                            the Italian problem.</p>
                        <p>France is not sending a Minister to the C–20 meeting (there is a conflict
                            with the first French Government Cabinet meeting on combating
                            inflation). <persName corresp="#p_SW_3">Simon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BA_1">Burns</persName> will discuss our gold proposal
                            with the Germans and British, and possibly in a larger group if reaction
                            is favorable.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">3.</hi> Worries over the
                            Eurodollar Market</p>
                        <p>Rumors about the insolvency of large <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                            and foreign banks operating in the Eurodollar market continue to be
                            common.</p>
                        <pb facs="1105" n="1063" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1063"/>
                        <p> The problem is this: The great bulk of new Arab money continues to be
                            deposited at site or very short term (a few days). The deposits are in
                            very large amounts, and are volatile. As is customary in the Eurodollar
                            market, these funds are relent at terms running up to five to ten
                            years.</p>
                        <p>In normal times the fairly predictable pattern of Eurodollar deposits,
                            and the banks’ own capital, enable them to act as financial
                            intermediaries, borrowing very short and lending medium to long. But
                            bank capital is not great (maybe 8% of deposits for the best American
                            banks, but 2% for some of the European banks active in the Eurodollar
                            market, and as little as 1% for the Japanese banks) and the volatility
                            of the new Arab oil deposits is posing an increasing strain.</p>
                        <p>The fact that there is no government lender of last resort for the
                            Eurodollar market, as there is in the Federal Reserve system, aggravates
                            the problem.</p>
                        <p>Adjustments needed are:</p>
                        <quote><p>—Eurobankers must discourage short term high turnover Arab
                                deposits by offering a lower interest rate (this is already
                                happening on a wide scale);</p>
                            <p>—Eurobankers must return to more conservative bank practices, in
                                particular increasing the ratio of capital to deposits (a concerted
                                effort by <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>, European, and Japanese
                                central banks is in order here);</p>
                            <p>—Central bankers must make clear that they will stand behind the
                                major <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>, European and Japanese
                                banks that operate in the Eurodollar market, provided these
                                institutions also make clear that they stand behind their Eurodollar
                                operations and affiliates (a larger effort among central bankers is
                                required here).</p></quote>
                        <p>As always in the banking area informal talks may be superior to formal
                            meetings. <persName corresp="#p_BA_1">Burns</persName> is the key, and
                            we are trying to make sure of using the C–20 meeting to the fullest for
                            the purposes outlined above.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>