<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-05-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-05-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="369" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                        <head>369. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d369fn1"><p><seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName> discussed the Italian
                                        political and economic situation.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                        Foreign Policy Files, P820117–2454. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Approved by Collums
                                        in S on July 12. The meeting took place at the SAS Hotel.
                                            <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName> was in
                                        Oslo from May 20 to 22 to attend a <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> ministerial meeting. In Backchannel
                                        Message 109 to <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName>, May 6, Volpe discussed the
                                        effects of the Church subcommittee investigations into the
                                        Lockheed affair on the Italian political scene. (Ibid.,
                                        Records of the Office of the <gloss target="#t_Coun_1">Counselor</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Helmut
                                            C. Sonnenfeldt</persName>, 1955–1977, Entry 5339, Box 7,
                                        Southern Europe 1976)</seg></p></note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Oslo</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-05-20">May 20, 1976</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss></hi></head>
                                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                                    <item><gloss target="#t_Coun_1">Counselor</gloss>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Helmut
                                        Sonnenfeldt</persName></item>
                                    <item>Asst. Secretary for European Affairs <persName corresp="#p_HA_2">Arthur A. Hartman</persName></item>
                                    <item>H. Allen Holmes (Notetaker)</item>
                                    <item>Neil Seidenman (Interpreter)</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <pb facs="1167" n="1125" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1125"/>
                            <item><list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi></head>
                                    <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Mariano
                                            Rumor</persName></item>
                                    <item>Secretary General of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                                        Raimondo Manzini</item>
                                    <item>Chef du Cabinet Rinaldo Petrignani</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> This is an interesting period in Italy.
                            I notice that the Pope is also getting interested in the elections.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi> I
                            would ask that we consider this part of our conversation confidential.
                            These are the most important elections we have ever faced.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> If you lose, I will never talk to you
                            again.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi>
                            During the last 15 days I have had the feeling that the situation is
                            getting better. The Italian people now realize that this is a decisive
                            moment. The Democratic Parties are together. We will all work from the
                            same position. The Communists have attempted to divide the government
                            forces but have been pushed back, and now the issues for the elections
                            are very clear-cut. Your messages were received in Italy, Mr. Secretary,
                            but with all respect, and admiration, we believe it would be better if
                            you would say no more . . .</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> I won’t say anything more.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi>
                            Perhaps you could say something positive . . . an expression of
                            appreciation for the majority.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> This will be done.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName>:</hi> We could do it now.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> (To <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName>) We will have to talk about that.</p>
                        <p>(To <persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>) We will definitely say
                            something positive.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi> The
                            middle classes were originally attracted to the left, but are now
                            reexamining where their true interests lie.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> Three leading Democrats in Washington
                            have been advocating the admission of the Communists to the Italian
                            government, and it would have been unfortunate if I had remained silent.
                            I will say no more along this line. I will see if the President can say
                            some positive things.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi> We
                            are seeking the commitment of all economic forces . . . trying to cover
                            all social categories with our electoral lists, including
                            representatives from the trade unions. Even Agnelli will be one of our
                            candidates for the Senate.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> If you win, we will have to cooperate
                            on some programs for progress.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi> In
                            the short time before the elections, it would help if you could give us
                            a hand in the monetary field. But this is a technical problem . . .</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> I will talk with <persName corresp="#p_BA_1">Arthur Burns</persName> about this. There are some
                            who don’t want to help before the elections.</p>
                        <pb facs="1168" n="1126" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1126"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi> But
                            the economic situation has great impact.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> The President, the Vice President and I
                            are in complete agreement. You were very effective with the Vice
                            President.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi> A
                            coalition of parties after 30 years in power has a record of
                            accomplishments and mistakes. It is important to emphasize the
                            accomplishments, the positive aspects.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> I understand. Our Government has said
                            nothing critical. Our opposition has distinguished itself by criticizing
                            the Communists all over the world, in places where they can’t do
                            anything about it, while advocating the admission of the Communists into
                            the Italian Government. We will have to find a vehicle for the President
                            to make a positive statement—perhaps a letter. I want to think about
                            this. I will be sure to say something.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi> If I
                            had spoken with you 15 days ago, I would have been much more pessimistic
                            than today.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> I am glad I didn’t speak with you
                            then.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>:</hi> The
                            trend is moving in a positive direction. However, the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and Lockheed revelations have done
                            great damage, particularly to the ruling classes.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary:</hi> It is inexcusable . . . completely out
                            of our control. Lockheed and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> are
                            explainable to sophisticated people.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion on Malta and Africa.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>