<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-07-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="376" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d376">

                        <head>376. Memorandum From the <gloss target="#t_Coun_1">Counselor</gloss>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName>) to Secretary of
                            State <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d376fn1"><p><seg type="summary">Summary:
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName>
                                        reported a series of talks between Italian leaders and
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">William
                                        Scranton</persName>.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Records of
                                        the Office of the <gloss target="#t_Coun_1">Counselor</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Helmut
                                            C. Sonnenfeldt</persName>, 1955–1977, Entry 5339, Box 5,
                                        Italy—Sensitive—July 1976. Secret; Sensitive; Eyes Only. Tab
                                        A is attached but not published. Notes on <persName corresp="#p_LHC_1">Henry Cabot Lodge</persName>’s
                                        discussions with Italian leaders in Rome indicate that he
                                        too assessed the post-election political situation and
                                        conveyed the message “that the U.S. often helps its friends,
                                        but that it is not part of our traditions to subsidize our
                                        enemies. This seemed to register.” (Ibid.) <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Andreotti</persName> announced his new
                                        Cabinet on July 29.</seg></p></note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-07-27">July 27, 1976</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName>’s Italian
                                Talks</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> saw five DC leaders,
                            including <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Andreotti</persName>, Cossiga,
                            Marcora, Orlando and Bisaglia. He also saw Cardinal Wright in the
                            Vatican, an old friend of his. These contacts are now a week old and to
                            some extent overtaken by developments since then (see Rome’s 9085 and
                            9086 NODIS) which have clouded <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Andreotti</persName>’s chances as well as increasing the CPI hold
                            on parliamentary commissions and hence on policy formulation.</p>
                        <p>At the time, <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName>’s judgment
                            was that there was a chance of a six month or so interim period with an
                                <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Andreotti</persName> government in
                            office seeking to implement a pretty solid economic program. <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> says he forcefully put forward
                            our conditions for support both in the political area and in the
                            economic sphere. He said all his contacts accepted the message,
                            expressing their strong preference for private approaches rather than
                                <persName corresp="#p_SH_1">Schmidt</persName>’s public warnings.
                                <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> said he found all
                            his contacts committed to reforming the DC but less sure of how to go
                            about it.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName>’s contacts thought that
                            once the vote of confidence for a government had been won, there would
                            be a better parliamentary situation for the program. But no one had a
                            clear idea how to get the vote of confidence. This problem is of course
                            even greater now.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> found <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Andreotti</persName> determined and impressive. He
                            said he would not include <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Moro</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_RM_1">Rumor</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CE_1">Colombo</persName> and Fanfani in his government
                            but would rely on Stammati (technocrat, now minister of finance—<hi rend="italic">not</hi> Treasury but more like <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss>), Cossiga and Forlani. These are all
                            relatively in their late forties. <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Andreotti</persName> said he would welcome it if <persName corresp="#p_SW_3">Simon</persName>’s people could establish running
                            contact with Stammati as he develops the economic program. <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> thinks this is a good idea.
                                <pb facs="1182" n="1140" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1140"/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName>’s generally favorable
                            view of <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Andreotti</persName> is tempered by
                            the recognition that to younger people in Italy and the DC he does not
                            connote change.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> found a general worry
                            about the Soviets and the CPI. The going theory is that the PCI will
                            remain “democratic” until Tito leaves the scene at which time the
                            Russians will make a major push in both Yugoslavia and Italy. (On
                            Yugoslavia, see a sensitive report <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> brought back from Belgrade, where there are
                            similar fears, TAB A).</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> found his friend Cardinal
                            Wright inexplicably complacent. The Cardinal questions that Italy can go
                            Communist nationally; he takes heart from the interest of the young in
                            the Church. <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> notes,
                            however, that Wright is not directly involved in matters of this kind in
                            the Vatican.</p>
                        <p>In sum, <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> thinks, as of a
                            week ago, that there is a chance for a DC start under <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Andreotti</persName> with a satisfactory program,
                            with a crisis coming some six months down the road, depending on the
                            attitude of the unions and the small parties, especially the <gloss target="#t_PSI_1">PSI</gloss>, which a week ago was at even looser
                            ends than now. <persName corresp="#p_SW_2">Scranton</persName> found
                            plenty of speculation about a possible popular front after the six-month
                            interim, though also some hope that with a new DC leader at that time,
                            there could be a democratic coalition. The Italians want our help, he
                            says, but understand our conditions. <hi rend="italic">This latter
                                judgment must now I think be seriously tempered by the Gelb-Ugo
                                Stille canard about the “<persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kissinger</persName> formula.”</hi> Please note Rome 9048,
                            which indicates that a “collaborator” of yours supposedly told Stille,
                                <persName corresp="#p_SH_1">Schmidt</persName> had attacked the
                            wrong target and that your “initiative” in Puerto Rico was designed to
                            give us <hi rend="italic">greater</hi> flexibility vis-à-vis DC–PCI
                            collaboration!</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>