<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State
                    Drafted by Mr. Hickerson; approved by the Secretary
                        of State.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d108</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">108</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" subject="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="guerrilla" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrillas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="108" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d108">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.20 Mission/9–748</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d108fn1">Drafted by Mr. Hickerson; approved by the Secretary
                        of State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-07">September 7,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Sir Oliver Franks, British Ambassador</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Secretary of State</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. John D. Hickerson, Director for European Affairs</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Sir Oliver Franks, the British Ambassador, called by appointment made at his
                    request at 11:20 this morning. He said that he had received a telegram
                    expressing Mr. Bevin’s concern over the possibility, in view of recent favorable
                    developments in Greece, of the withdrawal of the U.S. Military Mission in
                    Greece.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that Mr. Bevin feels that in spite of the gratifying
                    developments of recent months in Greece, there will continue to be attacks on
                    the Greek Government from within and without the country for a considerable
                    period of time. Mr. Bevin believes that the steadying influence of the U.S. and
                    British Military Missions present in the country will be essential for a
                    considerable period of time. The Ambassador said that the British Government has
                    been attacked from the Left Wing of the Labor Party about its Greek policy over
                    a considerable period of time and that it would be practically impossible for
                    the British Military Mission to continue in Greece if the U.S. Military Mission
                    were withdrawn.</p>
                <p>I told the Ambassador that with the continued military success of the Greek army
                    against the guerrillas, it is our hope that by December it will be possible to
                    begin a reduction of the Greek army looking to elimination of the necessity for
                    further U.S. military appropriations. I added that we have no intention of
                    withdrawing our Military Mission from Greece until the situation there is well
                    stabilized. I went on to say that in my opinion this will not happen any time
                    soon, certainly not in the next year.</p>
                <p>I told the Ambassador that I wanted to make a final comment off the record. This
                    was that if we find it necessary to withdraw our Military Mission from Greece, I
                    fully expect that the U.S. Government will give the British Government more
                    notice of this intention than Mr. Bevin gave me in February 1947 in regard to
                    the necessity for the British Government to discontinue its support of
                    Greece.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
