<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Governor Dwight P. Griswold
                        to the Secretary of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d14</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">14</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-01-15T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-01-15T11:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-01-15T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-15T11:00:00-05:00" n="14" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.5151/1–1548: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Governor <persName type="from">Dwight P. Griswold</persName>
                        to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-15T18:00:00+02:00">January 15, 1948—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Amag2">Amag</gloss> 96. 1. Urgently recommend to meet critical
                    situation here immediate and favorable decision by Department: First,
                    authorizing conversion into sovereigns of two million dollars Greek gold at
                    FRBNY and second, agreeing in principle to gradual repayment out of Greek
                    foreign exchange of remainder of loan and conversion into sovereigns of gold so
                    released, at such times and in such manner as Mission may recommend.<note n="1" xml:id="d14fn1">The Department of State and the Treasury Department approved
                        the recommendations in this paragraph on January 17 and suggested that the
                        Bank of Greece communicate with the Federal Reserve Bank of New York
                        regarding details of conversion and repayment (telegram <gloss target="#t_Gama1">Gama</gloss> 84, 868.51/1–1548).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sovereigns so acquired would be sold in accordance present conditions whereby
                    prior approval of Mission for each gold sale is required and every effort made
                    to limit gold sales to smallest amount possible. Drachma proceeds from gold
                    sales placed in suspense account and to be either retired from circulation or
                    used solely to help finance part of cost of larger army and additional refugee
                    aid.</p>
                <p>Prompt public announcement of decision should be made, preferably by Mission
                    because of our relation to government.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>6. As for future, we believe Greek Government now realistically undertaking to
                    implement essential military and economic measures. In their unanimous judgment
                    adequate reserve gold indispensable condition to degree of stability required
                    for successful implementation of both military and economic measures. Mission
                    endorses their judgment and regards it extremely inadvisable to gamble whole
                    success <pb facs="0050" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/> of aid program and Mission on
                    ability to control situation without gold sales.</p>
                <p>7. Embassy concurs fully and most strongly.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Griswold</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
