<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the united States Representative on the United Nations Special Committee on
                        the Balkans (
                        Kirk
                    ),Adm. Alan G. Kirk, U.S.N., whose
                        regular position was that of Ambassador to Belgium.
                    at Salonika</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d157</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">157</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-01-03T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-01-03T12:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-01-03T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-03T12:00:00-05:00" n="157" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d157">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Balkan/1–348: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the united States Representative on the United Nations Special Committee on
                        the Balkans</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>),<note n="2" xml:id="d157fn2">Adm. Alan G. Kirk, U.S.N., whose
                        regular position was that of Ambassador to Belgium.</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">at Salonika</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-03T12:00:00-05:00">January 3, 1948—noon</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2. Balcom 63. Dept considers <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> resolution
                    useful as warning and as basis possible future action. (<gloss target="#t_urtel1">Urtel</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Combal1">Combal</gloss> 50<note n="3" xml:id="d157fn3">This
                        undated communication is identified also as an unnumbered telegram from
                        Salonika, which was received in the Department on December 30, 1947. It gave
                        the text of a Brazilian resolution unanimously voted by <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss>, as follows: “The Committee is of the
                        opinion that a recognition, even de facto, of the movement describing itself
                        as the ‘provisional democratic Greek Government’, followed by direct or
                        indirect aid and assistance to this insurrectionary movement against the
                        government of a member of the United Nations in defiance of international
                        law, peace treaties and the principles of the charter, would constitute a
                        grave threat to the ‘maintenance of international peace and security’.”
                        (501.BB Balkan/12–3047)</note>)</p>
                <p>Pending further major developments most helpful role of <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> will be compilation authentic and
                    probative evidence re aid furnished Markos<note n="4" xml:id="d157fn4">Markos
                        Vafiades, President and Minister of War in the “First Provisional Democratic
                        Government of Free Greece”.</note> by foreign sources. Hope committee will
                    make every effort this regard even before arrival full observer personnel and
                    equipment. Personnel and eqpt will be available soon if Army permits <gloss target="#t_USAGG1">USAGG</gloss> to transfer to <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> matériel already in Greece. You will be advised shortly
                    decision concerning eqpt.</p>
                <p>If Albania, Bulgaria or Yugoslavia should recognize Markos junta (Dept seeks to
                    avoid use of word Government) as insurgents, belligerents or government, you
                    should propose or support resolution stating this action directly contrary to
                    General Assembly resolution.<note n="5" xml:id="d157fn5">October 21, 1947; for
                        information on the resolution, numbered 109 (II), see editorial note, <ref target="frus1947v05#pg_888">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1947, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 888</ref>.</note> If, in addition to
                    recognition, there is evidence of continuing or increased aid to junta, any
                        <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> finding that such aid constitutes
                    aggression or other Charter violation must involve not only question of fact on
                    basis evidence collected but also careful consideration consequences under
                    Charter. Therefore, in order insure tactical freedom action within UN and to
                    correlate US position in <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> with US
                    policy <pb facs="0243" n="223" xml:id="pg_223"/> as ultimately developed Dept
                    would like opportunity to study text any resolution concerning recognition plus
                    assistance before final adoption by <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss>.</p>
                <p>If <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> obtains clear evidence that aid by
                    Alb, Bulg or Yugo is increasing, but not accompanied by recognition, you should
                    propose that full report of facts be made at once to Syg of UN with request he
                    transmit it to member states. In this case Dept would prefer committee refrain
                    from specific recommendations thus permitting flexibility of action to be
                    followed.</p>
                <p>Sent Salonika 2 as Balcom 63; rptd to Athens 5, London 15, Belgrade 4, Sofia
                    3.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
