<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum Prepared in the Department of State
                    Sent to Francis O. Wilcox, Chief of Staff of the
                        Senate Foreign Relations Committee, by the Counselor (Bohlen) on February
                        9.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d26</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">26</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-02-06T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="armed-forces" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241" lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="guerrilla" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla warfare</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="inflation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112" lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="invasion" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="26" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/2–948</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum Prepared in the Department of State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d26fn1">Sent to Francis O. Wilcox, Chief of Staff of the
                        Senate Foreign Relations Committee, by the Counselor (Bohlen) on February
                        9.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-06">February 6,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Statement Concerning Greek-Turkish Aid</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Since liberation Greece has been almost wholly dependent upon foreign assistance
                    to meet her import requirements for the civilian economy and to equip the armed
                    forces needed to cope with guerrilla <pb facs="0064" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/>
                    warfare. With the termination last year of <gloss target="#t_UNRRA1">UNRRA</gloss> aid and assistance from Great Britain, Greece faced a
                    critical situation which threatened collapse. It is certain that had it not been
                    for the timely enactment by Congress of the American Aid Program there would
                    have been a breakdown in the Greek economy and a collapse of the resistance by
                    the Greek Army to the guerrilla bands, which would have resulted in domination
                    of Greece by the Communists.</p>
                <p>Even with American aid, however, the situation in Greece today remains critical.
                    In planning our program of assistance it was hoped that the United Nations would
                    be successful in cutting off foreign assistance to those forces in Greece
                    attempting to overthrow the government by violence; however, such foreign
                    assistance to the Greek guerrillas has, in spite of the United Nations’ efforts,
                    continued and has made it possible for their forces to be substantially
                    increased. In consequence of this intensified military activity, substantial
                    sums originally earmarked for reconstruction and development programs have
                    necessarily been diverted to military purposes. Continued insecurity has
                    retarded Greek production and trade, and has led to a serious condition of
                    inflation, aggravated by large internal military expenditures. These acute
                    difficulties have yet to be overcome, but it is clear that without the American
                    program conditions in Greece would be much worse than they are.</p>
                <p>Thus it can be said that while the economic recovery of Greece has been delayed,
                    the aid program has been successful in the maintenance of Greece as a free
                    nation and her continued alignment with the Western democracies. With American
                    assistance the size and strength of the Greek armed forces have been
                    substantially augmented, and they are now equipped to cope successfully with the
                    guerrilla problem provided, of course, that foreign aid to the guerrillas is not
                    substantially increased. In the meantime reconstruction projects and economic
                    programs most effective under the circumstances, including counter-inflationary
                    reforms, are being actively prosecuted with the assistance of the American
                    Mission and a basis for further recovery has been laid which can become
                    operative once the guerrilla menace has been eliminated.</p>
                <p>While the Turkish economy is better off than that of Greece, the cost of
                    maintaining a military establishment of adequate size to assure Turkish
                    security, and of modernizing the forces to improve their combat effectiveness,
                    is greater than could be borne without foreign help. Turkey is being subjected
                    to considerable pressures by the USSR and American support is deemed essential
                    to bolster the confidence of the people and to discourage foreign
                    aggression.</p>
                <pb facs="0065" n="45" xml:id="pg_45"/>
                <p>In Turkey the determination to resist foreign aggression is directly in
                    proportion to the ability the Turks feel they have to resist. While the Turks
                    would fight desperately to maintain their independence and integrity they are
                    aware that their armed forces, without assistance, are not sufficiently strong
                    to defend Turkey for an appreciable time against an all-out invasion. Our
                    program, which has been concrete evidence of the United States’ determination to
                    assist Turkey in her efforts to resist Russian pressures, has been highly
                    successful in bolstering the morale of the Turks, and appreciable progress will
                    have been made by the time the present program is completed in equipping the
                    Turkish army so that it will be better prepared to meet any eventuality. Our
                    major success, therefore, is that the determination of Turkey to resist
                    communist pressures is substantially greater than would have been possible
                    without American aid.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
