<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="289" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d289">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">871.00/10–848: Airgram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Legation in
                                    Switzerland</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-21">October 21,
                                1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_A1">A–268</gloss>. The continuing quarrels of the
                            Rumanian political exiles found new pretexts in the Gafencu–Coste
                            memorandum (<gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 1326, <pb facs="0452" n="432" xml:id="pg_432"/> Oct 8).<note n="1" xml:id="d289fn1">The telegram under reference is not printed. In
                                late July 1948, General Radescu issued membership invitations to
                                sixteen Romanian exile leaders to join a proposed Romanian National
                                Committee. Prior to the issuance of the invitation, Radescu was
                                informed that although the Department of State did not wish to
                                advise him as to whether or not such a Romanian National Committee
                                should be formed, his proposal as earlier outlined to the Department
                                was agreeable. Radescu’s proposal encountered various objections
                                from other Romanian exiles, and the Committee was not convened. On
                                September 3, 1948, former Romanian Foreign Minister Grigore Gafencu
                                and former Romanian Chargé in Washington Brutus Coste called on Mr.
                                Nickels of the Division of Southern European Affairs and had a long
                                discussion regarding the Department’s views with respect to the
                                Romanian exile movement. Gafencu and Coste prepared a transcript of
                                the conversation which was submitted in draft to the Department. A
                                copy of that transcript is included in file 871.00/10–1448.</note>
                            The rancorous quibbling appears to be essentially on a plane of
                            personalities rationalized as principles.</p>
                        <p>In the circumstances, on October 19 the Department informally
                            communicated to General Radescu through his secretary the following:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Some erroneous impressions of the Department’s position with
                                    respect to the Rumanian political exiles seem to exist. We do
                                    not suggest that the Department’s views in this regard have been
                                    consciously misinterpreted by persons to whom they have been
                                    expressed.</p>
                                <p>“As has been emphasized previously to all concerned, the US
                                    Government is not sponsoring any individual Rumanian exiles for
                                    membership in a proposed Rumanian committee or otherwise.</p>
                                <p>“It is felt that the Department’s views concerning the activities
                                    of the Rumanian exiles in the US and the proposed formation by
                                    them of a cooperative enterprise on behalf of Rumania,
                                    consistent with US objectives for a free and democratic world,
                                    have been expressed with sufficient clarity to all who are
                                    interested and it is our impression that these views have been
                                    understood by General Radescu.</p>
                                <p>“The continuance of the discord among the Rumanian exiles with
                                    particular reference to the proposed cooperative undertaking is
                                    regarded by the Department as prejudicial to the objectives
                                    which it would be designed to serve. If within the near future
                                    these regrettable dissensions are not composed in the interest
                                    of a constructive contribution to the principal objectives, the
                                    Department may be obliged to reassess its position regarding the
                                    feasibility and utility of such an enterprise.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>In your discretion, you may inform Michael or his Aide of the foregoing.
                            Substantially the same views have been conveyed to Messrs.
                            Niculescu-Buzesti, Cretzianu and Davila in the course of recent
                            conversations at the Department.</p>
                        <p>We have learned by informal transmission from General Radescu that he
                            contemplates making within the near future a new effort, suggesting
                            organization of a comprehensive “union” of such exiles as are prepared
                            to participate, and that he has Michael’s sanction for making such an
                            effort, the latter having reserved his position for the time being on
                            the formation of a Rumanian national committee.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>