<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Embassy in the United
                            Kingdom to the British Foreign Office
                    
                    This aide-mémoire, a copy of
                        which was transmitted to the Department as an enclosure to despatch 1638,
                        July 26, 1948, from London, not printed, was submitted to the British
                        Foreign Office in connection with discussions on July 17 and 21, 1948
                        between American and British officials on civil aviation policy towards the
                        Soviet Union and the East European satellites. Regarding those discussions,
                        see telegram 3302, July 21, from London, infra.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d308</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">308</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-07-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-07-19T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="discrimination" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376" lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recgO0zWiwmY4SEHo" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="airspace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002995" lcsh-match="bad_close">Airspace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005823" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Electronic equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec332ed97b3bcc404" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="middle-east-and-north-african-relations" subject="near-and-middle-east">Near and Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council" subject="national-security-council">National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-07-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-07-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="308" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d308">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.4027/7–2648</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States Embassy in the United
                            Kingdom</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">British Foreign Office</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d308fn1">This <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, a copy of
                        which was transmitted to the Department as an enclosure to despatch 1638,
                        July 26, 1948, from London, not printed, was submitted to the British
                        Foreign Office in connection with discussions on July 17 and 21, 1948
                        between American and British officials on civil aviation policy towards the
                        Soviet Union and the East European satellites. Regarding those discussions,
                        see telegram 3302, July 21, from London, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item> Ever since the Chicago Conference in International Civil Aviation at the
                        end of 1944,<note n="2" xml:id="d308fn2">For documentation on the
                            international civil aviation conference held in Chicago, November
                            1–December 7, 1944, see <ref target="frus1944v02#pg_355">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 355</ref> ff.</note> and until a
                        few months ago, the United States Government actively endeavored to induce
                        the U.S.S.R. to participate on a basis of full equality and reciprocity in
                        the orderly development of international civil aviation. A like endeavor was
                        made, without exception or discrimination, in regard to the various
                        countries which one after the other became satellites of the U.S.S.R.
                        (Poland, Yugoslavia, Rumania, Hungary). Throughout those years the products
                        of American aircraft and related industries and aviation material of all
                        kinds from Army surplus were available to the U.S.S.R. and her
                        satellites.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>This attitude was in conformity with the objective—shared by the United
                        Kingdom Government—of promoting worldwide air transport to serve as an
                        effective vehicle of trade and commerce among peace loving nations in a
                        peaceful world.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item> In the fall of 1947, it became evident that our active and repeated
                        endeavors of more than two years to obtain a reciprocal air transport
                        agreement with the U.S.S.R. were unsuccessful; that the U.S.S.R. is
                        unwilling to join I.C.A.O.; that through the control it exercises in the
                        satellite countries, the U.S.S.R. is preventing the satellite governments
                        from entering into operationally reciprocal air transport agreements with
                        countries outside the Soviet orbit.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>It further became evident that while the U.S.S.R. persevered in excluding
                        civil aircraft of Western nations from Soviet-controlled areas, it sought
                        purely unilateral penetration beyond the iron air curtain erected by its
                        exclusionary measures. This has been substantially accomplished by
                        non-reciprocal link arrangements or by Soviet-controlled and operated
                        satellite airlines which are in fact Soviet airlines.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>Through this ingenious policy, the U.S.S.R. has effectively accomplished
                        their political and military objective or wide penetration of non-Soviet
                        territories at the negligible cost of granting access only to the periphery
                        of the Soviet-controlled area.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In the fall of 1947, after more than two years of negative results, <pb facs="0478" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/> the United States Government in
                        consultation with the United Kingdom Government decided to follow a new,
                        though admittedly an interim, policy. In essence this policy reflected our
                        reluctance to draw the final conclusion that the U.S.S.R. had irrevocably
                        committed itself to a policy of non-cooperation, even of hostility, and was
                        definitely determined to bar access by civil aircraft of her former Allies
                        and of other presumably friendly nations to Soviet-controlled airspace.
                        Under this interim policy the United States refrains from taking the
                        initiative toward the conclusion of air transport agreements with the
                        U.S.S.R. or its satellites, but is prepared to consider on its merits and in
                        light of all relevant factors proposals made by any curtain country.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The interim policy did not contemplate any change in regard to the sale of
                        aircraft and aviation equipment to the U.S.S.R. and its satellites. However,
                        the continued exclusionary policy of the U.S.S.R. and persistent Soviet
                        attempts aiming at unilateral penetration of the non-Soviet world by their
                        aircraft, caused the United States increasing concern over the broader
                        implications of freely supplying such equipment to the curtain countries.
                        This concern was expressed in form of advice to manufacturers and
                        distributors of such equipment as a result of which the flow thereof to
                        curtain countries began to slow down at the beginning of this year. The
                        export license requirements for certain categories of war
                        potentials—including aircraft, components and electronic equipment—foreseen
                        in Presidential Proclamation No. 2776, effective April 15, 1948,<note n="3" xml:id="d308fn3">See editorial note, <ref target="#pg_528">p.
                            528</ref>.</note> although imposed for different reasons (i.e. the
                        Palestine situation), enabled the United States Government to exercise a
                        more direct and effective control and practically to stop the direct sale
                        and export of such equipment to the curtain countries.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item> Penetration by the U.S.S.R. and by the satellites of the non-Soviet
                        world—particularly Western Europe, the Near and Middle East—with their air
                        services on a unilateral and non-reciprocal basis, when viewed in the light
                        of their persistent attempts at further expansion, have caused increasing
                        concern to the United States Government. Our concern, of course, arises not
                        from economic considerations but from the obvious political and security
                        implications of this situation.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>The opinion of the United States Government that the primary objectives of
                        Soviet air transport operations are strategic and political rather than
                        commercial is strongly supported by the uneconomic management and operation
                        of the Soviet-controlled satellite airlines. The sudden burst of activity
                        following the Prague coup, seeking to expand operations of the Czech airline
                            <gloss target="#t_CSA1">CSA</gloss> (now completely under Communist
                        control) to the critical Near and Middle East region is <pb facs="0479" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"/> further indication of the correctness of this
                        estimate of the true Soviet aim in this regard. The coup in Czechoslovakia
                        in February, 1948, completely changed the picture. It gave the U.S.S.R. for
                        the first time a relatively competent and experienced airline with routes,
                        actual and potential, reaching into all parts of the non-Soviet world and
                        capable of serving, under Soviet controls, as a convenient instrumentality
                        of penetration into all corners of the globe.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The abrupt and disingenuous termination on April 30, 1948, by the
                        Hungarian puppet government of negotiations which it had initiated with the
                        United States, for an air transport agreement has finally convinced the
                        United States Government that it is necessary to re-examine with the United
                        Kingdom the civil aviation policy heretofore applied to the U.S.S.R. and the
                        satellites. A careful and searching analysis of our past course of action,
                        of the premises upon which our policy was based, and the wholly negative
                        results, have convinced the United States Government that unless the United
                        States, the United Kingdom and other countries outside the Soviet orbit
                        adopt a more restrictive policy, comparable to that actually followed by the
                        U.S.S.R., we shall fail in our major objective of lifting the iron curtain
                        and shall be giving away for virtually nothing, and, in the present
                        circumstances, to the detriment of our security, the operating privileges
                        which constitute our sole leverage and bargaining power.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item> As a result of this examination of the problem, the United States
                        Government has formulated certain views as to the line of action which we
                        are prepared to follow if the United Kingdom agrees and is prepared to join
                        in this course.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>The course of action (summarized hereafter) which the United States now
                        proposes to the United Kingdom Government has been concurred in by the
                        United States Occupation Authorities in Germany and Austria, has been
                        approved by the National Security Council of the United States upon
                        recommendation of the Department of State, and has the express approval of
                        the President of the United States. <list>
                            <label>(I)</label>
                            <item> It is proposed that: The United Kingdom and the United States,
                                together with countries of Western Europe and the Near and Middle
                                East outside the Soviet orbit would seek to prohibit civil air
                                operations (scheduled, non-scheduled and charter) by airlines of the
                                U.S.S.R. and her satellites to and through non-curtain territory
                                until the U.S.S.R. grants, on a truly reciprocal basis, transit and
                                commercial landing rights in U.S.S.R. territory proper to civil air
                                carriers of the United Kingdom and the United States and such other
                                countries outside the Soviet orbit which adopt this line of action
                                and desire such rights.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>The proposed measure of containment is intended to apply to <hi rend="italic">civil</hi>
                                <pb facs="0480" n="460" xml:id="pg_460"/> air transport only. It is
                                not intended to prevent the exchange with the U.S.S.R. and/or the
                                satellites on a fully reciprocal basis of noncommercial, military,
                                courier, diplomatic, or other government sponsored flights. The
                                immediate objective of this proposal—the confinement of Soviet and
                                satellite aircraft to Soviet-controlled airspace—is of a political
                                and security rather than of a commercial or economic character. The
                                primacy of political and security considerations, even though
                                dealing with <hi rend="italic">civil</hi> air transport, is,
                                however, justified, first because civil aviation is a vitally
                                important element of air power (just as the merchant marine is the
                                indispensable foundation of sea power); secondly, the U.S.S.R.
                                regards civil air transport largely from the political and military
                                point of view; thirdly, the present international situation puts the
                                accent on airpower <hi rend="italic">not</hi> on civil
                                aviation.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>The ultimate civil aviation objective of the United States
                                Government remains, as before, the development of worldwide air
                                transport on the basis of factual and operational reciprocity with
                                the least possible restrictions consistent with national security.
                                It is possible that the proposed course of action may build up
                                sufficient pressure to persuade the Soviet of the advantage of a
                                more cooperative attitude, although admittedly such a change in the
                                foreseeable future appears remote.</item>
                            <label>(II)</label>
                            <item>To implement this proposed course of action: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>The United Kingdom, the United States and other countries
                                        cooperating in this course of action would refrain from
                                        concluding air agreements with the U.S.S.R. or its
                                        satellites and from exchanging or authorizing commercial
                                        flights to or through their territories until the ultimate
                                        objective defined in paragraph (I) above is in sight.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>Any of these countries which have air transport agreements
                                        with curtain countries would take such steps as are
                                        necessary and open to them to prevent the further exercise
                                        of rights under these agreements.</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>The United Kingdom, the United States and France would
                                        withdraw or suspend authorizations granted to curtain
                                        countries for commerical services involving overflight or
                                        landing in their respective occupation zones of Germany and
                                        Austria, and would refuse to grant such permits in the
                                        future.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>The sale and export to the U.S.S.R. and her satellites,
                                        directly or indirectly, of aircraft, engines, spare parts
                                        and electronic equipment used in connection with aircraft
                                        operations would be prohibited.</item>
                                    <label>e.</label>
                                    <item>The use of facilities for overhaul, refitting and
                                        maintenance to the aircraft of the U.S.S.R. and her
                                        satellites would be denied.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>(III)</label>
                            <item> The suggested course of action would apply to the U.S.S.R.,
                                Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Rumania, Bulgaria and
                                Albania. So long as the present situation as regards Finnish-Soviet
                                relations remains unchanged it is felt that Finland should be
                                considered as a special case and the measures of containment should
                                not be applied to her. However, it is believed desirable that any
                                air <pb facs="0481" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/> agreement which a
                                cooperating country may conclude with Finland should be subject to
                                cancellation on short notice; and that the sale of any kind of
                                aviation equipment to Finland should be closely scrutinized and
                                adequately protected against possible diversion to the U.S.S.R. or a
                                Soviet-controlled airline.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>We believe that the proposed course of action and the measures of
                                implementation should be put into effect by the cooperating
                                countries with as little publicity as possible. It is recognized
                                that the adoption of a course of action on so broad a front as is
                                envisaged cannot be kept secret. At the same time it is believed its
                                effectiveness would be enhanced by taking the necessary steps with
                                the minimum publicity. By refraining from announcing a policy or
                                course of action, we would avoid, or at least delay, reaction in the
                                form of hostile propaganda or retaliatory measures by the countries
                                affected. Moreover, this tactic would permit quiet and inconspicuous
                                relaxation or retraction in case this course of action is effective
                                in penetrating the iron air curtain.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>In formulating this proposal, we have taken into account the following
                        considerations: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>The effectiveness of the proposed course of action depends upon
                                the obtaining the agreement of a number of countries in Western
                                Europe, the Near and Middle East to cooperate fully in all phases of
                                implementation. To secure such agreement is admittedly difficult,
                                but it is believed that the identity of national security interests
                                is a sufficiently strong motive for agreement. It is also evident
                                that through our control of the airspace over Germany and Austria
                                and the participation of key periphery countries, this course of
                                action can be made effective even without the cooperation of all
                                countries whose participation may be desirable.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>The proposed course of action involves the risk of retaliatory
                                measures and hostile propaganda by the countries affected and,
                                possibly, though by no means necessarily, of adding to the tension
                                between the West and the U.S.S.R. On our part, we are prepared to
                                assume these risks.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>The proposed course of action if put into effect, will probably
                                not accomplish its objective immediately; neither can we expect 100
                                per cent effectiveness. However, the choice between taking the
                                initiative and using what leverage we have and on the other hand
                                doing nothing, would appear to be obvious. It is the view of the
                                United States Government that positive action should now be
                                taken.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Should the Government of the United Kingdom agree with the Government of
                        the United States upon a positive course of action, it is further proposed
                        that the two governments consult at once upon the means to be employed in
                        obtaining the widest cooperation of the other Western European, Near and
                        Middle Eastern countries.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-07-19">July 19,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
