<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="343" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d343">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">660.119/5–648</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Report by the Ad Hoc Subcommittee of the Advisory
                                Committee of the Secretary of Commerce</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d343fn1">This Report was addressed by the Chairman of the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Subcommittee to the Chairman of
                                the Advisory Committee. <p>A copy of this Report was sent to the
                                    Ambassador in the United Kingdom, Lewis W. Douglas, under cover
                                    of a letter from Edwin M. Martin, Chief of the Division of
                                    Occupied Areas Economic Affairs. Martin explained that the
                                    Report was submitted to the Secretary of Commerce on May 6 for
                                    presentation to the Cabinet on May 7. Ambassador Douglas was to
                                    use the Report in connection with his discussions in London with
                                    British, French and <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>
                                    officials of the question of reparations deliveries to the
                                    satellite nations (London Embassy Files, 1948, File—850
                                    Reparations).</p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-04">May 4, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Ad. Hoc/Doc. 31 (Final)</p>
                        <p>At your request, the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Subcommittee set up an
                            Economic Working Group to formulate recommendations with respect to the
                            various economic instruments which could be used, as required, for
                            implementing U.S. foreign policy. Control of trade is an effective
                            instrument for this purpose. In view of the urgency of clarifying export
                            control policy with respect to Eastern Europe, the Working Group has
                            concentrated its attention on this problem thus far. This report of the
                                <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Subcommittee is based on Working Group
                            studies. It will be followed by subsequent reports on other economic
                            instruments.</p>
                        <p>In the judgment of the Subcommittee, U.S. policy on trade with Eastern
                            Europe has three major objectives: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>To assist Western European countries in obtaining necessary
                                    imports from Eastern Europe.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>To prevent or delay further increase in the war potential of
                                    Eastern European economies.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>To insure an adequate flow of manganese, chrome, and to a
                                    lesser extent, the platinum group of metals, and other essential
                                    commodities, from Eastern Europe to the U.S.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0557" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/>
                        <p>It must be recognized frankly that full pursuit of the first and third
                            objectives is not compatible with the second. Yet, in the judgment of
                            the Subcommittee, it is possible to make some progress toward all three
                            goals simultaneously.</p>
                        <p>It is obvious, however, that choices must be made. Consequently, it is
                            necessary to evaluate the relative importance of the three
                            objectives.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">East-West Trade in Europe</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>During the four years of the <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>, it is
                            estimated that Western European countries will require between $5 and $6
                            billion of imports from Eastern Europe. They expect to export about the
                            same amount in terms of value to Eastern European destinations. The
                            major raw material items supplied by Eastern Europe are: grain, timber,
                            coal, and potash. They are essential for Western European recovery.
                            Insofar as this trade is choked off, the ultimate burden on the U.S.
                            would be increased, both in terms of dollars and commodity exports. This
                            added burden might require further control measures in the United
                            States, and there would be less assurance that the material requirements
                            of the <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> countries could be met.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Imports into the U.S. from the
                                U.S.S.R. and Satellites</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The U.S. needs manganese, chrome, and platinum group metals from the
                            U.S.S.R. Other imports from the Soviet bloc are important to certain
                            industries, but not to the strength of the economy as a whole. It
                            appears possible that these imports of manganese, chrome, and platinum
                            might be replaced sometime in 1949 if all suitable measures are promptly
                            taken and actively pursued. This prediction is based on favorable
                            assumptions with respect to political stability in countries where new
                            supplies are expected to be available. Several million dollars worth of
                            scarce equipment may have to be diverted from domestic and other foreign
                            programs in order to boost imports from alternative sources rapidly.</p>
                        <p>If supplies of manganese and chrome from the U.S.S.R. are cut off before
                            imports from other sources are increased by an equivalent amount,
                            maintenance of present steel output would reduce privately owned stocks
                            to a seriously low level within one year. Strenuous and unpopular
                            conservation measures may be required.</p>
                        <p>The U.S.S.R. can probably be replaced with relative ease as a source of
                            platinum and related metals, but presently available data do not
                            indicate the time and cost involved.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Strategic Value of Trade With
                                Eastern Europe</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Soviet bloc obtained goods valued at about $425 million in 1947 from
                            the U.S., less than 3% of our exports. Over two-thirds of the $150
                            million exports to the U.S.S.R. were machinery and vehicles. <pb facs="0558" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/> During the last half of the
                            year, this percentage rose to about three-fourths. Including <gloss target="#t_UNRRA1">UNRRA</gloss> shipments, between ½ and ⅔ of
                            shipments to other Eastern European countries in 1947 were foodstuffs,
                            textiles, and miscellaneous.</p>
                        <p>Several of the Eastern European countries, including the U.S.S.R.,
                            strongly desire complex equipment from the United States. In part this
                            equipment is for the purpose of initiating or expanding industrial
                            output and services in certain lines; in part it is to serve as
                            prototypes for production of similar equipment there. It is probable
                            that at the present time much of this equipment cannot be obtained
                            elsewhere in the desired qualities and quantities, if at all.</p>
                        <p>The effects of restrictions on exports to the Soviet bloc would be more
                            severe for some of the industrialized satellite countries Which have a
                            considerable volume of trade with the West—especially Czechoslovakia and
                            Poland—than for the U.S.S.R. proper, or for the less developed countries
                            whose trade is largely within the Soviet sphere (for example, Bulgaria
                            and Albania). However, the effects on the satellite countries would be
                            in general to retard their further industrialization and to restrict
                            their future contributions to Soviet war potential. As to the Soviet
                            Union proper, it is likely that certain dislocations in Soviet
                            industrialization plans would be accentuated by restrictions on trade,
                            both because of the loss of goods and the loss of new techniques and
                            know-how, for which the Soviet bloc has to look to the U.S. to a large
                            extent in certain industries. To what degree this would affect the
                            Soviet war potential is difficult to forecast.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Conclusion With Respect to Trade Between U.S.S.R. and
                                U.S.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Prior to March 1, 1948, the U.S. was exporting goods to Eastern Europe
                            which, in the aggregate, had greater strategic value to the recipients
                            than the imports received from that source had for the United States. In
                            the judgment of the Subcomittee such an imbalance should not be
                            permitted to continue.</p>
                        <p>A selective control over exports from the U.S. should be maintained in
                            order to deny the Soviet bloc certain key commodities which affect vital
                            segments of the Eastern European economy. In general such controls
                            should have as their objective the prevention of a net transfer,
                            directly or indirectly, of war potential from this country and Western
                            Europe to Eastern Europe.</p>
                        <p>The Munitions Control Board, acting through the State Department,
                            consistently refuses licenses for shipments of arms, ammunition, and
                            implements of war to the Soviet bloc. A new and expanded definition of
                            such items is included in the Presidential Proclamation of March 26,
                            1948.</p>
                        <pb facs="0559" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/>
                        <p>Many items other than munitions should not be exported at all to Eastern
                            Europe, because they have too great military or strategic value. On the
                            other hand, it is worthwhile exporting some relatively plentiful items,
                            including some with strategic value, on a <hi rend="italic">quid pro
                                quo</hi> basis, to ensure the availability to the U.S. of manganese,
                            and chrome. It is even more important that we not take such drastic
                            measures as to force the U.S.S.R. to interrupt East-West trade in Europe
                            in retaliation. In addition it is desirable to ship certain types of
                            equipment to Eastern Europe which will increase output of items badly
                            needed in the <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>, provided there is
                            reasonable assurance that increased output will in fact be available to
                            the <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> countries.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">5. <hi rend="italic">Recommendations</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This report concentrates on the short-run problem of trade relations with
                            Eastern Europe. Long-run policies can be worked out only on the basis of
                            developments during the initial months ahead.</p>
                        <p>At present there is a virtual embargo on exports to Eastern Europe.
                            Practically no licenses are being approved. The Cabinet has already
                            decided that trade must proceed under appropriate restrictions. The U.S.
                            and the <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> countries are in danger of a
                            counter embargo, for example, on chrome and manganese. There is urgent
                            need to approve some license <hi rend="italic">applications</hi> for
                            Eastern European destinations immediately pending development of <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> policies. Those which cannot be
                            approved immediately should be denied as rapidly as possible or held
                            specifically for <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> bargaining
                            purposes.</p>
                        <p>The following recommendations are directed at the objective of getting
                            some export licenses approved in May. Policy and procedure for
                            subsequent months can be developed later.</p>
                        <p>A. The Subcommittee proposes that a program determination be approved
                            which would define four priority classes into which all commodities
                            should tentatively be divided: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Class 1 is defined as commodities which, by their nature, or
                                    because they can readily be converted, are of direct military
                                    significance or important in the manufacture of munitions; or
                                    commodities of the highest significance the denial of which
                                    would affect strategic sectors of the economy of the Soviet
                                    bloc. Whether or not an item is in short supply in the U.S.
                                    should have no influence on its inclusion in or exclusion from
                                    Class 1. (Note: Class 1 items should not be shipped from the
                                    U.S., to any Eastern European destination except in
                                    extraordinary circumstances. See B below.)</item>
                                <label>1A.</label>
                                <item>Class 1A is defined as military and semi-military items which
                                    should ultimately be controlled as munitions but which do not
                                    fall within the definition of munitions now in use. These items
                                    should be regarded as in Class 1.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Class 2 is defined as commodities of important though indirect
                                    military significance or of considerable importance to the
                                    industrial potential of Eastern European countries.</item>
                                <pb facs="0560" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Class 3 is defined as items which do not have any particular
                                    military significance in either peace or war but are of some
                                    importance in maintaining the basic economy of Eastern European
                                    countries.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Class 4 is defined as commodities of no particular
                                    significance either from a military point of view or to the
                                    maintenance of the economies of Eastern Europe; the so-called
                                    “non-essential items”.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The program determination should list commodities and materials according
                            to priority category. Illustrative lists are attached to this
                                memorandum.<note n="3" xml:id="d343fn3">The lists under reference
                                here are not printed.</note> (As soon as these lists can be
                            established, the <gloss target="#t_OIT1">OIT</gloss> should define the
                            items on it further by code number.)</p>
                        <p>3. Special consideration should be given to granting licenses which
                            otherwise might not be granted where: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The items will contribute directly and substantially to the
                                    availability to <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> countries of
                                    items essential to them and difficult to procure in adequate
                                    quantities from other sources, or</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The granting of a license can be used to procure a substantial
                                        <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> for the U.S. or the
                                    nations associated with it.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>In addition, account should be taken of any undue hardship on a U.S.
                            manufacturer or exporter who has made commitments in good faith prior to
                            any public knowledge of the institution of present export controls.</p>
                        <p>In general the granting of licenses for goods in categories 2 and 3 will
                            depend largely on the extent to which each individual Eastern European
                            country agrees to make political or economical concessions, including
                            provision of exports of needed goods to the U.S. and to Eastern European
                            countries. It may be expected that licenses will be granted less freely
                            if the pattern of a country’s requests for licenses is heavily weighted
                            with strategic items. Pending the possible establishment of more
                            formalized <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> bargaining arrangements,
                            strict caution should be used in granting licenses for Class 2
                            commodities, and unusual shipments of particular items in Classes 3 and
                            4, or an excessive overall volume of exports should not be licensed.
                            Requests considered to be excessive should in general not be denied, but
                            action should be withheld pending an opportunity to arrange for adequate
                            compensation.</p>
                        <p>C. The foregoing categories of goods, classified primarily for reasons of
                            security, must be considered in proper relationship to the positive list
                            of items in short supply. Insofar as administrative considerations
                            permit, the positive list should include those items which are not
                            available for export from the U.S. in quantities sufficient to meet the
                            total requirements of all countries upon the U.S. Shipments of positive
                            list items to the Soviet bloc should take place only if there is a
                            direct connection between such shipments and the <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> program, or another compensating <hi rend="italic">quid
                                pro quo</hi>.</p>
                        <pb facs="0561" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/>
                        <p>The question of the basis for denial of a license in the case of items on
                            the list based on security considerations, and also on the list of items
                            prohibited by reason of short supply and need under <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>, requires further study.</p>
                        <p>D. The Subcommittee also recommends, pending the development of a
                            long-term policy, a program determination to the effect that;</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>No item in Class 1 or Class 1A should be approved for export from
                                the U.S. to destinations in Eastern Europe<note n="*" xml:id="d343fn4">In this memorandum “Eastern Europe” includes:
                                    Finland, USSR, Eastern Zone of Germany, Czechoslovakia, Poland,
                                    Rumania, Bulgaria, Albania, Yugoslavia and Hungary. [Footnote in
                                    the source text.]</note> except in (extraordinary) circumstances
                                as defined in B above and after review by the Subcommittee.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>No item in Class 2 should be approved for export to Eastern Europe
                                until it has been reviewed individually, or in a group of cases, by
                                the Subcommittee;</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Items in Class 3 should be licensed by <gloss target="#t_OIT1">OIT</gloss> within the policy framework, except for special
                                cases which <gloss target="#t_OIT1">OIT</gloss> may wish to bring to
                                the attention of the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi>
                                Subcommittee;</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Items in Class 4 should be licensed relatively freely;</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Items on the positive list which may be available for shipment to
                                the Soviet bloc, in accordance with standards set forth in B, shall
                                not be licensed except after review by the <hi rend="italic">Ad
                                    Hoc</hi> Subcommittee.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Further Recommendations</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Subcommittee recognizes that the foregoing recommendations can be
                            made effective only if other corollary actions are carried out.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Control of Re-Exports</hi>. Eastern European
                                countries may try to buy through third parties the commodities that
                                they cannot obtain direct. This problem requires further study.
                                Meanwhile the <gloss target="#t_OIT1">OIT</gloss> should watch
                                diligently the volume of applications in each commodity group for
                                each country to detect and deny unusual requests, not adequately
                                justified and explained, which might indicate re-exporting or other
                                activities which should be discouraged.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Inspection</hi>. As export controls are tightened
                                on items which Eastern Europe urgently requires, there may be a
                                sharp increase in well-organized efforts to evade the law. The
                                Subcommittee considers it desirable that provision be made for
                                adequate inspection of all licensed exports and parcel post
                                shipments to Eastern Europe, as well as explored. All ships leaving
                                for Eastern Europe should be checked with especial
                                thoroughness.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Control of Other Sources</hi>. The Subcommittee
                                recognizes that Eastern Europe will try to buy from Western Europe
                                any imports they cannot obtain here. However, there will be
                                inevitably a lag involved in any such shift of procurement. Western
                                Europe is already selling <pb facs="0562" n="542" xml:id="pg_542"/>
                                all that it can produce currently. It cannot increase exports of
                                complex equipment rapidly.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>In order to make policy with respect to Eastern Europe effective
                                in the long run, it will be necessary, through the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> and diplomatic channels, to arrange
                                that Western European countries pursue export policies which are
                                more or less consistent with those of the U.S. The Subcommittee
                                recommends that the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> and the
                                State Department explore the possibilities along these lines.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>The appropriate agencies should review Western European exports of
                                Class 1 and Class 2 items to Eastern Europe on a continuing basis to
                                determine whether or not adequate caution is used by Western
                                European countries in limiting such exports.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>A few items in Class 1 and Class 2, especially raw materials, are
                                available in South American and other countries, Soviet bloc imports
                                from these sources should be the subject of early examination and
                                action. This subject will be explored in a subsequent
                                memorandum.</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>Other recommendations are being prepared with respect to: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Hardship cases in which owners are unable to secure
                                        licenses for goods produced or in the process of production
                                        for Eastern European buyers;</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Increasing imports of manganese and chrome from sources
                                        outside the U.S.S.R.; and</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Various other measures of economic warfare.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>