<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="385" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d385">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">840.811/5–848</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador of the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Panyushkin</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <p>The Secretary of State presents his compliments to His Excellency the
                            Ambassador of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics and refers to the
                            previous exchange of notes for the purpose of arranging agreement
                            regarding the holding of a conference on a new regime of navigation on
                            the Danube and the note of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics dated
                            May 8, 1948.</p>
                        <p>The Government of the United States regrets that the Union of Soviet
                            Socialist Republics does not agree to a preliminary meeting to exchange
                            views concerning arrangements for the proposed conference. The United
                            States Government believes that such an exchange would have expedited
                            arrangements for, and facilitated the convocation of the conference, on
                            terms acceptable to the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, the United
                            Kingdom, France, and the United States.</p>
                        <p>It is the opinion of the United States Government that, as matters now
                            stand, the date of May 30, 1948 could not possibly allow sufficient time
                            to make arrangements suitable to the participating governments.
                            Accordingly, the United States Government proposes that the Conference
                            be held in Belgrade on July 30, 1948 assuming that this is agreeable to
                            the other governments concerned and in light of the assurance of the
                            Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics of information
                            that the Yugoslav Government will be able to act as host in accordance
                            with an invitation as agreed to by the Union of Soviet Socialist
                            Republics, the United Kingdom, France and the United States. There is
                            enclosed a copy of a proposed note to the Yugoslav Government which
                            contains certain suggested modifications and additions to the invitation
                            proposed by the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in the Ambassador’s
                            note of May 8, 1948.</p>
                        <p>The United States Government deeply regrets the Government of the Union
                            of Soviet Socialist Republics’ position that it cannot agree to the
                            participation of Austria at the Conference as urged by the United States
                            Government. It is the continued view of the United States Government
                            that the central geographic position occupied by Austria and its
                            important role in the trade and commerce on the Danube River warrant its
                            inclusion in the Conference along with the other riparian states.
                            Accordingly, the United States Government would appreciate a
                            reconsideration by the Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist
                            Republics of its position. If the Government of the Union of Soviet
                            Socialist Republics still cannot agree to full participation on the part
                            of the Austrian Government, the United States Government requests that
                            it agree to Austrian attendance at the very <pb facs="0634" n="613" xml:id="pg_613"/> least in the same capacity in which Austria now
                            attends the Economic Commission for Europe; namely, by sending
                            representatives in a consultative capacity.</p>
                        <p>The United States Government would be grateful to the Government of the
                            Union of Soviet Socialist Republics for the earliest possible
                            notification to the effect that it agrees to transmitting simultaneously
                            the enclosed text of an identical communication by the four governments
                            to the Government of Yugoslavia in order to assure the holding of the
                            Danube Conference on July 30, 1948.</p>
                        <p>A similar communication is being sent to the governments of the United
                                Kingdom<note n="1" xml:id="d385fn1">The British Government sent a
                                note on June 10 for the Soviet Union and gave a copy of it on the
                                next day to the Department of State. The proposals advanced in the
                                United States note of May 25 were fully supported, but the note also
                                plainly declared that if a future conference failed to reach agreed
                                recommendations on a new régime of navigation for the Danube river,
                                then all British rights under existing treaties were reserved, and
                                any new convention made at a conference could not enter into effect
                                unless it had been accepted by all of the countries concerned.
                                (840.811/6–1148)</note> and France.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-25">May 25,
                                1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Proposed Text of an <gloss type="from">Identical
                                        Communication of the Four Governments</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Government of Yugoslavia</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>At the Council of Foreign Ministers meeting in December 1946, the
                                Governments of the United Kingdom, the French Republic, the Union of
                                Soviet Socialist Republics and the United States of America agreed
                                to the incorporation of the principle of free and open navigation on
                                the Danube in the treaties with Bulgaria, Hungary and Rumania, and
                                further agreed to the calling of a conference to work out a new
                                convention for a regime of navigation of the Danube.</p>
                            <p>The four governments have now decided to convene the conference on
                                July 30, 1948, and request the cooperation of the Yugoslav
                                Government in holding the conference in Belgrade. In the event that
                                the Yugoslav Government is agreeable to the proposed time and place,
                                its agreement is requested in the interest of adequate communication
                                to issue authorization for aircraft of the participating countries,
                                as deemed necessary by each participating country, to fly to and
                                from Belgrade to transport persons attending the conference and to
                                perform courier services during the course of the conference,
                                subject to normal Yugoslav regulations and controls regarding the
                                operation of aircraft. In addition, it is assumed that the Yugoslav
                                Government is prepared to assure adequate facilities for
                                representatives of the press and radio of the participating
                                countries who might wish to report <pb facs="0635" n="614" xml:id="pg_614"/> conference developments, which facilities
                                would include freedom from censorship on conference reporting.</p>
                            <p>If the Yugoslav Government is in agreement with the above, it is
                                suggested that it be good enough to signify its concurrence with
                                this communication and to issue invitations in the following form to
                                the enumerated governments: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Government of the Peoples Federated Republic of
                                        Yugoslavia has the honor on its own behalf and on behalf of
                                        the Governments of France, the United Kingdom, the Union of
                                        Soviet Socialist Republics, and the United States to invite
                                        the Governments of Austria, Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia,
                                        Hungary, Rumania, and the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist
                                        Republic to send representatives [or Bulgaria,
                                        Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Rumania and the Ukrainian Soviet
                                        Socialist Republic to send representatives and to the
                                        Government of Austria to send representatives to act in a
                                        consultative capacity]<note n="2" xml:id="d385fn2">Brackets
                                            appear in the source text.</note> to Belgrade,
                                        Yugoslavia, to participate in a conference beginning july
                                        30, 1948 to work out a new convention regarding the regime
                                        of navigation of the Danube in accordance with the
                                        agreements made by the above four Governments at the
                                        December 1946 meeting of the Council of Foreign
                                        Ministers.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>