<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Yugoslavia (
                        Cannon
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d446</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">446</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-08-13T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-08-13T06:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="sovereignty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-13T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-13T06:00:00-05:00" n="446" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d446">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.811/8–1348: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Yugoslavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cannon</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Belgrade</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-13T12:00:00+01:00">August 13, 1948—noon.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Deldu1">Deldu</gloss>61. Only amendment submitted to Article 4
                    of Danube Convention is Czecho-Hungarian proposed annex (document <gloss target="#t_ComGen1">ComGen</gloss> three) concerning Gabcikovo-Gonyu sector
                    of river and possible special administration there.<note n="1" xml:id="d446fn1">The Gabchikovo (Gabćikovo)–Gönyü sector of the Danube river, west of
                        Budapest, stretching between kilometers 1821 and 1791 from the mouth of the
                        river, presented special difficulties for the maintenance of a good state of
                        navigability, which particularly suffered from shallowness of the water
                        level in dry periods. The problems encountered to ensure normal conditions
                        of navigation along this sector formed the subject matter of Annex II of the
                        convention finally adopted by the Belgrade conference.</note> At my
                    suggestion, consideration of amendment deferred at yesterday’s meeting until
                    committee reaches Articles 17 and 18, on which <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> has submitted amendments. Soviet Article 4 then voted on
                    without amendment, with seven votes for, none against, and one abstention (US).
                    British and French took no part in voting.</p>
                <p>Radius presented our amendment to Article 5 with statement cabled <gloss target="#t_Deldu1">Deldu</gloss> 57, August 12. US position then subjected
                    to attack by Bebler and Pauker, with some distortions of fact to which I intend
                    to reply today. Both denounced our advocacy of non-Riparian participation <pb facs="0713" n="692" xml:id="pg_692"/> on Danube Commission as motivated by
                    policy of economic and political penetration (vide Marshall plan) aimed at
                    domination of Danubian states. Both also said pre-war Danube regime, with
                    non-Riparian representation, based on force and could not be reimposed. Bebler
                    said US Proposal amounted to claim for new regime of “capitulations”.</p>
                <p>Peake, defending our amendment and similar one tabled by UK, broadened discussion
                    by contradicting Bebler on <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>. He argued only
                    participants in position to judge it, that British people not worried about US
                    penetration. He then cited <gloss target="#t_UNRRA1">UNRRA</gloss> help to Yugo
                    asking whether that had resulted in enslavement of Yugos by western
                    imperialists. Turning to British claim to representation on commission, he gave
                    figures on British Danube shipping in past and British loans to European Danube
                    Commission enabling latter to improve maritime Danube.</p>
                <p>Concluding, Peake raised question of status of USSR as Riparian state if Ukraine
                    considered as such. He asked <gloss target="#t_SovDel1">SovDel</gloss> to
                    clarify distinction between Riparian and Danube states.</p>
                <p>At evening session Ukrainian and Bulgarian representative continued attack on US
                    motives and policies, saying purpose of use [<hi rend="italic">our</hi>]
                    proposal on Article 5, [as] shown by our own presentation, was intervention in
                    affairs of Danubian states.</p>
                <p>Vyshinski carried on with fifty minute speech, much of which was denunciation of
                        <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> as imperialism. This part was largely
                    read, in contrast to usual extemporaneous performance, and appears to have been
                    prepared well in advance for just such occasion. It contained usual charges of
                    Soviet propaganda that <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> aimed at holding off
                    US depression by stimulating exports and finding new markets; that aid to Europe
                    only incidental; that conditions set which put European nations under our thumb
                    through control of foreign exchange, etc.; that sovereignty of European states
                    gravely threatened by our program of so-called international economic
                    cooperation cloaking imperialist aims.</p>
                <p>In latter part of speech Vyshinski returned to Danube questions, rejecting US
                    amendment to Article 5. He held Ukraine and USSR both Riparian, latter because
                    it included former; also, USSR touched river at confluence of Prut outside
                    Ukrainian territory. In conclusion he rejected our arguments on Austria and
                    Germany on ground <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> 1946 decision clearly bars
                    Austrian membership on commission prior to peace treaty, and not proper to
                    mention Germany in connection with Danube until general settlement reached on
                    Germany in accordance with Potsdam.</p>
                <p>As major east-west controversies are aired here for propaganda purposes, Danube
                    questions tend to be lost from view. Vyshinski is at his domineering best in
                    such exchanges, obviously trying to drive home <pb facs="0714" n="693" xml:id="pg_693"/> idea that western powers impotent in this region. At
                    preceding session he had verbal encounter with Gros of French delegation in
                    which Gros, following lucid and impressive exposition, was challenged but hit
                    back sharply and had last word. Yesterday Vyshinski had gloves off in going for
                    us and for Peake. This morning I shall reply vigorously but very briefly in
                    rebuttal but at same time call conference back to business at hand.</p>
                <p>Sent Department as <gloss target="#t_Deldu1">Deldu</gloss> 61, Department pass
                    Moscow, London, Paris, Budapest, Berlin, Bucharest, Sofia, Praha, Vienna,
                    Geneva.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cannon</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
