<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Transportation and Communications (
                        Norton
                    ) to the Under Secretary of State (
                        Lovett
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d467</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">467</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-14T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="sovereignty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="467" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d467">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.811/9–1648</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Transportation and Communications</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Norton</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-14">October 14,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In my previous memorandum of September 16, same subject,<note n="1" xml:id="d467fn1">Not found in Department files; see, however, the circular
                        telegram of September 30, 1948, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> I
                    recommended a program of follow-up activities on the Danube Conference. <pb facs="0747" n="726" xml:id="pg_726"/> Since then the following actions have
                    been taken on the items referred to in my memorandum: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Suggest to all interested countries that formed
                                protest be lodged with USSR and Satellites that the Belgrade
                                Convention is null and void and publication of such
                            notice</hi>.</item>
                        <label> </label>
                        <item>Both the French and British have been advised of our thoughts on this
                            subject and have conveyed them to their respective foreign offices. We
                            have not yet received an expression of opinion from them. A draft of the
                            U.S. protest note has been prepared in <gloss target="#t_TRC1">TRC</gloss> and has been circulated to all interested divisions for
                            comments. Most of the divisions have suggested some changes and when all
                            comments are in, a final version of the note will be prepared for your
                                approval.<note n="2" xml:id="d467fn2">See the revised draft of
                                proposed note attached to the memorandum of November 17, 1948, by
                                John W. Tuthill, adviser in the Office of Transport and
                                Communications, <ref target="#pg_729">p. 729</ref>.</note> It is
                            hoped to deliver this note within the week. </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Use of any opportunity in U.N. or other international
                                bodies to refer to the Danube Conference criticising its conduct and
                                its results</hi>.</item>
                        <label> </label>
                        <item>The proposed text of a speech and other material has been sent to
                            Willard Thorp at the U.N. with the suggestion that it be used in the
                            course of the proceedings there.<note n="3" xml:id="d467fn3">Assistant
                                Secretary of State for Economic Affairs Willard L. Thorp was United
                                States alternate representative at the United Nations General
                                Assembly; see footnote 3, <ref target="#pg_732">p. 732</ref>.</note>
                            We have not yet been informed whether or under what circumstances Thorp
                            intends to use this material. </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">To advise the British and French that the United
                                States will support a move on their part to obtain an advisory
                                opinion from the International Court</hi>.</item>
                        <label> </label>
                        <item>French and British have been so advised. However, from our discussions
                            with the British Embassy in Washington, it appears as though the foreign
                            office is not certain whether it will be possible to bring this question
                            before the Court. Explorations on this question are still underway. The
                            British Embassy in Washington has been informed by their Paris Embassy
                            that the French Foreign Office has expressed general agreement with our
                            proposals. However, they agree that there are technical difficulties in
                            bringing this proposal before the International Court. Their inclination
                            is to try the Transport Subcommittee of <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss>. We have, however, received no direct response from
                            the French here in Washington. </item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">U.S. to take the initiative in raising the Danube
                                issue at a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> meeting on the German
                                and Austrian Peace Treaties</hi>.</item>
                        <pb facs="0748" n="727" xml:id="pg_727"/>
                        <label> </label>
                        <item>Since a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> meeting on these treaties
                            is still remote, no action is contemplated at this time. </item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Information activities to stir up Danube Satellite
                                States to regret the Belgrade Conference results</hi>.</item>
                        <label> </label>
                        <item>Information has been made available to <gloss target="#t_INP1">INP</gloss> and the Voice of America is now preparing such material
                            for use over their facilities. </item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Encourage American occupation authorities in Germany
                                and Austria to offer reciprocal shipping and trade arrangements with
                                the Satellites and instruct them not to deal with the Commission or
                                otherwise recognize the Convention</hi>.</item>
                        <label> </label>
                        <item>We are planning to authorize Legation, Vienna to concur in the opening
                            of negotiations for bilateral reciprocal agreements with the concurrence
                            of <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_OMGUS1">OMGUS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USFA1">USFA</gloss>. At the
                            same time all of these groups will be alerted to the need of avoiding
                            recognition of the Soviet Convention, Commission or any of its agencies. </item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Advising Italians, Belgians and Greeks of our plans
                                and reaffirming our support of their rights on the
                            Danube</hi>.</item>
                        <label> </label>
                        <item>Action on this matter has been held up until we can receive an
                            expression of opinion from the French and the British and after our
                            protest note has been approved. </item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Advise <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> of our
                                policy and request their cooperation</hi>.</item>
                        <label> </label>
                        <item>No action has been taken on this question pending the approval of our
                            protest note. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>As a further point in our educational campaign and maintenance of interest in the
                    Danube, the State Department <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> is planning the
                    publication in an early issue of an analytical article on the Danube Conference,
                    as well as the text of the American draft convention. The formal protests of
                    French, British, Austrians, Belgians, Italians and Greeks will also be
                    published.</p>
                <p>We have received from Embassy, Moscow; Legation, Sofia; Legation, Bucharest;
                    Embassy, London, and Legation, Vienna expressions of agreement on the
                    advisability of putting this program into effect. Both London and Bucharest also
                    emphasized the importance of an intensive Voice of America program to bring home
                    to the riparian states the economic and political losses resulting from Soviet
                    control of the Danube, as well as infringement of their sovereignty.</p>
                <p>It should be possible to make considerable progress with most of these points
                    when action on our protest note is completed and we have a definite reaction
                    from the French and the British.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Garrison Norton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
