<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union (
                        Smith
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d629</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">629</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-11-30T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-11-30T11:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-11-30T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-11-30T11:00:00-05:00" n="629" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d629">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.91261/11–3048: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-11-30T19:00:00+03:00">November 30, 1948—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2787. Censorship regulations for newspaper correspondents in USSR at present
                    require that two copies of telegraph despatches be filed through censorship
                    window at telegraph office and two copies of any article for publication which
                    is later to be mailed. (Re <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1340,
                    November 23.<note n="1" xml:id="d629fn1">Not printed.</note>)</p>
                <p>At present American correspondents file at censorship window three copies of
                    telegraphic despatches, one of which they receive back when censored usually
                    with indication of material deleted. If despatch not sent, he is handed piece of
                    paper on which is written his name, number of filed message and the words “ne
                    poidet”—in other words, “killed by censor”. Entire despatches sometimes held
                    days or weeks without giving reasons, leaving only recourse for correspondent
                    write Press Department Foreign Office.</p>
                <p>Under above system correspondent has no control over material actually despatched
                    by telegraph over his signature. He only learns what has been deleted after
                    despatch has gone and even then censor sometimes does not accurately mark
                    deleted portions on third copy. Routine cables take from half hour to several
                    hours pass censorship. Longer despatches usually based on articles in Soviet
                    periodicals often take several days. On material to be sent by mail original is
                    returned to correspondent with censored passages heavily inked out or in event
                    numerous censured items correspondent may be asked make clean copy. Material
                    thus passed by censor and stamped approved may be mailed abroad.</p>
                <pb facs="0959" n="938" xml:id="pg_938"/>
                <p>Press telephone calls abroad may be made only from special room at telephone
                    office. Two copies of material to be phoned handed in at censorship window and
                    upon return approved copy, it constitutes authorization telephone operator put
                    through call. Correspondent supposed read only from approved copy. Believe calls
                    not monitored simultaneously by censor but recording taken and deviations could
                    well lead future difficulties.</p>
                <p>The censorship is entirely arbitrary and unpredictable. Quite often material
                    taken directly from Soviet sources will be killed by censor. Worst aspect of
                    censorship, however, is that cabled despatches go out censored often giving
                    impression contrary to original without correspondent having opportunity argue,
                    change or withdraw despatch.<note n="2" xml:id="d629fn2">In this connection
                        Ambassador Smith expressed his conviction in telegram 2814 from Moscow on
                        December 2, not printed, that deliberate deception resulting from censorship
                        should not be concealed from the public: “As I have previously stated orally
                        to officials of the Department and to publishers at home, I consider it
                        unfair to the American public and to the American correspondents in Moscow,
                        if not downright dishonest, that press dispatches from the Soviet Union
                        which are tailored by Soviet censor to fit aims of Soviet propaganda appear
                        in the American press without a clear preceding indication that they have
                        been subjected to and passed by Soviet censors. I continue to feel the same
                        way and all the officers on my staff as well as every American citizen
                        correspondent in Moscow shares this feeling. I believe positive action by
                        the Department with regard this matter is overdue and that such action is in
                        fact a responsibility which we have toward American public.”
                        (861.918/12–248)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
