<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation
                        (
                        Hoover
                    ) to the Chief of the Division of Foreign Activity
                        Correlation (
                        Neal
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d669</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">669</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recuam8o24ZoLTXkC" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="personnel-foreign-service" subject="diplomatic-immunity" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038191" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Diplomatic immunity</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" subject="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="press-conference" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517" lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="669" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d669">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">702.6111/8–948</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hoover</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Chief of the Division of Foreign Activity
                        Correlation</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Neal</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-09">August 9,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Reference is made to the telephone call from this Bureau to you on August 7,
                    1948, concerning the above captioned matter.<note n="2" xml:id="d669fn2">This
                        was related to the disappearance of two Russian teachers from the special
                        private school operated for the children of members of the Consulate General
                        of the Soviet Union and other agencies at New York City.</note> The
                    following facts are being set forth for your information and consideration and
                    no further action will be taken by this Bureau.</p>
                <p>At approximately 2:15 PM on August 7, 1948, the Clarkstown, New York Police
                    Department advised that a complaint had been received that a woman was taken
                    from a rest home operated by Mrs. Alexandra Tolstoy by four men believed to be
                    Russians in a black Buick sedan.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Tolstoy, above mentioned, is identical with Countess Alexandra L. Tolstoy,
                    head of the Tolstoy Foundation.<note n="3" xml:id="d669fn3">Miss (Countess)
                        Alexandra Lvovna Tolstoy (Tolstaya) was the daughter of the Russian novelist
                        Count Lev (Leo) Nikolayevich Tolstoy (1828–1910). She was the head of the
                        Tolstoy Foundation (“Fund”), Inc., with offices at 289 Fourth Avenue, New
                        York City, which was a welfare organization, and which operated and
                        maintained the rest home of Reed Farm at Valley Cottage in Rockland County,
                        New York.</note> She and her assistant, Martha Andreevna Knutson, were
                    interviewed and Knutson advised that at about 1:25 PM, on August 7, 1948, she
                    was at the Reed Farm, Lake Road, Valley Cottage, New York, which is operated by
                    the Tolstoy Foundation and noticed a car with three or four men and one woman
                    arrive at the farm. Two men got out of the car and one of them approached her
                    and asked where “the school teacher with the twins” was.<note n="4" xml:id="d669fn4">The reference is to Mikhail Ivanovich Samarin. His wife was
                        Klavdiya Mikhailovna Samarina. Their twins, Tatyana Mikhailovna and Vladimir
                        Mikhail-ovich, had been born in New York. There was also an older daughter,
                        Elena (Helen) Mikhailovna.</note> Knutson told him she did not know and said
                    that Kasienkina<note n="5" xml:id="d669fn5">Mrs. Oksana Stepanovna Kasenkina
                        (Kasyenkina).</note> was the only teacher she knew. Knutson said she noticed
                    then that the other man who had gotten out of the car was talking to Kasienkina
                    who was working in the kitchen. At about this time, Knutson advised, Countess
                    Tolstoy arrived on the scene.</p>
                <p>Countess Tolstoy advised that Kasienkina came to her and said she was leaving,
                    that “she had to go”. Tolstoy went with Kasienkina to <pb facs="1046" n="1025" xml:id="pg_1025"/> the latter’s bedroom, locked the door and advised
                    Kasienkina that she did not have to go, that this was America and that if she
                    wanted to stay, Tolstoy could have the police at the farm within fifteen
                    minutes. Countess Tolstoy advised that Kasienkina insisted that “she had to go”
                    and proceeded to pack her bags and get her things ready. Tolstoy further advised
                    that she told Knutson to call the men on the farm-just prior to the time she
                    went to the bedroom with Kasienkina. When Kasienkina came out of her bedroom
                    with her bags one of the men who had arrived in the car took the bags and rushed
                    her to the car. Meanwhile the men at the Reed Farm had surrounded the car and
                    were going to rush it but Tolstoy told them that Kasienkina wanted to go and
                    that she had a right to go.</p>
                <p>Countess Tolstoy further advised that about ten minutes after Kasienkina left the
                    farm which was about 1:35 PM, a station wagon with New York license SU–225,
                    drove up and asked for Kasienkina. These individuals were told that Kasienkina
                    was not there and the station wagon left. Countess Tolstoy said that she then
                    called the Clarkstown Police Department and gave them the facts. She gave the
                    license of the station wagon and also advised the police that the first car was
                    a black Buick sedan.</p>
                <p>Advice has been received that the Clarkstown Police Department put out an alarm
                    for both of the above mentioned cars and subsequently the station wagon was
                    stopped, but after the occupants identified themselves and claimed diplomatic
                    immunity they were permitted to proceed.</p>
                <p>Countess Tolstoy stated that Kasienkina does not speak English, that she was
                    employed as a teacher in Agricultural Chemistry. Her husband was shot in Russia
                    and her child later disappeared. Some of her belongings were left at the Reed
                    Farm.</p>
                <p>Countess Tolstoy also explained that Kasienkina went to a man at the Russian
                    daily newspaper, “Novoye Rosskoye Slovoye”<note n="6" xml:id="d669fn6">The
                        reference is to Mark (Max) Weinbaum, editor of the <hi rend="italic">Novoye
                            Russkoye Slovo</hi> (New Russian Word) in New York City.</note> on July
                    29, 1948 and told her story. This man sent Kasienkina to Vladimir Zenzinov<note n="7" xml:id="d669fn7">Vladimir Mikhailovich Zenzinov was a journalist,
                        writer, and editor of the <hi rend="italic">Russian Review for Freedom</hi>
                        in New York City. He claimed that he had been a member of the Executive
                        Committee of the Soviet (Council) of Workers’ Deputies; in Petrograd in
                        March 1917 along with Iosif Vissarionovich Stalin and
                        Vyacheslav-Mikhailovich Molotov.</note> who called Countess Tolstoy and
                    asked her if she could, hide out a person for a few days. Countess Tolstoy said
                    she could but that she would have to turn the person over to the Immigration
                    and; Naturalization Service and thereafter the person would have to take her
                    chances on staying in this country. Countess Tolstoy also said that if it
                    developed this person was a spy she would, of course, be turned <pb facs="1047" n="1026" xml:id="pg_1026"/> over to the proper authorities. It was arranged
                    for Kasienkina to meet Countess Tolstoy on July 30, 1948, but Kasienkina did not
                    appear. However, on July 31, 1948, Kasienkina took a cab and told the people at
                    her residence that she was going to the pier to depart from this country.
                    Instead she went to Zenzinov’s office and the latter brought her to the Tolstoy
                    Farm by bus, arriving there at about 1:20 p. m. July 31, 1948. Countess Tolstoy
                    said that Kasienkina seemed to be quite happy at the farm.</p>
                <p>Countess Tolstoy further advised that on July 29, 1948, Mikhail Ivanovich Samarin
                    came into her office and begged her to hide him and his family. He indicated
                    that he needed help because he would be shot upon his return to Russia. Countess
                    Tolstoy warned him as she had Kasienkina that she could hide him for a few days
                    and then it would be necessary to turn him over to the Immigration and
                    Naturalization Service. She explained to him that he would have to take his
                    chances on being able to stay in this country and further informed him that if
                    he turned out to be a spy he would be turned over to the proper authorities in
                    this country. On Friday, July 30, 1948, Countess Tolstoy arranged a meeting for
                    Samarin with Andrew Shebanoff<note n="8" xml:id="d669fn8">Presumably intended is
                        Harry Sbibanov, owner of a chicken farm and a former revolutionary in
                        Russia.</note> of Freehold, New Jersey. At 1:00 a. m. July 31, 1948,
                    Shebanoff took a truck to Samarin’s apartment, picked up his family and his
                    belongings and took them to the hideout. Countess Tolstoy advised that she asked
                    Samarin if there was anyone else who wanted to leave and he advised her that
                    Kasienkina also wanted to leave and that he thought she was all right but would
                    not recommend her because he had learned never to trust anybody.</p>
                <p>Countess Tolstoy advised that she asked Kasienkina if there was anyone else among
                    the teachers who wanted to leave and Kasienkina advised she understood Samarin
                    wanted to leave but she did not know whether to trust him or not because she had
                    learned never to trust anyone.</p>
                <p>Countess Tolstoy stated that Shebanoff is a former member of the Communist Party
                    in Russia and was in prison with Stalin at one time.</p>
                <p>However, he has turned against Russia. He is fairly well off and has been known
                    to help many people. She also advised that she has known Zenzinov who resides at
                    294 Riverside Drive, New York City, for sometime, and that he is a Socialist
                    Revolutionary and a foe of the Communists. He is an author and when he was in
                    Russia he was friendly with Kerensky.<note n="9" xml:id="d669fn9">Alexander
                        Fedorovich Kerensky had been a minister and then prime minister
                        (July–November 1917) of the Provisional Government of Russia.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1048" n="1027" xml:id="pg_1027"/>
                <p>You will recall that Sunday newspapers reflected that a press conference was held
                    at the Soviet Consulate in New York City<note n="10" xml:id="d669fn10">The
                        statement made by Mrs. Kasenkina to the press at a conference arranged at
                        the Consulate General of the Soviet Union on August 7 is in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, August 8, 1948, pp. 1, 48.</note> and
                    at this conference, Kasienkina through an interpreter, claimed to have been
                    kidnapped and taken to the Reed Farm, after her arm was pierced with a
                    hypodermic needle. At the conference, Kasienkina claimed to have been approached
                    by one Vladimir Zenzinov and had also been influenced by a Dr. Alexander
                        Korchinsky.<note n="11" xml:id="d669fn11">Identification indefinite. A
                        Federal Bureau of Investigation memorandum of August 25, 1948, suggested the
                        possibility of an Alexander Kojansky who was a chemist but not a doctor,
                        although using that title. (702.6111/8–3048)</note> She claimed that both of
                    these men took her to the Reed Farm. She also claimed that while at the farm she
                    wrote a letter to the New York Consulate stating, “I am not an enemy. I am very
                    loyal to my country. I love my people with all my heart. I beg you not to let me
                    perish here. I have been deprived of my freedom.” The letter was apparently
                    longer but the above portion was the only one given to the press. At the press
                    conference it was further stated that this letter was postmarked August 5, 1948.
                    It allegedly was given to a vegetable man who was driving by the Reed Farm and
                    he later posted it.<note n="12" xml:id="d669fn12">This letter was postmarked
                        from Haverstraw, New York, August 5, 1948, 8 a. m. The envelope was directed
                        to A[lexander] E[fremovich] Porozhnyakov, an attaché of the Consulate
                        General, who resided in the same building as Mrs. Kasenkina. A photostatic
                        copy of this letter is on file under 702.6111/9–2048. The letter indicated a
                        strong wish not to return to the Soviet Union and an explanation why the
                        writer held that view. There was suspicion regarding the handwriting of this
                        letter, which could not be certainly resolved in a Federal Bureau of
                        Investigation Laboratory Report of October 5, 1948, because the handwriting
                        characteristics were not sufficiently comparable. (702.6111/9–2048) In an
                        interview on September 9, 1948, at the Roosevelt Hospital in New York with
                        officers of the Police Department, Mrs. Kasenkina believed the copy shown to
                        her was too long, being five sheets of paper whereas she had mailed about
                        two pages, and she did not recognize some of the characters as being in her
                        writing. The transcript of this interview is filed under 702.6111/9–1048.
                        See also footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_1049">p. 1049</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>At the press conference it was stated that when this letter was received by Yakov
                    M. Lomakin,<note n="13" xml:id="d669fn13">Yakov Mironovich Lomakin was consul
                        general of the Soviet Union at New York.</note> he notified the New York
                    City Police Department, advising them that he was going to the Reed Farm and
                    wanted the police to go with him. He said it was understood that the police
                    would have a representative at the farm but that when he arrived with his
                    assistant and his chauffeur, they did not see the police and therefore they went
                    in by themselves.</p>
                <p>At the press conference it was further stated that Kasienkina advised she wanted
                    to go back to Russia and it was necessary to use force to get her out of the
                    house where she was staying at the Reed Farm. About this time approximately
                    twelve men surrounded the car and grabbed Lomakin and his assistant but they got
                    away with Kasienkina.</p>
                <pb facs="1049" n="1028" xml:id="pg_1028"/>
                <p>At the press conference it was also stated that Mikhail Ivanovich Samarin, who
                    was a teacher of mathematics at the Soviet Private School and his wife who was a
                    teacher of languages at the same school, were scheduled to depart July 31, 1948,
                    aboard the SS <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, but were missing. Lomakin advised
                    the press conference that it was understood the Samarin family was taken to a
                    camp in New Jersey. He advised that he was going to make an effort to see if he
                    can obtain the release of the Samarin family, who allegedly are at the Rover
                    Camp, Cassville, New Jersey.<note n="14" xml:id="d669fn14">The Rova (Roova)
                        Camp, or Farm, was operated by the Russian United: Mutual Aid Society. The
                        Samarin family was not sheltered here.</note> Lomakin also advised that he
                    did not know what his next move would be, that if the <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> wanted to talk to Kasienkina, permission to do so might be
                    given on Monday.<note n="15" xml:id="d669fn15">August 9.</note> Lomakin also
                    indicated that he might get in touch with Commissioner Wallander<note n="16" xml:id="d669fn16">Arthur W. Wallander, Commissioner, New York City Police
                        Department.</note> at the Police Department and make some effort to obtain
                    the release of the people who are being held, if there are any, against their
                    will at the farm.</p>
                <p>Viktor Andreevich Kravchenko<note n="17" xml:id="d669fn17">For documentation on
                        Kravchenko’s own defection and the attempts by the-Soviet Government to
                        obtain his deportation, see <ref target="frus1944v04#pg_1224">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 1224</ref>–<ref target="frus1944v04#pg_1241">1241</ref>, and <ref target="frus1945v05#pg_1131">1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp.
                            1131</ref>–<ref target="frus1945v05#pg_1138">1138</ref>.</note> was
                    interviewed on August 7, 1948, and advised that Kasienkina had approached the
                    editor of “Novoye Rosskoye Slovoye” shortly prior to July 31, 1948, stating that
                    she did not wish to return to Russia and asked for assistance. The editor
                    referred her to Vladimir Zenzinov, 294 Riverside Drive, New York City, who is an
                    elderly Russian of right wing political leanings. Kravchenko advised that on
                    August 7, 1948, he called Zenzinov and Zenzinov immediately requested that
                    Kravchenko see him. At this time the occurrences at the Tolstoy Farm were
                    related to Kravchenko. It should also be noted that Miss Tolstoy advised that
                    after receiving this information Kravchenko communicated with Representative
                    Carl Mundt.<note n="18" xml:id="d669fn18">Karl E. Mundt of South Dakota was a
                        member of the Un-American Activities Committee of the House of
                        Representatives.</note> Kravchenko also advised that he had determined
                    through Zenzinov that no statements had been given by Kravchenko [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] or Miss Tolstoy. He also stated that newspaper men
                    had attempted to obtain the complete story from Zenzinov but he had cautioned
                    Zenzinov not to make any disclosures.</p>
                <p>Kravchenko stated that Samarin had been moved to a location other than the one
                    believed to be known to the Soviet Consulate and he offered to locate Samarin.
                    Kravchenko also stated that when located he would make him available for
                    interview.</p>
                <p>At 9:45 AM, August 8, 1948, Mikhail Ivanovich Samarin called at the <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> office in New York City accompanied by
                    Kravchenko. <pb facs="1050" n="1029" xml:id="pg_1029"/> Samarin was advised
                    through a Russian speaking agent that he did not have to make any statement and
                    was free to leave at any time.<note n="19" xml:id="d669fn19">See the account in
                        the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, August 9, 1948, p. 1.</note> All
                    agents present at the interview identified themselves as such.</p>
                <p>Samarin described himself and his wife as of working-class parentage. He advised
                    that he has a mother, two sisters and three brothers in the USSR, one of his
                    brothers being a Lieutenant Colonel in the Red Army. His wife has a mother,
                    brother and two sisters in the USSR. Both the Samarins were in infrequent
                    communication with their families.</p>
                <p>Samarin advised that he graduated from the Moscow Institute of Pedagogy in 1935.
                    He has been with the Ministry of Foreign Affairs as a teacher ever since except
                    for two years in the Red Army from which he was released in 1943 because of
                    wounds. He stated that he arrived in this country at Portland, Oregon, with his
                    wife, Klavdia, and daughter, Elena, on December 3, 1943, destined for the Soviet
                    Private School, Washington, D. C. He served there as instructor and director
                    until his arrival in New York City in July, 1946. At the Soviet Private School
                    in New York City he was instructor of mathematics and languages and was director
                    until replaced as director a short time ago by Konstantin G. Andrienko. However,
                    he continued on as a teacher.</p>
                <p>Samarin claimed that shortly after arriving in New York City, he decided, that if
                    possible, he would like to remain permanently in the United States. After being
                    ordered to return to the USSR on July 31, 1948, aboard the SS <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, he definitely decided to take steps in this direction.
                    Coincidently, on approximately July 25, or 26, 1948, while out walking with his
                    wife and twin children, who were born in the United States, he was approached by
                    a strange man and woman who admired the children, and with whom, with this
                    entree, he conversed in Russian. Samarin indicated that he was soon to return to
                    the USSR and the unnamed man suggested that this would not be necessary. Samarin
                    showed interest and the unnamed man offered to assist him in this direction. Two
                    more meetings were held between Samarin and the unnamed man on the same date. At
                    the final meeting Samarin was given the telephone number and address of the
                    Tolstoy Foundation, New York City, and told to contact them and mention the name
                    of one Pervuhov.<note n="20" xml:id="d669fn20">Not identifiable.</note> Samarin
                    was unable to state if this was the unknown man’s name, but believes not. He
                    made contact with Miss Tolstoy in New York City on July 29, 1948. She arranged
                    for a Mr. Shibanov to meet Samarin on July 30, 1948. At 11:00 PM, Shibanov
                    picked up Samarin and family in a truck and took them to his farm in Freehold,
                    New <pb facs="1051" n="1030" xml:id="pg_1030"/> Jersey. On July 31, 1948, they
                    were transferred to the farm of Mr. Kozak in the same vicinity, but described by
                    Shibanov as safer. Samarin’s family were at Kozak’s farm at the time of this
                    interview.</p>
                <p>Regarding his reason for his defection, Samarin stated he desired to rear his
                    children, including the twins born here, under the advantages available in the
                    United States; he feared constant surveillance if he returned to the USSR
                    because he was not a Communist Party member and had been in a foreign land for a
                    long period; he feared the possibility of war and was not convinced of the right
                    of the USSR cause. If there was a war, he foresaw an immediate draft and he did
                    not desire to readjust to the rigor of USSR life.</p>
                <p>Samarin stated that when he first contacted Miss Tolstoy she asked him if he knew
                    that another teacher was already at the Tolstoy Foundation. He advised that he
                    knew nothing whatsoever concerning the defection of Kasienkina until he heard
                    this. He advised that he has developed no information concerning Kasienkina’s
                    defection and has had no contact whatsoever with officials of the Soviet
                    Consulate since he left his home on July 30, 1948, with Shibanov. Samarin left
                    the <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> office at 5:20 PM, August 8, 1948,
                    accompanied by Kravchenko.</p>
                <p>. . . . . .</p>
                <p>The above is being furnished for your information only and is not to be
                    distributed outside of your Department. For your information, however, these
                    facts have also been made available to the Attorney General<note n="21" xml:id="d669fn21">Tom C. Clark.</note> and to the Immigration and
                    Naturalization Service.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
