<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Embassy of the Soviet Union to
                        the Department of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d671</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">671</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="671" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d671">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">311.6115/8–948</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Embassy of the Soviet Union</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 143</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">Translation</p>
                <p>The Embassy of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics presents its compliments
                    to the Department of State and has the honor to communicate the following:</p>
                <p>On July 31, 1948 the sudden disappearance of the Soviet citizens Oksana
                    Stepanovna Kasenkina, 51, a teacher by profession, and Mikhail Ivanovich
                    Samarin, 40, a teacher by profession, with his wife Klavdia Mikhailovna Samarina
                    and their children Tatiana, Elena, and Vladmir, was discovered. It must be
                    pointed out that all the aforesaid persons were ready to depart from the U.S.A.
                    for the Soviet Union on the steamship <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi> on July 31
                    and had all the necessary official documents and passage tickets. However, for
                    reasons unknown at that time, Kasenkina and Samarin with his family did not come
                    to the steamship <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi> at the moment of its departure,
                    nor were they in the apartments occupied by them as has been subsequently
                    ascertained.</p>
                <pb facs="1054" n="1033" xml:id="pg_1033"/>
                <p>On August 6 of this year Y. M. Lomakin, Consul General of the U.S.S.R. at New
                    York, received a letter from O. S. Kasenkina in which she implored him to snatch
                    her from the hands of the organization—the so-called “Tolstoy Fund”, to whose
                    farm the “Reed Farm,” Valley Cottage 4, she had been forcibly carried from her
                    apartment on July 31 of this year.</p>
                <p>On the following day the Consul General of the U.S.S.R. at New York went to the
                    address indicated by Kasenkina and, with his assistance, O. S. Kasenkina left
                    the farm. In this connection it should be noted that the heads of the
                    organization, A. L. Tolstaya and M. A. Knutson, attempted to detain Kasenkina by
                    force in spite of her categorical statement to them that she wished to leave
                    with the Consul General and did not want to remain at the farm.</p>
                <p>As O. S. Kasenkina has reported, the members of the organization, which is headed
                    by A. Tolstaya and M. Knutson, kept after her long before the day of her
                    departure for the Soviet Union, trying to induce her by intimidation and threats
                    not to return to her Fatherland. In this connection they did not even stop at
                    applying a narcotic injection with the obvious purpose of weakening her
                    consciousness and will. On the day of Kasenkina’s intended departure for the
                    Fatherland, members of this organization carried her away from her apartment to
                    the-farm mentioned above and forcibly kept her there. During Kasenkina’s stay on
                    the farm from July 31 to August 6, 1948, A. Tolstaya continued to intimidate
                    Kasenkina and demanded that she write slanderous articles against her
                    Fatherland, but Kasenkina rejected these base demands.</p>
                <p>According to available information, M. I. Samarin and his family were also
                    forcibly carried away from his apartment 3–B, 214 West 140th Street, New York,
                    to the Kessel farm in the State of New Jersey on the night of July 30–31 by
                    members of the same organization.</p>
                <p>As is evident from communications of the American press of August 9, M. I.
                    Samarin, after a week’s stay at the Kessel farm, was-turned over to the Federal
                    Bureau of Investigation by the organization headed by Tolstaya.</p>
                <p>The above-described cases of kidnaping of the Soviet citizens O. A. Kasenkina and
                    M. I. Sam’arin and his family, as well as a number of other cases in connection
                    with which the Embassy duly corresponded with the Department of State, bear
                    witness to the fact that the organization headed by Tolstaya is systematically
                    carrying on activities hostile to the Soviet Union, not stopping at the forcible
                    seizure of Soviet citizens with the acquiescence of certain government agencies
                    of the U.S.A., which must be well aware of the activities of the
                    organization—the so-called “Tolstoy Fund”. In this connection the statement of
                        <pb facs="1055" n="1034" xml:id="pg_1034"/> A. L. Tolstaya to
                    representatives of the press on August 8<note n="1" xml:id="d671fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, August 8, 1948, p. 48.</note> of this
                    year merits attention; from this statement it is clear that the so-called
                    “Tolstoy Fund” has at its disposal an “underground” organization, the activities
                    of which are directed toward preventing the return of Soviet citizens to their
                    Fatherland and which in such activities resorts to conspiratorial methods.</p>
                <p>The Embassy of the U.S.S.R. in the U.S.A. considers that the attitude of the
                    government agencies of the U.S.A. toward the above-mentioned criminal activities
                    of the so-called “Tolstoy Fund” constitutes a direct violation of the
                    obligations assumed by the Government of the U.S.A. on the basis of the exchange
                    of letters of November 16, 1933 between the People’s Commissar for Foreign
                    Affairs of the U.S.S.R., M. M. Litvinov, and the President of the U.S.A., F. D.
                        Roosevelt.<note n="2" xml:id="d671fn2">
                        <ref target="frus1933-39#pg_28">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Soviet Union, 1933–1939,
                            pp. 28</ref>–<ref target="frus1933-39#pg_29">29</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On instructions from the Soviet Government the Embassy of the U.S.S.R. in the
                    U.S.A. strongly protests the forcible seizure of the Soviet citizens O. S.
                    Kasenkina and M. I. Samarin and his family by members of the “Tolstoy Fund”
                    organization, as well as the toleration by government agencies of the U.S.A. of
                    the criminal activities of this organization, which are clearly directed against
                    the U.S.S.R. and which consist particularly in the prevention, by any forcible
                    means, of the return of Soviet citizens to their Fatherland and in attempts to
                    use them for purposes inimical to the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>The Embassy of the U.S.S.R. in the U.S.A. expects that measures will be taken by
                    the Government of the U.S.A. for the immediate release of M. I. Samarin and his
                    family and for their transfer to the protection of the Consulate General of the
                    U.S.S.R. at New York until their departure for the Fatherland and insists on the
                    discontinuation of activities of the so-called “Tolstoy Fund”, which are
                    incompatible with the obligations assumed by the Government of the U.S.A. with
                    respect to the Soviet Union.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-09">August 9,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
