<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-05-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="243" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d243">
                        <head>243. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d243fn1">Source: Department of State, Executive Secretariat,
                                Files of <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Alexander M. Haig,
                                    Jr.</persName>, 1981–1982, Lot 82D370, (3) Falklands Crisis
                                1982. Secret. All brackets are in the original. The meeting took
                                place at the Army-Navy Club. At the top of the memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_GSW_1">Goldberg</persName> wrote: “Import—the
                                message of unrest in B.A.” Also at the top of the memorandum, an
                                additional notation in an unknown hand reads: “Final version
                                5/12/82. <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> probably will send by
                                cable to B.A.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-05-08">May 8, 1982</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Carlos Guillermo</item>
                            <item>General Sanchez Mason, retired from Argentine Army</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AF_1">Francisco Aguirre</persName>,
                                Co-owner, <hi rend="italic">Diario de las Americas</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WVA_1">Walters</persName>,
                                Ambassador-at-Large</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Falkland Islands</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At the request of <persName corresp="#p_AF_1">Francisco
                                Aguirre</persName>, a co-owner of <hi rend="italic">Diario de las
                                Americas</hi> and perhaps the best informed man in Washington on
                            Latin American affairs, I met with retired Argentine General Sanchez
                            Mason at the Army Navy Club. Deputy Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BSW_1">Bosworth</persName> concurred that the meeting
                            should take place.</p>
                        <p>Sanchez Mason contended that former Argentine President and retired Army
                            General <persName corresp="#p_VRE_1">Viola</persName> sent him to alert
                            me that many Argentine officers, particularly Army officers, are
                            extremely disturbed by the Argentine occupation of the Falkland Islands
                            and the subsequent events.<note n="2" xml:id="d243fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_GSW_1">Goldberg</persName> drew a bracket in
                                the left-hand margin next to this sentence.</note> He explained that
                            he now works for MACK trucks and is using his business connection as a
                            pretext for his visit. Prior to his retirement, however, he was,
                            consecutively, in charge of suppression of the guerrillas, Commander of
                            the Fifth Corps (the forces used in the Falklands), Commander of the
                            Third Corps in Cordoba, Commander of the First Corps in Buenos Aires,
                            and Chief of Staff of the Army.</p>
                        <p>When <persName corresp="#p_AJI_1">Anaya</persName> was Chief of Navy
                            Planning, he developed plans for the occupation of the three Beagle
                            Islands and another for the Falklands; but <persName corresp="#p_VJR_1">Videla</persName><note n="3" xml:id="d243fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_GSW_1">Goldberg</persName> circled “<persName corresp="#p_VJR_1">Videla</persName>” and drew a line from the
                                circle to the bottom of the page where he wrote “<persName corresp="#p_VRE_1">Viola</persName>?”</note> rejected them in
                            1978 because of the damage either would have done to Argentine relations
                            with Great Britain and the U.S. When Admiral <persName corresp="#p_AJI_1">Anaya</persName> became head of the Navy, he
                            allied with <persName corresp="#p_GLF_1">Galtieri</persName> to oust
                                <persName corresp="#p_VRE_1">Viola</persName> from the Presidency.
                                (<persName corresp="#p_AJI_1">Anaya</persName> is the most
                            belligerent of the <pb facs="0553" n="506" xml:id="pg_506"/> three Junta
                            members, <persName corresp="#p_GLF_1">Galtieri</persName>, the most
                            excitable, and Lamidozo, the most thoughtful and moderate.) For some
                            reason, perhaps church pressure, <persName corresp="#p_AJI_1">Anaya</persName> then pressured <persName corresp="#p_GLF_1">Galtieri</persName> to support him in the seizure of the Falklands
                            as a repayment. Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_CMN_1">Costa
                                Mendez</persName> assured the military that (a) the Soviets would
                            veto any kind of anti-Argentine resolution in the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>, (b) that Argentina could rely on Soviet
                            assistance and (c) in any event, the British would not fight. He knew
                            the British and could guarantee they would not go to war over the
                            Falklands. [General Sanchez Mason added as an aside that <persName corresp="#p_CMN_1">Costa Mendez</persName> is the biggest liar in
                                Argentina.<note n="4" xml:id="d243fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_GSW_1">Goldberg</persName> underlined the
                                portion of the sentence beginning with “<persName corresp="#p_CMN_1">Costa Mendez</persName>” and ending with the word
                                “Argentina.”</note> Sanchez Mason knew the Foreign Minister
                            pretended to the U.S. that he knew nothing of the operation before it
                            happened.]</p>
                        <p>The original plan called for the occupation to occur in May, but the Navy
                            forced the issue early by sending Naval personnel ashore in South
                            Georgia disguised as civilian workers to dismantle the whaling station.
                            The British reaction coupled with domestic strife with the Peronistas
                            triggered the landing. Of the five corps commanders, only General Garcia
                            of the Fifth Corps knew of the operation well in advance. The others
                            were given only 48 hours notice. Troops moved under cover of exercises
                            and maneuvers. The corps commanders, who were kept in the dark, harbor a
                            certain amount of resentment.</p>
                        <p>Since the landing and occupation General <persName corresp="#p_GLF_1">Galtieri</persName> announced to a meeting of active and retired
                            generals of the Army, that he told Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> that Argentina, if backed to the
                            wall, would take help from any source, including the Soviet Union. This
                            greatly disturbed the generals. They now perceive the Junta, Sanchez
                            Mason explained, as having led Argentina into a foolish fight with old
                            friends in Great Britain and the United States over islands Argentina
                            would inevitably get anyway. Argentina is running the risk of destroying
                            the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> and endangering the ability of
                            the West to defend its values—values prized by the Argentine
                            military.</p>
                        <p>I asked him which officers felt this way. He cited General Vaquero, Chief
                            of Staff of the Army; General <persName corresp="#p_NC_1">Nicolaides</persName>, Commander of the First Corps in Buenos
                            Aires; General Trimarco, Commander of the Second Corps, and many junior
                            officers.</p>
                        <p>General Sanchez Mason stressed that he came to seek no assistance but
                            merely to ask for understanding “when something happens”. He feels that
                            the Argentine Junta will not negotiate under the present <pb facs="0554" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/> circumstances. They must be “knocked
                            around a little more”. He is convinced the British can do it. He also
                            pooh-poohed the claim that the U.S. gave the British information that
                            led to the sinking of the cruiser, <hi rend="italic">Belgrano</hi>,
                            saying that he had some knowledge of British intelligence—they were
                            quite capable of doing all these things by themselves. He felt that
                            after the Argentines had sustained a few more reverses, they might be
                            ripe for listening to something reasonable. He again hinted that he
                            hoped he would have our understanding if and when “something happened”.
                                <persName corresp="#p_VRE_1">Viola</persName> is anxious to keep the
                            U.S. advised of developments in Argentina. He had also been in touch in
                            Buenos Aires with Mr. Friedman and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1">Shlaudeman</persName>. The Navy got Argentina
                            into the mess; the Air Force has helped save the Navy’s face by sinking
                            the <hi rend="italic">Sheffield</hi>. The moderates plan to move after
                            the Junta sustains further reverses.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Aguirre, LCDR Martiny, General Sanchez Mason, Carlos Guillermo, and
                            myself were the only people present.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>