<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-05-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-05-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="277" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d277">
                        <head>277. Memorandum From the Special Assistant for Warning (<persName corresp="#p_CHC_1">Cochran</persName>e) to the Chairman of the
                            National Intelligence Council (<persName corresp="#p_RH_1">Rowen</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d277fn1">Source:
                                Central Intelligence Agency, National Intelligence Council, Job
                                83T00966R: Chronological Files (1982), Box 1, Folder 4: C/NIC
                                Chronological. Secret; [<hi rend="italic">handling restriction not
                                    declassified</hi>].</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <idno type="document-identifier">DDI #4242–81</idno>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-05-20">May 20, 1982</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Military Showdown in the Falklands: Alternative Outcomes</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>1. With the failure of Secretary General Perez de Cuellar’s mediation
                                efforts<note n="2" xml:id="d277fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_PDCJ_1">Pérez de Cuéllar</persName> informed
                                the Security Council President the evening of May 20 of the failure
                                of his negotiation efforts. For a summary of his efforts between
                                April 19 and May 20, see <hi rend="italic">Yearbook of the United
                                    Nations, 1982</hi>, pp. 1328–1329.</note> and with both Britain
                            and Argentina placing the blame for the impasse on each other, the
                            Falklands crisis will be settled by a test of military strength, skill
                            and resourcefulness and by a potentially more decisive trial of
                            political stamina in London and Buenos Aires. There are so many
                            variables in the balance of assets and liabilities—ranging from
                            unexpected changes in weather and sea conditions to the indeterminate
                            location of two Argentine attack submarines—that the outcome could be
                            determined as much by the random play of Murphy’s Law as by the
                            measurable military capabilities and political competence of the two
                            sides.</p>
                        <pb facs="0630" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/>
                        <p>2. Another possibly decisive but unpredictable determinant may be the
                            perceptions and psychological predispositions of the <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> government and the Argentine
                            junta. [<hi rend="italic">7 lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>3. Both governments have locked themselves into positions that cannot be
                            compromised without fatal domestic consequences. <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName>’s original calculation that
                            “diplomatic efforts are more likely to succeed if backed by military
                            strength” has been refuted by the junta’s performance during the past
                            eight weeks. The junta’s gamble that the U.S. or the United Nations
                            would somehow broker a compromise that would preserve at least a
                            reasonable prospect of vindicating Argentina’s claim to sovereignty over
                            the islands has <gloss target="#t_Backfire_1">backfired</gloss>. Now
                            that their mutual bluffs have been called, London and Buenos Aires are
                            left with an immensely risky roll of the iron dice.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Alternative Outcomes</p>
                        <p>A. <hi rend="italic">An unambiguous British military victory</hi>. The
                            British are counting on a prompt collapse of Argentine resistance
                            following initial engagements with the invasion force and on a surrender
                            of the Argentine garrison without substantial casualties. The failure of
                            Argentine forces on South Georgia and Pebble Islands to offer more than
                            token resistance will have encouraged the British to expect little
                            effective or prolonged opposition. At the outset, the British may elect
                            to avoid engaging the main body of Argentine forces in the Port Stanley
                            area by staging their initial landings in outlying areas such as Port
                            Darwin and Fox Bay. The British believe that the rapid defeat or
                            surrender of these outposts will demoralize the Port Stanley garrison
                            and soften it up for either quick defeat or surrender. [<hi rend="italic">9 lines not declassified</hi>] <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName>’s confidence in a quick and
                            relatively painless victory was reflected in her remark on 17 May that
                            if <persName corresp="#p_GLF_1">Galtieri</persName> does not make major
                            concessions, “We make him go.”<note n="3" xml:id="d277fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> made her statement
                                in a radio interview on May 17. (Glenn Frankel, “Britain, Argentina
                                Pessimistic About Peace Prospects,” <hi rend="italic">Washington
                                    Post</hi>, May 18, p. A1)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>B. <hi rend="italic">An inconclusive initial round of combat leading to a
                                war of attrition with heavy casualties on both sides</hi>.
                            Successful British landings will be countered by all-out retaliatory
                            strikes by the Argentine Air Force and Navy that will avert an early
                            demoralization and collapse of Argentine resistance on the ground. The
                            junta is determined to maintain resistance regardless of the costs in
                            lives and equipment, and it is gambling that a British failure to force
                            a prompt surrender and the shock of heavy losses of British personnel,
                            aircraft and ships will bring down the <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> government. The junta has persuaded itself that
                            Argentina can outlast the British in a costly and inconclusive war of
                            attrition, <pb facs="0631" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/> and that support
                            for <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName>’s policy will
                            evaporate quickly in these conditions, politically disarming Britain
                            from continuing the war.</p>
                        <p>C. <hi rend="italic">British landing operations will be defeated</hi> by
                            a combination of stiff resistance by the Argentine garrison and damaging
                            air and naval attacks on the British invasion force and fleet. <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> will be forced to resign and
                            her successor will have no choice but to order the evacuation of the
                            invasion force.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Argentine Political Initiatives</p>
                        <p>The Argentines will respond immediately to a British invasion by
                            announcing acceptance of Perez de Cuellar’s final proposal for a
                            compromise agreement. Following Britain’s expected rejection of this
                            proposal, Argentina will request a <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                            Security Council meeting at which it will propose, through Panama’s
                            delegate, an immediate and unconditional ceasefire in place without
                            provisions for a mutual withdrawal of forces. This move will be aimed at
                            forcing a British veto, supported by the U.S. The Argentines believe
                            these initiatives will place the onus squarely on Britain for a
                            continuation of hostilities and greatly strengthen Argentina’s position
                            in negotiations under the Secretary General’s aegis that will be
                            renewed. The junta also will calculate that British rejection of these
                            two “peace moves” will stimulate a backlash in British public opinion
                            and parliament that will bring <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> down, even if she is not forced out by heavy
                            British combat losses.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Weighing the Odds</p>
                        <p>The variables mentioned in paragraphs 1 and 2 preclude a confident
                            forecast, but a plausible case could be made that the most likely
                            outcome will be something that could be called a British military
                            success tempered by important Argentine political gains that may
                            eventually prove to be more significant than the military test of
                            strength. Even the military outcome may be considerably short of an
                            unambiguous British victory, and it may fall between the first and
                            second scenarios. The Argentines may well demonstrate an ability to deny
                            the British a prompt victory. If they can impose substantial losses on
                            the British invasion force, aircraft and warships, <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName>’s domestic political
                            vulnerability may prove to be greater than that of the junta. If the
                            encounter settles into a costly war of attrition, the junta may surprise
                            the world by showing greater staying power than the <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> government.</p>
                        <p>The third scenario—a British defeat and forced withdrawal—cannot be
                            completely ruled out. The greatest threat to British prospects would
                            seem to be overconfidence. [<hi rend="italic">4½ lines not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CHC_1"><hi rend="strong">Harry
                                    Cochran</hi></persName>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Special Assistant for Warning</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>