<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-06-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="359" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d359">
                        <head>359. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SBAF_1">Alfonso
                                Sapia-Bosch</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clark</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d359fn1">Source: Reagan Library, Executive Secretariat,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Country File, Latin
                                America/Central, Argentina (06/16/1982–06/30/1982). Confidential.
                                Sent for action. A stamped notation at the top of the memorandum
                                indicates that <persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clark</persName> saw
                                it.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-06-22">June 22, 1982</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Lifting Economic Sanctions on Argentina</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The sanctions on Argentina should be lifted without delay. As you know,
                            the European Community has already done so.<note n="2" xml:id="d359fn2">See <ref target="#d357">Document 357</ref>.</note> From the U.S.
                            perspective the sanctions are symbolic. The de facto ceasefire between
                            the two belligerents probably will hold, as there seems to be little
                            disposition on the part of Argentina again to take up arms. State’s
                            position is to use the sanctions issue to derive a larger gain from
                            Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName>, e.g.,
                            agreement to negotiate with Argentina over the final disposition of the
                            Islands. Additionally, State would like to deal with a functioning
                            government. Both of these are good points; State does not expect much
                            success with <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName>,
                            however.</p>
                        <pb facs="0783" n="736" xml:id="pg_736"/>
                        <p>If we lift the sanctions after her visit with the President it will be
                            viewed in Argentina and Latin America as if we needed her permission to
                            go ahead. Alternatively, if we act now we would give a signal that we
                            are taking a more neutral position on the sovereignty question. We will
                            eventually lift the sanctions, so our objective should be to derive the
                            most benefit for our side from the timing. By taking the initiative
                            immediately we would: reduce strains between the U.S. and Argentina;
                            strengthen the hand of the moderates in Argentina; assist the U.S.
                            banking community, thereby speeding up the restructuring of the
                            Argentine debt; perhaps bring some stability to the Argentine
                            government, whatever it turns out to be; prevent a further shift toward
                            anti-Americanism among the military; and, finally, remove sanctions as
                            an issue.</p>
                        <p>Lifting the sanctions is not without danger. Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> probably would not like it.
                            She could hardly suggest that we have been unsupportive, however. There
                            is always the danger that some Argentine leader will misinterpret our
                            action. Notwithstanding these problems, I urge that you suggest to the
                            President that the sanctions be lifted soon.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BDC_1">Blair</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FRW_1">Fontaine</persName> concur.<note n="3" xml:id="d359fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BDC_1">Blair</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FRW_1">Fontaine</persName> initialed their
                                concurrence by signing their initials over their typed names.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RJMT_1">Rentschler</persName> does not.<note n="4" xml:id="d359fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RJMT_1">Rentschler</persName> wrote “Jim”
                                above his typed name, indicating that he did not concur.</note> He
                            believes that cancellation of the original sanctions decision, a product
                            of inter-agency deliberations, is a significant step which needs to be
                            thoroughly addressed in existing inter-agency fora, preferably <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>, but perhaps in this case the <gloss target="#t_NSPG_1">NSPG</gloss>.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>