<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>85. Telegram From President Reagan to Secretary of State to Secretary of
                    State Haig</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1982-04-09T11:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1982-04-09T11:40:00-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-04-09T11:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-04-09T11:40:00-05:00" n="85" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                <head>85. Telegram From President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> to
                    Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d85fn1">Source: Reagan Library, Executive
                        Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Country File, Latin
                        America/Central, Falklands War [Cables 090131, 091000, 091154, 091640,
                        181715, 191650, 191754, 192115]. Top Secret. Sent for information to the
                        White House. Printed from a copy that was received in the White House
                        Situation Room. <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> was in
                        Barbados for meetings with the Prime Ministers of Barbados, Antigua and
                        Barbuda, Dominica, St. Christopher and Nevis, and St. Vincent and the
                        Grenadines. He had arrived in Barbados on April 8, following a brief
                        official visit to Jamaica. A notation in <persName corresp="#p_PJM_1">Poindexter</persName>’s handwriting in the top right-hand corner of the
                        telegram reads: “Judge— JP,” indicating that <persName corresp="#p_PJM_1">Poindexter</persName> forwarded the telegram to <persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clark</persName>. A stamped notation indicates that
                            <persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clark</persName> saw it.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bridgetown</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-04-09T16:40:00+00:00">April 9, 1982, 1640Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>10. Ref <gloss target="#t_Secto_1">Secto</gloss> 5010.<note n="2" xml:id="d85fn2">See <ref target="#d82">Document 82</ref>.</note> Subject: Your Discussions
                    in London.</p>
                <p>1. (TS) The report of your discussions in London makes clear how difficult it
                    will be to foster a compromise that gives Maggie enough to carry on and at the
                    same time meets the test of “equity” with our Latin neighbors. As you expected
                    there isn’t much room for maneuver in the British position. How much this
                    “going-in” position can be influenced is unclear although London headlines give
                    little basis for optimism. Point B looks to be the crux<note n="3" xml:id="d85fn3">See paragraph 8B of of <ref target="#d82">Document
                        82</ref>.</note> and I’d be interested in your further thinking on how a
                    multinational presence might be made more appealing in London. It’s my guess
                    from the diffident British stance that any compromise on <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName>’s part will take time. If that’s true
                    the closure of the British submarines is all the more worrisome. In this regard,
                    whether we can expect <persName corresp="#p_GLF_1">Galtieri</persName> to have
                    the wisdom and strength to keep his distance is obviously a central near-term
                    issue.</p>
                <p>2. (TS) On a separate subject, I was struck by reporting from Tel Aviv that
                        <persName corresp="#p_BM_1">Begin</persName> is moving Soviet tanks to the
                    northern border.<note n="4" xml:id="d85fn4">For documentation on U.S. responses
                        to the mounting crisis in Lebanon, see <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XVIII, Part 1, Lebanon, April
                        1981–August 1982.</note> Recognizing you have your hands full, I’d
                    appreciate your views on whether another intervention from us would be useful or
                    not.</p>
                <p>3. (TS) Here, we had useful sessions in Jamaica and Barbados.<note n="5" xml:id="d85fn5">For documentation relating to <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>’s discussions in Jamaica and Barbados, as well as
                        other documentation related to the Caribbean Basin Initiative, see <ref target="frus1981-88v17p1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XVII, Part 1,
                            Mexico; Western Caribbean</ref>, and <ref target="frus1981-88v17p2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XVII, Part 2,
                            Eastern Caribbean</ref>.</note> What struck me most was that while they
                    are interested in the contents of the <gloss target="#t_CBI_1">CBI</gloss>,
                    through it we have achieved the larger purpose of a breakthrough in U.S.
                    credibility in this part of the world. Their confidence that finally we care is
                    a fragile but terribly important achievement for which you should be very
                    proud.</p>
                <pb facs="0224" n="177" xml:id="pg_177"/>
                <p>4. (TS) On the press line you propose with respect to the Falklands, I agree. We
                    are saying nothing from here to color expectations.</p>
                <p>5. (TS) Al as you proceed to Buenos Aires, I’m very conscious of the enormity of
                    the task. I’d appreciate a call on the secure line when you have a chance to
                    discuss where things might lead in the days ahead.</p>
                <p>Warm regards.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
