<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Paper Prepared in the International Security Affairs Committee, Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recEmfen6T5wplQqD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Title II</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec8f8ab487d399bce" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="mutual-defense-assistance-act">Mutual Defense Assistance Act</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="15"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> Files: Lot 53 D 443: <gloss
                        target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> D–6</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Paper Prepared in the International Security Affairs
                        Committee, Department of State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d15fn1">A covering memorandum from <gloss target="#t_ISA1"
                            >ISA</gloss> Committee Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DRG1">Robert G.
                            Efteland</persName> stated that this paper was prepared in <gloss
                            target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> and was intended to serve as a basis for
                        discussion and judgment on the problems enumerated in the “Statement of
                        Considerations”. Appended to the source text, but neither printed, are, as
                        Tab A, a problem paper prepared in <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> on
                        increasing the Turkish military establishment, and, as Tab B, a memorandum
                        from the Ambassador to Greece transmitting a paper on expediting the
                        delivery of military equipment to Greece, Turkey, and Yugoslavia. Also
                        appended to the source text, as Tab C, is a copy of the letter from
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName> to Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>, with annex, dated
                        January 27, <ref target="#pg_21">p. 21</ref>. Pages 1–6 of this paper, not
                        printed, deal with the increase in the Turkish military establishment and
                        the delivery of military equipment to Greece, Turkey, and Yugoslavia during
                        1951.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> D–6</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-02-20">February 20,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Statement of Considerations Involved in a Discussion
                        Concerning the Feasibility of</hi>: (A) <hi rend="smallcaps">Increasing
                        Turkish Military Establishment</hi>; (B) <hi rend="smallcaps">Expediting
                        Delivery of Military Equipment to Greece, Turkey and Yugoslavia During
                        Calendar Year</hi> 1951; (C) <hi rend="smallcaps">Formulating Military
                        Assistance Programs for Israel and the Arab States</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">c. israel and the arab states, including egypt and
                        libya</hi> (Supporting Data–Tab C)<note n="2" xml:id="d15fn2">Not printed;
                        see footnote 1 above.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Background:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department of State has recommended that more affirmative U.S. action is
                    required to safeguard our vital security interests in the Middle East. In the
                    Department’s view the need for such action is made urgent by the political
                    deterioration which has taken place in the area. In order to clarify some of the
                    issues involved, the views of the Department of Defense have been requested on
                    the following proposals:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“1. That the United States make it clear to all of the countries of the
                        Middle East that the United States in coordination with the United Kingdom
                        is prepared to assist them in strengthening their capabilities to defend the
                        area as a whole against aggression.</p>
                    <p>“2. That the United States furnish small training missions and individual
                        service technicians to the Arab States and Israel to assist them in the
                        development of fighting groups and techniques which are best suited to local
                        capabilities and terrain and to the defense of the Middle East as a
                        whole.</p>
                    <p>“3. That the number of Arab and Israeli trainees in the United States
                        military schools be increased.</p>
                    <pb facs="0121" n="81" xml:id="pg_81"/>
                    <p>“4. That the United States furnish, in conjunction with the training in
                        paragraph 2, token quantities of arms and ammunition (of the order of
                        magnitude of $5–10 million) to the Arab States and Israel on a cash
                        reimbursable basis, making it very clear that greater quantities cannot be
                        made available for another 12–18 months.</p>
                    <p>“These token quantities could be diverted from the programs for Greece,
                        Turkey and Iran by delaying deliveries to these countries: if such a course
                        is absolutely necessary, we believe on political grounds that the diversion
                        should be made.</p>
                    <p>“5. That the United States discuss with the United Kingdom the establishment
                        in the Middle East of a combined military mission, or establishment of a
                        separate United States military mission for the purposes of: <list>
                            <item>“<hi rend="italic">a</hi>. stimulating and coordinating the
                                military efforts of all of the Middle East countries for the defense
                                of the Middle East as a whole;</item>
                            <item>“<hi rend="italic">b</hi>. creating stability in depth in the Arab
                                States and Israel so as to enable Greece, Turkey and Iran to make
                                the most effective use of the fighting power we are developing
                                there;</item>
                            <item>“<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. coordinating in terms of the concept of
                                area defense the activities of the United States and United Kingdom
                                military missions in the individual countries; and</item>
                            <item>“<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. stimulating and coordinating, with
                                appropriate backstopping in Washington and London, United States and
                                United Kingdom planning to make the maximum effective use of
                                available resources for the defense of the area.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <p>As the result of subsequent conversations in the Department of Defense, the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff informally have transmitted their views with respect to the
                    Middle East as follows:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Political and military conditions in <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> are
                        of such significance to the security interest of the Western nations that
                        provision should be made for grant aid to the other countries comprising the
                            <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> area. Firm programs of assistance for
                        these countries cannot be developed at the present time but it is highly
                        desirable that a contingency fund be provided that will permit immediate
                        military assistance to the <hi rend="italic">ground</hi> forces of these
                        countries if such need for assistance becomes urgent.</p>
                    <p>“Accordingly legislation should be sought which will provide a <hi
                            rend="italic">contingency fund</hi> that will permit additional <hi
                            rend="italic">grant</hi> military assistance in the amount of
                        $50,000,000 to countries in the <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> area.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recognized that, politically, the situation in the Arab States and Israel
                    has deteriorated in recent months. That steps should be taken to counter this
                    trend is also recognized. Partially to accomplish this end, an economic
                    assistance program is planned for the area and a program of reimbursable
                    military assistance to the extent of five to ten million dollars has been
                    recommended by the Department of <pb facs="0122" n="82" xml:id="pg_82"/> State.
                    However, the form in which this assistance should be provided is a question
                    which remains to be resolved.</p>
                <p>One method which is within the framework of present legislative authority would
                    provide military equipment on a cash reimbursable basis under Section 408(<hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Mutual Defense Assistance Act as amended. In
                    order to provide such assistance a determination would have to be made that each
                    country in the area “whose ability to defend itself or to participate in the
                    defense of the area of which it is a part is important to the security of the
                    United States”. Assuming that such determinations are made, the countries in
                    question could then request procurement assistance from the United States for
                    the required equipment for which they would agree to pay. Negotiations for such
                    an agreement with Saudi Arabia, which has been declared eligible under this Act,
                    are now under way.<note n="3" xml:id="d15fn3">For documentation on these
                        negotiations, see <ref target="#pg_1017">pp. 1017</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Another method, which would require new legislative authority, would involve a
                    series of grant aid programs for the countries in the area. Under this method
                    surveys would have to be made to determine equipment deficiencies, assumptions
                    would have to be made that the recipient countries were unable to pay for the
                    needed equipment and complete justifications would have to be provided for the
                    appropriations requested for this purpose.</p>
                <p>Still another method, also involving the steps described in the previous
                    paragraph, would be the creation of a contingency fund within the appropriation
                    provided for Title II countries (Greece, Turkey and Iran) which could be used in
                    the general area upon a determination by the President that the use of the funds
                    in the country or countries in question would be important to the security of
                    the United States. This latter method probably would provide more flexibility in
                    channeling equipment into the countries where maximum benefits would accrue.</p>
                <p>If deliveries of equipment can be limited to small quantities they probably would
                    not interfere to any greater extent with the programs under way in countries of
                    higher strategic importance unless given a high priority. However, if major
                    quantities of equipment are to be involved and if deliveries of that equipment
                    are to be expedited in order to achieve our objectives in the area, the programs
                    will have to be worked out against a background of all other <gloss
                        target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss> countries. It is inconsistent, for instance, to
                    suggest that there be a build up of strength in Greece and Turkey as in problems
                    A and B above, and at the same time to embark upon a program of military
                    assistance for the Arab States and Israel by diverting equipment from Greece and
                    Turkey as has been suggested as a possibility.</p>
                <pb facs="0123" n="83" xml:id="pg_83"/>
                <p>Present availabilities of military equipment are strictly limited and the demands
                    upon U.S. productive capacity are of such magnitude that deliveries of
                    presently-programmed equipment for <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>
                    countries will be long delayed for certain types of matériel. The only result
                    which can come from adding new recipients will be to further aggravate an
                    already difficult position unless production of the needed items is stepped up
                    substantially. Therefore, a great deal of study must be given to questions
                    involving the relative importance of the Middle East, <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>, and the Far East; the types and quantities of equipment that
                    would have to be provided to the Arab States and Israel in order to accomplish
                    our objectives; and whether or not assistance in the form of military equipment
                    is a necessary method to accomplish those objectives.</p>
                <p>Also, study will have to be given to possible developments between the Arab
                    States and Israel if military equipment to increase their war potential is
                    provided.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> should determine if the security
                    interests of the U.S. require military assistance programs for the Arab States
                    and Israel.</p>
                <p>2. If military assistance programs are to be instituted for the Arab States and
                    Israel, the Department of Defense should recommend to <gloss target="#t_ISAC1"
                        >ISAC</gloss> specific country programs in terms of quantities and types of
                    equipment.</p>
                <p>3. If military assistance programs are to be instituted for the Arab States and
                    Israel, <gloss target="#t_ISAC1">ISAC</gloss> should determine whether such
                    assistance should be provided on a reimbursable basis, on a grant basis with a
                    specific program for each country, or on a “contingency fund” basis.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
