<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-09-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="160" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d160">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference Files: Lot 59 D 95: “Wash
                                For <gloss target="#t_Min1">Min</gloss> Mtg—Position Papers”</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Agreed United States–United Kingdom
                                    Paper</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d160fn1">See editorial note, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-09-08">September 8,
                                        1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">The Sudan</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In discussing the defence problem the Conference took particular
                                account of Conclusion (H) of the Joint Appreciation prepared by <pb facs="0424" n="384" xml:id="pg_384"/> the United Kingdom and the
                                United States Ambassadors at Alexandria<note n="2" xml:id="d160fn2">Reference is to an undated 19-page Joint Intelligence Estimate
                                    agreed to by the American and British Embassies in Cairo, not
                                    printed. Two copies of this document were transmitted to the
                                    Department of State by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> in despatch 505 from Cairo, August 28,
                                    and are in Department file 641.74/8–2851.</note> to the
                                effect</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“no Egyptian Government would be ready to enter into a defence
                                    agreement without a simultaneous settlement of the Sudan
                                    question”.</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>The Conference also took account of the consequential recommendations
                                No. IV, V and VI of the Joint Appreciation as follows: <list>
                                    <label>IV.</label>
                                    <item>Renewed consideration should be given to the possibility
                                        of according public recognition to the legal and
                                        constitutional status of the Egyptian Crown in regard to the
                                        Sudan.</item>
                                    <label>V.</label>
                                    <item>An early date should be fixed for the attainment of
                                        self-government by the Sudan and the principle of
                                        self-determination for the Sudanese should be
                                        maintained.</item>
                                    <label>VI.</label>
                                    <item>Further thought should be given to the possibility of an
                                        international guarantee of an Egypto-Sudanese Nile Waters
                                        agreement.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>The United Kingdom representative pointed out that it was the
                                considered view of the Governor General of the Sudan that the
                                Sudanese make no distinction between the public recognition of the
                                legal and constitutional status of the Egyptian Crown in regard to
                                the Sudan and recognition of Egyptian sovereignty implying the
                                establishment of Egyptian rule. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRJ1">Bowker</persName> went on to say that for this reason he
                                thought it must be accepted as a fact that to attempt now to make
                                some public recognition of the legal and constitutional status of
                                the Egyptian Crown in regard to the Sudan would cause grave
                                disturbances in the Sudan and was impracticable.</p>
                            <p>The Conference took note of this view but felt that some move with
                                regard to the Sudan is an essential element in the success of
                                proposals about the Command.<note n="3" xml:id="d160fn3">Reference
                                    is to the Middle East Command.</note> They therefore considered
                                what other steps could be taken to try to meet Egyptian aspirations
                                over the Sudan. It was pointed out that apart from Egypt’s wish for
                                purposes of prestige to establish a constitutional link between
                                Egypt and the Sudan her main preoccupation was the fear that the
                                British were trying to use their position in the Sudan to insure
                                that the Sudan should ultimately be separated from Egypt and to
                                exercise their influence with the Sudanese to that effect. It was
                                agreed that the line which might be best presented as offering
                                satisfactory safeguards to Egypt in this respect was to suggest the
                                appointment of a United Nations or other international commission,
                                on which Egypt would be represented, whose functions would be to
                                keep a watch on constitutional developments in the Sudan and make
                                recommendations on the manner <pb facs="0425" n="385" xml:id="pg_385"/> in which the Sudanese should ultimately choose
                                their international status. The commission would be charged
                                specifically with the task of watching the interests both of the
                                Sudanese and Egyptians. It was thought that such a suggestion would
                                at the same time provide the Egyptians with the means of ensuring
                                that their own essential interests were not prejudiced during the
                                final stages of the Sudan’s constitutional development and also
                                provide Egypt with an acceptable way of relaxing her present
                                insistence on immediate public recognition of the constitutional
                                position of the Egyptian Crown in regard to the Sudan.</p>
                            <p>It was recommended that this suggestion should be accompanied by a
                                reiteration of the United Kingdom’s readiness to consider a
                                statement of agreed principles in regard to the Sudan on the lines
                                already put forward in the United Kingdom Ambassador’s recent talks
                                with the Egyptian Foreign Minister and to consider some form of
                                international guarantee of an Egypto-Sudanese Nile Waters Agreement
                                on the lines of Recommendation VI of the Joint Appreciation. This
                                might possibly be associated with the formulation of a Nile Valley
                                development authority for which the International Bank might if
                                necessary be asked to provide some financial assistance.</p>
                            <p>The Conference thought that there would be a considerable advantage
                                in aiming at the possibility of fixing an early date for the
                                attainment of self-government by the Sudan.</p>
                            <p>The Conference thought that the Egyptians would put themselves in a
                                weak position in regard to international opinion if they were to
                                refuse proposals of this kind and, that provided the new approach on
                                the defence issue were presented in a sufficiently attractive form,
                                there was reason to hope that the Egyptians would hesitate to risk a
                                complete deadlock owing to their attitude over the Sudan.</p>
                            <p>It was agreed that consideration would be given to any possible
                                further steps which might go some way towards meeting the Egyptian
                                position on the Sudan with the objective of eliminating it as an
                                obstacle to agreement on the defence issue e.g. perhaps the
                                appointment of a “neutral” Governor General.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>