<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-17T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-17T15:00:00-05:00" n="176" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">641.74/10–1751: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Egypt</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d176fn1">Repeated to London, Paris for
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MDII1">MacArthur</persName>, and
                                    Ankara.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                                    </gloss>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-17T22:00:00+02:00">October 17, 1951—10 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>507. The Brit <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> showed me this
                                morning reports from Suez about disturbances there yesterday and the
                                consequent measures taken by the Brit mil auths. The mil were forced
                                to fire on mob at Ismailia attacking Brit dependents and killed five
                                persons. At Port Said the <pb facs="0446" n="406" xml:id="pg_406"/>
                                Egypt police coop successfully in restoring order. (The Egypt Govt
                                seems desirous of playing down this action because in communiqué
                                they issued last night they mentioned that five persons were killed
                                but did not state that the Brit had done it.) There were cases of
                                looting Brit houses, burning Brit autos, etc. As the situation
                                seemed to be getting out of hand the Brit established roadblocks at
                                all entrances and exits of the canal zone. Brit <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> asked London for auth in case of
                                extreme necessity to cut the Cairo oil pipeline. Suez mil were
                                asking for reinforcements.</p>
                            <p>The Brit <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> sent a note this morning
                                inviting the attn of the Egyptian Govt to this situation.</p>
                            <p>There were also cases of difficulties with Egyptian laborers employed
                                at the base and deliveries of food supplies have been
                                interrupted.</p>
                            <p>The Brit <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> sent report on all this
                                to London and requested it be passed to State Dept.</p>
                            <p>The Brit <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> showed me a tel from
                                Wash inquiring as to measures contemplated in case of danger to Brit
                                and Amer lives. In conjunction with Brit mil Brit <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> has almost completed a
                                comprehensive report on this which if approved at London will be
                                transmitted to the State Dept. There are 27,000 Brit subjects in
                                Egypt.</p>
                            <p>Brit <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> sent this morning another
                                note to Egypt <gloss target="#t_MinFonAff1">MinFonAff</gloss>
                                protesting against anti-Brit articles appearing in extremist press
                                and against sermons preached in a number of mosques last Friday that
                                it was no crime to kill a Brit subj.</p>
                            <p>As Dept is aware the hostility to the US prevailing two years ago had
                                diminished very considerably. Of course, recent events have made us
                                again a full target for Egypt popular and press animosity. The govt
                                however up to now has been playing sharply down attempts to
                                bespatter US and officials, and the King especially have gone out of
                                their way in the past few days to show public sympathy with this
                                Emb. Of course we will avoid any attempt to drive wedge between
                                us.</p>
                            <p>The French and Turk <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>s returned to
                                Cairo yesterday, I return today and Brit tomorrow.</p>
                            <p>The 16th Parachute Brigade is arriving this evening in Suez.<note n="2" xml:id="d176fn2">In telegram 510 from Cairo, October 18,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> stated that
                                    while he believed the British “went beyond what was strictly
                                    necessary” in putting down disturbances in the canal zone,
                                    “their action has had a very salutary effect. If they had shown
                                    any disposition to give ground current situation throughout
                                    Egypt might well have become critical.” <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> added that he would,
                                    however, “take occasion to tell <persName corresp="#p_SRC1">Stevenson</persName> that I hope he will keep a close eye
                                    on his military and see that they do nothing which might worsen
                                    situation, as animosity against Brit has been considerably
                                    increased by happenings on the 16th October.” (641.74/10–1851)
                                    In telegram 516 from Cairo, October 18, <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> repeated that British
                                    actions had “had very salutary effect in Egypt” and added that
                                    American business representatives at Suez confirmed that British
                                    forces had taken “practical charge of canal zone” including the
                                    Sinai bridge thus cutting Egyptian communications with military
                                    forces in Gaza (641.74/10–1851).</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>