<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Egypt ( (Caffery) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-24T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-24T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-24T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-24T14:00:00-05:00" n="179"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">641.74/10–2451: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Egypt</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJ1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d179fn1">Repeated to London, to Paris for <persName
                            corresp="#p_MDII1">MacArthur</persName>, and to Ankara.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-24T21:00:00+02:00"
                            >October 24, 1951—9 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>565. Mytel 557, October 24.<note n="2" xml:id="d179fn2">Not printed; it read:
                        “King has sent me word he desires to see me urgently today. I am flying to
                        Alexandria.” (641.74/10–2451)</note> The King said he desired to talk first
                    about cutting off of fuel oil by Brit commanding general. He narrated in great
                    detail all the dire consequences, including eventually revolution, that would
                    entail. I was able to tell him that shipments had recommenced this morning. He
                    went on to criticize with some vehemence the activities in general of Brit
                    military in Canal Zone. I apprehend that he has lost most of his friendly
                    feeling for Brit. He said that they were making it impossible for him or any
                    Egypt Govt ever to accept a satisfactory solution of either defense problem or
                    Sudan question. He again lamented fact that proposals were put forward at so
                    inopportune a moment. He indicated that we and only we would ever be in a
                    position to help find reasonable solutions. He urged us not to do anything on
                    our side to worsen the situation. He then said, “I shall tell you and you only a
                    few secrets that even my govt do not know. First, they think that the <gloss
                        target="#t_Min1">Min</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_FonAff1">FonAff</gloss> will head the delegation at Paris<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d179fn3">Reference was to the forthcoming Sixth Session of the
                        United Nations General Assembly which met at Paris between November 6, 1951,
                        and February 5, 1952.</note> but I have decided that he would do no good
                    there and I shall send <persName corresp="#p_FBM1">Fawzi Bey</persName>. Second,
                    if Brit attempt remove my troops out of the Canal Zone I shall order them to
                    resist to the last man. Third, I had a spy a night or two ago at an Ikwan mtg
                    when oaths were taken to kill 13 men; I was first on the list and <persName
                        corresp="#p_ENPM1">Nahas</persName> second.</p>
                <p>He went on to say that he is extremely pessimistic about the way things are
                    going: “It looks like we are headed for real trouble from which only the Commies
                    would profit.”</p>
                <p>I told him he should understand that Brit military authorities in Canal Zone are
                    having a tough time and that they are justified in going even beyond the
                    strictly necessary in order to defend their position; but I agreed they should
                    do nothing provocative or uselessly irritating.</p>
                <p>I reminded him how frivolously his govt handled our proposals and that their only
                    endeavor was to have a domestic political triumph. He agreed.</p>
                <p>I believe it is clear he would still like Egypt to take part in an Eastern Medit
                    set-up but in face of inflamed and inflammatory sentiment and passions here he
                    is not optimistic about near future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
