<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="232" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d232">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">Athens Embassy Files: Lot 59 F 48:
                                    “Top Secret 49–57”</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador in Greece</hi>
                                        (<persName corresp="#p_PJE1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Peurifoy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                        Chief of the United States Joint Military Air Group in
                                        Greece</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FR2" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Frederick</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d232fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_YCW1">Yost</persName>.</note>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    </seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-24">August 24,
                                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>I should appreciate it if, in order to assist in supporting the
                                    American objective of maintaining political stability in Greece
                                    during and immediately after the forthcoming elections, you
                                    could take the following steps in relation to the Greek armed
                                    forces: <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>Take an early opportunity to point out to General
                                                <persName corresp="#p_GLT1">Grigoropoulos</persName>
                                            and General <persName corresp="#p_TLT1">Tsakalotos</persName>, particularly the latter, as
                                            I have pointed out to the King and the Prime
                                                Minister,<note n="2" xml:id="d232fn2">See telegram
                                                890 from Athens, August 22, <ref target="#pg_498">p.
                                                  498</ref>, and telegram 919, August 24, from
                                                Athens, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> the
                                            concern with which we regard measures calculated to
                                            influence the attitude of the armed forces and their
                                            leaders in the elections. You should emphasize the very
                                            unfortunate impression which would be created in the
                                            United States and elsewhere by any attempt to prevent
                                            the soldiers from voting by holding maneuvers or
                                            training on or about election day or by any other device
                                            of this kind. In this connection you might refer to the
                                            unfortunate effect created by General <persName corresp="#p_TLT1">Tsakalotos</persName>’ memorandum
                                            published in <hi rend="italic">Athenaiki</hi>, which
                                            gave the misleading impression that he and other
                                            generals opposed voting by the Army in the present
                                            election, whereas it is your understanding that their
                                            recommendation <pb facs="0542" n="502" xml:id="pg_502"/>
                                            referred only to future elections. In view of the
                                            misunderstanding created by General <persName corresp="#p_TLT1">Tsakalotos</persName>’ memorandum,
                                            it would be desirable that a circular be sent by the
                                            General Staff to all corps and division commanders
                                            instructing them to see to it that the soldiers are in
                                            no way prevented from voting.</item>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>You may also wish to point out to General <persName corresp="#p_GLT1">Grigoropoulos</persName> and
                                                <persName corresp="#p_TLT1">Tsakalotos</persName>
                                            that, while the ostensible purpose of the measures taken
                                            by General <persName corresp="#p_TLT1">Tsakalotos</persName> during recent weeks has been
                                            to remove or neutralize political influences in the
                                            Army, the actual effect has been to create the
                                            widespread impression that the High Command has been
                                            using its position to oppose and defeat one of the
                                            political parties. Such activities cannot help but
                                            jeopardize the morale and unity of the armed forces at a
                                            time when it is of the utmost importance that they be
                                            maintained at their highest pitch.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>Having made these points to Generals <persName corresp="#p_GLT1">Grigoropoulos</persName> and
                                                <persName corresp="#p_TLT1">Tsakalotos</persName>, I
                                            believe you should take every possible precaution to see
                                            to it that these recommendations are not ignored.
                                            Specifically, you and your staff should be alert to
                                            observe and, if possible, forestall any sanctions
                                            against any of the officers whose views on soldier
                                            voting and related matters differed from those of
                                            General <persName corresp="#p_TLT1">Tsakalotos</persName>. Most important of all, I
                                            hope that your officers in the field will watch for and
                                            report immediately to you any indications that
                                            substantial units of the Army are, through one device or
                                            another, about to be deprived of the possibility of
                                            voting, and that they will, insofar as possible, observe
                                            the actual situation on election day.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>