<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative on the Palestine Conciliation Commission (
                    (Palmer) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d451</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">451</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-08-03T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-08-03T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-03T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-03T06:00:00-05:00" n="451"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d451">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">357.AC/8–351: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative on the Palestine Conciliation
                        Commission</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PEE1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Palmer</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-03T12:00:00+01:00"
                            >August 3, 1951—noon.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>109. <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 422. <gloss target="#t_USDel1"
                        >USDel</gloss> has today, Aug 2, concluded discussions with Fr reps
                        <persName corresp="#p_ML2">Marchal</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BCB1">Boisanger</persName> and principal secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_AP1">Azcarate</persName> of Dept’s proposal for new efforts by
                        <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>. We are happy report there is full
                    measure agreement that Dept’s proposals are timely and necessary if <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> is to make contribution to solving any
                    Palestine problems or to contribute to stability in present uneasy situation
                        <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss>. All are agreed present air of great
                    expectation in area can be capitalized on by prompt effort of this kind and hope
                    our three govts can coordinate promptly their dipl support for comm’s action. Fr
                    reps have raised two questions concerning mtg place and Brit attitude on which
                    Dept’s guidance wld be most helpful.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <item>Fr feel it will be difficult persuade Arab govts to participate in mtgs
                        held Istanbul. <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Boisanger</persName> has pointed
                        out that in recent conversation with Atassi, Syrian <gloss target="#t_Amb1"
                            >Amb</gloss> Paris, Atassi spoke out against Turk initiative in area.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Boisanger</persName> also recalled that when
                            <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> proposed mtgs last year, <persName
                            corresp="#p_AM1">Abdul Monem</persName> Egypt rep, stated flatly
                        Egyptians wld never meet in Turkey. <persName corresp="#p_BCB1"
                            >Boisanger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_ML2">Marchal</persName>
                        regard Egypt as key to Arab acceptance. Fr reps, having talked with <gloss
                            target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss>, have therefore proposed Paris as
                        best mtg place. They feel that higher representation can be expected if
                        Paris is chosen and that in even conference continued beyond Nov 6 no
                        disruption of mtgs wld occur.<note n="1" xml:id="d451fn1">This is a
                            reference to the projected convening of the Sixth Regular Session of the
                            General Assembly of the United Nations at Paris on November 6,
                            1951.</note> They also feel it most important that in course of
                        conference close contact shld be maintained with Brit Govt and favor Paris
                        for this reason. They feel Dept’s other suggested mtg places wld create
                        communication difficulties for themselves as well as for Arab dels. Today
                            <persName corresp="#p_ML2">Marchal</persName> reported that preliminary
                        telephone conversations with Paris indicated <gloss target="#t_FonOff1"
                            >FonOff</gloss> was agreeable both to substance Dept’s proposals and to
                        Paris as mtg place. <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Boisanger</persName> has
                        returned to Paris for further consultation and <persName corresp="#p_ML2"
                            >Marchal</persName> will follow him on Saturday. <gloss
                            target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> will meet at Quai d’ Orsay with Fr reps
                        on Tuesday to learn <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> final
                        decision.</item>
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <item>Prior to this time Fr reps hope for clarification of Brit attitude toward
                        Dept’s proposals. They believe Brit opinion will greatly influence <gloss
                            target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> decision, and expect Fr. <gloss
                            target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> London to make immediate inquiries there.
                        In order have full info for our conversations with Fr <gloss
                            target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss>, we hope Dept can inform <gloss
                            target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> both Geneva and Paris by Monday
                        afternoon re Brit reaction.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Pending Fr <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> decision, Fr and <gloss
                        target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>s have agreed on draft of invitation to be
                    telegraphed govts concerned, which it is hoped, can <pb facs="0857" n="817"
                        xml:id="pg_817"/> be sent by Aug 10. Accordingly suggested date for
                    convening conference has been set at Sept 10. We have suggested to Fr reps and
                    will suggest to <persName corresp="#p_ATR1">Aras</persName> on arrival that comm
                    not reconvene in Jerusalem prior to receipt of parties’ acceptance or rejection
                    our invitation in order avoid comms being involved in discussions with local
                    auths of its proposals. <persName corresp="#p_ML2">Marchal</persName> had hoped
                    make immediate tour of area in order acquaint himself with area and
                    personalities, but has agreed postpone trip until immed after receipt of
                    parties’ final answers. He will not engage at that time, however, in discussion
                    of business of proposed conference. FrReps recognize necessity for <gloss
                        target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss>s of three govts represented on <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> to undertake gain parties acceptance.</p>
                <p>Emb Ankara has informed <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ATR1">Aras</persName> arrives Geneva tomorrow third. We
                    have scheduled mtg for immed after his arrival and will report promptly his
                    reaction.</p>
                <p>Fol is text proposed invitation as agreed with FrReps subj <persName
                        corresp="#p_ATR1">Aras</persName>’ approval:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“I have the honor to inform you that the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>, mtg in special session in Geneva, has
                        decided to invite the govts of Egypt, Jordan, Lebanon and Syria and the Govt
                        of Israel to participate in mtgs with the comm to discuss solutions to the
                        problems outstanding between Israel and the Arab states.</p>
                    <p>“During the period fol the adoption by the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1"
                            >UNGA</gloss> of its res of 14 Dec 1950, the <gloss target="#t_PCC1"
                            >PCC</gloss> has continued to seek solutions for problems arising out of
                        the Palestine situation. In accordance with the res, the comm created its
                        refugee office for the purpose of making practical arrangements for the
                        solution of the refugee problem. The comm is ready to make a new effort to
                        lend assistance to the parties in seeking solution of this and other
                        questions outstanding between them. In the course of the proposed
                        discussions, the comm will be prepared to exercise its mediatory functions
                        by suggesting specific solutions to specific problems for consideration by
                        the parties.</p>
                    <p>“The comm invites the govt of (blank blank) to participate in these mtgs and
                        to designate its reps. It is proposed that the conference be held in Paris
                        beginning on 10 Sept 1951, and it is hoped that it will be possible for the
                        comm to report the results of the conference to the next regular session of
                        the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>, 6 Nov, 1951.”<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d451fn2">In <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 423, August
                            3, identified also as telegram 115 from Geneva, not printed, Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_PEE1">Palmer</persName> stated in part that
                                <persName corresp="#p_ATR1">Aras</persName> had agreed in principle
                            with the Department’s proposal and draft letter of invitation
                            (357.AC/8–351).</note>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PEE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Palmer</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
