<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-27T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-27T11:00:00-05:00" n="521" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d521">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">357.AC/10–2751: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative on the Palestine
                                    Conciliation Commission</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PEE1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Palmer</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d521fn1">Repeated for information to
                                    London, Ankara, Cairo, Tel Aviv, Damascus, Beirut, Amman, and
                                    Jerusalem.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-27T17:00:00+01:00">October 27, 1951—5 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2477. <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 461. <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> met with Israel del afternoon 26.
                                Mtg opened with long statement by <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fischer</persName> reviewing present situation with respect to
                                conference. <hi rend="italic">Inter alia</hi>
                                <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fischer</persName> stated that by <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>’s “accepting Arab States refusal to
                                affirm the validity of the principles of the charter and decisions
                                of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, an organ of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> had declared itself satisfied with
                                Arab declaration which showed intention to pursue acts hostile to
                                Israel in violation of armistice conventions, treaties and
                                decisions.” Arab refusal subscribe to declaration originally
                                demanded by comm implied Arabs “refusal to negotiate, in as much as
                                no one could participate in negots having as their objective finding
                                of solutions for outstanding problems if in beginning they put in
                                doubt those questions already settled.”</p>
                            <p>Del of Israel hoped comm wld pursue its efforts obtain from Arab dels
                                “explicit recognition of their obligations under armistice
                                agreements and charter of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> …<note n="2" xml:id="d521fn2">All ellipses in the source text.</note>
                                conference called by comm was by nature negot between Israel and
                                Arab States. Such negots directed through comm were conditional upon
                                explicit recognition of Arab States of internatl engagements to
                                which they had subscribed … these negots cld not be continued until
                                Arab States substituted for their <pb facs="0961" n="921" xml:id="pg_921"/> declaration of 3 October an affirmation of
                                their intention to respect their obligations vis-à-vis Israel both
                                as signatories of armistice agreements as interpreted by <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> and as members of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.”</p>
                            <p>“Israel del reaffirmed its desire to collaborate with comm and was
                                ready to examine with comm any question which cld be subj of
                                discussion between Israel del and comm as an organ of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, it being understood that any
                                question implying negots direct or indirect with Arab States must be
                                postponed until Arab States had unequivocally subscribed to
                                armistice agreements, the decisions of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> and provisions of charter of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.”</p>
                            <p>As chairman I stated that observations of Israel del wld be studied
                                carefully by comm but that comm believed at same time Israel del wld
                                find it helpful receive same explanation of comms proposals as had
                                been communicated to Arab dels on Wednesday. <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fischer</persName> replied that he was prepared
                                to hear comms statement and wld transmit it to his govt. I then read
                                statement previously communicated to Arab dels (<gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 460).<note n="3" xml:id="d521fn3">
                                    <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 460, identified also as
                                    telegram 2396 from Paris, October 24, not printed, contained the
                                    text of a statement which the Palestine Conciliation Commission
                                    submitted on October 24 to the Arab delegations at the
                                    conference in Paris in further explanation of the five points
                                    constituting the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>’s
                                    comprehensive proposals (357.AC/10–2451).</note> Mtg adjourned
                                without further comment by Israel del or <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>US dels conversations during past few days with <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fischer</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SR2">Shiloah</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RG1">Rafael</persName> indicate Israel del may be prepared take up
                                with <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> unilaterally single
                                question of compensation. They seem to assume this is question which
                                can be considered by them with <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>
                                alone without engaging in “negots” with Arab dels. It seems clear
                                they are determined not to continue with conference as envisaged in
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>’s original invitation or
                                within framework of <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>’s mediation
                                between parties as outlined comms pattern of proposals.</p>
                            <p>Israel dels position seems to be based on firm Cabinet decision and
                                explicit instructions. <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> is,
                                therefore, faced with situation anticipated in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 2103, Oct 11 [<hi rend="italic">10</hi>].<note n="4" xml:id="d521fn4">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_889">p.
                                    889</ref>.</note>
                                <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> has made clear it cannot now
                                reopen question of nonaggression declarations, which Israel has made
                                conditions precedent to further negots through comm with Arab dels.
                                On other hand, while Israel has indicated willingness consider
                                unilaterally with comm individual questions, no official statement
                                as to which questions Israel has in mind has been communicated to
                                comm. Before <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> cld enter into
                                unilateral discussions with Israel, it seems to US del that present
                                conference wld have to be terminated. Questions arise as to
                                procedure <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> shld follow in
                                terminating conference and whether under these circumstances it is
                                desirable continue unilaterally afterwards with matters chosen by
                                Israel for discussion. In latter case <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>’s “authoritative” role of mediation wld seem to
                                terminate <pb facs="0962" n="922" xml:id="pg_922"/> likewise. In any
                                case it wld be at ah end as far as Arabs are concerned.</p>
                            <p>Situation will be considered by <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>
                                in mtg 29th. Dept’s views for our guidance wld be appreciated.</p>
                            <closer>[<signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PEE1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Palmer</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>]</closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>