<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The First Secretary of the Embassy in Turkey ( (Baxter) ) to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d634</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">634</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-01-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="634"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d634">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">882.181/1–1551: Despatch</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The First Secretary of the Embassy in Turkey</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BWO1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Baxter</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 377</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-15">January 15,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Ref: Department’s A–114, December 27, 1950<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d634fn1">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Turkish-Bulgarian Agreement on Resumption of
                    Immigration</p>
                <p>In the Grand National Assembly on January 5, 1951, Foreign Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_KF1">Köprülü</persName>, in reply to an interpellation, gave
                    information which answers the questions in the Department’s airgram No.
                    A–114.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister stated that, after the closing of the frontier on October 8,
                    the Turkish Government informed the Bulgarian Government of its willingness to
                    reopen the frontier and to accept all properly documented immigrants then
                    waiting at the border on the following conditions: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Bulgaria would issue exit visas only to those who were already
                            provided with Turkish entry visas;</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Bulgaria would immediately accept those persons detained by Turkish
                            frontier authorities because they had attempted to enter Turkey without
                            Turkish entry visas.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>After <persName>Sofia</persName> had accepted these conditions, the Turkish
                    Chargé in Sofia informed the Bulgarian Foreign Office on November 29 that the
                    Turkish Government was prepared to open the frontier to normal traffic on
                    December 2. On the same day the terms of the agreement were made public.</p>
                <p>“This agreement was not reached by an exchange of signed notes between the two
                    countries,” the Foreign Minister continued, “but following the delivery by our
                    Chargé d’Affaires to the Bulgarian authorities, in response to the demand
                    presented by Sofia for the opening of the frontier, of a text containing the
                    terms previously published in the communiqué released to the press, and of the
                    interview held the same day in the course of which the Deputy Minister of <pb
                        facs="1141" n="1101" xml:id="pg_1101"/> Foreign Affairs of Bulgaria, Mr.
                        <persName>Ivkof</persName>, orally and in his official capacity informed the
                    Turkish Chargé in Sofia that the text had been accepted. This kind of verbal
                    agreement, which in diplomatic language is called a ‘gentlemen’s agreement,’ is
                    as valid as a signed note.”</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KF1">Köprülü</persName> further stated that the
                    agreement with the Bulgarian Government contained no stipulations with regard to
                    the number of immigrants to be accepted by Turkey, the Turkish Government having
                    reserved its right to limit the number of immigrants to the material resources
                    of the country. Between the reopening of the frontier in early December and
                    January 1, 1951, a total of 18,847 immigrants have arrived in Turkey from
                    Bulgaria.</p>
                <p>Pointing out that no machinery had ever been set up to implement the article in
                    the 1925 Turkish-Bulgarian Convention providing for the transfer of property of
                    Bulgarians of Turkish origin and Turks of Bulgarian origin who wished to
                    emigrate, the Foreign Minister declared that the Turkish Government in all its
                    recent communications to Sofia had repeated its desire to reach an agreement on
                    this subject, and had, in addition, informed the Bulgarian Legation in Ankara of
                    its readiness to enter into negotiations. The Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs
                    of Bulgaria has now informed the Turkish Chargé d’Affaires in Sofia that
                    technical preparations for the opening of such negotiations have been undertaken
                    and that a definite reply to this question will shortly be given.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWO1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> O. <hi rend="smallcaps">Baxter</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
