<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="637" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d637">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/1–2451</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant
                                    Secretary of State for Near Eastern, South Asian, and African
                                    Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MGC2"><hi rend="italic">McGhee</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d637fn1">Drafted
                                    by <persName corresp="#p_MCR1">Moore</persName>, <gloss target="#t_GTI1">GTI</gloss>.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-24">January 24,
                                        1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Turkish Proposal that the U.S. Adhere to
                                the British-French-Turkish Treaty of Mutual Assistance of 1939.<note n="2" xml:id="d637fn2">Signed on October 19, 1939. League of
                                    Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cc</hi>, p.
                                    167; also British Cmd. 6165, Treaty Series No. 4 (1940): <hi rend="italic">Treaty of Mutual Assistance Between His
                                        Majesty in Respect of the United Kingdom, the President of
                                        the French Republic and the President of the Turkish
                                        Republic</hi> (<hi rend="italic">With Special Agreement and
                                        Subsidiary Agreements</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Angora,
                                        October 19, 1939</hi>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EFC2">Feridun C. Erkin</persName>—Ambassador of Turkey</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MGC2">George C. McGhee</persName>—Assistant Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCR1">C.
                                            Robert Moore</persName>—<gloss target="#t_GTI1">GTI</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Problem:</hi> Turkish Ambassador proposes that US
                                extend security commitment to Turkey through adherence to
                                British-French-Turkish Treaty of Mutual Assistance of 1939.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Action Required:</hi> To consider the feasibility
                                of this proposal</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Action Assigned:</hi>
                                <gloss target="#t_GTI1">GTI</gloss>
                            </p>
                            <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EFC2">Erkin</persName> stated that
                                he had asked for this appointment in order to present to the
                                Department a new proposal for extending a U.S. security commitment
                                to Turkey. He briefly touched on the background of his proposal as
                                follows: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>In late 1948 and early 1949 he had made known to the
                                        Department the Turkish Government’s desire to be included in
                                        the North Atlantic Pact which was then being formulated.
                                        However, Turkey was not included among the original
                                        participants in this Pact.<note n="3" xml:id="d637fn3">For
                                            documentation regarding U.S. relations with Turkey, see
                                                <ref target="frus1949v06#pg_1638">
                                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 1638</ref> ff.;
                                            regarding U.S. participation in the creation of the
                                            North Atlantic Treaty Organization, see <ref target="frus1949v04#pg_1">
                                                <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Upon his return from Turkey in the summer of 1949 the
                                        Ambassador reached the conclusion that a broader regional
                                        grouping of Mediterranean countries such as Turkey, Greece,
                                        Spain and Italy with, of course, U.S. participation, was
                                        more logical than an extension of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, and he so informed his Government.
                                        However, he found that in Turkey the emphasis was on <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and that the Foreign
                                        Minister preferred to concentrate on Turkey’s inclusion in
                                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, an organization
                                        already in existence, than to press for the creation of a
                                        new regional grouping in which Turkey would be included.
                                        This culminated <pb facs="1151" n="1111" xml:id="pg_1111"/>
                                        in Turkey’s formal request for inclusion in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> in August 1950, which was
                                        subsequently turned down.<note n="4" xml:id="d637fn4">For
                                            documentation regarding Turkey’s request in 1950 for
                                            membership in the North Atlantic Treaty Organization,
                                            see <ref target="frus1950v03#pg_1">
                                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff. and
                                                <ref target="frus1950v03#pg_1108">1108</ref> ff.,
                                            and <ref target="frus1950v05#pg_1224">
                                                <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 1224</ref> ff.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The Ambassador, recovering from his great disappointment
                                        at this development, thereupon began to give thought again
                                        to a security arrangement in a form which would be
                                        acceptable to the U.S. and in November 1950 proposed to his
                                        Government in Ankara a Mediterranean formula on a new basis
                                        which he felt eliminated many of the difficulties of the
                                        earlier <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> proposal. He
                                        had just received the agreement of his Government to make
                                        this proposal to us and understood also that President
                                            <persName corresp="#p_BC1">Bayar</persName> had raised
                                        the question during the visit to Ankara of Admiral <persName corresp="#p_CRB1">Carney</persName> several weeks
                                            ago<note n="5" xml:id="d637fn5">January 10–12,
                                            1951.</note> and that Foreign Minister Koprulu had
                                        likewise discussed it with Ambassador Wads worth. While the
                                        President and Foreign Minister understood the Ambassador’s
                                        basic idea, he was afraid they had not grasped the
                                        nuances.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Ambassador then advanced his proposal—that the United States
                                adhere to the British-French-Turkish Treaty of Mutual Assistance of
                                1939. He felt that this type of U.S. security commitment to Turkey
                                had a number of advantages: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>It would eliminate the protracted discussions which would
                                        be involved in extending full membership in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> to Turkey or in setting
                                        up any new regional organization.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The arrangement would not be regional in the broad sense;
                                        therefore, no other country would feel entitled to ask for
                                        inclusion.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The scope and purpose of the arrangement would be limited;
                                        no new commitment would be involved except as regards the
                                        security of Turkey (and Greece).</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>While Greece would not be a party to the Treaty, Article 3
                                        thereof would in effect guarantee the security of Greece.
                                        This Article provides that so long as guarantees given by
                                        France and the United Kingdom to Greece on April 13, 1939
                                        remain in force, Turkey will lend them all aid and
                                        assistance in its power in the event they are engaged in
                                        hostilities in virtue of the said guarantees.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>The framework would be created for a reciprocal agreement
                                        between Greece and Turkey.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Ambassador recognized that the Treaty would have to be modified
                                slightly—for example, protocol No. 2, which contains the reservation
                                that Turkey is not called upon to take action which would involve
                                armed conflict with the Soviet Union. This obviously had no meaning
                                today. U.S. adherence to the Treaty could be accomplished by a
                                protocol.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador urged that earnest consideration be given to this
                                proposal as soon as possible and he expressed the hope that I would
                                be able to inform him, before my departure for Turkey in early
                                    February,<note n="6" xml:id="d637fn6">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MGC2">McGhee</persName> arrived in
                                    Istanbul on February 11, 1951, proceeded to Ankara for
                                    high-level discussions with Turkish officials there on February
                                    12–13, and returned to Istanbul to conduct the Middle East
                                    Regional Conference, February 14–21. Regarding his trip, see the
                                    editorial note, <ref target="#pg_49">p. 49</ref>.</note>
                                <pb facs="1152" n="1112" xml:id="pg_1112"/> that, in principle, it
                                was acceptable to us. He emphasized that recent developments
                                necessitated extraordinary measures and that the Turkish proposal
                                was not a selfish one but one which would contribute to European
                                security.</p>
                            <p>I informed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EFC2">Erkin</persName>
                                that, as I was sure he knew, Turkey’s desire to be included in a
                                security arrangement was very much in our minds. While his new
                                proposal was a very interesting one I was afraid that many of the
                                considerations which made it difficult for the North Atlantic Pact
                                to be extended to Turkey would apply likewise to it. I felt that the
                                United States had never shown a lack of interest in helping the
                                Turks to develop their military strength and that a security
                                commitment was, in effect, not of very practical importance. I
                                informed him, however, that we would certainly give all appropriate
                                consideration to his proposal. I questioned whether Greece would be
                                well pleased with the Ambassador’s formula but he expressed
                                confidence that it would be satisfied. This led to some discussion
                                as to the present status of the UK and French guarantees to Greece.
                                With respect to the UK guarantee the Ambassador felt quite certain
                                that it was still in effect.</p>
                            <p>As the Ambassador was leaving I asked him if, since our conversation
                                of several weeks ago, he had changed his views as to the possibility
                                of Turkey’s entering into regional agreements in the absence of a
                                U.S. commitment. The Ambassador very emphatically indicated that
                                there was no change in his views and that he would strongly oppose
                                Turkey’s participation in such agreements.</p>
                            <p>Somewhat later in the day Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EFC2">Erkin</persName> telephoned Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCR1">Moore</persName> and asked him to tell me, with respect to my
                                question on regional agreements, that he wanted to amplify his
                                statement somewhat. It was his strong belief that, if Turkey and the
                                United States were linked together in a security arrangement of the
                                kind proposed by him, it would be easier and more feasible for
                                Turkey, through its increased prestige, to align the other countries
                                in that area in support of our common objectives. Turkey,
                                strengthened by this concrete evidence of U.S. support, would
                                constitute a center of attraction to the other neighboring
                                countries.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EM1">Esenbel</persName>, at the request of
                                the Ambassador, subsequently telephoned Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCR1">Moore</persName> regarding the UK guarantee to
                                Greece. The Ambassador’s view was that such a guarantee was in
                                effect until repudiated and that there was no evidence that it had
                                been repudiated. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EM1">Esenbel</persName>
                                himself had questioned one of his Greek colleagues on <pb facs="1153" n="1113" xml:id="pg_1113"/> this point, without
                                revealing the reason for his interest, and was told that Ambassador
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PAG1">Politis</persName> considered the
                                guarantee still in effect inasmuch as it had not been
                                repudiated.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MGC2">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">George C. McGhee</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>