<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in Liberia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d729</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">729</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="729"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d729">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">776.00/10–1851: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Liberia</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d729fn1">This airgram was drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_FGR1">Farmer</persName> (<gloss target="#t_NEA1"
                            >NEA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>), was cleared by <gloss
                            target="#t_TCA1">TCA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>, and <persName corresp="#p_BEH1"
                            >Bourgerie</persName> (<gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>) signed for the Secretary of State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-18">October 18,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–90. The Department believes that recent developments regarding the trial of
                    certain Liberians for sedition<note n="2" xml:id="d729fn2">In August,
                        approximately 20 members of the Liberian Reformation Party, which had
                        opposed President <persName corresp="#p_TWVS1">Tubman</persName> during the
                        May general election, were arrested by Liberian authorities and charged with
                        alleged sedition. Reformation Party leader <persName corresp="#p_TD1">Didwo
                            Twe</persName>, one of those indicted for sedition, fled to Freetown,
                        Sierra Leone. The trial of the other Reformation Party leaders was
                        eventually postponed and those charged were gradually released. It was
                        reported that at least one of the prisoners was slain in jail by a fellow
                        prisoner. Documentation on the detention and indictment of the Reformation
                        Party members is included in file 776.00.</note> necessitate steps to inform
                    the Liberian Government of the United States Government’s concern over this
                    matter. Realizing President <persName corresp="#p_TWVS1">Tubman</persName>’s
                    sensitiveness on this subject and the harm done the Embassy’s previous actions
                    by independent approaches to the President, the Department leaves to the
                    Embassy’s discretion the time and manner in which the following information is
                    given to the President. However, it is believed that fairly quick action should
                    be taken to put this information before the President before considerable harm
                    is done to Liberia’s reputation as a democracy.</p>
                <p>As the Embassy is aware, the recent Liberian elections<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d729fn3">Regarding the Liberian general election of 1951, see
                        despatch 380, May 15, from Monrovia, <ref target="#pg_1295">p.
                        1295</ref>.</note> have aroused considerable criticism in the United States,
                    particularly in the press. The Department has received protests from various
                    groups and individuals. Some of these protests sprang from self-interest and old
                    grudges against the <persName corresp="#p_TWVS1">Tubman</persName>
                    Administration. Others were obviously rooted in sincere concern at apparent
                    signs of undemocratic election practices in Liberia.</p>
                <p>The Department has defended the legality of the Liberian Government’s action in
                    not placing Didhwo <persName corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName>’s name on the
                    ballot. On the <pb facs="1348" n="1308" xml:id="pg_1308"/> strength of
                    information received from the Embassy, the Department has also denied recurring
                    rumors that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName>’s life has been in
                    danger.</p>
                <p>The Department is, furthermore, convinced of President <persName
                        corresp="#p_TWVS1">Tubman</persName>’s sincere intention to further
                    Liberia’s economic, social and political progress. It has repeatedly pointed to
                    the progress made under his Administration as evidence refuting many of the
                    arguments used against the President by his critics in the United States.</p>
                <p>However, the President’s reported insistence on pursuing the sedition trial of
                    Reformation Party officials and members is arousing a new round of protests.
                    Letters and inquiries are already arriving from persons who had formerly been
                    unaroused by protests concerning the elections or who had been satisfied with
                    the Department’s explanation of the legalities involved. Among these persons is
                    Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_RAE1">Eleanor Roosevelt</persName>,<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d729fn4">See <persName corresp="#p_HJD1">Hickerson</persName>’s
                        letter of August 9 to Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_RAE1">Roosevelt</persName>,
                            <ref target="#pg_1303">p. 1303</ref>.</note> whose position on the
                    United Nations Commission for Human Rights makes her particularly important. The
                    Department finds it difficult to justify either to these persons or to itself
                    the present exhibition of what amounts to vengeance for political
                    opposition.</p>
                <p>The Department is now trying to form an impressive delegation of prominent
                    Americans to represent the United States at President <persName
                        corresp="#p_TWVS1">Tubman</persName>’s inauguration.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d729fn5">A formal invitation to attend President <persName
                            corresp="#p_TWVS1">Tubman</persName>’s Second Inaugural Ceremony in
                        Monrovia, January 5–14, 1952, was delivered to the Department of State by
                        the Liberian Embassy on July 9, 1951. During the remainder of the year
                        arrangements were worked out by the Department for an American delegation to
                        the inauguration. Initially the Department considered a delegation
                        consisting of <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Nelson Rockefeller</persName>,
                        Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Mary Bethune</persName>, Col. <persName
                            corresp="#p_MHC1">Harry McBride</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_FGR1">Garland Farmer</persName>. Eventually a delegation
                        headed by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DER1">Dudley</persName> and
                        including Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Bethune</persName>, Gen.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJS2">James Stowell</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_MC3">Carl Murphy</persName> was approved by President
                            <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> and announced on January
                        1, 1952. For the text of the announcement regarding the delegation, see the
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, January 7, 1952, p. 13.
                        Documentation on the naming of the delegation is included in file
                        776.11.</note> Steps have been taken to have United States Air Force and
                    Navy units participate in the ceremonies. Liberia is one of the nations
                    receiving most Point 4 aid, and is beng pointed to as a model of the type of
                    progress achieved under Point 4 type programs.</p>
                <p>In view of these facts, it is most difficult to maintain that such actions as the
                    proposed trials should be considered as a strictly internal Liberian affair. The
                    trial of political opponents is an act repugnant to most Americans and to most
                    of the peoples associated with the United States in the present fight to protect
                    the free world. The trial of President <persName corresp="#p_TWVS1"
                        >Tubman</persName>’s opponents would reflect upon the United States, which
                    has evidenced and is evidencing in many ways its friendship for Liberia and the
                    present Liberian Government. Rightly or wrongly, a political trial of the sort
                    proposed would be considered <hi rend="italic">prima facie</hi> evidence of the
                    lack of real democracy in Liberia. This could endanger the entire American
                    program in Liberia because of the obvious possible reaction on the part of the
                    American public and the Congress.</p>
                <p>For these reasons, the Department earnestly hopes that the Liberian Government
                    can be persuaded to reconsider or modify its course of <pb facs="1349" n="1309"
                        xml:id="pg_1309"/> action regarding the Reformation Party. In so doing, it
                    would not only justify the faith and defense of its friends, it would also give
                    the lie to those critics who question the existence of democracy in Liberia.
                    Please keep the Department informed.<note n="6" xml:id="d729fn6">
                        <p>In his telegram 180, November 3, from Monrovia, Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_DER1">Dudley</persName> replied as follows:</p>
                        <p>“<persName corresp="#p_TWVS1">Tubman</persName> position slightly changed
                            in <persName corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName> sedition matter. <persName
                                corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName> will not be tried <hi rend="italic"
                                >in absentia</hi> (he is now in Freetown). All others indicted for
                            sedition are now out of jail. They will not be tried this term court.
                                <persName corresp="#p_TWVS1">Tubman</persName>’s reason is that a
                            relative of his (Judge Bond from Cape Palmas) has been assigned to this
                            jurisdiction by the Supreme Court. It is now possible all except
                                <persName corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName> may never be tried. No
                            softening of attitude toward <persName corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName>
                            can be expected this administration, because of <persName
                                corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName>’s long history of agitation. Feeling
                            generally high; if indictment keeps him out of the country so much the
                            better.” (776.00/11–351)</p>
                        <p>Telegram 219, December 7, from Monrovia, reported that <persName
                                corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName> had applied for political asylum in
                            the United States. The telegram observed that <persName corresp="#p_TD1"
                                >Twe</persName> was in no danger in Freetown and his presence in the
                            United States might adversely affect U.S.-Liberian relations. The
                            Embassy proposed to refuse <persName corresp="#p_TD1">Twe</persName>’s
                            request on technical visa grounds. (776.00/12–751) Telegram 179,
                            December 18, to Monrovia replied as follows:</p>
                        <p>“Dept concurs ur decision refuse visa <persName corresp="#p_TD1"
                                >Twe</persName> without reference polit appeal. Emb shld note
                            Section III–4 Regs (July 1939) which forbids dipl reps US from granting
                            asylum. Also, Hackworth Digest Internatl Law, Vol. <ref
                                target="frus1951v02#pg_622">II, p. 622</ref> which shows right of
                            asylum never recognized by US as principle of Internatl law, although on
                            occasion there has been sanctioned the granting of temporary refuge to
                            Amer dipl and con missions when necessary for the preservation of human
                            life.” (776.00/12–751)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
