<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bruce) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d783</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">783</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-12-17T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-12-17T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-12-17T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-17T15:00:00-05:00" n="783"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d783">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">651.72/12–1751: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bruce</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d783fn1">Repeated for information to Tunis.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-12-17T21:00:00+01:00"
                            >December 17, 1951—9 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3618. French reply to Tunisian note which <persName corresp="#p_CSM1"
                        >Chenik</persName> released to press (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1"
                        >Embtel</gloss> 3584, Dec 15) has given subj considerable comment.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d783fn2">The telegram under reference is not printed.
                        Regarding the Tunisian note of October 31, see footnote 3, <ref
                            target="#pg_1420">p. 1420</ref>. The text of Foreign Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s reply of December 15 is printed in
                            <hi rend="italic">L’ Année politique, 1951</hi>, pp. 591–592.</note> In
                    gen right-wing press defends govt note and claims Tunisian demands went much too
                    far while left-wing attacks govt for failing take any conciliatory steps toward
                    satisfying Tunisians.</p>
                <p>Line of reasoning of <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> note is that
                    while <persName corresp="#p_CSM1">Chenik</persName> letter of Oct 30 might form
                    basis for conversations, account must be taken of 70 years of French work in
                    Tunisia including continuing contribution of substantial portion of budget and
                    carrying out of large public works prog. French residents in Tunisia, note
                    continues, have played important role in development of country and govt cannot
                    consider setting them aside insofar as participation in public life is concerned
                    (i.e. French will continue to be represented in whatever Consultative Council
                    may be evolved). Future relations between France and Tunisia can only be founded
                    on recognition of “the definitive nature of the bond which unites them”. Note
                    adds that Bey shld now put into effect engagements which he has freely accepted
                    regarding municipal reforms as prerequisite to any other reforms (i.e. creation
                    of Tunisian Assembly). Finally <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>
                    states French Govt is ordering its rep Tunis to institute next month mixed
                    Franco-Tunisian commission to study what type of rep institution might replace
                    grand council whose mandate has expired.</p>
                <pb facs="1465" n="1425" xml:id="pg_1425"/>
                <p>Concurrently with publication French note press reports appointment of <persName
                        corresp="#p_VP1">Voizard</persName> now French <gloss target="#t_Min1"
                        >Min</gloss> to Monaco to replace <persName corresp="#p_PL1"
                        >Perillier</persName>. Text of reply is designed maintain intact French
                    position Tunisia and not offer much hope any widespread reform; dismissal
                        <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Perillier</persName> is considered further
                    indication determination French Govt follow firm line inasmuch as he was
                    considered apostle of concessions to Tunisians and as such anathema to French
                    colony. Combination of <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> reply and
                    appointment <persName corresp="#p_VP1">Voizard</persName> who is rumored to be
                    advocate firm line Tunisia shld satisfy restlessness French colony in
                    protectorate.</p>
                <p>Tunisian reaction to note (text of which is being airmailed) has been as expected
                    unfavorable. <persName corresp="#p_CSM1">Chenik</persName> announced to press he
                    considered French document equivalent to refusing to acknowledge Tunisian note
                    at all and was disturbed at ref to cosovereignty of France and Tunisia in ltr
                    country. Tels of protest from Tunisian nationalists and labor groups have
                    already been received in Paris, while Socialist <hi rend="italic">Populaire</hi>
                    and Independent <hi rend="italic">Combat</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Franc-Tireur</hi> are sharply critical of govt and predict difficulties in
                    future. <hi rend="italic">Figaro</hi> while approving French reply is rather
                    pessimistic as to future tranquillity but expresses hope mixed commission (to
                    which it is rumored Ramadier may be appointed) may find some way out of impasse.
                        <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> has little to add to above but
                    officer in charge of protectorates seemed somewhat disappointed govt reply had
                    offered Tunisians so little and omitted certain reforms Quai d’Orsay had
                    suggested such as lifting state of siege.</p>
                <p>Early reaction seems generally that French reply does not represent much progress
                    and leaves Franco-Tunisian relations approximately where they were when
                        <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Perillier</persName> went to Tunis.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bruce</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
