<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="793" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d793">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">845A.411/8–2151: Despatch</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Third Secretary of the Embassy in the Union of
                                    South Africa</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DM2" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dembo</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                    the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                    <lb/> No. 108</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Pretoria</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-02">August 2,
                                    1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Race Conflict and the Native Outlook</p>
                            <p>Native resentment of white <hi rend="italic">baaskap</hi> (supremacy)
                                and Native disappointment with America’s “failure” to oppose <hi rend="italic">apartheid</hi> were the main impressions made on
                                an Embassy officer after a two-hour talk with a group of Natives in
                                Pretoria. The group was informally brought together to meet the
                                officer by a Native minister. It included a school teacher, a clerk
                                in the Department of Native Affairs, a shopkeeper, a printer, an
                                employee of a non-European affairs department of the Municipality,
                                three others and the minister. Points made by them during this
                                discussion are put under three heads: <list>
                                    <item>I. Inevitability of race conflict;</item>
                                    <item>II. Shortcomings of Native organizations; and</item>
                                    <item>III. Disappointment with United States foreign
                                        policy.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">I. <hi rend="italic">Inevitability of Race
                                    Conflict</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The group agreed that a compromise solution of South Africa’s racial
                                difficulties was impossible. Revolution, they felt, was unavoidable.
                                The whites of all parties were one in their support of white <hi rend="italic">baaskap</hi>, while the Natives claimed equality
                                of opportunity as their right. They unhesitatingly blamed the
                                Nationalists for inflaming racial feelings to the point where today
                                every Native regarded every white man as his enemy.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">II. <hi rend="italic">Shortcomings of Native
                                    Organizations</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The group acknowledged that the bulk of the Native people were
                                unorganized. One said the <gloss target="#t_ANC1">ANC</gloss> was
                                like a head without a body. He guessed that the Congress only had
                                about 1,000 active members. Another claimed that the drawback to
                                effective Native organization was the “Native intellectuals”, that
                                is, themselves. The educated Natives were only interested in making
                                a good thing out of their education. They did not care to work among
                                the people in rural areas who were ready for leadership. Another
                                observed that dynamic leadership could never be expected from men
                                who were civil servants and who could be sacked if they became too
                                outspoken. Communist prestige, on the other hand, was rising because
                                they were the only ones who appeared ready to stake their all in the
                                struggle against oppression.</p>
                            <p>The certain feeling of the group was that whenever effective
                                leadership <hi rend="italic">did</hi> appear the Native people would
                                follow as one man the attack on <hi rend="italic">baaskap</hi>.
                                Their struggle against oppression, they felt, was a developing one.
                                The present unformed state of Native organizations was not,
                                therefore, a bad sign. This showed the Native pot was bubbling.
                                Fusion would come later. The Native minister here interjected that
                                African religious separation was a case in point. The 1,000-odd
                                separate Bantu churches showed that the Native was rejecting <pb facs="1489" n="1449" xml:id="pg_1449"/> white overlordship. They
                                were essentially a movement away from the oppressor. If it were not
                                for ministers like himself who tried to stem this separatism, the
                                Native religious rebellion by now would have been complete.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">III. <hi rend="italic">United States Foreign Policy
                                    and South Africa</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The reporting officer was impressed by the group’s disappointment
                                with America’s “support” of South Africa at <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. His counter-argument to put this issue into
                                perspective was not taken and they predicted that the Native people
                                would sympathize with the Soviets in a war with the West. The Native
                                people were not Communists, they stressed, but the Soviet Union did
                                appear to side with them in their struggle against oppression.
                                America did not and they could not see why. They understood British
                                truckling to Nationalist prejudice. Britain, they said, was a broken
                                power; but America was now the great western exponent of freedom and
                                they expected her to use her influence in their favor.</p>
                            <p>The group also showed concern with recent press stories of arrests of
                                American Communists. They are afraid that their own advocacy of
                                racial equality might lead to their arrest as Communists under the
                                Suppression of Communism Act. And without fully understanding the
                                American scene, they feared there was a “white supremacy” motive
                                behind these arrests.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Embassy believes the observations reported here are typical of
                                informed Native opinion in South Africa. Native anger and
                                frustration are apparent everywhere in those urban areas which are
                                best known to Embassy officers. Apartheid has only served to
                                intensify their bitterness. The informed urban Native, moreover,
                                assesses world developments in terms of the black and white struggle
                                in South Africa. He may be sophisticated enough to know that there
                                is more to Communist propaganda than appears on the surface but he
                                finds it hard to resist its magnetism because in South Africa
                                communism alone ranges itself on the side of racial equality. Our
                                information task with them is important because the value of South
                                Africa as a secure ally in a war against Russia is weakened to the
                                extent of their susceptibility to Communist propaganda. The system
                                of white supremacy is powerful and effective but, as the thinking
                                here reported reveals, Native anger is growing. An outstanding
                                leader willing to make personal sacrifices or harsh Government
                                action which provoked a large segment of the native people, such as
                                a pass system for Native women, could cause trouble.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DM2">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Morris Dembo</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>