<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Union of South Africa ( (Gallmari) ) to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d798</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">798</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="minerals-and-metals" lcsh-match="no_match">Minerals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="798"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d798">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">745A.13/11–551: Despatch</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Union of South Africa</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gallmari</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 296</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Pretoria</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-05">November 5,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Conversation between the Ambassador and Minister of
                    Defense, the Honorable <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">F. C. Erasmus</persName>
                </p>
                <p>I made my first call on Minister of Defense <persName corresp="#p_EFC1"
                        >Erasmus</persName> this morning. He received me in a very friendly way. At
                    the very outset he said he remembered vividly the friendly, sympathetic
                    understanding shown him by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName>
                    and General Marshall when he visited the States last year and discussed with
                    them South Africa’s armament needs.<note n="1" xml:id="d798fn1">For information
                        on <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erasmus</persName>’ meetings with <persName
                            corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName> and Marshall on October 5, see the
                        editorial note, <ref target="#pg_1427">p. 1427</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Erasmus then turned to the <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> agreement and
                    said he was very happy that appreciation of South Africa’s position had been
                    shown in Washington and that the way was now clear for signing the
                        agreement.<note n="2" xml:id="d798fn2">Regarding the exchange of notes of
                        November 9, constituting the agreement relating to mutual defense assistance
                        between the United States and the Union of South Africa, see the editorial
                        note, <ref target="#pg_1459">p. 1459</ref>.</note> This would be done any
                    day now, he added. South Africa, <pb facs="1496" n="1456" xml:id="pg_1456"/> he
                    said, particularly because of its present limited manganese supply, could not
                    give a blanket commitment covering assistance on its side. While there were
                    undoubtedly as yet a number of unknown sources of manganese in the country which
                    would in time be developed, the supply from present known sources was limited to
                    about fifteen years.<note n="3" xml:id="d798fn3">In a memorandum of November 5,
                        a copy of which was attached to this despatch, Embassy Minerals Attaché
                            <persName corresp="#p_FBR1">Frisbie</persName> commented that the
                        estimate of a 15-year supply of manganese ore appeared to be used as an
                        excuse for South Africa’s inability to give the kind of materials commitment
                        called for in a mutual defense assistance agreement. <persName
                            corresp="#p_FBR1">Frisbie</persName> observed that it had already been
                        reported to the Department of State that recent South African official
                        estimates had established manganese ore reserves sufficient for 50 years of
                        production at the current rate.</note> I interjected that the agreement as
                    originally drawn up was, as I understood it, a form agreement of the type
                    generally submitted to countries who had qualified for aid on a reimbursable
                    basis. I was happy, nevertheless, that an understanding had been reached by our
                    two Governments which now made the signing possible.</p>
                <p>Erasmus then said that he hoped an early start could be made in supplying South
                    Africa with the equipment needed. I asked <persName corresp="#p_EFC1"
                        >Erasmus</persName> whether the requirements, as given in the original list
                    submitted by him during his visit in Washington, had been materially altered,
                    and he said the list stood substantially as originally drawn up.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d798fn4">In a memorandum of November 5, a copy of which was attached
                        to this despatch, Embassy Army Attaché Col. John Davis said that <persName
                            corresp="#p_EFC1">Erasmus</persName> had obviously not been able to keep
                        up with the details of the negotiations and was in error in his observation
                        that the original South African list remained un-altered. Davis commented
                        that most of the equipment originally requested from the United States was
                        currently scheduled to be obtained from the United Kingdom.</note> He hoped
                    progress could also be made with the list which was recently submitted to the
                    British Government. He was very gratified, he said, to have been told that the
                    U.S. and U.K. would coordinate their efforts in supplying the Union.</p>
                <p>Korea was then touched upon. <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erasmus</persName> said
                    that because of the severe losses of machines and men in Korea, he had felt
                    compelled during the last session of Parliament to state in Parliament that the
                    Union Government would undertake to have its squadron in Korea equipped with
                    jets. He said that it was a big disappointment when he was told by both the
                    British and by us that jets were not now available. He said South Africa, in
                    view of public opinion, was in the position where unless jets were made
                    available the squadron would have to be grounded. From Britain word has come
                    that jets would not be available before 1953. From Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName>, however, he had just received word that
                    we would give the problem prompt consideration and that hope was held out,
                    according to <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName>, that perhaps by
                    January some jets could be made available. I asked <persName corresp="#p_EFC1"
                        >Erasmus</persName> from whom <persName corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName>
                    had received this information. That he said he did not know. The situation, he
                    then said, might, of course, be eased <pb facs="1497" n="1457" xml:id="pg_1457"
                    /> if the cease-fire were soon negotiated. In any event, he said even a few jets
                    by January would ease the Government’s position materially.</p>
                <p>Before we left this subject I reminded <persName corresp="#p_EFC1"
                        >Erasmus</persName> that we had two squadrons fighting alongside the South
                    African squadron in Korea, and that these squadrons, because of the shortage of
                    jets, were equipped no different from the South African squadron.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d798fn5">See Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WJE1"
                            >Webb</persName>’s memorandum of his conversation with <persName
                            corresp="#p_JGP1">Jooste</persName> on October 23, <ref
                            target="#pg_1451">p. 1451</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I then asked <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erasmus</persName> what steps, if any,
                    were contemplated during the coming session of Parliament to extend the time for
                    compulsory military service. He said that the draft legislation he had in mind
                    would extend compulsory military service (in active citizen force) from three
                    months over a three-year period to twelve months. Manpower shortage, however, he
                    pointed out, would at any time make it somewhat difficult to get such amending
                    legislation through Parliament. He could not say at present whether the question
                    would be opened in the coming session of Parliament. He wished to see first what
                    developments, in the field of disarmament, took place at the forthcoming General
                    Assembly meeting at Paris.</p>
                <p>As I was taking my leave, <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erasmus</persName> said
                    that he must apologize for having, in our first meeting, touched on the two
                    problems, the need of armaments for South Africa and the need for jets in Korea.
                    He would appreciate, he said, any help I could give him. I told him that I
                    would, of course, report our conversation and request that both problems
                    continue to be given sympathetic consideration.</p>
                <p>I was very favorably impressed with the friendly, frank way <persName
                        corresp="#p_EFC1">Erasmus</persName> received me and talked with me.</p>
                <p>Comments of the Army Attaché, Colonel Davis, and of the Minerals Attaché, Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_FBR1">Frisbie</persName>, on some of the statements
                    made by Minister <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erasmus</persName> are
                        enclosed.<note n="6" xml:id="d798fn6">Regarding the comments under reference
                        here, see footnotes 3 and 4, above.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_FWJ1">W. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Gallman</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
