<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-12-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                    <head>No. 104.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Holcombe</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-12-05"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 5, 1878</date>.
                            (Received February 24.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 84.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In the autumn of 1875, the Department was
                        informed of the appointment, by the Chinese Government, of Kuo Sungtao as
                        minister to the Court of Saint James.</p>
                    <p>I have now the honor to inform you that, in accordance with the rules of the
                        Chinese diplomatic service, His Excellency Kuo has been granted permission
                        to return to his native land, and the Marquis Tseng has been appointed as
                        his successor.</p>
                    <p>This appointment deserves something more than a passing notice. The marquis
                        is the son of the celebrated Tseng Kuo-fan, who was one of the ablest
                        statesmen of this country in modern times. He possesses at least a portion
                        of his father’s unusual ability, is about forty years of age, an elegant
                        Chinese scholar, and as avowedly progressive in his ideas as his father was
                        conservative.</p>
                    <p>Upon emerging from the retirement made necessary by the death of his parents,
                        he came to this capital, where he has resided for the past year, awaiting
                        his appointment to office. During this period he has openly cultivated the
                        acquaintance of foreigners in both the diplomatic and missionary circles,
                        making almost daily visits upon some of them, and inviting them freely to
                        his house.</p>
                    <p>So far as my knowledge goes, he is the only Chinese of high rank who has ever
                        sought to learn a foreign language. While in mourning he applied himself to
                        the study of English, and, although without an instructor, he made very fair
                        progress, and is now able to make himself understood in it.</p>
                    <p>You will be amused to know that his only text-books in this study were
                        Webster’s Unabridged Dictionary, the Bible, and a copy of “Watts’ Select
                        Hymns,” a book used fifty years ago in some of the churches in our country.
                        As a consequence his idiom is somewhat peculiar.</p>
                    <p>In my opinion his appointment is highly to be commended as one eminently fit
                        to be made and promising the best results.</p>
                    <p>The marquis, accompanied by his family and a numerous suite, has already
                        sailed for Europe.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>CHESTER HOLCOMBE.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>