<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-01-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-01-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="236" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d236">
                    <head>No. 215.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Evarts</persName>
                            to Sir <persName type="to">Edward Thornton</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-01-30"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 30,
                            1879</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                        your note of the 28th instant, communicating a copy of an instruction
                        addressed by the Marquis of Salisbury to Her Majesty’s chargé d’affaires at
                        Bogotá, directing him to protest against the law passed by the Colombian
                        Congress requiring all vessels arriving at the free ports of the republic to
                        deposit their registers with the principal national local authority, to be
                        returned by that officer when the vessel should clear for sea. You further
                        express the hope that such instruction’s may be sent to the minister of the
                        United States at Bogotá as may induce him to co-operate with Her Majesty’s
                        chargé d’affaires in this matter, as far as it may be proper for him to do
                        so.</p>
                    <p>In reply, I have to state that the legislation complained of has given rise
                        to difficulty at various times since 1854. It was thought, however, that the
                        diplomatic arrangement of the 27th of July, 1876, to which this government
                        was a party, would operate to remove the cause of complaint.</p>
                    <p>The more recent case of the American schooner “Lorine,” which was seized at
                        Aspinwall (Colon) under peculiarly aggravated circumstances, revived the
                        question as between this government and that of Colombia; and, on the
                        departure for his post of Mr. Ernest Dichman, the newly-appointed minister
                        of the United States at Bogotá, the subject was made the occasion of
                        specific instructions to that officer, who was informed that this government
                        was not aware of any modification, executive or legislative, of the
                        diplomatic accord of 1876; that even were that agreement annuled, we could
                        not freely assent to the delivery of the registers <pb facs="0583" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/> of national vessels into the custody of another
                        government, and that such custody was regarded as contrary to the principles
                        and usage of commercial international law.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Dichman was therefore instructed to bring the matter anew to the notice
                        of the Colombian Government, and to ask that steps be taken to complete the
                        arrangement of 1876, and remove the conflict then acknowledged to exist
                        between the law and the practice of nations, and especially to instruct the
                        local authorities in such terms as to prevent a recurrence of vexatious and
                        arbitrary acts like the proceedings had with regard to the “Lorine.”</p>
                    <p>Mr. Dichman replied, under date of October 27, 1878, that he had already
                        brought the subject to the notice of the Government of Colombia, and had
                        been assured that no desire existed to deviate from the diplomatic agreement
                        of 1876; that the inspector of the port at Aspinwall had been changed, and
                        that application would be made to Congress to have the law repealed.</p>
                    <p>Inasmuch as the interests of the United States Government in this matter are,
                        in the main, identical with those of the other countries concerned in the
                        agreement of 1876, Mr. Dichman will be instructed to exert himself, in
                        harmony with his colleagues, to bring about a definite settlement of the
                        question in the manner contemplated in his previous instructions.</p>
                    <p>A copy of your note and its inclosure will be sent to him for his
                        information.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>WM. M. EVARTS.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>