<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-09-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="258" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                    <head>No. 236.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Edward
                                Thornton</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-09-30"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 30, 1879</date>.
                            (Received October 1.)</dateline></opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>:</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to transmit herewith copy of a report of the privy council
                        of Canada, which I have to-day received from the governor-general of the
                        Dominion, relative to the prohibition imposed upon Canadian Indians from
                        following the buffalo into United States territory, and also respecting the
                        belief entertained by Lieutenant-Colonel McLeod and his subordinates that if
                        the Sioux Indians who took refuge in British territory were allowed to
                        retain their ponies, they would be willing to surrender their arms, and
                        would desire to return to the United States.</p>
                    <p>I venture to hope that the Government of the United States will give its
                        earnest and friendly attention to the two points which are treated of in the
                        inclosed report, and will take such measures as it may deem expedient to
                        meet the views of the Canadian Government with regard to matters which are
                        of such momentous importance to the interests of friendly neighbors.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>ED W’D THOENTON.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Copy of a report of a committee of the honorable the
                                privy council, approved by his excellency the governor-general</hi>
                                22<hi rend="italic">d September</hi>, 1879.</head>
                        <p>The committee of the privy council have had under consideration a
                            dispatch from Lieutenant-Colonel McLeod, commanding the northwest
                            mounted police force, dated <pb facs="0607" n="511" xml:id="pg_511"/>
                            Fort Walsh, 9th of August, 1879, inclosing three dispatches from
                            Superintendent Walsh, of the same force, dated from Hood Mountain on the
                            22d, 25th, and 31st days of July, respectively, with an inclosure in one
                            of them giving a <hi rend="italic">verbatim</hi> report of the views
                            expressed by certain chief men (four) of the Sioux Nation of Indians as
                            to the return of that tribe into the territories of the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>The committee of the privy council are deeply impressed with the urgent
                            importance of preserving peace among the Indian tribes of the northwest
                            territory. The policy pursued by “the company of adventurers trading to
                            Hudson’s Bay” from the beginning of their intercourse with the Indians,
                            and by the imperial government, has for generations secured not only
                            peaceful intercourse with them, but their full faith and confidence,
                            and, since the cession of the territory they inhabit to Canada, the
                            Dominion has maintained the same friendly relations with them, and they
                            on their part have continued to this government the loyal allegiance
                            which they have always shown to the Crown of Great Britain and those in
                            authority under it.</p>
                        <p>It has only been latterly and since large numbers of Indians from the
                            territories of the United States have forced themselves across the
                            boundary to take up their abode in Canada that any embarrassments have
                            arisen in dealing with our Indians. The paramount difficulty which
                            constantly presents itself arises from the scarcity of food. The
                            buffalo, which forms the staple of consumption amongst the Indians of
                            British North America, is diminishing rapidly in numbers, and their
                            migration northward into Canadian territory has, your committee are
                            informed, latterly been arrested (as far as it could be) by United
                            States troops stationed along the border, and while our Indians and
                            half-breeds are prohibited by the United States military authorities
                            from going south of the boundary in pursuit of the animal necessary to
                            feed themselves and their families, no restriction has ever been or is
                            placed by the Canadian authorities, when the buffalo herds come
                            northward, upon United States Indians coming into our territories in
                            pursuit of the game in which all are so much interested.</p>
                        <p>It is true that the American Government undertake to feed their Indians
                            if they remain upon the reservations provided for them within the United
                            States; but in fact they come north and chase the buffalo in our
                            country, diminishing the food supply of our Indians and half-breeds. The
                            Canadian Government is making great exertions to settle their Indians,
                            and to induce them to become herdsmen, and to cultivate land and raise
                            supplies of food for themselves, but in the mean time, and until this is
                            accomplishd, half-breeds and Indians alike depend upon the chase,
                            particularly of the buffalo, for sustenance.</p>
                        <p>The committee of the privy council respectfully submit that it would only
                            be reasonable that the same liberty which is extended by Canada to
                            American Indians should be extended by the United. States to such of our
                            Indians as may cross the border, without hostile intent or action, in
                            search of food.</p>
                        <p>Another great difficulty which has been created for the Canadian
                            Government in the northwest has arisen from the expatriation from the
                            United States into Canada of a portion of the Sioux Nation of Indians,
                            numbering about four thousand souls. This large additional population is
                            forced upon Canada and (with more wandering tribes temporarily crossing
                            the border) shares the rapidly-diminishing food supply of the Canadian
                            Indians.</p>
                        <p>The United States authorities are willing, it is understood, to settle
                            the Sioux upon their reservations within United States territory, if the
                            latter will surrender their arms and their ponies. Lieutenant-Colonel
                            McLeod and his subordinates believe that the Sioux are willing to give
                            up their arms, but state that the Indians think it unreasonable that
                            they should be asked to surrender their only means of transport of their
                            women and children and sick, and such chattles as they possess.</p>
                        <p>The committee of the privy council respectfully submit that the United
                            States Government may be moved to so far modify the terms held out to
                            the Sioux as to allow them to settle on the reservations by the
                            surrender of their arms only.</p>
                        <p>The committee trust that the Government of the United States may be
                            willing to relax somewhat rules which, however beneficially intended, in
                            practice increase so greatly the sufferings of the Indians, and add to
                            the difficulties of preserving peace among them, and to the alarm and
                            perhaps danger of the settlers now rapidly filling in the prairie
                            country of the northwest; and the committee believe that, should the two
                            objects contemplated in this report be attained, there would be no
                            longer any difficulty in dealing with our own tribes of Indians, or in
                            their obtaining a sufficient supply of food for themselves and their
                            families until the measures taken by the Canadian Government, and above
                            alluded to, shall have furnished them with more lasting and reliable
                            resources.</p>
                        <p>Certified:</p>
                        <closer><signed>W. S. HIMSWORTH<lb/><hi rend="italic">Clerk Privy Council,
                                    Canada.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
            </body></text></TEI>