<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 267.Mr. Evarts
                            to Mr. Preston.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1879</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d291</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">291</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1879-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1879-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376" lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-04-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="291" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d291">
                <head>No. 267.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Evarts</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Preston</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-04-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 19,
                            1879</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The undersigned, Secretary of State of the United States, has the honor to
                        acknowledge the receipt of the note of the 4th instant of Mr. Preston, envoy
                        extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of Hayti, stating that he had
                        been instructed to discuss directly with this Department the question raised
                        by a protest of Mr. Langston, the minister of the United States at Port au
                        Prince, against an act of the legislature of Hayti which levies a
                        discriminating tax against citizens of the United States engaged in trade in
                        that country.</p>
                <p>It appears that Mr. Langston deemed it his duty to protest against the
                        proposed discrimination, on the ground that the fifth article of the treaty
                        of 1864, between the United States and Hayti, stipulates that the citizens
                        of the contracting parties shall not be compelled to pay any contributions
                        whatever higher or other than those that are or may be paid by native
                        citizens.</p>
                <p>Mr. Preston contends that this stipulation is not applicable to the case. The
                        reasons which he assigns for this view are that such discriminations were
                        not only made anterior to the treaty, but also even subsequently to the date
                        of that instrument, without complaint on the part of citizens of the United
                        States or their representatives.</p>
                <p>The undersigned is not disposed to deny the correctness of this statement.
                        Whether true or otherwise, however, this cannot be regarded as <pb facs="0690" n="594" xml:id="pg_594"/> impairing the right to equality in
                        respect to license taxes, which is clearly and positively conferred by the
                        article of the treaty referred to. Citizens of Hayti are entitled to and
                        would receive the same privilege in this country for the same reason.</p>
                <p>Mr. Preston alleges that the question should be governed by the provision of
                        the sixth or thirty-fifth article of the treaty, rather than by the fifth.
                        Those articles, however, are obviously general in their stipulations, while
                        the fifth is specific, and applicable to the very case in controversy.</p>
                <p>The minister resident of the United States at Port au Prince had occasion
                        during the Presidency of General Domingue to protest against a similar act
                        of the legislature of Hayti. In consequence of that protest, the Haytian
                        Government for the time being gave notice of its wish to terminate the
                        treaty of 1864. That notice was, however, withdrawn by the subsequent
                        government. Mr. Preston supposes that that withdrawal was conditional upon a
                        similar withdrawal by the minister resident of the United States of his
                        protest against the objectionable license law.</p>
                <p>There is no proof in this Department, however, that any such condition was
                        authorized or even entertained.</p>
                <p>The treaty was concluded under very interesting circumstances, at a critical
                        period in the history of this country. Its provisions are believed to have
                        been well weighed by the parties. They are also believed to have been
                        mutually advantageous in practice. It would be a subject of regret that such
                        an instrument should be annulled when one of its stipulations should be
                        found to interfere with an act of the Haytian legislature which imposes a
                        discriminating tax upon citizens of the United States in that country.</p>
                <p>It may be as Mr. Preston says, that the number of persons affected by that
                        tax is not large; still, however small the number of citizens of the United
                        States who may be required to pay the discriminating tax, this government
                        has no discretion to waive their rights to equality, if, as is believed,
                        they are protected by treaty.</p>
                <p>It may also be said that if those numbers are few, it may be a matter for the
                        consideration of the Haytian Government whether the pecuniary advantage
                        which it would derive from exacting the discriminating tax would outweigh
                        the inconvenience of hazarding its good faith in violating the treaty.</p>
                <p>The undersigned avails himself of this occasion to renew to Mr. Preston the
                        assurances of his high consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WM. M. EVARTS.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
