<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-03-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-03-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="298" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                    <head>No. 274.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Marsh</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-03-31"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 31, 1879</date>. (Received April
                            17.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 822.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith a copy of
                        my recent note to the ministry of foreign affairs on the; case of
                        Largomarsino, and a copy and translation of the minister’s reply. If Mr.
                        Guiseppe Onesti had had the frankness to state in his letter to the
                        Department of State the fact, which was doubtless known to him, that
                        Largomarsino had still but a few months to serve, he would have saved all
                        parties unnecessary annoyance, as in such case I should not, without
                        positive instructions to that effect, have again addressed the Italian
                        Government on the subject.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>GEORGE P. MARSH.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 822.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Marsh</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Depretis</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: My attention has been again
                            called by the Secretary of State of the United States to the case of
                            Largomarsino, now serving as a conscript in the Italian army, which was
                            laid before the Italian Government by my note of 1877, and I am
                            instructed to make a further effort for his release. I have no new facts
                            and no new legal considerations to urge, but I venture to express the
                            hope that the peculiar hardship of the case, in the ruin of business
                            into which Largomarsino had entered, and of interests acquired in the
                            full belief of legal right, the length of time he has already served,
                            and the circumstances referred to in the accompanying communication from
                            a relative of his in America, may have some weight with the Italian
                            Government in inducing it to take a favorable reconsideration of the
                            facts, and to grant to Largomarsino the indulgence he desires.</p>
                        <p>I avail myself of this occasion to renew to your excellency the assurance
                            of my distinguished consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed>GEORGE P. MARSH.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in dispatch No.
                            882.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Peiroleri</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Marsh</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-03-26"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 26,
                                1879</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: I have received your note of the
                            15th instant, by which you call upon me again to use my good offices for
                            the release from military service of Giovanni Felice Largomarsino, at
                            present in the Italian army, on account of the serious injury to his
                            private affairs resulting from his continuing there.</p>
                        <p>I regret very much being unable to second your request, but in the face
                            of the laws of Italy it is not possible to make an exception in favor of
                            Largomarsino. Article 12 of the civil code of the kingdom explicitly
                            enacts that the loss of citizenship does not carry with it exemption
                            from the obligation of military service.</p>
                        <p>Matters of private interest, which, in fact, are common to all Italian
                            citizens on whom military service is incumbent, are not taken into
                            consideration by the laws on conscription. The royal government cannot,
                            therefore, hold them of any weight. Nevertheless, as I learn that
                            Lagomassina was enrolled on the 8th of January, 1877, I think it will
                            not be very long before he will be granted unlimited leave of absence,
                            as the term of service for the infantry in time of peace is only three
                            years.</p>
                        <p>Trusting that you will recognize the justness of these reasons which
                            prevent me from replying in a more favorable sense to your note, I avail
                            myself of this occasion to renew to you, Mr. Minister, the assurance of
                            my high consideration.</p>
                        <p>For the minister:</p>
                        <closer><signed>A. PEIROLERI.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>