<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 304.Mr. Bingham to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1879</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d328</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">328</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1879-08-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1879-08-18T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004" lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="confidence-building-measures" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257" lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579" lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662" lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-08-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-08-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="328" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d328">
                <head>No. 304.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bingham</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokei,
                                Japan</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-08-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 18, 1879</date>. (Received
                            September 29.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 941.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my No. 935, in which I inclosed
                        copies of certain correspondence between his excellency Mr. Terashima and
                        his excellency Mr. von Eisendecher, the German minister, in relation to the
                        violation by the latter of the quarantine regulations, I now have the honor
                        to inclose for your information the entire correspondence on the subject of
                        quarantine regulations between his excellency the minister for foreign
                        affairs and their excellencies the British and German ministers.</p>
                <p>From this correspondence it is clear that the representatives of Great
                        Britain and Germany in Japan deny the power of His Imperial Japanese
                        Majesty’s Government to declare and enforce a quarantine in Japanese waters
                        over the vessels of their respective countries without their consent and
                        approval. That each of these diplomatic representatives declined to approve,
                        and refused to respect or enforce the Japanese <pb facs="0767" n="671" xml:id="pg_671"/> quarantine regulations as heretofore proclaimed (of
                        which I advised you in my Nos. 918 and 925), is apparent in the inclosed
                        correspondence, as published in the Japan Herald of the 22d July last and
                        the 12th instant.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JNO. A. BINGHAM.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 941.—Extract from the
                                Japan Daily Herald, July 22, 1879.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Correspondence relating to quarantine.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The official correspondence relating to the institution of quarantine by
                            the Japanese Government, which we publish below, will serve to inform
                            the public of what has passed on that subject between the British
                            representative and the Japanese minister for foreign affairs, and tend
                            to remove the false impressions created by an article in the Japan Mail
                            and also one in the Tokei Times, both of them being written by persons
                            whose lack of knowledge of what they were writing about is conspicuous.
                            The intention of the writers is to put forward statements and advance
                            arguments which they hope may be pleasing to the government, with the
                            addition, in the case of the Tokei Times, of being, as usual, virulent
                            against Sir Harry Parkes, who seems to be the <hi rend="italic">bête
                                noir</hi> of the editor of that journal. The German Minister, in
                            this instance, however, divides the animadversions with him, and he is
                            accused of ordering the “Hesperia” to break quarantine, and of being
                            guilty of “countenancing a most flagrant rupture of the Japanese
                            regulations,” and he is threatened with “strenuous representations being
                            made to his government.” It seems to us that the servile officiousness
                            of these journals is calculated to be rather a source of embarrassment,
                            than otherwise, to the government they are so solicitous to serve. We
                            expect to be in a position also to print the correspondence relating to
                            the “Hesperia.”</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Translation.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-03">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">July</hi> 3,
                                1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to inform you that, in consequence
                            of the prevalence of cholera at Kobe and Ozaka, the inclosed provisional
                            regulations have been framed for the purpose of detaining vessels
                            arriving from those places at Nagaura, in Sagami, during a period of ten
                            days, and that they will be put in force as soon as our arrangements are
                            completed.</p>
                    <p>With respect,</p>
                    <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>TERASHIMA
                                    MUNENORI,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign
                                    Affairs.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency Sir <hi rend="smallcaps">Harry S. Parkes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>[The above note was only received by Sir H. Parkes, in consequence of
                                his absence from Yedo, on the morning of the 9th July.]</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-09">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">July</hi> 9,
                                1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my note of the 3d instant I informed
                            you that in connection with the prevalence of cholera in the localities
                            of Kobe and Ozaka, vessels arriving from those localities would be
                            detained during ten days at Nagauri, in Sagami, and inclosed some
                            provisional regulations; but I have now been informed by the authorities
                            that it has been decided that vessels which, upon being examined by the
                            health officer, are found to have had no cases of cholera during the
                            voyage, will be allowed to enter port after the lapse of seven days,
                            calculated from the day on which they left the diseased port.</p>
                    <p>I take, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>TERASHIMA MUNENORI</signed>, [<hi rend="smallcaps">l.
                                s.</hi>]<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign
                            Affairs</hi>.</closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency Sir <hi rend="smallcaps">Harry S. Parkes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-09">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">July</hi> 9,
                                1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to state that I have been informed
                            by the authorities that in consequence of the spread of cholera now
                            prevalent in various localities from Kioto and Ozaka to <pb facs="0768" n="672" xml:id="pg_672"/> the Shiga, Gifu, and Miye prefectures,
                            orders have been sent that travelers coming to Tokei by land will be
                            detained at points on the main lines of communication in the Yamanashi
                            and Gumba prefectures, and at Mishima, in the Shidzuoka prefecture,
                            during five days from the day of their arrival before being allowed to
                            pass on.</p>
                    <p>I take, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>TERASHIMA MUNENORI</signed>, [<hi rend="smallcaps">l.
                                s.</hi>]<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign
                            Affairs</hi>.</closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency Sir <hi rend="smallcaps">Harry S. Parkes</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Yedo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 12,
                                1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of Your Excellency’s note of the 3rd instant, informing me that
                            in consequence of the prevalence of cholera at Kobe and Ozaka vessels
                            arriving from those places bound for Kanagawa or Shihagawa will be
                            subject to a detention of ten days at Nagaura, and you inclose a set of
                            provisional regulations providing for the inspection and detention of
                            such vessels, which you observe will be put in force as soon as the
                            arrangements of your government are completed.</p>
                    <p>In a subsequent note of the 9th instant Your Excellency informs me that
                            the above-mentioned period of detention has been changed, and that those
                            vessels which are found to have had no cases of cholera on board during
                            the voyage from Kobe or Ozaka will be allowed to enter port after the
                            lapse of seven days, calculated from the day of departure from the
                            infected port.</p>
                    <p>In these notes Your Excellency makes no reference to foreign vessels, but
                            I learn from Her Majesty’s Consul at Kanagawa that the course which your
                            government proposes to adopt in their case has been stated in the
                            following terms in a letter addressed by the prefect of that port on the
                            7th instant to Mr. Bavier as Doyen of the Consular body.</p>
                    <p>The prefect observes, “I have received instructions from His Excellency
                            the minister for foreign affairs to inform you that when I receive from
                            Ozaka or Kobe a telegram announcing the departure of a foreign vessel
                            bound for this port, I am to report it to the consul under whose
                            jurisdiction she is, and he will be requested to accompany the health
                            officers on board, examine her, and, after consultation as to the
                            sanitary measures to be taken with her, she will be put in quarantine in
                            Nagaura Bay. In the event even of no telegram arriving in time from
                            Ozaka or Kobe, the Japanese man-of-war stationed on guard off Yokosuka
                            will, on perceiving a vessel coming in, proceed to stop her, and report
                            at once to me. I will then let the consul know and proceed as above
                            stated.”</p>
                    <p>At the interview which I had the honor to hold with Your Excellency on
                            the 9th instant you informed me that you had authorized the prefect to
                            make this communication to the senior Consul.</p>
                    <p>It affords me pleasure to assure Your Excellency of my readiness to
                            authorize Her Majesty’s Consul at Kanagawa to co-operate with the
                            prefect in applying to British vessels coming from Ozaka and Kobe, so
                            long as those ports remain in an infected state, a system of quarantine
                            in the sense of the general terms above stated, and I am now engaged in
                            making the arrangements necessary for this purpose, which I shall
                            speedily communicate to Your Excellency. I may mention, at once,
                            however, that it is not the Consul, but the medical officer whom he may
                            depute, who should visit British ships on their arrival off Kanagawa,
                            and that it will be requisite that the same medical officer should have
                            free access to any British vessel, her passengers or crew, during the
                            performance of quarantine.</p>
                    <p>In respect to the regulations inclosed in Your Excellency’s note of the
                            3d instant, I feel that, if these are to be regarded as the rules which
                            the Japanese Government intend to apply to their own ships, it would be
                            out of place for me to offer an opinion as to the suitableness of their
                            provisions. But presuming that Your Excellency’s government would
                            naturally desire to observe towards foreign vessels, as closely as
                            circumstances will permit, the quarantine system which they adopt in the
                            case of Japanese vessels, I feel that I should draw Your Excellency’s
                            attention to the incompleteness of these regulations as they at present
                            stand.</p>
                    <p>The deficiencies to which I allude will at once be observable on
                            comparing these regulations with those which Your Excellency
                            communicated to the foreign representatives at the close of last
                            August.</p>
                    <p>In those regulations Your Excellency’s government defined with much care
                            and minuteness the rules of quarantine which they then desired to
                            institute, and made provision for various important points and
                            contingencies which are left unnoticed in these new regulations.</p>
                    <p>Thus the regulations of last August provided that “upon the establishment
                            of a quarantine, a local board of quarantine shall be organized” (under
                            the direction of the central board of health at the capital) “at each of
                            the open ports, and shall consist <pb facs="0769" n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/> of properly educated and qualified Japanese or
                            foreign medical men, government officers, and a suitable staff of
                            assistants. The number of members shall be regulated in each instance by
                            the amount of shipping at the port, but in all cases shall be sufficient
                            to insure the speedy disposal of all matters of the quarantine.”</p>
                    <p>But by the new regulations all authority in regard to the enforcement of
                            quarantine is given to a single individual called “the medical
                            inspector,” and nothing is stated as to his nationality or
                            qualifications, as to the superior medical authority under which he
                            should act and by which he should be directed, or as to the organization
                            of the staff of health officers which is indispensable to the
                            institution of efficient quarantine.</p>
                    <p>Again, no distinction is made in the new regulations between the
                            treatment of a ship in which cholera has not appeared and one on board
                            of which the disease has already broken out. By the regulations of last
                            August the quarantine board were given power to reduce the detention to
                            less than seven days in the case of non-infected vessels, if the board
                            considered it safe to do so, but this judicious provision is not
                            mentioned in the new regulations. The latter contain no special
                            provision for limiting or regulating the visitation of a ship in
                            quarantine by persons from the shore. No provision is made for cases of
                            doubtful disease, and to remove non-choleraic patients to the cholera
                            hospital would not only be a very grave error, but also a flagrant
                            wrong, as their lives would thereby be placed in peril. No special
                            clause is introduced for the convenience of vessels in transit; no
                            mention is made of any modification of the term of detention of a ship
                            in the event of cholera breaking out during quarantine; and no
                            arrangement is made for the separation of suspected from infected ships
                            at the quarantine station.</p>
                    <p>All these points, however, are provided for in the regulations of last
                            August, and Your Excellency will therefore excuse me for observing that
                            I fail to understand the object of your government in substituting these
                            new and incomplete regulations for the much fuller and clearer rules
                            which were drawn up by the able medical officers composing the
                            quarantine commission which sat last summer.</p>
                    <p>Your Excellency I trust will perceive that it would be impossible to
                            establish an efficient system of quarantine without giving due attention
                            to the above-mentioned points and other details, with which I will not
                            burden this note, and also that I should be unable to authorize Her
                            Majesty’s Consuls to enforce the observation by British subjects of
                            quarantine rules which were manifestly inefficacious or impracticable.
                            In this case, however, I feel that it will not be difficult for me to
                            furnish such instructions to Her Majesty’s Consul at Kanagawa as will
                            enable him to co-operate effectively and cordially with the Japanese
                            health officers and to meet, as far as British subjects are concerned,
                            every prorjer requirement which quarancine entails.</p>
                    <p>For my own part I may observe that, though I do not share the opinion of
                            Your Excellency’s government, that a system of quarantine is preferable
                            to that of medical inspection, because quarantine, as Your Excellency is
                            aware, was-condemned by a large majority of the most eminent medical men
                            of all nations who formed the International Sanitary Congress at Vienna
                            in 1874, I am nevertheless entirely willing, in deference to the wishes
                            of your government, to co-operate with you earnestly in giving such a
                            system a trial in the present instance. The experience which will be
                            thus obtained will furnish evidence as to the degree of benefit that may
                            be derived from it. But I beg leave to mention that if the quarantine
                            which Your Excellency seeks to establish is to be carried out in the
                            manner which appears to have been followed in the case of the Japanese
                            passenger steamer “Genkai Maru,” it must prove entirely useless,</p>
                    <p>In that case, it appears that, some of the Japanese passengers were
                            allowed to leave the ship, while many Japanese, and also several foreign
                            visitors, some from Yokohama, were allowed to come off to her from the
                            shore, to mix freely with the passengers, to take meals on board, and
                            then to return to their houses. No doctor was appointed to remain on
                            board the ship in order to attend to the passengers, although they were
                            treated as infected persons, and as such should have been placed under
                            constant medical care, while the cattle on board were allowed to die for
                            want of food, and to create a degree of foulness in the ship, which
                            alone might have caused sickness to break out onboard. For some
                            particulars of the allegations made in this case I beg to refer Your
                            Excellency to the inclosed copies of letters addressed to Her Majesty’s
                            Consul by two passengers, Mr. Singleton and Mr. Mitchell, British
                            subjects, who were detained on board the “Genkai Maru,” and of a letter
                            addressed by the United States Consul-General at Kanagawa to his
                            colleagues. Your Excellency will perceive that these letters contain
                            grave complaints of the manner in which quarantine was conducted on
                            board that vessel.</p>
                    <p>I refrain from offering any obervations on the great difficulty which
                            your government will encounter in their efforts to institute the land
                            quarantine of which you informed me in another note of the 9th instant,
                            but it is obvious that unless that be efficient, maritime quarantine
                            must prove ineffective also. Allow me, however, to again assure Your
                            Excellency that I shall do all that lies in my power to promote the
                            objects of your government in this matter, as the spread of disease
                            concerns in equal degree <pb facs="0770" n="674" xml:id="pg_674"/> the
                            health and welfare of the Japanese people and the foreign residents of
                            this country.</p>
                    <p>I take advantage of this opportunity to renew to Your Excellency the
                            assurance of my high consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>HARRY S. PARKES.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>To His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Terashima Munenori.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British
                                        Legation</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Yedo</hi>
                            </placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 14, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my note of the 12th
                            instant, on the subject of the quarantine regulations issued by your
                            government on the 3d instant, I have now the honor to communicate to
                            Your Excellency a regulation which I have this day made and promulgated
                            for the purpose of vesting Her Majesty’s Consul at Kanagawa with such
                            legal powers as will enable him to co-operate effectually with the
                            Japanese authorities for preventing the introduction of cholera into
                            Kanagawa, by detaining British ships entering the Bay of Yedo from Hiogo
                            or Ozaka, and by causing them to submit to medical examination and other
                            precautions.</p>
                    <p>I take, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>HARRY S. PARKES.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>To His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Terashima Munenori</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 941.—Extract from the
                                Japan Daily Herald, August 12, 1879.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Correspondence relating to quarantine and the
                                “Hesperia.”</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Yokohama</hi>
                            </placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-04">4<hi rend="italic">th
                                        July</hi>, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nomura Yasushi</hi>, Esq.,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Kanagawa Ken Rei:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The <hi rend="italic">Doyen</hi> of the
                            Consular body has communicated to me the letter which you again this
                            year have written to him concerning quarantine measures against foreign
                            vessels arriving in Yokohama from infected ports.</p>
                    <p>I must again this year express my regret that you, in such an important
                            matter, which affects the rights of German vessels, did not confer with
                            me beforehand. I should willingly, jointly with you, have arranged such
                            measures as would not only have secured the desired object—the
                            prevention of cholera being imported—but would also have obviated your
                            communicating to me a measure taken by your government, the application
                            of which to German vessels I, under the existing circumstances, cannot
                            permit.</p>
                    <p>The standpoint which I again this year am obliged to occupy in the
                            quarantine question, is exactly the same as in the previous year.</p>
                    <p>I perfectly agree with you that precautionary measures ought to be taken,
                            without delay, in order to prevent cholera from being imported, and I
                            intend to meet your wishers in this respect by means of the circular to
                            German shipmasters arriving in Yokohama, which I inclose for your
                            perusal.</p>
                    <p>This circular enjoins on German shipmasters, as in the previous year, to
                            comply with such quarantine as the Kencho authorities may consider
                            necessary, until the provisional medical inspection to be ordered by the
                            imperial Consulate has been made.</p>
                    <p>I should again this year point out that it is of the greatest importance
                            that communications from the Japanese health-officers to me are made
                            with the least possible delay, and I therefore recommend that incoming
                            ships should be boarded and examined by them outside the harbor.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>E. ZAPPE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">circular.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>As cholera has appeared in Southern Japan, the Japanese Government, with
                            a view to prevent importation of the disease, has ordered that vessels
                            arriving from infected ports shall be inspected, and it has asked the
                            foreign Consuls to assist it in the carrying” out of such measures as
                            may prevent the spread of the disease; measures the necessity of which
                            is admitted by the undersigned, who therefore willingly has accorded the
                            Japanese Government his co-operation in their enforcement as far as
                            German ships are concerned. You are, therefore, hereby requested to
                            answer the inclosed questions with regard to the state of health on
                            board your ship, to write, your answers on the <pb facs="0771" n="675" xml:id="pg_675"/> space left open, and hand the same to the Japanese
                            health officer who presents this circular. If the latter, in consequence
                            of your statements, or of examination of patients on hoard, should
                            inform you that it is necessary that you go into quarantine then you
                            shall anchor in an isolated place, and there await the medical
                            inspection which I shall immediately cause to be made, and, in the mean
                            time, with quarantine flag hoisted, abstain from all communication with
                            the land.</p>
                    <p>To all masters of German merchant-vessels arriving from Southern
                            Japan.</p>
                    <p>The Imperial German consul,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ZAPPE</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Yokohama</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">the</hi> 4<hi rend="italic">th July</hi>, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Yokohama</hi>
                            </placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-08">8<hi rend="italic">th
                                        July</hi>, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nomura Yasushi</hi>, Esq.,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Kanagawa Ken Rei:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 4th instant I had the honor to
                            inform you in how far I would be able to assist you in enforcing the
                            proposed quarantine measures with regard to German ships.</p>
                    <p>At the same time I sent you a circular that authorizes the Japanese
                            health officers to board German vessels and take provisional measures,
                            which remain in force until this Consulate has been able to give
                            definitive orders.</p>
                    <p>This morning I received, through His Danish Majesty’s consul-general,
                            another letter from you, in which you so far modify the contents of your
                            letter, dated the 1st July, to the <hi rend="italic">Doyen</hi> of the
                            consular body, that incoming vessels are not to be put under quarantine
                            until the consul and the Japanese health officers have agreed
                            thereupon.</p>
                    <p>But I cannot consider my letter of the 4th instant answered by that
                            communication, and I therefore request you kindly to inform me, as soon
                            as convenient, whether you feel inclined to accept the way in which I
                            proposed to carry out quarantine measures against German vessels.</p>
                    <p>I consider it necessary that we should arrive at an understanding in this
                            respect before German ships arrive in this port from Hiogo.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ZAPPE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-10">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">July</hi> 10,
                                1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">To <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Zappe</hi>, Esq.,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">His Imperial German Majesty’s Consul:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your dispatch dated the 8th instant. The various points with
                            regard to the examination of German vessels, as mentioned in your
                            dispatch of the 4th instant, have not by any means been cast aside.</p>
                    <p>I have received information by telegram that the German steamer
                            “Hesperia” weighed anchor from the port of Kobe at 10 p.m. yesterday;
                            and I shall accordingly cause the inspecting officers to carry with them
                            the document sent by you, and measures shall be taken in the sea off
                            Yokoska, according to the regulations mentioned in your letter. I beg
                            you, therefore, to take note of the above.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>NOMURA YASUSHI</signed>, [<hi rend="smallcaps">l.
                                s.</hi>]<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Ken Rei of Kanagawa.</hi>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Yokohama</hi>
                            </placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-12">12<hi rend="italic">th
                                        July</hi>, 1879</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nomura Yasushi</hi>, Esq.,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Kanagawa Ken Rei:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the communication which you
                            caused to be made to me last night through Mr. Kono Michitomo, namely
                            that the German steamer “Hesperia,” coming from Kobe, had been sent to
                            the quarantine ground, and, in the opinion of the Japanese health
                            officers, would have to undergo a quarantine of seven days from her
                            departure from Hiogo, I have to inform you that chief staff-surgeon, Dr.
                            Gutschow, will this morning, under instructions from the Consul, proceed
                            on board the “Hesperia” and make an inspection, the results of which he
                            will afterwards report to me.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to request you to inform the superior officer on the
                            quarantine station of this, in order that Dr. Gutschow may have such
                            facilities as are requisite for him to attain his object in view.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ZAPPE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Yokohama</hi>
                            </placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-12">12<hi rend="italic">th
                                        July</hi>, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">To the same:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of my letter of this
                            morning, I hereby inform you that I, accompanied by chief staff-surgeon,
                            Dr. Gutschow, went to-day in His Majesty’s gunboat, “Wolf,” to the
                            quarantine ground at Nagaura, from whence I have just returned.</p>
                    <p>The result of the inspection of the “Hesperia,” which I, from want of
                            time, am unable <pb facs="0772" n="676" xml:id="pg_676"/> to forward
                            this evening <hi rend="italic">in extenso</hi>, is briefly this, that
                            the state of health and other conditions on board are so favorable that
                            the immediate release of the ship from quarantine cannot apparently, or
                            even probably, expose Yokohama to any danger of cholera being
                            imported.</p>
                    <p>This caused me to ask Mr. Kojima, the superior officer on the quarantine
                            station, to release the Hesperia at once, and as he declared that he had
                            no authority to do so, then I requested him to telegraph for orders to
                            that effect.</p>
                    <p>No answer having arrived in Nagaura by 7 o’clock p.m., I returned to
                            Yokohama, and I now have the honor directly to address to you the
                            request that you will, without further delay, order the quarantine of
                            the Hesperia to cease, as the same, in view of the state of health on
                            board, no longer appears necessary.</p>
                    <p>Finally. I urgently ask you to let me kindly know your decision by letter
                            this very night, or, at the very latest, before 10 a.m. to-morrow.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ZAPPE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokei</hi>
                            </placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-11">11<hi rend="italic">th
                                        July</hi>, 1879, <hi rend="italic">evening.</hi>
                            </date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Terashima
                                Munenori</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister of Foreign
                                Affairs:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor respectfully to inform
                            Your Excellency that I have requested chief staff-surgeon, Dr. Gutschow,
                            of Yokohama, to proceed to-morrow on board the German steamer Hesperia,
                            which is now provisionally detained at the quarantine grounds, there to
                            make a medical inspection, and report the result to me.</p>
                    <p>Your Excellency will have the goodness to make this known to the
                            quarantine authorities, in order that no difficulties shall arise at the
                            place.</p>
                    <p>I request your excellency to accept, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>VON EISENDECHER.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokei</hi>
                            </placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-07-12">12<hi rend="italic">th
                                        July</hi>, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">von
                                Eisendecher</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Imperial German Minister
                                Resident:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have had the honor to receive Your
                            Excellency’s favor of yesterday, in which you inform me that you have
                            instructed the German chief staff-surgeon, Dr. Gutschow, to proceed on
                            board the German steamer Hesperia, which is now, according to the
                            quarantine regulations, detained at Soshu Nagaura, there to make a
                            medical inspection, and in which Your Excellency requests me to take the
                            necessary measures, in order that no difficulties shall arise at the
                            place. I have immediately notified the authorities concerned, but, at
                            the same time, I must respectfully inform Your Excellency that the
                            inspection by the said medical officer can have no influence on the
                            duration of the prescribed term of quarantine.</p>
                    <p>With the highest consideration,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>TERASHIMA MUNENORI,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister of
                                    Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
