<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-11-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="358" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d358">
                    <head>No. 329.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-11-02"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 2, 1878</date>.
                            (Received November 19.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 827.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my No. 798, of the 5th ultimo, I sent the
                        note of the acting minister of foreign affairs, denying the right to
                        diplomatic intervention in the case of the forced loans exacted from Mr.
                        Walter Henry in Chihuahua, and my reply thereto.</p>
                    <p>The minister has seen proper to continue the discussion, by a note of the 9th
                        ultimo, in which he seems to profess an ignorance of the outrages inflicted
                        upon the American citizens resident in Chihuahua during the last revolution;
                        lays down the principle that the remedy, in case of forced loans and
                        military exactions, is an appeal to the Mexican courts; indicates that such
                        claims of American citizens must go into the general liquidation, which
                        means that they are to be considered a part of the interior <pb facs="0824" n="728" xml:id="pg_728"/> debt; and again refuses to consider the demand
                        of the legation that the claim of the murdered American citizen Henry be
                        adjusted through diplomatic intervention.</p>
                    <p>In my reply, inclosed herewith, I have thought it necessary to refer to the
                        general character of the exactions and outrages perpetrated upon American
                        residents of Chihuahua by the authorities of the present government; have
                        shown the folly of seeking redress through the courts, and that the only
                        method is by a diplomatic resort to the federal executive; that the latter
                        has been repeatedly recognized; and that our government cannot consent to
                        allow the claims of its citizens of the character in question to be made a
                        part of the interior debt, which is virtually worthless, a course which
                        amounts to an absolute confiscation of property, without compensation and by
                        wholly illegal means.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                827.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Avila</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-10-09"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 9,
                                1878</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: I have received your excellency’s
                            note of the 4th instant, in which, after it had been made known that the
                            vouchers for certain sums of money claimed from the Government of Mexico
                            in favor of Walter Henry were opportunely transmitted to the department
                            of finance for its information, your excellency insists upon considering
                            the action which you take in the name of the said Henry as a matter
                            which should be adjusted by diplomatic intervention, a position which
                            your excellency supports by mentioning, without specifying them, many
                            possible occurrences or consequences of the state of disorder existing
                            on the northern frontier of the republic in the year 1876.</p>
                        <p>Your excellency will permit me to state and here make plain, that it is a
                            principle of international law, universally admitted, that the person
                            who establishes himself in a certain country subjects himself by this
                            act to the laws existing there, and performs an act of tacit submission
                            to the regulations and practices in force; and this could not reasonably
                            be otherwise, since, on the contrary, it would result that the condition
                            of the foreigner would not only be different, but better and more
                            favorable than that of citizens. This principle being recognized, as
                            without any doubt whatever it is, by your excellency, the intervention
                            which you now claim in the matter of Walter Henry cannot be permitted
                            except in the case of a denial of justice, or the pronunciation of a
                            sentence which should be in notorious violation of the laws. As in the
                            case of Walter Henry such antecedents have not only not taken place, but
                            it has not even been presented before the Mexican tribunals, nor has the
                            republic given occasion for discussion respecting that which has just
                            been submitted to its authorities and is now pending examination, the
                            President has communicated to me instructions to say to your excellency,
                            that in virtue of former decisions it is not possible for him to admit
                            the diplomatic intervention of your excellency in the present state of
                            this matter, although, as I had the honor to inform you in my former
                            note, it has been submitted to the department of finance, which, without
                            doubt, will take it into consideration in the character of the
                            collection of a credit against the national treasury.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to reiterate to your excellency the assurances of my
                            very distinguished consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed>ELENTERIO AVILA.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 827.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Avila</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-10-22"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 22,
                                1878</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The pressure of other business has
                            heretofore prevented me from acknowledging receipt of your honor’s note
                            of the 9th instant, relating to the claims of Mr. Walter Henry presented
                            by this legation.</p>
                        <p>While I have no disposition to enter at length upon a discussion of the
                            principles <pb facs="0825" n="729" xml:id="pg_729"/> raised by your
                            honor’s notes on this subject, I deem it necessary to make some
                            observations upon your note of the 9th instant.</p>
                        <p>Your honor does not properly interpret my note of the 4th instant, when
                            you imply that I insist upon diplomatic intervention, because the
                            vouchers in the claim were transmitted to the department of finance. My
                            said note does not admit of a doubt that it was occasioned by the
                            declaration made by your honor that, a denial of justice not having
                            occurred, there was no motive for diplomatic intervention.</p>
                        <p>Your honor says I support my position by mentioning, without specifying
                            them, many possible occurrences or consequences of the state of disorder
                            existing on the northern frontier in 1876. Does your honor doubt these
                            occurrences? or was it designed to challenge me to a recital of the long
                            list of illegal and arbitrary exactions and outrages inflicted by the
                            authorities of the present government upon American citizens in the
                            State of Chihuahua during the last revolutions? These matters have been
                            frequently discussed by me with the late minister of foreign affairs.
                            Some of the American sufferers have made the journey of twelve hundred
                            miles to this capital to lay their complaints in person before the
                            Mexican Government, one of whom was the murdered man; in whose behalf I
                            have been pressing the claim now the subject of discussion. These
                            outrages have been widely published in the United States and have called
                            forth the indignation of my countrymen. They have led my government to
                            send urgent and positive instructions to this legation to secure a
                            redress of the wrongs done American citizens. If detailed demands have
                            not as yet been presented in all these cases, it has been for the reason
                            mentioned in my note, 2d instant, when I first brought your honor’s
                            attention to the claim of Mr. Henry. But in verbal conferences I have
                            narrated to the late minister in charge of the foreign office repeated
                            instances of forced loans having been levied on American residents in
                            Chihuahua by revolutionary chiefs, so often repeated at times as to have
                            been exacted from one mercantile house within six months no less than
                            thirteen separate and distinct times. And in default or hesitation in
                            paying promptly these illegal and arbitrary exactions, American citizens
                            have been torn from their houses and families by bands of armed soldiers
                            and held as prisoners until the money was paid. They have been required
                            in lieu of personal military service, to furnish arms, horses, or other
                            materials of war to sustain the revolution. Upon refusal to pay
                            oft-repeated levies, after having in individual instances contributed
                            tens of thousands of dollars, they have been carried off to the
                            mountains by roving bands of revolutionists, $50,000 as ransom being
                            demanded, and in default of payment in one case an American citizen was
                            held a prisoner for thirty days by one of these bands acting under the
                            direct orders of the present governor of Chihuahua, exposed in the
                            mountains to all kinds of hardships of weather and dangers of warfare,
                            and finally compelled to pay $3,500 to secure his release.</p>
                        <p>I did not think it necessary in presenting Mr. Henry’s claim to make a
                            recital of all these outrages, nor can I believe your honor now desires
                            it, notwithstanding the apparent challenge in your note of the 9th
                            instant; I only deemed it requisite to present to the Mexican Government
                            the unquestioned written evidences of the forced indebtedness contracted
                            by the chiefs, who were duly commissioned by the present chief
                            magistrate of the republic, in support of Mr. Henry’s claim.</p>
                        <p>But your honor says the President cannot allow the intervention of my
                            government in behalf of one of its citizens, except in case of a denial
                            of justice or the pronunciation by a court of a sentence in violation of
                            law. What can constitute a greater denial of justice than that which
                            exists in this case Military chiefs having the commission of General
                            Porfirio Diaz, and sustaining his cause in the late revolution, having
                            captured the city of Chihuahua, notify Mr. Henry that he is required
                            within a certain number of hours to appear before officers designated
                            and pay specified sums of money. Upon hesitation on his part, a file of
                            soldiers breaks open his residence and carries him off to the military
                            authorities, where he is held a prisoner till the last farthing is paid
                            or secured. This is an illegal and unconstitutional act, and so
                            pronounced by the supreme court of the nation, which says that not even
                            in time of war has the executive or military the power to levy taxes.
                            What opportunity had Henry to appeal to a court to interpose its
                            authority to protect him? The strong arm of the military power had him
                            in custody. But even if this were not the case, there were no courts in
                            existence. The revolutionary authorities had overthrown the tribunals
                            and the judges had fled or concealed themselves. The money once being
                            paid, there was no other method of obtaining its return but to await the
                            establishment of a new government and apply to the executive authority
                            under that government. This Mr. Henry did to the authorities in
                            Chihuahua, and they declined to restore to him the money exacted, but
                            referred him to the general government in this capital. I have already
                            stated that he came to this city nearly a year ago, and presented his
                            claim to the minister of the treasury, securing my unofficial
                            intervention. Nearly twelve months passed by without even a preliminary
                            answer being given to either Mr. Henry or to this legation. Upon the
                            occasion of his brutal murder, and the attempt to plunder his property
                            by Mexcan officials, of which this legation received authentic
                            information, the diplomatic presentation of the claim occurred. There is
                            nothing unusual <pb facs="0826" n="730" xml:id="pg_730"/> in this mode
                            of procedure. The Mexican foreign office has repeatedly recognized such
                            intervention in similar cases. I was therefore taken by surprise by the
                            position assumed by your honor, especially in view of the recent event
                            on the Rio Grande frontier.</p>
                        <p>Your honor says the case has not even been presented before the Mexican
                            tribunals. What precedent is there for such a course? Is not this class
                            of claims recognized as within the jurisdiction of the executive
                            department of the government? And is there not a special Obligation
                            resting upon it to examine and adjust these liabilities?</p>
                        <p>If Mr. Henry’s heirs are required to institute a legal proceeding to
                            recover the forced loans exacted to sustain the revolution of the
                            present government, against whom is the suit to be brought? Must it be
                            against the military officers who levied the loans? In that case, as
                            General Donato G____, to whom the most of the loans were paid, is dead,
                            shall his heirs or estate, if he has any, be made defendants in a suit?
                            Would you expect a proceeding to be instituted against General Trias,
                            now governor of Chihuahua? Would it be probable that any tribunal in
                            that State would mulct the man who was the chief instrument in
                            establishing the very government which gave it existence, and especially
                            for the acts which gave the revolution resources to triumph? Your honor
                            can hardly mean that the heirs of the murdered Henry shall seek to bring
                            the republic into court and prosecute a suit against it in these claims?
                            The simple asking of these questions is their own answer. It is well
                            known that the universal proceeding in the collection of these claims is
                            through the executive department of the federal government.</p>
                        <p>Nor can I agree to the course which, in the closing part of the note,
                            your honor indicates will be given to Mr. Henry’s claim, when you say
                            that it has been submitted to the department of Hacienda, which will
                            doubtless take it into consideration in the character of a credit
                            against the national treasury. If it is meant by this that the claim for
                            money which has been forced from Mr. Henry at the point of the bayonet,
                            by military chiefs, without law or justice, and contrary to the Mexican
                            constitution, is to partake of the character of, and be placed on a
                            level with, the interior debt of the country, I must here protest
                            against such a course, as I have heretofore done informally to the
                            minister of finance in other cases. As that debt has no market value,
                            and there is no early prospect of payment of either principal or
                            interest of the same, my government cannot consent that the property of
                            American citizens, taken in the manner as was that of Mr. Henry, shall
                            be subject to such a virtual confiscation. In this, and in all similar
                            cases, it will expect the Government of Mexico to make full reparation
                            for all the losses and damages sustained by American citizens at the
                            hands of its military authorities. The argument, often before made to
                            me, that such a course would make the condition of foreigners in Mexico
                            better than that of Mexican citizens, has no force with my government.
                            It is enough for it to know that American citizens are treated with
                            cruelty and outrage by military authorities, and in an arbitrary and
                            illegal manner; that their money and property are forced from them under
                            military duress. My government is not required in such cases to
                            investigate whether the same injuries and wrongs are inflicted upon
                            Mexican citizens. It would be a source of regret to know that the
                            established and recognized Government of Mexico had not the power and
                            the sense of justice to right the wrongs of its own citizens. But the
                            Government of the United States would not, on this account, fail to
                            protect its own citizens in Mexico, and require a reparation of the
                            outrages and damages sustained by them at the hands of those who
                            inflicted them, now the constituted authorities of Mexico.</p>
                        <p>I improve this occasion to renew to your honor the sentiments of my high
                            consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>