<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-05-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-05-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="422" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d422">
                    <head>No. 393.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Christiancy</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Lima,
                                Peru</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-05-20"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 20, 1879</date>. (Received June
                            16.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 15.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose to you the copies
                        of two letters of Hon. Thomas A. Osborn, of the 2d and 26th April, in
                        reference to the use of the American flag by foreign-built ships, and a copy
                        of my answer to same of this date, so far as the case of the Itata is
                        involved.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>I. P. CHEISTIANCY.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 15.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Osborn</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Gibbs</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Santiago, Chili</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-04-02"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 2, 1879</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the receipt of your
                            note of the 15th ultimo, referring to your action in the matter of the
                            steamship Itata.</p>
                        <p>It appears that you directed the consul at Callao to notify the captain
                            of the Itata that he had no right to use the American flag, and that you
                            advised the consul against giving such vessel a clearance or any other
                            document.</p>
                        <pb facs="0974" n="878" xml:id="pg_878"/>
                        <p>I find that I am unable to agree with you fully in your understanding of
                            the law, and I have therefore deemed it advisable to communicate with
                            the State Department on the subject and solicit the advice of the
                            honorable Secretary. I am informed by those competent to know that it
                            has been the custom for foreign-built ships wholly owned by American
                            citizens to carry the American flag, and that their right to do so has
                            been generally recognized by our public officers on this coast.</p>
                        <p>To avoid any clashing, however, I have directed that only vessels duly
                            registered under the law shall be cleared from Valparaiso to Peruvian
                            ports by our consul, until he is further advised.</p>
                        <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>THOMAS A. OSBORN.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Gibbs</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Minister, Peru.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 15.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Osborn</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Christiancy</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Santiago, Chili</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-04-26"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 26, 1879</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I see published in the Lima papers what
                            purports to be a note addressed by Mr. Gibbs to the foreign minister in
                            Lima, under date of the 7th instant, which I fear may result in
                            seriously imperiling the property interests of American citizens in
                            foreign-built ships on this coast.</p>
                        <p>It is unquestionably true that no law of the United States directly
                            authorizes this class of vessels to carry the American flag. Nor is
                            there any statute, so far as I have observed, directly conferring this
                            privilege upon any class of vessels whatever; but that the Government
                            recognizes the right of American citizens to purchase foreign-built
                            ships, and acknowledges its obligation to protect them in their property
                            thus acquired, is an undoubted fact.</p>
                        <p>I am credibly informed that there are many vessels of this character,
                            owned by American citizens, now doing business on this coast. Some of
                            them have been so engaged many years, and have been recognized by our
                            consular officers as American vessels. The consul at Valparaiso informs
                            me that only yesterday a vessel so owned came into port flying the
                            American flag, having been dispatched in due form by our consul at
                            Lambayeque, Peru. Her papers show that she was purchased by an American
                            citizen and the bill of sale recorded in the consulate at Lambayeque, as
                            is provided in sections 220 and 221 of Consular Regulations.</p>
                        <p>I am not prepared to believe that the State Department intended to be
                            understood as saying that our citizens might purchase foreign-built
                            ships, but that they should not sail them; hence, I cannot agree with
                            Mr. Gibbs in his understanding of section 226 of Consular Regulations. A
                            vessel without a country, to me, seems an anomaly. It would be in quite
                            as pitiable a condition as was the man without a country, of whom we
                            have read. To fully guard against fraud in these transfers, however, it
                            seems to me that some more stringent rules concerning them should be
                            adopted. I should be pleased to exchange views with you on this
                            subject.</p>
                        <p>Permit me to call your attention to the opinion of Mr. Cushing, referred
                            to on page 6 of the Digest of Opinions and Leading Cases on
                            International Law.</p>
                        <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>THOMAS A. OSBORN.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">I. P. Christiancy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Minister, Peru.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 15.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Christiancy</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Osborn</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Lima, Peru</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-05-19"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 19,
                                1879</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your note of the 2d ultimo to my
                            predecessor and that of the 26th ultimo to me have been received.</p>
                        <p>I did not answer the first note, as it was rather a question between you
                            and Mr. Gibbs which would soon be decided by the State Department, Mr.
                            Gibbs having written to the department fully on the subject.</p>
                        <p>I expected to have had an answer to that dispatch by the last mail, but
                            no mail came from New York this week.</p>
                        <pb facs="0975" n="879" xml:id="pg_879"/>
                        <p>While awaiting the reply of the department I will only take occasion to
                            say that I am inclined to agree with the decision arrived at by Mr.
                            Gibbs in the case of the Itata, but I think I should not have placed the
                            decision wholly, at least, upon the same ground upon which he rested
                            it.</p>
                        <p>I am prepared to admit, or at least do not for the present dispute, that
                            there may be cases in which a foreign-built ship, purchased and owned by
                            an American citizen, especially if officered and run by American
                            citizens, might be entitled to the protection of the American flag
                            outside of American waters.</p>
                        <p>It is not necessary to controvert your statement “that the government
                            recognizes the right of American citizens to purchase foreign-built
                            ships and acknowledges its obligation to protect them in their property
                            thus acquired;” but certainly no mere <hi rend="italic">form</hi> of
                            transfer under circumstances which show that transfer to be merely
                            formal and colorable, for the purpose of fraudulently obtaining the
                            protection of our flag, can create any such obligation on the part of
                            the United States, nor entitle the parties making use of so palpable a
                            fraud to claim protection, especially when the circumstances are such
                            that to grant the use of our flag virtually to one of the belligerents
                            might justly be complained of by the other belligerent as a breach of
                            that good faith which the duties and advantages of neutrality impose
                            upon the United States.</p>
                        <p>If our government could be bound by the necromancy of any such mere
                            forms, its good faith as a neutral and its peaceful relations might at
                            any moment be impaired or endangered at the will of any adventurer or
                            any belligerent who might choose, for his own private interest, to avail
                            himself of the like formal transfer. In such a case such mere formal
                            transfer is, in my opinion, not even <hi rend="italic">prima-facie</hi>
                            evidence of a real and <hi rend="italic">bona-fide</hi> sale; but in the
                            absence of express law, the onus of proving the good faith of the
                            transfer should, I think, rest, upon the pretended purchaser, and he
                            must show the fact satisfactorily before he can claim any right to the
                            protection of the American flag.</p>
                        <p>Perhaps a certificate of a collector of customs as to citizenship and
                            transfer might give a <hi rend="italic">prima-facie</hi> right. But this
                            we need not discuss, as clearly there was no such certificate here; and
                            all the circumstances connected with the transfer, so far as I have any
                            information, tend to show it to have been a palpable trick, a mere
                            colorable sale.</p>
                        <p>I await the Secretary’s opinion upon the dispatch of Mr. Gibbs, and you
                            will doubtless receive a communication upon the same matter.</p>
                        <p>I am, &amp;c.</p>
                        <closer><signed>I. P. CHRISTIANCY.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas A. Osborn</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary,
                                    Santiago, Chili.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>