<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 454.Mr. Stevens to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1879</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d486</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">486</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1879-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1879-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recbfb6dc62c599a48" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Tobacco</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="486"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d486">
                <head>No. 454.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Stevens</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Stockholm</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-05-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 19, 1879</date>. (Received June
                        9.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 42.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Swedish Diet has just completed the
                    legislation increasing the custom duties on articles imported into this country,
                    and the same is in force from this day, according to royal proclamation of this
                    date. The increase has been made on the following articles, and the duties
                    hereafter to be collected are represented by the annexed figures:</p>
                <p>Ether and spirits of ether, or so-called Hoffman’s drops, various kinds of
                    mixtures and preparations of ether, acetic ether, cognac, rum and arrack,
                    essence or oil, also fruit ether, 3 crowns per kanna. (The kanna is about ½ of
                    an English gallon.)</p>
                <p>Rum and spirits in casks: Of grain, potatoes, or other roots, per kanna: Of
                    arrack made from rice, sugar, or grapes, containing 50 per cent. of alcohol, 1
                    crown and 50 öre.</p>
                <p>When the said rum or spirits is made in France and is imported directly by sea, 1
                    kanna containing 50 per cent. alcohol will be required to pay a duty of 1 crown
                    and 15 öre.</p>
                <p>Rum or spirits made of other fruits, containing 50 per cent of alcohol, will pay
                    1 crown and 50 öre per kanna.</p>
                <p>In bottles or jugs, all kinds of rum or spirits, without regard to ratio of
                    alcohol, will pay 2 crowns and 30 öre per kanna.</p>
                <p>Coffee, 11 öre per pound.</p>
                <p>Sugar, all kinds of refined, such as loaf, candied, cake, also crushed and
                    pulverized, per cwt., 14 crowns.</p>
                <p>Sugar, unrefined, in color not darker than Kb. 18 of the Holland standard used in
                    commerce, of which the normal test is held by the <pb facs="1055" n="959"
                        xml:id="pg_959"/> general custom-house administration at the disposal of the
                    custom-houses concerned, per cwt., 14 crowns.</p>
                <p>Sugar darker than the above-mentioned standard, also if merchandise comes in a
                    dissolved or liquid state, per cwt., 10 crowns.</p>
                <p>Tobacco: Raw, leaf, and stalk, per pound, 42 öre; manufactured, cigars,
                    cigarettes, per pound, 1 crown and 30 öre; cut, per pound, 50 öre; ground or
                    powdered, per pound, 50 öre; folded, twisted, pressed, per pound, 50 öre; blocks
                    or corots, per pound, 55 öre.</p>
                <p>Wines all kinds, containing 21 per cent. or less of alcohol, in casks, per pound,
                    7 öre.</p>
                <p>Wines all kinds, 21 per cent. or less of alcohol, in bottles, per kanna, 55
                    öre.</p>
                <p>Wines containing more than 21 per cent. of alcohol, in casks, per pound, 20 öre;
                    in bottles, per kanna, 2 crowns.</p>
                <p>Vinegar all kinds, per pound, 8 öre.</p>
                <p>The excise duties on the following articles have been raised to the annexed
                    figures: Swedish brandy, pure, 1 crown per kanna; Swedish brandy, second class,
                    1 crown per kanna.</p>
                <p>When said brandy is exported the excise duty is refunded in full, and at the
                    ratio of 1 crown and 2 öre per kanna when it has been purified.</p>
                <p>The provision relating to refunding the excise in case of exportation goes into
                    effect October 1, 1879.</p>
                <p>In every case where pound is used in this communication, the Swedish pound, or 94
                    of the English or American pound is meant, and the kanna signifies 2.3 imperial
                    quarts, American or English standard.</p>
                <p>The above changes in the custom duties are in force from this date in Norway as
                    well as Sweden.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOHN L. STEVENS.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
