<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-05-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="49" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                    <head>No. 38.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kasson</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-05-14"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 14, 1879</date>.
                            (Received May 29.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 200.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The good order of this city, with its million
                        of inhabitants, its exemption from scandal in its financial and other
                        departments, its remarkably <pb facs="0161" n="65" xml:id="pg_65"/> small
                        number of crimes of violence and against property, its comparative freedom
                        from public beggary, the cleanliness of its streets, and its excellent
                        sanitary condition, have induced me to make a study of its organization and
                        administration.</p>
                    <p>The frequent agitation of questions relating to municipal government in the
                        United States, the constant demand for more effective grants or limitations
                        of municipal jurisdiction, and your own former official interest in these
                        questions, have induced me to forward to you the results of this
                        investigation. It may be that the system, prevailing here, the result of an
                        experience of centuries, will afford useful suggestions to some of the
                        American cities which are seeking improved systems and better securities of
                        good administration in municipal affairs.</p>
                    <p>The manner in which they have here solved the question of suffrage, so that
                        no one class of the population can secure absolute control of the interests
                        of all others, is especially worthy of consideration. This principle might
                        equally be adopted where the suffrage is universal, and where the
                        distinction of interests may require a different classification.</p>
                    <p rend="center">I.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">the municipal theory</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The theory of the municipality appears to be this: It has no sovereign
                        rights. It is merely a local corporation, designed chiefly to protect the
                        property and promote the business interests of the residents within its
                        jurisdiction, under the limitations of general laws imposed from without.
                        Its management is therefore committed to those who have vested interests in
                        it, who contribute to its support, bear its liabilities, suffer from its
                        mismanagement, and who are profited by its honest and successful
                        administration. It recognizes the existence in its midst of conflicting
                        local, class, and personal interests, and the danger of allowing any one
                        interest, whether of wealth, or of labor, or of locality, to obtain a
                        numerical control. To avoid this result, it divides the electoral population
                        into three great classes, each of which chooses its own representation in
                        the governing council.</p>
                    <p>In this way it becomes difficult to impose burdens upon one interest to the
                        exclusive advantage of another. Those who contribute nothing to defray the
                        expenses, and who bear none of the responsibilities of mismanagement, are
                        not considered as veritable stockholders in the municipality, and are not
                        allowed to elect its managers. It is, in effect, a modification of the
                        principle on which nearly all corporate business enterprises are founded,
                        such as railroads, insurance companies, &amp;c.: that those who furnish the
                        means and bear the losses should Control the administration of the
                        municipality.</p>
                    <p>I am informed that certain smaller towns of Switzerland have so successfully
                        carried this principle into execution in former years that they have ceased
                        to impose taxes and have become dividend-paying corporations. Wise and
                        interested management has there in the course of time accumulated sufficient
                        public property to provide from its rents for all town expenses, and leave a
                        surplus for distribution to the citizens. In these towns a vote of the
                        corporation was necessary to admit a new citizen, who was also upon his
                        admission required to pay a capital sum representing his interest in the
                        common property.</p>
                    <p>In Vienna, however, which is very far from such a degree of financial
                        prosperity, there is only required from municipal voters sufficient
                        qualification of some sort to indicate a vested interest in the welfare of
                        the <pb facs="0162" n="66" xml:id="pg_66"/> city, and some responsibility
                        for its administration and expenditures. To this end the law arranges the
                        organic control in the following manner:</p>
                    <p rend="center">II.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">electors and their
                        classification</hi>.</p>
                    <p>One electoral group is composed of those householders in the city who pay 500
                        florins or more of land or house tax; and of other persons who contribute
                        upon the industry pursued by them in the city, or upon their income, a tax
                        of not less than 100 florins.</p>
                    <p>Another electoral group embraces all householders paying taxes on real
                        property in the city to an amount between 10 florins and 500 florins; all
                        employés of the municipality, of the state, and of the court (whether active
                        or pensioned), who pay at least 10 florins of income tax; all officers of
                        the permanent militia, all clergymen of the recognized Christian churches,
                        all Jewish rabbis, “doctors” of all faculties whose degrees were conferred
                        by an Austrian university, all masters and professors of public schools. It
                        is intended to include in this group all the resident active, educated
                        classes, irrespective of their property—such as the medical and legal
                        professions, engineers, architects, &amp;c., all of whom contribute to the
                        revenue in some form.</p>
                    <p>The remaining electoral group is formed of all other persons who are taxed
                        within the city (upon either industry or income) less than 100 florins. All
                        the smaller industries and occupations of the city are here represented. All
                        “citizens” of Vienna not paying the amount of tax required, nor belonging to
                        one of the liberal professions, vote with this group.</p>
                    <p>Austrians <hi rend="italic">living in the town</hi>, but not “citizens” of
                        Vienna, have also the right to vote with their proper group, if they pay at
                        least 10 florins of direct taxes on houses possessed or trade carried on by
                        them within the city, or if they are rated with at least 20 florins of
                        income tax.</p>
                    <p>Those who do not exercise the elective function are minors, domestic
                        servants, transient laborers, bankrupts pending proceedings against them by
                        their creditors, paupers, and all persons who have refused or neglected to
                        pay the taxes on which their right to vote is dependent.</p>
                    <p>Each of the groups above described elects 40 members of the city
                            council.<note n="*" xml:id="d49fn1">In this system the charter seems to
                            have followed the principles recommended by Locke and by Montesquieu:
                            “Il y a toujours dans un État des gens distingués par la naissance, les
                            richesses ou les honneurs: mais s’ils etaient confondus parmi le peuple,
                            et s’ils n’y avaient qu’une voix comme les autres, la liberté commune
                            serait leur esclavage, et ils n’auraient aucun interêt à la defendre,
                            parceque la plupart des resolutions seraient contre eux. La part qu’ils
                            ont à la législation doit done être proportionnée aux autres avantages
                            qu’ils ont dans l’État; ce qui arrivera s’ils forment un corps qui ait
                            droit d’arrêter les entreprises du peuple, comme le peuple a droit
                            d’arrêter les leurs.”—<hi rend="smallcaps">Montesquieu.</hi></note></p>
                    <p>All citizens entitled to vote are enrolled in election lists, one for each
                        voting district and for each group to which the voters of that district
                        belong. Six weeks before election these lists are exhibited and published in
                        the official journal.</p>
                    <p>Reclamations may be made and must be decided (within six days of their
                        presentation) by the district magistrates. The revision must be completed a
                        fortnight before the election. One week before the election the voters are
                        notified of the time and place of holding the election and of the number of
                        seats vacant; and special election commissioners are appointed for each
                        district. They consist of one member of the city <pb facs="0163" n="67" xml:id="pg_67"/> council, one magistrate, and four other citizens. The
                        city councilor presides, assisted by a delegate of the governor of this
                        province, whose duty it is to preserve order at the election. The commission
                        receives the votes and supervises and certifies the entire act of the
                        election.</p>
                    <p>The protocol so certified is laid before the city council, where reclamations
                        may be made within a week. If the election is vitiated upon any such
                        reclamation, a new election takes place. If ratified, the elected member is
                        notified, and in turn notifies his acceptance.</p>
                    <p>All citizens of Vienna who are qualified voters are eligible to the city
                        council, after attaining the age of thirty years, except soldiers in active
                        service, municipal officers and employés, and dilatory debtors to the
                        community.</p>
                    <p rend="center">III.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">organization of the city council and
                            mayoralty</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The members of the city council are elected for a term of three years,
                        one-third being renewed annually, and are re-eligible. The mayor (<hi rend="italic">Burgermeister</hi>) is elected by them from their own
                        number, and for a term of three years, and must receive a two-thirds vote of
                        that body. At this election all the members are required to be present on
                        pain of forfeit of their places. The council chooses also two vice-mayors
                        for one year’s term, who may be ready to replace the mayor upon occasion.
                        The bur-germeister is subject to confirmation by the Emperor. He receives no
                        salary, but there is provided for him a spacious official residence and an
                        allowance of 10,000 florins for representation. The members of the common
                        council also serve without salary.</p>
                    <p>This council of 120 is, for the better consideration of business, divided
                        into eight sections, as follows: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>On general organization, law, central statistics.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>On internal department commerce, and trade.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>On education and public worship.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>On public safety and board of health.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>On poor, pauper, and humane institutions.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>On building and engineering.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>On financial affairs and control.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>On provisioning of the city and market police.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The burgermeister (mayor) is charged with the usual supervisory and executive
                        functions of a mayor, and has the right of veto of the municipal
                        resolutions. In case of such veto, the proposed measure can only become
                        valid if it shall subsequently be approved by the provincial Landtag. This
                        legislature corresponds to our State legislatures, and may of its own
                        initiative also impose laws upon the city, as its immediate sovereign in
                        authority.</p>
                    <p rend="center">IV.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">limitations of the powers of the city
                            government</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The municipal representatives, in addition to the usual powers in respect to
                        local ordinances and regulations, have the right to adopt a budget of city
                        expenditures for all purposes which may not (without special legislative
                        authority) exceed the fourth part (25 per cent.) of the amount of taxes
                        imposed upon the city for all public and national purposes. If a greater
                        revenue is required, the consent of the provincial legislature must be first
                        obtained. The portion now allotted to the city of the entire taxes is 30 per
                        cent.</p>
                    <pb facs="0164" n="68" xml:id="pg_68"/>
                    <p>In order to the creation of a city, debt, the sanction both of the Landtag
                        and of the Emperor is required. All current liabilities must be met by the
                        taxation, limited as stated above.</p>
                    <p>The city is not allowed to dispose of any of its real estate exceeding 10,000
                        florins in value without the like sanction of the Emperor and the Landtag.
                        Its moveable property is within its own control.</p>
                    <p>The city council does not control the general judiciary of the city nor the
                        general police. These functionaries, being charged with the enforcement of
                        the general state laws, and with the prevention and punishment of crimes, as
                        regulated by the state, are appointed by the state authority exclusively,
                        and are responsible to it. No changes are made in the police force except
                        for cause. Their vigilant attention to duty, and the rare breaches of good
                        order in the city, bear testimony in favor of this system. There are,
                        however, as hereafter described, certain functionaries of the city who
                        combine both administrative and judicial functions in respect to the
                        ordinances of the city. There is also a limited number of municipal police
                        or watchmen, charged with certain municipal duties.</p>
                    <p>Of the pay of the state police employed in the city, one-third part is borne
                        by the city.</p>
                    <p rend="center">V.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">the organization and distribution of
                            executive functions</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The general administration, apart from the mayor, is divided into 24
                        sections. The officers at the head of these divisions are individually
                        styled <hi rend="italic">Counsellor</hi> and collectively are called “The
                        Magistracy.” They are under the general control of the city council, and
                        when assembled, form a sort of executive council, and are the executive
                        organs of the municipality. The mayor is their controlling superior, and
                        presides at their assembled sessions. In his absence, a vice-burgermeister,
                        or some member of the magistracy itself, presides. Should their actions be
                        illegal or prejudicial to the rights of the city, it is to be reported to
                        the Landtag through the governor. When the Landtag is not in session, the
                        government itself may take provisional measures in such cases to prevent
                        injury or wrong to the city.</p>
                    <p>The magistracy supervises the execution of the city ordinances, and watches
                        over city property, city institutions, and municipal societies. It exercises
                        the functions of a local supervisory board of police. It has the judicial
                        right to punish violations of municipal ordinances, as well as of its own
                        orders and regulations, with fines not exceeding 200 florins ($100), and
                        with imprisonment in the proportion of one day for each 5 florins of fine.
                        Immediately superior to this body is a general director, relieving the mayor
                        of a portion of the labor of supervising the magistracy.</p>
                    <p>Each of the 24 divisions has at its head a counselor (rath), who is appointed
                        for life and becomes entitled to a pension on cessation of active service.
                        His salary is from 2,500 to 3,500 florins, according to length of service.
                        The general director receives a salary of 6,000 florins.</p>
                    <p>The director and counselors must, before appointment, have passed their state
                        examination, and must also have taken a regular degree of doctor of laws.
                        They hold their appointment from the city council.</p>
                    <p>The magistracy, through its proper bureaus, collects all taxes, local and
                        state, and employs in all, under authority of the city council, 36
                        secretaries and 62 clerks of all grades, who are distributed among the
                        bureaus according to their respective requirements.</p>
                    <pb facs="0165" n="69" xml:id="pg_69"/>
                    <p>The entire business of the city, including the judicial enforcement of its
                        ordinances and orders, is distributed among these 24 bureaus. Each chief of
                        section has the jurisdiction, in respect to violation of city ordinances, of
                        an ordinary justice of the peace or city judge, combining to this limited
                        extent executive and judicial functions. I give only an outline of the
                        distribution of business.</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>To section I is assigned the charge of important documents of the
                            administration, and of the ordinances of the council; the promulgation
                            of laws when this is not made the duty of another counselor, the
                            editorship of the Official Ordinance Journal; charge of public
                            collections, supervision of the city clerks and servants, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section II, examination and judgment on all law matters touching the
                            city. Preparation and issue of all documents and memorials,
                            &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section III, accounts and budget of the city of Vienna, administration
                            of loans; also statistics.</item>
                        <item>Section IV, collection of rates and dues, local police funds, certain
                            special taxes, certain church affairs, charitable institutions,
                            canalization, supervision of the chief city treasury, and other
                            specialties.</item>
                        <item>Section V, register of landed estates, direction of the district
                            (ward) committees, administration and inspection of real estate,
                            insurance and care of buildings, barracks, and tenements belonging to
                            the city, tire insurance on all city public edifices, bathing
                            establishments, both public and private, lighting of the streets and
                            squares, charge of the city clocks, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section VI, precautionary and administrative measures against and
                            during inundations, regulation, laying out and good condition of
                            streets, street railways, regulation of the municipal tariffs;
                            guaranties for current work and supplies furnished to the city,
                            &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section VII, the public and private water-works; supervision of
                            wells.</item>
                        <item>Section VIII, ordinances for the health of the city, especially for
                            that of the working classes, preventive measures against epidemic
                            diseases and the occupation of crowded and unhealthy lodgings;
                            management of the municipal hospitals, the cemeteries, licensed flayers
                            of animals, supervision of apothecaries and surgeons, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section IX, buildings and deposit of materials, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section X, all public schools and supervision of all private academies
                            and gymnasia, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section XI, all matters concerning the poor; alms-houses, workhouses,
                            foundling and orphan asylums, and other humane institutions.</item>
                        <item>Section XII, expenses of hospitals and interments and collection of
                            the same.</item>
                        <item>Section XIII, collection of fees and dues demandable from other public
                            authorities; also matters in reference to the stamping of gold and
                            silver plate and stamp duties.</item>
                        <item>Section XIV, local police, inquests, care of effects of persons
                            suddenly deceased, of suicides, and of insane persons.</item>
                        <item>Section XV, preventive measures for personal security, and in charge
                            of advertising apparatus, public closets, telegraphs, theaters, cruelty
                            toward animals, insurance against fire or accident, matters relative to
                            firemen, river police, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section XVI, provisioning and market ordinances; supervision of the
                            guilds of bakers, fishmongers, butchers, poulterers, gardeners,
                            wood-merchants, milk-dealers, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section XVII, charge of the census, emigration, growth of population,
                            and liability to military service, and all affairs touching the army and
                            militia.</item>
                        <pb facs="0166" n="70" xml:id="pg_70"/>
                        <item>Section XVIII, administration and correspondence in matters of
                            marriages, changes of religion, legitimation of natural children,
                            changing of names, acquirement of citizenship, supervision of the guilds
                            of founders, gold and silversmiths, jewellers, bronze-workers, potters,
                            copper and blacksmiths, platers, and tinmen.</item>
                        <item>Section XIX, collection of taxes and rates, additional charges of
                            state and city treasury, matters in relation to tax executions, state
                            loans, elections, jury-lists.</item>
                        <item>Section XX, affairs which concern the guilds and associations in
                            common; also toll matters, exercise of the trade and occupation of
                            peddlers 5 matters affecting fairs, voluntary auctions; also stock
                            companies, insurance companies, exchanges, supervision of printers,
                            booksellers, retail merchants, photographers, and the like.</item>
                        <item>Section XXI, legalization of documents; supervision of affairs
                            relating to pawnbrokers, builders, slaters, engravers, masons,
                            locksmiths, carpenters, shoemakers, watchmakers, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section XXII, relating to brewers, innkeepers, confectioners,
                            &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Scetion XXIII, relating to house-painters, bookbinders, chemists,
                            bar-biers, glovers, hatters, tailors, dress-makers, perfumers, saddlers,
                            rope-makers, upholsterers, weavers, &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Section XXIV, relating to gunsmiths, brush-makers, turners, coachmen,
                            cabmen, piano-forte makers, opticians, musical-instrument makers,
                            joiners and cabinet-makers, &amp;c.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>A handbook showing completely and in detail the distribution of business to
                        the different bureaus and counselors is published for the information of all
                        concerned. Any one having reclamations or coin-plaints about taxes,
                        licenses, nuisances, dangers, violations of ordinances, &amp;c., or whatever
                        else, knows his bureau and his judge, and the usual rules of administration,
                        and can seek relief without the intervention of a lawyer or other
                        intermediary. I forward by this mail a copy of this handbook to illustrate
                        the perfection of the system in its details.</p>
                    <p>I beg to call your special attention to this admirable organization for the
                        transaction of municipal business, its concentration in one building, its
                        distribution in bureaus or sections in such manner that there is the least
                        delay in dispatch of business and its perfect system of responsibility.
                        There is a distinct line drawn between the agents of the state, for the
                        enforcement of general laws and the punishment of crimes on the one hand,
                        and the agents for the enforcement of city ordinances and the application of
                        their limited penalties on the other. The former are appointed by and act
                        under state authority. The latter are appointed by and are responsible to
                        the city authority. In both cases the agents below the chiefs are appointed
                        for life, or during good behavior, and so become perfect masters both of the
                        principles and details of administration, and are in theory and in fact the
                        agents of good order and public security, instead of the will of struggling
                        politicians or parties. Their compensation is not large but increases with
                        length of service, and a pension follows disability. In this manner the
                        total cost of administration is probably less than that which follows our
                        higher paid but more loosely organized city governments. The application of
                        the principles and rules suggested in this paragraph would of itself effect
                        enormous reforms in the administration of our populous American cities.</p>
                    <p>The burgermeister stated to me that there is no record of any embezzlement or
                        pecuniary fraud as ever having occurred among their life appointees.</p>
                    <pb facs="0167" n="71" xml:id="pg_71"/>
                    <p rend="center">VI.</p>
                    <p rend="center">SANITARY ORGANIZATION.</p>
                    <p>Under the sanitary bureau (one of the 24 sections), the sanitary inspection
                        of the city is entrusted to two physicians, who are subject to the general
                        direction of the mayor and council. They are required to execute also such
                        orders as shall be addressed to them by the provincial governor (<hi rend="italic">Stadthalter</hi>), or the police magistrates. They are
                        equal in authority and their appointments are only revoked for cause. Their
                        legal fees are paid into the city treasury to be equally divided between
                        them. Obliged to live in the inner town, having a carriage allowance for
                        official duties in the suburbs and the cemeteries, neither of them may leave
                        the city on private business without the permission of the mayor
                        (Burgermeister).</p>
                    <p>The city physicians must strictly observe the sanitary regulations and direct
                        their greatest care to the state of the health in all parts of the city;
                        they assist each other and each may perform the duties of the other. Every
                        week they must have a conference. If they hear of unauthorized practice of
                        physicians or surgeons they send notice of it to the town authorities. At
                        the end of each year they must prepare a sanitary report respecting their
                        official activity, and the incidents observed. This report comes before the
                        council.</p>
                    <p>The work of the city physicians is divided into two main sections, for each
                        of which one of them is primarily responsible.</p>
                    <p>1st. One has the supervision of the houses, their sink-holes and canals; must
                        enforce the ordinances relative to sanitary interests in all new buildings
                        and rebuildings. He is to be present at the granting of licenses for steam
                        engines, water works and the like, which might interfere with the health and
                        comfort of the neighborhood. He has, moreover, to direct his attention to
                        all trades which are restricted by sanitary ordinances.</p>
                    <p>All articles of food, all vessels of earthenware and copper used for cooking,
                        etc., must be inspected and examined by him; as also the sale rooms, booths,
                        markets, eating and coffee houses, bars, taps, and the like, and the cook’s
                        galleys of the steamers landing at the city. He must superintend the traffic
                        of all objects which might contain poisonous substances, as stuffs,
                        paper-hangings, toys, cosmetics, etc., and insist on the Strict observance
                        of the ordinances respecting the sale of poisons and drugs. All traffic with
                        nostra, arcana, or prohibited remedies must be reported.</p>
                    <p>He has the sanitary supervision of all the public and private schools and the
                        gymnasia, as well as of all places of public gathering, which are liable to
                        be crowded, as churches, public walks, theaters, baths, hospitals, prisons,
                        and the like.</p>
                    <p>He is required to examine carefully the drinking water of the city, and to
                        supervise the cemeteries, upon which he is to make quarterly reports to the
                        city council.</p>
                    <p>2d. The other city physician, when ordered to do so by the authorities, must
                        pass judgment on the health of municipal officers and servants and on
                        reclamations for discharge from military service. He has the medical
                        superintendence of all work-houses, humane institutions, and the like,
                        belonging to the town, and the chief inspection of all lying-in hospitals,
                        lunatic asylums, and private hospitals in Vienna, as well as of all safety
                        apparatus.</p>
                    <pb facs="0168" n="72" xml:id="pg_72"/>
                    <p>In case of an epidemic lie has to apply all the necessary measures and to
                        superintend their immediate and strict execution.</p>
                    <p>In order to be well informed of everything concerning the health, diseases,
                        and sanitary police’ of the city, the city physician is required every month
                        to convoke the district surgeons and the municipal medical staff. He has the
                        superintendence of the corpse inspection, keeps evidence of all occurring
                        deaths, and collects the materials necessary for the use of the statistical
                        bureaus of the city, which he utilizes, together with all other incidents of
                        his experience, for the publication of the medical statistics of the city of
                        Vienna.</p>
                    <p>There is in each, of the ten bezicks (wards) from three to five sanitary
                        watchmen, who frequently visit house drainage and all suspected places of
                        disease, waste deposits, &amp;c., and report to the city physician. The city
                        makes a contract yearly for wagons for each ward, which call twice a week at
                        every house to carry away refuse at fixed charges.</p>
                    <p rend="center">VII.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">management of the poor and the
                        sick</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Vienna is richly provided with hospitals for the skillful treatment of
                        diseases and for surgical operations, without cost to the poor. Separate
                        hospitals are provided for contagious diseases. Foundling hospitals diminish
                        the temptation to infanticide. The charitable endowment funds of the city
                        are large. Any deficiency for the poor is made good by the city treasury.
                        The city has six houses for the poor, but this number is insufficient. The
                        oldest, the poorest, and the most infirm are assigned to these poor-houses.
                        A complete system of out-door relief is established under the city
                        government. Each bezick (ward) has its supervisor and his assisting
                        committee (without pay), who care for the humane concerns of the ward and
                        report to the mayor or to the proper bureau. Each case for charitable relief
                        is personally investigated, all the facts noted, and the necessary
                        allowances made. Begging in the streets is prohibited under penalties. But
                        it seems that certain known and deserving cases are excepted from the
                        prohibition (probably on certificate of the <hi rend="italic">armen-vater</hi>) (father of the poor) for I see at certain
                        church-doors and at certain points on thoroughfares, the same faces at
                        intervals of some days, appealing, but usually silently, for alms, and
                        always at the same stations. I venture the opinion that such permission
                        accorded to meritorious poverty is not alone beneficial to the pauper. It
                        tends to keep in the memory of the busy and prosperous world the existence
                        of human distress, and the Christian duty imposed on them to extend the hand
                        of relief. A whole community as well as an individual would unconsciously
                        become inhumane after a long suspension of the exercises of acts of
                        humanity.</p>
                    <p rend="center">VIII.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">system of cleaning streets</hi>.</p>
                    <p>There is rarely cause for complaint of unclean streets in Vienna. Different
                        systems are applied in the central and exterior districts. The old city with
                        narrow streets, and lying compactly within the Ringstrasse, a boulevard
                        replacing the ancient line of fortifications, constitutes the first
                        district, and its cleanliness is secured by a contract for a fixed price
                        with a transport company for the term of five years. The city authorities
                        have the right to impose on the contractor a fine not exceeding <pb facs="0169" n="73" xml:id="pg_73"/> 500 florins ($250) for each day in
                        which this duty is neglected. The inhabitants must keep their sidewalks
                        free, and in time of slippery frost must protect the pedestrians by sanding
                        the walks on their respective fronts. The transport company is entitled to
                        the sweepings, which are constantly made, and for which poor people are
                        usually employed who have no other regular labor. Snow is promptly gathered
                        aside in heaps and carted away, usually by night.</p>
                    <p>In the other nine bezicks or suburban wards a street supervisor is elected by
                        all voters together for a term of three years. He is allowed 1,000 florins
                        for incidental expenses, but no salary. His ward is divided into 15 to 18
                        sections, in each of which is a subordinate who watches over the work in his
                        section.</p>
                    <p>The men are employed as needed under the general control of the ward
                        supervisor, and the expenses are provided for in the city budget. The
                        ultimate control is in the city council and its magistracy. There is an
                        incidental economy in this system, as many people are employed in the work
                        of sweeping, women as well as men, who would otherwise be a charge on the
                        poor funds of the city.</p>
                    <p>In 1876 the whole area of the streets amounted to 3,993,350 square meters.
                        The cost of cleaning was— <table cols="2" rows="5">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Florins.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>In 1875</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,112,786</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>In 1876</cell>
                                <cell role="num">996,986</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>In 1877</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,046,980</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>In 1878</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,034,800</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table></p>
                    <p rend="center">IX.</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">system of paving streets</hi>.</p>
                    <p>With few exceptions the streets of Vienna are paved with granite cubic blocks
                        measuring in centimeters 23.7 by 13.2 by 18.4.</p>
                    <p>The quarries, which belong to the city, are situated a few miles above the
                        town on the Danube, down which the cubes are floated to the city front. The
                        quarries are leased to a contractor on the condition that he furnishes to
                        the city 18,000 per annum at a fixed price. A square meter of this pavement
                        costs 8 florins and 25 kreuzers (about $4), while the endurance of the cubes
                        is found to be 32 years, subject to repairs after 12 years. From the twelfth
                        to the thirty-second year the repairs, cost 2 florins 54 kreuzers, making
                        the cost of pavement for the term of 32 years 10 florins 79 kreuzers per
                        square meter (say $5.25). Its disadvantages are noise and rigidity. Its
                        advantages are its durability, rare need of repair when well laid, secure
                        grasp for horses, cheap maintenance, and facility for cleaning.</p>
                    <p>The judgment of the city has been against bituminous limestone and asphalt,
                        because of its dangerous smoothness; and against macadam, because of its
                        intolerable dirt and dust; and against wood, because of its rapid decay.</p>
                    <p rend="center">X.</p>
                    <p>I have given above the more important and distinctive features of the
                        municipal system of Vienna. The late burgermeister, Dr. Felder, was good
                        enough to give me personally much of this information, and to place at my
                        disposal various statistical publications of the city government. I also had
                        the aid in the analysis of their contents of a young American graduate of
                        the University of Vienna (and “doctor of laws”), Mr. Samson, voluntarily
                        attached, to this legation. The report on the <pb facs="0170" n="74" xml:id="pg_74"/> municipal affairs of Vienna for the three years of Dr.
                        F elder’s administration (1874–1876), which he presented to me, contains
                        much valuable information which may be of use to statisticians and municipal
                        economists. I therefore forward it, via Hamburg, for the use of the
                        Department.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JOHN A. KASSON.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>