<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 463.Mr. Fish to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1879</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d495</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">495</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1879-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1879-10-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-10-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="495"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d495">
                <head>No. 463.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-10-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 18, 1879</date>. (Received November
                        3.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 218.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your instruction No. 115, respecting the detention of the property claimed by
                    Mr. Franz Fassbind, of San Francisco.</p>
                <p>The action of the communal authorities in withholding the property of natives of
                    Switzerland naturalized in the United States, on various pretexts, has been,
                    from the early days of this mission, a frequent source of complaint, and of much
                    correspondence between my predecessors and the local authorities. Frequently the
                    sums involved are too small to pay for the trouble and expense of their
                    collection in the face of the objections raised. The recent case of Jacob
                    Zimmermann, of Ebikon, with which you are familiar, shows, one of the most
                    frequent pretexts for with holding the property of our citizens of Swiss birth,
                    viz, declining to recognize him as a citizen of the United States because he had
                    not been released from his native allegiance. This refusal was made in his case
                    although the man presented a certificate of his naturalization in the United
                    States, and a formal renunciation of his Swiss citizenship, both duly
                    authenticated by the Swiss consul at New York, where he was residing, on the
                    ground that the documents had not been authenticated by the Swiss Federal
                    Government, and because Zimmermann was formerly under guardianship, and no
                    certificate of his being able, notwithstanding such guardianship, to acquire
                    citizenship in the United States, or of his being able validly to renounce his
                    previous citizenship, had been presented.</p>
                <p>This refusal of the communal authorities was supported by the cantonal
                    government, and appears even to have had the sanction of the federal government,
                    inasmuch as the latter transmitted it to the legation. It was not until the
                    diplomatic representations of the legation had been brought to bear upon these
                    objections that the unreasonable requirements of the commune and canton were
                    allayed.</p>
                <p>That such annoyances and others of a like nature are of but too frequent
                    occurrence, the inclosed letter from Mr. Byers, the consul at Zurich, clearly
                    demonstrates. The government of that canton holds that— <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>A Swiss citizen acquiring the right of American citizenship without first
                            handing in to, and having accepted by, the proper authorities here, a
                            legal renunciation of Swiss citizenship, will still be considered as a
                            citizen of Switzerland at any time he may return to this country.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>While the right of the Swiss authorities to hold these views might possibly,
                    under Swiss law, be maintained in the case of such naturalized citizens of the
                    United States as return to Switzerland and establish themselves here, it is, I
                    believe, in conflict with the Constitution and laws of the United States, as
                    being a denial of the unalienable right of expatriation. More especially is this
                    the case where, as in Ziinmermann’s case, the naturalized citizen, while
                    residing in the United States, has sought to comply with the requirements of
                    Swiss law respecting renunciation of Swiss nationality, but is hindered in so
                    doing by the non-acceptance of his request for release from his native
                    allegiance, and thus the doctrine of perpetual allegiance is sought to be
                    maintained.</p>
                <p>These annoyances will continue until some one of our naturalized citizens shall
                    appeal to the tribunal federal or supreme court of Switzerland, <pb facs="1070"
                        n="974" xml:id="pg_974"/> when, I have no doubt, the enlightened justice of
                    that body would render its decision in favor of the appellant. A decision in
                    favor of the principle recognized by us, of the unalienable right of man to
                    expatriate himself, would be of immense benefit to thousands of our naturalized
                    citizens of Swiss birth, and to their heirs who are now deprived of the
                    enjoyment of their property by the vexatious opposition of local officials,
                    sometimes actuated by motives of personal interest, and who are likewise
                    deterred from combatting such opposition on account of the trouble and expense
                    involved therein.</p>
                <p>Mr. Byers, whose long and great experience in cases of collecting property for
                    this class of our citizens entitles his judgment to great-consideration,
                    estimates the amount of property within the jurisdition of his consulate alone,
                    belonging to such citizens of the United States, and withheld by the local
                    authorities by reason of the claim of native allegiance, at 1,000,000 francs, or
                    nearly $200,000.</p>
                <p>In the absence of an adverse decision by the tribunal fédéral, I cannot fully
                    share Consul Byers’s opinion that the higher courts will not remedy the evil,
                    nor do I share his opinion that Congress should seek to prevent the
                    naturalization of natives of this country who could not prove that they had
                    never been under guardianship in Switzerland.</p>
                <p>I believe that the remedy would be best attained were every Swiss, immediately
                    upon his naturalization in the United States, to comply, so far as within him
                    lies, with the provisions of the Swiss federal law of July 3, 1876, respecting
                    the renunciation of Swiss nationality (see <ref target="frus1876#pg_567">Foreign
                        Relations for 1876, page 567</ref>), and that in every case where such
                    compliance was thwarted by the action of the communal or cantonal authorities,
                    the legation should be instructed to intervene diplomatically, and, failing to
                    succeed, it should be empowered, after reference to the Department of State, to
                    carry the appeal to the tribunal fédéral.</p>
                <p>The decision of a test case by the latter in our favor would be the most
                    effective barrier to similar future annoyances, and were it adverse to us, it
                    would then be for us to consider the expediency of diplomatic negotiations for a
                    remedy of the evil.</p>
                <p>I particularly invite your attention to Mr. Byers’s letter, and I respectfully
                    ask your instructions on this important question involving the nationality and
                    the pecuniary interests of a large number of our naturalized citizens, a large
                    majority of whom are proud of their acquired citizenship, and can ill afford to
                    sacrifice their property for the sake of the exploded notion of a perpetual
                    allegiance.</p>
                <p>Should you adopt my views of the question, it might be advisable to intimate
                    through the public press to our citizens of Swiss birth that it is to their own
                    interest for them to formally renounce their allegiance to Switzerland.</p>
                <p>In Mr. Fassbind’s case, I have, in compliance with your instructions, instituted
                    inquiries concerning the facts, and shall be guided in my action by the result
                    of such inquiries.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>NICHOLAS FISH.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Byers</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Zurich</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-10-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 11, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I would respectfully call your attention to
                        the peculiar views taken by the government of this canton as to the status
                        of Swiss persons who have become citizens <pb facs="1071" n="975"
                            xml:id="pg_975"/> of the United States. It is maintained, first, that no
                        Swiss can become a United States citizen, or will he so considered by the
                        authorities of this canton, unless he had first handed in to the authorities
                        here a renunciation of his Swiss citizenship; second, this renunciation must
                        have been accepted by the authorities here.</p>
                    <p>I may here note that great discretion seems to be allowed the local
                        authorities as to whether this renunciation shall be accepted. Usually, if
                        the applicant has had a guardian in Switzerland, the application will not be
                        accepted at all, and the number of adults residing in America and still
                        having guardians in this country, is something remarkable.</p>
                    <p>The law permits the appointment of a guardian for adults by the local
                        authorities in various cases, and especially in cases where the person has
                        given signs of extravagance. I may add that the going to America is one of
                        these extravagances. This constant guardianship of other people’s interest
                        is manifestly for the sole purpose of giving the township control, and
                        finally possession, of other people’s property. In many cases not even the
                        interest will be sent him, the ward, and as to a collection of an
                        inheritance left him, it becomes, under the ruling of the authorities,
                        simply impossible, unless the guardian and local authorities see fit, of
                        their own free will, to permit it. I may add, that after years of experience
                        in collection cases here, the guardian and the local authorities nine cases
                        out of ten, do not see fit to permit it, and the cantonal authorities
                        justify them in their action.</p>
                    <p>In short, under past rulings, a naturalized Swiss in America, who has
                        inherited property in his native land, might almost give up all hopes of
                        ever securing it, so many are the obstacles put in the way, principal of
                        which are the informalities of his renunciation of citizenship, or rather
                        the impossibility of obtaining acceptance of the renunciation in case the
                        applicant is one of the hundreds and thousands who happen to have had a
                        guardian.</p>
                    <p>As a case in point, I inclose an extract from a letter written to me by the
                        cantonal government, in the case of Jacob Strehler, in which the doctrine is
                        repeated that any Swiss naturalized in America without his renunciation of
                        citizenship being <hi rend="italic">accepted</hi> will be, should he happen
                        to return here, <hi rend="italic">treated as a Swiss.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In Strehler’s case, as in almost hundreds of others of which I know
                        personally, the injustice is simply outrageous. Strehler had been many years
                        an American citizen, and had been allowed and encouraged by his guardian to
                        go to the United States. But when his father died and left him a large
                        property, the collection of it was interfered with and prevented by the
                        guardian and local authorities, on the ground that he was possibly not
                        capable of doing business in America, being still inflicted with a guardian
                        at home, and on the further ground that the local authorities, quite
                        naturally, had never granted his renunciation of citizenship. I petitioned
                        for Strehler myself, that this renunciation, properly offered, should be
                        accepted. I was (of course) refused, and the cantonal authorities to whom I
                        appealed justified the refusal to turn the property of Strehler over to me,
                        though I was properly empowered to receive it for him.</p>
                    <p>Strehler’s case, however, is only one of hundreds of the kind, where the
                        principle is maintained that <hi rend="italic">once a Swiss, always a
                            Swiss</hi>, unless the guardian and authorities here see fit to accept
                        renunciation, and I have pointed out that usually they will not accept
                        it.</p>
                    <p>The result of this action on the part of the local authorities of this
                        canton, and of the cantonal government which upholds them in it, is— <list>
                            <label>1st.</label>
                            <item>A virtual confiscation of estates inherited here by Swiss
                                naturalized in the United States, especially if they have once been
                                under guardianship here.</item>
                            <label>2d.</label>
                            <item>A deprivation for such persons of the rights of American
                                citizenship. They cannot collect their property, and should they
                                happen to come here, on a visit even, they are liable to be seized
                                upon and treated as Swiss, not as American citizens.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>To my mind there seems to be no remedy for this state of affairs (the higher
                        courts will not remedy it) except through a new treaty with Switzerland, by
                        which it shall be declared once and forever that the naturalization of Swiss
                        in the United States is not a mere farce, and it would seem just that an act
                        of Congress should prevent our courts from naturalizing a single Swiss
                        citizen who could not prove that he had <hi rend="italic">never been under
                            guardianship</hi> in his native country.</p>
                    <p>I believe there are to-day in this consular district a million francs
                        belonging to citizens of the United States, not one penny of which can be
                        collected, for the reason that the claimants, though supposing themselves to
                        be American citizens, are here declared to be still <hi rend="italic"
                            >Swiss</hi> citizens, and under guardianship at that.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>S. H. M. BYERS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="1072" n="976" xml:id="pg_976"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in Mr. Byers’note.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss type="from">Cantonal government of Zurich</gloss> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Byers</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Zurich</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-10-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 11, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. S. H. M. Byers, United States consul at Zurich, having asked us in his
                        letter of the 18th of March to furnish him with a list of all persons
                        registered as former American citizens in Zurich, and who have acquired
                        Swiss citizenship here, we reply:</p>
                    <p>The cantonal government, after examining a proposition of the interior court
                        of Zurich, concludes as follows:</p>
                    <p>1st. A Swiss citizen acquiring the right of American citizenship without
                        first handing in to and having accepted by the proper authorities here a
                        legal renunciation of Swiss citizenship, <hi rend="italic">will still be
                            considered as a citizen of Switzerland</hi>, at any time he may return
                        to this country.</p>
                    <p>According to article 44 of the federal constitution, no canton has the right
                        to deprive any of its citizens of the rights of citizenship here.</p>
                    <p>There is no limitation or prescription (<hi rend="italic">Verjährung</hi>) of
                        Swiss citizenship.</p>
                    <p>There are great numbers of persons living in this canton who have returned
                        here after having acquired American citizenship. A separate controle of
                        these persons is not kept, and therefore it is impossible to prepare a
                        list.</p>
                    <p>2d. Communication of the above to the department of the interior.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. STUSSI,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">For the Government of Canton Zurich.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
