<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-03-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="530" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d530">
                    <head>No. 496.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Baker</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-03-17"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 17, 1879</date>.
                            (Received April 8.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 105.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I send herewith a copy of a decree by General
                        Guzman Blanco, as the same appears in La Opinion Nacional of the 28th
                        ultimo, together with a translation thereof. This decree calls a congress of
                        plenipotentiaries to meet in the federal district on the 27th of April next,
                        or the most contiguous day, to be composed of the presidents of the States,
                        or of representative substitutes appointed by them; this congress to fix
                        provisional institutions for the country, elect a provisional president,
                        &amp;c. This document, like that transmitted with my No. 104, should be read
                        in full.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JEHU BAKER.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No.
                            105.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">guzman blanco, illustrious american, pacificator
                                and re generator of venezuela, supreme director of the
                                revindication, etc.</hi></head>
                        <p>In use of the powers which the people have conferred upon me for the
                            political and administrative reorganization of the republic—</p>
                        <p>I decree: <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1. On the 27th of April
                                    next, or the day most contiguous, a congress of <pb facs="1138" n="1042" xml:id="pg_1042"/> plenipotentiaries will meet in
                                    the federal district, composed of the presidents of the States,
                                    or of citizens in their places who represent them, whom they may
                                    name in case of not being able to be present.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. The congress of
                                    plenipotentiaries will install itself, and open each session
                                    with at least one more than half its members; and in default of
                                    this number on the day upon which it should install itself,
                                    those present will meet in a preparatory commission, and,
                                    previously electing one to preside over them, dictate means for
                                    the concurrence of the absentees.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 3. The congress of
                                    plenipotentaries will fix the institutions which shall
                                    provisionally rule the country until they are reformed according
                                    to the legal formulas.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 4. The congress of
                                    plenipotentiaries will elect the citizen who may have to
                                    discharge provisionally the presidency of the republic until he
                                    may be substituted constitutionally.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 5. The congress of
                                    plenipotentiaries will occupy itself with resolving the other
                                    matters which the supreme director may submit to its
                                    consideration in all the branches of the public
                                    administration.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 6. The minister of interior
                                    relations is charged with the execution of this decree.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">Given, signed with my hand, and
                                countersigned by the proper minister (ministro del ramo) in the
                                capitol of <placeName>Caracas</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-02-27">the 27th of February,
                                    1879</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>GUZMAN BLANCO.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Countersigned. The minister of interior relations:</p>
                            <closer><signed>DIEGO B. URBANEJA.</signed></closer>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>