<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 83.Mr. Osborn to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1879</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d96</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">96</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1878-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1878-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1878-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1878-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="96"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d96">
                <head>No. 83.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Osborn</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Santiago, Chili</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1878-11-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 15, 1878</date>. (Received December
                        26.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 71.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The mail which leaves Valparaiso to-morrow will
                    be closed here in about an hour, and I must therefore make my dispatch
                    exceedingly brief. It refers to the ship Devonshire, and the boundary dispute
                    with the Argentine Government.</p>
                <p>I neglected to say in my former dispatches that when I was informed by the
                    minister of foreign relations that an American vessel was loading with guano at
                    Monte Leon, I addressed a note to the captain in which I informed him of the
                    claim made by Chili to that territory, and suggested that it would be well for
                    him to avoid a conflict with the authorities of either the Chilian or Argentine
                    Governments. This note was left with the minister of foreign relations for
                    delivery, but from some cause it failed to reach its destination.</p>
                <p>In a conference which I had with the minister a few days since, I called his
                    attention to this fact and suggested that, inasmuch as the legation had taken
                    such steps as prudence seemed to dictate to prevent the vessel from coming in
                    conflict with the authorities of Chili, and that inasmuch as the letter to that
                    end failed to reach its destination through no fault of the legation, it seemed
                    to me that, in view of the friendly relations existing between our respective
                    countries, Chili could well afford to release the ship unconditionally.</p>
                <p>The suggestion was well received, and the minister yesterday informed me that the
                    government had determined, if I would embody in a note the ideas which I had
                    suggested to him verbally, to place the vessel at liberty. This I did yesterday,
                    and the orders were, the minister has just informed me, soon after issued
                    directing the governor of Magallanes to permit the Devonshire to go to sea. The
                    formal answer to my note has not yet been received, but there is no doubt of the
                    facts stated. A government vessel leaves Valparaiso to-day for Punta Arenas,
                    conveying necessary orders. The release is made unconditionally.</p>
                <p>The Chili Navy is moving in the direction of the Straits of Magellan, and it is
                    understood here that the Argentine Government is sending its war vessels in the
                    same direction. Negotiations are, however, being carried on here looking to a
                    peaceful settlement of the dispute, and I have reason for believing that actual
                    hostilities will be avoided.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>THOMAS A. OSBORN.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
