<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-02-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="98" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                    <head>No. 85.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Osborn</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Santiago,
                                    Chili</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-02-20"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 20, 1879</date>.
                            (Received March 26.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 83.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Chili is involved in another dispute
                        concerning her boundaries. It is with Bolivia now, and concerns the
                        territory on the Pacific coast lying between the 23d and 25th degrees of
                        latitude. Prior to 1866, jurisdiction over this territory was claimed by
                        both of these governments, but on December 9 of that year they promulgated a
                        treaty which had for its purpose a settlement of the dispute. In substance,
                        the treaty provided that the 24th degree should constitute the line of
                        division, but that all guano deposits within the territory prior thereto in
                        dispute, as also all duties which might be derived from the exportation of
                        minerals therefrom, should be equally divided between the two countries. It
                        soon became evident, however, that the treaty had failed to accomplish the
                        purpose for which it was intended, and on the 6th of August, 1874, they
                        celebrated another.</p>
                    <p>In this the 24th degree was reasserted as the line of division, and each
                        government relinquished its right, within the jurisdiction of the other, to
                        duties arising from exportation of minerals. They agreed, also, that within
                        the hitherto disputed territory neither government should, for the term of
                        twenty-five years, impose upon the exportation of minerals a higher duty
                        than was then provided for, and that neither government should, within said
                        territory tax the citizens, industries, or <pb facs="0245" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> capital of the other, of whatever character, in excess
                        of that then fixed by law.</p>
                    <p>The country referred to as the disputed territory is in the heart of what is
                        known as the desert of Atacama, and was regarded, until about the time of
                        the execution of the first treaty, except for the deposit of guano at
                        Majillones, its northern boundary, as of little or no value. The discovery
                        of vast nitrate deposits about that time, however, in that part of the
                        territory, set apart to Bolivia by the treaty, soon brought it into
                        prominent notice, and companies were organized for the purpose of developing
                        that industry. The business seems to have been monopolized by a corporation
                        known as “Elcompañia de Salitres y Ferrocanil de Antofagasta,” a company
                        composed mainly of gentlemen of means, citizens of Chili. It is claimed in
                        behalf of the company that it had full authority from the Bolivian
                        Government for the prosecution of its business, and that it relied upon the
                        good faith of Bolivia in making its investments. It is claimed that its
                        investments now exceed $4,000,000. It has constructed a railroad 40 miles
                        into the interior, running through the nitrate deposits, and Antofagasta,
                        the shipping-point for the nitrate, and the location of the principal works,
                        has developed into a city of nearly 10,000 people.</p>
                    <p>In February of last year the Bolivian congress enacted a law exacting a tax
                        of ten cents a quintal on all exportations of nitrate, and from this has
                        arisen the present difficulty with Chili. The Chili Government promptly
                        protested against the execution of this law, claiming that it was in direct
                        conflict with the guaranties of the treaty of 1874. The law was allowed to
                        remain dormant for several months, but no action was taken looking to its
                        revocation.</p>
                    <p>A short time since, however, the Bolivian authorities notified the company at
                        Antofagasta that the law was to be executed, and that the amount which was
                        due from it on account of shipments made since the passage of the law was
                        something in excess of $90,000. The Chili Government protested anew, and
                        caused Bolivia to be informed that if she insisted upon executing the law
                        Chili would regard the treaty as abrogated, and would proceed to assert her
                        right of dominion to the territory claimed by her prior to 1866.
                        Notwithstanding this threat the works at Antofagasta were levied upon and
                        notice was given that they would be sold; whereupon, on the 12th instant the
                        Chilian minister at La Paz was instructed by telegraph to demand his
                        passport, and forces were immediately forwarded by water with instructions
                        to take possession of the territory on the coast as far north as the 23d
                        degree of latitude. On the 14th the Chilian forces occupied Antofagasta
                        without firing a gun, and the disputed territory is now held by Chilian
                        troops.</p>
                    <p>The course of the government here meets with a hearty approval from all
                        classes. The movement was an exceedingly popular one. It is doubtful,
                        indeed, if the administration could have taken another course and sustained
                        itself. There is much anxiety concerning the course which Peru is likely to
                        take. That her people strongly sympathize with Bolivia in this affair is
                        undoubtedly true, and it is feared by some that the government may be driven
                        into an alliance with Bolivia. I think the fear is well grounded.</p>
                    <p>The Chili Government is endeavoring to prepare itself for any emergency. The
                        naval force has all been sent to the north and troops are being forwarded as
                        rapidly as possible.</p>
                    <p>It is understood that congress will be convened in extraordinary session
                        about the 10th of March.</p>
                    <p>I forward you by this mail a copy of a pamphlet entitled “The new <pb facs="0246" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> question of Chili with Bolivia,”
                        which was sent to me from the foreign office. Also, a copy of the “Diario
                        Official,” which contains a sort of manifesto from the government under the
                        head of “El conflicto con Bolivia.”</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>THOMAS A. OSBORN.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>