<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>111. Letter From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                    Affairs (Berger) to the Consul General in Hong Kong () to the Consul General in
                    Hong Kong (Rice))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-11-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-11-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="111"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                <head>111. Letter From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BSD1" type="from">Berger</persName>) to the
                    Consul General in Hong Kong (<persName corresp="#p_REE1" type="to"
                        >Rice</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d111fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> Files: Lot 75 D 76,
                        Blue Lion Consultations. Secret; Eyes Only.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-11-24">November 24, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Dear Ed:</p>
                <p>At the time of <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Chiang Ching-kuo</persName>’s visit to
                    Washington last September we discussed with him means of tuning up our machinery
                    for mutual <pb facs="0261" n="227" xml:id="pg_227"/> consultations. We on our
                    side felt this was necessary because of unmistakable indications that <persName
                        corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> felt excluded from U.S. thinking
                    on Viet-Nam and other Far Eastern policy problems. We found our thoughts on this
                    confirmed by <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Chiang Ching-kuo</persName>’s repeated
                    mention while in Washington of the need for closer U.S.-<gloss target="#t_GRC1"
                        >GRC</gloss> consultations on policy matters.</p>
                <p>We told <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Chiang Ching-kuo</persName> that we would be
                    ready to resume the Ambassadorial level consultations of the “Blue Lion”
                    committee, of which I think you are aware from the time you were in Washington,
                    when our new Ambassador arrives in Taipei. At the same time we made no
                    suggestion that the frame of reference for “Blue Lion” be relaxed and we intend
                    to adhere strictly to “Blue Lion” ground rules in future consultations. These
                    ground rules are: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>that the Chinese planners should develop detailed plans for landing on
                            the China coast on the assumption that uprisings had occurred on the
                            mainland;</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>that planning is to be based upon the <gloss target="#t_GRC1"
                                >GRC</gloss>’s current capabilities, without any additional materiel
                            support or participation by U.S. forces;</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>that completed plans would be reviewed by the U.S. side, which would
                            make appropriate criticisms and suggestions to the <gloss
                                target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In general the purpose of these restrictions has been to obviate any
                    participation by us in joint military planning with the <gloss target="#t_GRC1"
                        >GRC</gloss> in connection with operations against the mainland.</p>
                <p>One other proposal that we made to <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Chiang
                        Ching-kuo</persName> was an exchange of intelligence appraisals of
                    conditions on the mainland. We hoped in this way to stimulate more realistic
                    thinking by the Chinese on the possibility that widespread dissidence on the
                    mainland would permit a successful <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                    counterattack against the Communists. As by-products we might also gain
                    additional intelligence on the Communists and further insight into <gloss
                        target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> thinking. There has been a continuing exchange
                    of intelligence on the Communists [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source
                        text not declassified</hi>] and the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> on a
                    piece-by-piece basis; however, there has not been the more searching and
                    comprehensive type of intelligence exchange which we have in mind.</p>
                <p>The plan is that <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> will produce a study which,
                    after a review in the Department and in Defense, will be submitted to the
                    Chinese; the Chinese will produce a similar study for our review. There might
                    then be a meeting in which we and the Chinese would discuss our studies and
                    compare notes as to conclusions. We think it would be helpful if someone from
                    Hong Kong’s political section could participate in such discussions and we have
                    made this suggestion to Embassy Taipei for comment.</p>
                <pb facs="0262" n="228" xml:id="pg_228"/>
                <p>I would very much appreciate your own thoughts on this.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d111fn2">Rice replied in a December 13 letter to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> that he had “some qualms” about
                        this. Predicting that the Chinese Communists would hear of it, perhaps in a
                        distorted form, he commented, “Some may argue it would be useful to make the
                        ChiComs believe we are working with the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                        on plans for attacking the mainland, but I would consider this a highly
                        dubious and danger-fraught exercise.”</note> We will in any case see that
                    you receive copies of all materials on mainland China which are generated as a
                    result of this exchange.</p>
                <p>With all best wishes,</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Samuel D. Berger</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d111fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
