<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-01-02T12:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-01-02T12:45:00-05:00" n="116" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                    <head>116. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">White House Situation
                            Room</gloss> to President <persName type="to">Johnson</persName> in
                            Texas<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d116fn1">Source: Johnson Library,
                            National Security File, International File, Vice President Trip, Far
                            East, 12/27/65. Top Secret; Exdis. A handwritten “L” on the source text
                            indicates that the President saw it.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-01-02T17:45:00+00:00">January 2, 1966,
                            1745Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>CAP 66018. For the President from the Vice President. Report on conversation
                        with President <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d116fn2">Vice President <persName corresp="#p_HHH1">Humphrey</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang
                                Kai-shek</persName> on January 1. A record of the meeting by Special
                            Assistant to the President <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Jack
                                Valenti</persName> is ibid., President’s Office File, <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Jack</persName>, Memoranda of Conversations, Japan, the
                            Philippines, Taiwan, Korea, December 1965–January 1966. Another, sent in
                            telegram 722 from Taipei, January 3, is ibid., National Security File,
                            Country File, China, Vol. V. A January 5 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_HHH1">Humphrey</persName> to
                                <persName>Johnson</persName> pertaining to his visit to Taipei is
                            ibid., <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings, Vol. 3, Tab 37.</note> and
                        Foreign Minister Yi Tong-won of Republic of China; Prime Minister Chung
                        Il-kwon and President Park of Korea.</p>
                    <p>1. The meeting with <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>
                        went about as predicted, in that he stressed the need for the United States
                        to recognize that the real enemy in Southeast Asia was not the Viet Cong or
                        North Vietnam, but was Communist China. He stressed as he has before that we
                        could not expect to match Communist manpower in Asia, and that it would be a
                        mistake to think that sophisticated weapons could replace manpower, the
                        objective should be to utilize Asian manpower with American logistics
                        support. He again stressed that the Soviet Union would not intervene in a
                        situation in which a civil war would be created by a Chinese “return to the
                        mainland,” on the grounds that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                        commitment was in the event of a U.S. attack. He would not go into detail as
                        to the plans for returning to the mainland, or for further cooperation with
                        the United States in combatting Communism in Asia, but said that if we can
                        come to a consensus on the question of who is the real enemy, we can work
                        out such details.</p>
                    <p>Rather surprisingly <persName>Chiang</persName> commented that your peace
                        offensive was a wise and effective effort. He also commented that the
                        Russian moves were especially significant, and should be watched very
                        closely.</p>
                    <p>As all Asian leaders have stated, there has been a measure of concern about
                        the U.S. intentions in South Vietnam stirred by the peace program. But I
                        reassured him strongly that we had no intention of seeking a peace that left
                        our friends unprotected. I parried his question as to what you would do if
                        the peace effort failed, by saying only that this was a matter for the
                        highest policy level, and would of course be up to you to decide. But we
                        would undoubtedly take all measures necessary to defeat the aggression.</p>
                    <pb facs="0273" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Chiang</persName> looks rather old, but very healthy, with ruddy
                        complexion and obviously in full command of himself. There are no signs of
                        senility that I could detect. He, of course, asked particularly after your
                        health and asked me to extend to you his best wishes. The conversation was
                        extremely friendly and cordial, and there was no effort to press for
                        decisions, nor any hint of chagrin that he has not been consulted lately. I
                        gave him your warm personal greetings, as I did to the Chinese people both
                        on arrival and departure at the airport.</p>
                    <p>[Here follows a report of the Vice President’s conversations in Korea.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>