<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-11-23T20:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-11-23T20:40:00-05:00" n="214" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d214">
                    <head>214. Circular Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of
                            State</gloss> to <gloss type="to">Certain Posts</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d214fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                            Files, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 6 CHICOM. Confidential;
                            Priority. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_GWHJ1">Gleysteen</persName>;
                            cleared by <persName corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName> and by the
                            advisers for United Nations affairs in <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>;
                            and approved by <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>. Sent to 30
                            Embassies and repeated to Kingston, Port-of-Spain, Santiago, Taipei, and
                                <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-11-23T20:40:00-05:00">November 23, 1966, 8:40 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>90629. Subj: ChiRep. Ref: Depcirtel 88129.<note n="2" xml:id="d214fn2">Circular telegram 88129, November 19, sent to 79 Embassies, stated that
                            the United States would support the study committee resolution but would
                            not lobby for it; it instructed the recipient Embassies to explain to
                            their host governments that the principal U.S. aim was to ensure
                            reaffirmation of the important question resolution and defeat of the
                            Albanian resolution. (Ibid.)</note>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Study Committee res submitted this year by Italians and others offers
                            opportunity to improve votes in favor IQ res and against Albanian res
                            since this new proposition may appeal to some countries which have in
                            past either voted affirmatively or abstained on Albanian res in absence
                            other alternatives before Assembly. Dept considers it important that we
                            exploit this opportunity to maximum extent that is appropriate.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Apart from local problems there is especially delicate aspect of any
                            representations which posts may make to host govts. We have informed
                                <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> that while we will vote for
                            study committee res, we will not lobby for it. <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> is strongly opposed to proposal, and any discussions
                            which posts undertake must in no way appear to host govts as direct or
                            indirect effort to influence them toward favorable vote on study
                            committee res. Our purpose is strictly limited to maximizing margin of
                            votes in favor of IQ res and against Albanian res, in order to show that
                                <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> is opposed to extremist
                            solutions.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Department strongly recommends, unless objection perceived, that
                            representations be made urgently and at high level. Arguments given
                            below may be drawn on selectively depending on attitude of host
                            governments. While we desire maximum number of affirmative votes for IQ
                            res and negative votes for Albanian res, posts authorized as final
                            fallback in both instances to suggest possibility of abstention or
                            absence if effect would be net improvement from our viewpoint.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Posts requested to report priority results of representations to Dept
                            repeating info for <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Following are suggested arguments: <list>
                                <label>(a)</label>
                                <item>Host govt has in past supported (or abstained on) Albanian res
                                    because it favored admission of ChiComs and not because it
                                    wished to expel <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has made it clear that it has
                                    not and will not lobby for study committee res, but availability
                                    this res provides host government <pb facs="0488" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/> with an alternative that avoids extreme of
                                    Albanian res which would produce irrevocable decision to expel
                                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> contrary to host govt’s
                                    policy. Thus we urge host govt not support (or abstain on)
                                    Albanian res.</item>
                                <label>(b)</label>
                                <item>Where appropriate, also urge for same reasons that host govt
                                    re-examine its vote on important question res. Charter
                                    explicitly provides that important question must be decided by a
                                    two-thirds majority. Change in representation of China obviously
                                    important question. Aside from Charter provisions, however,
                                    there is also additional political consideration that failure to
                                    uphold important question procedure could at some future time
                                    result in expulsion of <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>, a
                                    situation both <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> and host govt
                                    wish to avoid.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                                <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>