<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-11-28T06:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-11-28T06:30:00-05:00" n="218" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d218">
                    <head>218. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Republic of
                            China</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d218fn1">Source: Department of State,
                            Central Files, UN 6 CHICOM. Secret; Immediate; Exdis. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>. Passed to the White House.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Taipei</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-11-28T11:30:00+00:00">November 28, 1966,
                            1130Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>1568. ChiRep. Ref: State 91770 [91771].<note n="2" xml:id="d218fn2">Telegram
                            91771, November 26, transmitted the text of
                            <persName>Johnson</persName>’s message to <persName>Chiang</persName>.
                            Telegram 91770, November 26, sent to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> and repeated to Taipei, transmitted the text of
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s message to <persName corresp="#p_WT1">Wei</persName>. (Both ibid.) For texts of the
                            messages, see <ref target="#d217">Document 217</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>I had forty-five minute conversation with President
                                <persName>Chiang</persName> at 11 this morning Nov 28 at his
                            residence to deliver Pres <persName>Johnson</persName>’s letter
                            contained reftel. <gloss target="#t_DCM1">DCM</gloss> accompanied me,
                            and as before only Mme <persName>Chiang</persName>, Acting FonMin
                                <persName>Shen</persName>, and interpreter Frederick Ch’ien were
                            present. Atmosphere was somewhat more relaxed than on my previous call
                            Nov 23 (Taipei 1515).<note n="3" xml:id="d218fn3">
                                <ref target="#d213">Document 213</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>I made same introductory comments about the burden I knew Gimo was
                            carrying, and hoped he had some relaxation over weekend. I said I
                            appreciated his making time to see me on short notice. Gimo said he
                            always took pleasure in seeing me and <gloss target="#t_DCM1">DCM</gloss>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HAWJ1">Hummel</persName>.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>I handed to Gimo original and copies of President
                                <persName>Johnson</persName>’s letter, and interpreter gave
                            immediate verbal rendering, Mme <persName>Chiang</persName> and
                                <persName>Shen</persName> reading copies as translation proceeded.
                            Gimo said he had listened carefully, and appreciated the letter.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>I told Gimo that it seemed likely that Secy <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> could come to Taipei on evening of Dec 6, staying
                            all following day and leaving about noon Dec 8.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Gimo said that of course he welcomed Secretary’s visit. He said that
                            insofar as <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> problems were concerned,
                                <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> still hoped Italian resolution
                            might not pass and then <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> would need
                            to take no action. The situation would of course be discussed with Secy
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>. However, he said, he
                            understood that voting in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> will take
                            place this week and if Italian resolution passes, <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> cannot remain silent. The timing is
                            very important. However, he said, referring to the letter from President
                                <persName>Johnson</persName>, which he considered to be sincere and
                            frank, he would bring the letter to the attention of officials of his
                            govt so that they could consult further on the problem.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>I asked if dates for Secy’s visit were convenient, and Gimo replied
                            that they were.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Gimo said that the most important question to study now is how to
                            defeat the Italian resolution. He said that once it has passed the GRC
                                <pb facs="0497" n="463" xml:id="pg_463"/> ”would have to make its
                            position clear to the world.” He hoped this was understood by <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>I replied that I understood what he had told me on this point in this
                            conversation and in previous conversations.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Gimo said that of course before he took any action he would have to
                            consult with officers of his govt. He said that he would inform the
                                <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> of his govt’s decision, would
                            get <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> reaction, and would continue
                            consult with us.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>I said I hoped we could keep in very close contact on this matter, and
                            that I was available at any hour of day or night for any
                            consultations.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Gimo repeated that the most important task is to defeat the Italian
                            resolution. He said that he had studied the Secretary’s letter to FonMin
                                <persName corresp="#p_WT1">Wei</persName>, and that although he
                            fully understood that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has adopted
                            passive attitude, it is still most important that the resolution be
                            defeated.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>I said I wished to give a brief resume of recent developments relative
                            to the pending UN resolutions. I said there had been full exchanges on
                            this in Washington, New York, and elsewhere with <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> officials and with representatives of many countries. I
                            said we had also told US Embassies to make it clear to other govts that
                            we are not lobbying for, pushing, or soliciting votes for the
                            resolution. Our representatives are also making it explicit that we
                            would not object to or hold it against any country wishing to oppose the
                            resolution.</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>I noted that our intention to vote affirmatively on Italian resolution
                            was based on the commitment we were compelled to give in order to obtain
                            the very crucial votes of certain countries that were wavering on the
                            Albanian resolution. We are now bound to honor our word but Gimo could
                            rest assured that our vote is not an enthusiastic one. We believe that
                            our tactical decision has safeguarded from 6 to 8 votes which are
                            essential in order to assure defeat of Albanian proposal. It could be
                            seen that our move would have a successful result.</item>
                        <label>14.</label>
                        <item>I said we had given careful and sympathetic consideration to the
                            diplomatic note sent to us November 26 asking us not to vote for the
                            Italian proposal.<note n="4" xml:id="d218fn4">Not found.</note> In view
                            of commitment we have already made to other nations in order to assure
                            defeat of the Albanian resolution, we cannot change our vote now.
                            However, I was confident other nations understood our position and
                            clearly realized we are not pressing any other country to vote for the
                            Italian proposal.</item>
                        <label>15.</label>
                        <item>Gimo asked if US position could be made clear to Japanese Govt. He
                            said similar diplomatic note had also been sent to Japanese Embassy here
                            requesting <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> abstain. He said that
                            what I had told him of US instructions should be made clear to <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> and he made a direct request that we
                            accomplish this.</item>
                        <pb facs="0498" n="464" xml:id="pg_464"/>
                        <label>16.</label>
                        <item>I said I was sure that this had already been done, but would send a
                            special message (see septel) asking that US position be explained once
                            again to <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss>.<note n="5" xml:id="d218fn5">
                                <persName corresp="#p_MCWPJ1">McConaughy</persName> sent this
                                message in telegram 1565 from Taipei, November 28. Telegram 92145,
                                November 28, conveyed the request to Tokyo, and telegram 3998 from
                                Tokyo, November 29, reported that Ambassador
                                    <persName>Johnson</persName> had spoken to Vice Foreign Minister
                                Shimoda, who stated that he would instruct the Japanese Ambassador
                                in Taipei to make it clear to the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> that the U.S. Government had never asked the
                                Japanese Government to support the Italian resolution. (All in
                                Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 6 CHICOM)</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>17.</label>
                        <item>Gimo expressed his thanks. He said that my approach today, the letter
                            from President <persName>Johnson</persName>, and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s letter to FonMin <persName corresp="#p_WT1">Wei</persName> would all be discussed with GRC
                            officials. He said that I would be informed of decision when it is
                            reached.</item>
                        <label>18.</label>
                        <item>I said we had carefully studied the voting prospects on all three
                            resolutions, and that on the essential ones, which were the important
                            question and the Albanian, we were confident of favorable outcome. We do
                            not yet know, however, what will be the result of voting on Italian
                            proposal. The position of many countries appeared uncertain, and we do
                            not know whether it will be defeated or passed.</item>
                        <label>19</label>
                        <item>Gimo repeated that if <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> were to
                            support <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> in working on this, Italian
                            resolution could be defeated. He said <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> is fully aware of the very important implications of
                            the Italian resolution and would have to take a position based on <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>’s own interests, and also those of US,
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and allies. He said all these
                            interests will be taken into account in <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> deliberations.</item>
                        <label>20.</label>
                        <item>I said we had been thinking of contingency planning in the event that
                            the Italian resolution were to pass and of appropriate action <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> might take to make its position clear.
                            I said I would like to suggest in rough form some language <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> might wish to consider for use in a
                            declaration in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in that event, along
                            following lines: “<gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> has every
                            confidence that any objective study of ChiRep must have the result of
                            reaffirmation of the status of the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                            as the only qualified, lawful and representative Government of China.
                            Therefore, <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> has nothing to fear from
                            a study of the question, although it is unnecessary. However, in the
                            event of any objectionable recommendation by the study committee, the
                                <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> reserves its full rights to take
                            any action it considers necessary and appropriate under the
                            circumstances.” I said it was our belief that such a statement would be
                            dignified, appropriate, and sufficient to safeguard GRC interests and
                            prestige.</item>
                        <label>21.</label>
                        <item>Gimo replied that my suggestion would be of value for <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> reference and discussion, but Chinese
                            people would never understand if such a statement were made. However, he
                            said, he would have to consult with other govt officials on this as well
                            as other points.</item>
                        <pb facs="0499" n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/>
                        <label>22.</label>
                        <item>I said I hoped the public would be enabled to understand the US
                            position. I noted that Chinese press seems to be giving the erroneous
                            impression that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has been proceeding
                            in the direction of a “two-Chinas” policy in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. This could be damaging to our joint interests if it
                            should become widespread. I hoped the impression could be
                            corrected.</item>
                        <label>23.</label>
                        <item>Gimo assured me he would do what could be done to see that Chinese
                            people understood and do not get wrong impression of US intentions.
                            However, the Chinese people would not understand if <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> were to take any action that does not
                            conform to its present foreign policies. He said he would carefully
                            consider this matter. Alloted time for interview was clearly up at this
                            point.</item>
                        <label>24.</label>
                        <item>As we left Presidential residence, I told Acting FonMin
                                <persName>Shen</persName> that I had a few additional points I
                            wished to make and we adjourned to Shen’s office for further
                            discussion.</item>
                        <label>25.</label>
                        <item>I told Shen that I wished to reaffirm the contingency assurance given
                            by Secretary Rusk in 1964 that USG intended veto any attempt at ChiCom
                            admission to Security Council, if veto would be effective. However, if
                            the GRC had already left the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, our
                            parliamentary position in trying to keep Chinese Communists out would be
                            vastly more difficult. We have grave doubt that veto in the Security
                            Council would be effective under those circumstances. Most Security
                            Council members would probably think that in absence of GRC from UN,
                            filling of vacant China seat would be purely procedural matter of
                            credentials, and that veto would be inapplicable on those grounds. I
                            told Shen GRC should not assume that it would be possible to keep
                            ChiComs out of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> if <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> withdrew. We anticipated that once GRC
                            left, ChiComs would have relatively easy sailing. If GRC stayed firmly
                            in UN, however, chances of keeping ChiComs out would be very good. GRC
                            should be under no delusion that walkout could be only a temporary
                            maneuver. Both from the viewpoint of psychological effect on vote of
                            countries that are already wavering, and in terms of parliamentary
                            procedures open to the opposition, walkout would likely be final,
                            however <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> intended.</item>
                        <label>26.</label>
                        <item>I noted that recent ChiCom public statements reveal a somewhat softer
                            position on conditions for ChiCom entry into UN. I referred to November
                            25 column in Peoples Daily, signed “Observer” which strongly attacked
                            Canadian proposition but which omitted any reference to the preposterous
                            conditions that ChiComs laid down last year as prerequisites to their
                            entry into <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. This article also
                            carefully avoided usual intemperate language which might alienate the
                            uncommitted. It is possible that ChiComs are now actively interested in
                            obtaining <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> entry. In any event, it is
                            evident to us that there would be great rejoicing in Peiping if GRC
                            walked out. <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> should give most sober
                            and skeptical consideration to any prospective course that would play
                            into hands of ChiComs and harm US, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>,
                            and allies.</item>
                        <pb facs="0500" n="466" xml:id="pg_466"/>
                        <label>27.</label>
                        <item>I said it was our considered view that US security position in
                            Southeast Asia could be seriously prejudiced by <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> walkout. I asked <persName>Shen</persName> to give this
                            his solemn consideration. Chinese Communists would be emboldened by
                            apparent success their tough stance, and might be tempted to intervene
                            more openly in SEA. I reminded Shen that Gimo had assured Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> on July 3 that GRC policy
                            was first and foremost to give help to US position in Vietnam, ahead of
                            any other <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> obligation. If GRC did not
                            hold fast in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, US position in Vietnam
                            would be affected adversely. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> said in letter to FonMin <persName corresp="#p_WT1">Wei</persName>, <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> departure would
                            confuse <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>’s friends and help its
                            enemies. It would be interpreted as a grave setback for the US and
                            allies, exposing allied position in Vietnam and undermining allied
                            influence in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>28.</label>
                        <item>I said that if <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> persisted in
                            withdrawal move, it would almost seem that GRC was not interested in
                            maintaining the traditional posture of a great national government,
                            aware of its international ties and responsibilities. In self-imposed
                            isolation from international life, GRC would have more the posture of a
                            local regime of some kind. A GRC with no <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> status would give impetus to the unfriendly argument in
                            the UN that government here was acting as a local regime and should be
                            considered as under the authority of Peiping. USG of course did not
                            share such unwarranted opinion but its widespread existence in UN might
                            make it difficult to uphold the juridical position of <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>29.</label>
                        <item>I repeated my view expressed to Chang Chun on Nov. 26 that GRC could
                            not really be humiliated by resolutely staying in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and defending its principles. I said that abusive
                            tactics of unworthy persons or nations cannot humilate those who are
                            worthy. By remaining in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> status would by no means be demeaned,
                            but rather would be enhanced by exhibition of GRC courage and resolve in
                            standing up to contemptible efforts of its enemies.</item>
                        <label>30.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Shen</persName> promised to convey all the foregoing
                            representations to President immediately. He said would give final
                            answer after further deliberations had been undertaken.</item>
                        <label>31.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Shen</persName> then said with considerable asperity that the
                            GRC had just about reached its limit in enduring insults at UN. He said
                                <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> position in Security Council had
                            been eroded, the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> had been “kicked
                            out of” Ecosoc, and with the departure of Wellington Koo for the first
                            time there was no representative on the ICJ of a permanent member of SC.
                            He said that most recently in course of tactical deliberation on
                            Israel-Jordan situation, USG had not consulted GRC, that GRC was not
                            included in any of consultative groups, and that the US officials
                            “walked right by GRC representatives in UN lounge, without greeting or
                            comment.” He said <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> is not in fact
                            highly regarded by <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> members or even by
                            some US officials. However, calming down considerably, he said <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> would give all these US representations
                            very serious consideration. He said he <pb facs="0501" n="467" xml:id="pg_467"/> did not know how the decision would come out, but
                            he thought it would be reached and would be conveyed to me in a very
                            short time.</item>
                        <label>32.</label>
                        <item>In closing the conversation I urged again that no final walkout
                            decision if Italian resolution were to pass should be taken before
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s visit.</item>
                        <label>33.</label>
                        <item>Comment: Failure of Gimo and <persName>Shen</persName> to reiterate
                            previous assertion that decision is final is of course hopeful sign.
                            However, I believe crisis is far from over and it is entirely
                            conceivable that Gimo has been somewhat stung by our references to rash
                            and precipitous decision and is merely demonstrating to us the soberness
                            with which GRC will consider all aspects of situation. It is also
                            possible that representations made by me and by Embassy officers to
                            substantial number of <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> figures may
                            have resulted in some voices being raised against Gimo’s proposed course
                            of action. If there have been such voices, however, they have probably
                            not been very loud and Gimo clearly has capability to override them if
                            he remains determined to walk out. <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                            mind seems a little less closed today than yesterday but situation
                            remains precarious.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MCWPJ1">
                                <hi rend="strong">McConaughy</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>