<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>229. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant (Rostow) to President
                    ) to President Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d229</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">229</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-01-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-01-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="229"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d229">
                <head>229. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant (<persName type="from"
                        >Rostow</persName>) to President <persName type="to">Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d229fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, China, Vol. VIII. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-01-09">January 9, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>China’s Vaulting Chaos</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName>’s regime is in serious difficulty,
                    to a degree that civil war has become a distinct possibility.</p>
                <p>Months of growing chaos in the top leadership are now followed by widespread
                    resistance to pro-Mao elements in Central, South and East China, as <persName
                        corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName>’s Red Guards and other “rebel” groups have
                    attempted to move the Cultural Revolution to farms and factories. You have noted
                    reports of violent clashes in Canton, Foochow, Shanghai, Nanking, the Chusan
                    Islands and Peking itself, and of the breakdown of rail service in several
                    sectors. In Nanking large-scale arrests (apparently of pro-Mao elements!) by
                    Army and public security forces have been reported.</p>
                <p>The source of most of our information on this highly confused situation remains
                    press reports of “wall newspapers” in Peking. However, both Peking and Shanghai
                    broadcasts have now confirmed serious resistance, and have warned of adverse
                    effects on production. At the same time the Peking broadcast insists “It is an
                    erroneous point of view that the Great Cultural Revolution antagonizes the
                    development of production!” <persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName> forces
                    are evidently determined to go through with their attempted “proletarianization”
                    of the nation despite mounting costs now threatening the regime itself.</p>
                <p>Most of the clashes have occurred in areas where Propaganda Chief T’ao Chu,
                    number four in the Peking hierarchy, retains strong support of the party
                    machinery. Much of this resistance has doubtless been triggered by recent
                    official attacks on T’ao, principally on the part of <persName
                        corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName>’s wife. Attacks on T’ao were probably in
                    turn prompted by his attempts to protect provincial party cadre who are opposing
                    the Mao-Lin line.</p>
                <p>The battle is clearly drawn. On <persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_LPLB1">Lin</persName>’s side appear to be: <list>
                        <item>—a small and seemingly dwindling minority in the party;</item>
                        <item>—probably the bulk of the seriously divided Red Guards; and</item>
                        <item>—an indeterminate percentage of the armed forces.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Ranged against these are, apparently: <list>
                        <item>—the bulk of both the leadership and the lesser party
                            apparatus;</item>
                        <item>—a goodly portion of the worker groups so far tested by Red Guard
                            revolutionary activity; and</item>
                        <item>—an unknown portion of the Army.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0534" n="500" xml:id="pg_500"/>
                <p>Much more resistance from workers and peasants seems sure to come, as <persName
                        corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName>’s revolution is carried further into the
                    provinces.</p>
                <p>The big question mark is the direction in which the Army will finally lend its
                    predominant support. It cannot stand aside much longer, if present chaos
                    continues. If it proves to be as divided as other major elements of the nation
                    have been, the “<persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName> dynasty” is in for
                    more bloody convulsions, and almost certain demise.</p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_CEZE1">Chou</persName> remains the best hope of
                    achieving a compromise in the interest of preserving the nation and the regime’s
                    hard-won, limited accomplishments. However, <persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1"
                        >Mao</persName> has made his war one of veritable “religious” fervor, and
                    compromise now appears highly unlikely. We must expect one side or the other to
                    win out. As of now the anti-Mao forces appear the stronger, and gaining. It is
                    curious that <persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName>’s heir apparent,
                        <persName corresp="#p_LPLB1">Lin Piao</persName>, has not appeared since
                    November 26. Mao-Lin interests in Peking appear to have been left primarily in
                    Madame <persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName>’s hands, and the precarious
                    condition of those interests is underlined today by wall posters announcing the
                    dissolution of the capital’s anti-Mao public security forces, and—perhaps the
                    most significant straw in today’s East wind—other posters accusing National
                    Defense Council Member, General Liu Chih-chien, of siding with the
                    anti-Maoists.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Walt</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
