<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>316. Memorandum From Alfred Jenkins of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Special Assistant ( of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Special Assistant (Rostow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-07-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recykDuvfC6iFH3Xe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="recr8VLurZi7KY9hd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture">Food shortages</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-07-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="316"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d316">
                <head>316. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_JALS1" type="from">Alfred
                        Jenkins</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s
                    Special Assistant (<persName type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d316fn1">Source: <persName>Johnson</persName> Library,
                        National Security File, Country File, China, Vol. XIII. Secret. A copy was
                        sent to <persName corresp="#p_JWJ1">Jorden</persName>.
                            <persName>Rostow</persName> sent the memorandum, along with some
                        intelligence reports, to the President with a covering memorandum of the
                        same date, noting that the disarray in China might help explain “the Soviet
                        willingness to proceed with arms control measures with the U.S. and to
                        interject itself so deeply in the Vietnam affair.” (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-07-02">July 2, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>China Mainland Situation</item>
                </list>
                <p>Since the Wuhan episode of last summer, the conservatives in general have had
                    their way more—often with Army collusion or acquiescence. This has concerned the
                    Maoists, and <persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao</persName> on June 2 issued one of
                    his infrequent delphic “instructions” to the effect that the masses were to be
                    given their rein at all costs. This has resulted, not unexpectedly, in a rise in
                    fighting throughout June. The level has not yet reached that of last summer, but
                    it is well on the way, and we have again a situation which could deteriorate
                    fairly rapidly.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the chief difference between last summer and now is that Cultural
                    Revolution dislocations have begun to bring suffering to larger and larger
                    numbers of citizens. Illegal immigrants into Hong Kong give most frequently as
                    reasons for fleeing, unemployment and food shortages. Lack of raw materials,
                    labor troubles and not infrequently sabotage have reduced production in many
                    enterprises to the point where salaries cannot be met. We have reports of both
                    grave robberies (especially in rur-al areas, valuables are still often buried
                    with the dead) and the sale of children—both typical phenomena in times of
                    crisis in China. (One woman spoke of being offered the equivalent of about
                    $45.00 for her son, but she was holding out for more.) Vehicles, even public
                    buses, are being stolen for use in factional fighting, and bicycles are at such
                    a premium in some places where public transportation has ceased to function,
                    that they are being wrested out from under the riders.</p>
                <p>Serious floods are reported from six provinces in Southeast China. The early rice
                    crop in Kwangtung may be off as much as 10–15%, and planting of late rice will
                    be delayed.</p>
                <p>All three North-South rail lines have had interruptions for considerable periods
                    in June from floods, landslides and fighting around the stations. (We are not
                    sure whether military-manned priority trains are getting through, where “acts of
                    God” are not the cause of the interruptions.) Many letters mention that the
                    writer is stranded away from home or work because of lack of transportation.</p>
                <pb facs="0722" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/>
                <p>No one knows what all this will ultimately mean, of course. However, one is now
                    tempted to alter the British witticism of last fall to the effect “the situation
                    is excellent, but not hopeless.” Things must be beginning to look pretty
                    hopeless to the average Chinese. If the regime could bring itself to give the
                    conservatives their way, things could quiet down, but there are no signs that
                    the regime will do that. Almost anything could happen in coming months, but the
                    best bet still is that a portion of the military will get fed up and take
                    matters into their own hands. If the Maoists’ opposition should begin to jell,
                    we should see radio stations taken over. So far, this has happened in only a
                    couple of places very temporarily some months ago. It was premature.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">AJ</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
