<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>80. National Intelligence Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d80</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">80</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-03-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recakeAztvHvxtY4X" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2013002394"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">MIG</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recPnftMNhM1QKAYO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Stockpile</term>
                    <term ref="recfkRWjb8Vcm4Gga" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005004553"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Warheads</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-03-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="80"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d80">
                <head>80. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d80fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/EAP Files:
                        Lot 90 D 110, <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 13–3–65. Secret.
                        Controlled Dissem. According to a note on the cover sheet, the estimate was
                        submitted by the Director of Central Intelligence and prepared by the <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and the intelligence organizations of the
                        Departments of State and Defense, Atomic Energy Commission, and the National
                        Security Agency. All members of the U.S. Intelligence Board concurred on
                        March 10, except the Assistant to the Director of the Federal Bureau of
                        Investigation, who abstained on the grounds that the subject was outside his
                        jurisdiction.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 13–3–65</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-03-10">March 10, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">COMMUNIST CHINA’S MILITARY ESTABLISHMENT</p>
                <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                <p>To assess the character and present effectiveness of Communist China’s armed
                    forces, and to estimate trends which would affect their future capabilities.</p>
                <p rend="center">Note</p>
                <p>This estimate is the first to attempt a comprehensive analysis of the broad range
                    of questions pertaining to Communist China’s military establishment. The Chinese
                    Communist regime’s intensive and highly effective security measures make China,
                    in general, a difficult intelligence target. Estimating the nature and scope of
                    the Chinese military production effort is made more difficult because much of
                    the program is still in the developmental and factory construction stages. We
                    are thus unable to make confident judgments on many important matters concerning
                    the nature, scope, and prospects of Chinese Communist military developments and
                    this paper should be read in the light of this general caution.</p>
                <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>Communist Party influence permeates all levels of the Peoples Liberation
                        Army (the entire Chinese Communist military establishment). The senior
                        political and military leaders are united by ties of comradeship in a long
                        revolutionary war. Political commissars are assigned to every command down
                        to company level. Although the troops are conscripts, they are selected for
                        political reliability and receive constant political indoctrination. (Paras.
                        12–13, and para. 1 of Annex B)</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese Communists continue to proclaim the military doctrine of
                            <persName corresp="#p_MTMZ1">Mao Tse-tung</persName> which stresses
                        self-reliance, the dominance of men and politics over weaponry, and the
                        concept of a protracted “people’s war.” This doctrine, deemed applicable to
                        “wars of national liberation,” <pb facs="0187" n="153" xml:id="pg_153"/> is
                        also applied to a potential conflict with the US. Communist China is
                        apprehensive regarding the possibility of a US nuclear attack followed by a
                        large-scale invasion, but holds that in such a case China could accept
                        nuclear devastation and still overwhelm the invaders in a protracted
                        “people’s war.” The Chinese leaders hope that this prospect will deter the
                        US. (Paras. 6–10)</item>
                    <label>C.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese leaders, however, cannot derive much comfort from this
                        rationalization of their present strategic situation. Since coming to power
                        in 1949, they have steadily sought to modernize their military
                        establishment. They have considered it a matter of first importance to
                        develop an independent nuclear capability. (Paras. 1, 11)</item>
                    <label>D.</label>
                    <item>Communist China’s military power derives primarily from the numerical
                        strength of the Chinese Communist Army (<gloss target="#t_CCA1"
                        >CCA</gloss>), some 2.3 million men, and tremendous reserves of manpower.
                        Although the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> is essentially an infantry
                        force, its capabilities for combat are formidable. In open warfare against
                        modern opposition, it would be hampered by shortages of armored equipment,
                        heavy ordnance, mechanical transport and <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                        >POL</gloss>. In mountainous or jungle terrain, these shortages would be of
                        less importance. In 1961, many Chinese units had serious shortages of
                        equipment and were understrength. The Chinese have sought to ameliorate this
                        situation by bringing up to strength and fully equipping selected divisions.
                        We estimate that as many as one-third of the combat divisions have been so
                        improved, and are distributed throughout most of China’s military regions.
                        We lack the information to make any confident estimates of present
                        production rates of specific items of army equipment, but Communist China
                        has sizable facilities for the production of such materiel. We believe that
                        the production at land armaments plants has increased over the low 1960–1963
                        level and that it will continue to increase. (Paras. 15–17, 28, 38, and
                        paras. 1–10 of Annex B)</item>
                    <label>E.</label>
                    <item>The mainstay of the Chinese Communist fighter force in the air force and
                        navy is the some 1,600 <gloss target="#t_MIG1">MIG</gloss>-15s and <gloss
                            target="#t_MIG1">MIG</gloss>-17s. There are also about 150 <gloss
                            target="#t_MIG1">MIG</gloss>-19s and 25 to 35 <gloss target="#t_MIG1"
                            >MIG</gloss>-21s. Except for the <gloss target="#t_MIG1"
                        >MIG</gloss>-21s, these aircraft are obsolescent and probably less than 10
                        percent of these fighters have airborne intercept equipment. The backbone of
                        China’s air offense would be the 270 or so IL–28 jet light bombers. They
                        also have 12 or so TU–16 medium bombers capable of carrying a bulky nuclear
                        weapon. Attrition has taken its toll of aircraft in service and the Chinese
                        aircraft industry is only now approaching the capability to arrest this
                        decline. The Chinese have been adding to all of their aircraft development
                        and production centers, and there are indications that they are getting
                        ready to produce the <gloss target="#t_MIG1">MIG</gloss>-19, or the <gloss
                            target="#t_MIG1">MIG</gloss>-21 and may, indeed be in the early stages
                        of production. We believe the chances are less than even that production of
                        bombers will begin during the next two or three years. (Paras. 22, 27,
                        41–43, and paras. 1–7 of Annex A)</item>
                    <pb facs="0188" n="154" xml:id="pg_154"/>
                    <label>F.</label>
                    <item>The primary mission of the Chinese Communist Navy (<gloss target="#t_CCN1"
                            >CCN</gloss>) is coastal defense. Its major combatant units are 21
                        operational W-class submarines, 4 Gordy-class destroyers, 4 Riga-class
                        destroyer escorts, and 14 patrol escorts. The <gloss target="#t_CCN1"
                            >CCN</gloss> also has about 155 motor torpedo boats. The capabilities of
                        the <gloss target="#t_CCN1">CCN</gloss> against modern opposition would be
                        limited by obsolescent equipment and probably by substandard combat
                        proficiency of its crews. We believe the Chinese have placed a high priority
                        on construction of submarines. We estimate that by mid-1966 the Chinese
                        Communist naval order of battle will include 25 W-class submarines. (Paras.
                        15, 25, 44, and paras. 8–11 of Annex A)</item>
                    <label>G.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese have given top priority to their nuclear weapons and missile
                        programs. On the basis of our scanty evidence, we estimate that the Chinese,
                        over the next two years, will be able to carry out a nuclear test program
                        and stockpile about 10 bombs. In the ballistic missile field, we believe the
                        Chinese are developing a medium-range missile (1,000 n.m.) modeled on the
                        Soviet SS–4. It is possible that by 1967 or 1968 the Chinese could have a
                        few such missiles with compatible fission warheads. The Chinese almost
                        certainly are determined to develop a nuclear strike capability against US
                        territory. This determination could be reflected in the initiation of
                        programs in the near future looking toward longer run development of a
                        limited number of <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>s and the
                        construction of a small fleet of missile carrying submarines. Even if the
                        Chinese have already begun work on such programs, we believe that they could
                        not pose a threat to the US until sometime after 1970. (Paras. 51–52,
                        56)</item>
                    <label>H.</label>
                    <item>During the last year or two, Communist China’s industry has begun to
                        revive from the severe setbacks it suffered when the Great Leap Forward
                        collapsed and the Soviets withdrew most of their assistance in 1960. We
                        believe the Chinese leaders will sustain substantial military production
                        even at the risk of serious economic difficulty. However, China’s economy
                        will not be able to support anything approaching a maximum production effort
                        by all sectors of military industry and in coming years the Chinese will
                        have to make a number of difficult decisions regarding priorities. We cannot
                        predict in what quantities Peiping may decide to turn out the various items
                        of equipment, and there is a good chance that the Chinese themselves do not
                        yet see their way clearly. (Paras. 31, 34, 56)</item>
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <item>Nevertheless, barring some major setback, Communist China’s military power
                        will gradually grow and this growing power will almost certainly increase
                        Peiping’s political leverage against its Asian neighbors—whether or not
                        Chinese Communist leaders actually engage in direct hostilities or commit
                        armed forces abroad. (Paras. 53, 55)</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follow the Discussion portion of the estimate and two annexes.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
