<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Smith) ) to the United States
                    Delegation at the Council of Foreign Ministers in Paris</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d177</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">177</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-06-17T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-06-17T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-17T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-17T02:00:00-05:00" n="177"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d177">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Moscow Embassy Files: Telegram<note n="37"
                        xml:id="d177fn37">Moscow Embassy 1946 Files, Lot F–96, Acc. No. 59 A 543,
                        Part VI, Box 367, File—500 Foreign Ministers Meetings—Paris.</note>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">United States Delegation
                            at the Council of Foreign Ministers in Paris</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-17T10:00:00+03:00"
                            >June 17, 1946—10 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>185. Personal for Matthews from Smith. While I have nothing specific on which to
                    base the following statements, nevertheless as the result of conversations with
                    Soviet officials and others I have the impression that while the Soviet
                    delegation is very pessimistic about the <pb facs="0550" n="528" xml:id="pg_528"
                    /> outcome of the Paris Conference, they are quite as anxious as we are to avoid
                    a complete break-up, and that it may become of great importance in connection
                    with irreconciliable questions such as Trieste to find some formula which will
                    allow the Soviets more time to make the changes of position which with them are
                    the essential preliminary to any compromise. Such formulas would not necessarily
                    be ones which we expected to offer even slight hopes of definitive success,
                    providing they are sufficiently reasonable on the surface to serve this interim
                        purpose.<note n="38" xml:id="d177fn38">
                        <p>Telegram 2003, June 25, 1946, from Moscow, retransmitted as telegram
                            3100, <gloss target="#t_Secdel1">Secdel</gloss> 350, June 26, 1946, to
                            Paris, added the following views of Ambassador Smith on this same
                            subject: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“There is becoming apparent an increasing Soviet tendency to pose
                                    as defender of Italian sovereignty and independence against the
                                    imperialistic designs of British and US. It is probable that
                                    Soviet press will shortly begin to sound a note of increasing
                                    appreciation of Italian contribution to the victory over Germany
                                    and of growing Italian democracy. It seems to me that this
                                    trend, given time to develop, may preface a less rigid attitude
                                    on Trieste as indicated in my last message to you.”
                                    (761.65/6–2546)</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>On the other hand, I would view with great reserve any report that the Soviets
                    are already preparing to recede at this time from their former intransigent
                    attitude.</p>
                <p>I know you realize better than anyone the pattern which our friends follow in
                    these negotiations. I repeat that the above is based on no specific information,
                    but only on the local atmosphere and my conviction that the important thing is
                    to allow the Soviets sufficient time for an orderly change of position.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
