<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-21T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-21T14:00:00-05:00" n="26" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/3–2146: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dunn</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                            the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-21T19:00:00+00:00">March 21, 1946—7
                            p.m.</date><lb/>[Received March 21—6:05 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>3255. This is <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 298 from Dunn. During
                        the discussion yesterday of the French proposals for the organization of the
                        Paris Conference (reference <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss>
                            297<note n="54" xml:id="d26fn54"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>)
                        the French representative asked the deputies to ascertain the views of their
                        governments whether the conference is to be held on May 1 even if the agreed
                        drafts are not yet ready.</p>
                    <p>I stated that there was still adequate time to prepare the necessary drafts,
                        that I was confident we could and would make progress in this respect, and
                        that my government expects the conference will be convened on May 1 as
                        agreed in Moscow. Jebb supported this position.</p>
                    <p>Soviet deputy declared that the sole purpose of the conference was to
                        consider the agreed drafts of peace treaties prepared by the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>, that it was not intended that it should
                        prepare such drafts and, if no drafts were ready, a new situation had arisen
                        which was not contemplated by the Moscow agreement. He asked what the
                        conference could accomplish in the event that the drafts were not completed
                        when it met as its terms of reference would only permit it to make
                        recommendations upon the basis of existing drafts.</p>
                    <p>French deputy is concerned lest his government, after having issued
                        invitations to the conference on behalf of the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>, will at the last minute be faced with the inability of the
                        Five Powers to agree upon the functions of the conference and that it will
                        meet without any useful task to perform. He urged the deputies to consult
                        their governments and to inform him as soon as possible of their views. It
                        was anticipated that the French Government would issue the invitations on or
                        about April 1 unless prior to that time an agreement to the contrary had
                        been reached between the states members of the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>As it was clear that Gusev was not ready to state whether his government
                        would agree to having the conference if the drafts had not been completed,
                        I, as chairman, suggested that in any matters with regard to the invitations
                        for the conference itself, upon which the French Government wished
                        clarification, it would be advisable for that government to deal directly
                        with the other governments represented on the Council of Foreign
                        Ministers.</p>
                    <p>Although Gusev stated he was without instructions, it was quite apparent to
                        me that by his insistence upon the literal interpretation of the opening
                        phrase of paragraph 2 of the Moscow communiqué of last December<note n="55" xml:id="d26fn55"><ref target="frus1945v02#pg_815"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 815</ref>.</note> he was indicating that his government
                        will oppose <pb facs="0051" n="33" xml:id="pg_33"/> the convening of the
                        conference at Paris until a further measure of agreement has been reached
                        upon the drafts, which to their minds probably means acceptance of the
                        Soviet position on at least some of the major points.</p>
                    <p>I had a talk with Couve de Murville this afternoon before his return to
                        Paris. He said that the French Government would address communications to
                        US, UK and USSR Governments in an effort to clear up two points with respect
                        to projected Paris Conference. One is the question whether all of the
                        countries that are invited will be expected and authorized to discuss all of
                        the treaties or whether certain countries would be restricted to discussing
                        only certain treaties as Gusev indicated yesterday might be what the Soviet
                        Government would suggest, The second point is the exact date upon which the
                        conference is to be convened. That entails a clarification and agreement
                        whether the conference will be held even in the event the drafts of all the
                        treaties are not entirely completed.</p>
                    <closer>[<signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dunn</hi></signed>]</closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>[In a message dated March 21, Foreign Secretary Bevin urged Secretary
                            Byrnes to postpone the issuance of invitations for a meeting of the
                            Council of Foreign Ministers in view of the developments in the Iranian
                            case before the United Nations Security Council. For the text of Bevin’s
                            message, see <ref target="frus1946v07#pg_368">Volume VII, page
                            368</ref>.]</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>