<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The British Ambassador (
                        Halifax
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-03-22T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">841.002/3–2246</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-22">22 March,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Secretary of State</hi>: Mr. Bevin received your
                    message through the United States Chargé d’Affaires in London early this
                    morning, March 22nd.<note n="56" xml:id="d28fn56">Reference here is to the
                        message quoted in telegram 2740, March 21, to London, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>He has asked me to give you the enclosed personal message in reply.</p>
                <p>This personal message was despatched after Mr. Bevin had received my account of
                    my telephone talk with you yesterday.</p>
                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Halifax</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Bevin</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-22">March 22,
                                1946</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Many thanks for your message of March 22nd.</p>
                    <p>I still think it would be a mistake to send your proposed message to Molotov
                        until at least the Security Council has had some discussion of the Persian
                        issue and we can see how things are going to work out. This would still give
                        Molotov plenty of time to make his plans to go to Paris on April 25th if he
                        so desires. I fully agree that we should call this Paris meeting of Foreign
                        Ministers in order to show that we are resolved that Peace Conference shall
                        meet on May 1st and be a success. The meeting would of course also deal with
                        questions raised by the French about Germany.</p>
                    <p>I really think I cannot attend a meeting next Monday. There are three
                        front-line Cabinet Ministers in India, and in addition there is the enormous
                        task of beating the famine in our areas in the Far East, as well as a heavy
                        Parliamentary programme. I assure you that I am absolutely with you on the
                        fundamental importance for <gloss target="#t_UNO1">U.N.O.</gloss> of the
                        Persian issue, but I really don’t think that it would contribute if I
                        hurried across to attend one meeting. I feel that, if I did come over and
                        Gromyko adopted the stalling tactics which he has threatened, <pb facs="0053" n="35" xml:id="pg_35"/> I should be placed in a difficult
                        position. You in such circumstances could retire to Washington; but if I
                        were to return to England with the business unfinished it would look
                        extremely bad. My view is that Russian tactics will not be influenced by my
                        presence at the meeting but I will remain constant. If a real crisis
                        threatening the whole future of <gloss target="#t_UNO1">U.N.O.</gloss> were
                        to develop of course I should try to overcome all difficulties and join
                        you.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
