<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>United States Delegation Minutes, Council of Foreign
                        Ministers, Third Session, Third Meeting, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, New York,
                        November 6, 1946, 10:30 a.m.
                    For a list of persons present at this meeting,
                        see Record of Decisions, infra.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d305</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">305</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-11-06T10:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-11-06T10:30:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-06T10:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-06T10:30:00-05:00" n="305" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d305">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> Files: Lot M–88: Box 2080: <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Minutes</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Minutes, Council of Foreign
                        Ministers, Third Session, Third Meeting, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, New York,
                        November 6, 1946, 10:30 a.m.</hi>
                    <note n="54" xml:id="d305fn54">For a list of persons present at this meeting,
                        see Record of Decisions, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-06T10:30:00-05:00">November 6, 1946, 10:30 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <lb/>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_USDELCFM46NY1">USDEL(CFM) (46) (NY)</gloss> 3d
                        Meeting</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Views of the Yugoslav and Italian Governments</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: The meeting is opened. I propose to invite
                    the Secretary General to bring the representatives of Italy and Yugoslavia into
                    the room and to hear the Yugoslavs first. We shall hear their views with regard
                    to Article 16 of the draft peace treaty with Italy.</p>
                <p>(The representatives of Italy and Yugoslavia entered the room and took their
                        seats.)<note n="55" xml:id="d305fn55">The Italian representatives were
                        Ambassador Tarchiani and Count Nicolo Carandini, Italian Ambassador to the
                        United Kingdom. The Yugoslav representatives were Foreign Minister Simić and
                        Sava Kosanovic, the Yugoslav Ambassador in the United States.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1046" n="1022" xml:id="pg_1022"/>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> extends a hearty welcome to the
                    representatives of Italy and Yugoslavia. We will hear the views of the
                    Yugoslavia representatives first. (The statement of Foreign Minister Simic is
                        attached.<note n="56" xml:id="d305fn56">Foreign Minister Simić’s statement
                        is printed separately as <gloss target="#t_CFM46NY1">C.F.M. (46)
                            (NY)</gloss> 5, November 6, 1946, <ref target="#pg_1031">p.
                        1031</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I invite the Italian Ambassador to present
                    his statement. (The statement of Ambassador Tarchiani is attached<note n="57" xml:id="d305fn57">Ambassador Tarchiani’s statement is printed separately as
                            <gloss target="#t_CFM46NY1">C.F.M. (46) (NY)</gloss> 8, November 6,
                        1946, <ref target="#pg_1038">p. 1038</ref>.</note>).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Does any member of the Council desire to
                    seek additional information from the Representatives?</p>
                <p>I desire to thank the Representatives of Yugoslavia and Italy for giving us their
                    views, which the Council will carefully study.</p>
                <p>(The Italian and Yugoslav Representatives left the meeting.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: Mr. Chairman, the Soviet Delegation
                    believes that the Council of Foreign Ministers will act correctly if it
                    instructs the Deputies to give a more detailed study to the statements made by
                    Yugoslavia and Italy. I am bound to say that the statements, in particular the
                    statement made by the Italian Delegation and its concluding remarks and threats,
                    make a bad impression upon the Soviet Delegation. Nevertheless, it is necessary
                    to give a more attentive consideration to these statements and to prepare those
                    questions which we shall have to examine finally, and therefore I think we shall
                    act correctly if we instruct our Deputies to this effect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Mr. Chairman, if the Council does
                    not wish to consider the recommendation of the Peace Conference at this time, I
                    have no objection to passing it over until such other time as is deemed wise,
                    but I must say that I do not think the Deputies can make very much headway or
                    progress in the consideration of these two papers.</p>
                <p>For instance, I have in mind this situation. We have agreed on a line. Now, when
                    we refer these two papers to the Deputies, are the Deputies to consider a change
                    in the line that the Ministers have already agreed to?</p>
                <p>We have been over this matter since September 1945, and we have on several
                    occasions referred to the Deputies the consideration of this line. We have sent
                    representatives to the field. We have considered their reports, we came to an
                    agreement, we submitted it to the Peace Conference, and the Peace Conference by
                    a two-thirds vote also reached an agreement.</p>
                <p>Now I am wondering whether, when we refer this question to the Deputies, the four
                    gentlemen who represent us in that capacity would feel at liberty to undo what
                    the Ministers have done and the Peace Conference has done. If they would not
                    feel that way, then we would be wasting time in placing that burden on them.</p>
                <pb facs="1047" n="1023" xml:id="pg_1023"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: The Soviet Delegation does not insist
                    that we instruct our Deputies right away to take up this question but it seems
                    proper to the Soviet Delegation to have an exchange of views in the Council of
                    Foreign Ministers. In connection with the remarks made by Mr. Byrnes, I should
                    like to recall that what he has said is true. But on the other hand, it is also
                    true that the Conference adopted a decision to give further hearing to the
                    Yugoslavs and Italians. I do not think that the Conference adopted this decision
                    because it considered that we should have time to spare and that we could afford
                    to waste that time in hearing the representatives of Yugoslavia and Italy. It is
                    clear, obviously, that the Conference adopted this decision because it
                    considered it useful to give a hearing to the Yugoslavs and Italians, and
                    because of that, we cannot but take into account the remarks made by them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Mr. Chairman, I agree that the
                    action of the Conference carries with it the implication that we should not only
                    hear them but should consider what has been said. It would certainly be my
                    thought that we should do that. I was speaking only of referring the matter to
                    the Deputies. I think the Council should consider what has been said. I am
                    willing to discuss here in the Council any proposal on the part of any member
                    with regard to the line. If any member wishes to make a change, I shall be glad
                    to listen to his views even though I have made a statement as to my views with
                    reference to conference recommendations. My proposal is that in as much as the
                    Yugoslav Delegate submitted in writing suggestions as to the Statute, that the
                    members of the Council should give consideration to those suggestions. We will
                    not be in session tomorrow. We will have an opportunity to study them and we
                    resume the discussion of the suggestions on Friday or some other day that is
                    satisfactory to the Council. We can take them up the same time we take up the
                    conference recommendations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: What is the motion? Mr. Molotov’s
                    suggestion is that we take up the study of these papers which involves the whole
                    question. Your proposal is that we take up the question involving the
                    Statute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: My proposal is that when we take up
                    the consideration of the conference recommendations, we shall at that time
                    consider in the Council, the proposals submitted by the Yugoslav Delegation
                    which have reference to Article 16. If at that time, any member of the Council
                    wants to move to change the formal agreement, I have no objection to it being
                    considered at that time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: The Soviet Delegation has no objection to
                    Mr. Byrnes’ proposal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: The proposal now is that if anyone desires
                    to move an amendment to our previous decision on the line, they will be entitled
                    to <pb facs="1048" n="1024" xml:id="pg_1024"/> do so. And the second point is to
                    take up the question of the Statute when the conference recommendations are
                    before us. Any objections to that?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Couve de Murville</hi>: Does this, Mr. Chairman, mean
                    that at our next meeting, we shall take up the discussion of the conference
                    recommendation regarding the Statute of Trieste?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: As I understand it, it is the entire
                    article.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Mr. Chairman, what I assumed we
                    would do would be to complete the consideration of the recommendations that we
                    have been considering for the last two days. When we have done so, we shall then
                    go back and consider them in the order in which they appear on this table before
                    us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: That is, we continue our agenda today and
                    then we go back to this problem which becomes the first problem we take up. Is
                    that correct?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Mr. Chairman, if we go back and take
                    them in the order set forth on the list it would not be the first matter to be
                    taken up. It is the third matter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Is there any objection to that course?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: No objection.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Is there any reason why we shouldn’t
                    continue?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: It’s a good proposal. We must avail
                    ourselves of the time we have. You expected to hear long speeches from the
                    Yugoslavs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I am disappointed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: I am surprised.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: Happily, affairs took a different
                    turn.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex</hi> 6, <hi rend="smallcaps">Part B</hi>
                    <note n="58" xml:id="d305fn58">Beginning at this point, the Council of Foreign
                        Ministers resumed its consideration of the unagreed articles set forth in
                        the Record of Recommendations by the Peace Conference on the Draft Peace
                        Treaty with Italy, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_889">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 889</ref>–<ref target="frus1946v04#pg_956">956</ref>. Article 6, Part B, is printed
                            <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_914">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 914</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Annex 3 is the next item.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: How about Annex 1? Is there anything on
                    that? The first item then is Annex 3.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Mr. Chairman, may I suggest that
                    there is no recommendation on 3. Annex 6 B is the next item.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: That will have to come up later then. As I
                    understand annex 3, it was not considered by the Conference and was to be
                    considered by the Council of Foreign Ministers, so that will come up after we
                    have completed the recommendations. The next one is Annex 6. This proposal was a
                    UK proposal and was adopted by the Conference by 15 votes to 6. Shall we accept
                    the recommendation of the Conference?</p>
                <pb facs="1049" n="1025" xml:id="pg_1025"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: Give me time to read this. I brought too
                    many papers with me. The proposal of the Soviet Delegation is to add in
                    paragraph 1, Part B, Annex 6, the words, “which will be granted to the citizens
                    of Italy.” This amendment implies that the United Nations nationals will enjoy
                    the same rights as the citizens of Italy on terms of equality and accordingly,
                    the Soviet Delegation suggests that paragraph 2 be excluded.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: What is the purpose of the amendment?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: The purpose of the amendment is not to
                    create any privileged position for foreigners in Italy, and it will not be a
                    good thing if foreigners in Italy enjoy the same rights as the citizens of
                    Italy. This is the purpose of the Soviet amendment. I should like to add that.
                    We know, prior to the Conference, the Soviet Delegation objected to the
                    insertion of this paragraph, considering this paragraph a superfluous one, since
                    this question is sufficiently covered by other articles of the Treaty, in
                    particular, by Article 68.<note n="59" xml:id="d305fn59">Article 68 of the Draft
                        Peace Treaty with Italy, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_28">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 28</ref>.</note> But by way of
                    concession, the Soviet Delegation is ready to accept this Part B of Annex 6
                    subject to the amendment proposed by it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: As I understand this, I don’t think Mr.
                    Molotov’s amendment covers our point. Perhaps I might try and explain it. When
                    war was declared by Italy, the business of United Nations nationals was
                    transferred to Italian control and there it has been ever since. The Italians
                    should restore this as it was. In the event they took everything in the
                    financing of the war thereby reducing the guarantees laid down by the Italian
                    law, the companies who were deprived of their business should be allowed to
                    build up again before they have to obey the Italian law. And it’s a very
                    important thing if when a country goes to war and takes the property of United
                    Nations nationals and then at the end of the war United Nations nationals are
                    not given a special position, we make a present of the property. It makes war
                    rather profitable. And I do think it is a rather important proposal. It would be
                    impossible for the United Kingdom to accept such an addition. If you added the
                    words Mr. Molotov suggests, it would really nullify the effect of paragraph (1)
                    altogether because the idea of paragraph (1) is they are nationals and if they
                    so desire they can resume their former portfolios, that is they can take up
                    their insurance where it left off. It doesn’t mean the Italians are compelled to
                    do it. Therefore, I would ask the Soviet Government to agree to this Article as
                    it stands. I think it is reasonable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: The Soviet Delegation sees no reason for
                    the apprehensions expressed by Mr. Bevin. There is Article 68, paragraphs 1, 2,
                    and 3 of which provide for sufficient guarantees as regards United <pb facs="1050" n="1026" xml:id="pg_1026"/> Nations property in Italy and I
                    wonder if the British Delegation intends by paragraph 6 to extend these rights
                    as against those provided for in Article 68. If this is not the purpose of the
                    British Delegation, if the British Delegation does not wish to extend the rights
                    as regards foreign property in Italian territory as compared to those provided
                    for in Article 68, then Article 68 fully takes care of what the British
                    Delegation wishes to take care of, but if this a matter of extending these
                    rights then the Soviet Delegation sees no reason to do so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I am advised that Article 68 does not cover
                    it. We don’t need to extend it, but it does not cover it. This is insurance
                    business in which the British companies and American companies and other
                    companies in the world have insured a person and that insurance business was
                    taken away when England declared war and the purpose of this is to allow the
                    facilities for the citizens of Italy who had insurance with these companies to
                    return and take up their business where they left off. It is said that Article
                    68 does not cover it. If I thought Article 68 covered this type of property, I
                    shouldn’t be arguing it, but I am advised it doesn’t.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: If Mr. Molotov thinks it is covered
                    by 68 and you, Mr. Bevin, have doubt about it being covered, can’t you agree
                    upon stating language in 68 that will remove the doubt?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I am willing for the deputies to do
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: I think that it is necessary to avoid
                    misunderstanding in this matter. It is my understanding that the insurance
                    companies will be satisfied within the limits of Article 68. They should be
                    satisfied. If the British Delegation wishes to go beyond what is provided for in
                    Article 68, the Soviet Delegation sees no reason to extend the limits of this
                    Article and, consequently, it is not a question of amending this Article but a
                    question of satisfying the insurance companies within the limits of Article 68.
                    The Soviet Delegation sees no reason to place these insurance companies in a
                    privileged position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Well, the whole question is whether—I don’t
                    want the insurance companies placed in a privileged position against other
                    property owners, but they have had their business confiscated when the Fascist
                    Government entered the war, and I think they are entitled to be in the position
                    they were in when that happened. I am told that Article 68 doesn’t cover this
                    special type of business, therefore, I would like to press that either provision
                    be made in Article 68—and if Mr. Molotov says that the insurance companies can
                    be satisfied under Article 68, I’d like to look at that again to see whether
                    that is a fact, whether it covers this point, because I am told it doesn’t and I
                    am quite willing for it to be looked at by the Deputies to see whether it does
                    cover it. I don’t think there is any dispute in principle.</p>
                <pb facs="1051" n="1027" xml:id="pg_1027"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Mr. Chairman, I suggest we ought to
                    see if we can reach agreement, and the language can be straightened out. In
                    Article 68, it is said the Italian Government undertakes that all property,
                    rights and interests passing under this Article shall be restored free of
                    encumbrance. Now, if it is the desire of the Council to make certain that there
                    is no discrimination against this particular kind of property, there should be
                    no objection to adding after the words “property, rights and interests” the
                    words “including insurance contracts or insurance portfolios.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: I’d like to ask you to repeat your
                    suggestion.</p>
                <p>(Translator repeated in Russian.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: They advise me that that is the
                    technical term for insurance “portfolio”—I accept that statement. The effect of
                    that would be to put it on the same basis as other property. The British
                    Delegation expressed doubt that that would be construed as including this kind
                    of property, therefore, you’d remove the doubt.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Couve de Murville</hi>: I should like to observe, Sir,
                    that the amendment suggested by Mr. Byrnes covers point 1 of the United Kingdom
                    proposal but not point 2 which is a special provision on insurance to facilitate
                    the reconstruction of their insurance business.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: This question can be referred for further
                    study to the Deputies without anticipating amendment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: You mean without submitting amendments
                    here?</p>
                <p>(Mr. Molotov nodded his head in agreement.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I have no objection to it going for further
                    study.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: If we can agree on the principle the
                    Deputies’ task would be much easier.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Sometimes the Deputies agree where we don’t
                    seem able to.</p>
                <p>Then that question will go to the Deputies.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex</hi> 7, <hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> 3<note n="60" xml:id="d305fn60">Annex 7, Part 3, of the Draft Peace Treaty with Italy,
                        which was adopted by the Paris Peace Conference without modification; for
                        text, see <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_57">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>,
                            p. 57</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The next one is Annex 7, part 3. This was adopted by 12 votes to 3. 12 votes to
                    6, 3 abstentions, I’m sorry.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: If all the Delegations present here
                    insist on this point, the Soviet Delegation will have no objection to its
                    acceptance.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: No objections?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: No objection.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Couve de Murville</hi>: No objection.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Thank you very much.</p>
                <pb facs="1052" n="1028" xml:id="pg_1028"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex</hi> 7, <hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> 5<note n="61" xml:id="d305fn61">The reference here is to the following proposal by the
                        United States Delegation: “Having regard to the legal system of the United
                        States of America, the provisions of Annex 7 will not apply as between the
                        United States and Italy.” In the Draft Treaty submitted by the Drafting
                        Committee to the Deputies on October 25, the proposal was quoted as Annex
                        VII, Part 5.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: The next one is part 5, a special provision
                    of the United States, and the proposal was adopted 15 to 4 with 2
                    abstentions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Well, if the negotiable instrument
                    clause is accepted as it has been, then the United States asks for the inclusion
                    of this provision because the negotiable instrument proposal has provisions
                    which cannot be agreed to or carried into effect by the Federal Government under
                    our system of government. It is controlled by state laws and that is why we
                    asked for the exception. We had to make a request of that kind in the Versailles
                    Treaty and the attorneys who are more familiar with the subject than I am say
                    the same thing will have to be done here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: I have a question to ask. Can such an
                    agreement to this point serve as a precedent for any other Delegation to make a
                    similar reservation?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Do you mean, Mr. Molotov, on any other
                    subject or on this subject? I was just thinking from memory and I have an idea
                    that Brazil was in a similar position.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: On any other question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Mr. Chairman, what would happen if
                    the Treaty was submitted to our Senate for ratification would be that the Senate
                    would not ratify it without a reservation which would make it plain it was not
                    exceeding the powers of the Federal Government. Because a matter of this kind is
                    affected by the laws of the several States. It is far better to put it here than
                    to have reservations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I think Mr. Molotov’s point, if I
                    understood him aright, was, would there be any reservations on any other part
                    besides this one?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Not so far as the United States is
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I don’t think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: There is none here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Couve de Murville</hi>: We have no reservations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: We haven’t got a written constitution so we
                    don’t need to make reservations. It is very useful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: I think so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: Probably it is useful.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: It has been going on a long time. Do we
                    accept this United States proposal?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: I have one more question. In the language
                    as it stands now it applies not only to negotiable instruments but also to the
                    provisions of the Annex. Is that the meaning of the language?</p>
                <pb facs="1053" n="1029" xml:id="pg_1029"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: There is nothing else left in the
                    Annex.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: The negotiable instrument is
                    included, and I call it to your attention.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: But still the language as proposed by the
                    American Delegation did not extend to a certain single point but to the
                    whole.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: That is true. It was meant to apply
                    to these several proposals that were offered by the United Kingdom Delegation.
                    Now the only one which has been adopted is negotiable instruments. But if
                    hereafter we should include any one or two of the other proposals which have
                    been offered by the British Delegation, then we would have to ask that this
                    apply to them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: In connection with the observation made
                    by the Soviet Delegation, it is anxious to give further study to this
                    question.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex</hi> 8<note n="62" xml:id="d305fn62">The United
                        States proposal supported by the Soviet Union for Annex 8, Part B, which was
                        adopted by the Peace Conference, is included in the Draft Peace Treaty with
                        Italy, <ref target="frus1946v04#pg_58">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p.
                            58</ref>, as are the French and United Kingdom proposals thereto.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Annex 8. This is on judgments. The proposal
                    was adopted by the Conference with 15 votes and 3 abstentions, England and
                    France voting against. The French proposal was not voted on by the Conference.
                    Has the French Delegation any observations?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Couve de Murville</hi>: Mr. Chairman, I confess that the
                    French Delegation is not very happy about the text voted by the Conference, but
                    considering the great majority of votes cast by member States we feel that we
                    should adhere to it, following the example set by you yesterday.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I also accept the resolution which was
                    proposed by the United States, supported by the Union of the Soviet Republics,
                    and therefore I withdraw any opposition to the adoption of the majority
                    decision.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: The Soviet-American bloc was
                    supported by the Peace Conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: It is not bad.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: That was agreed. Now I have got to the end
                    of the paper. Do you desire me to go back to the beginning again or adjourn?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: I suggest we adjourn.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Is that agreed; Now what time is the next
                    meeting?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Friday.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Friday at 3:30. There are some small points
                    referred to the Deputies. Shall they meet while we are not meeting? Perhaps they
                    could meet Friday morning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>: Not everything is ready.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Couve de Murville</hi>: Shall we go back to the Italian
                    Treaty or start with the preliminary examination of other things?</p>
                <pb facs="1054" n="1030" xml:id="pg_1030"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I understood we are to go back on Friday,
                    when we meet, to the Italian Treaty on the points outstanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I thought that was our decision
                    earlier.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary Byrnes</hi>: That is right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: We will adjourn until 3:30 on Friday.</p>
                <p>(The meeting adjourned at 1:45 p.m.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
