<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Representative in Bulgaria ( (Barnes) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-11-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-11-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="356"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d356">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">874.00/11–2546: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Representative in Bulgaria</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Barnes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sofia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-25">November 25,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>926. Resolution of Great National Assembly mentioned my telegram 923<note n="20"
                        xml:id="d356fn20">Not printed.</note> doubtless already communicated to
                    Council of Foreign Ministers by Bulgarian representative Washington. Text is as
                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>[“]Great National Assembly expresses unanimous views and aspirations of
                            whole Bulgarian people that Council of Foreign Ministers take into
                            consideration just demands of Bulgarian people and prepare just
                            honorable peace treaty with Bulgaria.</p>
                        <p>Bulgarian people have every reason to expect that present Bulgarian
                            frontiers will be preserved and that western Thrace which was unjustly
                            taken away will be returned to her and that she will thus obtain out to
                            White [<hi rend="italic">Black</hi>] Sea which is natural and vitally
                            necessary for country. People surprised that new cruel and unbearable
                            injustice being prepared by claim put forth to Bulgarian lands. These
                            claims of Greek Government are not justified; they threaten peace and
                            tranquility of Balkans. Great National Assembly declares that Bulgarian
                            people will never resign themselves to such injustice and believe firmly
                            that demands of Greek chauvinists will be rejected.</p>
                        <p>At same time Great National Assembly hopes that Council of Foreign
                            Ministers will take into consideration Bulgarian demands concerning
                            other questions of peace treaty. Nothing could justify refusal to
                            recognize Bulgarian cobelligerent as Bulgaria did not take part in war
                            on side of Germany but fought during eight months against German troops
                            and gave precious victims for liberation of Balkans and final defeat of
                            German Army. Attempt to impose enormous reparations on Bulgaria does not
                            take into consideration amount of real damages suffered by Bulgaria nor
                            merits of Bulgarian people before UN and financial possibilities of
                            plundered and ruined Bulgaria. Separations claims most unjust and must
                            be reduced to minimum sum.</p>
                        <pb facs="1309" n="1285" xml:id="pg_1285"/>
                        <p>Efforts and victims of Bulgarian people which are recognized by
                            international public opinion support hope of Bulgarian people to obtain
                            just and honorable treaty of peace. Bulgarian people await decision of
                            four Ministers with confidence and tranquillity.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Barnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
