<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-12-09T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-12-09T16:00:00-05:00" n="401" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d401">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> Files:
                        Lot M–88: Box 2080: <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Minutes</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Minutes, Council of Foreign
                            Ministers, Third Session, Nineteenth Meeting, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, New
                            York, December 9, 1946, 4 p.m.</hi><note n="58" xml:id="d401fn58">For a
                            list of persons present at this meeting, see the Record of Decisions,
                                <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note></head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-12-09T16:00:00-05:00">December 9, 1946, 4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <lb/>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_USDELCFM46NY1">USDEL(CFM) (46)
                                (NY)</gloss> 19th meeting</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: The Soviet Delegation proposed on
                            Saturday<note n="59" xml:id="d401fn59">December 7.</note> to hold the
                        next session of the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> in Moscow. I
                        would be happy to obtain agreement on this proposal.</p>
                    <pb facs="1506" n="1482" xml:id="pg_1482"/>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: The United States Delegation accepts
                        with pleasure Mr. Molotov’s invitation. In this connection I would like to
                        ask whether accommodations will be made available for the press since we
                        hope that the press may submit reports on the work of the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> as it did in Paris and here. I don’t
                        propose that we follow the same procedure as was followed at the Paris
                        Conference but I hope that the same liberal procedure we have observed will
                        be continued.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: The Soviet Government will be happy to
                        see the Ministers in Moscow and everything will be done in spite of the
                        housing difficulties to accommodate the correspondents and to create the
                        most favorable conditions for their work. They will be able to report from
                        Moscow on the proceedings of the Conference as they reported in Paris and
                        New York.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: That is satisfactory.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I agree to Mr. Molotov’s proposal.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Couve de Murville</hi>: I also accept.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: Are there any suggestions as to the
                        time of the Conference?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: I suggest either March 3 or March
                        10.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I prefer March 10.</p>
                    <p>The Ministers agreed to meet in Moscow on March 10.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Couve de Murville</hi>: The French Delegation has
                        submitted a draft agenda (<gloss target="#t_CFM46NY1">CFM(46)
                            (NY)</gloss>63).<note n="60" xml:id="d401fn60"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, p. 1478.</note> It includes the U.S. and Soviet
                            proposals.<note n="61" xml:id="d401fn61">The reference here is to <gloss target="#t_CFM46NY1">CFM(46) (NY)</gloss>57, December 6, 1946, and
                                <gloss target="#t_CFM46NY1">CFM(46) (NY)</gloss>60, December 7,
                            1946, <ref target="#pg_1464">pp. 1464</ref> and <ref target="#pg_1476">1476</ref>.</note> The only difference is in presentation. The
                        first item, i.e., frontiers, is not like the U.S. proposal. The Saar is not
                        mentioned although we wish to settle this question. The French Delegation
                        raised the question of the Saar in April and June and would normally ask
                        that this question be taken up again. But since we have all agreed that no
                        matters of substance be taken up at the present time the French Delegation
                        agrees that this matter be discussed at the next meeting. In this connection
                        I would like to inform my colleagues that the French Government might find
                        it necessary to take certain measures in the Saar of an administrative and
                        conservatory character. The food situation in the Saar has forced us to send
                        a considerable amount of food products, especially cereal, to the area.
                        French public opinion would not understand it if these products were
                        transferred to other areas of Germany. For this reason the French Government
                        may have to institute controls. Furthermore, monetary controls may have to
                        be placed in force. There is an inflow of German marks into the Saar which
                        amounted to 13 billion francs last month. The French Government might have
                        to take measures to control these matters. However, none of these economic
                        or financial measures will prejudice future <pb facs="1507" n="1483" xml:id="pg_1483"/> decisions of the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> on frontiers or reparations. They will not affect
                        decisions regarding coal from the Saar. I merely wish to inform you of the
                        preoccupation of the French Government in this respect and warn you of the
                        preservative measures it may have to take.</p>
                    <p>The French Government also wishes to place on the agenda the Ruhr and
                        Rhineland questions. French draft proposals in this connection have been
                        previously submitted. This matter has been brought to the attention of the
                            <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> over a year ago but no reply has
                        been received to the French proposals. Our proposals have a political and
                        territorial implication. The last question I wish to raise is of a drafting
                        character. The U.S. and Soviet draft agendas mention the future German
                        Government. We deem it more advisable to speak of the political organization
                        of Germany since this terminology is of a wider character and covers the
                        Potsdam Decision to decentralize Germany. That is the reason why we speak of
                        the political German organization rather than the future German
                        Government.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: Before we try to agree about the agenda
                        for the March meeting I suggest that we endeavor to agree on what we will
                        discuss and decide here. What will be done in Moscow will greatly depend
                        upon the determination of this question. I again urge that the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> agree to my proposal concerning the
                        appointment of the Special Deputies to consider the German question and to
                        report to the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> two weeks prior to its
                        next meeting. My second proposal was to the effect that the Deputies be
                        instructed to hear the views of the directly interested governments before
                        we make any decisions. The importance of that proposal is demonstrated by
                        the French paper which lists the German frontiers as the first problem for
                        discussion in March. It is perfectly clear what will happen when this
                        procedure is made known. All the interested countries will say that it will
                        be decided in Moscow to establish the German frontiers without giving those
                        countries a chance to express their opinions. There can be only one result.
                        Every representative will ask to be heard on the frontier question before
                        the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> takes a decision and he will be
                        told that there has been no agreement to discuss this matter prior to the
                        March meeting. He will be told that in March deputies will be appointed to
                        hear the views of the interested governments. The U.S. Government will
                        inform any interested government that it will reach no decision on the
                        German frontiers until that government has been heard.</p>
                    <p>I have submitted one more question for decision here—what information should
                        we request the Control Council in Germany to furnish us for our next
                        meeting. I agree to add the two items contained in the Soviet memorandum.
                        The next question I would like to decide here concerns the appointment of
                        special deputies for the drafting of the Austrian Treaty. Should we instruct
                        them to examine the U.S. and <pb facs="1508" n="1484" xml:id="pg_1484"/>
                        U.K. draft proposals,<note n="62" xml:id="d401fn62">The reference here is to
                            document <gloss target="#t_CFM461">CFM(46)</gloss>119, June 20, 1946,
                            containing United States proposals for a Draft Treaty with Austria, and
                                <gloss target="#t_CFM461">CFM(46)</gloss>151, June 26, 1946, the
                            Draft Heads of a Treaty with Austria, proposed by the United Kingdom.
                            Neither of these documents is printed.</note> and any other proposals
                        that might be submitted, and to report to us in March, or should we wait
                        until March and ask them to report back to us in July or November? I know it
                        has been urged that we should first inform the deputies what we expected
                        them to do. I disagree. I believe that the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> should obtain the information first and then should
                        inform the Deputies what to do.</p>
                    <p>I wish to revert to the Soviet proposal which requests reports from the
                        Control Council on the implementation of the decisions of the Berlin
                        Conference, on the liquidation of Prussia, on the Committee of Coal Experts
                        and on its activities in the past. Paragraphs 1, 5 and 6 list the subjects
                        the Soviet Delegation wishes the Control Council to report on. This leaves
                        points 2, 3 and 4 open for the Moscow Conference. Points 3 and 4 refer to
                        the preparation of peace treaties with Germany and Austria. That work can
                        only be done after the appointment of deputies. Thus only point 2 regarding
                        the central German administration and the question of the German Government
                        is left for the Moscow Conference. I wish to take decisions now so that when
                        we meet in Moscow we can really start our work and make actual decisions and
                        not restrict ourselves to the appointment of deputies.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I support the U.S. proposal for this
                        preliminary inquiry. I will not refer to the Saar now but may return to it
                        later. I am trying to imagine what we could do in Moscow if the preliminary
                        work suggested by Mr. Byrnes were not done. All I can see is a discussion of
                        the preliminary reports of the Control Council and then the consideration of
                        such questions as reparations. I am particularly anxious to give the
                        interested governments opportunity to express their views. There has been a
                        good deal of resentment in the past in this connection and much time was
                        lost because we did not take this step. It is extremely desirable that we
                        know the whole picture. We are all conversant with what happened in the past
                        and the different interpretations that have been placed on the Potsdam
                        Agreement. If we are going to Moscow merely to discuss the past, it would be
                        simpler for the Control Council to circulate to us written reports for our
                        consideration. There would be no need to convene to discuss these reports.
                        The forward looking method, which should be clear to us, would be to obtain
                        the whole picture before we meet. The deputies could obtain this picture and
                        their report, together with the reports from the Control Council on the
                        factual situation, would be extremely helpful to us. The deputies could not
                        make any decisions—that would be up to the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> But they could study their information and could submit
                        to us a better picture of the Germany we must deal with. This would include
                        a picture of the frontiers. <pb facs="1509" n="1485" xml:id="pg_1485"/> That
                        is why I suggest that the deputies and the Control Council be called upon to
                        investigate the German situation and to report to us. This preparatory work
                        has never been done before. We have the experience of the past and we should
                        be guided by it. The entire world is waiting for all decisions on how we
                        will prevent Germany from undertaking acts of aggression in the future. This
                        preparatory work will give confidence to the world that we are dealing with
                        Germany in the right manner.</p>
                    <p>With respect to Austria I don’t understand why we cannot proceed at once. We
                        have prepared five treaties and they would be good guides for the Austrian
                        Treaty. Two drafts on Austria have been submitted and others can be tabled.
                        I cannot see why the job cannot be completed by the deputies with the
                        exception of a few unsettled points which we can dispose of in Moscow. We
                        all wish to withdraw our troops from Europe. We could do so upon the
                        completion of the Austrian Treaty and then concentrate on Germany. In such a
                        circumstance the German picture would be much clearer.</p>
                    <p>It seems to me that the issue is a narrow one—namely, shall we decide to
                        start our work now or wait until after March. Shall our deputies consider
                        the views of the interested countries and the reports of the Control Council
                        at the present time or after March. If we can agree on this point, I would
                        then like to add a few items to the agenda but I believe that we should
                        obtain agreement on the appointment of the deputies.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: The Soviet Delegation is ready to give
                        more detailed study to the appointment of the deputies and will make known
                        its decision on this question at the next meeting of the Council. However,
                        we must ascertain when and where the deputies will meet and also the
                        questions they will discuss. I fear that if we appoint deputies at the
                        present time they may have to repeat much of their work after we have
                        exchanged views in the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> I fear if they
                        start their work, not before final <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss>
                        decisions but before an exchange of views in the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss>, they will have to repeat much of their work. But in
                        view of the fact that there are insistent requests for the appointment of
                        the deputies the Soviet Delegation is prepared to consider carefully this
                        question.</p>
                    <p>It has been said that the deputies should hear interested states on the
                        frontiers before the next meeting of the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> I am apprehensive that if we undertake to do this there
                        may be press reports that the deputies are considering territorial claims.
                        It will be reported that one country desires a section of Germany and
                        another country desires another section. There will be agitation and a
                        whetting up of appetites. This will produce disquiet in Germany. We shall
                        thus acervate [<hi rend="italic">acerbate?</hi>] the situation in Germany.
                        We will not be achieving <pb facs="1510" n="1486" xml:id="pg_1486"/> the
                        results we desire. If the frontier question is discussed by the deputies,
                        there will be disquiet in Germany and not only in Germany itself. I am also
                        disturbed to note that the U.S. and French agendas commence with the German
                        frontiers. I consider that it would be better not to separate this question
                        but to include it in the preparation of the peace treaty with Germany. It is
                        not advisable to concentrate interest on this question and to excite
                        comment. I feel that it would be difficult to consider this question apart
                        from the peace treaty as a whole. On the other hand, the Soviet Delegation
                        attaches great importance to the reports of the Control Council on
                        demilitarization, democratization, etc. Furthermore, the present situation
                        in Germany including the economic issues and reparations are most important
                        questions. The Control Council report should be one of the first questions
                        on our agenda. After considering these reports we will have a clearer
                        picture of Germany and we will be able to see more clearly how we can
                        prevent Germany from becoming again an aggressive state, a threat to Europe
                        and to the whole world. The question of German administration is also very
                        important. I do not think that it is clearly formulated in the U.S. draft
                        which speaks of a central German administration. It is even vaguer in the
                        French draft. I am not familiar with the British attitude in this
                        connection. However, this question will arise when we discuss Germany.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion I wish to state that if we increase the number of items on our
                        agenda up to 10 we shall be undertaking too great a task. The items should
                        be reduced as much as possible.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: I am glad to learn that the Soviet
                        Delegation will consider the question of appointing deputies. I hope that
                        Mr. Molotov will bear in mind that although the interested governments will
                        make a great deal of noise when it is known that the deputies are to hear
                        their views there can be no doubt that this noise will be greater in March.
                        Our deputies can ascertain the facts on which we will base our conclusions
                        or we can make our conclusions and then ask the deputies to ascertain the
                        facts to support our conclusions. The fact is that the interested
                        governments will know about our exchange of views and our directives to the
                        deputies. If the deputies do not find the right facts, there will be more
                        noise. I hope that Mr. Molotov will agree to permit the deputies to
                        ascertain the facts on which we will base our conclusions.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Mr. Molotov mentioned the U.K. position
                        on the German Government. The subject of the implementation of the Potsdam
                        Decisions has often been discussed at the Control Council. Our policy has
                        always been to support the Potsdam Decisions. We are in favor of a federal
                        Germany with certain services at the center such as foreign policy. Our main
                        worry is how to make ourselves secure. We have no <pb facs="1511" n="1487" xml:id="pg_1487"/> other motive. We want to build up a democratic
                        Germany which will give us security. We have no ideological motive. The
                        objective of the British people is to avoid war in the future. I will go
                        along with my colleagues and study the questions as to how to get security,
                        how to teach Germany the lessons of democracy and how not to have a cesspool
                        of cheap labor in the East. These questions need careful study but I am sure
                        we shall be successful if we approach them in the proper spirit. I see that
                        reparation is on the Soviet agenda. I am willing to discuss reparation but I
                        must warn you that we cannot find one more dollar to pour into Germany.
                        Germany must find its own means of paying reparations. With respect to the
                        reports of the Control Council I want to know how much has been taken out of
                        Germany. I want to know how much everybody has received. I want a factual
                        report. I also want to know how many German prisoners of war and other
                        Germans are abroad and how many Germans Germany will have to absorb. I think
                        we ought to know what is the value of German assets in the ceded
                        territories. A great part of Germany has been transferred to Polish
                        administration. We must have a clear picture of the financial situation. We
                        must know the whole value of the assets taken out of Germany. I would like
                        all these questions to be investigated so that in March we will have all the
                        facts. We should have all the territorial, economic, political and financial
                        facts.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion I would like to know whether the agreement to appoint deputies
                        includes the appointment of deputies to study the Austrian question.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: I would consider this.</p>
                    <p>May we discuss the agenda? I propose that the first question on the agenda be
                        the reports of the Control Council.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: I urge that first of all we agree on
                        what we shall ask the Control Council to report. I suggest that our request
                        include the U.S. items, the two Soviet items and any items the U.K. or the
                        French Delegations might like to add.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: I don’t object to the report covering
                        both items 5 and 6 of the Soviet agenda. The Soviet Delegation has suggested
                        that the report should deal with the decisions of the Berlin Conference
                        regarding demilitarization, democratization, etc. We believe that the report
                        should explain what has and has not been done to fulfill the decisions of
                        the Berlin Conference. I thought this had been agreed to. The second item
                        might be item 3 of the U.S. draft. It would be logical to arrange our
                        requests in this order. The first part would deal with the past and the
                        second part with the future.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: I suggested on Saturday that we add to
                        paragraph III of the U.S. proposal paragraph I of the Soviet proposal. Then
                            <pb facs="1512" n="1488" xml:id="pg_1488"/> subsection D of the U.S.
                        proposal would be paragraph V of the Soviet proposal. I believe that in
                        calling on the Control Council for a report we should include every subject
                        we are interested in. In addition to paragraphs I and V of the Soviet
                        proposal there will also be paragraph VI regarding coal.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: I do not object to this order but I
                        think it would be preferable to start with the past, that is the report as
                        mentioned in paragraph I of the Soviet proposal. We might then include A and
                        B of paragraph III of the U.S. proposal and then conclude with paragraphs V
                        and VI of the Soviet proposal. I think it would be better to switch
                        paragraphs A and B of the U.S. proposal because it would be more correct
                        chronologically to discuss the central agency first and then the composition
                        of the provisional government.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: I have no objection to this
                        re-arrangement. Paragraph III of the U.S. proposal merely calls on the
                        Control Council to prepare these reports and to be ready to file them two
                        weeks before we meet. This paragraph does not govern the order in which we
                        will discuss these subjects in March. If we can agree on the subjects we
                        desire to discuss, if we can appoint our deputies, we can name
                        representatives now to arrange the order of the agenda. The important thing
                        is to appoint our deputies and to ask the Control Council for the
                        information.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Couve de Murville</hi>: I must confess that I am
                        lost. Before clearing up the order of the agenda there are certain matters
                        of substance which we should clarify. We are asking for a report on the past
                        and present. We are not asking for decisions. But if we ask the Control
                        Council for a report on the provisional government of Germany this implies
                        that a decision has been taken to create such a government. This is an
                        entirely new question. We propose a report on the economic unity of Germany
                        and on the central agencies together with the political organization of
                        Germany under quadripartite control. We need information on these items.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: Does paragraph 3 of Section III of the
                        U.S. proposal deal with the past?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: Paragraph B deals with the
                        establishment of central agencies and other problems connected with the
                        economic and political future of Germany under quadripartite government. It
                        deals with those agencies which would have to be created in the future while
                        the Allied forces are in occupation of Germany. I am inclined to agree with
                        Mr. Couve de Murville and believe it would be preferable to say “the
                        provisional organization of Germany under quadripartite government” rather
                        than “the political future of Germany”. We know that we shall have to have a
                        political organization in Germany <pb facs="1513" n="1489" xml:id="pg_1489"/> for some time to come but how shall we obtain the best organization. Our
                        representatives there on the spot are qualified and they are the best men to
                        make recommendations for improving the political organization. They can
                        inform us of the best means of organizing Germany in the future.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Couve de Murville</hi>: Would Mr. Byrnes’ statement
                        mean that in paragraph A of Section III of the U.S. proposal the words “a
                        provisional German Government” would be replaced by “a provisional political
                        organization of Germany under quadripartite government”.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: There is some uncertainty in our
                        discussion. We must formulate an agenda that would not prejudice the
                        solution of these questions. If we accept the French language, we exclude
                        the possibility of discussing the question of a central German
                        administration.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Couve de Murville</hi>: We exclude this possibility
                        only in connection with the report from the Control Council. Does Mr.
                        Molotov believe that this formula would preclude the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> from discussing this matter?</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: It is difficult to reply. I am
                        primarily interested in what the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> will
                        discuss. We cannot bind the <gloss target="#t_CFM1">C.F.M.</gloss> by
                        decisions which might exclude the possibility of discussing a central German
                        administration. It is not important whether these discussions are based on a
                        report from the Control Council or not. I doubt that the Control Council can
                        report on this subject. If it does, we should not stop them from expressing
                        their views—that is single or several views.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: I agree.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I don’t know what is being proposed. I
                        would like to see a clean draft.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: I merely agreed with the statements
                        made. No proposals have thus far been put forward for acceptance. I believe
                        that we should request our deputies to reconcile our drafts. There are too
                        many papers and we cannot proceed very far. I agreed to what I thought was
                        the proposal, paragraph III, that is to arrange it chronologically. I
                        thought that there was no opposition but Mr. Bevin says he does not
                        understand the proposal. I think it would be best to ask that
                        representatives of each delegation endeavor to come to agreement on this
                        point.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: Do we surrender to the deputies?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: Yes.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: We can include in the proposal those
                        subjects we so desire.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: Our representatives would undertake to
                        go ahead on the other proposals.</p>
                    <pb facs="1514" n="1490" xml:id="pg_1490"/>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: Let’s decide one question. Shall we
                        come to agreement on the agenda tonight or shall we refer it to our
                        deputies.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: It would be better to refer the matter
                        to the deputies. We would have time to give them instructions tonight.</p>
                    <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi>: Could we meet tomorrow morning? There
                        is a session of the General Assembly at 4 o’clock tomorrow afternoon.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: What will we discuss? As I understand it
                        the deputies’ report is not ready.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Byrnes</hi>: We could meet in the morning if there
                        was any hope that we could make progress on the treaties. There is still the
                        financial question concerning funds for the Free Territory. There is a
                        report on this question. There is also an economic report which could be
                        discussed tomorrow morning.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bevin</hi>: I suggest that the deputies meet at 10
                        o’clock and we meet at 11:30. They could clear up this matter before lunch.
                        Could we meet twice on Wednesday to clear up all the outstanding points?</p>
                    <p>The Ministers agreed to meet at 11:00 a.m. on December 10.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>