<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-24T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-24T19:00:00-05:00" n="63" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/4–1946: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>, at Paris</hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-24T19:00:00-05:00">April 24, 1946—7
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1869. <gloss target="#t_Secdel1">Secdel</gloss>. In a note dated April
                            18<note n="20" xml:id="d63fn20">Not printed.</note>
                        <gloss target="#t_Yugos1">Yugos</gloss> Chargé, on instructions, requests
                        that “Govt of US invite Govt of Albania to Conference <pb facs="0105" n="87" xml:id="pg_87"/> scheduled to begin in Paris on May 1.” Note continues
                        along lines apparently similar to communication summarized <gloss target="#t_Delsec1">Delsec</gloss> 417 April 19 from London.<note n="21" xml:id="d63fn21">Not printed.</note></p>
                    <p>We are confining reply<note n="22" xml:id="d63fn22">The reply, not printed,
                            was dated April 25.</note> to simple acknowledgment and statement, that
                        matter being brought your attention for such consideration as may be
                        appropriate in circumstances. It occurs to us that this approach might serve
                        as opportunity to make additionally clear our attitude in regard to recent
                        developments in Albania particularly as they affect our relations that
                        country. Accordingly, it is suggested that in any <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> discussion this question you might wish to take occasion to
                        point out that while US has consistently made known its cognizance of
                        efforts of Albanian people to resist Fascist aggression and consequently
                        feels that Albanian people are entitled to be represented at peace
                        conference, US Govt does not consider itself in position to take initiative
                        in matter in view recent attitude of present Albanian regime toward US
                        representation in Albania and its failure to assume normal obligations
                        requisite to recognition by US.<note n="23" xml:id="d63fn23">For
                            documentation regarding the efforts of the United States to reach a
                            satisfactory basis for the reestablishment of diplomatic relations with
                            Albania, see <ref target="frus1946v06#pg_1">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff.</note></p>
                    <p>Sent <gloss target="#t_Secdel1">Secdel</gloss>, Paris; repeated Tirana and
                        Belgrade.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
            </body></text></TEI>