<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-10-30T20:43:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-10-30T20:43:00-05:00" n="101" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d101">
                        <head>101. Telegram 258216 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Morocco<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d101fn1"><p><seg type="summary">Summary: The Embassy was instructed to
                                        deliver a message from <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> to King Hassan concerning the
                                        proposed Green March into the Sahara. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> asked for the
                                        King’s views on Waldheim’s proposal for settlement of the
                                        Spanish Sahara issue and emphasized that the proposed march
                                        would increase tensions in the region.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: Ford Library, National Security
                                        Adviser, Presidential Country Files for Africa, Box 4,
                                        Morocco, State Department Telegrams, From SecState—<gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Secret; Immediate;
                                            <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by
                                            <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>;
                                        cleared by Borg; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> by
                                        telecon—Adams.</seg></p></note></head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-10-31T01:43:00+00:00">October 31, 1975,
                            0143Z</date>.</dateline>
                        <p>258216. Subject: Message for King Hassan—Spanish Sahara. For the Chargé
                            from the Secretary.</p>
                        <p>1. Please convey following message from me for King Hassan.</p>
                        <p>2. Begin text:</p>
                        <p>Your Majesty:</p>
                        <p>I very much appreciate your courtesy in receiving Assistant Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName> last week in
                            Marrakesh. I am grateful for your counsel and support with respect to
                            the Middle East negotiations. I also welcomed your views on the Sahara
                            situation, which have given us a full appreciation of Your Majesty’s
                            policy and objectives in this respect. We want to be helpful in any way
                            we can, within the framework of the United Nations, to achieve a stable
                            and amicable negotiated outcome, and it is in this spirit that I am
                            writing you today.</p>
                        <p>I want to report to Your Majesty that I have received a message from
                            President <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Boumediene</persName> expressing
                            deep concern over the potential consequences if the proposed march to
                            the Sahara goes forward.</p>
                        <pb facs="0309" n="283" xml:id="pg_283"/>
                        <p>I also want to inform you that we have now discussed with Secretary
                            General Waldheim the results of his recent mission, and he has described
                            to us his efforts to find a formula which could provide the basis for a
                            reasonable solution in the Spanish Sahara. After considering the formula
                            which the Secretary General is proposing, it occurs to us that Your
                            Majesty might find such a process acceptable. I would appreciate very
                            much knowing what Your Majesty’s views are and how Your Majesty intends
                            to proceed in relation to this formula. Meanwhile, now that matters seem
                            to be moving in the direction Morocco has been seeking, I am sure Your
                            Majesty will agree that it is important for all of us to exercise
                            continued patience and give the Secretary General all possible support
                            in these efforts. We believe they are promising and hope that this
                            matter can be pursued in an atmosphere of calm in your area which will
                            be conducive to a peaceful resolution.</p>
                        <p>I hope Your Majesty will agree that action such as the proposed march to
                            the Sahara, which would inevitably increase tension despite your best
                            efforts to the contrary, might prove unsettling to the hopeful process
                            now underway.</p>
                        <p>Warm Regards,</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName></p>
                        <p>End text.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>Ingersoll</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>