<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>43. Telegram 711 From the Embassy in Libya to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve09p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-06-18T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-06-18T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91001417"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arms sales</term>
                    <term ref="recoGY8BsVctNF3tT" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="arab-israeli-dispute">Arab-Israeli dispute</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="recfABRQvTqVuIjoA" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">C–130</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recgpNhn3NejuQEjr" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85075302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Law enforcement</term>
                    <term ref="recMpPwlFJwREQmrz" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="cultural-and-educational-exchanges" lcsh-match="no_match">Cultural relations</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-06-18T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-06-18T06:00:00-05:00" n="43"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                <head>43. Telegram 711 From the Embassy in Libya to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d43fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: The Embassy submitted its annual policy
                                assessment for Libya.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy Files. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1"
                                >Exdis</gloss>.</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Tripoli</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1975-06-18T11:00:00+00:00">June 18, 1975, 1100Z</date>.</dateline>
                <p>711. Subject: Annual Policy Assessment for Libya. Ref: 11 FAM 212.4.</p>
                <p>1. Summary: In the Embassy’s view the principal U.S. interests in Libya are that
                    (a) Libya not become a site for Soviet bases and area of exclusive Soviet
                    influence, and (2) that Libya give up its opposition to an Arab-Israeli
                    settlement. It is a fact that our power to promote these interests in present
                    circumstances is limited. We should, however, continue to use what leverage we
                    have. We should tell the Libyans clearly that their attitude on the Middle East
                    is a bar to better relations, and that arms sales will be considered in light of
                    the regime’s attitude toward the Arab-Israeli dispute. We cannot compete with
                    the Soviets as arms salesmen to <persName corresp="#p_QM_1">Qadhafi</persName>’s
                    regime, and we should not try. We should not rely too much on the argument that
                    Libya is a problem for the Egyptians to solve. Several structural factors are
                    working in our favor over the long term. One bright spot in the picture is the
                    continued eagerness of young Libyans to go to the U.S. for higher education, and
                    the regime’s willingness to finance their studies in U.S. universities. End
                    summary.</p>
                <p>2. I. U.S. Interests</p>
                <p>A. In the Embassy’s view, basic U.S. interests in Libya are:</p>
                <p>(1) That Libya, with its long Mediterranean coastline, not become an area of
                    exclusive Soviet influence or a site for Soviet military bases.</p>
                <p>(2) That Libya stop trying to undermine the settlement process in which Egypt is
                    engaged with Israel.</p>
                <p>(3) That U.S.-Libyan relations improve to the point where the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> has access to Libyan policymakers.</p>
                <p>(4) That the U.S. maintain its share of the Libyan market for goods and
                    services.</p>
                <p>B. In the absence of a Middle East settlement, or a change of heart by the regime
                    with regard to the existence of the Jewish State, it is a fact that our power to
                    promote these interests is limited, as our bilateral relations with Libya must
                    be subordinated to our larger interests in the area.</p>
                <p>(1) We should, nevertheless, use what leverage we have with the regime. It should
                    be brought home clearly to the Libyans that, while we <pb facs="0142" n="116"
                        xml:id="pg_116"/> will not threaten them with subversion or invasion, they
                    can expect no consideration from us as long as they continue to take a line on
                    the Middle East which is directly opposed to our vital interest in peace and the
                    continued existence of Israel. The best way to do this is not to ignore Libyan
                    approaches to us, or to deal with them in a tentative and piecemeal way.</p>
                <p>(2) We should not rely too much on the argument that Libya is basically a problem
                    for the Arabs or the Egyptians to solve for us. <persName corresp="#p_QM_1"
                        >Qadhafi</persName> has enough appeal throughout the Arab world to make it
                    hard for our Arab friends to keep him in permanent quarantine. In the case of
                    Egypt, it should be remembered that Libyans resent the Egyptian presence here;
                    to some extent Egyptians have become the focus for persistent anti-foreign
                    feeling which used to be directed against the U.S. and Britain under the
                    monarchy. An overly pro-Egyptian regime would soon find itself in hot water,
                    especially if its installation occurred through an Egyptian-backed coup. For
                    this reason, it would probably not be wise to encourage any Egyptian attempt to
                    overthrow <persName corresp="#p_QM_1">Qadhafi</persName>. Although we are
                    obviously sympathetic to the Egyptian position, we should not be associated with
                    any action which could redound to our discredit in the rest of the Arab
                    world.</p>
                <p>C. There follows a discussion of some of the outstanding issues between the U.S.
                    and Libya in the light of overall U.S. interests.</p>
                <p>3. II. U.S. Arms Sales to Libya</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_QM_1">Qadhafi</persName>’s military regime is inclined to
                    evaluate its relations with industrialized states in terms of the willingness of
                    those states to sell Libya arms. U.S. policy in this area is based on a desire
                    to avoid doing anything which could strengthen Libya’s offensive capability or
                    which could be read in the Arab world and elsewhere as implying approval or
                    tolerance of <persName corresp="#p_QM_1">Qadhafi</persName>’s policies. We
                    believe that this should be made clearer to the Libyans than it has been in the
                    past, and that the regime should be told that future sales of military matériel
                    under U.S. license will be considered on a case by case basis in the light of
                    progress toward a peaceful settlement in the Middle East. The Libyans must not
                    be allowed to entertain the illusion that they can make end runs around the
                        <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> with the help of various arms sellers
                    and the indirect exertion of commercial pressure.</p>
                <p>In our view, little purpose is served now by keeping the Libyans on the hook in
                    such matters as the delivery of the eight C–130’s they have bought and which are
                    awaiting an export license in the U.S., and it would be better to do away with
                    this contentious issue once and for all.</p>
                <p>4. III. <persName corresp="#p_QM_1">Qadhafi</persName> and the Soviets</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_QM_1">Qadhafi</persName>’s relations with the Soviet Union
                    are based on the willingness of the Soviets to sell him arms. They are
                    essentially relations of expedience and convenience on the Libyan and, we
                    presume, on the <pb facs="0143" n="117" xml:id="pg_117"/> Soviet side. We cannot
                    compete with the Soviets in selling Libya arms. Nor can we compete with the
                    Soviets in the acquisition of influence in Libya through covert and subversive
                    means, and we should not try.</p>
                <p>In the long term several factors are working in our favor. One is that, the
                    closer the regime gets to the Soviets, the more it needs a balancing U.S.
                    presence. We should be alert to seize the opportunities this situation may
                    present us with in the future. Another is that the Libyans are extremely jealous
                    of their political independence, and will not sell it cheap. The modern history
                    of the region which is now called Libya is one of resistance to foreign
                    intruders. Although the Soviets are walking on very soft feet at the moment, the
                    history of their dealings with other Arab states suggests that it will not be
                    long before a reaction against their presence will set in.</p>
                <p>Thus, in the Embassy’s view, the principal danger for U.S. interests of a Soviet
                    military presence in Libya lies in the fact that it strengthens <persName
                        corresp="#p_QM_1">Qadhafi</persName>’s hand in his efforts to undermine
                    movement toward a peaceful settlement of the Arab-Israeli dispute. We believe
                    that the regime’s basic anti-communist orientation has not changed, and that it
                    is not likely to change as long as <persName corresp="#p_QM_1"
                        >Qadhafi</persName> is in power.</p>
                <p>5. IV. Economic and Cultural Relations</p>
                <p>A. We should try to move our contacts with the Libyans away from the area of
                    military sales to that of economic and cultural relations, although even here we
                    face serious obstacles. During 1974 our sales of goods and services to Libya
                    remained at about the same level in terms of constant dollars, but fell as a
                    proportion of total Libyan spending which rose dramatically as a result of
                    increased oil revenues. In 1975–76 the projected sale of Boeing of three 727’s
                    and a VIP-equipped 707 should improve the picture. Our business people should be
                    aware, however, in trading with Libya that the regime finds itself in a
                    financial squeeze at the moment which may mean that payment for goods and
                    services will be delayed.</p>
                <p>B. A bright spot in the picture is the Libyan desire to educate large numbers of
                    their young men in the U.S. Over 1500 government-supported students have already
                    been sent, according to our latest reckoning, an increase of 50 percent over
                    last year’s total, and the flow shows no sign of slowing down. We should not try
                    to make political capital out of this; the facts speak for themselves, and as a
                    tactical matter we should keep our satisfaction to ourselves. At the same time,
                    we should work hard to minimize any frictions the program may create, and do our
                    best to smooth over the problems which may arise. If necessary, we should be
                    ready to go out of our way to reassure the suspicious regime that its students
                    will not be discriminated against or propagandized in any way. In particular,
                    Libyan students should not be questioned by U.S. law enforcement agencies unless
                    there is good <pb facs="0144" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/> reason to believe that
                    they are involved in illegal activity. Under no circumstances should they be
                    questioned about the political situation in Libya.</p>
                <p>6. V. Resources Projection</p>
                <p>A. Positions authorized:</p>
                <table cols="7">
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="2">
                            <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 75</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">
                            <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 76</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">
                            <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 77</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>FSL</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>FSL</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>FSL</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Executive:</cell>
                        <cell role="num">3</cell>
                        <cell role="num">1</cell>
                        <cell role="num">2</cell>
                        <cell role="num">1</cell>
                        <cell role="num">2</cell>
                        <cell role="num">1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Pol/Econ/Coml:</cell>
                        <cell role="num">5</cell>
                        <cell role="num">3</cell>
                        <cell role="num">5</cell>
                        <cell role="num">3</cell>
                        <cell role="num">5</cell>
                        <cell role="num">3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Consular:</cell>
                        <cell role="num">2</cell>
                        <cell role="num">3</cell>
                        <cell role="num">2</cell>
                        <cell role="num">2</cell>
                        <cell role="num">2</cell>
                        <cell role="num">2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Admin:</cell>
                        <cell role="num">5</cell>
                        <cell role="num">31</cell>
                        <cell role="num">4</cell>
                        <cell role="num">24</cell>
                        <cell role="num">4</cell>
                        <cell role="num">24</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Totals:</cell>
                        <cell role="num">15</cell>
                        <cell role="num">38</cell>
                        <cell role="num">13</cell>
                        <cell role="num">30</cell>
                        <cell role="num">13</cell>
                        <cell role="num">30</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>B. Cost in thousands of dollars:</p>
                <table cols="7">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Salaries and Allowances:</cell>
                        <cell role="num">352</cell>
                        <cell role="num">331</cell>
                        <cell role="num">325</cell>
                        <cell role="num">260</cell>
                        <cell role="num">335</cell>
                        <cell role="num">275</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Operations:</cell>
                        <cell role="num">—</cell>
                        <cell role="num">284</cell>
                        <cell role="num">—</cell>
                        <cell role="num">300</cell>
                        <cell role="num">—</cell>
                        <cell role="num">325</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Totals:</cell>
                        <cell role="num">—</cell>
                        <cell role="num">615</cell>
                        <cell role="num">—</cell>
                        <cell role="num">560</cell>
                        <cell role="num">—</cell>
                        <cell role="num">600</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>C. Remarks: COM, GSO and 4 FSL positions withdrawn in <gloss target="#t_FY_1"
                        >FY</gloss> 75 (State 32443). Four additional FSL positions to be withdrawn
                    in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 76 by realignment of functions. $50,000 in
                    severence payments were made to FSL’s in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss>
                    75.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_SRA_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SRA_1">Stein</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
