<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>71. Memorandum From Clinton E. Granger of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Deputy Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the
                    National Security Council Staff to the President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Scowcroft))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve09p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d71</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">71</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-10-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-10-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbm2CDfl6YlSCnq" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-10-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-10-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="71"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                <head>71. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_GCE_1">Clinton E. Granger</persName>
                    of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Deputy Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SBC_1"
                        >Scowcroft</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d71fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_GCE_1"
                                    >Granger</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_SBC_1"
                                    >Scowcroft</persName> of the delivery of tanks to Casablanca,
                                and Moroccan desires to have the tanks moved to another location. He
                                noted that State planned to refuse the Moroccan request.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser,
                                Presidential Country Files for Africa, Box 4, Morocco (2).
                                Confidential. Sent for information. A copy was sent to Bob Oakley of
                                the National Security Council Staff. <persName corresp="#p_SBC_1"
                                    >Scowcroft</persName> wrote on the memorandum: “How would we
                                help anyway?”</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-10-20"
                        >October 20, 1975</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Moroccan Tanks</item>
                </list>
                <p>We have delivered 28 M48A3 tanks to Morocco as part of the Moroccan force
                    modernization program. The tanks are currently located at Casablanca. Recently
                    the Moroccans, who do not have tank transporters, requested our aid in moving
                    the tanks to Oujda in the northeast of the country near the Algerian border.
                    State was about to agree when the Moroccans suddenly changed the desired
                    destination of the tanks to Ksah el-Souk, 200 km southeast of Casablanca.</p>
                <p>In this location the tanks would not be available for use in Spanish Sahara, but
                    would be strategically located to prevent possible Algerian incursion into
                    Morocco. However, State feels that the strategic niceties of the situation would
                    be lost on international opinion, and if we acceded to the Moroccan request to
                    move the tanks south we would be <pb facs="0214" n="188" xml:id="pg_188"/>
                    portrayed as giving aid and encouragement to Moroccan plans to take the Spanish
                    Sahara by force.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, State plans to refuse the Moroccan request, but to delay refusal
                    until after the visit of Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1"
                        >Atherton</persName> to Morocco on October 23.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
