<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>54. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v19p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d54</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">54</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-03-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recbm2CDfl6YlSCnq" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Troop withdrawal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-03-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="54"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d54">
                <head>54. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d54fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 541,
                        Country Files, Far East, Korea, Vol. II, 10/69–5/70. Secret; Eyes Only.
                        Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> who sent it to
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> under a memorandum in
                        which <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> recommended “in-house
                        distribution.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed
                        his approval on March 10. (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1970-03-03">March 3,
                            1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">William Porter</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">John H. Holdridge</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Senior Staff Member</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0166" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName>’s Comments on
                            <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Troop Withdrawals from Korea</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> reported that there had
                    been a session that day at State on the position State would take at the March 4
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting on Korea, in which the group had
                    recommended that withdrawals be expressed in terms of figures rather than units.
                    This would be more meaningful, as a division under certain circumstances could
                    amount to as few as 12,000 men. The Secretary had not commented on this, but
                    took up the proposal that the first slice should be 20,000 men, with 20,000 more
                    to be withdrawn after the two <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> divisions came
                    back from Vietnam. The thought was to let the generals strip off the figures,
                    but keep as much muscle in Korea as possible. Two-thirds of the division on the
                    line would be taken and sent home, which would give 8 to 10,000 of the 20,000
                    figure; 10,000 more would be stripped from the rear areas and service troops.
                    The <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s would be left to handle the increased
                    defense responsibility. State’s position on this, according to Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName>, was to support 16 modernized
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> divisions, not 18.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> observed that the reasoning
                    of the Joint Chiefs eluded him—their position was that 18 <gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> divisions could hold a North Korean and Chinese
                    attack, but that 16 divisions plus <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> forces
                    couldn’t do a thing. To a remark from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1"
                        >Porter</persName> that modernization of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                        >ROK</gloss> divisions would increase their effective strength a great deal,
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted that the Joint Chiefs
                    argue two <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and 18 unmodernized <gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> divisions or one <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss> and 18 modernized divisions are needed, but that one <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> division and 16 modernized <gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> divisions can’t do the job. This could not be
                    true. Their figures ought to be internally consistent. He had looked through
                    their figures, but could not determine what thought processes had been used to
                    reach their conclusion.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> recalled that in the
                    last withdrawals which we had made in 1954 and 1955, we had taken out a total of
                    six divisions, two corps headquarters, and non-divisional units. At that time
                    there had been 40,000 men in a division. Now we were talking about a 12,000-man
                    division withdrawal. This was a bare bones cut.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> mentioned that when General
                    Bonesteel had spoken to the President—there had been two sessions—the President
                    had been inclined to be helpful, but had been turned off by Bonesteel’s
                    presentation. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> said that
                    Bonesteel’s line with him in Korea was to preserve, and not to tear down; he had
                    replied that he had simply wanted to get the fat out of our commitment.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> stated that he understood
                    there was a disagreement between Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1"
                        >Porter</persName> and the military on the size of the force which we should
                    retain on the line. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName>
                    responded to <pb facs="0167" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/> the effect that the
                    military wanted sufficient forces to support any one point such as Panmunjom at
                    any one time. The military wanted a brigade. He thought, however, that a
                    battalion at Panmunjom would be sufficient to fulfill our responsibility of
                    guarding the <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss> meeting place. This could come
                    from the 7th Division, which with the addition of one brigade from the division
                    being sent home could rotate battalions to the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1"
                        >DMZ</gloss> and have enough strength at any one time to back this battalion
                    up. As for the rest of the line, we could let the <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                        >ROK</gloss>s take over. They already have seven-eighths of it.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> asked Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> when the scenario should be started.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> replied that the
                    discussions with the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s should be begun right
                    away before the Presidential election campaign opens, which would be in the Fall
                    after the nominating conventions. He wanted the essentials made known to the
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s and tied down so that the issue would
                    not bob up in the election campaign. If the process starts after the campaign
                    begins, there would be an effort to hold us off until the elections, which are
                    now scheduled for May 1971, were over. He would like to go back to Seoul on
                        Friday<note n="2" xml:id="d54fn2">March 6.</note> with approved
                    instructions.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> said he doubted the
                    instructions would be approved so soon and noted that the President usually
                    waits to make a decision until after the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    meeting is over. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName>
                    remarked that the sooner we begin, the better. He would like to see General
                        <persName corresp="#p_MJH1">Michaelis</persName> begin listing the matériel
                    we would leave behind for the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s, and then
                    move into discussions of further phases of modernization, so as to provide time
                    for Washington to consider the extra steps which would be needed. The first
                    modernization step would be from equipment already there, and the second might
                    be from what the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> troops in Vietnam brought
                    back with them. If President <persName corresp="#p_PCH1">Park</persName> were to
                    ask us what we intended to do, we could say that so much was ready, and continue
                    to negotiate from there.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> said that the decisions
                    might be made in perhaps two weeks. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1"
                        >Porter</persName> declared that this was acceptable. He was not
                    thin-skinned, and it wouldn’t bother him if the Koreans jumped around a bit.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PCH1">Park</persName> was rather expecting an early
                    decision, but could be put off. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> hoped that the decision might even be made on March 4.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> said that in any case
                    he felt it was better to move, and get <persName corresp="#p_PCH1"
                        >Park</persName>’s comments so we could see what we could do.</p>
                <p>Following a brief exchange on who would be attending the March 4 <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1"
                        >Porter</persName> asked Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> what kind of <pb facs="0168" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/>
                    information he might send in from Korea which would be helpful. Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> remarked that he had been very
                    interested in the materials which Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1"
                        >Porter</persName> had been sending back. He didn’t usually comment, but
                    read it all. He cited an account of a Vladivostok radio broadcast on My Lai
                    which Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> had forwarded;
                    this had come in very useful in a recent meeting with <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, who had been amazed that we had
                    picked up Vladivostok radio. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1"
                        >Porter</persName> said that he often saw things which were outside his own
                    bailiwick but which he thought might be interesting, and would send them back in
                    bits and pieces. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> urged
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> to send in anything he
                    considered significant. He trusted <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1"
                    >Porter</persName>’s judgment, and would make an effort to read his reports if
                    the Ambassador was willing to write them down.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> asked for Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName>’s views on Vietnam. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> expressed the opinion that the
                    Communists were preparing for another effort. They would let us pull down our
                    forces, and then have a go. They would have to do this—the leaders up North were
                    finding it hard to envisage peace, and “their lives were at stake”, i.e. they
                    had imposed too many casualties on the North to be able to stop now. There would
                    probably be another effort by the Communists to catch a government unit in an
                    isolated position. The <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> characteristically work
                    on some <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> unit out in front, watching its
                    officers’ movements, picking out its weak points, and working full time to lay
                    out their plans. They badly need a win because of the trouble they are now in,
                    and would try to achieve a psychological victory by catching a battalion and
                    decimating it. They would carefully select units to attack which are in areas
                    from which the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> has withdrawn. We would simply
                    have to face this situation.</p>
                <p>Continuing, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> commented
                    that Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> had wanted him to
                    talk about Vietnam and the Middle East, but that he had refused on the grounds
                    that these questions were outside his area of responsibility. On Korea,
                        <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> had inquired into nuclear
                    weapons, and had gone on and on about them. He had told the Senator that he had
                    no instructions to talk about nuclear weapons, to which <persName
                        corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> had accused him of “taking the
                    Fifth”. He had responded by expressing the hope that the Senator would not draw
                    this comparison too far. He had thought that the Senator would never let go.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> asked if Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> would need to be reconfirmed
                    if he were appointed to another post, to which the Ambassador said that he
                    thought this would be no problem. The Senator’s area of concern had really been
                    the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>, and he, <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1"
                        >Porter</persName>, felt that the hearings had gone quite well.
                    Surprisingly, Senator <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Symington</persName> had wanted
                    to let the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s loose against the North.</p>
                <pb facs="0169" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/>
                <p>Turning back to the troop withdrawal issue, Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> expressed the belief that we could swing
                    the option which we wanted. The <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>s would go
                    into their usual banging tactics, but could be held. They would want us to
                    modernize their forces first and then withdraw, but we should do both
                    concurrently. He urged that the commanding general in Korea be given the
                    authority to arrange these matters. This would strengthen his hand with respect
                    to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>, who wanted to run everything
                    himself, and who customarily took the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> view.
                    However, he had every confidence that <persName corresp="#p_MJH1"
                        >Michaelis</persName> would be able to strip off the forces properly, and
                    would also go further than the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> would in this
                    effort.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
