<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-10T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-10T11:00:00-05:00" n="144" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d144">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/11–1044: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-10T18:00:00+02:00">November 10, 1944—6 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received November 11—12:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>25. The Mountain Brigade arrived here yesterday morning<note n="27" xml:id="d144fn27">The Mountain Brigade, a unit of the Greek Army
                                    formed in the Middle East after the German occupation of Greece,
                                    had just returned from the battle front in Italy.</note>
                                parading without incident and with great popular demonstrations of
                                rejoicing. The troops looked fit and competent and marched well. In.
                                greeting Mr. Papandreou and General Scobie the Commander pledged
                                loyalty to the Government and to the British Command. For the moment
                                the arrival has benefited local morale by contributing a new feeling
                                of security.</p>
                            <pb facs="0150" n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/>
                            <p>I had a talk with Mr. Papandreou this morning. He expressed himself
                                as optimistic (which is his usual turn of mind) but said that the
                                most critical moment for his efforts to reestablish Government in a
                                demoralized country, by political means only and without force to
                                impose it, will come early in December when the guerilla
                                organizations have been ordered to disband (see my telegram No. 16
                                of November 7 [<hi rend="italic">9</hi>], 7 p.m.<note n="20" xml:id="d144fn20">Gen. Sir Henry Maitland Wilson.</note>). He
                                emphasized that while his careful and gradual methods of
                                tranquilizing and organizing would appear to have the support of EAM
                                and the Communists at present, all depends on getting the people
                                back to work, and he begged me to do all I can to insure the
                                necessary supplies and credits for that purpose. He said the
                                Liberals, though participating in the Government, are also providing
                                the only political opposition he has presently to contend with but
                                he believes this is not of a very serious nature and that in general
                                the old parties as such have lost their hold on the people. He added
                                that fear of Communism seems to be reviving Royalist sentiment
                                particularly in “old Greece” but merely stated this as a fact which
                                I believe it is, without expressing either pleasure or displeasure
                                in regard to it.</p>
                            <p>I asked Mr. Papandreou about the treatment to be accorded the
                                Quislings and other collaborators now in prison and he said “There
                                will have to be some executions”. It is essential, he said, that the
                                Government take this matter in hand and show severity with justice
                                otherwise the Communists will certainly attempt direct action not
                                only with the likelihood that much injustice will be done but with
                                fatal results to our Government’s prestige. I referred to the speech
                                he made here on arrival in which he said that the country had been
                                liberated from a tyranny of 8 years and asked him whether he intends
                                to make no distinction between Metaxists and traitors and he replied
                                that there would certainly be a distinction and that the proof is
                                supplied by the fact that already laws have been passed against the
                                collaborators but none as yet against participators in the Metaxas’
                                regime (see my 358 October 12, 6 p.m. from Cairo<note n="29" xml:id="d144fn29">Not printed.</note>). He says it may even be
                                that no specific laws against these persons will be passed at all
                                but emphasized that Greece’s sufferings under the Metaxist tyranny
                                have been too great to be overlooked: “That is why we must have a
                                plebiscite on the Monarchy. If the King had not supported Metaxas
                                the question would not arise.”</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>