<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-12-27T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-12-27T12:00:00-05:00" n="183" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/12–2744: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-27T19:00:00+02:00">December 27, 1944—7 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received December 28—7:10 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>190. For the President. I communicated your message<note n="70" xml:id="d183fn70">Telegram No. 680, December 26, <ref target="#pg_170">p. 170</ref>.</note> this morning to Mr.
                                Churchill, who expressed his appreciation, and this afternoon had a
                                long talk with him. He is clearly deeply disturbed over the
                                situation here, and its dangers for British prestige and his <pb facs="0185" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/> own position, but is also
                                determined to persist in military operations until Athens and its
                                surroundings are cleared, unless the present Greek negotiations for
                                a settlement of the governmental issue, which he himself set in
                                motion yesterday, bring about an earlier acceptance of General
                                Scobie’s terms. After that he appears to be thinking of the
                                possibility of composing matters in the rest of Greece through the
                                medium of a commission of the three great powers, somewhere along
                                the lines of my suggestion to you in my letter of December 8.<note n="71" xml:id="d183fn71">Not printed; the reference is to
                                    Ambassador MacVeagh’s suggestion for an international commission
                                    to oversee a plebiscite on the question of the regime; see
                                    telegram No. 132, December 8, 10 a.m., <ref target="#pg_145">p.
                                        145</ref>.</note> He showed himself to me, both yesterday
                                and today, to be resentful of American press criticism of his Greek
                                policy and deeply disappointed over what he feels to be our
                                Government’s lack of understanding of his attitude and its failure
                                to support him. I asked him if he wanted me to send you any message
                                and he replied <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Tell him that I hope he can help us in some way. We want
                                        nothing from Greece. We don’t want her airfields or her
                                        harbors—only a fair share of her trade. We don’t want her
                                        islands. We’ve got Cyprus anyhow. We came in here by
                                        agreement with our Allies to chase the Germans out and then
                                        found that we had to fight to keep the people here in Athens
                                        from being massacred. Now if we can do that properly—and we
                                        will—all we want is to get out of this damned place.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>While I was talking with him word came in from the Archbishop that
                                the Insurgents insist on a Regency as a prerequisite for continuing
                                conversations and that the other members of the Conference initiated
                                yesterday but now including a larger number of political figures
                                have all voted for a Regency to be set up under the Archbishop
                                either now or after the cease fire has sounded. Mr. Churchill said
                                that he would probably leave here tomorrow and have another go at
                                the King on this question.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>