<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-15T11:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-15T11:35:00-05:00" n="510" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d510">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">761.91/11–1544: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Morris</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-15T20:00:00+03:25">November 15, 1944—8 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received November 17—1:20 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>847. On instructions from Foreign Minister Eden British Ambassador
                                presented oral protest to Russian Ambassador Maximov stating Russian
                                action in holding up and suppressing Iranian Government <pb facs="0485" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> telegrams was in direct
                                violation of agreement entered into by Great Britain and Soviet
                                Union with Iranian Government. Maximov replied Russian censor here
                                acted on instructions of Russian military authorities in Iran whose
                                action was motivated by their own estimation that Iran had become
                                hostile to Russia. Russian Ambassador appeared completely
                                embarrassed and quickly passed responsibility to Vice Commissar
                                Kavtaradze. He said he would take up matter with Commissar who would
                                answer in name of Foreign Commissar Molotov. British Ambassador has
                                not yet received a reply to his <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi>
                                which took place day before yesterday. He believes and so do I that
                                matter has been referred to Moscow to determine nature of reply.</p>
                            <p>In view of his having received instructions to protest formally the
                                Russian censorship action Bullard did not believe that a tripartite
                                talk would be of utility or appropriate at present time as suggested
                                in Department’s telegram No. 666, November 7. Nevertheless I decided
                                to take up matter with Russian Ambassador myself. I had a long
                                conversation with him this morning: I took attitude I was acting on
                                my own initiative to express in friendly fashion my view that it was
                                not helpful to Russia’s own interest to have censored press
                                despatches intended to be sent to the great American news agencies
                                by our local correspondents. I said this step not unnaturally
                                aroused some misgiving in American press and through the press, in
                                the public, as to the nature and intent of Russian actions in Iran.
                                I expressed feeling that if American news agencies had been allowed
                                to carry reports of their own correspondents in American press
                                simultaneously with what came out from Moscow that the Russian
                                position and the thesis on which it was built would have been better
                                presented. I expanded this general theme considerably and rather
                                insistently.</p>
                            <p>I believe my colleague was somewhat impressed by the argument. He
                                defended Russian position, however, by counter stroke; he asserted
                                in all the [Millspaugh?] controversy [nothing?] had appeared in
                                Russian press detr[imental] to American financial mission. He said
                                he was responsible for this attitude. He further said the Russian
                                press had carried nothing about negotiations between Anglo-American
                                petroleum companies and Iranian Government prior to arrival of
                                Russian official delegation here. He put forward thought that right
                                manner for tripartite understanding on matters of this nature in
                                Iran was for each member nation to refrain from any comment upon
                                actions of other members in respect to negotiations or undertakings
                                with Iranian Government as long as matter at hand concerned only
                                Iranian Government and one of tripartite members. I answered that
                                his course might have tendency to keep from the public legitimate
                                    <pb facs="0486" n="474" xml:id="pg_474"/> news of world interest
                                and in the end would not serve interests of powers concerned or of
                                Iran itself. Maximov did not insist very far on this theme.</p>
                            <p>The upshot of our conversation was that Maximov has agreed to review
                                personally with me any future case where an American press
                                correspondent has his material withheld by Russian military censor.
                                Whether this arrangement will have any value only a test can show. I
                                have instructed our correspondents here to submit to Embassy at once
                                any case in point.</p>
                            <p>When Russian Embassy reply is given to British Ambassador I will
                                forward it to Department.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Moscow and London.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Morris</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>