<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé at Tangier ( (Elbrick) ) to the French Resident General in Morocco
                    ( (Puaux))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d563</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">563</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-04-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recDNr3fFoY74D9ro" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="563"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d563">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">881.044/36</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Elbrick</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the French Resident General in Morocco</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Puaux</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="14" xml:id="d563fn14">Copy transmitted to the Department in
                        despatch 2072, May 8, from Tangier; in this despatch the Chargé noted that
                        the last two paragraphs had been “recast to take into account subsequent
                        developments …” (The earlier copy had been transmitted to the Department in
                        despatch 1963, February 11, <ref target="#pg_510">p. 510</ref>.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-13">April 13,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Resident General</hi>: I have the honor to refer to
                    Your Excellency’s note no. 62–D of January 24, 1944<note n="15"
                        xml:id="d563fn15">Not printed.</note> which suggests that the <pb
                        facs="0529" n="517" xml:id="pg_517"/> Government of the United States be
                    requested to examine the possibility of its addressing general instructions to
                    the American consular authorities in French Morocco enjoining them to consider
                    as automatically applicable to American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi>
                    any decrees taken by the Protectorate authorities for the enforcement of the
                    enabling dahir of September 13, 1938, concerning the organization of the French
                    Zone in time of war.</p>
                <p>In this connection reference is made by Your Excellency to a note dated January
                    9, 1940,<note n="16" xml:id="d563fn16">
                        <ref target="frus1940v03#pg_772">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 772</ref>.</note> addressed by Mr.
                    Maxwell Blake to General Noguès to the effect that the then American Diplomatic
                    Agent was disposed to examine and report to the Department of State suggestions
                    concerning measures of cooperation with the Protectorate authorities designed to
                    avoid special difficulties which <hi rend="italic">might result from the failure
                        of the American Government to give its approval to French Zone legislation
                        enacted as a result of the present exceptional circumstances</hi>. It would
                    seem that Your Excellency’s above-mentioned proposal was put forward on the
                    assumption that it might be deemed to fall within the compass of the terms of
                    Mr. Blake’s note. That such is not the case is apparent from the terms of the
                    note itself, limited as they are to the consideration of situations arising from
                    the failure or the inability of the Department to validate certain Protectorate
                    legislation. The ensuing explanations, it is believed, will further elucidate
                    the position.</p>
                <p>Your Excellency’s suggestion has been brought to the attention of the Department
                    of State, and in pursuance of its instructions the Legation is directed to point
                    out that the enforcement upon American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> of
                    decrees and regulations to implement the dahir of September 13, 1938 would
                    necessarily be incumbent upon the American consular courts in Morocco and that,
                    pursuant to the Statutes of the United States, the system of laws, both criminal
                    and civil, to be applied in these courts shall, in all cases, be in conformity
                    with the laws of the United States.</p>
                <p>The Statutes, however, further make provision for the issuance of special decrees
                    emanating from the appropriate American authorities, necessary to furnish
                    suitable remedies where the provisions of the American system of laws applicable
                    in the American consular courts may be deficient to meet particular exigencies
                    in extraterritorial countries.</p>
                <p>In regard to Morocco, local laws or decrees validated by the Department of State
                    are deemed to be equivalent to the special decrees envisaged by the Statutes as
                    above said. It follows, therefore, that no local dahir, decree, or regulation
                    can become part of the corpus juris of the American consular courts in this
                    country, in the absence <pb facs="0530" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/> of the
                    Department of State’s previous validation, with its attendant reservations, of
                    each of such local enactments individually.</p>
                <p>From the foregoing Your Excellency will appreciate that, on treaty, statutory,
                    and juridical grounds the Department of State is not in a position to entertain
                    a proposal such as that submitted by Your Excellency, which would imply a
                    foregone approval to the enforcement by the consular courts upon American <hi
                        rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> of local legislation eventually to be
                    enacted.</p>
                <p>While, therefore, it is unable to consider any departure from the normal
                    procedure established for the validation of Moroccan legislation which it is
                    sought to apply to American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> in this
                    country, the Department is anxious at all times, as Your Excellency is aware, to
                    afford the Protectorate authorities the fullest cooperation. In all cases,
                    therefore, particularly those which the Residency General may consider of urgent
                    interest, the procedure under reference is carried out with the greatest
                    possible expedition.</p>
                <p>The Residency General at Rabat will have noted further that the Department’s
                    validation of dahirs and decrees appears not to have been withheld nor have its
                    reservations been formulated except in respect of legislation which, in the
                    opinion of the Department, was at variance with fundamental principles of the
                    Moroccan treaties, or for other cogent reasons.</p>
                <p>Prior to the receipt of Your Excellency’s note of January 24, 1944, no
                    suggestions have been submitted on the part of the Protectorate authorities in
                    response to Mr. Blake’s note of January 9, 1940. Nevertheless, the Legation at
                    Tangier and the American Consulates in French Morocco have, since then, been
                    consistently engaged in carrying its terms into practice. They have successfully
                    induced American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> voluntarily to comply
                    with local dahirs, decrees, and regulations issued in the interest of the
                    Moroccan community at large in the present exceptional circumstances, but to
                    which laws the Department is unable to give its formal assent because of their
                    departure from the basic treaty principles. As an instance, the matter of the
                    requisition of olive crops may be cited. While such expedient implies no waiver
                    of treaty rights, it brings about the desired cooperation with the Protectorate
                    authorities. In taking such action, the American Consuls concerned must of
                    course be assured that American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> shall not
                    incur discriminatory or otherwise inequitable treatment as a result of their
                    voluntary compliance with laws and regulations not legally binding upon
                    them.</p>
                <p>The efforts of American Consuls in French Morocco to promote the success of the
                    above <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> will be facilitated if they are <pb
                        facs="0531" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/> opportunely furnished by the
                    Protectorate authorities with complete data in regard to the requirements of the
                    pertinent Protectorate legislation and regulations. Through such mutual
                    cooperation it is hoped that such difficulties as are referred to in Your
                    Excellency’s note can be reduced to a negligible minimum.</p>
                <p>Finally, the two specific matters which have occasioned Your Excellency’s note,
                    namely, the suppression of the constitution of clandestine stocks and the
                    restraint of excessive consumption of water or electrical power, have occupied
                    the sympathetic attention of the Legation and of the Consulate at
                    Casablanca.</p>
                <p>As regards the first, it is obvious that the existence of local “black” markets
                    proceeds from temporary departure from observance of the basic treaty principle
                    of the liberty of commerce in Morocco. Consequently, as above shown, the
                    American Consulates’ treatment of this matter could not be conducted on a legal
                    plane. Consideration is, however, being given to the feasibility of applying
                    administrative action susceptible of deterring American <hi rend="italic"
                        >ressortissants</hi> from engagement in discreditable transactions on the
                    “black” markets. The particular case to which Your Excellency refers is
                    apparently the alleged constitution of clandestine stocks of kerosene by
                    Mohammed Ben Driss Drissi, a <hi rend="italic">semsar</hi> of the Socony-Vacuum
                    Oil Company at Moulay Idriss Zerhoun.</p>
                <p>Correspondence between the American Consul General at Casablanca and Your
                    Excellency’s Diplomatic Cabinet reveals that this matter had been complicated by
                    the unwarranted action of the local authorities of control in taking such
                    proceedings against the American <hi rend="italic">ressortissant</hi> as, in
                    virtue of the Moroccan treaties, are of the exclusive competency of the American
                    Consulates in their judiciary capacity. Incidentally the Legation has since been
                    informed that Mr. H. Earle Russell’s investigation in this connection has shown
                    the unsustainable character of the charges brought against the above named
                    Mohammed Ben Driss Drissi.</p>
                <p>As regards the regulation of the use of electrical power, the legislation would
                    not appear intrinsically to involve a basic treaty principle and might therefore
                    be susceptible of receiving the Department’s eventual approval, subject to
                    appropriate reservations, of its enforcement upon American <hi rend="italic"
                        >ressortissants</hi>, following the formal application to that end on the
                    part of the Sherifian Government. This initial procedure having now been
                    followed as the result of the presentation to the Legation of Your Excellency’s
                    note no. 235–D of March 14, 1944, the legislation in question is at present
                    under consideration.</p>
                <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Burke Elbrick</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
