<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Appointed Minister to Syria and Lebanon ( (Wadsworth) ) to the Secretary
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">874</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-11-02T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-11-02T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-02T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-02T09:00:00-05:00" n="874"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d874">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751.90D11/11–444: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Appointed Minister to Syria and Lebanon</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wadsworth</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Beirut</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-02T16:00:00+02:00"
                            >November 2, 1944—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 3—7:27 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>240. Syrian Foreign Minister Mardam has shown me his minutes of four meetings had
                    during last week by him and Premier with Beynet and Ostrorog to discuss “matters
                    in suspense”, notably question of transfer of Troupes Spéciales (Legtel 132,
                    July 4, 6 p.m.<note n="87" xml:id="d874fn87">Not printed.</note>).</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Finally Beynet insisted that meetings were designed to consider ensemble of
                    questions in suspense, and Ostrorog gave following five “heads of chapters” of
                    all questions requiring solution: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Treaty of alliance. This Beynet later described as treaty of
                            friendship which might be used as model for treaties with other powers
                            as well.</item>
                        <pb facs="0821" n="809" xml:id="pg_809"/>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Military convention. This, Ostrorog said, would regulate transfer of
                            Troupes Spéciales and collaboration of French military mission their
                            training as Syrian army.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Convention of establishment. This was to be concluded on basis of
                            absolute reciprocity; but Mardam commented to me that he conceived it as
                            designed to legalize the illegalities of 20 years during which France,
                            in violation of its mandate, had acquired various concessionary rights.
                            We have, he said, no railways or port concessions in France.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Consular convention. Spears tells me he asked Beynet what this meant
                            and received vague reply that it would provide for exchange of consuls.
                            Mardam fears French wish to include, as in 1936 treaty, right to protect
                            Syrians in foreign countries where Syria be not represented.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>University convention. This was to be concluded on basis of text sent
                            Department with my despatch 441, July 14.<note n="88" xml:id="d874fn88"
                                >Not printed.</note> American University and Mission are now
                            preparing further comment thereon to show potentially prejudicial effect
                            on our educational interest.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Syrians maintained their position that army should be transferred irrespective of
                    their unwillingness to conclude such a treaty and conventions or otherwise bind
                    themselves at his [<hi rend="italic">this</hi>] time to special relationship
                    with any power. Beynet insisted all France wanted was agreement on all questions
                    “made in most loyal spirit and which will not harm any interests”. He added: “My
                    Government is within its rights to consider as unfriendly your attitude towards
                    my country”; also “we are in a vicious circle”.</p>
                <p>Syrians replied it was “an impasse” which they would wish to take to the
                        Hague<note n="89" xml:id="d874fn89">The Permanent Court of International
                        Justice, located at The Hague.</note> were that Court functioning; such
                    being impossible they intended to appeal to British good offices, for British
                    Government had already intervened in broader questions at issue and army
                    question was one which peculiarly concerned Britain. Mardam explained to me that
                    by this last he referred to Britain’s primary military responsibility to the
                    Allies in Middle Eastern theatre of operations.</p>
                <p>Yesterday Secretary General to Syrian President called on me to say that a note
                    in foregoing sense would be delivered to Spears tomorrow. He adds that copies of
                    minutes of meetings and note to Spears would be given me for despatch to
                        Department<note n="90" xml:id="d874fn90">Despatch 566, November 22, from
                        Beirut, not printed.</note> which it was hoped would support Syrian
                    proposal. Spears has already wired proposal to London.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wadsworth</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
