<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-18T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-18T04:00:00-05:00" n="898" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d898">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense(M)Turkey/988:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-18T11:00:00+02:00">April
                                        18, 1944—11 a.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 9:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>702. See my 689, April 15, midnight. I am in receipt of a note from
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs under date of April 17 in reply to my
                                note of April 14 a translation of the text of which reads as
                                    follows:<note n="25" xml:id="d898fn25">Telegram 703, April 18, 7
                                    p.m., from Ankara, reported that a similar note had been
                                    delivered to the British Ambassador as a reply to the British
                                    note of April 14 (811.20 Defense(M)Turkey/989).</note>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Mr. Ambassador: The Government of the Republic has examined
                                        the note which Your Excellency was good enough to deliver to
                                        me on the 14th instant, in order to make to me, in the name
                                        of the Government of the United States of America, a
                                        communication regarding Turkey’s trade relations with the
                                        Axis countries.</p>
                                    <p>Your Excellency is fully aware that, even before the start of
                                        the world conflict, Turkey had chosen her place and in the
                                        various circumstances which have subsequently occurred, she
                                        has never, at any time, deviated from the clear-cut position
                                        which she had thus adopted. The collaboration which is
                                        requested of her today is, accordingly, in conformity with
                                        her foreign policy, and it is in this spirit that the
                                        Government of the Republic has received the words of the
                                        very Honorable Mr. Cordell Hull as well as the communication
                                        which Your Excellency has made to me in the same sense.</p>
                                    <p>The mutual aid which our two countries have given each other
                                        throughout all the vicissitudes of the war has been based
                                        upon a reciprocal understanding of the unavoidable
                                        necessities and of the vital interests of each of them, and
                                        I can assure Your Excellency that the same spirit of
                                        understanding is at the basis of the favorable consideration
                                        accorded by the Turkish Government to the suggestions of the
                                        Government of the United States of America.</p>
                                    <p>I can, therefore, state to Your Excellency that, in the
                                        spirit of sincere collaboration which forms the foundation
                                        of its policy, the Government of the Republic will, within
                                        the limits of its material possibilities, <pb facs="0842" n="830" xml:id="pg_830"/> give to the United States of
                                        America the aid which has been suggested.</p>
                                    <p>Please accept, Mr. Ambassador, the assurances of my very high
                                        consideration. Signed N. Menemencioglu.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>