<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Switzerland ( (Harrison))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d992</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">992</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">Detainees</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="992"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d992">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94114A/419: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-19">April 19,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1347. Request Swiss to inform Gorgé at Tokyo that the Department has noted with
                    appreciation (your 2357, April 15, 7 a.m.) that he is continuing to press the
                    Japanese Government fully to honor its commitment to implement Article 86 of the
                    Geneva Convention and thus establish full reciprocity between visits permitted
                    to places where Japanese nationals are held by the United States and visits to
                    places where American nationals are held by Japan.</p>
                <p>Request Swiss also to give Gorgé following information regarding activities
                    protecting Powers for Japanese interests:</p>
                <p>Representatives of the Spanish Embassy and Swedish Legation which have undertaken
                    the protection of Japanese interests in the continental United States and
                    Territory of Hawaii, respectively, have made frequent visits during the past two
                    years to all places without exception where Japanese nationals have been held as
                    detainees, internees, evacuees or prisoners of war, have been freely permitted
                    to interview them without witnesses and have been allowed the greatest freedom
                    in inspecting all features of the various places of detention.</p>
                <p>[Here follows an account of visits made by representatives of Spain and Sweden to
                    camps where Japanese nationals were held.]</p>
                <p>The Department has just received a request from the Spanish Embassy Washington
                    again to visit all places in the United States where Japanese nationals are held
                    and desiring to provide complete reciprocity in this respect wishes urgently to
                    learn from Gorgé what provision the Japanese Government has now made (or which
                    he has good reason to believe is being made) to enable the Swiss representatives
                    to visit all those places not yet visited where American nationals are held by
                    Japan.</p>
                <pb facs="0952" n="940" xml:id="pg_940"/>
                <p>The Department would be pleased particularly to learn that those places in the
                    Philippine Islands, Netherlands Indies, Malaya, Burma and Thailand which it
                    understands have not been visited since their establishment (in some cases more
                    than two years ago) may now be visited and that the Swiss representatives will
                    henceforth be permitted, as are the Spanish and Swedish representatives here,
                    fully to enjoy the privileges guaranteed to them by Article 86 of the
                    Convention.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
