<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-03-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="103" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d103">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.673/118</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Davis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-03-04"><hi rend="italic">March 4,
                                1921</hi></date><lb/>[Received March 22.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 4287</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my telegram No. 176,
                            March 4, 1 p.m.,<note n="82" xml:id="d103fn82">Not printed.</note> and
                            previous correspondence in regard to the jurisdiction of the Palestine
                            Courts over foreigners, I have the honor to transmit herewith copies of
                            a Note No. E. 2340/1647/88 dated March 2nd, 1921, which I have received
                            from the Foreign Office in this connection.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Office state that the British High Commissioner for |
                            Palestine has been instructed to hand over to the American Consul for
                            trial the American citizen who was recently convicted on a charge of
                            forgery by the Jaffa Court.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John W. Davis</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The British Secretary of State for Foreign
                                    Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Curzon</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American
                                    Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Davis</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-03-02"><hi rend="italic">2 March,
                                        1921</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">E 2340/1647/88</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: I have the honour to refer
                                to the note which Your Excellency was so good as to address to me on
                                the 3rd. February<note n="83" xml:id="d103fn83">See telegram no. 73,
                                    Feb. 1, to the Ambassador in Great Britain, <ref target="#pg_119">p. 119</ref>.</note> with regard to the
                                jurisdiction of the Palestine Courts over foreigners.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>His Majesty’s Government appreciate, while regretting the
                                    legal reasons and somewhat technical considerations which prompt
                                    the United States Government to press their representations for
                                    the <pb facs="0217" n="121" xml:id="pg_121"/> recognition of
                                    United States Consular jurisdiction in Palestine, pending the
                                    entry into force of the Treaty of Peace with Turkey and the
                                    mandate for Palestine, upon which date, as already pointed out
                                    in my note of December 29th., the extra-territorial rights
                                    enjoyed by foreigners in Palestine will definitely cease to
                                    exist. While therefore His Majesty’s Government are naturally
                                    reluctant to override the decision of the Jaffa Court, and thus
                                    not only to run the risk of adversely affecting the authority
                                    and prestige of the responsible British authorities in Palestine
                                    but also to render more difficult the heavy task which they have
                                    accepted, with, as they hoped, the cordial good-will of the
                                    United States Government, they are prepared in deference to the
                                    United States Government’s representations and as a mark of
                                    their friendly sentiments to accede to the United States
                                    Government’s wishes in this matter, pending the coming into
                                    force of the Treaty of Peace.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Instructions are accordingly being sent to His Majesty’s High
                                    Commissioner for Palestine that the United States citizen who
                                    was recently convicted on a charge of forgery by the Jaffa Court
                                    should be handed over to United States Consul for trial.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>(For the Secretary of State)<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lancelot Oliphant</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>