<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Haiti ( (Jordan))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1921v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1921-11-14T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1921-11-14T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-11-14T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-11-14T18:00:00-05:00" n="209"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d209">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">838.51/1152 supp.: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jordan</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-11-14T18:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 14, 1921—6 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>60. Department’s October 18, 1 p.m.</p>
                <p>You are instructed to confer further with the Acting Financial Adviser and to
                    request of the Minister for Foreign Affairs an audience with the President at an
                    early date in order that you may hand <pb facs="0314" n="218" xml:id="pg_218"/>
                    him, in company with Mr. Maumus, the following supplements note: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Due to the continued active assistance of the Department, the Financial
                            Adviser has now obtained a further loan offer from the banking firm of
                            Messrs. Lee, Higginson and Company, of New York, of which the following
                            is a summary: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>‘Subject to the approval of their Counsel as to the form and
                                    validity of the bonds and their conformity with provisions of
                                    Treaties and other diplomatic agreements between the Republic of
                                    Haiti and the United States of America, they offer 85 and
                                    interest for $16,000,000 30 year 6 per cent Sinking Fund Gold
                                    Bonds of the Republic of Haiti to be dated November 1, 1921, and
                                    to be payable November 1, 1951; the bonds shall not be callable
                                    for 15 years, except for the Sinking Fund, the operation of
                                    which shall be sufficient to retire the entire issue by
                                    maturity. Payments into Sinking Fund to be in accordance with
                                    the schedule annexed<note n="37" xml:id="d209fn37">Not
                                        transmitted with this telegram.</note> which provides for
                                    total annual payments, including interest and Sinking Fund of
                                    $1,110,000 per year, which amount is increased by $5,000 each
                                    year up to and including the 29th; the 30th year payment is
                                    $833,645. After all revenues of the Republic exceed $7,000,000
                                    per annum, 25 per cent of such excess, but not more than
                                    $250,000 a year, shall be used as a market fund to buy bonds of
                                    the issue up to par; payments for the Sinking Fund shall be used
                                    to buy and retire bonds at prices up to par; if not procurable
                                    below par, they shall be drawn at par to the extent of funds
                                    available from Sinking Fund; after 15 years the Government of
                                    Haiti shall have the right to pay off the entire loan at par and
                                    interest upon reasonable notice.</p>
                                <p>As in the case of the two previous offers transmitted, the
                                    bankers require that all legislative acts necessary to give full
                                    effect to the terms of the Protocol shall be enacted. Among
                                    these requirements the most important is one enacting that if
                                    upon the expiration of the Treaty of September 16, 1915, and of
                                    any extension thereof,<note n="38" xml:id="d209fn38">For the
                                        text of the treaty, art. XVI of which provides that it shall
                                        remain in force 10 years, see <ref target="frus1916#pg_328">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1916, p.
                                            328</ref>; for the additional act of Mar. 28, 1917,
                                        changing the term of the treaty to 20 years, see <ref
                                            target="frus1917#pg_807">
                                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 1917, p. 807</ref>.</note>
                                    bonds of this present issue, or other bonds issued in pursuance
                                    of said Treaty shall still be outstanding, the payment of
                                    interest and the amortization of such bonds shall continue to be
                                    a first charge upon all the internal revenues of Haiti, and a
                                    second charge upon the customs revenues of Haiti next in order
                                    after the payment, first, of salaries, allowances and expenses
                                    of the officer or officers duly to be appointed by the President
                                    of Haiti upon nomination by the President of the United States,
                                    which officer or officers shall be appointed to control the
                                    collection and allocation of the hypothecated revenues
                                    aforesaid, so as to make certain that adequate provision shall
                                    be made for the amortization and interest of the loan, all as
                                    contemplated by Article VIII of the Protocol of October 3,
                                    1919.</p>
                                <p>It is understood that the issue of bonds will be free of all
                                    Haitian taxes.</p>
                                <pb facs="0315" n="219" xml:id="pg_219"/>
                                <p>The bankers further state that they have recommended the sale of
                                    6 per cent bonds by the Republic of Haiti because they believe
                                    that a 6 per cent bond can be successfully marketed at the
                                    present time, and that thus Haiti’s credit will be established
                                    in the markets of the world on a much higher plain than if 7’s
                                    and 7½’s are sold. The bankers also state that this advantage
                                    can be gained by Haiti at no greater net cost over a period of
                                    30 years than if 10 year 7½’s are sold now at 95 and when they
                                    mature 20 year 6’s at 92, the best prices, in their opinion, at
                                    which these might be sold, provided market conditions at that
                                    time happen to be satisfactory. In either case the cost of the
                                    money would be practically 7.23 per cent over the entire period,
                                    assuming maturity of bond issue at 100. Attention is also
                                    invited by the bankers to the fact that interest and Sinking
                                    Fund charges will be lower on an issue of $16,000,000 than the
                                    larger amount required as collateral under the 10 year note
                                    plan. Moreover, $300,000 additional cash proceeds are obtained
                                    under the present plan.</p>
                                <p>The present offer also has the advantage over the 10 year note
                                    plan of concluding the loan in one transaction thus eliminating
                                    considerable expense and further negotiations at a later date
                                    between the two Governments and various groups of bankers.’</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Department has given careful study to the offer above outlined and is
                            of the opinion that it is the most favorable thus far received, both for
                            the reasons given by the bankers, and because the probabilities appear
                            to be greater that the world’s money markets will not offer a better
                            rate at the end of 10 years for 6 per cent 20 year bonds than 92.</p>
                        <p>If the 6 per cent 20 year bonds could be issued at more than 92 in 10
                            years the issue of short term notes is preferable, if not, it is
                            preferable to issue 6 per cent bonds at the present time at 85. However,
                            in view of previous financial history of periods following great wars,
                            and in view of the great debts of all the principal countries and the
                            great demand for capital for reconstruction, the probabilities seem to
                            be against an important reduction in the rate of interest within the
                            next ten years. Moreover, no offer has yet been made for the 10 year
                            notes at as high a price as 95.</p>
                        <p>The offer herewith transmitted is stated by the bankers to be conditional
                            upon acceptance thereof being received by them on or before November 19,
                            1921, and also upon the fulfillment on or before that date of the terms
                            and conditions they have specified. They state that an early date for
                            acceptance is fixed by them owing to the uncertainty of market
                            conditions; that, however, if the various conditions cannot be
                            accomplished within the time specified and their offer is nevertheless
                            the most acceptable of those under consideration by the Government of
                            Haiti, their offer may be provisionally accepted with the expectation
                            that it will be renewed by the bankers when all the conditions have been
                            complied with, unless there should be a substantial change in conditions
                            materially affecting, in their opinion, the marketability of the
                            bonds.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
