<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-06-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="300" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d300">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">741.9411/141½</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of a Conversation between the Secretary
                                of State and the Japanese Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shidehara</hi>), <hi rend="italic">June 30, 1921</hi></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1921-06-30">June 30, 1921</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>The Japanese Ambassador stated that he had called merely to present a
                            proposed statement which he desired to make public, with respect to the
                            renewal of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance, in case the Secretary had no
                            objection; that his Government had instructed him not to publish it if
                            there was objection. The Ambassador then handed the attached statement
                            to the Secretary who read it. The Secretary said that he would not
                            undertake to interpose any objection to the publication of the
                            statement; he would like to have it clearly understood that the
                            statement if made public by the Ambassador was to be made exclusively on
                            his own responsibility and not with the concurrence of this Government;
                            this Government did not desire to make any statement regarding the
                            publication or to assume any responsibility whatever in the matter. With
                            this understanding the Secretary had no objection.</p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Statement by the Japanese Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shidehara</hi>)<note n="55" xml:id="d300fn55">The
                                    statement appeared in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>
                                    of July 4, 1921.</note></head>
                            <p>Negotiations looking to the renewal of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance
                                have not yet begun. In the meantime, a campaign seems to be actively
                                at work misrepresenting the possible effect of the Alliance upon the
                                United States. By no stretch of the imagination can it be honestly
                                stated that the Alliance was ever designed or remotely intended as
                                an instrument of hostility or even defense against the United
                                States.</p>
                            <p>The Anglo-Japanese Alliance, in its history for nearly twenty years,
                                has twice been renewed. In each case, the fundamental policy
                                underlying it has remained unchanged. It aims permanently to
                                preserve and to consolidate the general peace of the Far East. The
                                original Agreement of 1902, in line with that policy, was calculated
                                    <pb facs="0413" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/> to localize any war
                                which might be forced upon either Contracting Party in defense of
                                its defined interests or vital security. It was made when China was
                                under menace of foreign aggression; and the United States, showing
                                the utmost friendliness towards both parties to the Alliance, viewed
                                the compact with sympathy and approval.</p>
                            <p>In 1905, when the Alliance was renewed and revised to meet the
                                changed conditions that followed the Russo-Japanese war, no thought
                                occurred to the statesmen of either country that the United States
                                might possibly become a potential enemy of either, and for that
                                reason, and that alone, no provision was inserted taking so remote a
                                contingency into consideration.</p>
                            <p>The Alliance was again revised in 1911, and Article IV of that
                                Agreement contains the following provision: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Should either High Contracting Party conclude a treaty of
                                        general arbitration with a third Power, it is agreed that
                                        nothing in this Agreement shall entail upon such Contracting
                                        Party an obligation to go to war with the Power with whom
                                        such treaty of arbitration is in force.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>This provision, in its relation to the United States, has often been
                                made the subject of conflicting interpretations. To a practical
                                mind, however, the circumstances which led up to its inclusion
                                should at once serve to remove all doubt regarding its significance.
                                The idea of revising the Alliance in 1911 was conceived primarily
                                with the object of facilitating the negotiations which were known to
                                be then in progress between London and Washington for the conclusion
                                of a general arbitration treaty. Neither Japan nor Great Britain has
                                ever contemplated, under the Alliance, any <hi rend="italic">casus
                                    foederis</hi> prejudicial or inimical to the interests of the
                                United States; and any plan designed to remove the possibility of an
                                armed conflict between the United States and Great Britain was of
                                course agreeable to Japan. It was in pursuance of this policy that
                                the quoted provision of Article IV was adopted.</p>
                            <p>The same policy inspires Japan as strongly today as ever before. It
                                has not, in any degree, been affected by the fact that the
                                Anglo-American general arbitration treaty<note n="56" xml:id="d300fn56">Signed Aug. 3, 1911; for text, see S. Doc. 98,
                                    62d Cong., 1st sess., p. 47.</note> failed to secure the
                                approval of the United States Senate. Nor is it practically
                                necessary to carry on the legal analysis of the question as to
                                whether the Peace Commission Treaty, signed and ratified by the
                                United States and Great Britain in 1914,<note n="57" xml:id="d300fn57"><ref target="frus1914#pg_304"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1914, p.
                                    304</ref>.</note> should be construed as a general arbitration
                                treaty within the meaning of Article IV of the Anglo-Japanese
                                Agreement. For, apart from that question, it was already well
                                understood at the <pb facs="0414" n="318" xml:id="pg_318"/> time of
                                negotiating the existing Agreement that the Alliance should in no
                                case be directed against the United States.</p>
                            <p>In explanation of Japan’s attitude, Count Uchida, the Japanese
                                Foreign Minister, made the following statement to the Budget
                                Committee of the Japanese House of Representatives on February 4,
                                1921.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“As far as I understand, when Article 4 of the treaty
                                    (Anglo-Japanese Alliance) was inserted, the United States was
                                    specifically in mind, and therefore, as a practical matter, the
                                    question whether the general arbitration treaty mentioned in
                                    Article 4 has been ratified by the United States Senate or not
                                    makes no particular difference. In other words, looking at the
                                    matter from a broad point of view, we can safely say that
                                    already at the time of the conclusion of the treaty
                                    (Anglo-Japanese Alliance) it was understood that there should be
                                    no application of this treaty to the United States.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>Japan is naturally anxious to strengthen the ties of friendship and
                                loyal co-operation between herself and the British Empire, which she
                                regards as of the utmost importance to the stability of the Far
                                East. At the same time, it is the firm and fixed determination of
                                Japan to permit nothing to hamper her traditional relations of good
                                will and good understanding with the United States. She is satisfied
                                that these two affiliations are in no way incompatible, but, on the
                                contrary, complementary and even essential to each other.</p>
                            <p>Charges have sometimes been made that the Alliance tends to encourage
                                aggressive designs on the part of Japan in China. If this were the
                                case, it would be contrary to the preamble of the Agreement, which
                                provides for, <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The preservation of the common interests of all Powers in
                                        China by insuring the independence and integrity of the
                                        Chinese Empire and the principle of equal opportunities for
                                        the commerce and industry of all nations in China.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>Japan fully realizes that any such venture of aggression would be not
                                only hopeless of attainment but destructive of her own security and
                                welfare. She sincerely wishes for China an early achievement of
                                peace, unity and stable government. She desires to cultivate her
                                relations with that country along the path of mutual respect and
                                helpfulness. Her vast commercial interests alone, if for no other
                                consideration, point unmistakably to the wisdom of such a policy.
                                This is a basic principle of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance. In no
                                adverse direction has the Alliance ever exerted its influence.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>