<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-05-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="570" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d570">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">235.11 B 76/90</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Paraguay</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Mooney</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Asunción</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-05-09"><hi rend="italic">May 9,
                                1921</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received June 28.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 794</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In confirmation of cablegram of this
                            Legation, No. 19, dated May 8th at 12 o’clock, noon,<note n="7" xml:id="d570fn7">Not printed.</note> I have the honor to inform you
                            that Doctor William H. Bricker, alias William H. Moore, a criminal
                            fugitive from Pennsylvania, left Asunción on the 8th inst. for Buenos
                            Aires en route for the United States. He was in the custody of Mr. Fred
                            C. Voigt, an officer of the Philadelphia police Department, who, as a
                            matter of precaution, was accompanied by a Paraguayan officer to the
                            Argentine border, and will be accompanied by an Argentine officer from
                            there to Buenos Aires.</p>
                        <p>The criminal Bricker finally contributed to his own extradition in the
                            way of waiving further contest after the crumbling of a number of
                            preliminary defenses he sought to interpose. The extradition, which was
                            formally granted by the Paraguayan Court, was upon the application that
                            he be extradited to receive sentence under his conviction for abortion
                            in the Courts of Pennsylvania, and to answer to the charge of an
                            indictment for a second offense of the same nature, pending in the same
                            jurisdiction. No disposition was made of the application for his
                            extradition on the charge of perjury. This application is still pending
                            and the accused has refused to waive any defenses he may have hereto.
                            This Legation is of the opinion that, under the illiberal construction
                            controlling proceedings of a criminal and quasi-criminal nature,
                            perjury, so designated, is not an extraditable offense under the
                            Extradition Treaty between the United States and Paraguay.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Daniel F. Mooney</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>