<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Great Britain ( (Harvey) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1921v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1921-10-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1921-10-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-10-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-10-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="92"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d92">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867n.6363/9</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harvey</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-10-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 28, 1921</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received November 10.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 596</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>Sir: Referring to my telegram No. 862, of October 27, 2 [<hi rend="italic"
                    >5</hi>] p.m.,<note n="42" xml:id="d92fn42">Not printed.</note> in reference to
                    the representatives of the Standard Oil Company in Jerusalem, and their desire
                    to continue geological examinations, I have the honor to transmit herewith
                    copies of the full text of the Note referred to, together with a copy of my Note
                    to the Foreign Office, No. 189 of September 15.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Post Wheeler</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Counselor of Embassy</hi>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0194" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The American Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Harvey</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the British Secretary of State for Foreign
                            Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Curzon</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 189</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The American Ambassador presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Secretary
                        of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to refer to conversations
                        held in March and April, 1920, between Sir John Tilley, of the Foreign
                        Office, and Mr. Wright, Counselor of this Embassy; to a conversation between
                        Sir John Tilley, Mr. L. I. Thomas, of the Standard Oil Company of New York,
                        and Mr. Wright on March 29, 1920; and to a conference at the Colonial Office
                        on the 9th instant, kindly arranged by Mr. Lindsay of the Foreign Office, at
                        which were present Mr. Shuckburgh and Major Young of that office,<note
                            n="44" xml:id="d92fn44">The Colonial Office.</note> Mr. Thomas and Mr.
                        Wright; all relative to the desire of the Standard Oil Company of New York
                        that representatives of that Company now in Jerusalem be permitted to
                        continue geological examinations of the areas covered by their rights or
                        concessions, in Palestine, which examinations were commenced by the Company
                        prior to the outbreak of the war in 1914.</p>
                    <p>In accordance with telegraphic instructions just received from his
                        Government, Mr. Harvey now has the honour to reiterate this request, and in
                        so doing desires to state that it is the opinion of his Government that the
                        granting at this time of such permission could not be construed as
                        inconsistent with the principles which have been accepted by the British
                        Government regarding the development of the economic resources of mandated
                        regions. Furthermore, the exploration and examination desired could
                        apparently in no way compromise the future authorities of the countries
                        concerned, since it is to be clearly understood that the investigations
                        which it is desired to undertake would not be conducted with a view to
                        acquiring new claims or to strengthening old ones.</p>
                    <p>In this connection Mr. Harvey is happy to improve this opportunity to confirm
                        the statement made by Mr. Thomas and Mr. Wright during the aforementioned
                        conversation, to the effect that there would be no objection on the part of
                        the Government of the United States if privileges with respect to travel or
                        to such geological examination in Palestine, similar to those accorded to
                        nationals of the United States, should also be accorded to nationals of
                        other countries.</p>
                    <p>Accordingly, Mr. Thomas, who is in London for a short time only but who will
                        be compelled to leave within a few days on account of urgent business, holds
                        himself in entire readiness to cooperate with the authorities of His
                        Majesty’s Government and with the Embassy to such ends, and adds to the
                        request of the Department of State his earnest hope that an early decision
                        may be reached by His Majesty’s <pb facs="0195" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/>
                        Government, in view of the fact that the rainy season in Palestine commences
                        about December 1st, and that delay which might compel postponement of
                        operations until next spring would increase the inconvenience and expense
                        already incurred by the Company.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-09-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 15, 1921</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Curzon</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Ambassador</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Harvey</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-10-26">
                                <hi rend="italic">26 October, 1921</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. E. 11576/264/88</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: In your note No. 189 of the 15th.
                        ultimo, you enquired whether the representatives of the Standard Oil Company
                        in Jerusalem might be permitted to continue the geological examination,
                        already begun before the war, of certain areas covered by rights or
                        concessions in Palestine acquired by that Company.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>In reply I have the honour to state that informal permission will be
                            accorded to the representatives of the Standard Oil Company by the
                            Palestine Government, to conduct researches within the limits of the
                            areas over which the Company is known to claim concessionary rights with
                            the object of discovering whether oil in payable quantities exists in
                            these areas, on the strict understanding that such permission is granted
                            without prejudice to the question of the validity of the Standard Oil
                            Company’s claims, that no permission can be granted for the exploitation
                            of these areas until the Treaty of Peace with Turkey enters into force
                            and until the terms of the Mandate for Palestine are finally settled,
                            and on the condition that the Company will undertake, to furnish a full
                            and complete report of the result of their investigations as required by
                            the Palestine Government and that they will comply with any instructions
                            which may be given by the Palestine Government.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>I would wish to make it quite clear to Your Excellency, that while the
                            question of the validity of the Standard Oil Company’s claims to the
                            areas in Palestine remains unaffected, the fact of their existence has
                            been a determining factor with His Majesty’s Government and the
                            Palestine Government in acceding to the request of the Company, and that
                            no precedent is thereby established for the treatment of any future
                            applications of a like nature.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>I shall be glad to learn from you whether the Standard Oil Company
                            agree to undertake operations in the Palestine areas on the terms set
                            forth above, as well as the names of the persons to whom the work of
                            investigation is to be entrusted by the Company, in order that the
                            Palestine Government may be informed.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>(For Secretary of State)<lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lancelot Oliphant</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
