<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in Thailand</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-06-22T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-06-22T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recTdbwPhSPuOaeNu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-06-22T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-06-22T16:00:00-05:00" n="111"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793B.00/6–2251: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Thailand</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-06-22T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 22, 1951—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2075. For Turner<note n="1" xml:id="d111fn1">William Taylor Turner, Counselor of
                        Embassy in Bangkok.</note> from Rusk for urinfo only. Question of asylum for
                    Dalai Lama is under discussion with US Emb not <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> New Delhi if Dalai Lama decides leave Tibet. US prepared make
                    substantial effort effect arrangements for asylum Thailand which is Buddhist and
                    has historic relationship with Tibet.</p>
                <pb facs="0256" n="1714" xml:id="pg_1714"/>
                <p>On Jun 22 Thai Amb was informed US desire be useful making arrangements asylum
                    Dalai Lama Thailand if agreeable both parties. To this end I handed Thai Amb ltr
                    from Comite for a Free Asia, Inc. addressed to Secy which contained fol
                    substance:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The Comite has followed with sympathy flight of Dalai Lama and his brave but
                        unsupported resistance to demands and threats of Chi Commie Govt. His
                        continued silence since Peiping reported agreement May 23 between Peoples’
                        Central Republic and Tibetan local Govt is indicative his non-acceptance of
                        terms. It is our belief that Dalai Lama is both a symbol and potential
                        leader of Asian resistance to Communism. As such he has become religious and
                        polit refugee without suitable asylum.</p>
                    <p>“The Comite for a Free Asia desires make contribution provision of asylum but
                        of necessity limited to moral encouragement and some financial assistance.
                        Asylum in the US wld be far from ideal for it wld take him away from peoples
                        of Free Asia and from direct contact with the followers of Buddha. Of the
                        various Buddhist countries to which Dalai Lama might go Thailand combines
                        profound devotion to Buddha with proud record of independence and has taken
                        lead among Asian countries in resisting Communism. Moreover for centuries
                        Thais and Tibetans have been neighbors and allies. In such atmosphere of
                        common religion the Dalai Lama might feel at home.</p>
                    <p>[“]If Thai Govt wld extend asylum to Dalai Lama and entourage and wld proffer
                        him a suitable invitation to that effect the Comite for a Free Asia wld
                        underwrite whatever expenses might be involved therein.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Thai Amb is communicating this info to his Govt for action. [Rusk.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
