<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-09-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="201" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d201">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Rankin Files: Lot 66 D 84</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Republic of China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Rankin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Chief of the Military Assistance Advisory
                                Group, Formosa</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Chase</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Taipei</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-09-30">September 30,
                                1951</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear General Chase</hi>: At my meeting with the
                            Ministers of Foreign Affairs and Finance<note n="1" xml:id="d201fn1">Yen
                                Chia-kan.</note> last evening we discussed your communication of
                            September 17 to General Chou<note n="2" xml:id="d201fn2">Not
                                printed.</note> regarding military budgets and budgetary control. In
                            general, the two ministers were in full agreement with your
                            recommendations. However, they raised the following points: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The new plan involves at least one important change which is a
                                    matter of high policy: the proposed transfer of authority over
                                    budgetary matters from the Chief of Staff to the Minister of
                                    National Defense (your paragraph 4). The ministers personally
                                    favored such action. However, they remarked that the Minister of
                                    National Defense<note n="3" xml:id="d201fn3">Kuo
                                        Chi-chiao.</note> himself preferred not to take a position
                                    in this matter, apparently to avoid creating the impression that
                                    he was seeking more power, and that a decision of a higher level
                                    than General Chou’s was required in any case. They queried me as
                                    to what General Chou’s reaction was to this proposal in his
                                    discussions with you. I replied that I did not know in detail
                                    but understood that he had raised no objection.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>A somewhat less significant change but nevertheless one of
                                    considerable importance organizationally is the proposal to
                                    divide the military establishment into about five groups for
                                    budgetary and accounting purposes (your paragraph 3), according
                                    to the two ministers. Again, they are inclined to favor your
                                    recommendation. It was pointed out, however, that this might
                                    bring up several old issues such as the status of the Combined
                                    Service Forces, created several years ago on American
                                    recommendation to support all other branches but in practice
                                    today serving only the Army. They remarked that the
                                    Generalissimo had long favored more or less parallel treatment
                                    for the Air Force and Navy, but that opposition from these
                                    services had prevented its realization. The ministers indicated
                                    that similar opposition to a system of combined budgetary
                                    control might be expected. However, they advanced these points
                                    by way of explanation and not because of any objection to the
                                    new plan on their part.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The ministers commented on the use of the word “supervise” in
                                    your paragraph 13<hi rend="italic">a</hi>. They remarked that
                                    the nearest Chinese equivalent is stronger than the English in
                                    meaning, and questioned <pb facs="0357" n="1815" xml:id="pg_1815"/> whether we intend to give direct
                                    administrative responsibility to American officers in the
                                    Chinese military establishment. I said that I thought not and
                                    that perhaps the expression “advise in” might be substituted for
                                    “supervise”. I should appreciate having your opinion on this
                                    point.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The Finance Minister expressed the urgent hope that, whatever
                                    may be decided as to your recommendations, nothing should be
                                    permitted to delay actual work on the 1952 military
                                    budget.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>I gathered that the two ministers were fundamentally very much in favor
                            of your recommendations and are only concerned lest we should not be
                            willing to push them enough to overcome possible opposition among the
                            military. In this connection, I assured them that we felt strongly as to
                            the principles involved, although we were ready to discuss details so as
                            to facilitate the implementation of the recommendations in the simplest
                            and most expeditious manner possible.</p>
                        <p>It is understood that General Chou will not reply in writing to your
                            September 17 communication, in view of the considerations mentioned
                            above. After reading the present letter and discussing the points raised
                            with anyone who you think might have further ideas to contribute, I
                            suggest that we get together to consider whether a more formal
                            communication to the Chinese Government on the same subject may be in
                            order.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>K. L. <hi rend="smallcaps">Rankin</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>