<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-24T18:21:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-24T18:21:00-05:00" n="217" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d217">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">601.9193/10–1851: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Embassy in India</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-24T18:21:00-05:00">October
                                    24, 1951—6:21 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>874. Urtel 1397 Oct 18.<note n="1" xml:id="d217fn1">The reference
                                telegram noted that it might be possible to talk with Panikkar, who
                                was in New Delhi, and requested guidance from the Department,
                                particularly the Department’s comments on the Chinese charge that
                                Chinese nationals were under arrest in the Philippines
                                (601.9193/10–1851).</note> In opinion Dept you shld make effort talk
                            with Pannikar preferably in presence Bajpai or other high official re
                            former’s reports subj treatment US Natls Commie China. Dept aware
                            Pannikar’s temperament, pol inclinations and possibility he may not
                            return Peiping but of opinion if possible case these Amers shld be
                            directly discussed with him, since he appears regard Chi Commies as
                            having a responsible Govt. Such interview wld be first opportunity Amer
                            official obtain first-hand account and ask questions. You shld of course
                            make request for conversations through <gloss target="#t_MEA1">MEA</gloss>. If not possible talk Pannikar you shld make effort
                            talk Bajpai re Pannikar’s reports.</p>
                        <p>In such conversations stress shld not be placed primarily on fact
                            imprisonment (as this may elicit reply China is sovereign state, etc.),
                            but more particularly on conditions detention, which in many cases
                            inhumane and contrary basic and well-recognized rights re treatment
                            foreigners, including indefinite detention without trial or even notice
                            of charges, holding incommunicado, denial access legal counsel. You shld
                            mention this Govt’s great anxiety re these Amers heightened by approach
                            winter.</p>
                        <p>Re ur request comment, as far as Dept is informed only small nr Chi have
                            been arrested Phils and those arrests have been for violation Phil laws,
                            such as illegal entry Phils, overstaying visitor’s visas, smuggling, and
                            black market operations. Dept not aware any deviation from generally
                            accepted standards treatment foreigners present in case arrests
                            Phils.</p>
                        <p>Any comment Pannikar or Bajpai may make re representations Pannikar or
                            other fon dipls Peiping to Commies, Commies’ reactions, Pannikar’s
                            estimate outcome representations wld be interest Dept.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>