<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs ( (Rusk) ) to the
                    Director, Far East Program Division, Economic Cooperation Administration (
                    (Griffin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-05-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjP7nK0m2r7YYXK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recXspHUMSpZmRAGk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture">Agricultural reform</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-05-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="84"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">894A.00–R/5–951</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director, Far East Program Division,
                        Economic Cooperation Administration</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Griffin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-05-09">May 9,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Allen</hi>: On May 3 Mr. Foster<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d84fn1">William C. Foster, Administrator, Economic Cooperation
                        Administration.</note> discussed with Mr. Acheson, among other subjects, the
                    possible need of some modification in the general policy framework within which
                    the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission in Formosa should conduct its
                    relations with the Chinese Government. He expressed the view that circumstances
                    now justify statement of a more <pb facs="0207" n="1665" xml:id="pg_1665"/>
                    forceful policy than that contained in my letter of March 19 to you. There, our
                    policy is stated as being that “The <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission
                    should advise but should not give direction to the Chinese, overtly or tacitly,
                    in the conduct of the economic administration of the Island.” You have met since
                    then, with Mr. Merchant, and agreed, I understand, that it would be desirable
                    for the Department to provide the Economic Cooperation Administration
                    amplification of our intent in the above policy statement.</p>
                <p>The Department of State fully recognizes the importance that the <gloss
                        target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission on Formosa should exert its influence
                    vigorously and firmly, in the Economic Stabilization Board and elsewhere, for
                    the improvement of Chinese Government policies and practices in the broad fields
                    of agricultural reform, export and import controls, industrial rehabilitation
                    and in the basic field of fiscal administration. In general, the <gloss
                        target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission should attempt to achieve the proper
                    and effective use of Chinese revenues from all sources as well as the most
                    effective utilization of American economic aid. To this end the <gloss
                        target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission should, of course, be adequately
                    staffed, work closely with <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> and the Embassy
                    to insure consistent policies and the exercise of coordinated pressures, and
                    should continue to assign as observers on the Economic Stabilization Board
                    representatives qualified to provide sound technical and policy advice.</p>
                <p>An important and relevant problem arises from Chinese military expenditures on
                    Formosa. It is probably inevitable that the military establishment must continue
                    to impose a heavy burden on the national budget. It is not necessary, however,
                    that its charges on Formosan resources be so unpredictable, arbitrary, and
                    irresponsible, in terms of the social and economic consequences they produce, as
                    to render sound economic planning almost, if not completely, impossible. I have
                    requested Mr. Cabot to give careful and urgent consideration to the feasibility
                    of working out arrangements, perhaps as a condition for the delivery of United
                    States military assistance, for bringing under some kind of rational control the
                    military expenditures of the Chinese National Government. If we can work out and
                    then obtain the cooperation of the Chinese National Government in such
                    arrangements, they would contribute basically to the prospects for the genuine
                    and enduring results which <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> is seeking in the
                    economic field. I am certain that Mr. Cabot will, in the near future be inviting
                    the cooperation of the Economic Cooperation Administration as well as that of
                    the Department of Defense in his study of this problem.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Rusk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
