<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="1062" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1062">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">890D.01/5–2345</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the
                                Office of Near Eastern and African Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-24">May 24, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                                <cell>Mr. J. Balfour, British Minister</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Merriam<note n="38" xml:id="d1062fn38">Gordon P. Merriam,
                                        Chief of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Henderson</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Mr. Balfour of the British Embassy left the attached <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi><note n="39" xml:id="d1062fn39">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> with me today. After glancing
                            at it I told him that we had already asked Caffery if in his opinion any
                            useful purpose would be served by the holding of discussions in Paris,
                            and that we would let him know the nature of Caffery’s reply.</p>
                        <p>I also told him in confidence that we were considering the advisability
                            of sending a strong note to the French Government on the subject of
                            French policy in Syria and Lebanon and outlined to him what we had in
                            mind. He was very much interested and said that he would appreciate it
                            if we would let him know the nature of any action which we might decide
                            to take.</p>
                        <p>He asked me if the United States opposed the granting of bases by the
                            Levant States to France. I said that I was not in a position to give an
                            answer to that question at the present time; that at present we were
                            confining our representations to France to the tactics which France
                            appeared to be employing rather than to French objectives. I doubted
                            that we would oppose the free granting by Syria and Lebanon of bases to
                            France, but I could make no positive statement on the subject.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Loy</hi> W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>