<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-24T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-24T16:00:00-05:00" n="1065" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1065">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">890E.01/5–2445: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister to Syria and Lebanon</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wadsworth</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Beirut</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-24T23:00:00+02:00">May 24,
                                    1945—11 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received May 24—5 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>152. 1. Syrian MinFonAff today informed Satterthwaite that Govt had
                            received from Beynet acknowledgment of Syrian reply to his <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> saying in view of prevailing
                            situation he had referred it to his Govt.</p>
                        <pb facs="1111" n="1099" xml:id="pg_1099"/>
                        <p>2. Lebanese MinFonAff repeated to me substantially as outlined in my 145,
                            May 21, his views on how escape from Franco-Levant impasse might be
                            found. He felt situation was deteriorating in Syria and tho now well in
                            hand in Lebanon, Lebanese would react sympathetically [if] serious
                            Franco-Syrian clashes should occur. He then diagnosed resulting problem
                            as requiring “combined palliative and direct treatment”.</p>
                        <p>The palliative he urged should be Allied statement that their troops
                            would be progressively withdrawn and <hi rend="italic">Troupes
                                Spéciales</hi> simultaneously progressively transferred to the
                            states implemented by exchanges of notes or <hi rend="italic">modus
                                vivendi</hi> defining status of Allied troops during such
                            transitional period. As direct treatment he was now prepared to offer
                            draft treaty proposals to three great powers and France; he had
                            completed first drafts and would go over them this week-end with Syrian
                            MinFonAff.</p>
                        <p>Pharaon then said he had already mentioned possibility of such direct <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> to Brit and Soviet Ministers; with me he
                            wished to go further on strictly personal plane should I so prefer; as I
                            had been helpful in obtaining text of our Norwegian treaty<note n="41" xml:id="d1065fn41">Treaty of friendship, commerce and consular
                                rights, and additional article, signed at Washington June 5, 1928,
                                and February 25, 1929, respectively, <ref target="frus1928v03#pg_646">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 646</ref>. Two copies of the
                                treaty were transmitted to the Minister in Syria and Lebanon in
                                instruction 306, February 2, 1945, not printed.</note> as suggestive
                            model he would like me to read and if possible comment on his drafts; in
                            their preparation he had consulted several other texts as well.</p>
                        <p>I agreed but can readily avoid offering any comment even of personal
                            nature should you so prefer. It was clear too that he would particularly
                            welcome some encouragement from you as to the wisdom and timeliness of
                            his suggested <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi>. He would of course find
                            it very awkward to be rebuffed in all quarters.</p>
                        <p>3. I found of interest also in this general connection comment made to me
                            2 days earlier by Gen Paget substantially as follows: “International
                            cooperation is needed to solve this problem; I can’t, even should I
                            persuade Beynet to agree to necessity for completing arming of <hi rend="italic">gendarmerie</hi>. World opinion as I see it can’t
                            accept the terms Beynet has offered; we couldn’t for example force Egypt
                            to give us bases; there they could be had only by mutual agreement based
                            on mutual interest. Why should the French be permitted to force these
                            countries to give them; besides this is no place strategically speaking
                            from which to protect French lines of communication.”</p>
                        <p>Similarly Gen Pilleau<note n="42" xml:id="d1065fn42">Maj. Gen. Gerald A.
                                Pilleau, Acting Commander of the British Ninth Army (Levant).</note>
                            commented to me yesterday evening that solution of this problem would
                            seem to lie only on highest international plane, e.g. by Big Three or
                            Anglo-American decision (preferably <pb facs="1112" n="1100" xml:id="pg_1100"/> with French participating and concurring) that
                            all Allied troops will leave progressively.</p>
                        <p>Such a decision he suggested might probably best be implemented by
                            General Alexander as Allied CinCMed<note n="43" xml:id="d1065fn43">Field
                                Marshal Sir Harold R. L. G. Alexander, Supreme Allied Commander,
                                Mediterranean Theater.</note> responsible to Combined Chiefs of
                            Staff.</p>
                        <p>Rptd Paris as 45, sent Dept as 152, paraphrases to Arab capitals.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wadsworth</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>