<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="1288" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1288">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.90J/4–1645</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary
                                    of State</gloss> to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                            </hi><note n="8" xml:id="d1288fn8">President Truman on May 1 verbally
                                informed the Acting Secretary of his approval of this
                                memorandum.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-01">May 1,
                                1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Suggested Establishment of Diplomatic Relations
                            with the Yemen</p>
                        <p>Mr. Clark, American Consul in Aden, acting on instructions from the
                            Department, recently made a visit to the Imam (King) of the Yemen at
                            Sanaa. Mr. Clark has reported that the Imam and the Royal Princes
                            extended to him courtesies and facilities not hitherto extended to any
                            foreigner.</p>
                        <p>In the course of their conversations, the Yemeni authorities stated that
                            the Yemen wished to enter into a treaty of friendship and commerce with
                            the United States, that it desired to employ American technicians to aid
                            in development plans, and that it would welcome economic and cultural
                            assistance from the United States. The Yemeni authorities added that
                            they feel that the United States is the only country on which they can
                            rely for disinterested help. The Imam is particularly interested in
                            securing medical supplies and the services of an American doctor without
                            delay.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Clark repeats unverified reports of the existence in the Yemen of
                            rich deposits of various minerals including petroleum.</p>
                        <p>The Yemen is one of the few independent countries of the world with which
                            the United States has no diplomatic relations. In view of American
                            interest in near-by countries such as Saudi Arabia and Ethiopia, and
                            also in view of possible future developments in the <pb facs="1327" n="1315" xml:id="pg_1315"/> Yemen, it is the Department’s belief
                            that the United States should indicate to the Imam its readiness to
                            extend formal recognition to the Government of the Imam (already in
                            treaty relations with the British and with Saudi Arabia) and to
                            establish a channel for the exchange of diplomatic correspondence. This
                            measure, it is believed, should precede any decision on Yemeni requests
                            for assistance.</p>
                        <p>As soon as recognition has been extended to the Government of the Yemen,
                            an exchange of notes could provide reciprocal, unconditional,
                            most-favored nation treatment pending negotiation of a formal treaty of
                            commerce and navigation.</p>
                        <p>The Department would appreciate an expression of your views on the
                            suggested establishment of relations with the Yemen. In the event you
                            approve its suggestion, the Department will be glad to take the steps
                            necessary to accomplish that end.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>