<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Egypt ( (Tuck) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="18"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d18">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.50/5–1245: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Tuck</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-12">May 12,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received May 24—8 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–245. From Hoskins.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>“1. I recommend that as a step in formulating an American postwar economic
                        policy in the Middle East, the United States Government <pb facs="0052"
                            n="40" xml:id="pg_40"/> hold a regional conference in this area as soon
                        as practicable. Such a conference under the sponsorship of the State
                        Department could consider local as well as various regional problems. It
                        would be expected to come to specific decisions and make recommendations for
                        consideration by appropriate authorities in the development of plans for
                        trade and general economic matters. Changing conditions due to progress of
                        war and consequent likelihood of early improvement in supplies and shipping
                        make decisions on many points of increasing urgency. Such a conference would
                        also have a sound psychological effect throughout this area as indicative of
                        America’s continued interest in the Middle East. As the Department may
                        recall, the dissolution of AEMME and Landis’<note n="12" xml:id="d18fn12"
                            >Mr. James M. Landis, who left his position as Director of the American
                            Economic Mission in the Middle East on January 3, 1945. In telegram 29,
                            January 2, 1945, 9 p.m., to the Minister in Egypt, the Department
                            stated: “In view of imminent departure of Landis and present unresolved
                            status of relationship of economic personnel at Cairo, you are hereby
                            instructed as Senior Diplomatic Representative in Egypt to take charge
                            of all American civilian personnel of AEMME in Egypt and to assume the
                            responsibility of broad local direction and overall general coordination
                            of their activities to the end that American participation in MESC and
                            other appropriate American economic functions may be carried on without
                            interruption.” (123-Tuck S. Pinkney)</note> press release on his
                        departure were interpreted by many elements in the area as a first American
                        step toward another period of economic isolationism.</item>
                    <item>“2. British recognized necessity for such a meeting on their side and
                        recently held near Cairo an economic conference attended by their chief
                        diplomatic and economic representatives throughout the area, as well as by
                        several officials sent especially out from London. I understand this
                        conference was considered to have been worth the expense and effort
                        involved. The conference was freely publicized after the event as
                        exemplified in article and photograph from local paper being sent by letter
                        to Fred Winant. Public reaction appears to have been excellent since it
                        emphasized to the people of the Middle East the keen and continued economic
                        interest of the British.</item>
                    <item>“3. I have discussed the holding of such an economic conference informally
                        with several Ministers in the area including Tuck and Wadsworth,<note n="13"
                            xml:id="d18fn13">George Wadsworth, Minister to Syria and Lebanon.</note>
                        as well as with Henderson<note n="14" xml:id="d18fn14">Loy W. Henderson, who
                            was appointed Director of the Office of Near Eastern and African Affairs
                            on April 17, 1945. Previously, he had been Minister to Iraq.</note>
                        before his departure and all have expressed their keen interest and
                        approval. While attending such a conference, no official would be more than
                        a few hours’ flying time away from his post.</item>
                    <item>“4. It is I believe important to hold such a conference at the earliest
                        possible date. Its convening should not be postponed for the ‘perfect’
                        moment which in actual fact will never occur since no movement chosen is
                        likely to be equally satisfactory to everyone involved. At the same time the
                        Department may feel it necessary to delay such a <pb facs="0053" n="41"
                            xml:id="pg_41"/> conference until the new heads of missions to several
                        of the countries in this area have arrived at their posts.</item>
                    <item>“5. I suggest that this, the first conference of its kind, be held in
                        Cairo as the most convenient post to a majority of the proposed delegates.
                        Similar conferences which might be arranged in the future could be held in
                        rotation at other convenient posts in the area. Minister Tuck has stated
                        that he will be glad to act as host to the delegates if it is decided that
                        Cairo is to be the first place of meeting.</item>
                    <item>“6. Some items which might usefully be considered by the conference are: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The pressing problem of dollar exchange which is universal
                                throughout the area.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Policy and plans regarding disposals of surplus materials and
                                military installations.<note n="15" xml:id="d18fn15">For
                                    documentation on this subject, see <ref target="#pg_82">pp.
                                        82</ref> ff.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The size, type and functions of American Government economic
                                organization needed in the Middle East.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Problems dealing with the sound promotion of American trade with
                                the Middle East, both imports and exports, including such problems
                                as our attitude toward the operation of import licensing in the
                                several countries.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                            <item>American attitude toward continuation of MESC.<note n="16"
                                    xml:id="d18fn16">For documentation on this subject, see <ref
                                        target="#pg_85">pp. 85</ref> ff.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Our economic relations with Pan-Arab Union.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                            <item>American petroleum problems in the area.<note n="17"
                                    xml:id="d18fn17">For documentation on this subject, see <ref
                                        target="#pg_49">pp. 49</ref> ff.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Civil air matters<note n="18" xml:id="d18fn18">For documentation
                                    on this subject, see <ref target="#pg_64">pp. 64</ref>
                                    ff.</note> including such items as sales of planes, landing
                                rights, etc.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>“7. It would be most desirable if the Merriam-Winant paper on Middle East
                        economic policy<note n="19" xml:id="d18fn19">See Report by the Coordinating
                            Committee, May 2, and footnote, <ref target="#pg_5">p. 5</ref>.</note>
                        could be presented to the conference as this would be the ideal place to
                        bring it before those people who are responsible for its
                        implementation.</item>
                    <item>“8. To insure greatest usefulness of conference, several representatives
                        should come out from Washington. Since it would be the first of its kind, I
                        hope Mr. Clayton can attend and serve as Chairman. I suggest that the newly
                        appointed deputy director of NEA<note n="20" xml:id="d18fn20">Presumably,
                            reference is, to newly appointed Director of the Office of Near Eastern
                            and African Affairs, Loy W. Henderson.</note> attend as well as at least
                        two other officers from the Department such for example as Taft,<note n="21"
                            xml:id="d18fn21">Charles P. Taft, Director of the Office of
                            Transportation and Communications.</note> Winant, Merriam or Allen, or
                        any other Department officers working in this field. FEA and/or Department
                        of Commerce also might wish to send delegates. Delegates from Middle East
                        should include the chief of each mission and the senior economic personnel
                        attached to his staff, as well as principal FEA representatives in the field
                        offices. From Egypt we would have all senior economic <pb facs="0054" n="42"
                            xml:id="pg_42"/> representatives including the Petroleum Attachés, Civil
                        Air Attaché, Treasury Representative, Principal FEA Representative, War
                        Shipping Administration Representative, Commanding General of AMET<note
                            n="22" xml:id="d18fn22">Africa-Middle East Theater.</note> or an Army
                        economic specialist. OWI<note n="23" xml:id="d18fn23">Office of War
                            Information.</note> representative, who could be helpful in obtaining
                        such publicity for the conference as might seem advisable, would also be
                        invited to attend.</item>
                    <item>“9. Although Turkey is not included within the framework of the unified
                        Middle East economic organization, it does have a variety of problems in
                        common with other countries of the area which will be represented at the
                        conference. It is suggested therefore that representatives from the American
                        Embassy in Ankara be invited to attend, and we would appreciate your
                        decision on this point.</item>
                    <item>“10. Agenda and arrangements for conference can be made by staff here
                        which also can serve as secretariat. I believe small auditorium of American
                        University can be obtained for official meetings.</item>
                    <item>“11. If this project is approved in principle, detailed plans will be
                        prepared in accordance with any departmental suggestions or instructions you
                        may give. I shall appreciate being advised of the Department’s approval for
                        holding such a conference as well as its suggestion of the earliest
                        practical date at which the Department believes the conference can be held.
                        Mr. Tuck suggests it be held not earlier than September or
                        October.[”]</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tuck</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
