<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Near Eastern and
                        African Affairs (
                        Henderson
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State
                    
                    
                        Attached to this memorandum and to the memorandum to President Truman,
                                infra, is a memorandum of November 17, 1945,
                            by the Director of the Office of Near Eastern and African Affairs
                            (Henderson) to the Under Secretary of State (Acheson) which stated:
                                
                                “You will recall that the Secretary was disturbed by recent
                                    telegrams from Athens concerning the deteriorating conditions in
                                    Greece and by the indication that General Morgan intended to
                                    recommend to the British Foreign Office that this Government be
                                    requested to share British responsibilities in Greece—by which
                                    he obviously meant military assistance.
                                In view of the urgency of the situation and the possibility that
                                    Mr. Attlee might bring up the subject of Greece with the
                                    President over the weekend, the attached memoranda were prepared
                                    and given to the Secretary late Saturday afternoon November 10
                                    without an opportunity of sending them through your office.”</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d228</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">228</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-11-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-10T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="228" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d228">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/11–1045</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Near Eastern and
                        African Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="13" xml:id="d228fn13">
                        <p>Attached to this memorandum and to the memorandum to President Truman,
                                <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>, is a memorandum of November 17, 1945,
                            by the Director of the Office of Near Eastern and African Affairs
                            (Henderson) to the Under Secretary of State (Acheson) which stated:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“You will recall that the Secretary was disturbed by recent
                                    telegrams from Athens concerning the deteriorating conditions in
                                    Greece and by the indication that General Morgan intended to
                                    recommend to the British Foreign Office that this Government be
                                    requested to share British responsibilities in Greece—by which
                                    he obviously meant military assistance.</p>
                                <p>In view of the urgency of the situation and the possibility that
                                    Mr. Attlee might bring up the subject of Greece with the
                                    President over the weekend, the attached memoranda were prepared
                                    and given to the Secretary late Saturday afternoon November 10
                                    without an opportunity of sending them through your office.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-10">November 10,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Deteriorating Conditions in Greece and Proposed U.S.
                    Action</p>
                <p>Present conditions in Greece are so alarming that British military authorities in
                    the theatre have recommended to London that the United States Government be
                    requested to “share British responsibility in Greece.”<note n="14" xml:id="d228fn14">See telegrams 4015, November 2, 10 a.m., and 4042,
                        November 4, 1 p.m., from Caserta, <ref target="#pg_251">pp. 251</ref> and
                            <ref target="#pg_253">253</ref>, respectively.</note> It is not known
                    how the British Foreign Office has reacted to these recommendations, but it is
                    possible that Prime Minister Attlee may bring up the question of Greece with the
                    President during his current visit. Although it is considered undesirable to
                    reverse our policy of undertaking no military responsibility in Greece, the
                    situation seems critical enough to justify active steps on our part to improve
                    conditions. If the economic situation there continues to worsen, it may
                    seriously prejudice the successful holding of the <pb facs="0276" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/> forthcoming elections, which this Government is committed
                    to observe.<note n="15" xml:id="d228fn15">For documentation on the decision of
                        the United States to participate in the supervision of elections in Greece,
                        see <ref target="#pg_98">pp. 98</ref> ff.</note> The present situation also
                    jeopardizes the chances of long run economic recovery in Greece which the United
                    States is trying to promote through UNRRA and other assistance. A weak and
                    chaotic Greece is a constant invitation to its already unfriendly neighbors on
                    the north to take aggressive action and constitutes a menace to international
                    peace and security.</p>
                <p>Since the failure in August of economic stabilization measures undertaken by Vice
                    Premier Varvaressos, the value of the drachma has continued to drop, prices have
                    risen rapidly, government expenditures have continued at a high level and
                    receipts to cover these expenditures have been entirely inadequate. The recovery
                    of industrial production has been extremely slow, the export and import trade
                    and the flow of remittances are practically at a standstill, and there is
                    wide-spread unemployment. The UNRRA program is feeding, clothing and helping to
                    provide shelter to the people of Greece, but under the conditions outlined
                    above, it cannot start them on the road to the self-sufficiency which they must
                    have achieved when UNRRA operations will cease, as scheduled, approximately one
                    year hence. Loans and other assistance would probably also have only a temporary
                    palliative effect, and without ultimate recovery in sight, the prospects of
                    repayment are obviously poor.</p>
                <p>It is the Department’s conviction that the following measures must be vigorously
                    undertaken in Greece if the present economic deterioration is to be halted and
                    the country started on the road to recovery: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Rigid price and wage control, the latter after adjustment has been
                            made to the increased cost of living.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Monetary controls, following a realistic revaluation of the
                            drachma.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>More effective and carefully supervised distribution of UNRRA supplies
                            in close cooperation with UNRRA officials, including rationing where
                            required. Reexamination of the present price policy for relief
                            goods.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Stringent taxation to increase government revenue.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>Review of government activities to eliminate all but essential
                            expenditures, especially in the civil services.</item>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>Revamping of the civil service to handle wisely and efficiently
                            present Greek economic problems with a minimum of personnel.</item>
                        <label>(7)</label>
                        <item>Positive action by the Greek Government to restore agricultural and
                            industrial production by insuring the provision of necessary raw
                            materials and the cooperation of management and labor.</item>
                        <label>(8)</label>
                        <item>A clear definition by the Greek Government of commodity fields in
                            which the private importing trade may again begin to operate.</item>
                        <pb facs="0277" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/>
                        <label>(9)</label>
                        <item>Direct encouragement to export trade after a revaluation of the
                            drachma again makes the revival of exports possible.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>It is clear in the present situation that we must determine either to abandon
                    Greece entirely to work out its own economic salvation without the assistance of
                    the United States or that we must insist on internal economic reforms in Greece.
                    This is essential if the assistance which the United States is now providing
                    through UNRRA or may provide through credits is to have any long run benefit and
                    if it is to come to an end in a reasonable period with Greece any better off
                    than it is today. I hope you agree that it should be the policy of the United
                    States to follow the second alternative. Some British officials suggest that
                    such a policy would entail active intervention, including the possible use of
                    United States military forces in Greece, but it is our belief that this is not
                    required. The Department suggests on the other hand that the United States in
                    concert with the United Kingdom and, possibly France make it clear that further
                    assistance to Greece is conditional on the enforcement by the Greek Government
                    of measures along the lines of those suggested above.</p>
                <p>It is encouraging that the newly formed Canellopoulos Government has already
                    expressed its intention of putting many of these measures into effect. Since the
                    beginning of 1945, however, no Greek Government, whether for reasons of its
                    political representation or other causes, has been able to enforce the rigid
                    kind of economic measures which are essential to Greek recovery. While it is
                    hoped that the present government will be more successful, fear of repercussions
                    in the coming elections and resistance of powerful groups which brought earlier
                    programs to ruin make the outcome doubtful. It appears, therefore, that some
                    measure of responsibility and firmness must come from outside Greece and it is
                    thought that making known the existence of this source of pressure might provide
                    the present government with an added bulwark in embarking on the essential
                    economic program which will inevitably be unpalatable to influential groups in
                    Greece.</p>
                <p>I suggest, therefore, that a note covering the four points outlined in the
                    attached memorandum for the President<note n="16" xml:id="d228fn16">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> be presented to the Greek Government by
                    the United States and at the same time be released to the press. It is
                    desirable, I believe, that such a note be presented in concert with some similar
                    communication from the United Kingdom, and perhaps other governments. If you
                    approve, the attached memorandum will be transmitted to the President.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Loy</hi> W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
