<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chargé in Iraq (
                        Moreland
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State
                    
                    The Department repeated the substance of this
                        telegram to London in telegram 3754, May 12, 1945, 6 p.m., with an
                        instruction that the appropriate British authorities should be asked “when a
                        final reply may be expected to Department’s April 18 note … pointing out
                        that we consider the matter to be of an urgent nature.”
                        (711.90G27/5–845)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d34</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">34</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-05-08T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-05-08T08:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-08T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-08T08:00:00-05:00" n="34" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.90G27/5–845: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Iraq</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Moreland</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="17" xml:id="d34fn17">The Department repeated the substance of this
                        telegram to London in telegram 3754, May 12, 1945, 6 p.m., with an
                        instruction that the appropriate British authorities should be asked “when a
                        final reply may be expected to Department’s April 18 note … pointing out
                        that we consider the matter to be of an urgent nature.”
                        (711.90G27/5–845)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Baghdad</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-08T16:00:00+03:00">May 8, 1945—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received May 8—2:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>180. From Curren<note n="18" xml:id="d34fn18">Ralph B. Curren, Civil Air Attaché
                        in Egypt; assigned concurrently to Missions in Ethiopia, Iran, Iraq,
                        Lebanon, Saudi Arabia, and Syria.</note> to Aviation Division. Despite
                    assurances given to the Department by Lord Halifax mentioned in your cable 164
                    May 3, 7 p.m.<note n="19" xml:id="d34fn19">Not printed (711.90G27/5–345); it
                        summarized the informal communication from Sir Ronald Campbell contained in
                        telegram 4239. April 26, from London, <ref target="#pg_67">p.
                        67</ref>.</note> there are many indications that British diplomatic
                    personnel in the Middle East countries and British Air Ministry representatives
                    have and still do exert every possible influence on local governments to refuse
                    American airlines fifth freedom privileges and delay acceptances of bilateral
                    air transport agreements. These governments are definitely unable to take action
                    regarding acceptance until sanctioned by British approval.</p>
                <p>My file in Cairo contains a copy of a letter dated early April addressed by
                    British Ambassador<note n="20" xml:id="d34fn20">To Egypt, Lord Killearn.</note>
                    to Minister for Foreign Affairs, received through highly confidential source,
                    definitely requesting <pb facs="0081" n="69" xml:id="pg_69"/> Egyptian
                    Government to take no action regarding acceptance of proposed American bilateral
                    air transport agreement until British Government reaches decision regarding
                    commercial aviation policy in Middle East. Will forward upon my return.</p>
                <p>Viscount Swinton<note n="21" xml:id="d34fn21">Chairman of the British delegation
                        to the Chicago International Aviation Conference.</note> during his visit to
                    Cairo personally officially warned Egyptians against fifth freedom privileges
                    and endeavored create fear regarding American aviation policy and ultimate
                    desires in Middle East. Recently British Air Ministry representative and
                    aviation and financial advisors to Egyptian Government were so incensed over our
                    satisfactory conclusion of MISR airplane transaction<note n="22" xml:id="d34fn22">In April, three surplus Douglas DC–2½ aircraft were sold by
                        the United States (Foreign Economic Administration) to the MISR
                        Airworks.</note> that they definitely told Roushdy Bey<note n="23" xml:id="d34fn23">Mohamed Roushdy, Director General of Civil Aviation in the
                        Egyptian Ministry of Defense.</note> that absolutely no dollar exchange
                    would be approved for maintenance by American personnel and that instead
                        BOAC<note n="24" xml:id="d34fn24">British Overseas Airways
                        Corporation.</note> would service and maintain.</p>
                <p>British Minister to Lebanon<note n="25" xml:id="d34fn25">Terence A. Shone.</note>
                    made definite statement last week to Wadsworth<note n="26" xml:id="d34fn26">George Wadsworth, Minister to Syria and Lebanon.</note> that British do not
                    want American airlines to operate in Middle East. Camille Chamoun<note n="27" xml:id="d34fn27">Lebanese Minister to the United Kingdom and delegate to the
                        Chicago International Aviation Conference.</note> was given free passage on
                    boat and sent from London to Beirut by British Government for purpose of
                    preventing Lebanese Government from granting Fifth Freedom privilege and
                    blocking El-Hoss<note n="28" xml:id="d34fn28">Fawzi el-Hoss, Director of Civil
                        Aviation in the Lebanese Government.</note> purchase of American planes and
                    technical assistance. British Air Ministry representative from Cairo arrived in
                    Beirut same day I arrived to endeavor counteract my activities. He used
                    unbelievable pressure against Lebanese as regards air transport agreement and
                    purchase of American planes, warning that if they cooperate with Americans they
                    will lose considerable British support and assistance generally.</p>
                <p>In Iraq, copies of proposed air transport agreement were distributed by Foreign
                    Office to RAF Air Vice Marshal in charge this theater, British Embassy and two
                    other British aviation advisors for study and consultation, which is causing
                    delay. It is apparent Iraq Government is unable to act definitively without
                    absolute approval of British authorities who do not want to see Baghdad made a
                    crossroads for American international air service. End of message. [Curren.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Moreland</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
