<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Iran (
                        Murray
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d363</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">363</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-09-07T04:35:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-09-07T04:35:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-09-07T04:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-09-07T04:35:00-05:00" n="363" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d363">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/9–745: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-09-07T13:00:00+03:25">September 7, 1945—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 1:14 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>701. Following is summary of formal statement on Iranian foreign policy made in
                    Majlis yesterday by Minister of Foreign Affairs Sepahbodi: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Begin summary</hi>. Difficulties placed in way of
                            despatch of security forces to maintain order in different parts of Iran
                            are source of all recent disturbances and unfortunate events. Such
                            difficulties should never have arisen. In accordance Tripartite Treaty,
                            presence of Allied troops on Iranian territory does not constitute
                            occupation.</p>
                        <p>Iran has fulfilled its engagements and Minister of Foreign Affairs does
                            not understand why Iran Govt should not have been free from beginning to
                            send troops or police to any part of country. Allied Forces are in Iran
                            with Iranian permission. They are furthermore forces of friendly powers.
                            Why then should despatch of Iranian troops to the regions in question
                            (northern provinces where there has been rioting and threatened tribal
                            attack) require special authorization or prior advice?</p>
                        <p>Even if war conditions made such prior advice necessary, end of war has
                            removed reason for it. Minister of Foreign Affairs has instructed Iran
                            Ambassadors Moscow and London to point out clearly lack of necessity for
                            such state of affairs. He is certain that this action will not only
                            remove present difficulties but also lay basis for better understanding
                            among nations concerned. This better understanding should have influence
                            on general relations of Iran’s two powerful friends.</p>
                        <p>During conversations of Minister of Foreign Affairs with Soviet
                            Ambassador 2 weeks ago, Sepahbodi received certain assurances which were
                            to his entire satisfaction. One of these concerned censorship which has
                            now been virtually abolished. If actions in other fields have not been
                            in accordance with expectations, Minister of Foreign Affairs is sure
                            this should not be construed as lack of sincerity between the two
                            friendly countries but rather imputed to delay in receipt of necessary
                            instructions.</p>
                        <p>Sooner these questions are adjusted, more friendly relations between the
                            two nations will be encouraged. Iran Ambassador at Moscow has reported
                            he has had lengthy and useful discussions with Soviets with view to
                            strengthening relations.</p>
                        <pb facs="0415" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/>
                        <p>Iran has asked to be represented in discussions at London regarding
                            manner of evacuation of foreign troops from Iran<note n="87" xml:id="d363fn87">See telegram 702, September 7, 2 p.m., <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note> basing this request on article
                            6 and annex 1 of Tripartite Treaty. Evacuation itself is certain since
                            treaty provides it must take place within 6 months after end of
                            hostilities with Japan. Minister of Foreign Affairs hopes it will be
                            completed sooner but Iranian interests must be safeguarded in connection
                            manner of withdrawal of troops. Although Iran has no treaty with United
                            States, United States Govt has been informed of request made to British
                            and Russians in view of great interest it has in such questions and fact
                            it will participate in London meeting.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Dept as 701; repeated Moscow as 216 and London as 55.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
