<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Shahanshah of Iran (
                        Mohammad Reza Pahlavi
                    ) to President Truman
                    
                    Handed to President Truman on November 29, 1945,
                        by Hussein Ala at the time be presented his letters of credence as first
                        Iranian Ambassador to the United States; see bracketed note, p. 461.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d367</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">367</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="diplomatic-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-09-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="367" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d367">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">701.9111/11–3045</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Shahanshah of Iran</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Mohammad Reza Pahlavi</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="94" xml:id="d367fn94">Handed to President Truman on November 29, 1945,
                        by Hussein Ala at the time be presented his letters of credence as first
                        Iranian Ambassador to the United States; see bracketed note, <ref target="#pg_461">p. 461</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName type="venue">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Palace of Saadabad</hi>,<note n="95" xml:id="d367fn95">Royal summer palace at Shimran, a suburb of
                                Tehran.</note>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-09-10">September 10,
                        1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: On appointing the first Ambassador
                    to your country, I seize the welcome opportunity to send Your Excellency my
                    warmest greetings and express the cordial sentiments of the Iranian people.</p>
                <p>The choice of Hussein Ala, my Minister of the Imperial Court, for the important
                    position of Iranian Ambassador to Washington is sufficient proof of my keen
                    desire for the closest understanding based on mutual trust and cooperation with
                    America.</p>
                <p>It is over sixty years since regular diplomatic relations were established
                    between my country and yours,<note n="96" xml:id="d367fn96">The first Minister
                        Resident of the United States to Iran arrived at Tehran on June 9, 1883; see
                            <ref target="frus1883#pg_702">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1883, p. 702</ref>.</note> and
                    some forty years ago Iran first sought expert financial advice from the United
                    States of America<note n="97" xml:id="d367fn97">For documentation on the
                        employment by Iran of American experts as financial assistants in 1911, see
                            <ref target="frus1911#pg_679">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1911, pp. 679</ref> ff.</note> as the
                    country best indicated to help her.</p>
                <p>The good understanding and friendly relationship existing between the two
                    countries have been daily extended and strengthened ever since, and we have at
                    all times looked upon your envoys to this country as the symbols of justice and
                    goodwill.</p>
                <p>The crowning event in our relations was the historic visit of the late President
                    Roosevelt who honoured the capital of this country by his stay in 1943.<note n="98" xml:id="d367fn98">In connection with his conference with Prime
                        Minister Churchill and Marshal Stalin at Tehran from November 28 to December
                        1, 1943; for documentation on this Conference, see <hi rend="italic">Conferences at Cairo and Tehran</hi>.</note> To that eminent
                    personality and his fortitude and farsightedness much is owed by the United
                    Nations. His death which was a shock to us in this country was a great loss to
                    the world. We shall always remember the days he spent amongst us in order, with
                    the help of the other Allied Nations, to plan the victory in Europe.</p>
                <p>We also remember with gratitude that the document acknowledging the contributions
                    and sacrifices made by Iran in this war,<note n="99" xml:id="d367fn99">The
                        Declaration Regarding Iran.</note> which by God’s Providence has ended in
                    the complete victory of those who stood for justice and freedom, bears his
                    signature, and that he established the policy of the United States of America to
                    maintain and confirm the independence and integrity of Iran.</p>
                <pb facs="0418" n="406" xml:id="pg_406"/>
                <p>As Your Excellency already knows, during this world conflict, Iran helped her
                    Allies with determination and all the means at her disposal. In her services to
                    the cause of victory over tyranny and injustice, she sustained her share of
                    hardships and privations. Now that victory has been gained, the Iranian people
                    look forward to see a better day dawn for them as well as for all the nations of
                    the world; they expect to have opportunity to live undisturbed within their
                    frontiers and to lay the foundations of a life conducive to prosperity and
                    peace. In order to achieve this, Mr. President, Iran expects that her sufferings
                    and sacrifices shall not have been in vain, and that the assistance she needs
                    for that purpose will be forthcoming from her great Allies and in particular
                    from the United States of America.</p>
                <p>Let me assure you, Mr. President, that the sincere friendship felt by the people
                    of Iran and myself for you and the people of the United States is deep-seated in
                    our hearts.</p>
                <p>I wish particularly to stress the fact that the clear-sighted and high-minded
                    policy which Your Excellency has pursued with such distinction, ability and
                    success in the short period of the leadership of the United States of America is
                    a source of real gratification and of confidence for the future peace of the
                    world.</p>
                <p>I avail myself of this opportunity, Mr. President, to express to Your Excellency
                    my best wishes for your personal health and happiness and the prosperity of the
                    steadfast and freedom-loving people of the United States.</p>
                <p>Yours Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mohammad Reza Pahlavi</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
