<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Near Eastern and
                        African Affairs (Henderson)Addressed to the Acting Secretary of State (Acheson), the
                        Deputy Director of the Office of European Affairs (Hickerson), and the Chief
                        of the Division of Eastern European Affairs (Durbrow). In marginal notes,
                        Mr. Hickerson and Mr. Durbrow indicated their agreement and Mr. Acheson
                        stated: “I agree but don’t see where it gets us.”</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d375</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">375</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-09-17T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-09-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="375" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d375">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/7–1445</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Near Eastern and
                        African Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>)<note n="4" xml:id="d375fn4">Addressed to the Acting Secretary of State (Acheson), the
                        Deputy Director of the Office of European Affairs (Hickerson), and the Chief
                        of the Division of Eastern European Affairs (Durbrow). In marginal notes,
                        Mr. Hickerson and Mr. Durbrow indicated their agreement and Mr. Acheson
                        stated: “I agree but don’t see where it gets us.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-09-17">September 17,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The contents of this telegram<note n="5" xml:id="d375fn5">Reference is to No.
                        3269, September 14, from Moscow, <ref target="#pg_407">p. 407</ref>.</note>
                    assists in making more clear present Soviet policies with regard to Iran and
                    serves to emphasize the gravity of the problems which face Iran and which may
                    eventually affect the relations of various great powers in the Middle East. The
                    publication of the appeal of the Tabriz Azerbaidjani nationalists in the Moscow
                    press is significant because it shows that Moscow is now beginning openly to
                    show its sympathy for and support of the Azerbaidjani movement in Iran. The
                    strengthening of Azerbaidjani nationalism in northern Iran would do much to
                    weaken the effectiveness of the Iranian central government, and a nationalistic
                    slogan would probably be more helpful in winning the support for Soviet policies
                    of the northern population of Iran than Communist propaganda. It is our
                    understanding that the Soviet propagandists are accompanying their attacks upon
                    the Iranian treatment of the Azerbaidjanians by words <pb facs="0423" n="411" xml:id="pg_411"/> of praise of Moscow’s treatment of the Azerbaijanians in
                    the Caucasus, most of whom, as you know, live in the Azerbaidjani Socialist
                    Soviet Republic, the capital of which is Baku.</p>
                <p>It is not as yet entirely clear whether the Russians hope to use aroused
                    Azerbaidjani nationalist feelings in northern Iran to strengthen a movement for
                    the annexation of the Azerbaidjani portions of Iran into Soviet Azerbaidjan in
                    the not distant future or whether they hope to make use of Azerbaidjani
                    nationalists in strengthening Soviet influence over all Iran.</p>
                <p>It is possible that if the Russians can gain control of the leadership of the
                    Azerbaidjani nationalist movement, they may endeavor to ally that movement with
                    other political or racial groups, including Armenians, Kurds and the pro-Soviet
                    Tudeh Party, in an effort to gain the ascendancy over the central Iranian
                    government.</p>
                <p>Analysis of this situation strengthens our belief that we should do everything
                    possible, even though we may suffer certain inconveniences and may have to sell
                    our equipment and installations in Iran<note n="6" xml:id="d375fn6">This refers
                        to the question of the disposition of United States surplus property in
                        Iran; for documentation on this subject, see <ref target="#pg_566">pp.
                            566</ref> ff.</note> at lower prices, to draw all of our military forces
                    out of Iran as rapidly as possible and that we should earnestly endeavor to
                    prevail upon the British and the Russians also to effect complete withdrawal of
                    their armed forces from Iran.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Loy</hi> W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
