<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Iran ( (Murray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d426</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">426</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-11-25T02:35:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-25T02:35:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHrSmzhfG78SwqX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recHhqoArQDK36RN7" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="hiv-aids"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98003941"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">AIDS</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-25T02:35:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-25T02:35:00-05:00" n="426"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d426">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/11–2545: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-25T11:00:00+03:25"
                            >November 25, 1945—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 25—8:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>998. British Vice Consul Lang arrived Tehran yesterday by Intourist plane from
                    Tabriz and brought pouch from Ebling including his telegram No. 9 to Dept<note
                        n="63" xml:id="d426fn63">Dated November 20, not printed.</note> which we
                    despatched last night. Summary of situation as derived from Ebling’s written
                    reports and Lang’s oral statements follows:</p>
                <p>“Democratic Party” is in control most towns and rural districts comprised in
                    rough triangle formed by Sarab, Mianeh and Bukan (south of Miandoab). Govt
                    offices generally are functioning but under party direction. Party patrols
                    control main roads, search passengers and occasionally requisition vehicles but
                    there has been relatively little bloodshed. Lang guesses perhaps 20 persons have
                    been killed. Chief party hostility directed against gendarmes who have been
                    largely disarmed and disbanded in districts under party control. British Consul
                    visited Mianeh November 22 and found all quiet there.</p>
                <pb facs="0467" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/>
                <p>No disturbances Tabriz and none reported western Azerbaijan.</p>
                <p>Soviets taking no open part in movement but reported to have discouraged Iranian
                    Commander Tabriz from making any move to put down party groups.</p>
                <p>Central Committee of Democratic Party calling itself “National Congress of
                    Azerbaijan” established Tabriz and is more or less directing activities in
                    outlying areas although disclaiming responsibility for any extreme acts. On
                    November 23 Congress presented to American, British and Soviet Consuls
                    declaration setting forth policies and aims of party. Salient points are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Azerbaijan claims right of self-determination under Atlantic Charter
                            and is determined to have Democratic regime and full cultural
                            autonomy.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>With this aim people of Azerbaijan want to form own “national govt”
                            within framework of Iranian State electing at same time their
                            representatives to Tehran Majlis.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Deny they wish to separate from Iran.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>“National Congress” is composed of 20 delegates and supported by
                            signatures of 150,000 people.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Congress has appointed governing board of 30 persons which has been
                            authorized to take steps to assure the “national aims” conduct elections
                            for Govt of Azerbaijan and deputies to Tehran Majlis and negotiate with
                            central Govt for peaceable realization of Azerbaijan
                            self-administration.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Congress desires avoid conflict but if central Govt attempts to defeat
                            its aids [<hi rend="italic">aims</hi>] by force Congress and people
                            Azerbaijan will fight to last. Governing board has no authority to
                            relinquish power of self administration of Azerbaijan.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Lang says Congress is expected to hold elections about December 3.</p>
                <p>Full text declaration by mail.<note n="64" xml:id="d426fn64">Despatch 164,
                        November 26, 1945. In this message, the Ambassador stated: “I think the
                        Department will agree that the most interesting feature of the declaration
                        is that it presents what amounts to a demand for complete autonomy. Although
                        any intention to separate from Iran is specifically denied, the effect of
                        the announced platform, if realized, would be scarcely less than the
                        independence of Azerbaijan, subject to the merest shadow of Iranian
                        authority. It is particularly interesting that the local bodies which have
                        been set up or whose creation is proposed are referred to as ‘national’
                        organizations and that the local ‘National Government of Azerbaijan’ is to
                        be elected from the members of the local legislature and to be responsible
                        to it.” (891.00/11–2645)</note>
                </p>
                <p>To Dept as 998, repeated Moscow 290, London 95.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
