<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="435" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d435">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/11–2845</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Near
                                    Eastern and African Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-28">November 28,
                                        1945</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The [appointed] Iranian Ambassador urgently requested an appointment
                                with you this morning to discuss the situation in his country. <pb facs="0474" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/> I felt confident that he
                                had nothing particularly new to report and consequently took the
                                liberty of telling him that you were fully occupied this morning and
                                suggested that he come to see me.</p>
                            <p>He left with me the attached communication<note n="78" xml:id="d435fn78">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> addressed to you,
                                expressing his full appreciation for the note which we sent to the
                                Soviet Government and reiterating reports of Soviet obstruction.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador was highly alarmed by present reports that the rebels
                                are advancing on Teheran. He pointed out that the Soviet authorities
                                have leased a large number of important buildings and houses in
                                Teheran during the past three years and still retain possession of
                                them, despite Soviet claims of having evacuated Teheran. The
                                Ambassador feels confident that these houses are serving as depots
                                for arms and ammunition, and that the Soviets have prepared a
                                well-organized fifth column movement inside the city, to be supplied
                                with arms at the proper moment from these Soviet depots. He is
                                afraid that the capital may be lost to the rebels and the Shah, high
                                Government officials, and members of the Parliament are in great
                                physical danger. The Ambassador thinks that most energetic measures
                                are necessary, and wondered whether it might be possible for
                                American forces in Iran to make some kind of demonstration in
                                Teheran in support of the central Government, “somewhat similar to
                                the support you are giving the central Government in China”.</p>
                            <p>We told the Ambassador that while we would of course bring his views
                                to the attention of the appropriate authorities, we felt it
                                necessary to point out immediately that any movement of American
                                forces toward Teheran would be directly contrary to the sense of our
                                proposals to Russia and Great Britain for the withdrawal of all
                                foreign troops. I pointed out that since we have no combat troops in
                                Iran any demonstration by service forces might appear ridiculous. I
                                expressed sympathy for the difficulties of the Iranian Government
                                and said that the most effective action it could take, in my view,
                                would be to take every step to maintain its authority within the
                                capital.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>L[<hi rend="smallcaps">oy</hi>] W. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">enderson</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>