<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="452" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d452">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">701.9111/12–345</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">President <persName type="from">Truman</persName>
                                    to the Shahanshah of Iran</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Mohammad Reza Shah
                                    Pahlavi</hi></persName>)<note n="91" xml:id="d452fn91">Enclosed
                                    with instruction 303, December 7, to Tehran, for transmittal to
                                    the Shah.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-05">December 5,
                                        1945</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Majesty</hi>: I am deeply grateful to Your
                                Majesty for your gracious letter of September 10, 1945, and I take
                                pleasure in extending to you on behalf of the American people
                                friendly greetings and best wishes for Your Majesty’s personal
                                well-being and for the happiness and welfare of the Iranian
                                people.</p>
                            <pb facs="0488" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/>
                            <p>It was a source of considerable gratification to me to welcome His
                                Excellency Hussein Ala as the first Iranian Ambassador to the United
                                States, since I recognize the special position of trust in which
                                Your Majesty has long held him. I am confident that the traditional
                                bonds of friendship and cooperation between our two countries will
                                be further strengthened by his efforts.</p>
                            <p>The considerable sacrifices which Iran has made in pursuit of the
                                victory of the United Nations have not gone unrecognized in the
                                United States, and the American people join with me in expressing
                                the hopes that Iran’s recovery and reconstruction will be effected
                                rapidly and completely, with Your Majesty’s guidance and leadership,
                                and with the assistance and support of the United Nations.</p>
                            <p>I wish to convey to Your Majesty my deep appreciation for the
                                friendly sentiments which you have expressed, and to reaffirm to you
                                my desire for ever closer relations between our two countries.</p>
                            <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer>[<signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Harry S. Truman</hi>
                                </signed>]</closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>