<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-25T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-25T18:00:00-05:00" n="538" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d538">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">891.51A/7–945: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Murray</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-25T19:00:00-04:00">July 25,
                                    1945—7 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>379. Urtel 473 July 9.<note n="27" xml:id="d538fn27">Not printed.</note>
                            We have given careful consideration to your suggestion of bringing in
                            from abroad some disinterested and <pb facs="0566" n="554" xml:id="pg_554"/> highly qualified man such as Landis<note n="29" xml:id="d538fn29">James M. Landis, Director of American Economic
                                Operations in the Middle East until his resignation, effective
                                January 23, 1945.</note> to survey the Mission and to make
                            suggestions for its reorganization. We are inclined to believe however
                            that in view of what has occurred during the last 2 years it would be
                            impossible to erect an effective advisory structure on what remains of
                            this Mission.</p>
                        <p>It seems to us that for the last year at least the Mission has drifted
                            aimlessly and futilely. The basic factor which has militated against its
                            success has been the failure of the Iranian Government to implement its
                            repeated assurances (Deptel 65, February 10, 1945 and urtels 37, Jan.
                            19; 50, Jan. 24; 102, Feb. 16 [<hi rend="italic">15</hi>]) that the
                            Mission would be accorded full cooperation and support. We are inclined
                            to agree with the statements made by prominent Iranians that so long as
                            Iran is occupied by foreign troops and so long as the representatives of
                            great powers interfere in Iranian internal affairs, it will not be
                            possible for a strong central government to exist in Iran. No weak
                            government would have the character or the courage in the face of
                            certain opposition to give unqualified support to the Mission. However,
                            we feel that even with the full support and cooperation of the Iranian
                            Government the Mission would not be able in the future to function
                            effectively in view of the irreparable damage which has already been
                            done to its prestige. The fact should also not be overlooked that
                            certain members of the Mission, by their pettiness, incapacity, and
                            sometimes even by their misbehavior, have contributed to the
                            discrediting of the Mission.</p>
                        <p>We feel that the time has come to inform the Iranian Government that in
                            our opinion the Mission will not be able in the future to be of
                            effective assistance to Iran and to suggest that the Iranian Government
                            take steps at once to bring about its complete withdrawal. In making
                            such an approach it may be pointed out it is our belief that the
                            presence of the Mission in Iran under prevailing circumstances would be
                            prejudicial rather than beneficial to American-Iranian relations, and
                            should be made clear that the dissolution of the Mission would in no way
                            diminish this Government’s interest in Iran’s welfare or its desire to
                            contribute thereto within the means at its disposal, nor would it affect
                            Dept’s attitude towards any future requests by Iranian Government for
                            American aid or advice. It might be added that we hope that the Iranian
                            Government will accord all possible support to the Ridley and
                            Schwarzkopf Missions<note n="30" xml:id="d538fn30">For documentation on
                                the interest of the United States in the continuation of these
                                missions, see <ref target="#pg_526">pp. 526</ref> ff.</note> since
                            the American Government would deeply regret the necessity of suggesting
                            that they also be withdrawn.</p>
                        <p>We would appreciate a frank statement of your views. We do not
                            contemplate taking action in this regard until after the return of <pb facs="0567" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> American Delegation to
                                Potsdam<note n="31" xml:id="d538fn31">The reference is to the
                                Tripartite Conference of Berlin which was held from July 17 to
                                August 2, 1945.</note> since developments may have taken place there
                            which would influence our final decision.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>