<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-16T07:54:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-16T07:54:00-05:00" n="853" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d853">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">890F.515/4–1645: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Saudi Arabia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Eddy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Jidda</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-16T16:00:00+03:06">April 16,
                                    1945—4 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 10:05 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>167. ReDepts 105, April 7, 7 p.m.<note n="71" xml:id="d853fn71">Not
                                printed.</note> Saudi Government requests as special favor that gold
                            slugs be flown out by airplane when ready May 15 as was done with first
                            shipment received December 2, 1944.<note n="72" xml:id="d853fn72">In
                                telegram 276, September 12, 1944. 9 a.m., the Minister in Saudi
                                Arabia reported a request from the Saudi Arabian Government for the
                                purchase of gold bars worth $1,000,000 (890F.515/9–1244). In
                                telegram 370, December 15, 1944, the Minister transmitted the
                                expression of gratitude of the Saudi Arabian Government for the
                                shipment of gold bars which had been received at a time of economic
                                crisis. This message also transmitted the Government’s order for a
                                second shipment of gold equal in value to the first and in the form
                                of round pieces with milled edges (890F.515/12–1544). This shipment
                                arrived by plane on May 29 and was delivered the same day.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Comment: I recommend this request be granted, taking the liberty to
                            remind the Department that Saudi Government has not yet any definite
                            assurance as to amount or duration of joint subsidy and has heard
                            nothing of progress on the subject of Department’s 283, December 24, 2
                                p.m.<note n="73" xml:id="d853fn73">
                                <ref target="frus1944v05#pg_759">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 759</ref>.</note> Riyal
                            deliveries will probably be late, first supply of gold long since
                            exhausted, and purchasing power will be sorely needed to furnish free
                            food to oases eaten out by locusts. (Legs 164, April 15, 9 a.m. [<hi rend="italic">p.m.</hi>]<note n="74" xml:id="d853fn74">Not printed;
                                it stated: “Saudi Government has addressed to both American and
                                British Ministers appeal for increase in foodstuffs to be procured
                                for Saudi Arabia during 1945 to offset catastrophic loss of crops
                                from current infestation of locusts … I recommend immediate steps to
                                provide substantial increase in cereals for Saudi Arabia Government
                                with early provision for increased quotas at loading areas to
                                prevent fatal delay. My British colleague is sending similar
                                recommendation.” (890F.48/4–1545)</note>) Since gold has been
                            proposed by Department as important means of assistance during 1945
                            (Department’s 82, March 22, 3 [<hi rend="italic">7</hi>] p.m.) this
                            early delivery by air seems reasonable. Furthermore early plans now for
                            subsequent minting of slugs could assure delivery by surface vessel at
                            intervals of 3 months whereas even air delivery this time makes interval
                            5 months since first delivery. Finally gold being the form of assistance
                            by USA which has actually materialized as distinct from other proposals
                            merely pending I recommend it be exploited. Our political position and
                            our economic claims need all the present support that can be given.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Eddy</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>