<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Secretary of War (
                        Stimson
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d862</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">862</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-04-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-04-25T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="862" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d862">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890F.248/3–2445</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Secretary of War</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stimson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, [<date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-25">April 25,
                            1945</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I refer to the desire of the
                    War Department to secure rights in Saudi Arabia for the establishment of an air
                    route directly from Cairo to Dhahran and thence to India, and for the
                    installation of a flying field at Dhahran and other necessary facilities; and
                    particular reference is made to telegram no. 122, dated March 24, 1945, 11 a.m.,
                    from Jidda, a copy of which was forwarded to the War Department.</p>
                <p>In preparing instructions for the guidance of the Legation in Jidda in its
                    impending negotiations for air rights, it is believed that consideration should
                    be given to a recent indication by the Saudi Government of its desire to improve
                    the Jidda airport, including the installation of night-lighting, runways and
                    maintenance and repair facilities.</p>
                <p>When negotiations for the Dhahran field and route are begun, the Saudi
                    authorities may be expected to bring up the subject of the desired installations
                    at Jidda in that connection, and, with a view to expediting the negotiations, a
                    decision on this point might be made by the War Department beforehand.</p>
                <p>It is therefore suggested that in addition to offering the assistance described
                    in the telegram mentioned above, the Legation at Jidda be given discretionary
                    authority to agree that the Army will carry out the desired improvements at
                    Jidda if, in the Legation’s opinion, such agreement is necessary to secure the
                    field at Dhahran and the required transit rights.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
