<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="876" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d876">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">890F.51/5–1745</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary
                                of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Acheson</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-17">May 17, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                                <cell>Senators Barkley, George and Walsh<note n="4" xml:id="d876fn4">Alben W. Barkley of Kentucky, Senate Majority Leader;
                                        Walter F. George of Georgia, Chairman of the Senate
                                        Committee on Finance; and David I. Walsh of Massachusetts,
                                        Chairman of the Senate Committee on Naval Affairs.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Under Secretary of Navy Bard</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Colonel Brownell<note n="5" xml:id="d876fn5">George A.
                                        Brownell, Executive Officer to the Assistant Secretary of
                                        War for Air (Lovett).</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Acheson</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Mr. Bard, Colonel Brownell and Mr. Acheson met with the three Senators by
                            appointment this afternoon. Mr. Acheson stated the problem in summary as
                            follows: He showed the Senators a map of the United States with the
                            Middle Eastern oil-bearing areas superimposed upon it and gave them a
                            brief résumé of the amounts of oil involved in the various areas and the
                            national interests in that oil. The Senators agreed that the United
                            States had a vital interest in Saudi Arabia, both in order to prevent
                            internal disturbance and foreign intervention and in order to protect
                            American national interests in the oil reserves of that country. He then
                            briefly stated the King’s <pb facs="0908" n="896" xml:id="pg_896"/>
                            financial position, showing them a chart of estimated recent
                            expenditures and the estimated deficits. He pointed out the consequences
                            which might follow upon failure to care for these deficits. The Army and
                            Navy representatives supported this position strongly. The Senators
                            agreed that something was required.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Acheson then stated the four broad methods of approach, that is, by
                            secured loan, by unsecured loan, by gift and by purchase of oil in the
                            ground. He stated to them the result of our conference with the House
                                leaders.<note n="6" xml:id="d876fn6">See memorandum of March 8 by
                                the Assistant Secretary of State, <ref target="#pg_861">p.
                                861</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Senators were unanimous in agreeing that a gift to the King would not
                            have Congressional support and that an unsecured loan might meet with
                            Congressional difficulty. The conference then became somewhat involved
                            in details of the various plans. Colonel Brownell stressed the
                            importance of Congressional direction as to the plan to be followed.
                            After some discussion Senator Barkley summed up the conclusions by
                            stating that the three Senators were unanimous in their opinion that
                            some action was required and in their assurances of support. He stated
                            their agreement that this should be done with as little legislation as
                            seemed necessary and certainly without legislation which specified the
                            particular area under discussion. Senator George stated his preference
                            for a plan which would be based upon a purchase of oil since he regarded
                            that as the simplest to understand and explain. He was quite willing,
                            however, to consider other plans or a combination of plans. It was
                            concluded that the representatives of State, War and Navy should work
                            out in more detail alternative plans, one based upon a loan through the
                            Export-Import Bank, and possibly in conjunction with a collateral
                            contract between the Navy and the oil company and possibly the
                            Export-Import Bank. The other plan should be based upon a purchase of
                            oil in the ground. Both plans shall be as specific as possible and
                            include the legislation and the appropriation required.</p>
                        <p>In a short discussion after the conference Mr. Bard thought that it was
                            important at once to arrange a conference with the President so that we
                            might have President Truman’s approval of the broad project, as we had
                            had President Roosevelt’s. Mr. Bard will make this appointment for as
                            early a date as possible and notify Colonel Brownell and Mr.
                            Acheson.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>