<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-08-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="89" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d89">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/8–1345</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. William O. Baxter
                                of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-08-13">August 13, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. Tandy of the British Embassy called this afternoon at his request in
                            order to discuss two telegrams from the British Foreign Office
                            requesting the views of the Department on questions relating to the
                            proposed Allied supervision of elections in Greece. This matter was
                            considered urgent as Mr. Bevin has indicated that he wishes if possible
                            to include some statement on Greece when he addresses Parliament on
                            August 16.</p>
                        <p>I told Mr. Tandy that the Department had no objection to discussing
                            informally with the Greek Regent the possibility that the terms of the
                            Varkiza Agreement be modified to allow the elections to precede a
                            plebiscite provided that the initiative for such modification is
                            undertaken by the Greek Government itself. I also suggested that since
                            the proposed supervision is to be tripartite, the French Ambassador in
                            Athens should be asked to concert with the British and American
                            Ambassadors in their informal talk with the Regent.</p>
                        <p>The proposed British text for public announcement concerning Greek
                            elections is completely acceptable to the Department, which proposes
                            that the simultaneous public statements in London, Athens, Paris, and
                            Washington should agree in fundamentals but need not be worded
                            identically. It is of course understood that the Soviet Government will
                            be informed at least a day in advance of our proposed action.</p>
                        <pb facs="0151" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/>
                        <p>The Department also has no objection to the possible inclusion of
                            Dominion representatives in the British supervisory delegation.</p>
                        <p>The Department is in agreement with the British Foreign Office that it
                            would be preferable for Allied supervision to be exercised both in the
                            elections and in the plebiscite. However, the timing of the plebiscite,
                            if it should not follow the elections closely, raises some questions
                            concerning the length of time for which American personnel is available.
                            I told Mr. Tandy that it is impossible at this time to give him a
                            definite answer on this question but that the possibilities would be
                            explored at once.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>