<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-30T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-30T17:00:00-05:00" n="987" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d987">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.7490F/4–2045: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Minister in Saudi Arabia</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Eddy</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-30T18:00:00-04:00">April 30,
                                    1945—6 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>127. ReLegs 180, April 20, 11 a.m. While the contract is not entirely
                            clear on the point, it appears that failure of the Saudi Government to
                            propose specific modification of its contract with the Eastern Telegraph
                            Company before June 1 would prejudice its right to demand consideration
                            of such proposals if presented later. If, however, the modification is
                            proposed before June 1, there appears to be no time limit within which
                            agreement must be reached.</p>
                        <p>You should therefore approach the Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs and
                            suggest that the Saudi Government propose before June 1 a modification
                            in the contract with the Eastern Telegraph Company.</p>
                        <p>The proposal might be phrased substantially as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>In continuation of the Saudi Government’s communication to the
                                    Eastern Telegraph Company, Ltd., dated November 21, 1944,
                                    concerning its intention to modify the agreement dated April 17,
                                    1935, between the Saudi Government and the Sudan Government on
                                    the one hand and the Eastern Telegraph Company and the Cable and
                                    Wireless, Ltd. on the other, and in conformity with the
                                    provisions of Article 17 of that agreement, the Saudi Government
                                    proposes the following amendment to the agreement to become an
                                    additional article in Part III: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“Neither Article 11 nor any other article of this
                                            agreement shall be construed to limit the right of the
                                            Saudi Government to use or to permit the use of radio
                                            stations in Saudi Arabia for the establishment and
                                            operation of direct radio communications <pb facs="1032" n="1020" xml:id="pg_1020"/> circuits with other
                                            countries when, in the opinion of the Saudi Government,
                                            the use of such channels would be in the interest of
                                            Saudi Arabia.”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>An alternate, though less desirable modification, would be the amendment
                            of Article 17 to provide that the Saudi Government will have the right
                            to propose modifications of the agreement at any time. This alternative
                            should not be mentioned unless the first suggestion is unacceptable to
                            the Saudi Government.</p>
                        <p>You should point out that the Saudi Government has already signified its
                            intention of proposing a modification of the agreement, and that the
                            step now suggested merely carries out the intention previously announced
                            to the American and British Governments.</p>
                        <p>In view of impending developments in Saudi Arabia, the Saudi Government
                            can scarcely consent to have its economic and transport development
                            hampered by a monopolistic arrangement which can be revised only at
                            5-year intervals, which does not respond to the needs of the country,
                            and which imposes exorbitant rates.</p>
                        <p>In your discretion you may add that the proposal suggested above has been
                            couched in terms of a sufficiently broad nature to guarantee that the
                            Saudi Government will retain full liberty not only to continue
                            discussions looking toward the establishment of direct radio contact
                            with the United States but also to insist on alterations being made hi
                            terms of the concession which would enable the Saudi Government to
                            prevent the continuance of restrictions on international communications
                            which might later handicap the normal development of economic
                            enterprises in Saudi Arabia. You have likewise discretionary authority
                            to inform the Saudi Government that we are asking the British Government
                            not to oppose the taking of measures by the Saudi Government for the
                            purpose of establishing direct radio circuits between the United States
                            and Saudi Arabia.</p>
                        <p>There will be repeated to you in a separate message for your information
                            only the text of further instructions on the subject sent to the Embassy
                            in London.<note n="9" xml:id="d987fn9">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>