<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Winant
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d997</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">997</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-11-01T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-01T17:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-01T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-01T17:00:00-05:00" n="997" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d997">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.7490F/11–145: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-01T17:00:00-05:00">November 1, 1945—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>9614. Urtel 11003 Oct 20. You are hereby instructed to contact appropriate
                    officials of Brit Govt and convey the substance of the following message on
                    subject of direct radiotelegraph circuit between US and Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>US Govt appreciates interest the British Govt has shown in this matter and is
                        happy to know that Brit Govt is genuinely interested in coming to an
                        understanding in regard to it.</p>
                    <p>However, there are certain factors connected with this situation which we
                        would like to mention. To begin with the intimation in above mentioned
                        telegram of Oct 20 that Mr. de Wolf informed Mr. MacLean of Brit Embassy
                        Washington that State Dept on 11 January was “quite prepared to see the
                        American installed transmitter in Saudi Arabia confined to the Saudi
                        Arabia–US circuit leaving the Eastern Telegraph Company in possession of all
                        other traffic” is not accurate. Mr. de Wolf merely informed Mr. MacLean that
                        main interest of US was a Saudi Arabia–US circuit.</p>
                    <p>The Dept would next like to point out that Saudi Arabian Govt (SAG) may find
                        it uneconomical to maintain a station for sole purpose of communicating with
                        US, and that as a result the future of a station so limited in scope would
                        be uncertain. After station is built it may be necessary for SAG to decide
                        (1) that it cannot afford not to use station for sending and receiving of
                        messages to countries other than US or (2) to abandon this station
                        altogether. In opinion of US Govt it might therefore be unfortunate for SAG
                        at this time to give any definite statements to the effect that in future it
                        would not use proposed station for communication with any other country than
                        US.</p>
                    <p>Furthermore, US Govt cannot encourage or permanently acquiesce in
                        restrictions upon telecommunications of the type suggested by Brit Govt in
                        urtel 11003 without contravening its basic policy in regard to worldwide
                        telecommunications which is reflected in its refusal to support any US
                        communications company in an effort to enter into contracts of an exclusive
                        nature in countries outside US. It intends at forthcoming Bermuda
                            Conference<note n="36" xml:id="d997fn36">The Bermuda Telecommunications
                            Conference which met at Hamilton, Bermuda, from November 21 to December
                            4, 1945.</note> to propose an undertaking by the Govts represented there
                        not to support their communications companies in applications for exclusive
                        contracts in countries outside the US and the British Commonwealth.</p>
                    <p>In view of considerations advanced above it appears to this Govt that it
                        would be more conducive to a mutually satisfactory solution of this problem
                        if Brit Govt, in instructing Brit Minister at Jidda to inform SAG that Brit
                        Govt would have no objection to the erection and operation of a SAG wireless
                        telegraph station, would add the hope that if at some future date SAG
                        desired to expand the list of <pb facs="1042" n="1030" xml:id="pg_1030"/>
                        countries covered by the station, SAG would consult with Brit Govt, and such
                        other Govts as may have a direct interest in the change.</p>
                    <p>In connection with the above US Govt assumes that Brit Govt will raise no
                        objection to the use of this SAG station as an automatic relay for radio
                        messages from US to points in Far East where existing direct radio circuits
                        between US and such Far Eastern points are not satisfactory for technical
                        reasons. Such automatic relay would of course have no effect on traffic
                        arrangements between SAG and other communications companies, notably Cable
                        and Wireless.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>For your information the President has indicated his interest in this problem and
                    Dept has asked the Brit Emb here to obtain a commitment from Brit Govt at
                    earliest possible date. In the circumstances it will be appreciated if you will
                    obtain a final confirmation of Brit Govt’s acquiescence to the agreement
                    suggested in this telegram at earliest possible moment. Dept wire to Jidda held
                    pending British reply.</p>
                <p>Sent London. Repeated Jidda as Dept’s 321.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
