<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-02-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-02-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="135" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d135">
                        <head>135. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_2">Scowcroft</persName>) to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d135fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Library, National Security Adviser, Trip
                                Briefing Books of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry
                                    Kissinger</persName>, Box 5, February 10–18, 1975, Middle East
                                and Europe, HAK Messages for President, February 16, 1975. Secret;
                                Sensitive. Sent for information. <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> initialed the memorandum.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-02-16">February 16,
                                    1975</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> asked that I
                            pass the following report to you on his latest observations now that he
                            has completed his Middle Eastern stops.</p>
                        <p>“Now that I am flying to Europe and have completed all of my Middle
                            Eastern stops, the latest today being talks with King <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Faisal</persName> and his key advisors,<note n="2" xml:id="d135fn2">No memorandum of conversation has been found
                                of a meeting between King <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Faisal</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>. A memorandum of conversation of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s meeting with Prince
                                    <persName corresp="#p_EE_1">Evron</persName>, February 15 at
                                3:10 p.m. at the Royal Guest House in Riyadh, is in the Library of
                                Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, CL 208, Geopolitical File, Saudi
                                Arabia, February 5–March 26, 1975, Folder 4.</note> I want to share
                            with you my latest observations. There are two principal unanswered
                            questions which concern me as I look ahead to my next mission to the
                            Middle East.</p>
                        <p>“First, will Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>
                            and his key advisors take the major strategic decision to withdraw east
                            of the passes and out of the oil fields and bring within reason the kind
                            of quid pro quos they will insist upon from <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>? I, of course, hope so, and the Israelis have no
                            rational alternative. The formulas developed by <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> can be built upon if Israel
                            accepts the real situation. But prediction is most uncertain. The public
                            statements being made by <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>
                            since I left Israel seem unduly rigid and are likely to have the effect
                            of reducing his flexibility once we get into the detailed negotiations
                            in early March.</p>
                        <p>“Second, is the critical question as to whether <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> will feel able to move ahead on
                            an agreement without a simultaneous agreement between Israel and Syria
                            on the Golan Heights. What has impressed me is the strength of Asad’s
                            expressed intention to cause difficulties for the Egyptians if they go
                            ahead on their own in this next piecemeal step. An added factor is
                                <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Faisal</persName>’s view as expressed
                            to me today in which he underscored that he was opposed to the idea of
                            another step by Egypt alone on the grounds that this would split the
                            Arab world and would pose serious problems for Saudi Arabia. Even if we
                            are able to get common ground achieved between Egypt and Israel on the
                            next step, it is altogether possible that the combined pressure from
                            Asad and <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Faisal</persName> that there must
                            be a parallel step on the Golan Heights could become a critical
                            impediment to <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>’s freedom of
                            action.</p>
                        <pb facs="0539" n="513" xml:id="pg_513"/>
                        <p>“In my meeting today with <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Faisal</persName>
                            and his advisors I underscored our determination to make rapid progress
                            towards peace in the area and our desire to cooperate closely with Saudi
                            Arabia on economic matters. I told the King we will be consulting
                            closely with him as we move ahead on the negotiations over the next
                            several weeks and arranged for Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName> to hold immediate follow-up
                            talks with Saudi officials on economic issues.</p>
                        <p>“On the political side, <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Faisal</persName>
                            wished us well and underscored the need for progress on a very urgent
                            basis. Leading to an overall settlement on the question of resuming the
                            Geneva Conference, he said it would be better not to go to Geneva until
                            we are ready to endorse an overall settlement. He sees the opportunities
                            given to the Soviet Union to exploit any Geneva convention.</p>
                        <p>“On the economic side, I told <persName corresp="#p_FAS_1">Faisal</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_FAAS_1">Fahd</persName>
                            and <persName corresp="#p_YAZ_1">Yamani</persName> that we are prepared
                            to work with Saudi Arabia bilaterally as well as multilaterally to
                            cooperate and coordinate in dealing with such questions as preparing for
                            a constructive producer-consumer conference (rather than a chaotic
                            confrontation), a possible long-term agreement on a minimum oil price,
                            and investment of oil revenues in the United States. I also indicated
                            our interest in helping the Saudis develop their economy through the
                            Joint Commission and by increasing their agricultural and fertilizer
                            production.</p>
                        <p>“The King reacted favorably, saying he wanted to work closely with us to
                            remove obstacles between producers and consumers and to agree to things
                            of mutual interest to both countries.</p>
                        <p>“Last night I had a good talk with <persName corresp="#p_HBT_1">Hussein</persName> at Aqaba,<note n="3" xml:id="d135fn3">No
                                memorandum of conversation has been found.</note> reassuring him of
                            continued U.S. support after Rabat. He is against going to Geneva until
                            his problem with the other Arabs and the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> is resolved. He is also worried about Syria’s
                            determination to work with the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> to
                            forestall a separate Egypt–Israel agreement but believes that while it
                            would be most difficult, <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>
                            would still be inclined to accept such an agreement if there was no
                            other alternative. <persName corresp="#p_HBT_1">Hussein</persName> would
                            like to call on you in Washington in late April and I have asked
                                <persName corresp="#p_SB_2">Scowcroft</persName> to arrange a
                            date.</p>
                        <p>“I now go on to Bonn as the first stop in Europe.”</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>