<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>176. Telegram From Secretary of State Kissinger to the President’s Deputy
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs ( to the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (Scowcroft))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-05-27T16:55:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-05-27T16:55:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-05-27T16:55:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-05-27T16:55:00-05:00" n="176"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                <head>176. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> to the President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_2">Scowcroft</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d176fn1">Source: Library of Congress, Manuscript
                        Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, CL 158,
                        Geopolitical File, Israel, May 1975. Confidential; Black Patch.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1975-05-27T21:55:00+00:00">May 27, 1975, 2155Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Hakto_1">Hakto</gloss> 2. Ref: Tel Aviv 3195.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d176fn2">In telegram 3195 from Tel Aviv, May 27, the Embassy
                        reported a local American journalist’s May 26 interview with <persName
                            corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>, which was described as “off the
                        record.” <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName> claimed that <persName
                            corresp="#p_AY_1">Allon</persName> had brought Israeli proposals “in
                        writing” to Washington in April. He also expressed pleasure with the letter
                        sent by 76 Senators to <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>
                        declaring their “stern” support for Israel. <persName corresp="#p_RY_1"
                            >Rabin</persName> acknowledged the letter served as a “concrete example
                        of real limitations on administration potential to ‛pressure’ Israel,” and
                        claimed it supported his policy of holding fast in the “face of
                        administration pressure.” (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. Please show <gloss target="#t_reftel_1">reftel</gloss> to the President at the
                    earliest opportunity but before his departure. Please draw his attention
                    particularly to paragraphs 5, 6, and 7. This provides concrete evidence of
                        <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>’s willingness to treat us as an
                    antagonist and to use the senatorial letter<note n="3" xml:id="d176fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d175">Document 175</ref>.</note> to support his
                    intransigence.</p>
                <p>2. You should then call <persName corresp="#p_DS_1">Dinitz</persName> to express
                    our extreme outrage over this latest violation of confidence. First of all, he
                    knows that it is simply not true that <persName corresp="#p_AY_1"
                        >Allon</persName> brought written proposals to Washington.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d176fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_AY_1">Allon</persName> visited Washington and met with
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> on April 21 from 11:45
                        a.m. until 2:40 p.m. in the Secretary’s office and then in the Madison Room
                        at the Department of State. (Memorandum of conversation, April 21; Library
                        of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> Papers, CL 157, Geopolitical File, Israel, April
                        21–30, 1975)</note> Secondly, we regard it as a matter of great concern that
                        <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName> would reveal what we regard as
                    confidential communications prior to the <persName corresp="#p_SA_1"
                        >Sadat</persName> meeting. Additionally, you should point out that the tone
                    of <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>’s remarks sounded as if he were
                    not even talking about a friendly government. The final point you should make is
                    that the Israelis should not necessarily count on a realization of the
                    relaxation of tensions which <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName> claims
                    is emerging of the weakness of the administration vis-à-vis the Congress.</p>
                <p>3. You should make this a very, very strong protest.</p>
                <p>4. Warm regards.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
