<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>177. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d177</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">177</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-06-01T11:05:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-06-01T12:46:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7Bwbos1G7X7n" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2013002394"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">MIG</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recP1TxBSuFrpDZ2S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Interim agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recydYSQ1GmGAh8yu" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019102796"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Boycott</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="public-diplomacy" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomacy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-06-01T12:46:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-06-01T11:05:00-05:00" n="177"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d177">
                <head>177. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d177fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Records
                        of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry Kissinger</persName>, 1973–77, Box 11,
                            <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss> Memcons, June 1975, Folder 2.
                        Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName> on June 7. According to the
                        President’s Daily Diary, the meeting took place from 5:05 until 6:46 p.m.
                            (<persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Library, Staff Secretary’s
                        Office Files) <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> traveled to
                        Salzburg, Austria, from June 1 to June 3 to meet with Austrian Chancellor
                        Kreisky and President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>. He then
                        visited Rome and Vatican City on June 3 to meet with Italian President
                        Leone, Italian Prime Minister Moro, and Pope Paul VI.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Salzburg</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-editorial-annotation"
                            calendar="gregorian" from="1975-06-01T17:05:00+01:00"
                            to="1975-06-01T18:46:00+01:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">June
                            1, 1975</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Anwar al-Sadat</persName>, President</item>
                    <item>Major General <persName corresp="#p_MH_1">Mubarak</persName>, Vice
                        President</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_FI_1">Ismail Fahmi</persName>, Foreign Minister</item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Joseph J. Sisco</persName>, Under Secretary for
                        Political Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>The President: I would like to make two points in particular. First, the
                    importance of the letter signed by 76 Senators<note n="2" xml:id="d177fn2">See
                            <ref target="#d175">Document 175</ref>.</note> is being distorted out of
                    proportion; half of them didn’t read it and a quarter didn’t understand the
                    letter. Whereas the additional quarter knew very precisely what it was doing.
                    The impact of the letter is negligible. Secondly, I want to tell you that
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and I have a close
                    personal and professional relationship. There is no more trusted person than
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> that I deal with. He
                    speaks for me. We work closely together. In time my hope is that the Senate will
                    see to it that we work as a team. I am confident that the execution of our
                    policy will be successful.</p>
                <p>I was very disappointed in the position taken by Israel last March; the Israelis
                    decided to go off in a direction different than we expected. I want to tell you
                    that as far as we are concerned, stagnation is unacceptable. As you know, we are
                    in the process of a reassessment. It would be helpful to me for you to tell me
                    where you believe we are and any suggestions that you may have on how we can
                    work together in the future towards peace in the Middle East.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: Mr. President, I want to
                    thank you for the statement that you have just made and, in particular, what you
                    have said that you will not tolerate stagnation; that is marvelous. These words
                    have made a great impact on me.</p>
                <p>As to where we are now, I must say to you that the process of peace has slackened
                    to a certain extent due to problems in the United States. <pb facs="0677"
                        n="651" xml:id="pg_651"/> Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> made two visits this year and, as you know, we were
                    quite ready to achieve progress and we went beyond where it might reasonably be
                    expected that we might go. We did this for two reasons: I want to push the peace
                    process; and, secondly, I want you to know that I have been in power since 1952.
                    I have dealt with Secretaries of State since Dulles. The first time I met
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry Kissinger</persName> was in November of
                    1973, and I felt at that time that I could put full confidence in him, that he
                    was a man of trust, and I could rely on his word. This is very essential. We
                    have never felt the small power complex in relationship to big powers. I can
                    recall how we together developed the six principles<note n="3" xml:id="d177fn3"
                        >See <ref target="#d5fn8">footnote 8, Document 5</ref>.</note> and then the
                    first disengagement agreement. This brought about a new image of the United
                    States in the area.</p>
                <p>Candidly, Mr. President, I felt <persName corresp="#p_NGA_1">Nasser</persName>
                    had treated the United States unfairly because I recall that in 1956 the United
                    States had ordered Israel, the U.K., and France out of Egypt. The Soviet
                    ultimatum at that time came after the United States had already achieved Israeli
                    withdrawal. <persName corresp="#p_NGA_1">Nasser</persName>, unfairly in my
                    judgment, attributed the Israeli withdrawal to the Russian ultimatum. The United
                    States’ image in the area has been changing completely since the first
                    disengagement agreement. Egypt leads the Arab world. We started promoting better
                    relations with the United States. The United States has all the cards in its
                    hands and Israel should heed the United States. After the failure of the
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> mission in March, an angry
                    Egyptian reaction was expected. Yet I told Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> that we would extend the <gloss target="#t_UNEF_1"
                        >UNEF</gloss> for three months. I decided that the Suez Canal should be
                        opened.<note n="4" xml:id="d177fn4">The Suez Canal was reopened on June 5
                        after it had been closed in June 1967 due to the 1967 Arab-Israeli
                        War.</note> Israel fears peace. It is not capable of making peace, of taking
                    the decisions. You supported Israel during the October War. It received
                    ultra-sophisticated arms from the United States. Syria has replaced its losses
                    by getting weapons from the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> for the last
                    year and a half. I remain without any replacements. Syria has been stimulating
                    the Palestinians against Egypt in the Arab world. I went to the Arab world and
                    got the embargo lifted after the disengagement agreement. Egypt is key in the
                    Arab world. We have helped promote a new image of America in the Arab world.</p>
                <p>Mr. President, this is a moment of decision. Nobody in the Arab world believes
                    that the United States cannot put pressure on Israel. I have said that I am
                    ready for a peace agreement with Israel. I am opening the Canal, even though it
                    inhibits military operations. I am not intending to start military operations. I
                    returned 39 corpses to Israel without conditions. Egypt is different from other
                    Arabs. We have a <pb facs="0678" n="652" xml:id="pg_652"/> background of
                    patience, of civility and understanding. Millions greeted President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> and Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> when they came to Egypt<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d177fn5">See <ref target="#d92">Document 92</ref>.</note> saying we
                    want to be friends with America. The failure of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>’s mission has not been taken as a failure of the whole
                    image of the United States. The question that is being asked is whether the
                    United States is unable to achieve peace after all that it gives to Israel. We
                    don’t want war again, but I will never submit one inch of my land to Israel. We
                    have patience. The time may come when we will have to liberate our lands.</p>
                <p>The Soviets don’t lose time to exploit the situation. Israel is undermining the
                    policy of the step-by-step approach which is attacked by the Soviet Union and
                    defended by me. The Egyptian people cannot understand. My people have faith in
                    me and I tell them I have confidence in President <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1"
                        >Ford</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry
                    Kissinger</persName>. Everyone in Egypt is waiting for the next step. The Soviet
                    Union has stimulated the Syrians and Palestinians against me and against United
                    States’ policy. They have given me no military replacements since the October
                    1973 ceasefire. I have not received over 10 planes from them since last June.
                    The Soviets are sending no ammunition and 44 airplanes is the maximum, including
                    20 MIG–23’s (not Foxbats). They did this when I started attacking them after the
                    failure of negotiations.</p>
                <p>Our people want to see a real peace but they will not give up one inch of Arab
                    land.</p>
                <p>The prestige of the United States is in balance. I say Israel, not the United
                    States, is responsible for the failure of negotiations. The Soviets can connect
                    U.S. and Israeli policies. The Soviets are trying to undermine me and the entire
                    world. The lastest development is in Libya where there is 2,000 kilometers of
                    sea (?) line, where they have sent a large arsenal of arms; $12 billion worth
                    for 12½ million people. There are no frontiers in Libya. The Soviets are trying
                    to outflank me from Libya. It is against your interest and against the global
                    balance in the Middle East. The Soviets can build anything they want there and
                    no Libyan will see it because there are large areas of empty land. Also the
                    Soviet economic squeeze on me is continuing. They refuse to give me any grace
                    period on loans or sale of arms. Economic cooperation has stopped. They want to
                    paralyze me. The latest act is in Libya. I shall fight it in Libya.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We will support
                    Egypt in international forums if the Russians do something in Libya.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: My people have not lost
                    confidence in Doctor <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>. I have
                    been looking forward to this meeting. I want you to <pb facs="0679" n="653"
                        xml:id="pg_653"/> look at me as a friend. If the United States cannot do
                    something, I will not be able to defend the United States again because Israel
                    gets everything it needs from the United States. I want good relations with the
                    United States. I will be very disappointed if nothing can be achieved. Mr.
                    President, we have gone beyond where any Arab has gone in the past. My people
                    will be very disappointed if nothing can be achieved. I want us to make
                    progress; to make a complete peace. And I want the United States only to achieve
                    it, not the Soviet Union, not through a Geneva Conference, where the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is sitting. The United States can achieve
                    anything without the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>If a meeting can be achieved, then we have to go to Geneva, even though there are
                    no bright prospects there. I won’t be able to defend you at Geneva because you
                    are defending Israel. We will reach stagnation if we try to broaden the
                    participation in Geneva. Israel can blame everything on the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> issue since I will have to insist upon its
                    participation. Israel wants to gain time until your next election. Israel wants
                    to get rid of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry Kissinger</persName>. Israel
                    wants to cause difficulties with the Congress. They want to wait until your
                    election when Israel can monopolize the situation. I face a confrontation with
                    the Soviet Union this summer. The situation in our relations with them will get
                    worse. All of my arms have come from the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                    and there was no other way for me. The <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is
                    suspicious. It is clumsy in diplomacy. There is no leadership there. This is the
                    situation there.</p>
                <p>The President: I want you to know that the reassessment which I have announced is
                    more than words. It is a bona fide analysis of how we can proceed best as a
                    nation towards peace on a fair and equitable basis. However, we can make a
                    contribution. Our Israeli friends don’t believe it. The initial shock and
                    disbelief has sunk in. Israel has reacted in the wrong way. Instead of saying
                    whether they made a mistake, they have reacted to try to convince people that
                    they are right. There has been typical pressure in the Congress. I don’t intend
                    to capitulate to this kind of pressure. It could lead to difficulties within our
                    society and a struggle. The Israelis have misjudged American public opinion and
                    me. I want you to know that I have heard nothing but good about you. You are a
                    powerful leader with a broad approach. It is a pleasure to deal with you. I want
                    to work with you to try to help achieve continued progress.</p>
                <p>I would like to have any key points from you as to specifics for when I talk to
                        <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>. When I talk to the Prime
                    Minister, I will lay it on the line. Of course, we have created an impression of
                    going to Geneva with a broad comprehensive approach. The Israelis would not like
                    us to take such a broad approach. You know that at Geneva the prospects for
                    progress are negligible. Yet we might have to do it as the only option we see if
                    there is no progress on the interim agreement. I have im<pb facs="0680" n="654"
                        xml:id="pg_654"/>pressed Israel on the need to cooperate. The options you
                    know. If Israel takes the same attitude as it took in February and March, I see
                    no hope. They have to hear this from me. They know the pitfalls of Geneva. I
                    can’t imagine that they want the Soviet Union involved. It is beyond my
                    comprehension as to why they have taken this view. Israel knows it will be
                    isolated if they stay with their position and if we shift our attitude.
                    Israeli-U.S. relations are good but difficult. I want to assure you that we will
                    exercise as much leadership as we can. Some alternatives are worse than others
                    for Israel. I appreciate your suggestion that there has to be a framework for
                    negotiation soon or we have to go to Geneva. Israel ought to be shrewd enough to
                    see this.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: If we can keep complete
                    understanding between the United States and Egypt regarding the efforts that are
                    made before Geneva or at Geneva, if they know that the United States won’t be
                    behind them 100 percent at Geneva, all of this would help. I am furious that
                    after all that the United States has done for Israel they could not agree to a
                    second step. I want us to agree on a strategy of our own of course. We can
                    achieve together a lot and we can save the Arab world from Soviet
                    infiltration.</p>
                <p>The President: Is there a strong reservation by <persName corresp="#p_QM_1"
                        >Qadhafi</persName> regarding the Soviets in Libya?</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: Can you imagine $12
                    billion? <persName corresp="#p_QM_1">Qadhafi</persName> is insane. Therefore,
                    there has been no Arab comment. We got this information from those who actually
                    signed the contract. I put it out publicly myself because I didn’t want you to
                    have to get charged by the Soviets that you had done so. The Soviets know that
                    their days are numbered in Egypt. Every ship that leaves Egypt never comes back.
                    Take, for example, the 4 <gloss target="#t_Foxbat_1">Foxbat</gloss> planes in
                    Egypt. Last week I received something very queer. I was told by the Soviets that
                    they wanted to replace the 4 Foxbats with 4 others sent in a large transport
                    plane. I refused this. I ordered the 4 planes to be grounded. I said either you
                    deliver 4 planes to us, train us, or get them out. This is a popular issue in
                    the Arab world.</p>
                <p>I need help from you in trying to convince those idiots in Israel to come to
                    their senses. I have 270,000 Egyptians in Libya and I can send more. I have all
                    of the training people in Libya. I don’t need help in Libya. I can take care of
                    that by my effort. This front has to be kept quiet.</p>
                <p>The President: Let me assure you our policies will coincide with your thoughts.
                    It may have repercussions with Israel. If we can talk about specifics, I think
                    it would be helpful to me. To <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName> it is
                    this interim agreement or Geneva. They have to recognize that at Geneva it will
                    not be to their liking. We want the friendship between the United States and
                    Egypt to grow. I don’t like pressure. We can work together; we will work
                    together.</p>
                <pb facs="0681" n="655" xml:id="pg_655"/>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We have spoken
                    frankly. We have outlined the concrete possibilities. The Israeli strategy is to
                    divide our Administration, if not to gain time to drag it into our elections. In
                    the meantime, even President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> cannot
                    keep the situation quiet. By that time the Arabs will be anti-American. Israel
                    has said to us resume the interim negotiations. They have also talked in terms
                    of a broader interim agreement. Our approach to this latter proposal is that you
                    can explore it if you want but, in our judgment, it is a trap. And Geneva is the
                    third alternative. What we need is a result this year. President <persName
                        corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> is prepared to go the overall route if
                    necessary. While it would be prolonged and difficult, we are not rejecting it.
                    The other alternative is the resumption of the interim negotiations. We will be
                    accused domestically of trying to impose this—that we will be trying to impose a
                    U.S.-Egyptian solution. If we could find some modification in the Egyptian
                    position on an interim agreement—we know your range is limited for I have told
                    the President that you have gone well beyond anything that was thought
                    possible—if, for example, Egypt could make a move, we could then make an
                    American proposal. If the Israelis then turn down an American proposal, they
                    would be considered wrong by American public opinion. What I am talking about
                    are Egyptian modifications in their position on an interim agreement which would
                    be used as an excuse to put forward an American proposal on an interim
                    agreement. If Israel did refuse, we would be in a better tactical position for
                    moving to a comprehensive plan. You would have to help us in 1976, since we
                    could take a position on an overall settlement at Geneva even though we could
                    not implement it during 1976.</p>
                <p>The President: If something could be done in 1975, our overall approach would
                    keep U.S. domestic problems from festering. They can’t attack us on peace and
                    war issues.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If you have time, we
                    can go to the overall approach. If you want something very fast, it would have
                    to be the interim approach. They have said if you change, they will change. We
                    do not intend to communicate anything of substance to <persName
                        corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName> regarding our meeting here. It would be
                    possible for a quick shuttle to be undertaken by Mid-July. The Soviets are very
                    anxious to go to the European Security Conference and they would be terribly
                    disturbed if the President didn’t go to Helsinki in July and if there were no
                    conference. You will recall that the Israelis have also talked about a wider
                    interim agreement but they would expect a declaration of non-belligerency. We
                    could try that but I am very uneasy about it. I know that you are insisting on
                    the Israelis getting out of the passes and the oil fields. We noticed that the
                    Israelis now have shifted from non-belligerency to an emphasis on the duration
                    point which they say is the point which most concerns them. There is also a
                    focus on the warning stations and other elements re<pb facs="0682" n="656"
                        xml:id="pg_656"/>garding the boycott. I have not discussed these with the
                    President. What we need from you is not anything fundamental but anything which
                    would permit us to say there has been a shift in the Egyptian position and would
                    give us a chance to make an American proposal. A proposal where the line would
                    be drawn east of the passes and you would be given land access to the oil
                    fields. There would be a chance to do it in a month. We have been scaring the
                    Israelis with plans regarding the Geneva Conference. And this has been leaked
                    back to the Israelis. I want to stress, however, if we first go to the interim
                    agreement and then to Geneva, then you will have to be patient. If there was no
                    war and no embargo, we could win and even if it doesn’t work in July, we could
                    prove to our public that we have done everything possible. If you can tell us
                    tomorrow what specifically you might be able to do.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: In what direction?</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: First, the renewal
                    of <gloss target="#t_UNEF_1">UNEF</gloss> for more than a year and afterwards
                    for annual periods. And the question of a warning station perhaps under <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> control. You could get a similar one. You might
                    also see whether there is something you can do on the boycott. Maybe you could
                    add some additional firms.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: Don’t ask this of me. The
                    boycott will raise havoc for me.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: You have agreed
                    selectively to remove some American firms. The boycott could be done
                    bilaterally.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: What if they refuse the
                    interim agreement?</p>
                <p>The President: We can go to the overall settlement.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: In such circumstances you
                    must be with me at Geneva. I have no objections to the United States having good
                    relations with Israel. As far as I am concerned, it can have the full protection
                    of the United States. If we go to Geneva, I shall anticipate we will be working
                    towards an overall solution with the United States taking the initiative.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: We probably can put
                    forward something on borders.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: Borders with minor
                    rectifications; demilitarized zones on both sides of the border.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It is important that
                    the Arabs not start a holy war against us if our overall settlement proposal is
                    not all that you want. If what America puts forward at Geneva is rebuffed by
                    both Arabs and Israelis it would be bad.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: I shall be raising hell
                    at Geneva but really agreeing with you.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Suppose we succeed
                    on an interim agreement in July. Can Syria be managed?</p>
                <pb facs="0683" n="657" xml:id="pg_657"/>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: There must be a Syrian
                    disengagement. This must be discussed before Geneva.</p>
                <p>The President: If we talk in terms of the 1967 borders isn’t that enough to keep
                    the Syrians quiet?</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>: No, there is jealousy.
                    The Soviets will find the basis to cause further difficulties. In any interim
                    agreement there has to be a change of a kilometer or two. And they settle for
                    that. (Conversation had to be terminated at that point because of schedule. It
                    was agreed that the talk would be continued at the next session.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
