<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>273. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d273</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">273</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1976-03-25T14:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-03-25T14:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-03-25T14:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-03-25T14:45:00-05:00" n="273"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d273">
                <head>273. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d273fn1"
                        >Source: Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, CL 347, Department of
                        State Memorandum of Conversations, Internal, December 1975–March 1976.
                        Secret; Sensitive.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1976-03-25T14:45:00-05:00"
                            >March 25, 1976, 2:45 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Deputy Assistant Secretary Day</item>
                    <item>Jock Covey, Notetaker</item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Lebanon</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Secretary: Have you seen the reply from <persName corresp="#p_KAH_1"
                        >Khaddam</persName>? (Damascus 1808)<note n="2" xml:id="d273fn2">Telegram
                        1808 from Damascus, March 25, transmitted <persName corresp="#p_KAH_1"
                            >Khaddam</persName>’s replies to the questions posed by the United
                        States in telegram 70097 to Damascus, March 24. (Library of Congress,
                        Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                        Papers, CL 237, Geopolitical File, Syria, March 1976)</note> What do you
                    think it means?</p>
                <pb facs="1000" n="974" xml:id="pg_974"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>: I think it means they want to
                    try to do it in a way that will avoid a direct confrontation with Israel.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: Where is Bekaa?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>: East and north of Beirut.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: I see that they gave us no real
                    idea of the time frame.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: What do you think?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: I personally think that they are
                    moving very fast now towards some sort of intervention. My own recommendation
                    would be that we tell the Israelis pretty quickly what is going on.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: Now all of this is said in the framework of a study being done by
                    the Foreign Minister that has not yet been submitted to the President.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>: I would be very surprised if
                    they moved before they had a response from us.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: Oh yes, I agree.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>: And I think we should wait to
                    hear from the Israelis before we go back to the Syrians.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: We’re not going to get a reply very fast.</p>
                <p>All right, I think we should get a message back to the Syrians quickly. Tell them
                    we are studying it but repeat our warning against any unilateral move and its
                    consequences. And I guess we might as well tell the Israelis what is going on.
                    (Secretary phones <persName corresp="#p_DS_1">Dinitz</persName>)</p>
                <p>Do you agree with what I told him?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: Okay, I think we can take our time drafting a reply. There’s no
                    need to shoot it right back.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: I personally see no sense in
                    sending it out before close of business tonight.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: But don’t tell anybody else about this.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: Henry, I just want you to know
                    that I am personally coming more and more to <persName corresp="#p_FI_1"
                        >Fahmy</persName>’s view—that is, of involving the United Nations Security
                    Council in this. You have seen his latest cable?<note n="3" xml:id="d273fn3">Not
                        further identified.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary: No, of course I haven’t seen his latest cable yet because it
                    probably hasn’t passed mustering among the geniuses in my outer office.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: Here, you can read mine. (The
                    Secretary reads cable)</p>
                <p>The Secretary: I think we better do a cable to <persName corresp="#p_FI_1"
                        >Fahmy</persName> telling what the difficulties are in going to the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Security Council, and I think we should sound
                    out the French.</p>
                <pb facs="1001" n="975" xml:id="pg_975"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: The French are working up an
                    initiative to move the question into the Security Council. Or possibly as a
                    combined French, British, US move. Of course, this would not affect the
                    situation on the ground.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: Well, then maybe we should do a message to the French to say that
                    we have had further world that the situation may be getting out of control.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: You know their man here in
                    Washington would be ideal. He’s the former Ambassador to the United Nations.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: Except that he is already on his way to Minnesota. Well, perhaps
                    he hasn’t actually left yet. (The Secretary asks for call to be put through to
                    Kosciusko-Morizet). After we do up this message I think you should get ahold of
                        <persName corresp="#p_RP_1">Ramsbotham</persName> and bring him up to
                    date.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: How much do you want to tell
                    him?</p>
                <p>The Secretary: I think you should give him the gist of the Syrian response. He is
                    the only European who knows about this, however, and I specifically don’t want
                    the French to be approached by the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> about the
                    Security Council thing before they get our message.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: I understand. (The Secretary
                    speaks to <gloss target="#t_Amb_1">Amb</gloss>. Kosciusko-Morizet)</p>
                <p>The Secretary: And I guess we had better tell <persName corresp="#p_DS_1"
                        >Dinitz</persName> right away. (Speaks to <persName corresp="#p_DS_1"
                        >Dinitz</persName>)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>: I think we have to keep one
                    thing in mind. This shouldn’t look like our idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: Especially since most of the
                    parties will be opposed to it.</p>
                <p>The Secretary: Oh we are not proposing it. That’s the beauty of it. That means
                    the French have to go around and sell it. Although perhaps I better call the
                    French Ambassador right back and make that clear.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>: I would put it in terms of the
                    great advantage to their doing this alone—not in terms of our
                    preference—otherwise that will make the French cool off. I think you have to
                    tell him, you alone is better because we would be suspect.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
