<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-01-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="8" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d8">
                        <head>8. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_2">Scowcroft</persName>) to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d8fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 44,
                                HAK Trip Files, January 10–20, 1974, Europe and Mid East State
                                Cables, Memos, Misc. Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. A
                                handwritten notation reads: “Back from President.”</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-01-16">January 16,
                                    1974</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> has asked
                            that you be passed the following report on his latest meetings with
                            President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>:</p>
                        <p>“1. After two meetings with <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>
                                today,<note n="2" xml:id="d8fn2">No memoranda of conversation have
                                been found. See <ref target="#d3fn2">footnote 2, Document 3</ref>.
                                According to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s
                                Record of Schedule, he met with <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> on January 16 from approximately 2:30 to 4:30
                                p.m. and approximately 8:15 to 9 p.m. (Library of Congress,
                                Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 438, Miscellany,
                                1968–76)</note> I can report that we are on the verge of an
                            agreement between Egypt and Israel on disengagement.</p>
                        <p>“2. In essence the agreement calls for:</p>
                        <p>“—Israeli withdrawal of its forces from the west and east of the Canal to
                            a line no more than 20 kilometers east of the Canal;</p>
                        <p>“—Egyptian forces maintain roughly their present line east of the
                            Canal;</p>
                        <p>“—A <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> buffer zone between the two
                            forces.</p>
                        <p>“3. <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> has accepted most of the
                            limitations on his forces which Israel has suggested; the few exceptions
                            relate to numerical strength and types of weaponry. I should be able to
                            get Israel’s agreement to the Egyptian exceptions tomorrow. I shall also
                            have to get Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Meir</persName>’s agreement
                            to release about 90 Egyptian <gloss target="#t_POW_1">POW</gloss>’s when
                            disengagement has been accomplished.</p>
                        <p>“4. In order to make all this possible <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> has agreed to:</p>
                        <p>“—A public document describing the three areas outlined above.</p>
                        <p>“—A classified letter from you to <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Meir</persName>
                            describing the limitations on Israeli and Egyptian forces and personnel.
                            Both leaders will sign this proposal on separate copies, thereby
                            incorporating it in the basic agreement.</p>
                        <p>“—A classified letter to you from <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> stating that Egypt will not interfere with free
                            passage of Israeli ships and cargoes through the straits south of
                            Israel, and that, after the Canal is opened, Egypt will allow Israeli
                            cargoes through immediately. <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> promises to permit free passage for Israeli ships
                            through the Canal when the state of belligerency has ended.</p>
                        <p>“5. We will also be providing <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Meir</persName>
                            with letters from you expressing satisfaction at the signing of the
                            agreement, and assuring <pb facs="0095" n="69" xml:id="pg_69"/> them
                            that we will do our utmost to see to it that it is fully implemented.
                            Finally, we will be transmitting to <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>, in a classified letter from you, the Prime
                            Minister’s assurance that Israel will not attack the civilian areas to
                            be established by <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> in the
                            Sinai.</p>
                        <p>“6. The existence of the classified documents listed in the two preceding
                            paragraphs is extremely sensitive. Public knowledge of their existence
                            could ruin the whole deal.</p>
                        <p>“7. Assuming I get <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Meir</persName>’s
                            concurrence to the remaining changes suggested by <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>, the plan is for a simultaneous
                            announcement on Thursday<note n="3" xml:id="d8fn3">January 17.</note> in
                            Jerusalem, Cairo and Washington at 9:00 p.m. Cairo/Tel Aviv time (3:00
                            p.m. Washington time).</p>
                        <p>“8. The announcement which <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>
                            has cleared and which we will be clearing with the Israelis tomorrow
                            reads as follows:</p>
                        <p>‛In accordance with the decision of the Geneva Conference, the
                            Governments of Egypt and Israel, with the assistance of the Government
                            of the United States, have reached agreement on the disengagement and
                            separation of their military forces. The agreement will be signed by the
                            Chiefs of Staff of Egypt and Israel at noon Egypt–Israel time, Friday,
                            January 18, at Kilometer 101 on the Cairo–Suez road. The Commander of
                            the United Nations Emergency Force, General <persName corresp="#p_SE_2">Siilasvuo</persName>, has been asked by the parties to witness the
                            signing.’</p>
                        <p>“9. We will be sending you a suggested draft statement you may wish to
                            make in Washington at the same time.</p>
                        <p>“10. President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> has asked me
                            to defer my visit to Damascus until after he, himself, has visited
                            there. He argues that if he first sets the stage for my visit with Asad,
                            my own visit may make it possible for us to get things moving with the
                            Syrians. Thus, <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> has
                            rearranged his own travel plans so that he can be in Damascus on
                            Saturday. I will follow him on Sunday, and then return to Washington
                            late Sunday evening.”</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>