<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-05-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-05-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="116" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 116.</seg></opener>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Smithers</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-05-04"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 4,
                            1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 431.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received Mr. Young’s dispatch No. 658,
                        dated the 23d February, with inclosure, informing the Department that he had
                        instructed the consul at Canton to recognize the right of John Frederick
                        Pearson to American citizenship, and have given it my careful attention as
                        well as Consul Sickels’ dispatch No. 135, of January 3, 1880, to the
                        Department, and Mr. Payson’s approval of his course in this matter, of March
                        24, 1880.</p>
                    <p>I inclose you an opinion on the question by the law officer of the Department
                        by which you will see that inasmuch as Pearson’s father was an American
                        citizen, the nationality of his mother previous to marriage would make no
                        difference in the son’s nationality, provided he was legitimate, unless the
                        father was a citizen of one of the States which prohibit marriage with
                        Chinese, of which there is no allegation in the present instance.</p>
                    <p>There appears to be no doubt of the son’s good faith, and in the previous
                        correspondence Consul Sickels speaks of him when at Bangkok as a young man
                        of good character, and very clearheaded and intelligent.</p>
                    <p>As regards his legitimacy, the best way to bring out the facts would be to
                        require Mr. Pearson to apply for a passport through the consul at Canton,
                        making an affidavit to the circumstances of his case as given in Consul
                        Seymour’s No. 101, of January 24 last, and substantiating it with
                        certificates of his birth and of his parents’ marriage at Shanghai, by Rev.
                        Father Desaggrue, which you say appears on the records of the Catholic
                        church. This will make a complete record of the case, one copy of which can
                        remain on the files of your legation, and another may be sent to this
                        Department.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>T. F. BAYARD.</signed></closer>
                    <pb facs="0300" n="172" xml:id="pg_172"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 431.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Law
                                        Bureau</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-04-29"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 29,
                                1885</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The prevalent opinion undoubtedly is that the fourteenth amendment of the
                            Constitution of the United States does not confer citizenship on Chinese
                            not born in the United States. We have several adjudications from
                            Federal, circuit, and district courts to this effect, and although the
                            question has not been definitely settled by the Supreme Court of the
                            United States, yet not only from the terms of the amendment, but from
                            the weight of authority, I must hold that there can be no such
                            citizenship of Chinese born in China. But whether the legitimate child
                            of an American citizen, such child being born in China from a Chinese
                            mother, is an American citizen, is an entirely different question. As a
                            general rule the legitimate children of American citizens born abroad
                            partake of their father’s nationality. Were the question before us
                            whether or no an illegitimate child of an American citizen by a Chinese
                            woman would be an American citizen, the conclusion might be different;
                            but I can see nothing in the fact that the mother is a Chinese that
                            takes the case out of the general rule, that the child of an American
                            citizen born abroad acquires its father’s nationality. If such is the
                            case, the law that governs is the law of the father’s domicile.</p>
                        <p>There are, I believe, one or two States in the Union which prohibit the
                            marriage of white citizens with Chinese. There is no allegation in the
                            present case, however, that the father of the child, whose status is now
                            investigated, was domiciled in one of these States. I must, therefore,
                            hold that the child in question is <hi rend="italic">prima facie</hi> a
                            citizen of the United States. No doubt the case may be embarrassed by
                            the statement in Mr. Seymour’s dispatch, hereto annexed, that the
                            question as to whether this son “was born in wedlock is not settled”;
                            but the rule of law undoubtedly is that, in doubtful cases, the
                            presumption in favor of legitimacy is to control, and the conclusion,
                            therefore, must be that John Frederick Pearson, whose rights are here
                            investigated, being a legitimate son of Frederick Pearson, by a Chinese
                            wife, assumes his father’s nationality. This view is strengthened by the
                            fact that a woman’s nationality merges on marriage in that of her
                            husband, and the Chinese wife of Frederick Pearson became, by the mere
                            fact of her marriage, an American citizen. The difficulty which
                            encounters us in the present case, however, is one that is independent
                            of the rules I have just stated. While the law is indisputable that the
                            child of an American father, born abroad, takes his father’s nationality
                            when an infant, I apprehend that the rule also is settled that when he
                            arrives at full age he may elect or surrender such nationality and
                            accept that of the country of his birth and residence. The preponderance
                            of authority is that when such election is made it is final. The facts
                            which are rather referred to than stated, in the accompanying dispatch,
                            render it doubtful whether John Frederick Pearson made this election on
                            arriving at full age. If he did I hold that the election was final and
                            cannot be reviewed or recalled by any subsequent action on his part. But
                            the evidence as to this specific issue being by no means as full as
                            could be desired, I submit that the papers be remanded to the United
                            States minister in China for the purpose of further inquiry.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully submitted.</p>
                        <closer><signed>FRANCIS WHARTON,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Law
                                Officer.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>