<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Scruggs to Mr. Bayard..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1885</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d162</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">162</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-07-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-07-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-07-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-07-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="162"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d162">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 162.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Scruggs</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bogota</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-07-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 21, 1885</date>. (Received September
                        15.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 221.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: There have been no important changes in the
                    military situation since the abandonment of the siege of Carthagena. It is
                    believed here that the insurgents are still fortified in Barranquilla. They
                    certainly have possession of the Magdalena River from the Delta to Naré, a
                    distance of nearly 600 miles.</p>
                <p>It is true the Government forces hold the canal between Carthagena <pb
                        facs="0345" n="217" xml:id="pg_217"/> and Calamar, and that they have
                    entrenched themselves at the last-named place. Calamar is a town of some 5,000
                    inhabitants, situated at the junction of the Carthagena Canal and the Magdalena
                    River, 62 miles above Barranquilla. But the river at that point is very wide,
                    and its banks flat and marshy; so that without gunboats or other floating
                    batteries, the national forces, however numerous and well armed, cannot prevent
                    the passage of the rebel steamers.</p>
                <p>The Government has infantry forces stationed at different points on the river
                    between Calamar and Naré; and on the 17th ult. a general engagement took place
                    near Humareda, some 16 leagues below Naré. The loss on both sides was
                    considerable, and one of the rebel gunboats was blown up. But it was essentially
                    a drawn battle, without decisive results.</p>
                <p>The entire rebel force probably numbers only about 3,500 men, but generally well
                    armed and equipped. All the river steamers except one have been in their
                    possession since December last. The exception referred to is the Emelia Duran, a
                    light-draught vessel of less than 150 tons, designed for navigating the Upper
                    Magcjalena, between Handa and Ambalema. Some weeks ago she was brought down
                    below the Rapids and armed by the Government for defensive operations on the
                    lower river.</p>
                <p>The Government claims to have 12,000 men under arms. Its efficient armed force is
                    about 8,000. These are distributed over different parts of the Republic, its
                    efficient force on the line of the river being about 6,000 men. They are
                    generally well armed and disciplined and commanded by able and experienced
                    officers.</p>
                <p>In the interior, off the line of the river, all seems to be quiet. Occasional
                    raiding parties penetrate within a few leagues of the capital and render
                    telegraphic and mail communication with the Pacific coast uncertain. But aside
                    from these predatory excursions the authority of the General Government is not
                    contested.</p>
                <p>However, with the great fluvial highway in the possession of the insurgents,
                    Bogota is practically under siege, as it has been since the 25th December last.
                    There is also a factious and insurrectionary spirit among the people in nearly
                    all the interior states. The Government troops have not been paid for nearly two
                    months past, and there is said to be dissatisfaction in consequence. One of the
                    Government generals, Aldana, has retired from the service, and is known to be
                    disaffected. He is at the present time governor of the State of Cundinamarca,
                    and very popular with the masses. So that, unless the insurgents should be
                    dislodged from their stronghold in the Magdalena Valley before the fever season
                    fairly sets in, there may be a second outbreak in the interior and northern
                    States, the end whereof no man can tell.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM L. SCRUGGS.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
