<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Bayard to Mr. Thompson..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1885</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d382</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">382</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-10-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-10-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="382"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d382">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 382.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Thompson</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-10-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 2, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 24.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I herewith inclose a copy of a letter from Mr. C.
                    A. Van Bokkelen, of the 19th ultimo, in reference to his illegal imprisonment at
                    Port-au-Prince and his claim for damages in consequence thereof.</p>
                <p>In view of Mr. Van Bokkelen’s present statement of facts and those already before
                    your legation in regard to his case, I desire that you will call the attention
                    of the Government of Hayti to his claim. There can be no doubt that Mr. Van
                    Bokkelen was wrongfully imprisoned by the Haytian authorities and that great
                    damage accrued to him thereby.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances, therefore, you are directed to ask and to press for
                    the redress claimed by Mr. Van Bokkelen, or, if the amount to be paid cannot be
                    immediately agreed upon, for a reference of the question to an arbitrator, so
                    that the case may be disposed of without unnecessary delay.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>T. F. BAYARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 24.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Van Bokkelen</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>504 <hi rend="smallcaps">Clinton Avenue, Brooklyn, N. Y.</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-09-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 19, 1885</date>. (Received
                            September 28.)</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: Upon receiving reply to my letter
                        addressed to your Department, inquiring as to rights possessed by American
                        citizens residing in Hayti, under articles 6 and 9 of treaty, 1864, I made
                        an assignment of $56,000 in favor of my creditors. This was done in 1882, at
                        the civil court in Port-au-Prince, depositing in due form my assets of
                        $56,000; liabilities, $10,500. This remained before the court a year and a
                        half without action, no attempt being made to molest me. On March 5, 1883, I
                        was arrested on the street by order of the judge of the civil court. The law
                        distinctly states that no foreigner of any nationality shall be arrested
                        without the order of <pb facs="0666" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/> arrest and
                        the judgment on which he is arrested having first been submitted to the
                        attorney-general of the Government, for his revision, and then only on his
                        approval, signature, and seal can the foreigner be put in confinement.</p>
                    <p>These important and, to me, valued formalities being entirely overlooked, and
                        notwithstanding the attention of the judge and jailor being most positively
                        called to this fatal omission, I was thrust into jail. This law had been
                        made by the Government expressly to prevent the arrest of foreigners until
                        the Government could itself act advisedly in each case as it arose, having
                        had previously to pay for each illegal arrest.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Garrido, secretary to the United States legation, had been arrested a few
                        days previous for debt, and great care was taken to have all the formalities
                        complied with. Is not the law the same with the native born as the
                        naturalized?</p>
                    <p>Thus being put in jail illegally by the judge, I addressed myself to the
                        general term court to annul my imprisonment, not on the violation of the law
                        by the Government, but on the illegality of the judgment on which I was
                        imprisoned. At this trial the same judge presiding (who had refused me this
                        right) the judgment was annulled and I was ordered to be put at liberty;
                        this proving, had in the first instance the formalities of the law been
                        complied with, I never would have entered the jail. Here was the first
                        illegal and arbitrary action on the part of the Haytian officials.</p>
                    <p>Being put at liberty by the court I demanded of the jailor to be let go, when
                        he informed me that I had been recommitted by the Haytians (Mr. St. Ande,
                        Nadal, and Delencourt) in virtue of the laws of Hayti, 1843, giving Haytians
                        the right to detain a foreigner in jail, without right of bail, until they,
                        the Haytians, could present to the court their claim and have the matter
                        adjusted and decided for or against.</p>
                    <p>Finding myself then barred from all justice, illegally imprisoned, I moved
                        the civil court to take action on the assignment made by me one and a half
                        year previous. A date was fixed for hearing, when my creditors presenting
                        themselves accepted my assignment, thus virtually giving me liberty. The
                        court took the papers, reserving its decision. At the lapse of twenty days a
                        decision was handed down, that notwithstanding the acceptance of my
                        creditors (that), being an American citizen, I was not entitled to my
                        liberty, and that articles 6 and 9 of the treaty never intended it, and that
                        I must remain in jail.</p>
                    <p>Of this decision I informed your Department and received for reply “that I
                        must fulfill all the formalities of the law in Hayti and that I would be
                        protected.”</p>
                    <p>After awaiting all of the delays of the law, and having a written opinion of
                        the attorney-general of Hayti, addressed to the United States minister, that
                        I had the right under articles 6 and 9 of the treaty to make an assignment,
                        and the formal promise of Mr. B. St. Victor, minister of foreign affairs,
                        that the supreme court would see justice done, I appealed to that tribunal,
                        obtained a hearing, and after fifteen days was informed that it was of
                        opinion that I did not have the rights claimed under the treaty. This result
                        was communicated to the Department and action taken, my release being
                        demanded, arrest declared illegal and against the rules of the civilized
                        nations, and in violation of the treaty rights. Four times was my release
                        demanded by my Government, and when at last, in the most positive terms, did
                        you again demand it, with indemnity for illegal acts, did reason prevail. On
                        May 27 I was taken by the Government attorney from jail, where I had been
                        illegally confined fourteen months and twenty days, to the United States
                        legation and delivered to the United States minister, who asked by what
                        process and how I was brought there, and received for reply that the
                        President would explain to the United States Government. The only
                        explanation given, notwithstanding the frequent and positive refusal of the
                        courts and Haytian Government to release and accord me the rights of an
                        American citizen as guaranteed by treaty, is, as far as I know, to be found
                        in the message of President Solomen to the General Assembly, in which he
                        says that on the demand of you, the Honorable Secretary, he had put me at
                        liberty.</p>
                    <p>There exists on the prison books at Port-au-Prince, relative to my discharge,
                        the notice “that, on account of ill-health, the parties by whom I had been
                        confined consent to the discharge.”</p>
                    <p>In view of the foregoing facts it is clearly and indisputably shown— <list>
                            <label>1st.</label>
                            <item>I was imprisoned illegally fourteen months, twenty-two days,
                                proved by the papers on which I was imprisoned being annulled and
                                declared informal by the court ordering my confinement; and had the
                                formalities of the law been complied with in the first instance I
                                would not have been put into jail and obliged to suffer from the
                                illegal action of the courts.</item>
                            <label>2d.</label>
                            <item>Had I not been illegally confined I would not have been
                                recommitted by the Haytians, thus being detained without right to
                                give bail.</item>
                            <label>3d.</label>
                            <item>The civil court giving judgment and refusing my liberty,
                                notwithstanding the acceptance by my creditors, without judging on
                                the merits of the case, simply because I was an American citizen,
                                did wilfully deprive me of my treaty rights and liberty, illegally
                                causing my detention in jail.</item>
                            <pb facs="0667" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/>
                            <label>4th.</label>
                            <item>The supreme court of Hayti again committed the same illegal and
                                arbitrary-action, maintaining decision of civil court, and thus
                                refusing my rights, as proved by my release by the Government after
                                oft-repeated demands.</item>
                            <label>5th.</label>
                            <item>That I am justly due and entitled to compensation of $200 for each
                                and every day from the day that I was deprived of my liberty, and
                                denied rights guaranteed by articles 6 and 9 of the treaty, simply
                                on the ground that being an American citizen I had not the same
                                rights as a Haytian as regards an assignment, and $500 per day for
                                each and every day I was deprived of my liberty, from the time the
                                demand was made by our minister direct to the Haytian Government,
                                until final release, and for which compensation I have made claim
                                through our minister in Port-au-Prince. For such compensation the
                                Haytian Government has certainly confessed its liability by the fact
                                that it has satisfied the original claim, for which I was first
                                thrown into prison, and also the claims of the Haytians upon whose
                                recommendation I was continued, and by holding said payments as
                                offsets against damages claimed by me, and which my Government will,
                                I know, see are promptly satisfied, as in its demand for my release
                                it formally declared to the Haytian Government that I was entitled
                                to just and due compensation for my illegal detention. I therefore,
                                in consideration of my health being destroyed, unable to carry on my
                                business, which was one of the best in Hayti, come again to ask, Mr.
                                Secretary, that positive instructions be given our minister resident
                                in Hayti that he must forcibly call the attention of the Haytian
                                Government to the necessity of a prompt and speedy settlement, and
                                also see that some proper and public announcement be made, so that
                                all will know that not from any criminal act was I thrown into a
                                loathsome prison, but because being an American citizen, I suffered;
                                that in future all claiming the same blessed privilege would have
                                their rights respected, and that although born in that country my
                                children would not be ashamed of their nationality.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The documents in proof of all the foregoing are on file in your
                        Department.</p>
                    <p>I, therefore, Mr. Secretary, pray that my case will meet your careful and
                        prompt attention, and not be allowed to slumber.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>C. A. VON BOKKELEN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
