<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Thompson to Mr. Bayard..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1885</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d383</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">383</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-10-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-10-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-10-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-10-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="383"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d383">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 383.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Thompson</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Port-au-Prince, Hayti</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-10-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 17, 1885</date>. (Received Oct.
                        31.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 44.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Reports received from Cape Haytien indicate since
                    the arrival there of General Brenor Prophète, minister of war and marine, strong
                    measures have been taken to find out those persons connected with the insurgent
                    movement of the 11th ultimo. It appears that a person named Albaret Laroche, who
                    was active in the late insurrection, was secreted on board of a French bark, the
                    Panama, which was loading in the port of Cape Haytien. The authorities therefore
                    asked permission of the French vice-consul to go on board of that vessel for the
                    purpose of arresting the man. The vice-consul communicated with the legation of
                    France in this city for instructions. In the mean time boats surrounded the
                    Panama, and remained there day and night to prevent the man escaping. The French
                    minister refused them permission to go on board. Consequently the authorities
                    would not expedite the vessel, hoping they could prevail upon the French
                    minister to give up the man. Finding eventually that he would not do so, they
                    allowed the Panama to leave with the revolutionist on board.</p>
                <p>Communicating these facts opens for me a channel of inquiry, and I would
                    respectfully ask the view of the Department in such a case, viz, where a
                    revolution has taken place and parties connected therewith seek refuge in an
                    American vessel. A case of the kind I believe is without precedent here, but in
                    a country like this, where insurrections are liable to spring up at any moment,
                    I deem it worthy of attention to prepare for contingencies.</p>
                <pb facs="0668" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/>
                <p>In asking advice with regard to a possibility of this kind, I do not lose sight
                    of articles 39 and 41 of our treaty with Hayti, neither do I neglect the
                    established rules of international law, but it must also be remembered that
                    generally in these revolutionary movements sundry persons are killed, as
                    happened in the affair at Cape Haytien. Under those circumstances, although it
                    would be difficult to distinguish the perpetrator of the murder, it cannot be
                    denied that any one of the revolutionists was liable to be the guilty party.</p>
                <p>With the hope that I may receive a dispatch with reference to this question,</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOHN E. W. THOMPSON.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
