<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-11-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="387" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d387">
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 387.</seg></opener>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Thompson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Bayard</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Port-au-Prince,
                                    Hayti</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-05"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 5, 1885</date>.
                            (Received Nov. 18.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 50.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to produce, as herewith
                        inclosed, two communications from Mr. Alexander C. d’Almena, the American
                        citizen who was held in the common jail of this city, charged with the
                        purloining of certain mandates, to the detriment of the National Bank of
                        Hayti. The inclosed statement brings forth all the facts of the case. There
                        has been no official statement of the trial published.</p>
                    <p>I attended many days during the proceedings of the “court of cassation,” and
                        it was remarked daily that all the evidence produced in the prosecution was
                        in favor of Mr. d’Almena; indeed, the attorney-general almost ignored any
                        statement with regard to our citizen. At the end of the thirteen days he was
                        acquitted, with two others, a British subject and a Haytian citizen.</p>
                    <p>Since the trial the attorney-general and his deputy have been suspended from
                        office.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JOHN E. W. THOMPSON.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 50.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">d’Almena</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Thompson</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-10-01"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 1,
                                1885</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Honorable Sir</hi>: As a loyal American citizen, I
                            have the honor to bring under your notice the following case of denial
                            of justice, wanton violence, arbitrary imprisonment, and persecution, of
                            which I have been a victim at the hands of the Haytian Government, the
                            facts of which are as follows:</p>
                        <p>By order of the judge “d’instruction,” Mr. Ernest Bonhomme, of the civil
                            tribunal of Port-au-Prince, I was arrested on the 10th of December,
                            1884, falsely accused of complicity in an embezzlement of public
                            effects, to the detriment of the National Banking Company of Hayti,
                            alleged to have been committed by a Mr. F. B. Coles, at the time when
                            the latter was chief accountant in the aforesaid establishment. Seized
                            upon by the police, I was forcibly conveyed to the prison of this city,
                            and at once placed in special confinement (“au secret”); that is, shut
                            up in a narrow, filthy cell, devoid of light, and the suffocating air
                            contaminated by its noxious proximity to a cesspool liberating foul
                            stenches, provocative of infectious disease. It was in this hole that I
                            was kept in close confinement for the space of fifteen consecutive days
                            and nights, at the end of which time only, the judge thought fit to
                            cause the door to be opened, and it was only then that your predecessor,
                            Mr. J. M. Langston, who had <pb facs="0672" n="544" xml:id="pg_544"/>
                            vainly endeavored hitherto to obtain access to me, was enabled to
                            inspect the horrible den in which I had been confined, in contempt of
                            the most elementary principles of humanity.</p>
                        <p>I have every reason to believe that these persecutions were the result of
                            a preconcerted plot contrived to ruin my credit and bring disgrace upon
                            me, a conviction which I no longer doubted, when, on my insisting that I
                            should be brought face to face with my calumniators who had declared
                            that I had received $1,000, the amount of a public effect twice paid, I
                            was told by the inquiring judge <hi rend="italic">that it would be time
                                enough for that when the assizes came on.</hi></p>
                        <p>Events have proved that they were evidently resolved to persecute an
                            innocent man, and it was only on the 19th instant that I recovered my
                            liberty, after having endured a most cruel imprisonment of 283 days, and
                            been placed for thirteen days more on the criminal benches at the public
                            assizes of a country where the dispensation of law is a mockery and
                            simply a tool in the hands of those who ought to administer it with the
                            greatest impartiality. Although during the private examination prior to
                            the trial they could bring forward no proof of my guilt, they
                            nevertheless kept me in prison and strenuously refused bail.</p>
                        <p>I would respectfully beg to call your attention to the fact that I am a
                            man of 52 years of age, and have all my life enjoyed a stainless
                            reputation for honor, and have been surrounded with all that commands
                            private and public respect. The Haytian authorities however, did not
                            hesitate to hold me up to the public in the light of a miscreant thief
                            worthy of a convict prison, in order more fully to crush and humiliate
                            me in that which a man holds dearest, his character and his honor,
                            Indeed, during the preliminary investigations they obstinately
                            disregarded all evidence of the truth and discarded every principle of
                            justice, and, basing themselves solely on false accusations and
                            groundless assertions, they decided, on the 14th of March last, that I
                            should be remanded until the assizes and take trial in the criminal
                            dock, this time as <hi rend="italic">an author</hi> of the theft of the
                            public effects to the prejudice of the National Bank of Hayti.</p>
                        <p>By this act of wanton injustice and refined persecution on the part of
                            the judicial council chamber of Port-au-Prince, I was struck in my
                            nearest interests, for, contrary to the usage and practice of the
                            Haytian law, they published this decision in the official journal of the
                            Republic (Le Moniteur), knowing that copies of it are regularly sent
                            abroad, where the effect was calculated to utterly ruin my credit and my
                            interests. Happily, however, in doing this they did not calculate upon
                            the evidence it contained against them of their preconcerted decisions.
                            Such a decision was too unjust, and wanting in all spirit of fair play
                            and equity to be overlooked, and I attacked it in the court of appeal of
                            Port-au-Prince. I did so not only on the plea of its want of equity, but
                            also on several technical flaws it contained. It is needless to add that
                            the appeal was without effect, the court coming to two decisions dated
                            1st and 17th July, 1885, maintaining the former decision of the council
                            chamber, and ignoring my appeal altogether, thus clearly setting forth
                            their premeditated intention of committing and maintaining a complete
                            denial of justice.</p>
                        <p>I must remark that at the same time I lodged, as you are doubtless aware,
                            my formal protest in the hands of your predecessor, both against the
                            writ of the council chamber, and also these two latter decisions, which
                            caused me to undergo the ordeal, though innocent, of a trial in a
                            criminal court. During this trial, which lasted thirteen days, it is
                            noteworthy to remark that all the witnesses for the prosecution gave
                            evidence in my favor, and also that the public prosecutor
                            (attorney-general) himself throughout was completely embarrassed, and
                            totally at a loss to bring forward the slightest fact in proof of my
                            would be guilt, and up to the end was unable to say a word tending to
                            prove that I was in any way concerned in the matter with which I was
                            charged, his only statement being false and empty insinuations to my
                            discredit. I came out of prison innocent and acquitted, it is true, but
                            with the stigma of a criminal jail hanging about me, and having to bear
                            the consequences of the terrible sufferings of a contaminating
                            confinement of more than nine months.</p>
                        <p>The positive damages which this odious and unjust trial has occasioned me
                            are nevertheless immense. When one takes into account that on my arrival
                            here I held a contract with a financial establishment of Paris (of which
                            there is a legalized copy in the hands of his Excellency the President
                            of Hayti), engaging itself to furnish, progressively, funds to the
                            extent of 15,000,000 francs for the establishment of central sugar
                            factories in the plains of “Cul de Sac” and the “Grand Plain,”
                            ultimately to be connected by railways; to further connect the “Etang
                            Salé” with the sea by steam navigation, and to develop the exploitation
                            of the rich timber forests in that district, and, lastly, to found in
                            Port-au-Prince a banking establishment, with branch associations, for a
                            “crédit foncier et agricole.” The industry and technical knowledge I was
                            furnishing to this enterprise was estimated at the sum of 500,000
                            francs, which, bearing interest, was to form my capital. Apart from
                            this, I was to receive annually a sum of $20,000 for my expenses,
                            administration, displacements, &amp;c. All this was on the eve of being
                            realized, and already one of the chief capitalists was to start for <pb facs="0673" n="545" xml:id="pg_545"/> Port-au-Prince, on the 21st of
                            December, 1884, from Paris, when the news arrived there, on the 15th
                            December of that year (by cable), of my arrest here for my connection in
                            the embezzlement of public effects from the National Bank of Hayti. As
                            soon as the news was confirmed, the fate of all my future prospects was
                            naturally doomed.</p>
                        <p>The news of the arrest of a man of such good repute and on such a charge
                            created the greatest astonishment, but when came the announcement of the
                            decision of the council chamber of the 14th March 1885, published as it
                            was in the official journal of the Haytian Government, the final blow
                            was struck and I was simply ruined. Thus, not content with having
                            violently assailed without cause the character and standing of an
                            innocent man in their own country, the Haytian Government must needs
                            disgrace him abroad, and even before the rendering of the verdict they
                            must, by aid of their official means, hold him up to public odium and
                            scorn. I will not expatiate any longer on the injustice I suffered at
                            the hands of the authorities here.</p>
                        <p>The harm occasioned to me by the Haytian Government, both morally and
                            physically, by an imprisonment as trying as it was arbitrary, and as
                            long as unjust in the jail of this city, under a false and slandering
                            accusation devoid of the least particle of evidence to support it; the
                            great publicity given to the decision of the 14th March, 1885, by the
                            Government official journal, wholly based on suppositions, occasioning
                            the loss of my credit and financial and industrial combinations; and,
                            lastly, the denial of justice committed to my prejudice by the supreme
                            court of appeal, on the application I made, the principal object of
                            which was to spare my having to sit in the criminal dock, innocent
                            though I was, and exposed to the derision and even contempt of the
                            public (causing me thus to drink the bitter cup of shame to its very
                            dregs)—are not these weighty wrongs, at however just pecuniary value one
                            may estimate them, of a nature never adequately to be compensated by
                            their authors towards their victim?</p>
                        <p>The answer is plain, and I think that in naming $1,000 per day, that is,
                            $283,000 as compensation for the 283 days passed in the prison cells of
                            this city, on the one hand, and of $200,000, in all $483,000, taking as
                            a basis five years only of my aforesaid industrial administration and my
                            500,000 francs’ capital, on the other, as reparation and indemnity for
                            the material wrongs inflicted on me by the arbitrary persecutions of
                            which I have been the object, from December last to the day of my
                            release, 19th of September of this year, will be but a feeble estimate
                                <hi rend="italic">in money</hi> of the irreparable wrongs and losses
                            which I have had to bear at the hands of those by whom they have been
                            inflicted.</p>
                        <p>I have, therefore, sir, the honor to hand over to you the present
                            statement and claim, for the length of which I must apologize, begging
                            you, at the same time, to use your good offices to obtain from the
                            Haytian Government that compensation to which you will agree with me I
                            am so justly entitled.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>C. <hi rend="smallcaps">d</hi>’ALMENA.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 50.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">d’Almena</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Thompson</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince, Hayti</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-10-23"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 23, 1885</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Honorable Minister</hi>: Without wishing to modify
                            any of the considerations advanced in the statement, of date 10th of
                            this month, which I had the honor to lodge with you for the information
                            of yourself and of my Government, in support of my claim against the
                            Government of Hayti, it may not be superfluous to call your further
                            attention to the following facts, for the consideration of the honorable
                            the Secretary of State and Cabinet of the United States Government: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>No law has ever existed, nor does at present exist, with
                                    reference to the “Banque Nationale d’Hayti” which can justify my
                                    arrest, based upon the conditions and circumstances of fact or
                                    of reason, which have preceded, accompanied, or followed, the
                                    unjust imprisonment of which I have been the victim during so
                                    many months. For this reason, the “juge d’instruction”
                                    (magistrate who conducted the preliminary examination of the
                                    case) was obliged to allege in his commitment, as a motive for
                                    my imprisonment and solitary confinement (“secret”), my
                                    pretended participation in a breach of confidence of which one
                                    Mr. F. B. Coles, chief accountant at the “banque,” and then “en
                                    fuite,” was accused of being the principal. Later on, it became
                                    evident that my pretended complicity was but a pretext, not a
                                    legal motive for placing me under arrest; that this complicity
                                    was so unfounded that they subsequently abandoned it to make me
                                    one of the principals in a domestic robbery of public securities
                                    committed at the “Banque Nationale d’Hayti,” and to the
                                    prejudice of said “banque.”</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>After having thus proceeded—that is to say, in the absence of
                                    any legal provision—without any law foreseeing or determining,
                                    from a penal standpoint, the proper <pb facs="0674" n="546" xml:id="pg_546"/> and exact character of the facts on which,
                                    notwithstanding, the prosecution against me was based, they did
                                    not hesitate, the victim being once secured and thrown by force
                                    into a dungeon in contempt of all law, to pursue thenceforth a
                                    course in violation of justice. Later on still, in contempt of
                                    all the testimony previously given before the “juge
                                    d’instruction,” establishing my complete innocence—for, repeated
                                    orally before the jury, said testimony has established how the
                                    real facts were falsified by both said magistrate and the
                                    “chamber du conseil” (a sort of secret grand jury)—in order to
                                    arraign me before the criminal court (assizes), I was accused
                                    gratuitously, wickedly, and without the least reasonable
                                    presumption, of being one of the principals of said domestic
                                    robbery, although the facts, such as they were developed at the
                                    preliminary examination, constituted neither domestic nor simply
                                    robbery, nor any other offense qualified crime by the laws of
                                    Hayti or of any other country. In default of Mr. F. B. Coles,
                                    then absent from the country, it is obvious that they wanted to
                                    lay hands on some high officer of the “banque,” on whom to
                                    saddle a responsibility which they had taken off the shoulders
                                    of the director, to whom a “safe-conduct” was granted for
                                    leaving the country, but in fact to discharge the bank’s
                                    administration of the obligation of paying the securities
                                    fraudulently placed in circulation.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>It is therefore evident and incontestable that I have been
                                    arbitrarily and illegally proceeded against, thrown into a
                                    “cachot,” kept in secret confinement under the false accusation
                                    of having committed or participated in a domestic robbery, the
                                    indictment itself being false and defective in legal
                                    form.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>I could not allow such a gross illegality to be perpetrated
                                    against me without appealing to the supreme court (“cour de
                                    cassation”), for a condemnation and reversal of the foregoing
                                    proceedings, and I did appeal accordingly. But it was in vain,
                                    in support of my appeal, that the strongest and most
                                    unretortable legal facts and arguments were presented, among
                                    others, the precedents established by the supreme court itself
                                    during many years, the resolution had been taken beforehand to
                                    place me in the criminal dock.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The most outrageous denial of justice has been committed by the supreme
                            court of Hayti in contempt of all my rights. Two judgments, the second
                            intended to rectify and explain the other, dated the 1st and 17th of
                            July, of this year, were rendered by the supreme court on the appeals of
                            two other persons accused at the same time and of the same crime (both
                            being British subjects), which appeals were made, like mine, against the
                            said indictment dated the 14th of March, which sent them for trial
                            before the criminal court of this city; but, in defiance of every legal
                            principle, the said supreme court refused to examine my appeal, and
                            consequently did not render judgment at all upon it, although the appeal
                            was based upon the text of the law governing the proceedings of
                            preliminary examination in criminal cases.</p>
                        <p>A formal protest was addressed at this time by the Hon. Dr. Thompson—I
                            mean yourself—to the secretary of state for foreign affairs of Hayti,
                            with regard to this attitude of the supreme court towards me. In answer
                            to this protest the Haytian secretary of foreign affairs advanced to the
                            American legation all sorts of considerations irrelevant to the question
                            at issue, and failing to justify the attitude of the supreme court with
                            regard to my appeal. In that response the Haytian secretary of foreign
                            affairs asserted, among other things, that “the appeal of Mr. d’Almena
                            aimed at a destruction of all grave presumptions both against himself
                            and against those accused with him” (a consequence which would
                            inevitably have followed if the appeal had been admitted as it ought to
                            have been), as if there existed in that fact any motive which could
                            justify the supreme court in refusing an examination of my appeal.</p>
                        <p>It was also affirmed in this same dispatch of the Haytian minister that
                            “it is the fact itself with which all the accused are charged that
                            constitutes the object of Mr. d’Almena’s appeal.” How could my appeal
                            have any other object than that of the accusation itself, based, as it
                            was, precisely on the very same consideration mentioned in the first
                            provision of article 205 of the “Code d’Instruction Criminelle,” which
                            clearly declares that the fact charged against me is not qualified as a
                            crime? The inference is self-evident.</p>
                        <p>The same dispatch adds further, that “the maintenance of the bill of
                            indictment by the supreme court is <hi rend="italic">a proof</hi> that
                            the fact, which is the object of the prosecution, constitutes a crime in
                            the eye of the law.”</p>
                        <p>Here one is forced to demand how a fact, bad in itself, is able to become
                            good by simply maintaining this same fact in its primitiveness without
                            the least modification? In other words, how could the bill of indictment
                            of the 14th March, 1885, framed contrary to the law (see first provision
                            or clause of article 205 of the Code d’Instruction Criminelle), become
                            conformable to the law because simply of its having been maintained as
                            such by the supreme court?</p>
                        <p>The denial of justice enacted by a subservient court has evidently filled
                            up the measure of all that I was made to suffer physically and morally
                            during the 283 days of my imprisonment in one of the “cachots” of
                            Port-au-Prince, from the first hour of my arrest, to the day when I was
                            set at liberty, thanks to Divine Providence. <pb facs="0675" n="547" xml:id="pg_547"/> That my innocence was and is unquestionable is
                            clear from the fact that a jury, however bribed and menaced as they
                            were, shrunk from the awful responsibility of returning a verdict
                            against me.</p>
                        <p>On submitting, honorable minister, both this explanation and the
                            statement, dated the 10th of the present month, alluded to above, to you
                            as the representative of my Government, I respectfully request that you
                            will cause an official certificate of the deposit of these documents at
                            the legation to be delivered to me, and, upon due consideration of all
                            the circumstances, inform me whether a doubt may exist of the
                            responsibility of the Haytian Goverment for the outrages committed
                            against my liberty, honor, and interests, in order that the damages
                            which I have sustained may be immediately repaired.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>C. <hi rend="smallcaps">d</hi>’ALMENA.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>P. S.—As another evident proof of the long-entertained conviction of
                                my innocence in “high spheres,” I beg to subjoin a number, dated the
                                26th September last, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>, eight days after
                                my release, of the “Œil,” a newspaper which receives subsidies from
                                the Government, and is owned and acknowledged as being the
                                semi-official organ of same. This spontaneous declaration reads as
                                follows:</p>
                            <p>“We have announced in our last number the acquittal of Mr. d’Almena.
                                For our part, we had never entertained a doubt on that matter.”</p>
                            <closer><signed>C. <hi rend="smallcaps">d</hi>’A.</signed></closer>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>