<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1884-12-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1884-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="415" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d415">
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 415.</seg></opener>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Frelinghuysen</persName> to
                            Mr. <persName type="to">Morgan</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-12-20"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 20,
                            1884</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 698.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am in receipt of your telegram of the 17th
                        instant to the effect that your official diplomatic intervention in behalf
                        of Monahan, had, on the ground that he is not matriculated, been refused by
                        the Mexican Government.</p>
                    <p>This telegram is assumed to be in response to the Department’s instruction,
                        instructing you to present evidence of Monahan’s citizenship. The object was
                        to place on record in that case, as in any other of the same character which
                        may arise, our official non-acceptance of the Mexican doctrine of
                        matriculation.</p>
                    <p>There is perhaps in the relations of the two countries no one subject upon
                        which an accord is more necessary than this of the right of the citizens of
                        the one country in the territory of the other to the protection of their own
                        Government. The Mexican law of matriculation seeks to impair this
                        inalienable duty of protection by making its exercise depend <pb facs="0699" n="571" xml:id="pg_571"/> upon a domestic law of one of the parties. We
                        hold, in broad terms, that it is not within the scope of municipal
                        legislation to impair the relation of an alien toward his own Government, or
                        to impair the international right of his Government, as one among equals in
                        the community of states, to intervene with another Government to secure him
                        justice.</p>
                    <p>It is desired that you submit to the Department a report on this submit,
                        which may be laid before Congress. This report should show— <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>The provisions of the Mexican matriculation law.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>Whether applicable to transient sojourners, travelers, officers
                                and crews of vessels, and the like, who have no purpose or
                                opportunity of sojourn.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>What rights as a foreigner are established by the fact of
                                matriculation.</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>What rights are denied in the event of non-matriculation.</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>Whether the Mexican law denies the validity of any evidence of
                                alien status save that presented by the certificate of
                                matriculation; if not—</item>
                            <label>(6)</label>
                            <item>What evidence of citizenship may be presented to establish the
                                fact of alienage.</item>
                            <label>(7)</label>
                            <item>A list of the cases in which, on proof of citizenship according to
                                the laws of the United States, diplomatic intervention has been
                                rejected because of non-matriculation.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>In addition to this, your report may embrace any other pertinent
                        consideration suggested by your familiarity with the subject.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>FRED’K T. FRELINGHUYSEN.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>