<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-10-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="465" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d465">
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 465.</seg></opener>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Buck</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Bayard</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Lima,
                                Peru</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-10-10"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 10, 1885</date>. (Received
                            November 6.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 42.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The deserters who arrived in Lima on the 3d
                        instant from the command of the revolutionist, Pacheco Cespedes, estimate
                        the forces of General Cáceres at not exceeding 2,000 men; this agrees with
                        estimate from another quarter, that of Iglesias Lozer, who believes the
                        revolutionary leader has only from 1,800 to 2,000 men. Colonel Ibarra left
                        Arequipa on the 2d instant with 300 men, having been apparently reinforced
                        previously by some troops under Major Cortez. It is stated he left only 280
                        men in Arequipa, and he started from that place in direction of Cuzco.</p>
                    <p>It appears from La Libertad, published in the latter place, that the
                        provinces in the department of Cuzco which were reported to have declared
                        for General Iglesias have been pacified in the interest of General Cáceres,
                        and the report that the city has renounced allegiance to General Cáceres was
                        untrue. A file of celedores (policemen) had been sent from there to Santa
                        Rosa to receive rifles for the battalion Cazadores del Cuzco, composed, as
                        is stated, of 370 men.</p>
                    <p>A letter published in La Opinion Nacional of September 27, from Truxillo,
                        states that Romero is moving in the direction of Cajamarca, perhaps <pb facs="0751" n="623" xml:id="pg_623"/> ultimately to join General Cáceres
                        in the valley of the Janja, as hertofore intimated. It is also said
                        dissensions among Cáceresta leaders in the north resulted in the arrest and
                        execution of Becerra, and other chiefs affiliated with him, by La Barrara
                        and Romero, upon which Becerra’s men, estimated at 400, disbanded and
                        dispersed. I can state no definite particulars.</p>
                    <p>The Government forces which moved out of this city on September 25,
                        reoccupied Canta without resistance. They also seem to have reoccupied and
                        opened the whole line of the Oroya Railroad to its terminus, Chiclayo,
                        Colonel Chocano having arrived at the latter place.</p>
                    <p>From San Bartolome, on that line, Subprefect Alcazar reports that the
                        revolutionist column, Remac, composed of 250 men, has disbanded; and Colonel
                        Chocano reports from Mattucana, also on line of that railroad, that part of
                        the squadron Sama Pachia revolted and dispersed at Antarana on the 6th
                        instant, leaving Cespedes Pacheco (revolutionist) only a few
                        Arequipeños.</p>
                    <p>General Cáceres is reported drawing his forces back to Tarma.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>CHAS. W. BUCK.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>