<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-11-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="603" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d603">
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 603.</seg></opener>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Magee</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-11-03"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 3,
                            1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 16.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatch, No. 34, of the 9th ultimo,
                        asking for instructions in regard to the propriety of your course in
                        refusing to issue a passport to a naturalized citizen of the Territory of
                        Utah on the ground of his proselyting for the Mormon Church, is
                        received.</p>
                    <p>As your archives Will show, and as you are doubtless aware, in August, 1879,
                        this Government sent circular instructions to all our ministers abroad to
                        request all proper assistance from the Governments to which they were
                        accredited in suppressing the proselyting for the Mormon Church. In the face
                        of such a circular, it would seem to be inconsistent to issue passports to
                        persons who are undoubtedly Mormon emissaries, even if they are American
                        citizens. The law as to issuing passports is permissory, not obligatory, and
                        the decision is left with the Secretary of State under section 4075 of the
                        Revised Statutes.</p>
                    <p>Inasmuch as polygamy is a statutory crime, proselytism with intent that the
                        emigrants should live here in open violation of our laws would seem to be
                        sufficient warrant for refusing a passport. But it would be well to have the
                        fact of the applicant for the passport being a Mormon emissary, and actively
                        engaged in proselyting, conclusively proved to <pb facs="0917" n="789" xml:id="pg_789"/> your satisfaction by some kind of evidence which can
                        be put on the files of your legation and this Department. This might be
                        obtained, perhaps, from the police authorities or the public press in case
                        any meetings were held for the object of inciting to emigration.</p>
                    <p>It is noticed that in your report of the case you did not give the
                        applicant’s name. It would be as well to obtain in all such cases of refusal
                        of passport application a detailed statement from the applicant duly signed
                        and sworn to in support of his application, a copy of which can then be
                        forwarded to this Department for its action and to refer to in case the
                        application is renewed here.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>T. F. BAYARD.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>