<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Porter to Mr.
                                Winchester..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1885</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d623</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">623</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-09-14T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274" lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="reci0GubnZFV3spJe" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011003316" lcsh-match="bad_close">Infant</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-09-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="623" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d623">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 623.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Porter</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Winchester</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-09-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 14,
                            1885</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 14.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In reply to your No. 8, of 26th August, 1885,
                        concerning the application of Mr. Robert Emden for a passport, I have to say
                        that I now understand the facts in the case to be as follows: Mr. Emden was
                        born in Switzerland in 1862, and has never been in the United States. His
                        father, a Swiss by origin, was naturalized at New York in 1854, and appears
                        to have soon afterwards returned to Switzerland, where, as far as the papers
                        show, he is still resident.</p>
                <p>In view of the many attempts in late days of persons, Swiss by birth, to
                        relieve themselves of Swiss allegiance by formal naturalization in this
                        country, without accepting permanently the duties imposed by citizenship in
                        the United States, it is impossible not to desire to scrutinize closely an
                        application of this kind, made by a young man who has never been in the
                        United States, basing his claim on the naturalization of his father, who
                        appears never to have permanently accepted the duties of his
                        naturalization.</p>
                <p>Undoubtedly, by the law of nations, an infant child partakes of his father’s
                        nationality and domicil. But there are two difficulties in the way of
                        applying this rule to the present case. In the first place, a parent’s
                        nationality cannot, especially when produced by naturalization, be presumed
                        to be adhered to after a residence in the country of origin for so long a
                        period as in the present case. In the second place, the rule as to children
                        only applies to minors, since when the child becomes of age he is required
                        to elect between the country of his residence and the country of his alleged
                        technical allegiance. Of this election two incidents are to be observed;
                        when once made it is final, and it requires no formal act, but may be
                        inferred from the conduct of the party from whom the election is
                        required.</p>
                <p>Applying these tests to the present case it can hardly be said that Mr.
                        Robert Emden’s claim to be a citizen of the United States is, as a matter of
                        international law, made out. The burden of proof is always on the applicant
                        for the passport, and here there is no evidence to prove either his father’s
                        non-abandonments of his United States citizenship or his own election of
                        such citizenship, save the applications of father and son for passports.</p>
                <pb facs="0940" n="812" xml:id="pg_812"/>
                <p>In the foregoing remarks, the sections of the Revised Statutes bearing on
                        questions of this class have not been considered. These sections are as
                        follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 2172 [originally enacted April 14,
                                1802]. The children of persons who have been duly naturalized under
                                any law of the, United States, or who, previous to the passing of
                                any law on that subject by the Government of the United States, may
                                have become citizens of any one of the States, being under the age
                                of twenty-one years at the time of the naturalization of their
                                parents, shall, if dwelling in the United States, be considered as
                                citizens thereof; and the children of persons who now are or have
                                been, citizens of the United States, shall, though born out of the
                                limits and jurisdiction of the United States, be considered as
                                citizens thereof. * * *</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 1993 [originally passed April 9,
                                1866]. All children heretofore born or hereafter born out of the
                                limits and jurisdiction of the United States, whose fathers were or
                                may be at the time of their birth citizens thereof, are declared to
                                be citizens of the United States; but the rights of citizenship
                                shall not descend to children whose fathers never resided in the
                                United States.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>If reliance is placed on the first clause of section 2172, the application
                        must fail, since that clause applies only to children “dwelling in the
                        United States.” If, however, Mr. Emden seeks to come in under the second
                        clause of section 2172, or under the more general terms of section 1993, he
                        is met with the difficulty that he is no longer a “child,” but that he is of
                        full age, and that his citizenship is no longer derivative, but is a matter
                        of personal election, If he solemnly elected, on arriving at full age, to be
                        a citizen of the United States, the proofs of such election must be
                        produced. If, on the other hand, he made no such election, but by remaining
                        in Switzerland is to be inferred to have accepted Swiss nationality, he
                        cannot now obtain a passport as a citizen of the United States, If this be
                        the case, his proper course, should he desire to become a citizen of the
                        United States, is to come here in person and become naturalized.</p>
                <p>In accordance with these views, you are, therefore, requested to decline to
                        issue a passport to Mr. Robert Emden.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JAS. D. PORTER,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Acting
                            Secretary.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
