<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Cox to Mr.
                                Bayard..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1885</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d668</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">668</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-10-10T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="religious-freedom" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93000083" lcsh-match="good_close">Religious freedom</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-10-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="668" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d668">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 668.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cox</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-10-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 10, 1885</date>.
                            (Received October 26.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 25.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Upon April 9, 1885, General Wallace, in his
                        No. 491, reported the adverse decision of the Government of Turkey to the
                        claims for indemnity for the assault upon Rev. Drs. Knapp and Reynolds, and
                        Maurice Pflaum, M. D.</p>
                <p>On the 17th August ultimo, in instruction No. 10, you advised me to pursue
                        the claims for pecuniary indemnity. Your letter was quite imperative. It was
                        what it ought to have been. The reply of the minister of foreign affairs you
                        summarized. You declined to accept his reply as either final or
                        satisfactory. Thereupon I made a study of the <pb facs="0997" n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/> cases, reading up and noting all the points in each
                        from our imperfect records; and I wrote to the minister <hi rend="italic">ad
                            interim</hi> the inclosed dispatch.</p>
                <p>You observe that I have made your non-acceptance of the minister’s reply the
                        basis of the renewed application, copying proper parts of your instruction
                        for the reopening of the cases; only as yet the reopening.* * * I am now
                        awaiting the appearance and action of a new minister, Said Pasha, minister
                        at Berlin. He will come to the foreign affairs office here with a reputation
                        for sense and liberality, and for special knowledge and judgment in affairs
                        of this very nature. Therefore I do not press the matter overmuch as yet. In
                        this I have the concurrence of the Bible-house people and missionaries.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S. S. COX.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 25.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cox</persName> to the
                                    <gloss type="to">minister of foreign affairs ad
                                interim</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-09-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 28,
                                    1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: The inclosure is an extract from
                            the letter of the Hon. T. F. Bayard, Secretary of State. It pertains to
                            a question which has been unduly vexed. A new administration has
                            supervened in my country; a new President has been elected; a new
                            cabinet have been installed; a new condition also obtains here; so that
                            we may reopen these matters without prejudice.</p>
                    <p>The tenets of religious freedom of our new order are not unlike those of
                            the great men of your race who have tolerated differences of faith.</p>
                    <p>It was one of the sentiments which led me here, viz, that this land, so
                            often impugned, had been gracious toward religions of differing ceremony
                            and thought. I had read its history and believed in its ultimate and
                            liberal justice.</p>
                    <p>When, therefore, such a stringent letter came as this I inclose, which
                            looked to the embarrassment if not unhappiness of my service here, I had
                            either to blame my predecessor (which would have been discourteous) for
                            his lack of suavity, or to blame the Turkish Government for its
                            insensibility to an unredressed crime. There is no real remedy on the
                            proposition allowing us to sue your magistrates, because they have
                            prejudiced by their irregularity the cases referred to.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary of State advises me that he will not accept this reply as
                            final or satisfactory.</p>
                    <p>The question, then, is, before we discuss the merits of the case will you
                            review the cases? If not, my duty is plain. It is only to report that
                            fact to my Government. I have avoided making this question for almost a
                            month, for I knew you were preoccupied with other troubles, in which you
                            have the sympathy of a great people, quite aloof from you in every way,
                            except in sympathy.</p>
                    <p>The answer to this dispatch will be simply regarding the reopening of the
                            cases referred to, with a view to pecuniary remedy.</p>
                    <p>I avail, &amp;c.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>S. S. COX.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>P. S.—For full particulars of the above cases I refer to dispatch of
                                my predecessor No. 198, January 24, 1884, and other dispatches in
                                your archives. May I add the letter of Mr. Cole, which is a painful
                                commentary on this delay and denial of justice and reward of the
                                guilty by promotion in office? I earnestly entreat your attention to
                                this extraordinary state of affairs. Evidenced by the inclosures:
                                Extract and translation from instruction No. 10 of Hon. T. F.
                                Bayard, Secretary of State, Washington, in reference to the Knapp,
                                Reynolds, and Pflaum assault cases; and letter of R. M. Cole, and
                                translation.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
