<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Bayard to Mr.
                                Baker..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1885</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d687</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">687</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1885-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1885-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692" lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856" lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1885-04-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1885-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="687" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d687">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 687.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Baker</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-04-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 9,
                            1885</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 56.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my instruction to you, No.
                        51, of the 24th ultimo, relative to the injury to the American schooner
                        Lanie Cobb, I have now to transmit for your information a copy of dispatch
                        No. 201, March 14 ultimo, from the consul at La Guayra, containing a
                        statement in detail of the facts attending the damages sustained by the
                        aforesaid schooner.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>T. F. BAYARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bird</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hunter</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">La
                                    Guayra</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-03-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 14,
                                1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 201.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to dispatch No. 197 of date
                            March 4 instant, upon the subject of damages sustained by the American
                            vessel Lanie Cobb while in this port, I have the honor to submit the
                            following additional and more explicit details:</p>
                    <p>As has been stated, the master of said vessel made application to this
                            consulate on February 24 ultimo, for a survey. The preliminaries were
                            arranged, and Benjamin F. Cushman, master of the schooner Addie M. Bird,
                            of Rockland, Me., Evan Jones, master of the brig Fleetwing, of Cardiff,
                            Wales; and Charles G. Jackson, an English ship-carpenter, long resident
                            at this port, were selected to hold said survey. Thereupon they repaired
                            to the custom-house with a dispatch, as follows:</p>
                    <p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">La Guayra</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 24, 1885.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Señor</hi>: The American schooner Lanie
                                    Cobb, having suffered serious damages and injuries from being
                                    run into by the Venezuelan schooner Ana Eulogia, I have the
                                    honor <pb facs="1034" n="906" xml:id="pg_906"/> to request that
                                    three surveyors may he permitted to go on board of said vessel
                                    to ascertain her present state and condition and what had best
                                    be done for the interest of the parties concerned.</p>
                            <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <p rend="right">WINFIELD S. BIRD.</p>
                            <p>Señor <hi rend="smallcaps">Marceliano Martin</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Collector of Customs at La
                                Guayra.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The above is substantially, if not literally, an exact copy of said
                            dispatch.</p>
                    <p>These surveyors returned to this consulate shortly afterward, and
                            reported that the said collector had refused to grant them the permit
                            thus requested.</p>
                    <p>At 3 o’clock, p.m., of the same day, in company with said surveyors I
                            went personally to see the said collector. He informed me that my
                            dispatch to him was written in English, a language not understood by
                            him, and that until the return of the official interpreter from Caracas,
                            about which he could give me no intelligence, he would decline to
                            proceed in the matter. I asked permission to explain, in his language,
                            what I desired; but, in polite terms, he refused. I urged upon him the
                            necessity of holding the survey without further delay, in order that the
                            master might assume the responsibility to move the vessel from her
                            position in dangerous proximity to the rocky beach. He voluntered to
                            render us all necessary assistance, but, with due thanks, he was
                            reminded that until a lawful survey had been held we could not take the
                            risk to move her. He then insisted that he had the right to nominate one
                            surveyor, the master of the Venezuelan should name another, and the
                            American master should appoint a third, to hold said survey.</p>
                    <p>Against such a demand I respectfully and firmly protested, and assured
                            him that I proposed to hold this survey merely in compliance with my
                            official duty, and that such survey had no reference to proceedings in
                            the Venezuelan courts but was to be instituted in pursuance of the laws
                            of the United States. He declined to allow the American consul even to
                            go on board of said vessel, but, on referring to the law, concluded that
                            he might be permitted to go <hi rend="italic">unofficially</hi>. He
                            finally consented, after much persuasion, to allow the surveyors also,
                            as private individuals, to go on board. A permit for the consul and the
                            surveyors, in writing and in such terms, was then conceded. The consul
                            declining to proceed on board under such conditions, but without
                            intimating, in any manner, his refusal or dissatisfaction, then
                            requested the said surveyors to repair on board of said vessel. Owing to
                            the lateness of the hour, they suspended action until the following
                            morning, when they went on board, held the survey, and made their report
                            on oath and in due form of law. It should be remarked that, before
                            proceeding on board, these surveyors were informed by the consul that
                            the Venezuelan vessel belonged to the President of Venezuela, and that
                            they should be very careful to make an accurate survey and to render a
                            just and reasonable estimate.</p>
                    <p>On the following day, at the solicitation of the American master, the
                            consul, in a purely private capacity and acting as the agent of said
                            master, thereto duly authorized and instructed, repaired to Caracas to
                            see General Crespo, and, out of respect to him, to endeavor to effect an
                            amicable and private adjustment of the affair. In company with Charles
                            R. Rohl, esq., United States consular agent at Caracas, he called three
                            times, when, a last, an interview was accorded, in which General Crespo
                            remarked that, although the Venezuelan vessel belonged to him yet she
                            was in the service of the Venezuelan Government, and that therefore we
                            should call to see the minister of war in reference to it. During the
                            interview Mr. J. E. Linares, a confidential friend and reputed business
                            agent of General Crespo, was also at the house though not present. At 3
                            o’clock, p.m., of the same day we called to see the minister of war, and
                            were informed by a sentry at the door that he had gone to the country,
                            and that it was impossible to say when he would return. I then went to
                            the legation of the United States and requested Mr. Baker, the minister,
                            to address a note to the said minister of war, hoping by this proceeding
                            to reach his ear. He advised me to follow up my action and to appeal to
                            him later on, when, in his judgment, his intervention would be more
                            effective. Having to dispatch a vessel from La Guayra I then returned
                            there by the first train, leaving the matter in the hands of Mr. Rohl,
                            the aforesaid United States consular agent, from whom, on Saturday
                            evening, February 28, ultimo, I receive the following dispatch:</p>
                    <p>
                        <quote>
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consular
                                        Agency</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi>, <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 27, 1885.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As you had to leave yesterday
                                    without being able to settle the affair of the Lanie Cobb, and
                                    requested me to do all I could during your absence, I went to
                                    see Mr. J. E. Linares, who is, as it seems, an intimate friend
                                    of General Crespo. I told Mr. Linares I had nothing to do
                                    officially in this business, but I would be glad if a settlement
                                    could be arrived at, and that I acted as a friend to the
                                    master.</p>
                            <pb facs="1035" n="907" xml:id="pg_907"/>
                            <p>Mr. Linares was at first entirely indisposed to make any advances
                                    looking to an amicable and equitable adjustment of the
                                    difficulty, alleging that the Venezuelan master was not to blame
                                    for the accident; but after an extended conversation, during
                                    which I assured him that the American master was disposed to
                                    entertain a fair and reasonable proposition, and that such
                                    matters were usually arranged between the parties without resort
                                    to legal process, I prevailed upon him to write to Mr. W. Carias
                                    Perez, his agent in La Guayra, and consignee of the Venezuelan
                                    schooner Ana Eulogia, to ascertain the damage and try to come to
                                    an agreement with the master of the Lanie Cobb.</p>
                            <p>I beg to felicitate you over the now favorable aspect of this
                                    most disagreeable affair.</p>
                            <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <p rend="right">CHARLES R. ROHL.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Winfield S. Bird</hi>, Esq.,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States Consul at La
                                Guayra.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>On receipt of the foregoing dispatch, I promptly repaired to the office
                            of Mr. W. Carias Perez, the agent of Mr. Linares, and represented to him
                            that we had been informed that Mr. Linares had instructed him to confer
                            with us. He replied that he had been thus instructed, and asked for a
                            statement of our demands. I assured him that we did not come to him in
                            that spirit, but that we only asked for a fair and equitable settlement.
                            We requested him to make to us some proposition to that end, but he
                            declined. We then proposed that he should select one surveyor, we would
                            name another, and those surveyors should call a third, neither of whom
                            should be a Venezuelan or American, who should proceed to arbitrate and
                            settle the question, and that we would be bound by their decision. He
                            said that the proposition was satisfactory, but that he must consult
                            with Mr. Linares by telephone before he could accept it, and that on the
                            following morning at 9 o’clock he would give me a definite reply. On
                            passing along the street the same evening at 9 o’clock, however, I met
                            with him, when, calling me to the light, he drew from his pocket a
                            memorandum, as he stated, of his telephonic conversation with Mr.
                            Linares, wherein he was instructed to make no compromise, but to advise
                            us that the courts were open to us.</p>
                    <p>Thus thwarted, delayed, and finally repulsed in our earnest endeavors to
                            arrive at a prompt and mutually satisfactory arrangement of the cause,
                            we were at last driven to resort to legal redress in the Venezuelan
                            courts. Accordingly on Monday morning, March 2 instant, a note was
                            addressed and delivered to the judge of hacienda in La Guayra as
                            follows:</p>
                    <p>
                        <quote>
                            <p rend="center">[Translation.]</p>
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">La Guayra</hi>, <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 2, 1885.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The American schooner Lanie Cobb,
                                    under my command, having suffered material damages by a
                                    collision from the Venezuelan schooner Ana Eulogia, I have to
                                    beg that you will please name experts to estimate the damages
                                    and to accord me justice.</p>
                            <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                            <p rend="right">C. H. COBB, <hi rend="italic">Master.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nicholas Bello y Bello</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Judge of Hacienda.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>After perusing the foregoing note, said judge politely informed us that
                            the cause was not within his jurisdiction, and referred us to the law,
                            as follows: Article VI, Attribution VI, Chapter II, Law V of the
                            Custom-House Regulations; also articles 118, 119, and 120, Title VII of
                            the Marine Register. He then directed us to carry our complaint to the
                            collector of customs, who is <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi> the
                            captain of the port, and before whom all proceedings in such cases must
                            he primarily instituted. After addressing a note to that officer, in
                            terms exactly similar to those of the foregoing note addressed to the
                            judge of hacienda, we went to the custom-house and delivered the same in
                            person. On reading it he remarked that the matter was not within the
                            scope of his duty. Even after he was cited to the law, as above referred
                            to, and after examing it, he insisted that we should go back to the
                            court of justice from whence we came. On returning to said court the
                            judge, in courteous and convincing terms, ordered us back to the said
                            collector of customs. On a final presentation of the matter to the
                            attention of said collector, after informing us that the other vessel
                            had left the port, which had been effected with his permission and under
                            cover of night, he put a period to our oscillatory peregrinations and
                            solaced our suspense by stating that he would not further consider the
                            case.</p>
                    <p>From various unofficial sources the information comes that the
                            authorities here claim that the Venezuelan was crossing the bows of the
                            American, and to avoid the collision called to the latter to pay out her
                            chain, which she neglected or refused to do, and that therefore the
                            Venezuelan is not responsible for the casualty. In the light of all the
                            evidence this assertion is a mere afterthought and subterfuge, since it
                            is distinctly proven that the Venezuelan was some distance to windward,
                            and, attempting to tack ship, failed in the effort and drifted
                            helplessly down npon the American without dropping her anchor or hauling
                            in any sail.</p>
                    <pb facs="1036" n="908" xml:id="pg_908"/>
                    <p>Such are the facts and circumstances surrounding this affair from
                            inception to conclusion.* * * For the wrongs and injuries offered to the
                            American master no words will suffice to express the sincere contempt
                            and the profound detestation of every generous nature.</p>
                    <p>Herewith are submitted copies of all of the official papers in this
                            cause.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>WINFIELD S. BIRD.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">La
                                        Guayra, Venezuela</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-02-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 23, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winfield S. Bird</hi>,
                                Esq.,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States Consul at La
                            Guayra:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The schooner Lanie Cobb, under my command,
                            arrived at this port on the 15th instant from Savannah, Ga., laden with
                            lumber, and in consequence of damages sustained by being run into on the
                            21st instant by the Venezuelan schooner Ana Eulogia, I have to request
                            that you will please call a survey upon the said schooner to ascertain
                            her present state and condition, and what had best be done for the
                            interest of the parties concerned.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>C. H. COBB, <hi rend="italic">Master.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 2.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States
                                        Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="italic">La
                                            Guayra</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-02-23">
                                    <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 23,
                                        1885</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Evan Jones</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Master of the brig Fleetwing, of Cardiff,
                                    Wales;</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Benjamin F.
                                    Cushman</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Master of schooner Addie M.
                                    Bird, of BocJcland, Me.;</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles G.
                                    Jackson</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Master
                                Ship-Carpenter:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: Application having been made to
                                this consulate by C. H. Cobb, master of the schooner Lanie Cobb, of
                                Bangor, Me., of the burden of 230.85 tons, or thereabouts, for
                                survey upon said schooner in consequence of having sustained damages
                                and injuries on the 21st instant by being run into by the Venezuelan
                                schooner Ana Eulogia, whereby she is rendered unseaworthy, you are
                                hereby respectfully requested to repair alongside and on board of
                                said schooner, and after a careful and minute examination and survey
                                of every visible part of her hull, spars, sails, and rigging, report
                                to this consulate under your own hands in writing her present state
                                and condition, and what in your opinion had best be done for the
                                interest of the parties concerned.</p>
                        <p>Given under my hand and the seal of this consulate the day and year
                                above written.</p>
                        <table cols="2" rows="1">
                            <row>
                                <cell>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>WINFIELD S. BIRD,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">United States
                                            Consul.</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 3.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">La
                                            Guayra, Venezuela</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-02-24">
                                    <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 24, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Winfield S. Bird</hi>,
                                    Esq.,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Consul at La
                                    Guayra:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Pursuant to the accompanying warrant
                                of survey to us directed, we, the undersigned, repaired on board of
                                the American schooner Lanie Cobb, of Bangor, Me., of the burden of
                                230.85 tons, or thereabouts, and after a careful and minute
                                examination and survey of every visible part of her hull, spars,
                                sails, and rigging, do report as follows:</p>
                        <p>We find the patent of windlass gone, the bowsprit broken, the
                                cut-water gone, the bobstay bolts dragged out of the stem, the
                                martingale and jumper-stays gone, the bee on starboard side of
                                bowsprit gone and plate on bowsprit bent, the stays chafed, the
                                head-rails on both sides gone, the jib-boom guy on starboard side
                                gone, the flying-jib halyard parted, the anchor with sixty fathoms
                                of new 11/16 inch chain lost, thirty fathoms of new 3-inch line
                                lost, one hawser parted, the forecastle head started, and the
                                flying-jib damaged.</p>
                        <p>And we recommend that the master make such temporary repairs as are
                                necessary, and proceed with dispatch to Curaçao or some other
                                contiguous and safe port in order to make permanent repairs. In
                                confirmation of which we are willing, if required, to attest. Given
                                under our hands at La Guayra this the 24th day of February, A. D.
                                1885.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <list>
                                    <item>EVAN JONES,<lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Master of the brig
                                                Fleetwing, of Cardiff, Wales</hi>.</item>
                                    <item>BENJAMIN F. CUSHMAN,<lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Master of
                                                the schooner Addie M. Bird, of Rockland,
                                            Me.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>CHARLES G. JACKSON,<lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Master
                                                Ship-Carpenter of Maiquetia, Venezuela.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <pb facs="1037" n="909" xml:id="pg_909"/>
                        <postscript>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="italic">Estimate of repairs.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">No. 3½.]</p>
                            <p>Estimate of the probable cost of repairing the schooner Lanie
                                    Cobb, of Bangor, Me., agreeably to the report of the survey of
                                    the 24th February instant, and in accordance with the cost of
                                    labor and material at the port of La Guayra, as follows, viz:
                                        <table cols="2" rows="19">
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For repair of windlass</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">$25 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For new bowsprit</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">300 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For a cut-water</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">350 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For repairing bobstays</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">10 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For new martingale and jumper-stays</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">25 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For new bees and plate on bowsprit</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">50 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For repairing stays</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">15 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For new head-rails</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">20 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For new jib-booni guy</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">20 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For new flying-jib halyard</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">12 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For new anchor, 1,600 pounds, at 8 cents</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">128 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For 60 fathoms new 11/16-inch chain, 7,500 pounds,
                                                at 10 cents</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">750 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For 30 fathoms new 3-inch line</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">6 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For repairing hawser</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">5 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For repairing forecastle head</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">15 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For repairing flying-jib</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">5
                                                00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Total repairs</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">1,736 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>For two weeks’ delay</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">250
                                                00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Total in United States gold</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">1,986 00</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                        <postscript>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">La Guayra, Venezuela</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-02-24">
                                        <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 24, 1885</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>We, the undersigned, surveyors of the schooner Lanie Cobb, of
                                    Bangor, Me., aver on oath that the above and foregoing estimate
                                    of repairs is accurate and just, to the best of our knowledge
                                    and belief.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>EVAN JONES,<lb/>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Master of brig
                                                  Fleetwing, of Cardiff, Wales</hi>.</item>
                                        <item>BENJAMIN F. CUSHMAN,<lb/>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Master
                                                  of schooner Addie M. Bird, of Rockland,
                                                Me.</hi>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>CHARLES G. JACKSON,<lb/>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Master
                                                  Ship-Carpenter, of Maiquetia,
                                                Venezuela.</hi>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Sworn to and subscribed before me
                                        this 24th day of February, A. D. 1885.</dateline>
                                <signed>
                                    <table cols="2" rows="1">
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</cell>
                                            <cell>WINFIELD S. BIRD,<lb/>
                                                <hi rend="italic">United
                                                  States Consul.</hi>
                                            </cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </postscript>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Received, La Guayra, February 24, 1885, of Winfield S. Bird,
                                    United States consul, the sum of $5 each, for holding the
                                    foregoing survey and making estimate of repairs.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>EVAN JONES.</item>
                                        <item>BENJAMIN F. CUSHMAN.</item>
                                        <item>CHARLES G. JACKSON.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">No. 4.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States
                                        Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="italic">La
                                            Guayra</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-02-24">
                                    <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 24,
                                        1885</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I, the undersigned, consul of the United States at the port of La
                                Guayra, do hereby certify that the foregoing are the true and
                                genuine signatures of Evan Jones, Benjamin F. Cushman, and Charles
                                G. Jackson, surveyors, appointed by me, of the American schooner
                                Lanie Cobb, of Bangor, Me., and as such are entitled to full faith
                                and credit.</p>
                        <p>Given under my hand and the seal of this consulate this the day and
                                year above written.</p>
                        <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>] <signed>WINFIELD S.
                                        BIRD,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States
                                    Consul.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">La
                                    Guayra</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-02-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 28,
                                    1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>By this public instrument of declaration and protest be it known and made
                            manifest unto all to whom these presents shall come or may concern, that
                            on this the 28th day of February, A. D. 1885, before me, Winfield S.
                            Bird, consul of the United States at the port of La Guayra, personally
                            comes C. H. Cobb, master of the American schooner Lanie Cobb, of Bangor,
                            Me., U. S. A., of the burden of 230.85 tons or, thereabouts, recently
                            arrived <pb facs="1038" n="910" xml:id="pg_910"/> at the port of La
                            Guayra from Savannah, Ga., U. S. A., laden with lumber, and requires me
                            to note his protest: and together with the said C. H. Cobb, master, also
                            came W. M. Wentworth, mate, and H. P. Baker, seaman, of and belonging to
                            the crew of said schooner Lanie Cobb, all of whom being by me duly sworn
                            on the Holy Evangelists of Almighty God, did severally, voluntarily,
                            freely, and solemnly declare, depose, and state as follows, that is to
                            say:</p>
                    <p>That these appearers, in their capacities aforesaid, arrived in and with
                            the said schooner at La Guayra, Venezuela, without accident or causalty
                            on the 15th day of February, A. D. 1885, at 3 o’clock p.m., and took
                            good and safe anchorage in said port of La Guayra; that on Saturday, the
                            21st day of February instant, at 4 o’clock in the evening, the Venezuela
                            schooner Ana Eulogia, belonging, as they are informed and believe, to
                            the Venezuelan Government, started to sail out of the port of La Guayra;
                            that she stood across the bow of the Lanie Cobb, and that when she was
                            to the windward and about 400 feet from the said Lanie Cobb, then lying
                            safely at anchor, she attempted to tack ship and mis-tacked, and that
                            thereupon, making no effort to haul down any sail nor to drop anchor,
                            she drifted down upon the said schooner Lanie Cobb; that no anchor was
                            dropped from the said schooner Ana Eulogia before she drifted upon said
                            schooner; that some party on board of the Ana Eulogia hailed the Lanie
                            Cobb, but that their language was in Spanish and could not be
                            understood, but that said party did not hail until the schooners were in
                            collision; that the mate of the Lanie Cobb called out in English before
                            the collision occurred to the parties on board of the Ana Eulogia to
                            drop anchor and he would pay out his chain; that no anchor was dropped;
                            that before the Ana Eulogia struck the Lanie Cobb the mate of the latter
                            vessel began to pay out the chain; that the said Ana Eulogia drifted
                            against the Lanie Cobb, and to save the latter from further damage or
                            total loss her anchor and chain was slipped; that when the chain was
                            slipped a line was bent into it, but that the keel of the Ana Eulogia
                            cut the line and the anchor and chain were lost; that thereupon the
                            Lanie Cobb drifted away from the said schooner, and with her second
                            anchor was anchored in a most dangerous position near the beach; that
                            her windlass patent was broken, and she was therefore so disabled that
                            it Was impossible to extricate her from her perilous situation; that in
                            the collision the windlass patent was broken, the cutwater, obstays,
                            martingale, and all head-gear were broken, and the bow-sprit and all
                            attached to it was carried away.</p>
                    <p>And these appearers, upon their oaths aforesaid, do further declare and
                            say: that at the time of during and after said casualty they, together
                            with the others of the ship’s company, used their utmost endeavors to
                            preserve the said Lanie Cobb from all manner of loss, damage, or
                            injury.</p>
                    <p>Wherefore, the said C. H. Cobb, master, hath protested, as by these
                            presents I, the said consul, at his special instance and request, do
                            publicly and solemnly protest against all and every person and persons
                            whom it doth or may concern, and against the winds and waves and billows
                            of the seas, and against all and every accident, matter, and thing had
                            and met with as aforesaid, whereby and by reason whereof the said vessel
                            Lanie Cobb already has or hereafter shall appear to have suffered or
                            sustained damage or injury. And do declare that all losses, damages,
                            costs, charges, and expenses that have happened to the said Lanie Cobb
                            are and ought to be borne by those to whom the same by right may
                            appertain, by way of average or otherwise, the same having occurred as
                            before mentioned and not by or through the insufficiency of the said
                            Lanie Cobb, her tackle or apparel, or default or neglect of this
                            appearer, his officers or any of his mariners.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">This done and protested in the port of
                                    <placeName>La Guayra</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-02-28">this the 28th day of
                                    February, A. D. 1885</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>C. H. COBB, <hi rend="italic">Master</hi>.</item>
                                <item>W. M. WENTWORTH, <hi rend="italic">Mate.</hi>
                                </item>
                                <item>H. P. BAKER, <hi rend="italic">Seaman.</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>In testimony whereof these appearers have hereunto subscribed their
                                names, and I, the said consul, have granted to the said master this
                                public instrument, under my hand and the seal of this consulate, to
                                serve and to avail him and all others whom it doth or may concern as
                                need and occasion may require.</p>
                        <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>] <signed>WINFIELD S.
                                        BIRD,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States
                                    Consul.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">La
                                    Guayra</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-03-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 2,
                                1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Before me, Winfield S. Bird, consul of the United Slates at La Guayra,
                            personally appeared Benjamin F. Cushman, master of the American schooner
                            Addie M. Bird, of Rockland, <pb facs="1039" n="911" xml:id="pg_911"/>
                            Me., who, being by me duly sworn on the Holy Evangelists of Almighty
                            God, voluntarily and freely deposes and states, as follows:</p>
                    <p>On the evening of February 21, 1885, I witnessed the casualty that
                            occurred to the American schooner Lanie Cobb, then lying quietly at
                            anchor in the port of La Guayra. I saw the Venezuelan schooner Ana
                            Eulogia as she filled away, her foretop boom high up and sheet well off,
                            so that the foresail was not full to the wind, and could not, therefore,
                            drive the vessel from across the bows of the American schooner. I
                            remarked immediately to my mate that she would collide with the American
                            schooner. When the Venezuelan captain saw the danger he undertook to
                            tack ship, but never hauled in any head sail; and so he drifted down
                            about three hundred feet on to the American schooner without attempting
                            to drop anchor. And even after he was afoul of the American schooner and
                            across her bows he never hauled in any sail except the mainsail. While
                            afoul of the American schooner a kedge anchor was run from the
                            Venezuelan schooner to windward, but failing still to haul in sail, the
                            American was helpless to free herself from the Venezuelan schooner
                            without slipping her anchor, which was promptly done.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>BENJAMIN F. CUSHMAN,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Master Addle M.
                                    Bird.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this the day and date first
                                aforesaid, as witness my hand and official seal.</p>
                        <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>.] <signed>WINFIELD S.
                                        BIRD,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States
                                    Consul.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No. 56.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Consulate</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">La
                                    Guayra</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1885-03-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 2,
                                1885</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>By this public instrument of declaration and protest be it known and made
                            manifest to all to whom these presents shall come or may concern, that
                            on this day before me, Winfield S. Bird, United States consul at the
                            port of La Guayra, personally came and appeared C. H. Cobb, master of
                            the American schooner Lanie Cobb, now lying in this port of La Guayra,
                            who, being duly sworn upon the Holy Evangelists of Almighty God, does
                            voluntarily, freely, and solemnly depose and state as follows; that is
                            to say:</p>
                    <p>That on the evening of the 21st day of February, 1885, the Venezuelan
                            schooner Ana Eulogia, which schooner, according to information and
                            belief, is either owned or chartered by the Venezuelan Government, ran
                            afoul of the said Lanie Cobb, then lying quietly at anchor, and
                            seriously damaged and injured said schooner Lanie Cobb; that he called a
                            survey upon said ship and sought to have the matter settled amicably,
                            without resort to law, to this purpose engaging the good offices of the
                            United States consul at La Guayra and the United States consular agent
                            at Caracas; that no offer of arrangement or compromise was made to him,
                            and that all offers of compromise made on his part were peremptorily
                            refused; that, in the mean time, the port authorities had permitted the
                            Ana Eulogia to sail from the port of La Guayra; that on Monday a.m., the
                            day and date herein first aforesaid, he addressed a note to the judge of
                            hacienda, in La Guayra, asking a survey on his vessel, and measures of
                            justice, by whom he was referred to the collector of customs; that he
                            thereupon addressed a note in similar terms to the collector of customs
                            but that the said collector referred him back to the said judge; that
                            thereafter the said judge refused to act in the matter and referred him
                            back to the said collector; that on again recurring to said collector,
                            he absolutely refused to offer or afford to him, the said C. H. Cobb,
                            any relief or any measure looking toward relief.</p>
                    <p>Wherefore the said master, C. H. Cobb, hath protested, as by these
                            presents I, the said consul, at his special instance and request, being
                            fully cognizant personally of the truth of every statement made on this,
                            his said declaration and protest, do publicly and solemnly protest
                            against all and every person and persons whom it doth or may concern,
                            and against the winds and waves and billows of the seas, and against all
                            and every accident, matter, and thing had and met with aforesaid,
                            whereby and by reason whereof the said schooner Lanie Cobb already has
                            or hereafter shall appear to have suffered or sustained damage or
                            injury, and especially against the action of the legal authorities of
                            the Republic of Venezuela as aforesaid. And do declare that all losses,
                            damages, costs, charges, expenses, and delays that have happened to the
                            said schooner Lanie Cobb are and ought to be borne by those to whom the
                            same by right may appertain by way of average or otherwise, the same
                            having occurred as before mentioned and not by or through the
                            insufficiency of the said Lanie Cobb, her tackle or apparel, or default
                            or neglect of this appearer, his officers or any of his mariners.</p>
                    <pb facs="1040" n="912" xml:id="pg_912"/>
                    <p>Thus done and protested in the port of La Guayra this the 2d day of
                            March, A. D. 1885.</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof this appearer has hereunto subscribed his name, and
                            I, the said consul, have granted to the said master this public
                            instrument under my hand and the seal of this consulate, to serve and to
                            avail him and all others whom it doth or may concern as need and
                            occasion may require.</p>
                    <closer>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>] <signed>WINFIELD S. BIRD,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">C. H. Cobb</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Master
                                    Schooner Laney Cobb.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
