<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State ( (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-10-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-10-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="139"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">124.93/139</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Johnson</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-10-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 30, 1928</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Chinese Minister told me that he had had a conversation with the Chief of the
                    Far Eastern Division regarding the raising of our <pb facs="0324" n="206"
                        xml:id="pg_206"/> legation to the status of an embassy and that the Chief of
                    the Far Eastern Division had told him the Secretary was discussing this matter.
                    He said he had hesitated to report to the Nationalist Government at Nanking that
                    we were discussing the matter with the other governments as they would feel
                    somewhat disturbed as they are quite certain that the different powers would not
                    be disposed to take the proposed action and it was their hope that we would not
                    wait upon them. The Minister went on to say that in the history of this question
                    it had come as a proposal to Wellington Koo, then Chinese Minister at
                        Washington,<note n="20" xml:id="d139fn20">Vi Kyuin Wellington Koo was
                        Chinese Minister at Washington from December 1915 to March 1921.</note>
                    directly from President Wilson at a time when the question of the raising of
                    legations to status of embassies was up in this country, President Wilson having
                    told Wellington Koo that if China desired this to be done, he was quite prepared
                    to do it.<note n="21" xml:id="d139fn21">No record of this statement has been
                        found in Department files.</note> The Minister stated that at that time he
                    was in London and had been one of the chief objectors to the proposal on the
                    ground that it would merely add a financial burden to the chief of mission and
                    would not accomplish anything of value.</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that some time later when he came to Washington Congressman
                        Burton<note n="22" xml:id="d139fn22">Representative Theodore E. Burton of
                        Ohio.</note> had asked him his reasons for objecting as he, Congressman
                    Burton, proposed to introduce the bill into the Congress raising the status of
                    our legation at Peking to that of embassy. The Minister stated he had furnished
                    Congressman Burton with a memorandum of the pros and cons on the subject.</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that subsequently when the Chinese Government had conveyed
                    the opinion that they desired to raise the legation to the status of embassy he
                    had taken the matter up with Secretary Hughes who had discussed it with Mr.
                    MacMurray who had proposed that the matter be discussed with the powers and
                    that, of course, the matter fell through at that time because there were
                    objections on the part of Great Britain.</p>
                <p>I told the Minister that the Secretary felt he should communicate the matter to
                    the powers for the purpose of ascertaining their views on the subject; that the
                    Secretary had not decided in his own mind what to do in the matter and that in
                    communicating with the powers he was not binding himself to be guided by what
                    they might or might not do in the matter. The conversation here ended.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">elson</hi>] T. J[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ohnson</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
