<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Chargé in China ( (Perkins))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d325</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">325</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-08-21T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-08-21T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-08-21T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-08-21T19:00:00-05:00" n="325"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d325">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">125.643/45: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Perkins</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-08-21T20:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 21, 1928—8 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>281. Your 637, August 17, 7 p.m., 638, August 17, 10 p.m. and 644, August 20, 1
                        p.m.<note n="35" xml:id="d325fn35">None printed.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Your 637 and 638 were received after the Department’s 273, August 17, 6
                        p.m. was sent. Portions of them were unintelligible because of garbling.
                        Referring to points not covered in the Department’s No. 273, you are
                        instructed as follows:</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Renewal of consular lease at Nanking on year to year basis approved.
                        Spiker should proceed with repairs and replacement of government property
                        obtainable locally. Articles not obtainable locally should be requisitioned
                        from the Department. Department would expect the Nationalist authorities as
                        owners of the premises to defray cost of their restoration to former
                        condition. Cost of replacing United States government property was included
                        in the reparation estimate of $8,321.97 (see paragraph 1, Department’s
                        telegram 112 of April 4, 5 p.m.). Department can, if necessary, arrange to
                        advance the necessary funds in anticipation of reimbursement by the Chinese
                        authorities of the cost of repairs and payment of the reparation indicated.
                        Instructions regarding drafts will be telegraphed upon receipt of estimates.
                        In estimating cost of furnishing, amount of reparation estimate should not
                        be exceeded and allowance should be made for cost of articles to be
                        purchased by the Department. Use of temporary quarters, if provided by the
                        Nationalist authorities, may be accepted.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Department appreciates courtesy of British Consul General Hewlett<note
                            n="36" xml:id="d325fn36">W. M. Hewlett, British consul general at
                            Nanking.</note> but has no preference in regard to priority of American
                        or British reoccupation of premises. The Department does not appear to have
                        been informed concerning the proposal in regard to ceremonies made at the
                        time of the Nanking Settlement Agreement in March last, other than in
                        Section 2 of the Legation’s telegram 213, April 7, 3 p.m.<note n="37"
                            xml:id="d325fn37">Not printed.</note> The Legation may use its own
                        discretion regarding this matter. However, insistence upon particular
                        ceremonies should not be allowed to interfere with carrying out of the
                        Department’s instruction 273 of August 17, 6 p.m. Department considers it
                        would be inexpedient for a secretary of legation to proceed to Nanking to
                        attend such ceremonies as may take place.</item>
                    <pb facs="0470" n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Department believes return of American citizens to Nanking should still be
                        discouraged but it desires an early telegraphic recommendation from Spiker
                        after he takes up residence there.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Castle</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
