<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (MacMurray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1927-12-29T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1927-12-29T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1927-12-29T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1927-12-29T07:00:00-05:00" n="366"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d366">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">693.003/800: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1927-12-29T20:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 29, 1927—8 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received December 30—9:15 a.m.<note n="62" xml:id="d366fn62">Telegram
                            in three sections.</note>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1134. 1. Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs of the Peking Government December 8th
                    asked my sympathetic consideration of a proposal for acquiescence by the powers
                    in certain tariff arrangements which it was hoped could be arrived at between
                    delegates of North and South. He outlined the project only in vague, general
                    terms stating that it would be more fully explained to me by the officiating
                    Inspector General of Customs.<note n="63" xml:id="d366fn63">A. H. F.
                        Edwardes.</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. On December 21st Edwardes called, under instruction of the Wai Chiao Pu, to
                    discuss this project with me and permitted me to read a memorandum of it of the
                    following general purport: intra-regional tariff autonomy, as recently
                    considered by the Nanking Government, is impracticable and economically unsound.
                    It does not envisage special <hi rend="italic">pro quo</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                        >quid pro quo?</hi>] arrangement between China and other countries
                    beneficial to the trade of those concerned. China has no national tariff at
                    present; there should be such in which duty on all kinds of goods is
                    specifically laid down. China has a perfect right to compile her own tariff and
                    there should be no question of any international tariff conference to assist her
                    in its compilation. It is impossible however during present unfortunate
                    political strife for any single government now functioning in China to compile
                    national tariff since other governments would repudiate it. Two or three
                    representatives from each of the governments functioning in <pb facs="0495"
                        n="377" xml:id="pg_377"/> China should meet in the interests of Chinese
                    national fiscal economy at Shanghai and there compile a national tariff in an
                    entirely nonparty spirit. The Maritime Customs would be available for exports
                        [<hi rend="italic">experts?</hi>] and for such information as the Commission
                    might require as also for assistance in making necessary arrangements to bring
                    together such a commission.</p>
                <p>When the national tariff is compiled in accordance with the idea that it be used
                    as a means of obtaining <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> arrangements with
                    the various powers the tariff should be sent individually to the representatives
                    of all foreign governments for study accompanied by a definite offer on the part
                    of China that if any articles in the tariff are found to be detrimental to the
                    trade of the countries concerned China is willing to enter into reciprocal
                    arrangements with a view to bettering economic relations between that country
                    and China.</p>
                <p>The question arises as to how this tariff is to be presented to each of the
                    foreign powers since recognition of territorial rights of the different
                    governments in China has not yet been settled. Unless some united commission is
                    appointed expressly to deal with foreign affairs, the tariff conference (local
                    Chinese conference by commissioners described above), which will be composed of
                    duly accredited representatives from all the governments functioning in China,
                    might assume in any negotiations with any individual powers or any combination
                    of powers the rights and functions of a united foreign affairs commission so far
                    as the tariff and economic relations are concerned, seeing that tariff affairs
                    are fundamental and their settlement is essential to the future welfare of
                    China.</p>
                <p>Question of tariff autonomy should be approached by stages, first stage being
                    acceptance by the powers of collection by China customs administration of
                    existing two and one-half percent surtax. When this is established China might
                    reasonably approach the diplomatic body with the request that until national
                    tariff has been properly compiled and promulgated, the arrangement as
                    recommended by America, Great Britain and Japan bases [<hi rend="italic"
                        >basis?</hi>] 1926,<note n="64" xml:id="d366fn64">See “Washington Treaty
                        Surtaxes” in sec. ii of the report submitted to the Secretary of State on
                        July 8, 1926, by the American delegation to the Special Conference on the
                        Chinese Customs Tariff, <ref target="frus1926v01#pg_767">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1926, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 767</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1926v01#pg_833">833</ref>. See minutes of meetings of
                        Sub-Committee to Draft a Resolution on the Levying of the Interim Surtaxes,
                            <hi rend="italic">The Special Conference on the Chinese Customs Tariff
                            October 1925–April 1926</hi> (Peking, 1928), pp. 382 ff.</note> shall be
                    enforced, all other existing taxes by the Maritime Customs to remain unchanged
                    with the exception of two and one-half percent surtax which would be abrogated
                    in favor of the increased import duty. Until all China is united, Maritime
                    Customs should meet all obligations secured thereon from this collection and
                    should hand over the surplus monthly to the governments in control of the
                    collecting ports. <pb facs="0496" n="378" xml:id="pg_378"/> It is computed that
                    available surplus would be some sixty million Haikwan taels per annum on the
                    basis of the 1926 customs returns. Question of abolition of likin is a purely
                    internal affair of the various governments in China. Although the difficulty
                    tantamount almost to impossibility of effecting total abolition of likin should
                    not be minimized.</p>
                <p>3. [Paraphrase.] I am informed by Edwardes that in this project, which is
                    heartily approved by the Peking Government, a member of Customs is acting as
                    intermediary with the Nanking authorities. Edwardes informed me at that time and
                    later that a point has been reached in these informal negotiations at which the
                    Southern regime has voiced its approval in principle, but is still undecided as
                    to the practical problem of how, without impairment to its claims to national
                    authority, to take part in the arrangement.</p>
                <p>4. Prior to my return to Peking, Edwardes stated, the proposal had been explained
                    by him to the other ministers who in any considerable degree were interested and
                    all had been found favorably disposed toward it with the exception of the
                    Japanese, who at first had taken an unsympathetic attitude but later had given
                    what appeared to be an indication that it might be considered favorably by
                    Japan.</p>
                <p>5. Without hesitation I informed Edwardes that the United States Government, I
                    felt sure, would approve the proposal in principle, but that for reasons arising
                    from the treaty-making system in the United States, I was doubtful whether it
                    would be practicable for our trade to be subjected by us to any interim surtaxes
                    during the period between the present time (when, by virtue of broad
                    construction of the Washington customs treaty,<note n="65" xml:id="d366fn65">
                        <ref target="frus1922v01#pg_282">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 282</ref>.</note> we are making no
                    objection to the two and a half percent surtax) and the date of exchange of
                    ratifications of a new treaty by which “tariff autonomy” is accepted.</p>
                <p>6. Before it had been possible for me to consider this matter fully and report to
                    you, it became necessary to consider it in the light of the Department’s 418,
                    December 18, noon.<note n="66" xml:id="d366fn66">
                        <ref target="frus1927v02#pg_366">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 1927, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                            p. 366</ref>.</note> My original belief that the plan is deserving of
                    the full support of the United States is confirmed by such reconsideration.</p>
                <p>7. Although appearing to restrain my judgment that it may not be misguided by
                    false hopes, it is my belief that this project, with the measure of success it
                    has already achieved, is the most hopeful and concrete basis for constructive
                    action for the solution of the present chaotic condition in China that has been
                    suggested thus far. Only through developing cooperation in meeting problems of a
                        <pb facs="0497" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> national character having a
                    definite relationship to the actual internal conditions of China can there be
                    any prospect of bringing about any degree of unification. Not only would
                    agreement in regard to some phase of fiscal arrangement afford such an
                    opportunity, but, once effected, it would constitute a continuing incentive for
                    the maintenance and development of cooperation. On the other hand, no such
                    purpose would be served by an ephemeral and purely localized combination for the
                    sole purpose of contesting and probably terminating the existing treaty rights
                    of one or more powers.</p>
                <p>8. Furthermore, the project presents a means of meeting the main difficulty
                    anticipated in executing the plan of negotiations on tariff matters as discussed
                    by me with you last October. It will be recalled that although suggesting that
                    the effort would be worth making I conceded that the chances were against the
                    possibility of being in a position to negotiate with the several factions
                    jointly or to undertake preliminary conversations with either faction without
                    encountering partisan opposition of the other. By reason of its recognition as
                    the representative body with which negotiations for the purpose we have in view
                    could be carried on, the Joint Commission created pursuant to the present plan
                    would solve this difficulty.</p>
                <p>9. Accordingly, with a view to its potential value as a stabilizing agency in the
                    affairs of China and with a view to its direct applications to us in promoting
                    the plans which we have for adjusting tariff questions with China, it is
                    recommended that I be directed by you to make known in any appropriate way your
                    approval of the project and to make the influence of the United States
                    Government available for the support of the project. [End paraphrase.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
