<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-02-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-02-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="37" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d37">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.4215 Air Pollution/48</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Canada</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-02-18"><hi rend="italic">February 18,
                                    1928</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 160</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In your despatch No. 182 of December 22,
                                1927,<note n="52" xml:id="d37fn52">Not printed.</note> you reported
                            that you had addressed a note to the Secretary of State for External
                            Affairs, suggesting that the question of the extent of damages to trees
                            and crops of property owners in the State of Washington from the drift
                            of fumes from the Consolidated Smelting and Mining Company of Canada be
                            referred to the International Joint Commission for investigation, report
                            and recommendations.</p>
                        <p>The complaint of property owners in Washington whose property has been
                            damaged by the fumes from the smelter was called to the attention of the
                            Canadian Government by the Consulate General at Ottawa as long ago as
                            June 1927.</p>
                        <p>If the matter is to be referred to the Joint Commission as suggested it
                            will be necessary to obtain from the present Congress an appropriation
                            to defray the portion of the cost of the investigation which will be
                            chargeable to the United States. It is therefore important that the
                            Department be informed at an early date regarding the attitude of the
                            Canadian Government with respect to the suggested reference to the Joint
                            Commission.</p>
                        <p>The Department will appreciate anything that you can do to expedite a
                            reply to the note which you stated in your 182 of December 22, 1927, had
                            been addressed to the Secretary of State for External Affairs.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wilbur
                                    J. Carr</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>