<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-05-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-05-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="58" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">842.0144/10</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Canadian Minister</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Massey</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-01"><hi rend="italic">May 1,
                                1928</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your note No. 78, dated April 27, 1928, concerning stray
                            bullets alleged to have been fired by preventive officers of the
                            Government of the United States, which have lodged in Canadian
                            territory. You request that an inquiry be made with a view to furnishing
                            an explanation of the events set forth in your note and preventing the
                            occurrence of similar incidents in the future.</p>
                        <p>I have requested the appropriate authorities of this Government to cause
                            an investigation to be made with respect to these matters and upon
                            receipt of replies a further communication will be addressed to you. It
                            would be helpful if you could find it possible to furnish <pb facs="0217" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> a complete statement of the
                            facts and circumstances under which these incidents occurred, including
                            the names of the persons injured, the approximate place at which each
                            incident occurred, the approximate place on the boundary of the United
                            States from which the shots are alleged to have been fired, and the
                            grounds for believing that preventive officers of this Government fired
                            the shots. Such information would greatly facilitate the investigation
                            of these incidents, which I assure you this Government is anxious to
                            make in order to ascertain whether the charges are warranted and if so
                            to punish the guilty persons.</p>
                        <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>