<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Egypt ( (Gunther) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d751</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">751</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="751"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d751">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">883.05/285</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gunther</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-11-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 3, 1928</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received November 22.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 69</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my telegram No. 44
                    of even date reporting the receipt of and commenting briefly on an identic Note
                    addressed under date of October 28th, 1928, by the Minister for Foreign Affairs
                    to the representatives in Egypt of the capitulatory powers reopening the general
                    subject of the modification of the capitulatory regime as effective in this
                    country and requesting, in particular, that the limited proposals in this sense
                    made by the Egyptian Government in its Note of December 25th, 1927, be recalled
                    to the attention of the Governments of the interested powers.</p>
                <p>A copy of the identic Note as addressed to this Legation, together with a
                    translation thereof, is submitted herewith.</p>
                <p>The Legation will, of course, follow this matter closely and report fully to the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Franklin Mott Gunther</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation<note n="18"
                                xml:id="d751fn18">File translation revised.</note>]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Egyptian Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi> (<persName
                            type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Afifi</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Minister</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Gunther</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Bulkeley</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-10-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">October 28, 1928</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 32–10/6 23 R</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: By letter of December 25th,
                            1927,<note n="19" xml:id="d751fn19">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_747">p. 747</ref>.</note>
                        my predecessor had the honor to draw the attention of the American Chargé
                        d’Affaires to the hindrance which the capitulatory regime presents to the
                        Egyptian State in matters of legislation, taxation, and jurisdiction, and to
                        the desire of the Egyptian Government to see substituted for this regime an
                        organization which, while adopting the measures <pb facs="0886" n="768"
                            xml:id="pg_768"/> necessary to the protection of foreign interests,
                        should be in harmony with modern ideas and more compatible with the
                        sovereignty of the country, its interests, its evolution and its
                        progress.</p>
                    <p>Solicitous of the vital interests of the country, the Government of His
                        Majesty is constantly preoccupied with this revision and hopes soon to be in
                        a position to discuss its projects with you with a view to arriving at an
                        agreement or agreements with the powers on this subject.</p>
                    <p>In the meantime, the Government of His Majesty desires to arrive at a prompt
                        realization of those reforms set forth in the aforesaid letter of this
                        Ministry and which deal with the modification of article 12 of the Mixed
                        Civil Code as well as with certain dispositions of the organic statute
                        (Règlement d’Organisation Judiciaire) of the Mixed Courts.</p>
                    <p>The proposed modification to article 12 of the Mixed Civil Code has as its
                        object the harmonizing of this article with the provisions of article 35 of
                        the Egyptian Constitution. It is true that in the present circumstances this
                        reform no longer retains the same urgent character; but the Egyptian
                        Government desires nevertheless to bring it to fulfillment, considering that
                        the suspension of Parliament is provisional.</p>
                    <p>As to the other projects which have as their object the facilitating of the
                        repression of crime (<hi rend="italic">infractions criminelles</hi>) and the
                        furtherance of justice, the Government of His Majesty is persuaded that they
                        will be readily recognized as being in the general interest and that they
                        cannot but be favorably received by the interested powers.</p>
                    <p>It is with this hope that I have the honor to resort to Your Excellency’s
                        good offices in begging Your Excellency to have the kindness to recall this
                        question to the attention of the Government of the United States.</p>
                    <p>I take [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">H. Afifi</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
