<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-11-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="863" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d863">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">462.11 W 892/1123</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The German Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Von Prittwitz</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation<note n="42" xml:id="d863fn42">File translation revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-11-26"><hi rend="italic">November 26,
                                    1928</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: I have the honor to
                            inform Your Excellency that inasmuch as a checking by the German agent
                            of the list of such claims of American nationals against Germany as were
                            presented at too late a date has made it possible to ascertain their
                            approximate number, character and amounts, my Government is determined
                            to do its share to bring about a settlement of these claims which are
                            more precisely enumerated in section (2) paragraph (<hi rend="italic">j</hi>) of the Settlement of War Claims Act of 1928.<note n="43" xml:id="d863fn43">Approved Mar. 10, 1928; 45 Stat. 256.</note> In
                            doing so it adopts the point of view also shared by the Government of
                            the United States that the essential competence of the Mixed Claims
                            Commission shall remain the same as fixed in the agreement of August 20
                                [<hi rend="italic">10</hi>], 1922,<note n="44" xml:id="d863fn44"><ref target="frus1922v02#pg_262"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p.
                                    262</ref>.</note> e. g., that it should not be extended to
                            include claims which have arisen since the end of the war and which are
                            included in the list of late claims in considerable number. Furthermore,
                            the German Government considers it as a prerequisite that the
                            preparation and adjudication of the late claims should be governed by
                            the same legal principles as have so far been applied in the proceedings
                            of the Mixed Claims Commission.</p>
                        <p>On the other hand, my Government is of the opinion that the purpose of
                            the above-mentioned statutory provision can only be accomplished to the
                            best interests of all concerned if means and ways are found by which a
                            prompt and speedy preparation and adjudication of the claims involved
                            may be fully guaranteed. Among other means my Government would consider
                            it an appropriate means to this end if definite and final terms were
                            fixed by agreement for the filing of claim and defense material,
                            including the necessary evidence, and if the two Governments were to
                            agree that the cases to be adjudicated by the Commission would have to
                            be presented for judgment within fixed <pb facs="1013" n="895" xml:id="pg_895"/> and final terms. Due to the fact that the
                            adjudication of the late claims will necessitate the continuance of the
                            expensive machinery of the German-American Mixed Claims Commission for
                            months to come, which would not have been necessary or which would not
                            have been necessary to the same extent if the claims in question had
                            been presented within the statute of limitation, expiring April 9, 1923,
                            and could have been dealt with together with the properly filed claims,
                            my Government would consider it furthermore justified to have the new
                            claimants, to whom a remedy is thus extended, participate to an
                            appropriate extent in the expenses caused by a prolonged procedure of
                            the Commission. This could be accomplished by the collection of fees,
                            and indeed a fee for the final filing of the claim, in order to
                            eliminate to the greatest possible extent claims which are unfounded or
                            which are presented in unjustified amounts, and an additional fee for
                            preparing and adjudicating each individual case. The payment of these
                            fees should, in the interest of a speedy procedure, also be required to
                            be made by definite and final date.</p>
                        <p>I may add that I have been invested with plenary power to enter into a
                            binding exchange of views with Your Excellency at any time, with a view
                            to the conclusion of an agreement based upon the points of view above
                            stated.</p>
                        <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Prittwitz</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>