<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>118. Telegram From the Embassy in Israel to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-06-07T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-06-07T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recsAlIqkRxd1fShH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="harbor-mining" lcsh-match="no_match">Mine laying</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-06-07T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-06-07T09:00:00-05:00" n="118"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                <head>118. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Israel</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d118fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 674.84A/6–755. Secret; Priority. Received at 9:31 p.m. Repeated to
                        Cairo and London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tel Aviv</hi>
                        </placeName>,<date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-06-07T16:00:00+02:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 7, 1955—4 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1034. I met with Prime Minister at noon yesterday in his office in Tel Aviv
                        (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1028)<note n="2" xml:id="d118fn2"
                        >Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LEB1">Lawson</persName> reported on June 6
                        that he had met with Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_SM1"
                            >Sharett</persName> that day and had conveyed to him the message
                        transmitted in telegram 693 to Tel Aviv (<ref target="#d111">Document
                            111</ref>) as well as the Department’s other comments suggested in
                        telegrams 699 (same as 1850 to Cairo; see <ref target="#d116fn3">footnote 3,
                            Document 116</ref>) and 700 to Tel Aviv (see <ref target="#d111fn2"
                            >footnote 2, Document 111</ref>). (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                        674.84A/6–655)</note> and handed him memorandum transmitted <gloss
                        target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 693. In subsequent oral conversation I
                    emphasized to him that our representations to Egypt were stated strongly and
                    dealt with specific measures required by Egypt to bring the Gaza strip situation
                    under control. Secondly, I informed him that we were pressing <gloss
                        target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> to agree to high level talks, adding that the
                    British and French were taking similar measures (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 699). With reference to <gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 700 I reminded <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName>
                    distinctly that the tripartite declaration applies to armistice lines as well as
                    to frontiers.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister read the memorandum and although apparently taking the final
                    paragraphs most seriously, made no comment until he had finished reading and I
                    had completed my statements as indicated above. He then said he would like to
                    give me his reactions in a completely friendly manner and with full appreciation
                    of the promptness with which the US Government had made representations to
                        <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> and informed him of those actions.</p>
                <p>His first comment referred to paragraph three <gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 693. He said with regard to the tragic sequence of events
                    since February 28, he must point out that the initial action in every case had
                    been taken “by the other side”—that every cycle of trouble had been started by
                    Egypt. He also reiterated his previous arguments to the effect that, while
                    opinions may differ regarding Israel’s use of patrols, there was no
                    justification whatever for Egypt to follow its program of persistent firing on
                    those patrols.</p>
                <pb facs="0255" n="227" xml:id="pg_227"/>
                <p>Regarding high level talks and cooperation with <gloss target="#t_UNTSO1"
                        >UNTSO</gloss>, he said he was planning to talk with <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName> the following morning. He
                    underlined the fact that Egypt had not yet replied to
                    <persName>Burns</persName>’ invitation to a joint high level meeting, which
                    invitation the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> had accepted immediately. He
                    then raised certain objections to the new conditions which had been introduced
                    in connection with the proposed talks as reported to him by <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName>. He was especially critical of
                        <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>’s insistence that high level
                    (military) talks must be premised on prior acceptance by <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> of <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>’s proposal
                    for a demilitarized zone.<note n="3" xml:id="d118fn3">Reference is to a proposal
                        which <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> made to
                            <persName>Burns</persName> on June 1 and <persName>Burns</persName>
                        conveyed to the Israelis the following day for withdrawal of all Egyptian
                        and Israeli troops from a zone one half or one kilometer wide on both sides
                        of the line of demarcation. (Telegram 346 from Jerusalem, June 3;<hi
                            rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 674.84À/6–355)<persName corresp="#p_BHA1"
                            >Byroade</persName> reported on June 5 that <persName corresp="#p_FM1"
                            >Fawzi</persName> had told <persName corresp="#p_SA1"
                            >Stevenson</persName> the previous day that the Egyptians were willing
                        to conduct high-level talks with the Israelis if they accepted this
                        proposal. (Telegram 1850 from Cairo, June 5;<hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi>
                        674.84A/6–555)</note> He remarked that the theory of demilitarized zones had
                    been proven generally in practice as ineffective and a source of continuing
                    trouble. He spoke at some length on the inequities of the proposal as viewed by
                    Israel, pointed out that infiltration was solely an Egyptian action as Israel
                    did not practice it. He said, “we do not infiltrate into Gaza. The infiltrators
                    come from Gaza and although the situation has improved in that respect and it is
                    not the major problem now, the demilitarized zone proposal would recreate this
                    problem in a very serious manner. Thus, the emphasis would be shifted from the
                    present military problem to that of infiltration”. With regard to both
                    infiltration but especially military actions by persons in Gaza, he said “we do
                    not say our irregulars or unknown persons perpetrate these actions. Quite the
                    contrary. We decided, as in a recent incident, who was responsible. The
                    Egyptians say they cannot be responsible for some of these actions. In the
                    latest Burns-Nasser talk,<persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>
                    admitted that Egyptian troops had opened fire but repudiated responsibility for
                    mine laying, saying he did not know who did it. We do not say this. In the face
                    of mutual evacuation, therefore, it could not be the same for Israel as for
                    Egypt; Egypt will not be prevented from using irregulars, and this is of no
                    small danger from Israel’s viewpoint”. He also said, “to evacuate troops from
                    the area would leave the ground free for marauding, theft, pillaging and other
                    incidents. The presence of troops prevents that. Any suggestion to Israel to
                    accept the withdrawal of troops proposal unconditionally would seem to betray a
                    lack of familiarity with the problem and could lead to one-sidedly grave
                    effects”.</p>
                <p>I suggested that joint patrols could supply the necessary controls in the
                    evacuated areas. He gave no convincing reply to that point <pb facs="0256"
                        n="228" xml:id="pg_228"/> and after an exchange of arguments and comment, he
                    admitted that this point could be considered at any joint high level meeting
                    eventually set up. I also suggested that <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>’s
                    initial lack of enthusiasm for the “no man’s land” plan was to a considerable
                    extent due to the fact that the plan was advanced by <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>. He then inquired whether the present
                    reaction to the plan might be substantially improved if the project were
                    presented formally by <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName>.
                        (<persName corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName> had previously advanced claim
                    that Egypt was clearly the aggressor and was now seeking its reward for
                    aggression by presenting this plan and Israel could not accept such dictation
                    “at the point of a bayonet”.) The reply to my question was non-committal but it
                    was clear that he saw the point. I took this opportunity to again emphasize the
                    very substantial progress which would be made if a high level military meeting,
                    without any prior rejections or prior acceptances of conditions applying to
                    subjects which might be discussed at such meetings, could be arranged.</p>
                <p>At the close of our conversations, which were conducted pleasantly and in a
                    relaxed atmosphere, we summed up our understandings as described above and it
                    was agreed that I would report back to Washington that <persName
                        corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName> had no objections to a high level
                    military meeting and would make no advance rejection of any concrete proposals
                    prior to such meeting. This understanding with <persName corresp="#p_SM1"
                        >Sharett</persName> was arrived at, however, only after I had urged him not
                    to fake [<hi rend="italic">make</hi>?] a categorical rejection of the proposal
                    for a “no man’s land”, pointing out that such action would be as open to
                    criticism as was <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName>’s demand for a
                    categorical acceptance by Israel of his plan—a condition to which <persName
                        corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName> had strongly objected.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: I was unable to determine whether <persName
                        corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName> was reflecting directly the sense of the
                    Cabinet meeting held on Sunday,<note n="4" xml:id="d118fn4">June 5.</note> which
                    is reported to have considered the Gaza situation. This seems likely although no
                    firm or formal decision may have been made at that meeting. When I left him, I
                    again reminded him that there should be no rejection of any proposal prior to
                    the talks and he confirmed my understanding.<persName corresp="#p_HCC1"
                        >Herzog</persName> of Foreign Office, who was present during the
                    conversation, undertook to again stress to the Prime Minister the visible
                    disadvantages to Israel of a rejection of the demilitarized zone plan prior to
                    the high level meeting.</p>
                <p>However, some afternoon papers carried stories that the <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> had rejected the demilitarized zone plan. Later in the day I
                    talked to <persName corresp="#p_HCC1">Herzog</persName> about these stories and
                    he assured me that they had no authorized basis but that they would add a new
                    factor and that Prime Minister had commented to him that every effort should be
                        <pb facs="0257" n="229" xml:id="pg_229"/> made to speed up the high level
                    meeting. The Prime Minister would take this line with <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName> in his conversation today.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LEB1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Lawson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
