<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-08-30T18:54:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-08-30T18:54:00-05:00" n="238" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d238">
                        <head>238. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Egypt</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d238fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 684A.86/8–3055. Top Secret;<gloss target="#t_Niact1">Niact</gloss>; Alpha; Limited Distribution. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BWC1">Burdett</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RFH1">Russell</persName> and approved by the
                                    Secretary.<persName corresp="#p_RFH1">Russell</persName> signed
                                for <persName>Dulles</persName>. Also sent <gloss target="#t_Niact1">niact</gloss> to Baghdad, Beirut, Amman, Damascus, Jidda, and
                                Tripoli. Repeated to London, Paris, Tel Aviv, and
                            Ankara.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>,<date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-08-30T18:54:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">August 30,
                                        1955—6:54 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>401. Prelim reactions to Secretary’s speech have in main been
                            gratifyingly thoughtful, sober and responsible. Dept desires make most
                            of present momentum provided by speech and supporting statements by
                                <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>,<note n="2" xml:id="d238fn2">See
                                    <ref target="#d230fn2">footnote 2, Document 230</ref>.</note>
                                France,<note n="3" xml:id="d238fn3">Telegram 898 from Paris, August
                                28, transmitted the text of a statement to be issued that day by the
                                French Foreign Office. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                684A.86/8–2855)</note><gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss><gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>-Gen,<note n="4" xml:id="d238fn4">See
                                the New York Times, August 27, 1955, p. 1.</note> Ceylon,<note n="5" xml:id="d238fn5">The Embassy in Colombo furnished the Department
                                with the text of the Government of Ceylon’s statement on August 28.
                                (Telegram 77; Department of State, Central Files,
                                684A.86/8–2855)</note> and additional statements which may be
                            forthcoming. Effort is complicated of course by Gaza developments but we
                            intend treat Gaza flareup separately and as far as Alpha concerned, use
                            it only to underscore necessity moving forward.</p>
                        <p>Meeting of Arab states Cairo Sept 3 will be important in setting Arab
                            course. Despite probable reiteration of past polemics for bargaining and
                            domestic polit purposes, we hope fol may materialize from meeting: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Approval of Secretary’s sincerity and effort at impartiality
                                    in stating problems;</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Expression of desirability exploring significance and fuller
                                    meaning of Secretary’s statement.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <pb facs="0449" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/>
                        <p>We wish avoid necessity deal with Arab states as bloc. Hope they will
                            tacitly agree Egypt take lead in exploring Secretary’s ideas.
                            Intimations from Nuri and Bashayan that Egypt holds key to Arab position
                            give reason think Arab states may agree to Egypt moving first.</p>
                        <p>We assume Arabs not yet ready tackle problems by their reps sitting
                            around table with Israelis. Exchange of views of various parties
                            therefore might be achieved through suitable person or commission
                            designated by <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, or by any govt or
                            person agreed upon by both sides.</p>
                        <p>Chiefs of mission should in their discretion seek impress upon delegates
                            to Sept 3 meeting essentiality avoiding negativism and of indicating
                            their govts’ desire explore further significance of statement.</p>
                        <p>Chiefs of mission authorized to use, informally and orally only, and in
                            response inquiries from govts to which accredited, any of points in
                            guidance contained <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 139 to Tel
                            Aviv rptd other posts, except para 3(e).<note n="6" xml:id="d238fn6"><ref target="#d214">Document 214</ref>.</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>