<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>310. Memorandum of a Conversation, New York, September 26, 1955, 9:45
                    p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-09-26T20:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-09-26T20:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-09-26T20:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-09-26T20:45:00-05:00" n="310"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                <head>310. Memorandum of a Conversation, New York, September 26, 1955, 9:45
                        p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d310fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Conference Files: Lot 60 D 627,<gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 555. Top
                        Secret. Dated September 30. A note on the source text states that it is not
                        a verbatim report but a paraphrase from notes. The drafter is not
                        indicated.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_POMNYMC1">POM(NY)MC</gloss>–1</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-09-26T21:45:00-04:00"
                            >September 26, 1955, 9:45 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">US</hi>:</item>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RFH1">Russell</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BWC1">Burdett</persName>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                        </hi>:</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Sir <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Roger Makins</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCAE1">Evelyn Shuckburgh</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. Patrick Hancock</item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Egypt—Purchase of Arms from <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>: I took advantage of a call
                    by the Egyptian Ambassador on September 23 to express very strong concern
                    regarding the reports of an Egyptian-Soviet arms agreement. From New York, I
                    sent a telegram asking our Ambassador in Cairo to seek particulars from
                        <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> and to repeat to him the
                    strong language used in London.</p>
                <pb facs="0545" n="517" xml:id="pg_517"/>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>:<persName corresp="#p_PMGWBJ1">Persons</persName>
                    in whom we have confidence confirmed from <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> today that an agreement of the character reported has
                    been made. The size of the shipments was not indicated but the presumption is
                    that the detailed information we received previously is correct. Our
                    representatives made known our concern and set out the grave consequences for
                    Egypt. We are faced by a difficult situation. We could give arms aid or a
                    security guarantee to Israel but this would only involve us in a cycle. We could
                    throw more weight behind the Turk-Iraq-Pakistan Pact and try to isolate Egypt.
                    Up to now we have supported the Northern Tier but have not been eager to have
                    Arab states bordering on Israel join; nor have we desired to build up an Iraqi
                    challenge to Egypt’s position of leadership in the Arab world.</p>
                <p>If the French agree, the three of us could speak to <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d310fn2">
                        <persName>Dulles</persName>,<persName corresp="#p_MHM1"
                        >Macmillan</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Pinay</persName> spoke
                        with <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> on the subject of the
                        Soviets’ selling arms to Egypt on September 27 at 9:30 p.m. For a summary of
                        this conversation, see <ref target="#d317">Document 317</ref>.</note> I
                    raised the matter with him on September 20.<note n="3" xml:id="d310fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d286">Document 286</ref>.</note> I said I thought it was a
                    grave step which would increase area tension and expressed the hope that the
                    reports were untrue. He unconvincingly tried to pass it off by saying it was a
                    commercial sale with no political implications. In the US the development will
                    have serious effects because of widespread anti-Communist feelings accentuated
                    by the powerful influence in the Jewish press. It will disturb the new
                    atmosphere between Soviets and the Western Powers. I mentioned the matter to
                        <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>, who was concerned and feared
                    that Soviet arms might filter through Egypt and Libya to North Africa. I doubt
                    that the Soviets will stop the deal but they might moderate the amounts.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>: We are faced by a major
                    issue. I have not been able to understand why the Soviets have not made this
                    move previously. It constitutes an aggressive entrance into a new area.</p>
                <p>We could reward the “good boys” and punish the bad. We could extend more help to
                    the Turk-Iraq Pact. We are now considering issuing a statement indicating we
                    would welcome Iranian entrance into the Pact. We would not extend additional
                    guarantees, but the statement we have in mind might be helpful to the Iranian
                    Government. We could also give Iraq more equipment and encourage Jordan and
                    Lebanon to join the Pact.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>: We could become involved in an expensive process
                    because the Soviets have available obsolescent equipment with which they can
                    make attractive offers which we would be hard-put to meet. Saudi Arabia and
                    Syria particularly might be tempted to accept.</p>
                <pb facs="0546" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/>
                <p>I believe the transaction will go far to shatter the spirit of Geneva. I
                    mentioned it to Casey, MacDonald and Pearson and all felt it was bad business.
                    It is a reckless proceeding by Moscow which will only intensify the strains in
                    the area. I do not know what Israel will do.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_RFH1">Russell</persName>: Israel is frightened of a
                    situation in which the Arabs can rush in and bargain off their resources between
                    the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the West. Israel knows she has
                    nothing comparable to offer.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>: We should approach <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> now. It is impossible to believe in the
                    co-existence of two worlds, if the Soviets choose this moment to make such a
                    mischievous move.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_SCAE1">Shuckburgh</persName>:<persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> could reply that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> would be glad to stop if the West would cease efforts to build
                    up military defense arrangements. He could ask whether we are interested in a
                    neutral Middle East.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>: Our efforts are directed at an Arab-Israel
                    settlement. We should consider the Russian move in the context of its effects on
                    the prospects for such a settlement. The whole world has recognized that the
                    Alpha proposals are fair. The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> offer will
                    destroy them. We are not talking of the Northern Tier or our efforts to prevent
                    Soviet aggression. This matter is completely apart from our differences
                    regarding the value of collective security arrangements.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>: With <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> we should stick to the argument that
                    the arms offer will adversely affect prospects for an Arab-Israel
                    settlement.</p>
                <p>At the same time we should not abandon efforts at getting <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> to abandon the arrangement.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>: If <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> rejects the offer, he may well be overthrown and we could
                    get someone worse.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>: We must try a combination of
                    the carrot and the stick. We could help <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> as well as hurt him in the Sudan. We could permit him to
                    purchase the minimum arms necessary to keep his position and the US could help
                    him with the high dam at Aswan.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>: We might be able to sweeten up our arms offer,
                    but we are not in a position to do much with respect to grant military
                    assistance without causing trouble with Israel.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>: We could turn to the
                        stick.<persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> cannot have thought
                    out all the consequences of his move. We could tell him frankly that we cannot
                    tolerate it. It is a breach at least of the spirit of the Suez base agreement.
                    The world will not allow the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to become the
                    guardian of the Suez Canal. We could make life impossible for <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> and ultimately bring about his fall by
                    various pressures.</p>
                <pb facs="0547" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/>
                <p>The development is certain to be attacked by the Right Wing Tories in the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> on the grounds that we left Egypt and let the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> in. The Tories will claim that this is
                    the result of Mr.<persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>’s moderate
                    policies.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>: Mr.<persName corresp="#p_SCAE1"
                        >Shuckburgh</persName> and Mr.<persName corresp="#p_RFH1">Russell</persName>
                    might draw up a paper covering the above points for our consideration.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d310fn4">No such document has been found in Department of
                        State files.</note> Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>’s
                    comments regarding the Suez base are very important. We did not all work so hard
                    to get a Suez base agreement in order to turn the base over to the Soviets.</p>
                <p>In the United States we will not be able to put a good face on the matter. It
                    will be regarded as a major defeat.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>: We have not yet completed
                    our withdrawal from the Suez base and a demand might arise in Parliament to stop
                    withdrawal. If we had your support, we might call the whole thing off.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_RFH1">Russell</persName>: If we could get <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> to move on Alpha we would want to
                    telescope our tactics. We might discuss with <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> in detail the settlement we have in mind and then present
                    this to Israel. The above course immediately involves the question of whether
                    the US and the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> are prepared to exert pressure
                    on Israel.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>: We cannot make a deal with Egypt without prior
                    consultation with Israel. We must continue to serve as a friend of both
                    sides.</p>
                <p>If Egypt lines up with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, I doubt that US
                    public opinion would permit us to use coercive restraints in the event of an
                    Israel attack. The only reason Egypt doesn’t attack Israel now is that she knows
                    we will take restraining action.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_SCAE1">Shuckburgh</persName>: Can the Soviet-Egyptian
                    agreement be used to persuade Israel that she had better make more substantial
                    concessions than we previously had in mind?</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>: I believe Israel would be more disposed now to
                    make a settlement. She might give up a bigger slice of the Negev.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>: If we think Israel will
                    accept what we consider a fair settlement, we could then offer this to
                    Egypt.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_RFH1">Russell</persName>: If <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> maintains he is unable to withdraw
                    from the arrangement now, perhaps we could still work matters out if he would
                    agree immediately to an Alpha settlement and would strictly limit the arms
                    purchased from the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to those definitively
                    contracted for.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName corresp="#p_MHM1">Macmillan</persName>:<persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> would have to agree to exclude any Russian
                    technicians.</p>
                <p>Mr.<persName>Dulles</persName>: I agree with the suggestion, but we must also
                    work to soften up the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
