<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-10-31T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-10-31T20:00:00-05:00" n="374" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d374">
                        <head>374. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission at the United
                                Nations</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d374fn1">Source:
                                Department or State, Central Files, 674.84A/10–3155. Confidential;
                                Priority. Received at 8:48 p.m. Transmitted priority to Geneva on
                                November 1 as <gloss target="#t_Tosec1">Tosec</gloss> 105 and
                                repeated to London and Paris. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                Conference Files: Lot 60 D 627,<gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss>
                                618)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>,<date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-10-31T20:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">October 31,
                                        1955—8 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>393. Re Palestine in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. During meeting
                            with <persName corresp="#p_DSPJ1">Dixon</persName> (<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>) and <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> (France) held at British request this noon, it
                            was agreed that we should seek to determine what position of Secretary
                            General and <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName> was
                            on desirability having Council meeting in light of present situation at
                            El Auja. We also discussed problem created by likely injection into any
                                <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> debate of Soviet arms deal with
                            Egypt.</p>
                        <p>At meeting this afternoon with <persName>Burns</persName> and
                            Hammarskjold present we considered private report in nature of “Program
                            of Action” made by <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General
                                Burns</persName> to Secretary General, text of which contained in
                            immediately following telegram.<note n="2" xml:id="d374fn2">Telegram 394
                                from <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, October 31, not printed.
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Central Files,
                                674.84A/10–3155)</note></p>
                        <p>Purpose of “Program of Action” in Secretary General’s words was to seek
                            practical answers to developing situation between Egypt and Israel.
                            Hammarskjold felt solution lay more in direct implementation of this
                            program by <persName>Burns</persName> with parties supported by vigorous
                            joint démarches by <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, France and US
                            Ambassadors in two capitals. He felt it was hopeless to attempt
                            negotiate in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> since parties would only
                            freeze positions in any public debate.</p>
                        <p>Secretary General also felt <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting now
                            undesirable because, while Egypt might agree to implementation of
                                <persName>Burns</persName>’ “Program of Action” without insisting
                            that Israel withdraw Kibbutz from <gloss target="#t_DZ1">DZ</gloss>, if
                            matter discussed in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> they would most
                            assuredly point out paramilitary character of Kibbutz and demand its
                            withdrawal.</p>
                        <p>Since Israel would obviously refuse to do this, whole program would fall.
                            He did not rule out, however, possibility of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> action confirming this program of <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName> if in circumstances as
                            they develop this seemed desirable or necessary.</p>
                        <p>Hammarskjold regards this program as a coordinated approach for which
                            agreement of three governments necessary and no action will be taken on
                            it until comments and concurrence of three governments available.</p>
                        <p>Hammarskjold envisages that three points made in
                                <persName>Burns</persName>’ “Program of Action” be put forward
                            essentially as a simultaneous and unified proposal which, however, could
                            be implemented in certain <pb facs="0716" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/>
                            logical steps. He therefore believes that <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName> should proceed from point three, that the
                            old international frontier be demarcated. This idea could be acceptable
                            to Israelis if done by <gloss target="#t_UNTSO1">UNTSO</gloss>, acting
                            alone, provided they silently acquiesced in it and did not openly push
                            their claims, which <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> regards as very
                            weak, for sovereignty over present demilitarized zone up to old
                            international frontier.</p>
                        <p>Second logical step of program would be point two, i.e., withdrawal by
                            Egypt of checkposts which are now on Israeli side of old frontier line
                            and in <gloss target="#t_DZ1">DZ</gloss>. From his talks with <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> (Egypt) Hammarskjold believes
                            Egyptians realize that once frontier has been marked by <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, position their checkposts beyond it will
                            be untenable and they can see their way clear to withdrawal.</p>
                        <p>Thereafter point one of program could be implemented, i.e., withdrawal by
                            Israel of military personnel in excess of Kibbutz inhabitants and
                            civilian police who were present prior to 26 August. <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName> at several points in
                            discussion emphasized strongly necessity of complete and immediate
                            backing of his action with parties by tripartite approaches in
                            capitals.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that three delegations would transmit text of “Program of
                            Action” to their governments for instructions. I said we should not
                            decide in principle against having <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                            meeting nor should we prejudice General Bum’s efforts in implementing
                            his program by premature meeting. Continuing to speak personally I felt
                            it might be desirable to start with <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName> implementing his program. Meanwhile we
                            could jointly consider desirability of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                            meeting with attendant publicity if that appeared in the circumstances
                            to be desirable. Hammarskjold said he agreed 100 per cent with this
                            approach. It was understood that <persName>Burns</persName> would not
                            undertake any action on his program until comments and concurrence of
                            three governments had been received.</p>
                        <p>Request Department’s comments on suggested plan of action.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1"><hi rend="strong">Lodge</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>