<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-12-30T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-05T02:09:00-05:00" n="393" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d393">
                        <head>393. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>On November 9, Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> met with President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> in Denver at 12:10 p.m. During the course of
                            their conversation, which lasted approximately 20 minutes, the President
                            and the Acting Secretary reviewed the current situation in Geneva at the
                            meeting of Foreign Ministers and then discussed the status of Alpha.
                            According to the memorandum of conversation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Mr.<persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> told the
                                    President of the hope of the State Department to send Bob
                                    Anderson to that spot, first going to London to get lines
                                    squared off with the British, then going to Egypt and then to
                                    Israel. There are two objectives: (1) to try to get Colonel
                                        <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasser</persName> back on the
                                    track; second, to try to bring peace to the area and revive the
                                    Alpha project of the Secretary of State.</p>
                                <p>“The President’s only comment to Bob Anderson’s selection was:
                                    you certainly have picked a good one.</p>
                                <p>“The Acting Secretary told the President that the State
                                    Department did not think Israel and Egypt would move within the
                                    near future.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>After informing President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> about the Soviets’ explosion of another
                            atomic bomb and describing his conversation with the President of
                            Guatemala, Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> and “The President went over draft of statement
                            to be issued on Mid East, in connection with Sharrett’s visit to this
                            country. Statement is to be issued, saying it has the Secretary’s
                            concurrence.” (Eisenhower Library, Whitman
                                File,<persName>Dulles</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> Series) For text of President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s statement of November 9,
                            see Department of State<hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November 21,
                            1955, page 845.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>