<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-04-29T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-04-29T10:00:00-05:00" n="85" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                        <head>85. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Consulate General at
                                Jerusalem</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d85fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 674.84A/4–2955. Confidential.
                                Received at 5:22 p.m. Repeated to Cairo, Tel Aviv, London,
                                    Paris,<gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, Amman, Beirut, and
                                Damascus.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi></placeName>,<date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-04-29T17:00:00+02:00"><hi rend="italic">April 29,
                                        1955—5 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>306. <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName> left with me
                            April 28 copy aide-mémoire he had given Eytan same day re Israel’s
                            refusal participate joint patrols Gaza area. Aide-mémoire states that
                            while no reasons given for refusal <persName>Burns</persName> assumes
                            they may have been based on thoughts expressed article<hi rend="italic">Jerusalem Post</hi> diplomatic correspondent April 22 (Tel Aviv
                            telegram 908 to Department<note n="2" xml:id="d85fn2">The<hi rend="italic">Jerusalem Post</hi> article of April 22 justified
                                the Israeli Government’s rejection of joint patrols on the grounds
                                that this would foment popular indignation, would infringe upon
                                Israel’s sovereignty, would reflect adversely upon the competency of
                                the Israel Defense Force, and would make the Israeli Government a
                                party to the deception that Egypt was fulfilling its obligations to
                                implement <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">General Burns</persName>’
                                proposals. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 674.84A/4–2255)</note>)
                            upon which <persName>Burns</persName> proceeds to comment. Summary
                            herewith.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Begin Summary:</hi>
                            <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Egyptians have informed <persName>Burns</persName> officially
                                    that only regular troops are in positions within one kilometer
                                    of <gloss target="#t_DL1">DL</gloss>. <persName>Burns</persName>
                                    offers investigate Israeli allegations to the contrary and
                                    requests details.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Position expressed by Egypt about erecting barbed wire fence
                                    along certain parts of frontier would not appear rule out
                                    discussions regarding erection effective continuous obstacle
                                    along the <gloss target="#t_DL1">DL</gloss>.</item>
                                <pb facs="0196" n="168" xml:id="pg_168"/>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Referring<hi rend="italic">Jerusalem Post</hi> reasoning
                                    against joint patrols,<persName>Burns</persName> expressed
                                    opinion that if joint patrols had been established following
                                    discussions begun last December incidents, which Israeli
                                    complained to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> on April 4,
                                    would not have occurred. He points out that Israeli patrols
                                    adjacent <gloss target="#t_DL1">DL</gloss> are peculiarly
                                    vulnerable. Such patrols further back would be less exposed and
                                    more effective; while joint patrols would show those
                                    evilly-disposed toward Israel that Egypt cooperating preventing
                                    violations. On the contrary, Israel’s refusal accept joint
                                    patrols plus continuance Israel patrols along <gloss target="#t_DL1">DL</gloss> possibly indicative Israeli
                                    refusal cooperate efforts relieve tensions, prevent further
                                    incidents.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Argument that joint patrols infringe sovereignty is
                                    unrealistic since for all practical purposes patrols would be
                                    moving along the <gloss target="#t_DL1">DL</gloss> and would not
                                    infringe territorial rights.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Finally, statements in newspaper believed to carry official
                                    views to effect Egyptians acting in bad faith respecting
                                    measures they have accepted may well endanger possibility
                                    arranging the “high level conference” which Israel professes to
                                    desire; since Israel’s refusals consider one of the proposals
                                    which Egypt has accepted may result in latter’s withdrawal of
                                    her agreement to the other proposals. This would destroy basis
                                    for holding conference.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">End Summary</hi>.<note n="3" xml:id="d85fn3">The
                                Embassy in Tel Aviv informed the Department that the Israeli Foreign
                                Ministry on the evening of May 2 had replied to
                                    <persName>Burns</persName>’ aide-mémoire, saying that Israel
                                “(a) was prepared to have this question included in agenda for joint
                                talks, but (b) that its position on joint patrols was one of
                                opposition.” (Telegram 933 from Tel Aviv, May 3;<hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 674.84A/5–355)</note></p>
                        <p>Pouching text.<note n="4" xml:id="d85fn4">Reference is to despatch 168
                                from Jerusalem, May 2. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                674.84A/5–255)</note></p>
                        <p>Have informed Bums regarding <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>
                                125.<note n="5" xml:id="d85fn5">Also transmitted to Tel Aviv as
                                telegram 628; see <ref target="#d83fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                    83</ref>.</note> He considered Shimoni’s<note n="6" xml:id="d85fn6">Ya’acov Shimoni, Counselor of the Israeli Embassy in
                                Washington.</note> observations numbered paragraph 5 as
                                “erroneous.”<note n="7" xml:id="d85fn7">When Department officials
                                spoke with representatives of the Israeli Embassy on April 27 and
                                urged Israel to accept <persName>Burns</persName>’ joint patrol
                                proposal, Shimoni justified Israel’s refusal on the grounds that
                                Egypt had in fact only accepted <persName>Burns</persName>’
                                proposals for joint patrols and a modified form of his suggestion to
                                erect physical barriers, but had failed to agree as well to the
                                conclusion of a local commander’s agreement or to the exclusive use
                                of regular forces along the frontier. (Telegram 628 to Tel Aviv;
                                Department of State, Central Files, 674.84A/4–2755)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CWEJ1"><hi rend="strong">Cole</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>