<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Article 40, paragraph 1 a</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d166</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">166</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-07-28T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-10-15T17:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-15T17:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-07-28T18:00:00-05:00" n="166" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">C.P.(Gen)Doc.1.E.6.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Article 40, paragraph 1 a</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-outside-research" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1946-10-15T23:59:59+01:00" notBefore="1946-07-29T00:00:00+01:00">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>Add to the text of Article 40, paragraph 1, A, the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>… “But Italy may maintain or build permanent fortifications, situated not
                            less than 20 kms. from the frontier, solely for the purpose of ensuring
                            the defence of her territory.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">Justification</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>After examining the conditions of the Treaty of Peace with Italy, we note
                        that the clause in Article 40, paragraph 1 a, contains the following words:
                            <pb facs="0700" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“1. The system of permanent Italian fortifications and military
                                installations along the Franco-Italian frontier, and their
                                armaments, shall be destroyed or removed.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>To impose such a condition on Italy, in the light, moreover, of the
                        precedent of the Treaty of Versailles which was imposed on Germany, would
                        clearly result in Italy being deprived of her elementary right of defence
                        against possible invasion, or other form of military aggression against her
                        frontiers by land forces. The fact of preventing Italy from becoming a
                        possible aggressor or disturber of the peace and thus preventing the
                        outbreak of a fresh armed conflict, should not deprive that country, in our
                        opinion, of the right to organise and maintain a system of fortifications
                        along its frontier; for the country would otherwise be entirely at the mercy
                        of its neighbours.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Although it is evidently very difficult to determine where the line
                        between defensive and offensive action should be drawn, in other words to
                        determine what constitute means of attack, and active or passive means of
                        defence, <hi rend="italic">permanent fortifications</hi> (subject to slight
                        restrictions as regards their dispersal and use, as well as regards the
                        range of the Artillery employed) this should not deprive a nation of the
                        elementary right of self-defence and of safeguards for its sovereignty, in
                        the same way as individuals are entitled to defend their own homes; all the
                        more so since being permanent and stationary, these fortifications cannot
                        well be transformed into elements or means of aggression. On the contrary,
                        they constitute aids to world peace; for by preventing territories being
                        invaded, they would give the United Nations the necessary time for
                        intervening in the conflict.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Under these conditions, and in view of the moral and military aspects of
                        the clause in question, and without any other intentions than those based on
                        respect for the principles of international right and justice, which are
                        those by which Brazilian national policy is inspired, the Brazilian
                        Delegation submits this amendment.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
