<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Annex 3</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d197</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">197</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-07-28T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-10-15T17:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-15T17:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-07-28T18:00:00-05:00" n="197"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d197">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">C.P.(Gen)Doc.1.J.20.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex 3</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-outside-research" calendar="gregorian"
                        notAfter="1946-10-15T23:59:59+01:00" notBefore="1946-07-29T00:00:00+01:00"
                        >undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>Add a new sub-paragraph (3) to paragraph 1 of Annex 3, reading as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Any cession or transfer of Italian State or parastatal
                                property on the territory of the Dodecanese made subsequent to
                                September 3. 1943, shall be null and void</hi>.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Under paragraph 1 of Annex 3 of the draft Peace Treaty with Italy “The Successor
                    State shall receive without payment Italian State and parastatal property within
                    territory ceded to it”. As certain information would seem to show that, after
                    September 3, 1943, the Fascist Republican Government of Italy improperly
                    transferred certain property falling under the above category, it would be
                    advisable to have a special clause implicitly confirming that such acts are null
                    and void.</p>
                <p>Add a new paragraph following paragraph 1, reading as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">The Italian Government will immediately hand over to
                                the Greek Government archives, manuscripts, registers, plans,
                                topographical maps, deeds and any kind of document relating to the
                                civil, military, financial, judicial or other administration of the
                                Dodecanese. If any of these documents, archives, registers, deeds or
                                plans have been removed, they will be restored by the Italian
                                Government at the request of the Greek Government</hi>.</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">The Italian Government agrees to trace and restore
                                similarly to the Greek Government any documents, archives or objects
                                of archeological, historical, religious or artistic value which have
                                been removed from the Dodecanese following the Italian occupation of
                                the Islands</hi> (<hi rend="italic">5.5.1912</hi>).</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Any disputes concerning the interpretation or
                                execution of the present Article will be referred to an arbitrator
                                designated by UNESCO: the arbitrator’s ruling will be
                            final</hi>.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>A special Article will be required defining the character of the archives
                    referred to in Art. 1 of Annex 3, and including objects of archeological,
                    artistic or historical importance. The point is that these <pb facs="0720"
                        n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/> objects relating to the Dodecanese constitute the
                    moral and spiritual patrimony of the Islands and are evidence of the splendid
                    part they have played in the age-old civilisation of Greece.</p>
                <p>Substitute the following new Text for paragraph 2 of Annex 3: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Within a period which it shall determine, the
                                Successor State shall make arrangements for the conversion into its
                                own currency of Italian currency held within the Ceded Territory by
                                persons continuing to reside on the said territory or juridical
                                persons continuing to carry on business there</hi>.</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Italy shall credit the Successor State with the
                                sterling equivalent of the Italian lire thus converted. The rate of
                                conversion shall be the average parity rate between the pound
                                sterling and the lire obtaining in the Dodecanese during the Allied
                                occupation</hi>.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Under paragraph 2, Annex 3, of the draft Peace Treaty with Italy “The Successor
                    State shall make arrangements for the conversion into its own currency of
                    Italian currency held within the Ceded Territory by persons continuing to reside
                    on the said territory or juridical persons continuing to carry on business there
                    …”</p>
                <p>Italian lire and British military currency (B.M.A.) issued by the British
                    occupation authorities are now in circulation in the Dodecanese. The only fair
                    way to convert such currency into currency of the Successor State is the
                    following:</p>
                <p>Greece will arrange to make the conversion in question within a limited period
                    which she herself should determine. The exchange rate of the Italian lira in
                    relation to the drachmae will correspond to the parity rate obtaining in the
                    Dodecanese between the pound sterling and the lira (£1=400 lire). The
                    inhabitants of the Dodecanese have been obliged to invest the proceeds of
                    merchandise sold abroad and foreign exchange received from relatives abroad, in
                    lire calculated at the foreign exchange rate fixed by the British authorities in
                    the Islands—i.e. 400 lire to the pound sterling, or 100 lire to the dollar.
                    Consequently, the drachmae received in exchange for their lire will be
                    calculated at the corresponding rate (400 lire per 20,000 drachmae). The Bank of
                    Greece, in remitting lire to the Bank of Italy, will be credited with an
                    equivalent sum in pounds sterling.</p>
                <p>After paragraph 3, add a new paragraph 3 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), as follows:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Italy shall be responsible to the Successor State for
                                any obligations or debts assumed by her in virtue of international
                                conventions where the holders are persons acquiring the nationality
                                of the Successor State or juridical persons retaining their head
                                office or principal place of business there</hi>.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0721" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/>
                <p>After line 1 of paragraph 5, Annex 3 (or possibly as a new paragraph 3(<hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>) between paragraphs 3 and 4 of Annex 7) add a new
                    paragraph reading as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Contracts concluded prior to September 3, 1948,
                                between natural or juridical persons residing in the Dodecanese, of
                                the one part, and the Italian State or its nationals residing in
                                Italy, of the other part, the execution of which has been suspended
                                as a result of the war, shall remain operative. Nevertheless,
                                contracts in respect of which the Greek Government, in the general
                                interest, shall have notified the dissolution within a period of six
                                months from the coming into force of the present Treaty, shall
                                become inoperative. Should such compensation calculated solely on
                                the capital involved, regardless of any loss of profit which, in
                                case of disagreement, will be determined by the Conciliation
                                Commission set up under Article 72</hi>. [sic]</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>In respect of contracts concluded prior to September 3, 1943 by natural or
                    juridical persons residing in the Dodecanese, of the one part, and the Italian
                    State or its nationals residing in Italy, of the other part, provision should be
                    made for their execution and possible dissolution in the general interest at the
                    request of the Greek Government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
