<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>111. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, January
                    25, 1956</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v23p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">111</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-01-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recqSTpdPTuXLGB8v" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Inspection team</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military balance</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-01-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="111"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                <head>111. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, January
                    25, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d111fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Central Files, 795.00/1–2556. Secret. Drafted by <persName>Jones</persName>
                        on January 26 and initialed by <persName corresp="#p_RWS1"
                            >Robertson</persName> as correct.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1956-01-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 25, 1956</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Neutral Nations Supervisory Commission (<gloss target="#t_NNSC1"
                            >NNSC</gloss>)</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Ambassador Erik Boheman, Swedish Embassy</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Walter S. Robertson</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JWG1">William G. Jones</persName>, Officer in
                        Charge, Korean Affairs, <gloss target="#t_NA1">NA</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>William Nunley, RA</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador Boheman said that he had just received information from Stockholm on
                    the progress on the negotiations between the Swedes and the Communists with
                    respect to the removal of the inspection teams to the Demilitarized Zone. The
                    Swedish Charge in Peiping recently had been called in by the Chinese Communist
                    Foreign Minister. The Minister had expressed his appreciation of Swedish efforts
                    on the <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> and said that serious consideration
                    had been given to the Swedish proposal to remove the inspection teams to the
                    Demilitarized Zone. There were, however, practical difficulties involved, the
                    Foreign Minister had said, and he therefore proposed to reduce the inspection
                    teams from three to one in each Zone. In the north the remaining team would be
                    stationed at Sinuiju and in the south either at Inchon or Pusan. He also
                    proposed to substantially reduce the size of the mobile teams and the <gloss
                        target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> personnel in the Demilitarized Zone. The
                    Swedish Minister in Poland had been given the same proposal, but in addition the
                    Poles had emphasized that if this proposal was not satisfactory to the Swedes
                    they wished to continue the conversations on the subject.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Boheman said the Swedes had decided to tell the Chinese and Poles that
                    they would accept the Communist counterproposal provided the remaining
                    inspection team in each Zone was also removed. Instructions to this effect had
                    gone out to Peiping and Warsaw, but the Swedish representatives had been
                    instructed not to act until further advice from Stockholm. The Ambassador said
                    the purpose in this delay was to give the Swedes time to consult with the Swiss.
                    In this connection, he pointed out that the Swedes were in fact carrying on the
                    negotiations although the Swiss were concurring in the Swedish positions.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d111fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> also discussed the <gloss
                            target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> problem with Swiss Minister De Torrenté
                        on January 25. De Torrenté indicated that he had not received any recent
                        information from Bern on the subject but offered to inquire. On January 30,
                        De Torrenté saw <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> again and
                        told him that Swiss representatives in Beijing, Warsaw, and Prague had
                        received the same response to the Swedish and Swiss proposal to remove the
                            <gloss target="#t_NNIT1">NNIT</gloss>s to the Demilitarized Zone that
                        Ambassador Boheman had outlined to <persName corresp="#p_RWS1"
                            >Robertson</persName> on January 25. The Swiss Government was
                        disappointed in the Communist reply, but again counseled that results could
                        only come with time and patience. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1"
                            >Robertson</persName> dismissed the Communist counter-proposal as a sham
                        and urged the Swiss to press for the withdrawal of the <gloss
                            target="#t_NNIT1">NNIT</gloss>s to the Demilitarized Zone before
                        demonstrations resumed in South Korea. (Memoranda of conversations; <hi
                            rend="italic">ibid.,</hi>., 795.00/1–2556 and 795.00/ 1–3056)</note> The
                    Ambassador said Bern now had been <pb facs="0233" n="205" xml:id="pg_205"/>
                    informed of the Swedish position and he thought that the instructions to Peiping
                    and Warsaw to inform the Communists of the Swedish position would go out in a
                    day or two.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> said that he was gratified
                    at the progress being made, but he was concerned at the amount of time that
                    these actions were taking. He said he wished to clarify the Swedish position in
                    his own mind. As he understood it, the Swedish position as made clear to the
                    Communists was that the inspection teams stationed in the north and south should
                    be removed to the Demilitarized Zone, and if the Czechs and Poles refused to
                    agree to this proposal the Swedes would be unable to continue on the <gloss
                        target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1"
                        >Robertson</persName> said he wished to know whether this position was
                    negotiable or not.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Boheman replied that everything he knew indicated that the position
                    was not negotiable. Certainly it was the Swedish belief that the Czechs and
                    Poles were clearly under this impression. From the manner in which the Peiping
                    counter-proposal had been made and the manner in which the Poles had reiterated
                    that proposal with emphasis on their desire to continue the negotiations if
                    necessary, the Swedes believed that there was a good possibility the Communists
                    would accept the removal of all the inspection teams to the Demilitarized Zone.
                    The Ambassador believed that it was important that the original Swedish position
                    be maintained. To leave one team in each Zone, he told Stockholm, would be a
                    constant source of irritation from the Swedish point of view. The Swedes in
                    these circumstances would continue to have some responsibility for the figures
                    submitted by the two sides without the capability of checking these figures.
                    Leaving but one team in each Zone would be a sham and it would be most
                    undignified for the Swedes to take part in such an operation.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Boheman said that he recently had had a long conversation with Admiral
                        <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName>, and that the Admiral had
                    confirmed the impression which the Ambassador had gained from Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> that anything short of removal of the
                    inspection teams to the Demilitarized Zone would be unsatisfactory.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> said this was certainly so.
                    If the teams had been allowed to function properly, it might have been another
                    matter. They were not allowed to function properly, however, and to leave <pb
                        facs="0234" n="206" xml:id="pg_206"/> one team in each Zone would, as the
                    Ambassador had said, be a perfect sham, and would place the Swedes in the worst
                    possible position. Ambassador Boheman said that not only would this be an
                    irritant from the Swedish point of view, but also an irritant because of the
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> concern with the Communists stationed on
                    their territory. In addition, the Ambassador said that he understood that the
                    U.S. felt that there was an absolute necessity to strengthen the military
                    matériel of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Command in the south and that
                    it might be necessary to inform the Military Armistice Commission that new
                    materiel will be introduced.<note n="3" xml:id="d111fn3">On January 24,
                        Ambassador <persName>John M. Cabot</persName> wrote to <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> from Stockholm to warn that the
                        Secretary General of the Swedish Foreign Office, Arne Lundberg, was
                        irritated by reports from Washington that seemed to suggest that the United
                        States was prepared to act unilaterally to satisfy <persName
                            corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s grievances concerning the <gloss
                            target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss>, and that U.S. interest in removing the
                            <gloss target="#t_NNIT1">NNIT</gloss>s from South Korea related to a
                        desire to introduce modern weapons into Korea in violation of the Armistice
                        Agreement. Lundberg referred to a conversation between Ambassador Boheman
                        and Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> in which
                            <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> pressed for a solution
                        to the <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> issue because of the weapons
                        problem, and he also made reference to a promise allegedly made by
                        Eisenhower to <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> that the <gloss
                            target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> would be abolished or withdrawn.
                            <persName>Cabot</persName> expressed doubt that Eisenhower had made such
                        a promise. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>., 795.00/1–2456)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> emphasized the difficulties
                    with respect to aircraft. The <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Command aircraft
                    were antiquated, and spare parts for these planes were no longer manufactured.
                    It was thus impossible to replace aircraft in Korea with identical types. This
                    was a practical difficulty and while there was a problem of technicalities,
                    replacement of these planes with more modern aircraft would not violate the
                    spirit of the Armistice Agreement. One of the purposes of the <gloss
                        target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> was to preserve the military balance between
                    the two sides. This, however, had been impossible to do in view of the Communist
                    violations of the Armistice, and their obstruction of the inspection functions
                    of the Commission. Ambassador Boheman, while suggesting his thought might be
                    somewhat out of order, nevertheless said he thought it would be most advisable
                    from a public opinion point of view to produce tangible proof that the Communist
                    forces in fact had strengthened themselves with more modern weapons. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> pointed out that the
                    reports of the Swiss and Swedish members of the <gloss target="#t_NNSC1"
                        >NNSC</gloss> show that the teams had not been allowed to inspect properly
                    in the north. He pointed out that the Communists had introduced some 450 planes
                    into North Korea, of which over 250 were jet aircraft.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> again expressed concern with
                    the slowness with which the negotiations with the Communists were going. He
                    pointed out that we had hoped to get something done on the <gloss
                        target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> by October, and now it was almost February.
                    Ambassador Boheman said that he felt the only thing that could be done was to
                    repeat what the <pb facs="0235" n="207" xml:id="pg_207"/> Swedes had already
                    told the Communists—namely, that if the Communists refused to agree to the
                    Swedish proposal the Swedes would leave the Commission. The Ambassador’s
                    impression was that if the Swedes stick to this position they will gain what
                    they want.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> pointed out that the
                    Communist delay in reaching a conclusion in the negotiations with the Swedes was
                    a deliberate tactic and one with which he was all too familiar. He then
                    described to Ambassador Boheman the difficulties in attempting to negotiate with
                    the Chinese at Geneva, particularly their delaying tactics and lack of good
                    faith in adhering to even formal public commitments. In response to Ambassador
                    Boheman’s question, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>
                    confirmed his impression that there was no necessary relationship between what
                    happened to the inspection teams in Korea and what might happen to the
                    inspection teams in Indochina. He pointed out that in Indochina as in Korea the
                    Communist member of the inspection teams, a Pole, had been able to effectively
                    block the functioning of these Commissions. While the Canadians had made
                    commendable efforts to hold the teams together, the Indian member under Nehru’s
                    instructions had been reluctant to take a position against the Pole. The
                    Ambassador was glad to have this confirmation. The Canadians, he said, asked the
                    Swedes “every second month” not to do anything about the <gloss
                        target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> because of the influence they feared such
                    action would have on the Commission in Indochina.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Boheman concluded the meeting by saying that he felt the Communists,
                    in view of the promptness of the Swedish reply to their counter-proposal, were
                    aware that the Swedes desired a quick conclusion of the negotiations.
                    Nevertheless, he said he would send a cable out suggesting that his Government
                    make clear to the Communists the urgency with which the Swedes regarded the
                    matter.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
