<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-08-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="82" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                        <head>82. Memorandum of a Telephone Conversation Between the Assistant
                            Secretary of Defense for International Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_GG1" type="from">Gray</persName>) and the Acting
                            Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName type="to">Sebald</persName>), Washington, August 24, 1955<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d82fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 795.00/8–1955. Secret. Drafted by Sebald.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-08-24"><hi rend="italic">August 24,
                            1955</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Termination of <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> Activities in
                                the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Pursuant to instructions from the Secretary, I called <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gordon Gray</persName> for the purpose of obtaining
                            Department of Defense clearance to Course “B” in the attached paper<note n="2" xml:id="d82fn2">Not found attached. A note on the source text
                                indicates that the paper was the memorandum <ref target="#d81"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note> which had been
                            approved by the Secretary. I told Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> that the Secretary had approved the proposal (a
                            copy of which had been informally sent to him previously) and that we
                            desired to have his concurrence so that we could move ahead with
                            implementing this policy.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> questioned some of the
                            language but, in the light of a previous conversation which I had had
                            with the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense, Vice Admiral Arthur C.
                            Davis, said that he would not make a point of insisting upon any
                            language changes— providing paragraph 3 of the proposal means that the
                                <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> will be given notice to
                            terminate its activities no later than October 15, 1955. Additionally,
                            he wished to be assured that the proposal was not contingent upon
                            agreement by the sixteen other countries and that the United States was
                            now prepared to move ahead unilaterally, if necessary. One additional
                            request which he wished to make was that the Swiss and Swedes be
                            informed of our desire that they endeavor to <pb facs="0182" n="154" xml:id="pg_154"/> prevent any request being made by the <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> for spot inspections in South Korea
                            before October 15.</p>
                        <p>I told Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> that the date
                            October 15, 1955 did, in fact, represent the terminal date by which time
                            the <gloss target="#t_NNSC1">NNSC</gloss> would terminate its activities
                            in <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> territory. Secondly, although we
                            would inform The Sixteen of the action to be taken, the proposal was not
                            contingent upon concurrence by The Sixteen. Finally, I agreed that we
                            would endeavor to carry out the request regarding the prevention of spot
                            inspections but would, necessarily, have to make this in the form of a
                            suggestion rather than a request.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> said that he was satisfied
                            with these replies and was glad to give his concurrence. He felt that we
                            had come a long way to meet the wishes of the Department of Defense and
                            hoped that this troublesome problem would soon be ended.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>