<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>96. Memorandum From the Deputy Director of the Office of Northeast Asian
                    Affairs (Hemmendinger) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                    Affairs () to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs
                    (Robertson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v23p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d96</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">96</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-10-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-10-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="96"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d96">
                <head>96. Memorandum From the Deputy Director of the Office of Northeast Asian
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HN1" type="from">Hemmendinger</persName>) to the
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_RWS1" type="to">Robertson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d96fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 795.00/10–2455.
                        Secret. Drafted by Norred on October 21. Also sent to Sebald.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-10-24">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 24, 1955</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Forthcoming <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Recommendations on Future
                        Force Levels for the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Army</item>
                </list>
                <p>A member of <gloss target="#t_NA1">NA</gloss> has been shown privately a
                    September 6, 1955 letter from General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1"
                        >Lemnitzer</persName> to the Army Chief of Staff<note n="2" xml:id="d96fn2"
                        >Not printed. (Enclosure to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1776/542;
                        National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                            >JCS</gloss> Records, <gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> 383.21 Korea
                        (3–19–45)(2))</note> presenting <gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss>’s
                    recommendations for future force levels of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                        >ROK</gloss> Army. Defense, (ISA), has action on it, and it is expected to
                    be acted on favorably by the Joint Chiefs of Staff in the near future.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> says that the military
                    situation in Korea does not require permanent maintenance of a force of twenty
                    active and ten reserve divisions, and recommends a stage-by-stage cut-back,
                    reviewed every six months. The tentative force levels he recommends are: July
                    1957, twenty active, ten reserve (as at present); January 1958, seventeen
                    active, thirteen reserve; July 1958, thirteen active, seventeen reserve; January
                    1959, nine active, twenty-one reserve. He says that he requires a lead time of
                    eighteen months to retire a group of divisions, allowing time for locating a
                    site and constructing facilities, and asks for immediate approval of this
                    tentative schedule and approval of the necessary construction funds so that the
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> can be informed of the necessity for
                    some cuts at the earliest possible moment and necessary preparations can be made
                    for an orderly retirement. Presumably General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1"
                        >Lemnitzer</persName> has in mind notifying the <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                        >ROK</gloss> about next January.</p>
                <pb facs="0206" n="178" xml:id="pg_178"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment and Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Agreed Minute of Understanding of November 1954 states that “…<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d96fn3">Ellipsis in the source text.</note> as trained reserve
                    strengths are obtained, the total number of active military personnel will be
                    adjusted accordingly.” In negotiating the Agreed Minute it was made clear to the
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> that the United States believed the
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> had neither the manpower nor economic
                    resources to support its present armed forces indefinitely. General <persName
                        corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName>’s recommendation is moderate in
                    terms of its timing and is in line with the Agreed Minute. The only real
                    difficulty that I can see at this time is the furor which will be created in the
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> on announcement of such plans despite
                    their signature of the Agreed Minute.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d96fn4">In a November 2 memorandum to the Secretary of
                        Defense, the Joint Chiefs of Staff noted that they had approved in principle
                        a future reduction in active <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> army
                        forces, but they did not specifically approve the final number of divisions
                        and did not specify the date at which the reduction would be feasible. The
                        Joint Chiefs concluded that conditions in Korea remained sufficiently tense
                        so that “any reduction of forces at this time could cause a deterioration of
                        the Far East situation which would be detrimental to U.S. interest in that
                        area.” (Washington National Records Center, OASD/ ISA Files: FRC 60 B 1025,
                        091.3 Korea)</note> and Defense are now considering General <persName
                        corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName>’s recommendation and we are not yet
                    called upon for our views. My preliminary thought is to concur in these
                    recommendations but to examine carefully the timing and methods of informing the
                        <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>. Probably it would be best to approach
                    the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> only on the first stage of the reduction
                    and to do so at the working level where an examination would be made of the
                    manpower resources of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and the status of
                    the reserve program on the assumption that the Agreed Minute establishes the
                    general policy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
