<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-10-02T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-10-02T11:00:00-05:00" n="157" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d157">
                        <head>157. Memorandum of Conference With President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d157fn0">Source: Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Diaries. Secret. Drafted
                                by <persName corresp="#p_GGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName> on October 7.
                                A note on the source text indicates the conversation was “off the
                                record.”</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-10-02T12:00:00-04:00">October 2, 1958, noon</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>OTHERS PRESENT</head>
                            <item>Netherlands Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName></item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YP1">Young</persName></item>
                            <item>General <persName corresp="#p_GGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The President recalled that he had last met Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName> in Paris at the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting and had enjoyed the
                            opportunity to talk with him.<note n="1" xml:id="d157fn1">Reference is
                                most likely to the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Heads of
                                Government meeting, held in Paris December 16–19, 1957. No record
                                has been found of a conversation between <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName>.</note> Although the meeting was intended to be
                            quite informal and non-substantive, the discussion immediately turned to
                            Dutch New Guinea when the President asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName> for his views. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName> stressed the difficulty that the
                            government in the Netherlands is experiencing in terms of public opinion
                            because of their effort to maintain a moderate attitude toward the
                            United States on this matter. He said he and the government fully
                            understood the United States position—of avoiding actions which would
                            drive the Indonesians into the arms of the Soviets. Certain types of
                            arms the United States is supplying the Indonesians, however, cause a
                            great deal of concern. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YP1">Young</persName> confirmed that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName> and the government had been extremely understanding
                            in this matter. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName> said
                            that the Indonesians of course have no claim on Dutch New Guinea, since
                            the natives are non-Indonesian, and strongly desire to stay free of the
                            Indonesians. The land is very lightly settled, however, and the
                            possibility exists of the Indonesians making small landings at various
                            places. He felt that a “deterrent” in the form of a joint
                            Dutch-Australian statement would be very important and hoped that the
                            United States would support that.</p>
                        <p>The President commented with regard to the limited amounts of arms being
                            furnished the Indonesians, that many of these require ammunition and
                            spare parts in order to be effectively utilized, and that this gives us
                            a degree of control over their misuse; also, any recipient must
                            undertake not to use the arms for aggressive purposes.</p>
                        <p>The President recalled that we have recently been stressing very strongly
                            in the Far East the principle of “no territorial expansion by force of
                            arms.” He asked whether this would not have application in
                            Indonesia.</p>
                        <pb facs="0318" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/>
                        <p>The President and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName> next
                            discussed Dutch New Guinea in more detail, as to population, area,
                            economic development, etc. The President asked what value Dutch New
                            Guinea had to the Dutch. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName>
                            said that it does not have much real value, but that the Dutch feel they
                            have an obligation to administer and protect it. He added that other
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> members should honor this
                            feeling.</p>
                        <p>The President said he would talk in more detail to the Secretary of State
                            regarding this matter.<note n="2" xml:id="d157fn2"><persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName> and
                                    <persName>Dulles</persName> had already discussed the issue in
                                Washington on September 30. (Memorandum of conversation, September
                                30; Department of State, Central Files, 611.56D/9–3058) See
                                Supplement.</note></p>
                        <p>The President concluded by asking Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJ12">Luns</persName> to remember him to his many friends in Holland,
                            mentioning particularly Prime Minister Staf, Prince <persName corresp="#p_Bernhard1">Bernhard</persName> and Queen Juliana.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">AJG</hi></persName><lb/><hi rend="italic">Brigadier General, <gloss target="#t_USA1">USA</gloss></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>