<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>208. Telegram From the Embassy in Indonesia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d208</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">208</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-06-18T04:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-06-18T04:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recfgV5j0WMmONcRO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-06-18T04:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-06-18T04:30:00-05:00" n="208"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d208">
                <head>208. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d208fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 756D.00/6–1859. Secret. Transmitted in two sections and also sent to
                        the Department of the Army and <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1"
                        >CINCPAC</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Djakarta</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1959-06-18T17:00:00+07:30">June 18, 1959, 5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3776. <gloss target="#t_DEPTAR1">DEPTAR</gloss> for ACSI. <gloss
                        target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> also for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1"
                        >POLAD</gloss>. Deptel 1961.<note n="1" xml:id="d208fn1">Telegram 1961,
                        April 24, noted that the Department was following closely internal political
                        developments in Indonesia as reported by the Embassy and the Army Attaché.
                        “As and if situation begins to crystallize so that Embassy in position make
                        more conclusive evaluation,” the telegram reads in part, “Dept would require
                        on priority basis any recommendations Embassy might make as to optimum
                            <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> courses of action in this situation.
                        Important that such recommendations be submitted in time to permit complete
                        and careful review by all concerned here prior to formulating any decision
                        on possible <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> action.” (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid</hi>., 756D.00/4–2259)</note> Impasse produced in Constituent
                    Assembly over GOI proposal return 1945 constitution differs only in sharpness of
                    focus from fundamental impasse which has ripped Indonesian political life since
                    independence. It boils down to fact that Moslem parties cannot govern Indonesia
                    alone. No other parties or combination thereof can govern without support or at
                    least acquiescence of Moslem parties.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> has regularly utilized this
                    fact to help retain power in own hands, thus Indonesia traditionally has been
                    able maintain effective government only through intervention <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>. Accordingly his absence now has
                    brought Indonesian political leadership to almost complete road block, and there
                    is no prospect stabilizing political situation until he returns.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d208fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> was scheduled to return
                        to Indonesia from his worldwide tour on June 28.</note> Most serious
                    consequence is lack of effective government to deal with deteriorating economic
                    situation.</p>
                <p>Whether or not this stalemate deliberately produced by army conniving with <gloss
                        target="#t_NU1">NU</gloss> (and there is some evidence to suggest this) fact
                    is that when confronted with opportunity to take strong measures in President’s
                    absence, <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> has failed to move
                    either through reluctance disrupt democratic process or fear of internal army
                    divisions, probably latter. It is all the more certain that any moves that
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> may ultimately make will be
                    in the name of <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>, not against
                    him. Conversely <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> unlikely able
                    establish political stability functioning government without, at this stage,
                    full support of the army.</p>
                <p>While in past Indonesia has been able to afford political upheavals which have
                    temporarily paralyzed central government, as is the case now, there is serious
                    question whether current [upheaval?] may not result in permanent far-reaching
                    damage to nation unless strong corrective action taken immediately upon
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>’s return. This danger <pb
                        facs="0429" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/> becoming acute now because of the
                    rapidly deteriorating economic situation which may easily become extremely
                    serious unless appropriate remedies applied soon. Yet there is no reason to
                    believe that <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> will be any more
                    impressed by this danger now than heretofore; and it would be unrealistic to
                    assume that whatever measures he decides to take in the political field will be
                    taken swiftly and decisively.</p>
                <p>Although present economic crisis has not yet affected vast majority Indonesians
                    who subsistence farmers on largely non-monetary economy, it is beginning ominous
                    pinch in cities among laborers, white collar workers, armed forces, from which
                        <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> hopes draw support its ultimate
                    revolutionary goals. (Embtel 3775)<note n="3" xml:id="d208fn3">Telegram 3775,
                        June 18, reported on the deterioration of the Indonesian economy and
                        emphasized the extent to which this trend was accentuated by the political
                        crisis. (Department of State, Central Files, 756D.00/6–1859)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Because of worsening economic picture fact <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1"
                        >Nasution</persName> apparently unable or unwilling act without <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> may mean it will be too late for
                    him to take any kind of strong action with the President by the time <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> ready to proceed. This true not
                    only because economic difficulties enhance prospects, but because of renewed
                    importance party will have as supporter of President’s program where until
                    Consembly crisis <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> was gradually being boxed
                    in by being forced to choose between two unpalatable alternatives; support of
                    1945 constitution which could curtail its powers or open break with <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> which in end it feared more. It now
                    may have opportunity to wiggle off hook, perhaps recover some of position
                    previously lost.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> certainly will need political
                    strength of <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> for whatever program he
                    determines upon. <persName corresp="#p_SBG1">Colonel Sukendro</persName> has
                    informed Embassy he believes he has assurance of enough votes from Moslem
                    parties to vote dissolution of Consembly, after which President would decree
                    1945 constitution in effect. Even if <persName corresp="#p_SBG1"
                        >Sukendro</persName>’s expectation justified program remains based on
                    support also of <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>, which has taken lead in
                    demanding such course of action.</p>
                <p>It has not been <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> but Moslem parties which have
                    frustrated President’s plans, and his foremost objective upon return will
                    undoubtedly be overcome Moslem opposition in some way, for which must have aid
                    of <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> as well as <gloss target="#t_PNI1"
                        >PNI</gloss>. Former will have a price, domestically and internationally, a
                    price which <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> probably will not
                    consider unduly high.</p>
                <p>In these circumstances it would be wishful thinking to anticipate drastic action
                    against Communists by army or GOI in near future unless <gloss target="#t_PKI1"
                        >PKI</gloss> provides army with sufficient excuse by jumping traces in some
                        <pb facs="0430" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/> way. <persName corresp="#p_SBG1"
                        >Sukendro</persName>’s comments this regard (<gloss target="#t_ARMA1"
                        >ARMA</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_DEPTAR1">DEPTAR</gloss> CX–74)<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d208fn4">Not found.</note> encouraging but no certainty he speaking
                    for <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SBG1">Sukendro</persName> privately has long favored provoking
                    clash with <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Assuming that <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> still fears
                        <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> threat his own position (I have no
                    reason to doubt that he does) easiest apparent way out would be effect
                    compromise between <gloss target="#t_PNI1">PNI</gloss>, Moslem parties, which
                    would bring about legal return 1945 constitution. Common antipathy toward
                    communism then would enable Moslem parties, <gloss target="#t_PNI1">PNI</gloss>,
                    army, President work together against <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>.
                    Unfortunately this easier said than done. Fact is religious controversy in part
                    only convenient battleground for other less open but no less fundamental issues,
                    such as support of, or opposition to <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                        >Sukarno</persName>, regionalism versus centralism, Java versus outer
                    islands, et cetera. Consequently, problem of lining up anti-Communist parties
                    against <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> difficult one, and this doubtless
                    primary reason <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> tactic supporting <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and governmental issues.</p>
                <p>In determining most effective courses action <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                    must recognize <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> essential
                    element political picture for foreseeable future; thus his acquiescence,
                    preferably active support, needed for achievement any objective. If objective is
                    reduction Communist power in Indonesia through GOI repressive action, means must
                    first be found reduce <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>
                    dependence on Communists internally, externally. Alternative might be to back
                    strong rival leadership so as to neutralize importance <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>, but recent events strongly suggest
                    this is out of question for present. It seems to me the army has shown its
                    present inability to fulfill such a role, and there apparently is no available
                    understudy of suitable talents.</p>
                <p>Seemingly then we have only limited freedom of action in dealing with situation.
                    We must be prepared to continue a policy of patient strengthening of
                    anti-Communist elements in ways that may be open to us with a view to
                    surrounding <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> with right sort
                    of pressures; we must continue to attempt to convince President and associated
                    leaders Indonesia can count on <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> friendship and
                    support and that we are not attempting to dictate internal or external
                    policies.</p>
                <p>This is what we have been doing for nearly a year with some success. Fact that we
                    may have to expect temporary setback resulting from present situation, with
                    relative position of <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> enhanced, should not
                    tempt us to embark on new, unorthodox methods for mere sake of change. Our cue
                    now is to remain alert for developments capable of exploitation while
                    recognizing that in so complex a situation, trends may not uninterruptedly flow
                    in our favor.</p>
                <pb facs="0431" n="405" xml:id="pg_405"/>
                <p>In the long run we have good ground for optimism because of the political
                    leadership, including <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>
                    himself. The underlying antagonism of not only the Moslem but nationalist
                    parties toward communism and all its works, the determination of army leadership
                    to prevent a Communist take-over and our own capability to encourage and
                    strengthen these elements are dependable assets.</p>
                <p>Summing up, I am convinced that, considering all factors, our present policy of
                    gradually increasing economic, military assistance, coupled with continuing
                    efforts to build Indonesian confidence in West, exploit Indonesian fear of
                    Communist expansionism/is all we should undertake for the time being. At same
                    time we should not be deterred from doing that much by temporary deterioration
                    of political, economic situation which likely occur next few months.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JHP1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Jones</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
