<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-05-08T07:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-05-08T07:30:00-05:00" n="86" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d86">
                        <head>86. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d86fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 756D.00/5–1858. Secret; Niact. Transmitted in two
                                sections.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Djakarta</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-05-08T20:00:00+07:30">May 8,
                                    1958, 8 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>4116. Deptels 3207<note n="1" xml:id="d86fn1"><ref target="#d81">Document
                                    81</ref>.</note> and 3213.<note n="2" xml:id="d86fn2">See <ref target="#d84fn2">footnote 2, Document 84</ref>.</note> Made call
                            on General <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> this morning
                            accompanied by Col. Cole, Army Attaché.<note n="3" xml:id="d86fn3"><persName corresp="#p_JHP1">Jones</persName> summarized his
                                talk with <hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> in Indonesia: The Possible Dream</hi>,
                                pp. 137–139.</note> General treated my call as important occasion.
                            Honor guard had been turned out and he later informed me this was first
                            time he had ever received a call from an Ambassador. With him at
                            conference were General Subroto, Col. Ibnu, Lt. Col. <persName corresp="#p_SBG1">Sukendro</persName>, and interpreter for Subroto
                            among others. General <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName>’s
                            English turned out to be quite fluent.</p>
                        <p>General <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> struck me as a
                            highly intelligent, determined man of character with definite philosophy
                            and most attractive personality, <pb facs="0176" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> latter feature I had not anticipated. After we had established
                            rapport he opened up and talked freely, at one point nearly 15 minutes
                            without pause.</p>
                        <p>General received me standing, flanked by his staff officers and we spoke
                            for some minutes together before coffee was served and we sat down. In
                            connection usual exchange of courtesies. I observed that I had heard a
                            great deal about him since coming to Indonesia and that it had all been
                            good. I expressed regret that it was impossible for him to attend my
                            dinner for <persName corresp="#p_FRALH1">Admiral Frost</persName><note n="4" xml:id="d86fn4"><persName corresp="#p_FRALH1">Admiral Laurence
                                    H. Frost</persName>, Chief of U.S. Naval Intelligence, arrived
                                in Indonesia on May 8 as part of a larger trip to the Far East for
                                the purpose of inspecting U.S. naval intelligence operations. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 147)</note> tonight but that I
                            understood completely, knowing how busy he must be. However, I hoped
                            that when he saw <persName corresp="#p_FRALH1">Admiral Frost</persName>
                            tomorrow morning he would not treat the Admiral’s call as a courtesy
                            call but would discuss Indonesian situation frankly with him and
                            anything else he had on his mind. I said this would be mutually
                            beneficial.</p>
                        <p>General <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> responded that
                            he would do so. He said, “There have been serious misunderstandings
                            between United States and Indonesia.” I agreed, commenting that I hoped
                            these were in process of being cleared up.</p>
                        <p>Expressing regret but also understanding that he had been unable to send
                            observers to <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> exercise, I then
                            led into invitation from <persName corresp="#p_SAFB1">Admiral
                                Stump</persName> to attend or send representatives to modern weapons
                            demonstration and handed him draft of <persName corresp="#p_SAFB1">Admiral Stump</persName>’s letter.<note n="5" xml:id="d86fn5">Not
                                further identified.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> replied that he would
                            have liked to have sent observers to <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> exercise but that in present situation it was
                            impossible as he needed every competent officer. He said he sincerely
                            welcomed <persName corresp="#p_SAFB1">Admiral Stump</persName>’s
                            invitation, indicated that if timing were different he would have
                            accepted with pleasure but that he was afraid he would have to make same
                            response as to <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>. However, he
                            appreciated invitation and would write <persName corresp="#p_SAFB1">Admiral Stump</persName>.</p>
                        <p>I then referred to long standing arms request which Indonesian military
                            had with <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Government and outlined
                            substance of reference telegrams in less detail but otherwise as
                            presented to Foreign Minister and Prime Minister last night (Embtel
                                4112).<note n="6" xml:id="d86fn6"><ref target="#d84">Document
                                    84</ref>.</note> General appeared gratified by news that <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> was now prepared to be responsive to arms
                            request but made no specific comment. I emphasized my government wished
                            to demonstrate its confidence in leadership Indonesian Army by this <pb facs="0177" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/> move. Statement evoked
                            gratified nods from staff officers present and this was point at which
                                <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> himself began to
                            unbend.</p>
                        <p>He said he wanted me to know his thinking on position of Indonesian Army
                            within democratic government structure. (General had previously been
                            described to me as officer who talks over heads of associates. This
                            characteristic was clearly evident as General pursued theme of place of
                            Indonesian military in hierarchy.) He was disciple of late General
                            Sudirman, founder of Indonesian Army and Chief of Staff during
                            revolution, he said, in his strong conviction that Indonesian Army must
                            be protector of democratic Indonesian state based upon constitution and
                            Pantjasila. Constitution was important but Pantjasila with its five
                            principles was basis of philosophy establishing republic.</p>
                        <p>He wanted me to understand this because this was reason Army would never
                            permit Communists to take over government. <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> did not agree with two points of Pantjasila and Army
                            considered all five points fundamental to Indonesian philosophy of
                            revolution. Army had fought for individual freedom as well as
                            independence of country and was determined to preserve this.</p>
                        <p>For same reasons, he was equally and unalterably opposed to Moslem state
                            which would violate principles Pantjasila. This was old-fashioned
                            concept. It might have been all right 500 years ago in period absolute
                            monarchies but not today. He knew <persName corresp="#p_NM2">Natsir</persName> intimately. They had worked together during
                            revolution but he had never been able to subscribe to <persName corresp="#p_NM2">Natsir</persName>’s philosophy.</p>
                        <p>He was likewise opposed to military junta concept, he said. Indeed,
                            differences between himself and former members of his staff, such as
                            Colonel <persName>Lubis</persName>, revolved around this central point.
                            There was no difference in their attitude toward communism and he said
                            this represented basis misunderstanding on America’s part of issues
                            involved in current conflict. Colonel <persName>Lubis</persName> wanted
                            to use army as road to political power; other dissidents were merely
                            interested in “commercial aspects of Warlordism”. This was great evil in
                            Indonesian Army as it had been in Chinese Army in old days, and he was
                            determined to crush this and develop strong, vigorous, cohesive army
                            responsive to commander-in-chief with function of preservation
                            Indonesian democracy. He implied China might never have gone Communist
                            had this been true.</p>
                        <p>Position of Indonesian military was different and would continue to be
                            different from that of military in any other country in world that he
                            knew of, he said. He has repeatedly been urged to take over power and
                            establish military dictatorship. “I will not do this,” he said. “This is
                            what happens in Latin America. It must not happen in Indonesia. If I
                            seize power today someone else will seize power tomorrow and throw me
                            out. This does not make for stable democracy, which is our
                            objective”.</p>
                        <pb facs="0178" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/>
                        <p>Neither, however, would Indonesian military ever accept traditional
                            position of military in European democracies and under all circumstances
                            take orders from civilian politicians. Indonesian military would
                            continue active in policy. They had fought and won revolution and
                            considered they had right to be heard in councils of nation. They did
                            not want to take over power—their objective, he repeated, was to protect
                            and preserve fruits of revolution. “It is our job to preserve freedom in
                            Indonesia,” he said, “and to prevent its curtailment from whatever
                            source. This is what Pantjasila means to us.”</p>
                        <p>To carry out this concept, Army would insist on strong emergency powers
                            being provided in constitution. They must be able to move in and take
                            over legally when threat to democratic state loomed on horizon. What he
                            seemed to be saying was that Indonesian Army would in effect be
                            policeman to constitution and guardian of Indonesian liberties and that
                            he was determined to weld it into effective instrument for this
                            purpose.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: I was much impressed with General
                                <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> and believe
                            conversation was most useful from standpoint both sides. Better
                            assessment of results, however, can be made after discussions within
                            Cabinet are known and Indonesians follow up this approach.</p>
                        <p>Department’s prompt action relation above matter deeply appreciated. It
                            apparently was close thing. British Ambassador informed me today he was
                            waiting for <persName corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName> yesterday
                            at 1 p.m. and that Foreign Minister was delayed considerable length of
                            time in Cabinet meeting. His aide informed Ambassador, “there is
                            terrible argument going on in there”, and when Foreign Minister finally
                            emerged he confirmed this and indicated in meeting great pressure had
                            been brought to attack <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> openly as
                            aggressor. Events of last night and this morning already appear to have
                            brought great change in atmosphere.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JHP1"><hi rend="strong">Jones</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>