<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-11T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-11T09:00:00-05:00" n="154" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d154">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">781.02/5–1150: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Minor</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-11T16:00:00+02:00">May
                                        11, 1950—4 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1081. Venizelos called on me at noon today. I read him excerpts from
                                    <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 838 May 8<note n="1" xml:id="d154fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> and urged on him necessity
                                full cooperation himself and Liberal Party in this critical year of
                                reconstruction. He replied that he is fully behind government and
                                has no intention of overthrowing it. To this I answered that
                                impression prevails here and abroad that without his personal
                                participation there is only half a government without assured
                                stability. Venizelos then took view that it is better for him to be
                                outside government since he cannot work with Papandreou<note n="2" xml:id="d154fn2">George Papandreou, Deputy Prime Minister and
                                    Minister of Interior.</note> who is completely impossible.
                                Government, he said, would be more stable without him for this
                                reason. I replied that since coalition government is essential under
                                present conditions, it would appear that leaders have duty to
                                cooperate with each other and not consider personal preferences. I
                                asked him about his plans and he said he is leaving on 20th and will
                                consider entering government on his return. I replied frankly I did
                                not think this was good enough and hoped he would heed Department’s
                                advice that it is essential for him and Liberals to take full and
                                active role in this government. After this further reiteration of
                                our views he said he would like a little time to think the matter
                                over. Our conversation, which was entirely pleasant ended on this
                                note.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Minor</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>