<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Paper Prepared in the Bureau of Near Eastern, South Asian, and African
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d210</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">210</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-02-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec0IxeMNnec48ljR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional security</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec9wzMIGHUgT4FsE" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="north-atlantic-treaty-organization" subject="north-atlantic-treaty-organization" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092473" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">North Atlantic Pact</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-balance" lcsh-match="no_match">Military program</term>
                    <term ref="rec9e37bd484b75494" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="truman-doctrine">Truman Doctrine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-02-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="210"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d210">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Politico–Military Adviser Files: Lot 484:
                        <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>—Country Statements <gloss
                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1951<note n="1" xml:id="d210fn1">Lot 484 contains
                        the files of the Politico-Military Adviser in the Bureau of Near Eastern,
                        South Asian, and African Affairs for the years 1946–1950, including records
                        and documents of the Foreign Military Aid Coordinating Committee; Foreign
                        Assistance Correlation Committee; State, Army, Navy, Air Force Coordinating
                        Committee; and the Military Assistance Program.</note>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Paper Prepared in the Bureau of Near Eastern, South Asian, and
                        African Affairs</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d210fn2">The source text is Tab D attached to the
                        memorandum, February 10, by Assistant Secretary McGhee to James Bruce,
                        Director of the Mutual Defense Assistance Program, not printed. The paper on
                        Iran was part of <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>’s response to a
                        memorandum, February 4, by Mr. Bruce to Assistant Secretaries Butterworth
                            (<gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>), McGhee (<gloss target="#t_NEA1"
                            >NEA</gloss>), Miller (<gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>), and Perkins
                            (<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>) on the military assistance program
                        for fiscal year 1951. Regarding needs for military assistance of countries
                        in the Near East, South Asia, and Africa in fiscal year 1951, <gloss
                            target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> submitted statements on Greece, Turkey,
                        Iran, Saudi Arabia, Burma, India, Pakistan, Afghanistan, and Liberia with
                        the qualification in Mr. McGhee’s covering memorandum of February 10, that
                        “the information contained in these statements should be considered as raw
                        material for use in justifying legislative programs since the limited time
                        allotted for their preparation has not permitted a careful examination of
                        all the factors involved nor consultation with the diplomatic missions
                        concerned.” Copies of Mr. Bruce’s memorandum (undated), Mr. McGhee’s reply
                        of February 10, and ‘the statement on Iran were transmitted by Instruction
                        17, February 14, to Tehran, with a request for any comment deemed
                        appropriate (788.5 <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>/2–1450). No comment
                        by the Embassy in Iran on this paper has been found in Department of State
                        files.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content"
                            calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1950-02-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                            notBefore="1950-02-04T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Political and Economic Factors Involved in Military
                        Assistance to Iran in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                    </hi> 1951</p>
                <p>The primary objective of our policy toward Iran is to prevent its domination by
                    Soviet Russia, and to strengthen its orientation toward the West. Our policy
                    lays first emphasis on economic and social development to strengthen the
                    country’s resistance to communism. Principal reliance in this connection is
                    placed upon the Iranian seven-year program which is expected to draw largely
                    upon the country’s own financial resources for its implementation. American aid
                    to Iran in the economic and social fields, as now planned, will be confined to
                    technical assistance under the Point Four, Smith-Mundt and Fulbright program. A
                    second facet to the implementation of our policy is to develop Iranian
                    self-confidence and power to resist by providing military assistance under
                        <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>. The third element is diplomatic
                    support, when and where required, principally through the mechanism of the
                    United Nations.</p>
                <p>Politically, Iran is extremely important to the security of the United States in
                    the cold war. Its fall under Soviet control would have a tremendous moral effect
                    on other friendly nations, and would render it <pb facs="0488" n="466"
                        xml:id="pg_466"/> quite probable that most of the other Near Eastern
                    countries would soon fall under communist domination. The consequences of such
                    an eventuality are obvious to anyone familiar with the strategic and political
                    importance of the area and of its resources.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">problems of internal security</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The object of Soviet policy in Iran is to replace the government with a Soviet
                    puppet regime so that complete domination—political, economic and military—could
                    prevail, and to incorporate large segments of Iranian territory forcibly into
                    the Soviet Union. Access to the Persian Gulf is a historic Russian objective,
                    and in accomplishing this the USSR would acquire advance bases for subversive
                    activities or actual attack against the vast contiguous area; obtain a base
                    hundreds of miles nearer potential US–UK lines of defense in the Middle East
                    than any held at present; control part and threaten all of the Middle Eastern
                    oil reservoir; control continental air routes across Iran and threaten those
                    traversing adjacent areas; be in a position to menace shipping in the Persian
                    Gulf; and undermine the will of all Middle Eastern countries to resist Soviet
                    aggression. The stakes, therefore, are extremely high and it is obviously to the
                    interest of the United States that any such development be precluded.</p>
                <p>Russian attempts to subvert Iran have taken almost every conceivable form of
                    pressure, threats and subversive operations. It is known that numbers of Soviet
                    agents are operating within Iran. The Tudeh (communist) Party, now outlawed by
                    the Iranian Government, continues to exist as an underground movement, and with
                    Soviet support represents a substantial threat to the internal security of the
                    country. Iranian communists and Russian agents play heavily upon the economic
                    and social inequities within the country and the inability of the present regime
                    to improve the condition of the population. The greatest threat to Iranian
                    independence, assuming that Russian forces will not overtly attack the country
                    under present world conditions, lies in the economic problems confronting the
                    mass of the people. The Shah and the Iranian Government recognize this to be the
                    case, and realize that the best defense against communism lies in the
                    implementation of an effective program to improve the welfare of the people. The
                    energetic seven-year program has therefore been inaugurated with the advice and
                    assistance of an organization of experts from American technical firms, under
                    which Iranian resources, mainly those derived from operations of the
                    Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, will be employed in projects of considerable
                    magnitude.</p>
                <p>One of the principal difficulties in implementing the economic and social program
                    will be in the selection by the Shah and the Iranian Government of able leaders
                    to see it through. The proponents of the plan and most Iranians are
                    enthusiastically behind it, but it remains <pb facs="0489" n="467"
                        xml:id="pg_467"/> to be seen whether they will in fact be able to carry it
                    through within the period contemplated. We shall, of course, continue to
                    encourage the Iranians to devote their attentions to progress in this field.</p>
                <p>The maintenance of internal order and the Shah’s strategic plan of having an army
                    capable of fighting a delaying action of sufficient duration to permit the Shah
                    and some of his forces to retire to the south where they could carry out
                    guerrilla warfare, requires an Iranian army presently numbering approximately
                    130,000 men, but with an authorized strength of 150,000 men. While the
                    maintenance of this force imposes a considerable burden upon the resources of
                    the country, it is considered necessary for direct security purposes and to give
                    to the people a degree of confidence so that they will not give way to Soviet
                    pressures short of all-out attack.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">problems of external security</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In 1945, while the area was occupied by Soviet troops, the Soviet Union sponsored
                    the creation of a puppet regime in Azerbaijan which it supported by force
                    against the attempts of the Iranian Government to restore order. The Soviets
                    also refused to fulfill their treaty obligation to withdraw their troops on a
                    specific date and remained in occupation of Azerbaijan. It was largely because
                    of the strong position taken by the United Nations and particularly by the
                    United States that these forces were withdrawn, and it is probably only because
                    of Russian fear that such precipitous action might result in war that the USSR
                    refrains from armed invasion at the present time. The Iranian forces now under
                    arms or any potential force which might be mobilized could do no more than
                    briefly delay overt Russian aggression.</p>
                <p>The Iranian Government has steadfastly resisted Russian demands. It has brought
                    before the United Nations problems relating to its security and has received the
                    overwhelming support of non-Soviet countries.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">iranian assistance to other countries in the area friendly
                        to the united states</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Iranian Government has repeatedly requested that Iran be included in the
                    North Atlantic Pact or in some other regional arrangement underwritten by the
                    United States, under which Iran would participate with other countries in
                    maintaining security. As in the case of similar requests by Greece and Turkey,
                    however, we have taken the position that the United States Government is not
                    prepared at this time to extend its commitments in further regional pacts of
                    this type. It is believed that in time of crisis Iran would render to the United
                    States and other friendly countries whatever support it could provide.</p>
                <pb facs="0490" n="468" xml:id="pg_468"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">action recommended</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The attainment of American objectives in Iran will require the continued
                    extension of effective United States military assistance to that country; the
                    extension of technical and advisory assistance under Point Four, Smith-Mundt and
                    Fulbright programs; support of Iranian requests for economically justified
                    International Bank loans for development purposes; and continued diplomatic
                    support before the United Nations and otherwise as may be needed.</p>
                <p>The Iranian Government and people consider themselves closely aligned with the
                    West and have shown no tendency to weaken in their resistance to communist
                    pressures. It is considered certain that any military aid rendered by the United
                    States to Iran would, so long as Iran remains independent, be used to achieve
                    American objectives in that country.</p>
                <p>Military aid authorized for Iran in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1950
                    represents only a small amount, sufficient only to provide items of the highest
                    priority required by the Iranian forces. The program contemplated for <gloss
                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1951 likewise will be confined to relatively few
                    essential items. To the extent that these programs materialize they will avoid a
                    drain upon Iranian foreign exchange resources which otherwise would be required
                    in obtaining necessary items of military equipment. The program as contemplated
                    would not be prejudicial to economic and social progress. The supply of military
                    equipment to Iran will have an extremely beneficial psychological effect as it
                    will provide evidence of the determined attitude of the United States in giving
                    material as well as moral support.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">general nature and extent of proposed military
                        assistance</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The small military program proposed for Iran will have greater psychological
                    results than the accomplishment of appreciable improvement in the military
                    potential of the country. While, therefore, it is largely justified on the basis
                    of its morale effect, the equipment is needed to enable the army effectively to
                    prepare against possible internal disorders precipitated by Russia. The program
                    would improve the confidence of the Shah and of the Iranian leaders in the
                    ability of the army to resist, at least temporarily, anything short of an
                    all-out attack. It is probable that this assistance would have an appreciable
                    effect on the Iranian Army’s resistance even in the event of a direct attack,
                    since knowing it has proper equipment and that the United States is interested
                    in its success, it would have a will to resist not in evidence in the past.</p>
                <p>It is considered essential that military aid to Iran be continued in the <gloss
                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1951, as the probable result of failure to do so
                    would be extreme Iranian disappointment and fear that the United States has <pb
                        facs="0491" n="469" xml:id="pg_469"/> little interest in preserving Iranian
                    integrity. Such action, coupled with our refusal to include Iran in any regional
                    security arrangement underwritten by the United States and our refusal, thus
                    far, to consider the extension of financial aid requested by Iran, would have
                    extremely serious consequences.</p>
                <p>While it is difficult to predict the probable duration of the proposed military
                    aid program, it is considered likely that some quantities of aid during the
                    course of the next several years will be recommended, or at least for the period
                    during which general military assistance programs are in effect for Western
                    Europe, Greece and Turkey.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">nature and extent of U.S. involvement if military aid is
                        provided</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The extension of military aid to Iran involves no new policy, but represents
                    inclusion of Iran in a supply program similar to those which have been in
                    operation in Greece and Turkey for some time. It is consistent with the
                    principle of the Truman Doctrine, established in early 1947, which provides that
                    the United States will extend assistance to free peoples resisting aggression
                    wherever that assistance can be effective.</p>
                <p>As has been pointed out, military aid is considered necessary to support the
                    forces deemed by Iran to be essential, and to bolster Iranian morale and
                    determination. The military program proposed should involve no United States
                    commitment in relation to the economic situation in the country, but on the
                    contrary it will make it possible for Iran to devote her own foreign exchange
                    resources to the implementation of the seven-year program. Termination of the
                    Iranian program during a period when other countries are receiving substantial
                    aid would have an extremely serious and possibly disastrous effect upon the
                    attainment of our objectives in that country, as it would imply an American
                    interest in Iran less than in the case of other countries which have manifested
                    their friendship toward the United States.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">estimate of reactions to united states efforts to furnish
                        military aid</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The reaction of the Iranian Government to the announcement of United States
                    intentions of including Iran in the military aid program<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d210fn3">For text of the joint statement issued at Washington on
                        December 30, 1949, following discussions by President Truman and the Shah of
                        Iran, see <ref target="frus1949v06#pg_592">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 592</ref>.</note> has been an important
                    factor in developing Iranian-American cooperation. The program represents the
                    first material assistance which we have given to Iran to supplement the strong
                    moral and <pb facs="0492" n="470" xml:id="pg_470"/> diplomatie support extended
                    for some time. The reaction of other friendly countries in the area has been and
                    continues to be favorable. On the other hand, this new demonstration of American
                    interest in Iran will serve further to dissuade Russia from infringing upon
                    Iranian territorial integrity by providing more concrete evidence of the
                    American position vis-à-vis Iran.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
