<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Joseph J. Wolf of the Mutual Defense
                    Assistance Program, Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d241</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">241</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-05-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="recPOhBog0KB3BlCU" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Anti-tank weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="241"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d241">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">788.5 <gloss target="#t_MAP1"
                    >MAP</gloss>/5–950</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Joseph J. Wolf of the
                        Mutual Defense Assistance Program, Department of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-09">May 9,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: List Discussions <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>1950 for Iran<note n="1" xml:id="d241fn1">The
                        terms of reference of these discussions, held at Washington, March 24–May
                        16, by representatives of the Governments of the United States and Iran are
                        given in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, March 24, <ref
                            target="#pg_502">p. 502</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Aram, Chargé d’Affaires, Iranian
                            Embassy</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. C. V. Ferguson, Officer in Charge of Iranian
                            Affairs</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. P. Halla, <gloss target="#t_GTI1">GTI</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. J. J. Wolf</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb facs="0564" n="542" xml:id="pg_542"/>
                <p>Mr. Aram, on May 8th, had telephone [d] Mr. Wolf and said that he would like to
                    speak with him concerning the issue of the tanks before the next session between
                    the two delegations. He indicated at that time that he would prefer to have the
                    U.S. state whether or not it was impossible for the U.S. to give the tanks as it
                    was difficult for the Iranian Generals to be put in the position of having to
                    say that they insisted on them. The appointment was made for 11:00 A. M. May
                    9th, but Mr. Aram called Mr. Ferguson prior thereto, said that the Generals had
                    now received their instructions, and that there was no need for the conversation
                    before the delegations met. At about noon on May 8th, he again called Mr.
                    Ferguson and asked that the meeting he had originally sought be held, and it was
                    set for 4:30 P. M.</p>
                <p>The meeting opened with Mr. Aram stating that he had sought from his Government
                    instructions which would permit him to accept the English phraseology of the
                    Bilateral Agreement,<note n="2" xml:id="d241fn2">Mutual Defense Assistance
                        Agreement between the United States and Iran, effected by exchange of notes
                        at Washington, May 23; see the editorial note, <ref target="#pg_551">p.
                            551</ref>.</note> rather than having the English text follow the
                    Persian. Mr. Ferguson indicated that we would cable our Embassy at Tehran along
                    similar lines.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aram then said that with respect to the tanks he would like to know whether
                    or not the U.S. found it impossible to include them in the list. Mr. Wolf stated
                    that Mr. Ferguson and himself had spent many hours in conference with Defense
                    officials in an attempt to insure that every effort was made by the U.S. to meet
                    the last Iranian list. As a result of these conversations, Mr. Ferguson and Mr.
                    Wolf were confident that the list that would be presented at the next meeting of
                    the delegations would go a good way toward including most of the items sought by
                    the Iranian Government in their last list, although it was not one hundred
                    percent in accord therewith. However, all items of armor are necessarily omitted
                    from the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1950 Program. Mr. Wolf stated that
                    although the word “impossible” could have several meanings, it could truly be
                    said that in order to meet the Iranian desires in any other aspect, to provide a
                    balanced program, to present a program which could stand on its own feet and not
                    jeopardize possible future programs for Iran, and in view of fiscal limitations,
                    it might sincerely be said that the inclusion of armor in this program was an
                    impossibility.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aram asked whether this included all tanks or just the medium tanks, and he
                    was told that it included all tanks and armored vehicles. Mr. Ferguson
                    emphasized the fact that we had to be in the position to report to Congress that
                    we were providing a program which we ourselves believed to be sound, and we were
                    really not able to do that if the tanks were included. Mr. Wolf referred to the
                    fact that <pb facs="0565" n="543" xml:id="pg_543"/> the new program which would
                    be presented was well rounded, well balanced, and contained a good deal of
                    infantry support and antitank weapons of the most efficient and modern type. He
                    indicated that the new list would include some of the 3.5 bazookas which the
                    Shah had expressly requested, and further indicated that we had broken our backs
                    to include some of the very new and extremely powerful recoilless rifles which,
                    subject to high level consideration, he hoped would finally be included.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aram emphasized that the medium tanks were the particular desire of His
                    Majesty, the Shah, and that one of their major purposes was to bolster the
                    morale of the Iranian Army by the visible display of such heavy power. Mr.
                    Ferguson emphasized that we had given every consideration to the psychological
                    problem involved therein, but felt that these tanks were bound to become
                    deadlined, and would not be a positive morale factor in such case. Mr. Wolf
                    referred to General Duff’s statements<note n="3" xml:id="d241fn3">For a
                        statement by Maj. Gen. Robinson Earl Duff, Deputy Assistant Chief of Staff
                        for Operations, Department of the Army, on the question of supplying medium
                        tanks to Iran, see the minutes of the United States-Iranian meeting, April
                        25 in <gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MDAP1"
                            >MDAP</gloss> Files, Lot 52–26, <gloss target="#t_MDAP1"
                        >MDAP</gloss>—Iran.</note> with regard to the enormous expense of upkeep of
                    these tanks, and to the fact that we could not insure that spare parts for these
                    tanks would be available. He said that he was confident that demonstration of
                    the anti-tank power contained in the mobile weapons we had under consideration
                    would have a tremendous morale value amongst the Iranian troops.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aram wondered what these tanks cost. Mr. Wolf replied that if we were to
                    include only 50 of the medium tanks requested, together with necessary
                    maintenance, support and recovery vehicles, we would more than exceed the value
                    of the original list which we had tendered to Iran, and that to provide the
                    tanks would of course mean that all anti-tank weapons would have to be
                    dropped.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aram indicated that he believed that if Iran had the choice, they would
                    probably choose the tanks over the other weapons. It was stated that such an
                    unbalanced program would be very difficult to support here, that the program we
                    did propose would be so well balanced, so much along the lines of General
                    Collins’ conversations when he was in Iran,<note n="4" xml:id="d241fn4">See
                        Annex 5 to the memorandum, April 10, by General Collins to the Secretary of
                        the Army, Gordon Gray, <ref target="#pg_507">p. 507</ref>.</note> so mobile
                    and useful in connection with Iran’s strategic plan of withdrawal to and
                    protection of a national redoubt, that we felt it impossible to prejudice such
                    an excellent program.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aram repeated several times throughout the conversation that of course we
                    would have to convince his Generals of the military aspects of this program. He
                    also asked whether we would provide all of the bazookas and recoilless rifles
                    which Iran had requested. He was <pb facs="0566" n="544" xml:id="pg_544"/>
                    informed that there would be delays on delivery of these items, which were so
                    new and modern that there were none available on hand for immediate delivery. He
                    was also told that for this first fiscal year 50 program, only a beginning was
                    made to meet the net Iranian requirement, but that our people believed that
                    there was sufficient numbers included to permit thorough training in the applied
                    tactical use of this weapon.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aram then asked about the fiscal year 51 program and whether armored vehicles
                    might not be included therein, particularly medium tanks, but not them, at least
                    more light tanks which we appeared to approve. He was told that it was
                    impossible to make a commitment in view of the fact that Congress had not yet
                    approved any figure for 1951 and in view of our increasing world-wide
                    commitments. He then indicated a concern on the part of Iran with respect to our
                    increasing commitments elsewhere, referring to the press report that it has been
                    indicated in London that we would be sending arms to Indochina.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d241fn5">For documentation on the extension of U.S. military
                        assistance to French Union Forces, see <ref target="frus1950v06#pg_690">vol.
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 690</ref> ff.</note> Mr. Wolf
                    noted that the situation in Indochina was one of active warfare which
                    fortunately was not the case in Iran. Mr. Aram repeated his concern at the share
                    the other nations were getting and was reminded that a quick reading of the MDAA
                    indicated that Iran was one of the most preferred nations of the whole world,
                    inasmuch as all of the nations were seeking grant aid from us and very few were
                    receiving it. He asked whether Pakistan had, as reported in the press, requested
                    us to sell arms,<note n="6" xml:id="d241fn6">For documentation on Pakistan’s
                        interest in obtaining military equipment from the United States, see the
                        policy statement, April 3, with respect to Pakistan, <ref target="#pg_1490"
                            >p. 1490</ref>; telegram 629, May 5, from New Delhi; telegram 460, May
                        9, to New Delhi; and the memorandum of conversation, June 15, by Secretary
                        Acheson, <ref target="#pg_1408">pp. 1408</ref>, <ref target="#pg_1410"
                            >1410</ref>, and <ref target="#pg_1412">1412</ref>.</note> and was
                    informed that we were not sure, but that almost every nation in the world had
                    presented such a request to us.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aram then indicated that he would cable this general information to Mr. Ala
                    in Paris so that Mr. Ala would be in a position to discuss it with the Shah on
                    his arrival in Iran. A meeting was arranged for May 11th at 3:00 P.M. of the
                    Iranian-United States delegations,<note n="7" xml:id="d241fn7">The editors have
                        not found a record of this meeting in Department of State Files.</note> and
                    a further meeting with Mr. Aram at 10:00 A. M. on May 10th, concerning the
                        Bilateral.<note n="8" xml:id="d241fn8">For documentation on the meeting of
                        May 10, see the memorandum of conversation, May 12, by Mr. Wolf in
                        Department of State file 788.5–<gloss target="#t_MAP1"
                        >MAP</gloss>/5–1250.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It was apparent that Mr. Aram was seriously concerned at the absence of armor in
                    the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1950 Program; but his reaction was not,
                        <pb facs="0567" n="545" xml:id="pg_545"/> at that time, indicative of the
                    presence of a major obstacle to a successful conclusion of the discussions on
                    the proposed basis.<note n="9" xml:id="d241fn9">At the United States-Iranian
                        meeting of May 16 on the Mutual Defense Assistance Program for Iran for
                        fiscal year 1950, Mr. Aram expressed “the formal gratitude of the Government
                        of Iran at the equipment list proposed by the United States at the meeting
                        of May 11, 1950, and stated that, under instructions from the Iranian
                        General Staff, General Mazhari would be able to advise the United States
                        that the list was acceptable to the Iranian General Staff. General Mazhari
                        then read a short prepared statement, repeating the position stated by Mr.
                        Aram and setting forth certain general concepts of the Government of Iran
                        with respect to the Program.” (Minutes of the United States-Iranian
                        Negotiations, May 16, 1950; <gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> Files, Lot 52–26, <gloss
                            target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>—Iran). A copy of the agreed equipment
                        list is attached to the memorandum of May 18 by Mr. Only to Major General
                        Lemnitzer, neither printed (788.5 <gloss target="#t_MAP1"
                        >MAP</gloss>/5–1850).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
