<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-11-30T07:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-11-30T07:30:00-05:00" n="289" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d289">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">611.88/11–3050: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Richards</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                    the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-11-30T16:00:00+03:30">November 30, 1950—4 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1220. Please pass Ambassador Grady.<note n="1" xml:id="d289fn1">Ambassador Grady had left Iran on November 27 for consultations
                                    in Washington.</note>
                                <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 218, November 29.<note n="2" xml:id="d289fn2">Not printed; it reported that the Shah
                                    had given to a Renter’s correspondent; an interview that was
                                    critical of United States policy, and that further details would
                                    be telegraphed. (611.88/11–2950) The interview was given to
                                    Leopold Herman at the Green Palace in Tehran on November 27. He
                                    gave a copy of the interview to Richards who subsequently
                                    transmitted it to the Department of State in despatch 398,
                                    December 1, not printed (788.11/12–150).</note> Following are
                                main points given to Reuter’s correspondent by Shah for publication: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Shah said, “Persian people and I myself are fully aware of
                                        the importance of American friendship to Persia but I would
                                        like the Americans to realize as well how much Persia’s
                                        friendship, Persia’s integrity and Persia’s independence
                                        mean to them. So far American aid has in no way justified
                                        early expectations despite wide publicity regarding the
                                        extent of the aid which was to be given. This may change in
                                        the future. As matter now stands we have spent $3,500,000
                                        during the past 2 and ½ years on the salaries of American
                                        advisers <pb facs="0641" n="619" xml:id="pg_619"/> working
                                        here. Also we have paid our full share to the International
                                        Bank which amounts $25,000,000. What have we received so
                                        far? <list>
                                            <label>
                                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>One consignment of arms for which we have paid and
                                                another consignment free of charge. Most of these
                                                arms out of date and quite inadequate for defense
                                                against a well-equipped force.</item>
                                            <label>
                                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>$500,000 under President Truman’s Point IV
                                                program.</item>
                                            <label>
                                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>A $25,000,000 loan which has been offered to us
                                                after considerable delay by the Export-Import Bank
                                                under terms of 3½ percent.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>No occasion has been missed by certain sections of the US
                                        press to accuse our country of corruption. What is the
                                        corruption in Persia in comparison with corruption
                                        elsewhere, particularly in those countries which have
                                        already received substantial free American aid?”</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Speaking of Persia’s position in the world, Shah said
                                        country did not expect “carping criticism and idle gossip of
                                        dictatorship in Persia. We have no need of dictatorship. My
                                        people need the guidance of a strong Monarchy and
                                        continuance of the work of my father by other
                                        methods.”</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Embassy has learned in confidence Shah’s original statements were
                                much more anti-American but were subsequently approved in milder
                                expurgated form for publication. He reportedly concentrated, in his
                                off-the-record remarks, almost entirely upon US failure to give
                                promised aid to Iran and contrasted most unfavorably treatment
                                received by Iran when compared with aid given others, particularly
                                Greece and Turkey. He also said, off-the-record, that he could not
                                understand why Americans accused him of flirting with Soviets when
                                the northern provinces were in a dire condition while only aid US
                                had offered was loan at high interest and under onerous
                                conditions.</p>
                            <p>He reportedly inquired of Renter’s correspondent at one time, “do you
                                think that our dealings with Soviets are cause of Ambassador Grady’s
                                return to US?”</p>
                            <p>Interview has been widely distorted in local press and over Tehran
                                radio. Universal feeling in Tehran is that Shah has given vent to
                                strong anti-American feelings [and Renter’s?] correspondent got
                                impression that Shah thought interview would assist Ambassador
                                Grady’s present mission. Local result of incident will be to cause
                                further deterioration in already greatly weakened US position here.
                                Press and radio versions Shah’s interview will undoubtedly be
                                adopted by Government officials and public as guide to relations
                                with us. For example, last evening ⅔ members Iran-American relations
                                society failed appear at meeting reportedly because of
                                    interview.<note n="3" xml:id="d289fn3">
                                    <p>On December 2 Richards reported that Razmara “deplored Shah’s
                                        action” and pointed out that many times the “Shah is
                                        emotionally hasty”. Razmara asked Richards to tell
                                        Ambassador Grady that the interview reflected no change in
                                        Iranian policy. Richards commented:</p>
                                    <p>“Obviously, regardless of what <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> says, Shah’s action has done
                                        considerable damage our position here. It has reinforced
                                        prevalent belief US is not carrying out promises of aid to
                                        Iran and in addition has created unfortunate impression US
                                        military aid consists of junk.” (Telegram 1235,
                                        611.88/12–250) On December 4 Richards reported that Razmara
                                        was still concerned about the incident and that the Prime
                                        Minister had talked to the Shah to indicate the unfortunate
                                        outcome of the interview. On the same day in a telegram
                                        approved by Ambassador Grady, Richards was sent the
                                        following:</p>
                                    <p>“<gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> only. As we see it from
                                        here Shah’s remarks primarily motivated by his desire to
                                        increase his personal popularity now that anti-Americanism
                                        is vogue in Tehran and are accurate reflection basic
                                        weakness of character which has been apparent for some time.
                                        Dept does not contemplate raising matter with him at least
                                        until <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> Grady’s return
                                        when desirability of conveying Dept’s views to him can be
                                        considered in light of situation prevailing at the time.”
                                        (Telegrams 1250 from and 946 to Tehran, neither printed;
                                        611.88/11–3050)</p>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Richards</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>