<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d338</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">338</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-01-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-01-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recGromwzrmMueyr5" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-embargoes">Arms
                        embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec43c89ba39282f56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="vietnam-conflict" subject="peace-talks">Peace talks</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-01-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-01-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="338"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d338">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">486.418/1–3150</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d338fn1">Drafted by Mr. Rockwell.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-01-31">January 31,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: British Arms Shipments to the Arab States and Israel’s
                    Defense Needs.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>S—The Secretary</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Honorable Eliahu Elath, Ambassador of Israel</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>—Mr. Hare</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_ANE1">ANE</gloss>—Mr. Rockwell</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>I received Ambassador Elath at his request. He stated that he had been instructed
                    by his Government to take up with me the matter of British arms shipments to the
                    Arab states.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that he had long been a student of the Arabs and felt that he
                    knew them very well. He believed that the defeat of the combined Arab states by
                    the tiny new state of Israel was an event which the Arab leaders would never
                    forget and which they would do everything possible to avenge themselves for.
                    Almost every day there were statements by responsible Arab personalities
                    advocating the resumption of hostilities. People in Israel had made the same
                    “stupid” kind of remarks, but the responsible leaders of the Israeli Government
                    had never done so. The Israeli Government sincerely desired peace, and certainly
                    wished to avoid the necessity of making large expenditures for military
                    equipment. However, the shipment by the United Kingdom of arms to the Arab
                    states when conditions in the Near East were still so delicate could have no
                    effect but to encourage the Arab statesmen in their plans to recommence
                    hostilities. The Ambassador added that the British shipment of arms, and my
                    letter to Representative Javits<note n="2" xml:id="d338fn2">Dated January 12,
                            <ref target="#pg_684">p. 684</ref>.</note> on this subject, would also
                    give people in the Arab states the impression that the United Kingdom and the
                    United States approved the resumption of hostilities.</p>
                <p>Never since the establishment of the State of Israel had the leaders of his
                    country been so apprehensive for the security of the nation, the Ambassador
                    continued. Information which the Israeli government had obtained showed that the
                    Arab states now had ten times as much military equipment as they had had on May
                    14, 1948. Egypt, for example, had received 200 tanks from England, and 100 more
                    were on order. Moreover, Egypt had acquired large naval vessels in the United
                    Kingdom. In defensive military equipment Israel was now weaker than the Arab
                    states, although Israel also had received new arms. No sensible person could
                    believe that Egypt or any other of the Arab <pb facs="0735" n="713"
                        xml:id="pg_713"/> states could use this heavy equipment effectively to repel
                    an attack by the Soviet Union. The only purpose to which the equipment could be
                    put would be to attack Israel, and to place such arms in the hands of the
                    irresponsible Arab leaders was only encouraging them to undertake such a
                    venture. Israel was a small country, and especially vulnerable, at least in the
                    coastal area, to tank attack. This latter point made the Israeli Government
                    particularly apprehensive.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador wished to assure me that Israel did not have the slightest doubt
                    that the United Kingdom was supplying arms to the Arabs with the best of
                    intentions. England was not encouraging the Arabs to attack Israel, but
                    unfortunately there was no way of fully controlling arms provided for domestic
                    security purposes. The recent <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> in Syria<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d338fn3">For documentation on this subject, see <ref
                            target="frus1949v06#pg_1630">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 1630</ref> ff.</note> revealed this.
                    The Israeli Government also knew that the United States Government sincerely
                    desired not to see the present tranquility in the Near East disturbed. Israel
                    was grateful, said the Ambassador, for my statement to Mr. Javits that the
                    United States Government, should it learn of serious preparations by any party
                    to resume the conflict, would be quick to use all of its influence in an attempt
                    to prevent this. The trouble was that a lot could be done in a military way
                    before the international community could effectively intervene. The Palestine
                    war had revealed to the Near Eastern nations that the cynical policy of <hi
                        rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> was a very profitable one, and that
                    resolutions of the United Nations could be safely violated. Mr. Elath said that
                    Israel itself was at present violating a resolution of the United Nations
                    concerning Jerusalem, with the intent of reaching a speedy agreement with Jordan
                    and the Vatican concerning the Holy City. The Israeli Government was now very
                    much concerned that the Arabs would try the policy of <hi rend="italic">fait
                        accompli</hi> themselves, and Israel desired to be in a position to defend
                    itself against any surprise attack. Arming of the Arabs was particularly
                    unfortunate at a time when peace talks with Jordan were going well, and there
                    were prospects for similar talks with Egypt.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Elath wished to assure me that the Israeli Government in instructing
                    him to make this approach, was motivated solely by a genuine concern for its
                    security. There was absolutely no other purpose. In this background, the
                    Ambassador continued, he had been instructed to ask me to do what I could to
                    persuade the British not to ship any more arms to the Arab states, and to enable
                    the Israeli Government to purchase in this country the military equipment it
                    needed to defend itself. He did not know exactly what this equipment was, but
                    was aware that his Government had a list of materiel it would <pb facs="0736"
                        n="714" xml:id="pg_714"/> like to acquire. The Ambassador said that Israel
                    could not purchase arms in the United Kingdom and that the United States was the
                    only source open.</p>
                <p>I inquired whether the Ambassador’s second request referred to applications which
                    had already been made. The Ambassador replied that the request referred as well
                    to these applications. He mentioned a request for anti-tank guns, a purely
                    defensive weapon, which he said his people had been unable to obtain because
                    Department representatives had informed them that a policy decision was
                    necessary on military equipment of this nature.</p>
                <p>I then said that this whole subject was a very delicate one which had to be
                    studied in a very calm atmosphere. I added that I regretted that this atmosphere
                    did not seem to be present now, and I referred to the statements which were
                    being made by Israeli officials on the armament situation. We thought it
                    particularly unfortunate, I said, that the Israeli Embassy should have seen fit
                    to circulate in an official press release in this country comments of the
                    Israeli Government criticizing my letter to Representative Javits. I would not
                    do such a thing in Israel, and I preferred not to see it done in this country,
                    although the Israeli Embassy, of course, had a perfect right to circulate the
                    comments if it so desired.</p>
                <p>I then said that I was not aware of the exact status of the applications made by
                    the Israeli Government for export licenses for military equipment, but that I
                    would ask the people in the Department concerned with this to let me know about
                    it. As the Ambassador knew, our arms export policy as regards the Near East was
                    to grant export licenses only for military equipment which we thought necessary
                    for legitimate self-defense needs and for maintaining internal order. In general
                    we thought that it was undesirable to have the standard established that any one
                    country in the Near East would have to receive a piece of military equipment to
                    match every piece of military equipment acquired by any other country. I said
                    that we had no information which led to the conclusion that any party in the
                    Near East was making active preparations to attack any other party. I personally
                    did not believe that the Arab states were planning to begin the hostilities
                    again. I did not think that they would be so foolhardy as deliberately to
                    unleash upon themselves the disaster which such a move would surely bring. It
                    seemed to me that the best insurance against the resumption of warfare would be
                    the conclusion of peace settlements by the Israel and the Arab states, and I was
                    glad to hear from Mr. Elath that progress was being made in this direction.</p>
                <p>With regard to the United Kingdom, I said that I had discussed the shipment of
                    arms to the Near East many times with Mr. Bevin. The <pb facs="0737" n="715"
                        xml:id="pg_715"/> Ambassador was aware of the treaty commitments binding
                    Great Britain to some of the Arab states, and the United States Government had
                    persuaded the British not to furnish arms under these commitments until the
                    Palestine arms embargo was lifted. I completely agreed with the Ambassador that
                    the arms being supplied to the Arab states would not enable them to stand off an
                    attack by the Soviet Union. For that matter, the arms we were furnishing the
                    Western European states would not enable them to do this either. But I thought
                    that I could understand the desire on the part of the Arab states to restore
                    their self-confidence by strengthening their armies, and the necessity from the
                    British point of view of having this self-confidence restored to strategic
                    nations in the Near East. I reiterated that we had no evidence that the Arab
                    states were planning to use these arms for aggressive purposes. In conclusion on
                    this point, I said that the Ambassador must realize that our influence upon what
                    the United Kingdom did or did not do was not unlimited.</p>
                <p>I added that of course I was anxious to do anything I appropriately could to help
                    out the Israeli Government. The two requests made by the Ambassador would be
                    given full consideration, and I would ask the appropriate people in the
                    Department to give careful study to the question of the export licenses for
                    military equipment desired by Israel. I then inquired whether Mr. Hare or Mr.
                    Rockwell had anything to add to what I had said.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rockwell stated that since the Department desired to be as fully informed as
                    possible on the military situation in the Near East, it would be interested to
                    receive any information available to the Israeli Government indicating that the
                    Arab states are making serious preparations to resume the war. Ambassador Elath
                    said he believed such information was on its way from Tel Aviv, and that he
                    would be happy to furnish it to the Department.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then apologized for the Israeli Embassy’s press release on my
                    letter to Representative Javits. He said that although he had not known of this
                    release, he naturally accepted full responsibility for it. However, the Israeli
                    Embassy was still a “young” one and had much to learn.</p>
                <p>I said that it was really not a very important matter and that there was no
                    question of an official protest. However, I was sure Mr. Sharett would be
                    surprised if I were to issue in Israel an official release criticizing an
                    exchange of correspondence between himself and a member of the Israeli
                    Parliament.</p>
                <p>After apologizing again for this incident and thanking me for receiving him, the
                    Israeli Ambassador took his departure.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
