<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. James W. Barco to the Director of the Office of United Nations Political
                    and Security Affairs ( (Bancroft))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d372</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">372</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Reparations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="372"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d372">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">357.<gloss target="#t_AC1"
                    >AC</gloss>/2–2750</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">James W. Barco</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d372fn1">Attached to the U.S. Delegation to the Palestine
                        Conciliation Commission.</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Office of United Nations Political and
                        Security Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bancroft</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">personal and confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-02-27">27 February
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Harding</hi>: I think that by now you must feel that
                    some sort of personal report from Geneva is due. Until the present there has not
                    been a sufficiently clear overall picture to encourage me to furnish you with my
                    impressions. Meanwhile I have tried to keep the telegrams to a minimum and to
                    report therein only such facts as had some significance. I remember quite well
                    that we erred on the other side both in Indonesia and in Lausanne by reporting
                    every small conversation and every event which a few days later had lost the
                    significance they may have once had. On the whole I think that by our stripping
                    the telegrams to their essentials you should have received a fairly accurate
                    impression of the situation here.</p>
                <pb facs="0782" n="760" xml:id="pg_760"/>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> has in general followed carefully the
                    outline of procedure contained in the memorandum which was prepared before we
                    left Washington.<note n="2" xml:id="d372fn2">Presumably the Halderman-Barco
                        memorandum of January 3, <ref target="#pg_661">p. 661</ref>.</note> This has
                    proved to be, I think, a very satisfactory guide. I discussed our views as soon
                    as I arrived with Azcarate, the Turkish adviser and Boisanger and found that in
                    general they appreciated this approach. Certainly in the case of Dr. Azcarate
                    there has been very close understanding and cooperation. Boisanger has been
                    somewhat more anxious to start off with definite proposals by the Commission to
                    the parties, but with the passage of the last several weeks he has come more and
                    more to view things as we do. Our position of course has been very satisfactory
                    to the Israeli representatives, with whom so far we have been in quite close
                    agreement and very cordial relations. Upon his arrival, Rafael, who showed a
                    very reasonable and cooperative attitude within the limits of their policy with
                    respect to the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>, agreed with us that an
                    indirect approach through the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> to direct
                    negotiations might prove most profitable in the end. This is the thing that we
                    have been largely concentrating on in the last few weeks, but at the same time
                    we have had frequent meetings with each of the representatives of the Arab
                    States separately, both <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> and the
                    Commission, and have kept our discussions largely on the question of direct
                    negotiations. Discussion of this question has just about been exhausted, with no
                    break in the Arab line. We took each one separately and avoided meetings with
                    all the Arabs together in order in fact to increase the pressure slightly and to
                    encourage frank discussion. Mr. Palmer was opposed to this procedure because he
                    felt that the Arabs themselves did not like it and that they would hence feel
                    less inclined to speak frankly. I felt on the other hand that the old approach
                    of full Arab representation in all meetings had long since been proved barren of
                    results and hence urged the separate meetings. The results did prove that this
                    was in fact a desirable procedure and the resulting frank and fuller discussions
                    I believe convinced Mr. Palmer.</p>
                <p>At the same time these discussions were being held we have been studying the
                    question of a so-called indirect approach to direct negotiations. The relative
                    success of the Mixed Committee on Blocked Accounts encouraged us to think that
                    the best approach might be through additional mixed committees. We began
                    discussing the question with the representatives of both sides several weeks ago
                    when we were thinking of setting up, after our return from Paris, a series of
                    committees to consider all questions outstanding. This would have been quite
                    satisfactory to the Israelis on the theory that the work of such a series of
                    committees would lead to a general peace conference. They hoped that each
                    committee might in time be regarded as a national committee, <pb facs="0783"
                        n="761" xml:id="pg_761"/> that is, a committee for considering questions
                    between Egypt and Israel, Jordan and Israel, etc. The Arabs on the other hand
                    shied away from this more ambitious project and in the last two weeks we have
                    been concentrating on a joint committee of Israel and Egypt to consider
                    proposals made by Egypt in New York last October. This has several advantages in
                    that it would be highly desirable to start off with Egypt in the hope that a
                    committee of this kind might encourage those Egyptians who are thinking of a
                    full-scale conference with Israel, and it has seemed to us it would be very
                    difficult for Egypt to refuse, inasmuch as the Committee’s terms of reference
                    will be based on Egypt’s own proposals regarding refugees in the Gaza strip. I
                    am enclosing a copy of the recommendations to the Commission by the General
                    Committee, which has had this question under study. The Committee’s draft may
                    prove to be the actual terms of reference adopted. At this moment Eban and
                    Rafael object to setting up a committee whose work will be concerned primarily
                    with the three Egyptian proposals without having a provision for consideration
                    of all other questions outstanding between Israel and Egypt. We hope to persuade
                    them that Paragraph 3(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of the enclosed draft<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d372fn3">Entitled “Report to the Conciliation Commission on the
                        question of the establishment of a Joint Committee on the Egyptian proposals
                        concerning the Gaza refugees and on other related questions”. This report,
                        not printed, was prepared by the General Committee of the Palestine
                        Conciliation Commission and is identified as Com Gen./14. Paragraph 3(<hi
                            rend="italic">b</hi>) reads as follows: “Either the Chairman or any
                        member of the Joint Committee will be entitled to request that any related
                        question whose examination, in his opinion, becomes necessary in the course
                        of the work be placed on the agenda of the Joint Committee.”</note> provides
                    a proper device for enlarging the agenda of the committee, but that to begin
                    with, in order to obtain Egyptian consent, the terms of reference will have to
                    be at least this restricted. Unless we can set up this committee there seems
                    little hope at the moment for setting up anything else. I rather think the
                    Israeli position on all these questions fluctuates with the ups and downs of the
                    negotiations with Jordan. When things do not appear to be going well in Shuneh,
                    Israel is much more anxious for the Commission to find a device which might lead
                    to direct negotiations; when it appears that an agreement with Jordan is more
                    likely, they are not so interested in help from the Commission, on the theory, I
                    suppose, that if an agreement can be announced between Israel and Jordan, that
                    will be encouragement enough to the others to do likewise. However, from the
                    beginning we have emphasized to the Israeli representatives that the Commission
                    can really be of help in bringing about direct negotiations and that our efforts
                    will be concentrated in this direction. Israel will not be able to say that we
                    have not cooperated fully with them and on the whole I think that the Commission
                    is in a very strong position with <pb facs="0784" n="762" xml:id="pg_762"/> its
                    proposal for a joint committee on the Gaza question. If it is refused by the
                    Israelis, they will refuse something that they have in effect asked us to do and
                    which has been worked out in accordance with their own desires. If on the other
                    hand the Egyptians refuse, it will not look well for them, since they will be
                    refusing to cooperate in the Commission’s effort to give effect to their own
                    proposals. I rather think that about the time you have this letter we will be
                    able to report that the committee is to be set up. Some of this perhaps could
                    have been put in telegrams, but again I felt that it would be better to report
                    accomplishments or failures, as the case may be, rather than hypothetical
                    situations.</p>
                <p>The question of compensation has been more or less in abeyance while we have
                    concentrated on the joint committee on Gaza. If and when we are able to set up
                    the Gaza committee, we will then give more attention to a similar procedure on
                    compensation. Boisanger, as you know from the telegrams, was at the beginning
                    anxious for the Commission to make an immediate proposal to both sides for the
                    setting up of a fund for compensation, and to announce at the outset that the
                    Commission regards the question of compensation as separate from reparations or
                    the peace settlement. We discouraged this procedure and persuaded him to leave
                    the question open for the time being. He is, however, anxious to return to the
                    question and the French Foreign Office is definitely behind him in this respect.
                    He has given us a memorandum from Parodi<note n="4" xml:id="d372fn4">Alexandre
                        Parodi, Secretary General of the French Ministry for Foreign Affairs. The
                        copy of the French memorandum was attached to the source text and bore no
                        date; it is not printed.</note> which I will translate and enclose. You will
                    notice that the Foreign Office agrees with Boisanger that the Commission should
                    begin by taking up the question of separation of compensation from reparations
                    and the peace settlement. This would, in my opinion, lead to a fruitless wrangle
                    with Israel which would successfully prevent any more useful work being done on
                    the question of compensation. On the other hand the Foreign Office agrees with
                    us apparently that a committee to appraise the value of lost property and to
                    study methods of payment would be useful.</p>
                <p>There are a good many more things I could tell you, but I really prefer to wait
                    until we can talk together. The Commission’s work up to now has been, I think,
                    entirely satisfactory, given the circumstances of so wide a gap between Israeli
                    and Arab viewpoints. If and when the parties permit a more active role by the
                    Commission, I may have a different opinion, but so far it has been largely a
                    question of using tact, restraint and judgment. These are things which perhaps
                    are easier to achieve in a situation like the present one than in the give <pb
                        facs="0785" n="763" xml:id="pg_763"/> and take of full-scale negotiations.
                    We shall see if there will be a chance to display such sterling qualities in the
                    latter situation.</p>
                <p>I am always anxious to have your views.</p>
                <p>Best Always,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Jim</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
