<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-03-07T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-03-07T16:00:00-05:00" n="391" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d391">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">357.<gloss target="#t_AC1">AC</gloss>/3–750</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative on the Palestine
                                    Conciliation Commission</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Palmer</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                    the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-03-07T22:00:00+01:00">March
                                        7, 1950—10 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>338. <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 337. In dinner
                                conversation with Barco last night Rafael again took occasion to
                                request Commissioners’ utmost patience and restraint. Israel’s
                                position with Jordan was confused and fluid and it would be most
                                unfortunate if Commissioner took step which might cause Jordan’s
                                ultimate withdrawal from negotiations on theory more could be hoped
                                for from Commissioner. Rafael admitted it was possible no accord
                                would be reached with Jordan and that Israel would certainly not
                                enter into empty agreement. He believed two or three weeks might see
                                decision taken one way or other. Meanwhile Egypt was watching
                                progress of negotiations with Jordan closely and the <pb facs="0807" n="785" xml:id="pg_785"/> outcome would be important factor in
                                Egypt’s own decision whether or not to have talks with Israel. Egypt
                                was of course at same time trying in every way to sabotage
                                Israeli-Jordan talks. Rafael admitted success or failure Jordan
                                talks might be equally effective in deciding Egypt to have
                                negotiations with Israel.</p>
                            <p>Asserting that “windfall” of most strictly confidential information
                                had come to hand, Rafael claimed Egypt and Soviet Union had made
                                deal in New York whereby Russia would support Egypt in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in return for certain agreements.
                                Israel now knew for certain Egypt was being called on to make good
                                her commitments. Rafael was not in position to allude to this except
                                in these general terms, but matter was intimately connected with
                                Egypt’s present review of her policy with respect to international
                                situation in general and Palestine in particular. Egypt was
                                considering alternatives of agreement with Israel or resumption of
                                war. In interest of stability of Middle East it was therefore
                                essential that every assistance be given Israel in her attempt reach
                                agreement with Jordan. <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> would not
                                contribute to this effort by seeking piece-meal solutions such as
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> proposal for committee on
                                Gaza. Egypt was not concerned over form which negotiations with
                                Israel might take, but only with principal question of whether to
                                have peace with Israel at all. Under these circumstances pressure on
                                Egypt was needed, primarily from US and secondarily from <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>, by demanding that Egypt enter
                                direct negotiations.</p>
                            <p>Barco recalled to Rafael that <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> had
                                in numerous conversations with Abdel Monem<note n="1" xml:id="d391fn1">Head of the Egyptian Delegation to the
                                    Palestine Conciliation Commission. His name is also
                                    transliterated as “Muniem”.</note> pressed without success for
                                Egypt’s agreement to direct talks and that he did not believe <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> could continue demand direct talks
                                without offering some compromise proposal either as to procedure or
                                substance. Barco said also that whereas US might not be willing
                                exert pressure on Egypt on the sole question of direct negotiations,
                                the American Government, in view of its policy of supporting <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> activities and procedures, might see
                                fit to indicate to both parties its support for a reasonable
                                procedure if such were proposed by <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>. He therefore hoped Israel would regard any <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> suggestions for breaking impasse in
                                this light. The pressure which Israel desired might best be
                                furnished in this way. Rafael agreed reflect on this possibility.
                                Our impression is however that Israel representatives here are dead
                                set against any proposal by <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>
                                which in any sense might improve Arab states negotiating
                                position.</p>
                            <p>Rafael and Eban regard Boisanger as “agitator” and quite pointedly
                                indicate <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>, “in America’s own
                                interest”, must counteract French impatience. Rafael asserted French
                                Government views possibility <pb facs="0808" n="786" xml:id="pg_786"/> Israel-Jordan accord with “panic”. It was principally for this
                                reason that Eban was talking over week end with Parodi in Paris. His
                                first purpose was attempt convince French there was no danger to
                                their position in Middle East in agreement between Israel and
                                Jordan. At same time Eban wished impress Parodi with necessity
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>’s forbearance.</p>
                            <p>Having in mind all of foregoing and fact Arab delegates continue ask
                                for <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> action in each and every
                                conversation, I believe time has come for consideration of new
                                approach. Labbane of Egyptian delegation declared on Friday if
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> remained inactive much
                                longer, Arab delegates would not participate further. Fisher, <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> press officer JELM, reported in
                                meeting with <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> today that Abdullah
                                told him his present policy was “one of despair” which he was
                                pursuing because <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> had “let him
                                down”. Amman telegram 38, 5 March, 3 p. m. indicates probable
                                postponement Israel-Jordan discussions until after Jordan elections.
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> will with difficulty remain
                                inactive for this period of time. Heretofore <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> has been well aware of
                                desirability avoiding any action by <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> which would lend credence to Israeli claim of
                                interference in imminent agreement between Israel and Jordan. We
                                must in our opinion still avoid giving cause for claim by Israel
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> has by its action stiffened
                                Abdullah’s attitude, as long as there is still honest hope for
                                agreement. Such assertions by Israel could be avoided if Jordan saw
                                fit to request direct talks, coupled with request for mediation if
                                necessary, under <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> auspices.
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> itself could not suggest
                                this to Jordan without encountering Israel’s claim of interference.
                                In view of deteriorating situation here and in Palestine, <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> suggests Department give
                                serious consideration to suggesting at Amman that Jordan Government
                                make such an official request to <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>. Abdullah will of course have to be convinced that
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> will in fact follow-up such
                                request with results at least more favorable to him than present
                                stalemate. In order convince Abdullah of this we must be prepared
                                play more active role both within <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> and outside. A proposal by <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>, following request from Jordan, for direct
                                negotiations under <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> coupled with
                                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>’s mediation might be
                                difficult for Israel and Arab States refuse and could provide means
                                breaking present impasse. This might be sufficient give impetus to
                                direct negotiations without necessarily committing <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> to finding solution for every
                                problem. Parties themselves might be relied on after initial break
                                in logjam to keep ball rolling. Department consideration this
                                suggestion and possible alternatives urgently requested. <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> feels present instructions have
                                outlived their usefulness.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Palmer</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>