<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting United States Representative on the Palestine Conciliation
                    Commission ( (Barco) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d499</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">499</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-06-21T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-06-21T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-06-21T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-06-21T07:00:00-05:00" n="499"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d499">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">357.<gloss target="#t_AC1">AC</gloss>/6–2150:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting United States Representative on the Palestine
                        Conciliation Commission</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Barco</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-06-21T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >June 21, 1950—1 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>763. <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 364. Jordan Representative, Abdul
                    Hadi, telephoned this afternoon from Paris Jordan Government’s reply to <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> note 30 May, substance of which, from Arabic,
                    follows (Abdul Hadi agreed forward confirming letter):</p>
                <pb facs="0959" n="937" xml:id="pg_937"/>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>First, Jordan Government notes failure Government Israel implement <gloss
                            target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> resolution December 1948.</p>
                    <p>Second, Jordan Government stresses fact Israeli authorities continue drive
                        numerous Arabs into Jordan territory in order facilitate settlement new
                        Jewish immigrants arriving Israel.</p>
                    <p>For these reasons, Jordan Government considers no useful purpose would be
                        served in beginning negotiations with Israel as long as Israel has not
                        fulfilled conditions required by Arab Governments.<note n="1"
                            xml:id="d499fn1">This note, datelined Amman, June 20, was sent by
                            Foreign Minister Shureiqi to the Jordanian Minister at Geneva. A
                            supplemental note, dated the following day, elaborated on the earlier
                            one, stating that Jordan would not initiate peace talks inasmuch as they
                            would be contrary to the joint policy of its Arab sisters. It also
                            repeated a denunciation of the expulsion of the tribal population. It
                            concluded that when Israel exhibited goodwill, Jordan would be ready to
                            understand its position, on the bases of preserving Arab rights and of
                            respecting the wishes of the Arab states. The texts of the two Jordanian
                            notes are given in telegram 779, identified also as <gloss
                                target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 369, June 24, from Geneva, 357.
                                <gloss target="#t_AC1">AC</gloss>/6–2450.</note>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <p>Immediately after receipt of above, <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> informed
                    by telegraph from Jerusalem that Quimper, <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>
                    secretariat had talks with Jordan Foreign Minister afternoon 20th in which
                    Foreign Minister stated negative reply had been sent to <gloss target="#t_PCC1"
                        >PCC</gloss> 30 May note that morning. Quimper had interview with King also
                    that morning in which King declared Jordan’s reply would be forthcoming and
                    would be negative. Twenty-first Quimper received telephone call from Jordan
                    Foreign Minister requesting Quimper revisit him in Amman on morning 22nd.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Barco</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
