<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-02T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-02T11:00:00-05:00" n="565" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d565">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">684A.85/10–250: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Israel</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Ford</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tel Aviv</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-02T18:00:00+02:00">October 2, 1950—6 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>191. Herlitz, Israel Foreign Office told me October 2 that Eytan
                                conferred with King Abdullah Amman October 1 at King’s invitation on
                                general question relations between Israel and Jordan. Eytan reported
                                King professed still be very keen for peaceful understanding with
                                Israel, but that his Cabinet, and especially Prime Minister and
                                Foreign Minister who “sang Egypt’s tunes” made things difficult for
                                him, that King said was going dismiss his present Cabinet and
                                appoint new one within one or two weeks which would be more amenable
                                King’s wishes, that this connection Samir Rifai being recalled from
                                Lebanon, and that King all ready resume relations with Israel where
                                they had been broken off some months ago and possibly conclude five
                                year nonaggression pact or “something similar”. Eytan reportedly
                                proposed this point that form negotiations heretofore followed
                                between two countries be changed and that instead of hit-or-miss
                                midnight meetings followed “large indigestible dinners” a more
                                businesslike procedure be adopted with regular meetings attended by
                                duly authorized representatives. King allegedly said this made sense
                                and that he had <pb facs="1043" n="1021" xml:id="pg_1021"/> hopes
                                that with new cabinet some such regularity might be instituted.</p>
                            <p>Eytan is reported have been impressed by King’s attitude, but feels
                                that while King ready reach agreement with Israel he must first
                                reach agreement within his own official family. He said that, for
                                example, when he expressed pleasure over resumption Article 8
                                Special Committee meetings, King admitted nothing constructive could
                                come these meetings under present Jordan Cabinet.</p>
                            <p>King reportedly had never seen map showing Yarmuk River “concession”
                                and was extremely shocked to see Jundi’s signature affixed thereto.
                                King is said to have asked Eytan as personal favor to “return”
                                occupied zone, and Eytan says he agreed some such step might be
                                considered within framework general settlement.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Next step possible negotiations
                                between Jordan and Israel would appear to be determination and
                                clarifications of person or persons in Jordan who have necessary
                                power and discretion treat constructively with Israel
                                representatives looking toward settlement. Eytan says his Government
                                ready appoint representatives with full powers, but that he and
                                other high officials Israel Government continue skeptical Jordan’s
                                willingness and ability undertake serious discussions. <hi rend="italic">End comment</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Sent Department 191; repeated information Jerusalem 12. Department
                                pass Amman 13, London 18, Paris 11.<note n="1" xml:id="d565fn1">A
                                    handwritten notation states the message was also sent to Cairo
                                    on October 12.</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ford</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>