<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of Staff, United States Army (
                    (Collins))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d691</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">691</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-03-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recPnftMNhM1QKAYO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Stockpile</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec9wzMIGHUgT4FsE" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="north-atlantic-treaty-organization" subject="north-atlantic-treaty-organization" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092473" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">North Atlantic Pact</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-balance" lcsh-match="no_match">United States Army</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-03-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="691"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d691">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">780.5/4–1750</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of Staff, United
                        States Army</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Collins</hi>)<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d691fn1">This memorandum was Appendix 1 to Annex 4 of a memorandum
                        of April 10, not printed, by General Collins to the Secretary of the Army on
                        the subject “Inspection by the Chief of Staff, U.S. Army, of the Middle East
                        Covering the Period 20 March to 8 April 1950,” a copy of which was
                        transmitted to Mr. McGhee on April 17. The present memorandum of March 26
                        was prepared by the General’s aide, Col. Douglas V. Johnson, in consultation
                        with Ambassador Wadsworth, and was approved by General Collins.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-03-26">March 26,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Turkish War Planning</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Present:</hi>
                </p>
                <table cols="2" rows="5">
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Turks</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Americans</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>President Ismet Inönü</cell>
                        <cell>General J. Lawton Collins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Minister of National Defense Shukru<note n="2" xml:id="d691fn2">Hüsnü
                                Çakir.</note>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Ambassador Wadsworth</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Chief of Staff, General Gurman<note n="3" xml:id="d691fn3">Gen.
                                Abdurrahman N. Gürman.</note>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Maj. Gen. Horace L. McBride</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Deputy Chief of Staff, General Axelun<note n="4" xml:id="d691fn4">Gen.
                                Izzet Aksalur.</note>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Colonel Douglas V. Johnson</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="center">2 Interpreters</p>
                <p>The President and General Collins exchanged greetings.</p>
                <p>General Collins said he had been Deputy Chief of Staff when he had been here
                        last<note n="5" xml:id="d691fn5">See the editorial note, <ref
                            target="frus1949v06#pg_1638">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 1638</ref>.</note> but now that he was
                    Chief of Staff he was even more interested than before in seeing what the
                    American Aid Mission had accomplished.</p>
                <p>The President replied that he had no doubt the General would be satisfied and
                    asked where he had been in Western Europe, especially had he been to France.</p>
                <p>General Collins said that he had been in Rome, Trieste and Athens.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d691fn6">See the memorandum of conversation, April 10, by David A.
                        Robertson, Politico-Military Adviser, Bureau of Near Eastern, South Asian,
                        and African Affairs, <ref target="#pg_362">p. 362</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1264" n="1242" xml:id="pg_1242"/>
                <p>The President asked if they were working hard in Western Union–harder than in
                    Turkey.</p>
                <p>General Collins replied that he did not know—probably not!</p>
                <p>The President asked how the problem of defense of Western Europe would be worked
                    out.</p>
                <p>General Collins replied that it was being most carefully studied under the
                    Atlantic Pact.</p>
                <p>The President said that he was hoping for the best in the future but that he had
                    not yet had the assurance that there was determination in Western Europe to
                    establish a front.</p>
                <p>General Collins stated that he felt confident the North Atlantic Pact
                    Organization would be able to organize and establish a front in Western
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>The President asked how long it would take.</p>
                <p>General Collins said it would be three to four years before the western powers
                    would be sufficiently strong.</p>
                <p>The President asked why it should be so long since those were rich countries and
                    the United States was doing its best to help. If they decided seriously today,
                    it would not take long.</p>
                <p>General Collins replied they could raise the men but they could not create the
                    equipment overnight.</p>
                <p>The President said the front could be established with insufficient equipment and
                    deficiencies eliminated in time.</p>
                <p>General Collins said Yes, but at least two or three years would be required in
                    Western European countries, including Italy.</p>
                <p>The President said first of all they must make up their minds.</p>
                <p>General Collins said we thought they had made up their minds but that the
                    equipment of modern armies cannot be constructed in a year or so.</p>
                <p>The President said that he was glad that the General was optimistic about the
                    completion of the organization in the West but that he was afraid that the
                    progress was sluggish—if the slow progress continued the task would not be
                    finished in time. Turkey is impatient because it is under the guns.</p>
                <p>General Collins said that we were doing our best to help Turkey prepare its Army,
                    Navy and Air Force for war.</p>
                <p>The President said he was grateful for that and asked the Ambassador what good
                    news he brought from the United States.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador outlined the memorandum which he had brought from Mr. Acheson to
                    the Turkish Foreign Minister,<note n="4" xml:id="d691fn10">Enclosure 1 to
                        Instruction No. 19, March 20, to Ambassador Wadsworth, <ref
                            target="#pg_1239">p. 1239</ref>.</note> stressing that it had received
                    careful consideration and approval at highest level; the territorial integrity
                    and the national defense of Turkey was <pb facs="1265" n="1243" xml:id="pg_1243"
                    /> continuously in our minds; it was part of our overall thinking but not
                    confined to thinking alone; that was what General Collins meant when he said we
                    are “doing our best to help”. He could, too, add an important point made in
                    Washington in support of General Collins’ argument that it must take a
                    relatively long time to get Western Europe working together; the foreign
                    ministers take little time to agree on policies, the ministers of national
                    defense agree easily on desired contributions to the common defense, and the
                    Chiefs of Staff are anxious to make it work; but current difficulty comes when
                    the finance ministers oppose measures which will affect their countries internal
                    economies. Mr. Acheson had told him he felt confident that substantial progress
                    on this score would be achieved at the Atlantic Treaty foreign ministers’
                    meeting next month.<note n="5" xml:id="d691fn11">For documentation on the
                        meeting of the North Atlantic Council at London, May 15–18, see <ref
                            target="frus1950v03#pg_1">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp.
                            1</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The President observed that General Collins was very calm. He asked, “How long
                    before the next war”.</p>
                <p>General Collins replied that we do not think war is imminent.</p>
                <p>The President asked, “Why not?”</p>
                <p>General Collins replied that we think Russia has no stockpile of atomic bombs;
                    that she has no navy and only now has begun the creation of a long range air
                    force, and that since Russia is gaining a large number of her objectives without
                    fighting, there is no reason for her to go to war now.</p>
                <p>The President said that he had heard rumors that the Russians would take over
                    Berlin in the near future.</p>
                <p>General Collins said he believed the Russians would cause disturbances in late
                    May, using boys organizations but he did not think they would seek to occupy
                    Berlin.</p>
                <p>The President said that occupation of Berlin would mean a collision.</p>
                <p>General Collins replied, “We will remain in Berlin”.</p>
                <p>The President said you have United States forces in Berlin. If the Russians want
                    to occupy Berlin by force a collision will result.</p>
                <p>General Collins said that we expected that German civilians would be used to
                    cause the disturbances but that we did not believe that Russian troops would
                    seek to enter the Western Sectors.</p>
                <p>The President asked if we were going to raise an army of Germans.</p>
                <p>General Collins replied, “There is no plan now to do so”.</p>
                <p>The President asked if defense was possible without them.</p>
                <p>General Collins replied in the affirmative.</p>
                <p>The President asked if the Ambassador too would comment on this point.</p>
                <pb facs="1266" n="1244" xml:id="pg_1244"/>
                <p>The Ambassador said he had heard nothing to the contrary in Washington;
                    specifically he had heard of no plans to arm or otherwise use Western Germany
                    within the framework of the North Atlantic mutual defense program unless it be
                    in the moral field.</p>
                <p>The President told General Collins that he would find Turkey as strong as it had
                    been on his (General Collins) last visit. Valuable economic and military aid,
                    including the work of General McBride’s group, had been received from the United
                    States and had been utilized to the maximum. The President of the United States
                    had said that aid for Turkey would continue.<note n="6" xml:id="d691fn12"
                        >Possibly a reference to the President’s budget message to the Congress,
                        January 9 (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United
                            States: Harry S. Truman, 1950, p. 44</hi>).</note> That statement gave
                    Turkey a pleasing and reassuring feeling. Turkey was working very hard to
                    overcome its difficulties. The United States and Turkey are at the world’s
                    geographic extremes, but their cooperation had been necessary and been carried
                    out in a fine way; that working together should be established as our national
                    policies. He asked if General Collins had any questions.</p>
                <p>General Collins stated that he was happy to learn that General McBride’s group
                    had been working with the Turkish General Staff on the Turkish War Plans and
                    that he felt it very important that they continue to do so. We wished to
                    continue to furnish military aid and equipment but it was necessary, in order to
                    get Congress to appropriate the money, that Congress be assured of sound plans
                    and that the equipment provided would be used in the implementation of such
                    plans. He cited as an example the questions which he had been asked last week,
                    when he and General Bradley<note n="7" xml:id="d691fn7">Gen. Omar N. Bradley,
                        Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</note> appeared before a Committee of
                    our Senate, by very influential senators of the opposition as to whether the
                    plans for Western Europe were being soundly developed. He pointed out that he
                    must answer similar questions when he appeared before the committee asking new
                    appropriations for aid to Greece, Turkey and Iran. He stated that one of his
                    reasons for visiting those countries was to assure the Committees of Congress
                    that sound plans were being developed and that the costly equipment was being
                    well used. He stated that the members of the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                    must know how much money to allot to the Turkish Army, Navy and Air Force
                    respectively and that it was, therefore, necessary to know something of the
                    Turkish plans.</p>
                <p>The President asked if the Americans were not informed of the Turkish plans and
                    stated that the Turks had been very open with the Americans.</p>
                <pb facs="1267" n="1245" xml:id="pg_1245"/>
                <p>General Collins said that we had no complaints but that until recently General
                    McBride dealt in training matters rather than the matters concerning the
                    location in which the forces would be employed. He pointed out that we were
                    concerned that they had proper plans, not only for the stationing of their
                    forces, but to provide for the complicated logistical requirements which must be
                    thought out ahead of time. General Collins explained by an example which pointed
                    out the vulnerable position of a large part of the petroleum storage in Turkey.
                    Although he realized this storage was a commercial project which could not be
                    removed to a safer place, he felt that an analysis should be made of the
                    situation in order that any new military storage should be placed in some
                    position, such as the vicinity of Iskenderun, where it would be relatively safe
                    and could be re-supplied by sea.</p>
                <p>The President stated that he saw no reason why the American and Turkish officers
                    should not deal with such matters. General McBride had probably already told
                    General Collins that he, The President, was very sensitive on the subject of
                    storage for oil reserves which he felt would be a strategic problem of the
                    utmost importance. He supposed that General McBride would give some advice on
                    the subject in the near future.</p>
                <p>General Collins stated that if the President wished we would be happy to
                    reinforce our group that is working on the Turkish war plans.</p>
                <p>The President said that he would be very grateful, and the Turkish Chief of Staff
                    agreed.</p>
                <p>General Collins said that he was aware that the Turks did not wish their war
                    plans disclosed to anyone who did not have to have the information. He reassured
                    the President that Turkish war plans would not be discussed with the American
                    Congress but would be handled as they are in our own service, that is, they
                    would be known only by people who needed to know them. The Congress needed only
                    to be assured that good plans do exist.</p>
                <p>The President said, “We are working with America and have nothing to conceal from
                    you”. He said that the Turkish planning was progressing slowly but that it was
                    being done with care and attention to detail. He said that discussion of
                    military problems did not mean necessarily that agreements would be reached
                    technically. Discussions would help both and as the work progressed the persons
                    responsible for the defense of Turkey would make decisions in the light of the
                    broad strategic concept adopted. Officers of both nations would explain their
                    ideas and reach agreement. He had no doubt that General Collins would find
                    proper plans would be established so that America could give more aid. He
                    recognized that the current discussions <pb facs="1268" n="1246"
                        xml:id="pg_1246"/> were one-sided; full cooperation would come when both
                    sides could discuss their plans.</p>
                <p>General Collins stated that military men in the US could not discuss military
                    plans without prior political agreements, but he could tell the President that
                    if war started there would be a tremendous strategic air offensive launched
                    against Russia which would be of immense help to Turkey as well as the countries
                    of Western Europe.</p>
                <p>The President said that was a very important point and he requested more detail,
                    particularly as to whether the United States would bombard Russia if Russia
                    attacked Turkey.</p>
                <p>General Collins answered that, if Congress declared war, we would. The question
                    of declaring war was one for Congress to decide but that it was his personal
                    opinion, as an individual, that if Russia attacked Turkey, such an attack would
                    be part of a world war in which Russia would attack on several fronts. He
                    reminded the President that the President of the United States had said that the
                    security of Turkey was vital to the security of the United States.<note n="8"
                        xml:id="d691fn8">Possibly a reference to President Truman’s address of March
                        12, 1947, before Congress, cited in footnote 5, <ref target="#pg_1239">p.
                            1239</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The President asked if General Collins had said that if Russia attacked anywhere
                    it would initiate a third world war and asked if General Collins was sure.</p>
                <p>General Collins replied that it was the case, in his personal opinion—again
                    stressing that this was his personal opinion.</p>
                <p>The President stated that he accepted it as a personal opinion—that it was very
                    important to him to hear General Collins, as Chief of Staff of the United States
                    Army, give his views and that it was very refreshing to hear those views. He
                    stated that when Turkey is engaged in war it will have to face attacks from
                    land, sea and air—that if Russia would be subjected to long range bombardment
                    the weight against the Turkish Armed Forces would be lessened.</p>
                <p>General Collins assured the President that would be true if it came to a third
                    world war.</p>
                <p>The President commented that it was painful to think an attack on Turkey would
                    start a third world war.</p>
                <p>General Collins stated that, as an individual, he believed Russia would first
                    attack to the West.</p>
                <p>The President then recapitulated by saying: “Without any political commitment or
                    agreement our two countries are working very closely together; Turkey has the
                    very valuable statement of the President of the United States; and the personal
                    opinions of American military and political leaders are that Turkey will not be
                    left alone.” He asked if this was the case.</p>
                <pb facs="1269" n="1247" xml:id="pg_1247"/>
                <p>General Collins replied in the affirmative.</p>
                <p>The President then stated that Turkey would await the future calmly and
                    confidently.</p>
                <p>General Collins stated that that was good but that General McBride told him there
                    was much yet to be done in developing sound Turkish war plans. The Minister of
                    Defense and the Turkish Chief of Staff must understand that, if they wished it,
                    he, General Collins, would, be happy to discuss the matter in more detail.</p>
                <p>The President replied that was very good—that the more advice General Collins
                    gave the better he would be pleased.</p>
                <p>General Collins commented that he wanted his point clearly understood. He,
                    General Collins, was not suggesting this, and any further discussion he might
                    have with the Turkish General Staff would have to be on their initiative and not
                    on his.</p>
                <p>The President stated that in his view there was no reason why such discussions
                    should not be held; the Turks would be only too pleased! to know on which points
                    they were deficient.</p>
                <p>The Chief of Staff of the Turkish Army expressed his pleasure.</p>
                <p>General Collins said to the Turkish Chief of Staff, “We will be happy to do this
                        together”.<note n="9" xml:id="d691fn9">
                        <p>General Collins and heads of the American military mission in Turkey met
                            in Ankara on March 27 with Minister of Defense Çakir, with General
                            Gürman, Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, and with other Turkish
                            officials; General Collins also met privately with Minister Çakir at the
                            latter’s request.</p>
                        <p>“Full details of these conferences were furnished to Ambassador Wadsworth
                            who thoroughly approved the major points listed by General McBride and
                            General Collins. Ambassador Wadsworth said that he would follow up with
                            Minister Çakir on the problems involved in possible mining of the
                            Straits.” (Record of conference, Appendix 2 to Annex 4 of the source
                            text, 780.5/4–1750, not printed.)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>The President closed this audience by saying, with obvious sincerity, “General,
                    our discussion has been most useful”.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
