<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Turkey ( (Wadsworth) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d718</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">718</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-07-30T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-07-30T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="rec0QsshUhjiMmm5v" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Security Policy</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007242"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Defense budget</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec_korean_war" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="korean-war" subject="korean-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073119" lcsh-match="exact">Korean War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-30T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-30T16:00:00-05:00" n="718"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d718">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">782.5/7–3150: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wadsworth</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Istanbul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-31T00:00:00+03:00"
                            >July 31, 1950—midnight.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>44. 1. At their requests I called on Foreign Minister July 29 and on Prime
                    Minister July 30. Both conversations surveyed major objectives Turk-US
                    collaboration in military, economic and political fields. On both occasions I
                    was guided by and stressed position given me in Department’s most helpful
                    telegram 41, July 26. On latter occasion I was able emphasize to Prime Minister
                    supplementary instruction given me in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>
                    47, July 28<note n="1" xml:id="d718fn1">Not printed; it suggested that
                        Ambassador George Wadsworth caution Turkish officials against drawing the
                        conclusion that the Turkish offer to assist in Korea might result in
                        Turkey’s inclusion in the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and have a
                        bearing on the extent of U.S. economic aid to Turkey (795.00/7–2550).</note>
                    received morning July 30.</p>
                <pb facs="1308" n="1286" xml:id="pg_1286"/>
                <p>2. In re subject latter instruction (i.e. Department’s concern lest Senator
                    Cain’s statements lead Turkish Government believe its offer assist in Korea
                    might result in Turkey’s inclusion Atlantic Pact and increased economic aid), I
                    can assure Department these statements played no part in formulation Turkish
                    policy which had already before his arrival been well thought out by Foreign
                    Minister in consultation with President and Prime Minister. Cain press
                    conference, held at request official Turkish press bureau just prior to his
                    leaving Ankara,<note n="2" xml:id="d718fn2">In reply to a question asked at a
                        news conference in Ankara on July 25, Senator Cain said “I can say we are
                        going to be much more sympathetic in helping those who helped most in Korea,
                        we want all of our friends tied together as free nations militarily,
                        economically and politically” (telegram 57, July 25, from Ankara,
                        795.00/7–2550).</note> was unfortunate in that it suggested such conclusions
                    to certain editors. In all prior conversations with Turkish officials Cain had
                    been discreet, emphasizing that while he could report major reactions American
                    public he spoke as an individual, as a Senator who represented minority view
                    even in his own party and in no wise as spokesman official US Government
                    policy.</p>
                <p>3. Foreign Minister, after repeating earlier assurances government’s intention
                    implement McBride recommendations for immediate strengthening Turkish defense
                    forces, informed me he proposed stress again in conversation with Schuman<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d718fn3">Robert Schuman, French Minister of Foreign Affairs;
                        see telegram 124, August 22, from Ankara, <ref target="#pg_1296">p.
                            1296</ref>.</note> in Paris and with Bevin<note n="4" xml:id="d718fn4"
                        >Ernest Bevin, British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, met with
                        Turkish Minister of Foreign Affairs Fuat Köprülü at the offices of the
                        British Delegation to the Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe in
                        Strasbourg on August 5 (the London <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, August
                        7).</note> at Strasburg Turkish view that critical world situation impelled
                    reconsideration Turkey’s place in over-all western mutual defense. Basic foreign
                    and security policy considerations, he said, had long pointed to desirability
                    Turkey joining Atlantic Pact, “a view shared alike by former and present Turkish
                    governments.” He hoped this “vital matter” could be considered by American,
                    British and French Foreign Ministers at their September meeting.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d718fn5">For documentation on the Tripartite Meeting of the Foreign
                        Ministers of France, United Kingdom, and the United States, New York,
                        September 1950, see <ref target="frus1950v03#pg_1108">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1108</ref> ff.</note> He himself
                    hoped to head Turk delegation to GAUNT and at time convenient to Mr. Acheson be
                    afforded opportunity elaborate Turkish government views.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d718fn6">Turkish Minister of Foreign Affairs Köprülü did not serve
                        as Chairman of the Delegation of Turkey to the Fifth Regular Session of the
                        U.N. General Assembly. No record of a conversation between him and Secretary
                        of State Dean G. Acheson has been found in Department of State files for
                        1950.</note> He said he would leave Ankara that evening, would make similar
                    communication to British and French Ambassadors in Istanbul and fly Paris next
                    day. Prime Minister would give me <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> confirming
                        <pb facs="1309" n="1287" xml:id="pg_1287"/> that position he had outlined
                    was official position Turkish Government.</p>
                <p>4. Foreign Minister then said fuller Turk-US collaboration in military and
                    economic fields might in present emergency situation require additional US aid
                    to attain objectives to be mutually determined. Generals McBride and Yamut would
                    make recommendations re military. On economic side he handed me <hi
                        rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    <note n="7" xml:id="d718fn7">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aide-memoire</hi>, July 29, from the Turkish Ministry of
                        Foreign Affairs (enclosure 1 to despatch 62, August 5, from Ankara,
                        882.10/8–550, not printed).</note> and asked that I study it carefully with
                    Dorr and inform Prime Minister our views. Dorr and I believe position presented
                    in this <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> is substantially same as that given
                    Department by Turkish Chargé July 21.<note n="8" xml:id="d718fn8">See memorandum
                        of conversation, July 21, by Mr. McGhee, <ref target="#pg_1278">p.
                            1278</ref>.</note> We will comment further after my visit Ankara August
                    3 with Admiral Ballentine.<note n="9" xml:id="d718fn9">Vice Adm. John J.
                        Ballentine, Commander, Sixth Task Fleet, visited Ankara, August 3–4.</note>
                </p>
                <p>5. Prime Minister began by referring to Yalova conference (see <gloss
                        target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 51, July 22). His communiqué had stated
                    that “new measures for re-organization of armed forces had been examined.” Now,
                    he could tell me, orders to implement them immediately had been issued and
                    provision made for closest working relationship between Generals McBride and
                    Yamut. He referred in detail and without notes to McBride’s June 30
                        recommendations;<note n="10" xml:id="d718fn10">Recommendations in a letter,
                        June 30, from Maj. Gen. Horace L. McBride, Chief of the Joint Military
                        Mission for Aid to Turkey, to Gen. Nuri Yamut, Chief of Staff, Turkish
                        General Staff (Ankara Embassy files, lot 58F33, box 3299, 400 <gloss
                            target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> January-June 1950, not printed).</note>
                    then stressed urgency completion military airfields project. They, he said
                    “constitute basic link for close collaboration with American forces.”</p>
                <p>6. Prime Minister continued, “I have given particular instructions that defense
                    planning by our staff and your officers be given top priority; but planning does
                    not depend on one party alone. We naturally want to know what you are planning
                    and are prepared to do in, and for joint defense of, Turkey in event of war.” In
                    reply I reiterated Department’s answer to Turkish request for joint staff talks
                    as given Turkish Government in writing on my return from Washington last
                        March.<note n="11" xml:id="d718fn11">See Enclosure 1 to Instruction No. 19,
                        March 20, <ref target="#pg_1239">p. 1239</ref>.</note> Its essence was that
                    such talks could not precede political commitment. He promised read answer and
                    memo of ensuing conversation between President Inonu and General Collins;<note
                        n="12" xml:id="d718fn12">See memorandum of conversation, March 26, <ref
                            target="#pg_1241">p. 1241</ref>.</note> then said, “this brings us
                    naturally to need for coordination our political views and first and foremost to
                    Turkey’s vital interest in joining Atlantic Pact. Our collaboration should be as
                    close in political as in military and economic fields.”</p>
                <pb facs="1310" n="1288" xml:id="pg_1288"/>
                <p>7. Prime Minister then handed me <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    <note n="13" xml:id="d718fn13">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aide-memoire</hi>, July 30, from the Turkish Ministry of
                        Foreign Affairs (enclosure 2 to despatch 62, August 5, from Ankara,
                        882.10/8–550, not printed).</note> promised by Foreign Minister. It
                    recapitulates major points outlined above; urges that military and economic aid
                    “respond to exigencies of the present hour”; and stresses common interest in
                    “moral reinforcement” of Turkish public opinion as defense against “harmful
                    propaganda” by “bringing to contractual stage” present close, friendly
                    collaboration and “thereby adding a link to the system for the safeguarding of
                    general peace and security.” It concludes with urgent plea that “moment is
                    propitious for admission of Turkey as member of system of defense and security
                    instituted by the Atlantic Pact” and requests that “US Government kindly see to
                    it that the necessary measures be taken to the end, that this question be
                    examined and resolved with the shortest possible delay.”</p>
                <p>8. In reply, after carefully laying before Prime Minister all major points made
                    in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 41, July 26, I promised wire
                    Department detailed report my conversations with him and Foreign Minister.</p>
                <p>9. Our conversation then turned to military and economic aid programs. Turkey
                    would not, he said, reduce its defense budget but he could not see how it could
                    be increased. In particular, if some 20 million Turkish liras were to be needed
                    to augment NCO and technician corps, where could he find them; he would cut
                    economic investment program wherever possible and would not undertake new
                    projects (e.g. Sariyir hydroelectric dam project)<note n="14" xml:id="d718fn14"
                        >The Chief of the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission to Turkey,
                        Russell H. Dorr, and the Turkish Minister of State, Fevzi Lütfi
                        Karaosmanoglue, signed the Sariyar hydroelectric power agreement on
                        September 22, 1950 (despatch 307, December 5, from Ankara, 882.2614/12–550,
                        not printed).</note> unless contributing immediately to over-all defense.
                    Could I see, he asked, possibility that US Government might help if supplied
                    with careful analysis of needs? Generals McBride and Yamut were to prepare such
                    an analysis on military side; he was himself giving close study to economic.</p>
                <p>10. In reply I made following suggestion: In same way that our two generals were
                    elaborating military recommendations for submission to us at end first week in
                    August, so it would seem highly desirable that Dorr and new Turkish Minister of
                    State submit to us at same time economic recommendations including major
                    elements <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> and Turkish Government investment
                    programs for current <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>. He concurred and set
                    August 8 as date with me, two generals, Dorr and Minister of State.<note n="15"
                        xml:id="d718fn15">The meeting set for August 8 was held on August 19.</note>
                </p>
                <p>11. Before ending conversation Prime Minister referred to official reports made
                    him by Provincial Governors that Turkish decision to send troops to Korea had
                    met with wide enthusiastic support, and <pb facs="1311" n="1289"
                        xml:id="pg_1289"/> he belittled any lasting effect of Opposition Party’s
                    criticism “because it was so patently prompted by considerations of domestic
                    policies”. He concluded: “Korean war has opened new era, one in which we must
                    strive harder and work faster towards common objectives. We will not be Utopians
                    but apply ourselves to practical realities.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wadsworth</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
