<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-09T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-09T18:00:00-05:00" n="793" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d793">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">690D.91/5–550: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                        India</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-09T19:00:00-04:00">May 9,
                                        1950—7 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>460. <gloss target="#t_urtel1">Urtel</gloss> 629 May 5. Dept suggests
                                fol be conveyed informally to Menon in ur discretion: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Since it is our understanding both Govts doing best to
                                        carry out minorities agreement, we find it difficult
                                        understand why Liaquat’s visit to US shld heighten
                                        nervousness in Delhi, particularly as <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> knows trip is state visit
                                        identical with Nehru’s and planned many months ago.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>While we not in position discuss with <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> substance of Liaquat’s
                                        statements we do not find it surprising that Liaquat has
                                        mentioned interest in obtaining mil equipment. It will be
                                        recalled that when Nehru was here <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> officials took up with US officials
                                        question of obtaining ammunition; Indian mil mission
                                        endeavored obtain mil equipment last year and Ind <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss> is continuing
                                        efforts.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>There has been no change in situation affecting
                                        procurement of arms in US by <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                                        since last year. Although U.S. cannot commit itself in
                                        advance to any specific transaction, in gen there is no
                                        objection in principle to purchases from commercial sources.
                                        There are still serious obstacles to procurement aid in
                                        obtaining items from Govt stocks. (<hi rend="italic">End
                                            remarks to Menon</hi>.)</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> Dept finds implications third
                                para <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> exceedingly disturbing.
                                This tends substantiate Dept’s fears <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> making mil pressure an instrument of policy in
                                Nehru-Liaquat talks instead of believing <pb facs="1433" n="1411" xml:id="pg_1411"/> Liaquat genuinely anxious for peace
                                regardless of Indian troop movements.</p>
                            <p>Dept concurs Parson’s remarks fourth para. Re sixth para Dept is
                                carefully considering possible effect on <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> of anything we say to Liaquat just as <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> was kept in mind during our
                                conversations when Nehru was in US. Dept does not however consider
                                it any more appropriate to keep <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                                currently informed of talks with Liaquat than it wld have been to
                                inform <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> of talks with Nehru,
                                which as you know was not done.</p>
                            <p>Re last para, Liaquat is quite naturally endeavoring present <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> views in same way Nehru presented
                                    <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> views when he was here and
                                has expressed interest in obtaining mil equipment. Dept does not
                                recall any complaints from <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss>
                                during Nehru visit. However, in addition to approaches to you, Ind
                                    <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss> official here has already
                                made informal representations to Dept re certain remarks made by
                                Begum Liaquat and <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>