<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-11-10T00:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-11-10T00:30:00-05:00" n="832" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d832">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">791.00/11–1050: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-11-10T11:00:00+05:30">November 10, 1950—11 a. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1161. 1. We have reliable and even authoritative information to
                                effect that events in Tibet and unrest in Nepal<note n="1" xml:id="d832fn1">For documentation regarding U.S. relations with
                                    Tibet and Nepal, see <ref target="frus1950v06#pg_256">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 256</ref> ff., and <ref target="frus1950v06#pg_1484">pp. 1484</ref> ff. herein,
                                    respectively.</note> have resulted in increasing dissatisfaction
                                in top Indian government and party circles with India’s present
                                foreign policy. Even those members of Cabinet who [are] Nehru
                                adherents appear to be convinced that time has come for India to
                                recognize that international communism is country’s chief danger and
                                to make corresponding shifts in policy. Patel<note n="2" xml:id="d832fn2">Vallabhbhai Patel, Indian Deputy Prime
                                    Minister.</note> has been stating privately that within next few
                                days he will insist in Cabinet meeting that India not only change
                                policy in direction of closer cooperation with western powers,
                                particularly US, but that it make announcement to that effect.
                                Another Cabinet Minister who is in Nehru’s camp said privately two
                                days ago that Nehru is now only member of Cabinet who insists that
                                there is still hope friendship between Communist China and India and
                                that <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> should make no move which
                                may endanger development that friendship. Patel’s speech reported in
                                this morning’s press (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>
                                1160, November 10)<note n="3" xml:id="d832fn3">Not printed.</note>
                                condemning Communist China for attack on Tibet is believed opening
                                gun in this internal struggle. Patel is reliably reported to have
                                said in private conversation with one of his most trusted
                                lieutenants that he would be willing to defer to Nehru in matters of
                                foreign policy so long as India’s security was not at stake; “he was
                                convinced now <pb facs="1497" n="1475" xml:id="pg_1475"/> however
                                that continuation of Nehru’s policy would endanger security of India
                                and he could no longer remain passive. He felt so strongly in the
                                matter that he would prefer to resign from Cabinet and to break
                                openly with Nehru rather than to allow matters to drift.</p>
                            <p>2. One unfortunate feature of situation is that Patel and others
                                advocating change in India’s policies are arguing that India must
                                strengthen its military establishment if it is effectively to face
                                its Communist neighbor, and that it cannot properly strengthen its
                                military establishment without aid from West, particularly US; that
                                it cannot expect aid from US unless it makes it clear before whole
                                world that it stands with West against aggressiveness of
                                international Communism. In this connection please see <ref target="#pg_7">page 7</ref> enclosure <gloss target="#t_Embdes1">Embdesp</gloss> 200 July 26<note n="4" xml:id="d832fn4">Not
                                    printed.</note> in which outline Patel statement to me re need
                                for US military equipment. It might be embarrassing if change of
                                    <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> policy would be based on
                                expectation of receiving substantial military equipment from US in
                                view of our own shortages in this respect.</p>
                            <p>3. So far as I know, no one this mission has been recently approached
                                even informally by emissaries of those Indian leaders desiring
                                change in foreign policy. Nevertheless whenever occasion arises we
                                have been endeavoring to make it clear that demands on US for
                                military equipment are so much in excess of our ability to supply
                                such equipment that regardless of what India’s foreign policy might
                                be it should not expect any substantial quantities of arms from US
                                in near future.</p>
                            <p>5.<note n="5" xml:id="d832fn5">There is no paragraph numbered
                                    4.</note> We have also from time to time indicated that we have
                                no desire to press India to “align itself” with US or to join any
                                “bloc;” we would however like for India to cooperate with US fully
                                in strengthening existing systems of collective security, for it to
                                join wholeheartedly with other free nations in opposing aggression,
                                and for it to make decisions on international questions on their
                                merits rather than on desire to “keep from taking sides.”</p>
                            <p>6. We are inclined to believe that in spite of declared determination
                                of Patel and others to make foreign policy disagreements major
                                issues, Nehru and Patel will be able to work out some kind of
                                formula which will enable India gradually to shift in direction
                                towards West without too much publicity being given to this change.
                                Nehru is said to be showing somewhat more friendliness to US than
                                heretofore and he appears to be steadily losing enthusiasm for
                                Communist China.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>