<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Union of South Africa ( (Erhardt) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d860</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">860</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recjP7nK0m2r7YYXK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="860"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d860">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">399.50 JO/11–2250</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Union of South Africa</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Erhardt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d860fn1">This despatch was prepared by Henry H. Kelly, Allan
                        H. Smith, and John A. Birch (identified in the document printed
                        here).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">unclassified</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 271</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Pretoria</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-11-22">November 22,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Report of United States Delegation of Observers to
                    Central and Southern Africa Transport Conference, Johannesburg, Union of South
                    Africa, October 25–November 16, 1950</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>A Central and Southern Africa Transport Conference was held at Johannesburg,
                    Union of South Africa, October 25–November 16, 1950, and was attended by
                    Government representatives of the four metropolitan powers with overseas
                    territories in Africa south of the Sahara—Belgium, France, Portugal and the
                    United Kingdom; the Union of South Africa and South West Africa; Administrations
                    of Southern Rhodesia, Northern Rhodesia, Nyasaland, East Africa High Commission
                    (Tanganyika, Uganda, Kenya), Belgian Congo, Mozambique; United Kingdom High
                    Commission for the Protectorates of Basutoland, Bechuanaland and Swaziland; and
                    Madagascar. The United States and the International Bank for Reconstruction and
                    Development were represented by observers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Conference:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Failed to agree on the establishment of a permanent transport
                            organization. However, the Conference, in referring this matter back to
                            the Governments for further consideration, did forward a draft
                            constitution, as well as designate February 28, 1951 as the final date
                            for reaching agreement in principle on the establishment of a permanent
                            organization. Should the Governments so agree, the Conference
                            recommended that a further Conference be held on June 1, 1951 to
                            complete and sign the draft constitution.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Adopted a highway numbering system and a highway classification system
                            with maximum permissible load and traffic limits.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Adopted African standard railway gauge (42 inches) and made important
                            recommendations on railway equipment, service, and interchange of
                            equipment.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Examined in detail all present proposals for railway and port
                            development in Africa north of the Union and south of the Sahara, but
                            avoided decisions on conflicting proposals, and failed to make judgments
                            on economic needs.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Endorsed international through-rates and recommended principles for
                            establishing rates, but failed to examine existing tariffs and existing
                            rate agreements.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1604" n="1582" xml:id="pg_1582"/>
                <p>At the final Plenary Session on the night of November 16, the Conference adopted
                    a statement by the Secretary-General as a public summary of the work performed.
                    (See Document P/5, attached as Annex A<note n="2" xml:id="d860fn2">Not
                        printed.</note>).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Background and Agenda</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Conference was held at the invitation of the Government of the Union of South
                    Africa, pursuant to a decision made at a Conference on Central African
                    Transportation which had been convened at Lisbon in May, 1949 upon the
                    initiative of the Government of Portugal. The Agenda for the Johannesburg
                    meeting was fixed at the Lisbon session. Further preliminary discussion of the
                    problems under consideration occurred at a Special Meeting on Transport Problems
                    in Africa South of the Sahara, convened by the Organization for European
                    Economic Cooperation at Paris in February, 1950. At both these preliminary
                    meetings the United States was represented by observers.</p>
                <p>The Agenda of the Johannesburg Conference was printed in the Department of State
                        <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> of July 4, 1949. In general, the objective
                    of the Conference was to consider the sound and coordinated improvement and
                    expansion of transport facilities as a basic factor in the general economic
                    development of the vast and promising region south of the Sahara. To achieve
                    this objective the Conference was to consider the establishment of a permanent
                    inter-territorial organization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The United States Delegation of Observers was composed of the following persons:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The Honorable John G. Erhardt, Ambassador Extraordinary and
                            Plenipotentiary of the United States of America to the Union of South
                            Africa, Pretoria.</p>
                        <p>Henry H. Kelly, Chief, Inland Transport Policy Staff, Department of
                            State, Washington, D.C.</p>
                        <p>Allan Hugh Smith, Director, Overseas Territories Division, <gloss
                                target="#t_OSR1">OSR</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>,
                            Paris.</p>
                        <p>George Clemens, Alternate Representative for <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                                >ECA</gloss>, Paris.</p>
                        <p>Frank H. Whitehouse, Assistant Chief, Economics Division, Munition Board,
                            Dept. of Defense, Washington, D.C.</p>
                        <p>John A. Birch, Commercial Attaché to the Embassy of the United States of
                            America, Pretoria.</p>
                        <p>Miss Virginia M. Robinson, Attaché (Geographic) to the Embassy of the
                            United States of America, Pretoria.</p>
                        <p>Stephen J. Shuttack, (Secretary) Administrative Officer, American
                            Consulate General, Johannesburg.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The United States representatives took part in the deliberations of all of the
                    eight Committees of the Conference except two (the Steering <pb facs="1605"
                        n="1583" xml:id="pg_1583"/> Committee, composed of the heads of the various
                    participating Delegations, and the Final Act Drafting Committee). They based
                    their work in the Committees upon detailed instructions which had been prepared
                    at Washington during the months preceding the Conference, by the Department of
                    State in consultation with the Economic Cooperation Administration, the
                    Department of Commerce, the Department of Defense and other governmental
                    agencies.</p>
                <p>[Here follow five pages in the source text headed “Organization of the
                    Conference” and “Work of the Committees”. The full text of those sections
                    together with some of the material already printed here were included in the
                    version of the Report of the United States Delegation printed in the Department
                    of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, January 15, 1951, pages 110–112. The
                    remainder of the despatch not printed here, comprising approximately three pages
                    in the source text, was a comparison of Conference decisions with the
                    instructions to the United States Delegation. Also omitted here are the eight
                    annexes reporting in greater detail on the work of the various Conference
                    committees.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Action Requested</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Distribution of this report and its enclosures to all interested
                            Government agencies, including The Office of the Special Representative,
                            Paris, and to U.S. Diplomatic and <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>
                            Missions in the countries and territories concerned with the
                            Conference.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Publication of appropriate sections of this report in the Department
                            of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Erhardt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
