<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>140. Memorandum From the President to the Secretary of Defense ( to the
                    Secretary of Defense (Wilson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d140</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">140</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-07-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recCP2IC3LozXMzXn" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="rec7wEECiiCfq0TDz" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123713"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Smuggling</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-07-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="140"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d140">
                <head>140. Memorandum From the <gloss type="from">President</gloss> to the Secretary
                    of Defense (<persName corresp="#p_WCE1" type="to">Wilson</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d140fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> Library, Whitman File, DDE Diaries.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-07-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 25, 1956</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>While I was in Panama, the President of that country told me that in certain
                    instances the arrangements between the Canal authorities and his country were
                    not, in his opinion, working fairly, or were tending in such a way that he
                    foresaw future trouble.</p>
                <p>I recall instances that he mentioned specifically. The first had to do with the
                    tax on liquor. It being manifestly impossible to establish custom guards or any
                    kind of surveillance on the numerous roads leading from the Zone into Panamanian
                    territory, it is clear that if an article can be purchased much more cheaply in
                    the Zone than in Panama, smuggling will occur. He said that this was the case in
                    the matter of liquor. As I understand it, Zone personnel, whether in the civil
                    or military service, are able to purchase liquor at such a low rate of taxation
                    that the total price in the Zone is little more than one-third what it is in
                    Panama. He pointed out that the liquor tax <pb facs="0315" n="281"
                        xml:id="pg_281"/> was an item on which they had to depend for considerable
                    revenue and that the existing situation was working great hardship on them.</p>
                <p>Another point of complaint was what he termed the “slowness” in securing action
                    on any Panamanian complaint or protest. He said that while the Ambassador was
                    always readily available for hearing a complaint and forwarding it promptly to
                    Washington, when a matter got into the hands of the Defense Department and the
                    Canal authorities, seemingly endless delays ensued. With respect to this one, I
                    told him that I would ask you to keep as close touch with such matters as
                    possible so that you could personally determine that no unwarranted delays
                    occurred.</p>
                <p>He then referred to a difficulty that he foresaw as arising out of the recently
                    concluded treaty. One article of that treaty provides for equal pay for equal
                    work. But the President said that a system of work classification was being
                    developed which the Panamanians were fearful was designed to place all the
                    Panamanians in the lowest of pay categories. He asked assurance that entry into
                    any grade would be strictly on merit, conducted by fair examination. To this I
                    replied that the United States was in the habit of maintaining the spirit as
                    well as the letter of its treaties.</p>
                <p>I bring these matters to your attention because, first of all, I know that you
                    would want to know of them. My more important reason is, however, that we must
                    be exceedingly careful that the future years do not bring about for us, in
                    Panama, the situation that Britain has to face in the Suez.</p>
                <p>Local politics can feed on resentments brought about by real or imagined
                    injustices to the native population. I think it behooves us to be <hi
                        rend="italic">scrupulously fair and considerate of Panamanian problems, and
                        more than ready to meet them halfway</hi>, in any matter that seems to
                    require adjustment between us, but <hi rend="italic">without</hi> incurring the
                    risk of divided control or beclouding our clear title to ownership.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">D.D.E.</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d140fn2">Printed from a copy which bears these typed
                            initials.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
