<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>226. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, September
                    13, 1956</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d226</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">226</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-09-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recR0zhXxdC8M9meR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic recovery</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recDNr3fFoY74D9ro" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recNK3sc8DGxVC02u" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Public sector</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-09-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="226"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                <head>226. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, September
                    13, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d226fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Central Files, 835.10/9–1356. Limited Official Use. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMM1">Bernbaum</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1956-09-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 13, 1956</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>United States-Argentine Loan Negotiations</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Señor Dr. <persName corresp="#p_VAA1">Don Adolfo A. Vicchi</persName>,
                        Ambassador of Argentina</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Maurice M. Bernbaum</persName>, Director for
                        South American Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VAA1">Vicchi</persName> stated that he wished to
                    consult with the Secretary regarding some of the problems which had arisen in
                    connection with the loan negotiations of the Argentine Financial Mission with
                    the Export-Import Bank. He wanted first to express to the Secretary his
                    appreciation and that of the Financial Mission for the invaluable assistance and
                    understanding displayed by the Department of State in the discussions. He also
                    wanted to reaffirm the desire of his Government for the closest possible
                    relations with the U.S. and the belief that this attitude was reciprocated
                    here.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VAA1">Vicchi</persName> stated that his
                    Government had instructed him to express to the Secretary its disappointment
                    over what was considered to be the limited results achieved by the Argentine
                    Financial Mission. The $100 million loan decided upon by the Export-Import Bank
                    fell far short of the minimum requirements set forth in the negotiations which
                    were looked upon by the Argentine Government as essential to meet the first and
                    urgent stage of its <pb facs="0481" n="447" xml:id="pg_447"/> program of
                    economic recovery. He stated that the expectations of his Government had been
                    much higher owing to: (1) The belief that the financial credit and ability of
                    the Argentine Government to repay a much higher volume of loans had been
                    demonstrated during the negotiations; (2) repeated indications of the desire of
                    the U.S. Government to enter into close political and economic relations with
                    the Argentine Government; and (3) a comparison with the financial assistance
                    rendered other countries (he was thinking of Brazil).</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then stated that despite the disappointment in the outcome of the
                    negotiations, the next step was to make the best of the existing situation. He
                    felt in this regard that the division of the $100 million into $85 million for
                    transportation and $15 million for private enterprise represented an undue
                    restriction on the amount to be allocated to the most urgent field of
                    transportation. He, therefore, requested the Secretary’s assistance in having
                    the whole amount authorized for transportation. The Ambassador added that it
                    would be even better if it were found possible to raise the allocation for
                    transportation to $112 million, which represented the latest estimate of his
                    Government regarding absolute minimum requirements in transportation to permit
                    the marketing of the increased crops projected for the economic recovery
                    program. His Government would, in such case, welcome an additional amount for
                    urgent projects in the private field but would be content to postpone such
                    projects if it were decided that additional funds could not be made available at
                    this time. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VAA1">Vicchi</persName> asked also
                    for the Secretary’s assistance in having included in the public announcement of
                    the loan a statement to the effect that the Argentine and U.S. Governments were
                    to continue discussing projects involving Argentina’s economic recovery
                    program.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stated that although familiar with the overall aspects of the
                    problem, he was not acquainted with some of the details raised by the
                    Ambassador. He was aware that the final decision involved an overall loan of
                    $100 million, of which up to $85 million would be allocated to urgent projects
                    in the public field and $15 million for private enterprise in industry and
                    agriculture. His initial impression, upon learning of the $100 million loan, was
                    that it far exceeded his earlier expectations when it appeared that the pattern
                    of Argentine trade would limit its ability to repay dollar loans. He turned to
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Bernbaum</persName> at this point, recalling a
                    meeting held in his office when the matter was discussed and ways and means were
                    being sought to get out of the dilemma thereby presented.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d226fn2">Apparently a reference to the meeting of July 16; see <ref
                            target="#d216">Document 216</ref>.</note> Under the circumstances, and
                    taking into consideration the normal procedures of the Export-Import Bank, he
                    could not help <pb facs="0482" n="448" xml:id="pg_448"/> feeling that the $100
                    million line of credit represented a distinct achievement for the Argentine
                    Financial Mission.</p>
                <p>With regard to the specific requests made by Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_VAA1">Vicchi</persName>, the Secretary expressed the opinion
                    that it would not be feasible to increase the amount of the line of credit. He
                    thought that this amount was the result of lengthy discussions between
                    representatives of the various U.S. agencies concerned and that there was no
                    reason to believe that a change could be effected. Although not aware of the
                    factors leading to the division of the $85 million for transportation and $15
                    million for private enterprise, he expressed his readiness to consult on the
                    matter with a view to seeing what could be done. He turned at this point to Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Bernbaum</persName> to inquire whether he knew
                    of the reason for the division. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMM1"
                        >Bernbaum</persName> stated that the division was due to the belief that
                    some part of a loan of this magnitude should be devoted to private enterprise
                    and not concentrated wholly in the public sector. The Secretary also expressed
                    his readiness to look into the possibility of having included in the public
                    announcement a statement to the effect that the two Governments would continue
                    their joint discussions regarding the Argentine economic program.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VAA1">Vicchi</persName> expressed his
                    appreciation in departing for the Secretary’s interest in the matter.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d226fn3">In a letter to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BWL1"
                            >Beaulac</persName>, September 14, <persName corresp="#p_VVP1"
                            >Vaky</persName> summarized recent developments regarding the question
                        of financial assistance to Argentina. He informed <persName
                            corresp="#p_BWL1">Beaulac</persName> of <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                            >Dulles</persName>’ conversation with <persName corresp="#p_VAA1"
                            >Vicchi</persName> on September 14. He also summarized a conversation,
                        along the same lines, which <persName corresp="#p_VAA1">Vicchi</persName>
                        had with Under Secretary of the Treasury <persName corresp="#p_BWR1"
                            >Burgess</persName> on September 14 as well as several “long chats”
                        between <persName corresp="#p_VAA1">Vicchi</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BV1">Brand</persName>. “By and large,” <persName
                            corresp="#p_VVP1">Vaky</persName> concluded, “the outcome is fairly
                        good. It was certainly much more than we had thought we could get when this
                        whole affair first started. (<persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                        told <persName corresp="#p_VAA1">Vicchi</persName> as much.) Also the facts
                        of the case are that the Bank may well allocate the full $100 million to
                        transportation. Likewise, the Bank is quite prepared to consider additional
                        financing. In a very real sense, therefore, this credit represents only the
                        initiation of a period of cooperation of a nature that has never taken place
                        with Argentina.” (Department of State, <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>
                        Files: Lot 59 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 509, Argentine Financial
                        Mission)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
