<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-08-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-08-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="239" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                        <head>239. Memorandum From the Director of the Office of South American
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMM1" type="from">Bernbaum</persName>) to
                            the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1" type="to">Rubottom</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d239fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 835.311/7–2457. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WLD1">Watrous</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-08-08"><hi rend="italic">August 8,
                                1957</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Possible Financial Aid to Argentina</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>During the time the US Delegation is in Buenos Aires for the Economic
                                Conference<note n="2" xml:id="d239fn2">Reference is to the Economic
                                Conference of the Organization of American States, which met at
                                Buenos Aires, August 15–September 4. For documentation, see <ref target="frus1955-57v06#d135">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>,
                                    Documents 135</ref> ff.</note> it seems inevitable that it will
                            be approached by the Argentines on the subject of further US loans. In
                            point of fact, <persName corresp="#p_CBC1">Coll Benegas</persName> has
                            lately been pressing hard for an invitation to come to Washington to
                            talk about new loans (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>
                                167).<note n="3" xml:id="d239fn3">Dated July 24. (Department of
                                State, Central Files, 835.311/7–2457)</note> He has been basing his
                            argument on the alleged fact that the meatpackers question has been
                            settled in “principle”, and that the Argentines have submitted a
                            “proposal” in the ANSEC case. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BWL1">Beaulac</persName> has quite correctly pointed out that the
                            meatpackers problem cannot be considered settled until the pertinent
                            decree is published,<note n="4" xml:id="d239fn4">In telegram 304 from
                                Buenos Aires, August 16, the Embassy reported that an Argentine
                                governmental decree settling the problem of past accounts of
                                meatpacking firms operating in Argentina was officially published on
                                August 14. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 835.311/8–1657)</note> and
                            that there has been no serious proposal in the ANSEC case since the
                            Government failed to carry out its out-of-court settlement idea.</p>
                        <p>Be that as it may, our position has always been that we could not
                            consider further loans until some progress had been made on these
                            problems, although we have been careful not to define the amount of
                            progress necessary. Now, however, it appears that either some progress
                            will have been made or the Argentines will take the position that it
                            has, and I suggest we should begin to consider what our position should
                            be in several situations. These thoughts may be <pb facs="0509" n="475" xml:id="pg_475"/> of use to you in discussions with either Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_WSC1">Waugh</persName> or the Argentines.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">No real progress in either meatpackers or ANSEC</hi>.
                            In this situation, I can see no alternative to holding firm to our stand
                            of no loans. We would be under pressure not to adopt a “banker’s
                            mentality”, to consider political factors, etc., but I think it would be
                            a mistake to yield to these arguments.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Progress, or settlement, of meatpackers’ case; no
                                progress in ANSEC</hi>. This situation would be more difficult, for
                            the Argentines could maintain that they had gone as far as a Provisional
                            Government could go in coming to grips with our problems. Nor have we
                            ever told them that a complete settlement of <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
                            the problems was a sine qua non of additional assistance.</p>
                        <p>Logic would indicate, it seems to me, that if the Argentines have come
                            part way in meeting our conditions we might then well go part way in
                            meeting their requests. This would imply limited financial aid in
                            carefully selected fields, with again the clear understanding that
                            large-scale assistance would not be forthcoming in the absence of an
                            ANSEC settlement. Further attentions to transportation and industrial
                            equipment suggest themselves. The field in which financing is vitally
                            needed—electric power—could not, of course, be touched in this
                            situation.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Settlement of both meatpackers and ANSEC problems</hi>.
                            In a way this happy situation would present us the most difficulties,
                            for the Argentines would unquestionably expect aid on a scale beyond
                            anything we could contemplate. We would, however, be morally committed,
                            I think, to providing as much assistance as we could. Here two problems
                            arise. The first is the amount of foreign debt Argentina can assume in
                            the next few years. (The <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> is
                            particularly apprehensive on this score, and feels that Argentina may
                            not be able to service much more in the way of foreign debt. A study on
                            this subject is in process in the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss>.)</p>
                        <p>Secondly, we come face-to-face with the question of electric power, which
                            is, excluding petroleum, admittedly Argentina’s prime need. In this
                            field, we have taken the position that until the situation of <gloss target="#t_AFPAFP1">A&amp;FP</gloss> was regularized, and until
                            Argentina’s power policy was clarified, we could offer no help; even in
                            this case we would presumably maintain the line that we could not
                            intervene should private capital be available. But the recent Argentine
                            action in regard to <gloss target="#t_CADE1">CADE</gloss> and ITALO very
                            definitely raises some questions as to Argentina’s future power policy.
                            Even should <gloss target="#t_AFPAFP1">A&amp;FP</gloss>’s problems be
                            settled and ANSEC allowed reasonable operating conditions, it would be
                            difficult for us to consider a power loan unless we knew the shape of
                            things to come in the rest of the industry. At present it appears that
                            the <gloss target="#t_CADE1">CADE</gloss> and ITALO cases will be in the
                            courts for <pb facs="0510" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/> some years to come;
                            it is also possible that the forthcoming Constitutional Convention will
                            write nationalization of all public utilities into the reformed
                            Constitution. Under circumstances such as these it would be extremely
                            difficult for the <gloss target="#t_EXIMBankEximbank1">Eximbank</gloss>
                            to supply financing for the power industry. (The analogy of
                                Petrobras<note n="5" xml:id="d239fn5">Reference is to Brazil’s
                                government-owned oil company.</note> is perhaps pertinent.) This
                            question, however, should be gone into thoroughly, as the question would
                            arise: Is private capital available?</p>
                        <p>Intermediate situations, such as Argentina’s buying out <gloss target="#t_CADE1">CADE</gloss> and turning it over to Argentine
                            capital or to a mixed company, are also possible. Under these
                            circumstances it is conceivable that <gloss target="#t_AFPAFP1">A&amp;FP</gloss> might be interested in further investment in
                            Argentina; in any case, we should seek clarification of <gloss target="#t_AFPAFP1">A&amp;FP</gloss>’s position before determining
                            ours.</p>
                        <p>Cutting across these questions is the problem of what fields could be
                            benefited by US loans. Here we must face the fact that if petroleum and
                            power are excluded, the field is narrowed sharply. Transportation can
                            absorb a further amount, after which the field appears limited to
                            equipment for industry and agriculture.</p>
                        <p>In this connection, two points should be emphasized to the Argentines in
                            any discussion of loans. First, it is obvious that their problems are of
                            such magnitude that they cannot under any circumstances be solved solely
                            by Government loans. Stimulating the inflow of private capital should be
                            their first concern; an attitude of confidence would certainly be
                            created by settlement of our outstanding problems, while actions like
                            that in the <gloss target="#t_CADE1">CADE</gloss> case can hardly do
                            other than harm in the long run.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, the Argentines seem reluctant to channel loan funds into the
                            private sector, while, I believe, it is our policy to encourage this.
                            Apparently, Argentine reluctance has been based largely on ignorance of
                            techniques in this regard; some salesmanship in this field might well be
                            productive.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>