<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-02-15T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-02-15T17:00:00-05:00" n="24" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d24">
                        <head>24. Telegram From the Ambassador in Guatemala (<persName corresp="#p_AN1" type="from">Armour</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d24fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                033.1100–NI/2–1555. Confidential; Priority.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Guatemala
                                        City</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-02-15T16:00:00-06:00"><hi rend="italic">February 15,
                                        1955—4 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>493. For <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>. My personal observations here
                            supplemented by conferences with Embassy and government officers
                            including President convinces me that vigorous US support essential to
                            preserve in power the first government in history resulting from
                            overthrow of a Communist regime. Failure abundantly to insure stability
                            this government would mark loss of opportunity which may not recur for
                            years; will discourage oppressed peoples everywhere in world and would
                            reflect unpardonable inaction on part US Government. I appreciate
                            efforts of various government agencies heretofore but I am convinced
                            they have been inadequate and that danger to <persName corresp="#p_CACC1">Castillo Armas</persName>’ government is
                            increasing. I urgently recommend to you, to President and all members
                            cabinet following program.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Strong support for Congressional appropriation next fiscal year
                                adequate to complete and pave inter-American highway Guatemala City
                                to Mexican border. Bureau public roads estimates total cost $27
                                million. Completion highway will produce increase in tourist trade
                                which is critically needed and afford solution grave unemployment
                                problem. Financial straits Guatemalan Government caused by robberies
                                Arbenz regime and falling coffee prices make it <pb facs="0101" n="67" xml:id="pg_67"/> essential US contribute entire $27
                                million including Guatemalan share cost completing inter-American
                                highway.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>International Bank should lend dollar component cost completing
                                Pacific coastal highway and Guatemala-Puerto Barrios highway both
                                essential economic development of country and crucial in solving
                                unemployment problems plaguing government. <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> funds available next fiscal year for highway
                                purposes estimated not less $3 million should be used defray local
                                currency costs these two highways leaving burden on Guatemala to
                                supply balance local currency cost estimated approximately $10
                                million.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Announcement that administration and International Bank will support
                            foregoing program for next fiscal year will have decisive political and
                            psychological effect here and will in my judgment give <persName corresp="#p_CACC1">Castillo Armas</persName> government stability
                            necessary to continue in power and carry out its programs for economic
                            development Guatemala. Achievement this end so important to US
                            throughout world that we cannot afford to haggle as to whether few
                            millions less or few months more delay would be dangerous. I feel
                            strongly limitations amount aid granted heretofore and delays in its
                            extension have gravely imperiled basic and vital interests US in
                            world-wide fight against Communism. I urge complete revision our
                            approach regarding aid to this government and realization measures
                            generally applicable in this hemisphere must not control our decisions
                            regarding Guatemala.</p>
                        <p>Foregoing comments and recommendations have complete approval Ambassador
                            and Counselor as well as Chief, <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss>,
                            representative International Bank, and Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName>.</p>
                        <p>In submitting foregoing recommendation regarding financing inter-American
                            highway I am not foreclosing possibility that during or after my trip
                            through area I may recommend additional appropriation for further work
                            on highway in other Central American countries. I am more and more
                            convinced that there is nothing which our government can do in this area
                            which will serve our foreign policy as effectively as would completion
                            of this highway to the Panama Canal.</p>
                        <p>Recommend this cable be repeated to International Bank with request that
                            it advise urgently whether it will promptly grant Pacific Coastal and
                            Guatemala City–Puerto Barrios loans. If it cannot they should
                            immediately be referred to Export-Import Bank.<note n="2" xml:id="d24fn2">A handwritten notation beside this paragraph
                                indicates that these recommendations were carried out by the Bureau
                                of Economic Affairs.</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AN1"><hi rend="strong">Armour</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>