<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="264" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d264">
                        <head>264. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                Bolivia</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d264fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 724.5/2–757. Secret. Repeated to
                                Panama for <gloss target="#t_CINCARIB1">CINCARIB</gloss>. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SRM1">Sayre</persName> and
                                    <persName>William T. Briggs</persName> and initialed by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Bernbaum</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-03-15"><hi rend="italic">March 15,
                                1956</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>268. Joint State–Defense–<gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss> message. You
                            are authorized discuss with President <persName corresp="#p_SZH1">Siles</persName> proposed program (paragraph 39d Bolivia 1290d
                                paper<note n="2" xml:id="d264fn2">Reference is to the Operations
                                Coordinating Board’s “Analysis of Internal Security Situation in
                                Bolivia and Recommended Action,” December 21, 1955. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss>
                                Files: Lot 61 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 385, Latin America
                                1953–58) Paragraph 39 reads in part: “While no increase in the size
                                of the armed forces need be sought at this time, it is in the U.S.
                                interest that their morale and effectiveness be improved and that
                                the confidence of the government and the people in those forces be
                                restored. The Bolivian Government has given the armed forces the
                                mission of aiding in the economic development of the country. By
                                assisting the armed forces to perform this constructive role, the
                                U.S. will help them regain the confidence of the government and the
                                people. At the same time our assistance should be designed to
                                enhance the prestige and to increase the effectiveness of the armed
                                forces in their internal security role and to promote political
                                stability based ultimately upon constitutional processes.” Paragraph
                                39–d recommended provision of “end item grant aid in the form of
                                individual weapons to one battalion-sized unit (the President Escort
                                Regiment.)”</note>) strengthen Bolivian Army. You may state US
                            prepared at this time assist Bolivia obtain small arms and training or
                            President’s escort battalion approximately 550 men. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> only recommendations your despatch 413
                            February 7<note n="3" xml:id="d264fn3">There is no despatch of February
                                7 numbered 413. Despatch 412 of March 6, however, is the report and
                                recommendations of the country team with reference to the <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> analysis of internal security in
                                Bolivia. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Central Files,
                                724.5/3–656)</note> broader program under <pb facs="0575" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/> consideration here. However action herein
                            contemplated authorized in paragraph 39d and considered within scope
                            your recommendations. Since we have no military assistance agreement
                            with Bolivia … in order avoid 1) possible accusation US intervention and
                            2) criticism by other <gloss target="#t_LA1">LA</gloss> countries which
                            likewise do not have agreements and have requested but not received
                            grant aid (End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>) we suggest Bolivia
                            buy under Section 106 Mutual Security Act<note n="4" xml:id="d264fn4">Reference is to <gloss target="#t_PL1">P.L.</gloss> 665; for text,
                                see 68 Stat. 832.</note> list equipment we would propose for this
                            battalion approximate cost $119,915 and request (also under 106)
                            training Army’s ZI and Canal Zone schools about $157,440 for key
                            personnel this battalion and 4 US mobile training teams provide training
                            in Bolivia. Requests for equipment and for training would be made
                            separate notes. Since we recognize Bolivia in present situation should
                            not be encouraged devote foreign exchange military purposes, US for its
                            part in developing grant economic program would take into account any
                            increases required by effect purchase this equipment on Bolivia’s dollar
                            foreign exchange position. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> only we
                            desire avoid commitment requiring US match dollar for dollar foreign
                            exchange [if] Bolivia utilizes purchase military equipment we suggest.
                            Since US supporting Bolivia <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1957
                            extent some $28 million and considering Bolivia has unilaterally spent
                            $185,000 for F–51 and <gloss target="#t_ABC1">C</gloss>–47 military
                            aircraft recently we believe Bolivia should be willing accept general
                            assurance US will provide if necessary adequate dollar support
                            compensate military expenditures this program. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>If <gloss target="#t_GOB1">GOB</gloss> concurs, Army Mission would assist
                            implementation program.</p>
                        <p>We recognize proposed program might be politically infeasible <persName corresp="#p_SZH1">Siles</persName> accept or he may desire different
                            type assistance or timing. We are prepared consider any proposal
                                <persName corresp="#p_SZH1">Siles</persName> may have which would
                            achieve our general objective strengthen Bolivian Army as opposed
                            militia. Considering our relations other <gloss target="#t_LA1">LA</gloss> countries we consider best method financing that
                            outlined above.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HCA1"><hi rend="strong">Herter</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>