<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-09-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="342" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d342">
                        <head>342. Memorandum of a Conversation Between the Brazilian Ambassador
                                (<persName corresp="#p_PEA1" type="from">Amaral Peixoto</persName>)
                            and the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_HHF1" type="to">Holland</persName>),
                            Department of State, Washington, September 10, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d342fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 832.1901/9–1056. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> on September
                            11.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1956-09-10"><hi rend="italic">September 10,
                            1956</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Atomic Energy—Brazil</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador that in a very informal and personal way I wanted
                            to express to him the concern that is growing within this Government and
                            the adverse public opinion that is being created by recent occurrences
                            in Brazil in the field of nuclear energy. I referred specifically to the
                            recent cancellation of the agreement regarding the sale of thorium and
                            cancellation of the agreement regarding exploration for uranium. These
                            events, plus some other problems were having, I feared, a serious effect
                            here.</p>
                        <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said that he wanted me to understand his position; that
                            before he had come here many of his friends had <pb facs="0755" n="721" xml:id="pg_721"/> urged him not to accept this post, but to stay on
                            in Brazil where his political position was secure. He had decided to
                            come because he felt that he could make a real contribution to good
                            relations between the United States. He felt that in coming here he was
                            serving the real best interests of Brazil.</p>
                        <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said that he would specifically recommend … that the
                            Brazilian Government push ahead as rapidly as possible to the conclusion
                            of agreements with the United States in this field and … that the Atomic
                            Energy Commission which has been set up in Brazil negotiate new
                            agreements for the sale of thorium and exploration of uranium in lieu of
                            those which have been canceled.</p>
                        <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>He showed to me a press statement that he intended to issue when he left
                            my office, and I agreed that it would be satisfactory.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>