<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-11-21T18:07:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-11-21T18:07:00-05:00" n="344" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d344">
                        <head>344. Telegram From the Acting <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Brazil</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d344fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                Central Files, 832.1901/11–1056. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SEV1">Ernest V. Siracusa</persName>, Officer in
                                Charge of Brazilian Affairs, and approved by <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-11-21T18:07:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">November 21,
                                        1956—6:07 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>419. <persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName>–Strauss meeting
                                (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 371)<note n="2" xml:id="d344fn2">Telegram 371, November 9, transmitted to the
                                Embassy a proposed agenda for the <persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName>–Strauss meeting, arranged at the latter’s
                                request. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 832.1901/11–956)</note> held
                            21st. <persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName> did not ask for
                            specific new areas cooperation but spoke at length re “now favorable”
                            atmosphere U.S.-Brazilian cooperation. Said he did not know why power
                            reactor instructions not yet received but if not received within month
                            would go Brazil straighten things out.</p>
                        <p>Strauss assured <persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName> our desire
                            cooperate fully establish sound atomic energy program with Brazil but
                            indicated technical problems arising as result uncertain status existing
                            agreements beginning to cause some difficulty. <persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName> said he had recommended
                            prospecting be resumed. Also although <gloss target="#t_GOB1">GOB</gloss> had approved Brazilian <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> recommendation no intention cancel sales contracts. He
                            added new commission good; chairman his personal friend and other
                            members three of whom recently in U.S. all good men and well
                            disposed.</p>
                        <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>Department believes, your discretion, it might now be useful reinforce
                                Strauss–<persName corresp="#p_PEA1">Peixoto</persName> talk by
                            taking advantage opening afforded FonMin statement (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 495)<note n="3" xml:id="d344fn3">In telegram 495, November 16, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">Briggs</persName> reported a recent
                                conversation with Macedo Soares in which the Foreign Minister noted
                                the Brazilian armed services’ concern about the international
                                security situation in light of the Suez and Hungarian crises. Macedo
                                Soares had suggested, accordingly, that it was a propitious time for
                                the United States to move ahead and obtain solutions to its various
                                problems with Brazil, including arrangements in the atomic energy
                                field. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 732.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/11–1656)</note> to seek full discussion atomic
                            energy situation with him along lines your talk with <persName corresp="#p_MJC1">Muniz</persName>. Emphasis should be placed on
                            desirability full cooperation in policy and organization field Brazil’s
                            program to prevent possible monopoly orientation but problems existing
                            contracts, which are of more importance Brazil than U.S., might be
                            mentioned as symptomatic of present unsatisfactory situation. While
                            status contracts should not be overemphasized it might be pointed out
                            that their early clarification would not only serve as indication
                            Brazilian intentions but would also solve certain technical problems re
                            personnel and funds. … Action on this case becomes increasingly
                            important as leasing arrangement <pb facs="0758" n="724" xml:id="pg_724"/> for reactor fuel should be signed soon to avoid upsetting
                            construction schedule.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HHJ1"><hi rend="strong">Hoover</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>