<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>357. Memorandum From the Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Inter-American Affairs (Rubottom) to the Under Secretary of State () to the
                    Under Secretary of State (Hoover))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d357</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">357</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="357"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d357">
                <head>357. Memorandum From the Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1" type="from"
                        >Rubottom</persName>) to the Under Secretary of State (<persName
                        corresp="#p_HHJ1" type="to">Hoover</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d357fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                        711.56322/1–2357. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SRM1"
                            >Sayre</persName>; concurred in by Brigadier General <persName
                            corresp="#p_WBGJKJ1">James K. Wilson, Jr.</persName> of Defense,
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-01-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 23, 1957</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Circular 175:<note n="2" xml:id="d357fn2">Circular 175, December 13, 1955,
                            concerned the proper exercise of the treaty and executive
                            agreement-making power of the United States, as well as the approval of
                            texts of treaties and the making of arrangements for signature. It is in
                            a file retained by the Records Management and Regulations Division of
                            the Bureau of Personnel, Department of State.</note> Army Communication
                        Facility Agreement with Brazil.</item>
                </list>
                <p>On July 2 you authorized negotiations with Brazil to obtain military rights
                    including a guided missile tracking station, an Army communications facility,
                    three <gloss target="#t_LORAN1">LORAN</gloss> stations, and operating rights at
                    three Brazilian airbases. A Guided Missile Station Agreement was concluded on
                    January 21 pursuant to your authorization of December 22. Defense now desires to
                    negotiate an agreement for the Army Communications Facility at Maceio and has
                    requested the Department to negotiate the Agreement appearing in the attached
                    telegram. The draft Agreement is identical with the Guided Missile Station
                    Agreement except for the deletion of Article 6 and minor changes required to
                    convert the agreement to one for an Army Communications Facility. Article 6 was
                    deleted because it involves a commitment <pb facs="0783" n="749" xml:id="pg_749"
                    /> on the part of the United States to discuss with Brazil increased military
                    responsibilities Brazil considers it has assumed by granting use of Brazilian
                    territory. Since the commitment has been made in the Guided Missile Agreement,
                    it should not be necessary to repeat it in this Agreement.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That you sign the attached telegram authorizing Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_BEO1">Briggs</persName> to negotiate for an Army Communications
                        Facility.<note n="3" xml:id="d357fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName> approved the draft telegram
                        and it was transmitted to the Embassy on January 26 as telegram 622. It
                        included a draft agreement for the proposed Maceio communication facility
                        almost identical to the Guided Missiles Agreement. (Department of State,
                        Central Files, 732.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/1–557)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
