<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>363. Telegram From the Ambassador in Brazil (Briggs) to the ) to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d363</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">363</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-05-22T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-05-22T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-05-22T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-05-22T17:00:00-05:00" n="363"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d363">
                <head>363. Telegram From the Ambassador in Brazil (<persName corresp="#p_BEO1"
                        type="from">Briggs</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                        State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d363fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 832.10/5–2257. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-05-22T19:00:00-03:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 22, 1957—7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1272. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1109.<note n="2" xml:id="d363fn2"
                        >In telegram 1109, May 17, the Department informed the Embassy that
                        Brazilian officials in the United States had recently complained that U.S.
                        policy regarding financial support for Brazilian development had changed. In
                        a conversation with Minister-Counselor Valle, <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1"
                            >Rubottom</persName> had stated “categorically” that U.S. policy had not
                        changed and that the Export-Import Bank and the Department had merely agreed
                        to apply the letter and spirit of the agreement made with Brazil the
                        previous year that new large-scale development financing would be unwise
                        until inflation was checked. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                        832.10/5–1757)</note> In realm current Brazil-U.S. relations, problem posed
                    by Brazilian desire additional <gloss target="#t_EXIMBankEximbank1">EXIM
                        Bank</gloss> financing at <pb facs="0790" n="756" xml:id="pg_756"/> time
                    when performance regarding inflation, etc. unimpressive may be one of our most
                    difficult questions, bearing directly on broad political as well as economic
                    matters. It has been Embassy’s belief shared insofar we aware by Department,
                        <gloss target="#t_EXIMBankEximbank1">EXIM Bank</gloss>, and Treasury, that
                    no easy solution this problem likely, … Reluctance stems from political factors
                    which we also recognize no government can ignore.</p>
                <p>At same time <gloss target="#t_EXIMBankEximbank1">EXIM Bank</gloss> loans to
                    Brazil should not be dependent on satisfaction of impossible prerequisites nor
                    upon ultimate lowering Bank’s standards to permit extension of loans when
                    prerequisites unfulfilled. Either we should be serious about prerequisites or
                    refrain from establishing them.</p>
                <p>With foregoing factors in mind, Embassy concurs position taken Department and
                        <gloss target="#t_EXIMBankEximbank1">EXIM Bank</gloss> that it would be
                    unwise finance any new large-scale electric power projects until there has been
                    substantial performance in reducing rate of inflation. … Specifically, Embassy
                    suggests <gloss target="#t_EXIMBankEximbank1">EXIM Bank</gloss> now indicate
                    willingness further to consider loans for major new electric power projects when
                    satisfactory legislation has been enacted and when rate of inflation has been
                    reduced to approximately 10 percent per annum (inflation during first 4 months
                    current year approximately 7½ percent).</p>
                <p>Suggest our views be presented to Brazilians informally rather than in writing,
                    without prescribing specific anti-inflationary measures, and that publicity
                    should of course be avoided. Subject highly critical and politically explosive
                    in Brazil and should Bank express views in writing thereon and communication
                    thereafter become public, government could be seriously embarrassed by
                    accusation and misrepresentation of extreme nationalists.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d363fn3">In telegram 1147 to Rio de Janeiro, May 28, the Department
                        informed the Embassy that <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Arey</persName> had
                        told Pinheiro on May 23 that the Export-Import Bank was not at that time
                        prepared to undertake study applications for the Furnas power project or any
                        other large Brazilian projects. <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Arey</persName>
                        had pointed out that the inflation rate in Brazil during 1956 had been
                        substantial, and that it would be necessary to wait for some months to
                        determine whether real progress was being made during 1957 in curbing
                        inflation. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 832.10/5–2857) In conversations
                        with Department officials, Pinheiro mentioned that financing the Furnas
                        hydroelectric power project would require an initial credit of $50
                        million.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Briggs</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
