<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="448" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d448">
                        <head>448. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington,
                            March 30, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d448fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 821.413/3–3056. Confidential.
                                Drafted by Gerberich.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1956-03-30"><hi rend="italic">March 30, 1956</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Religious Problems in Colombia<note n="2" xml:id="d448fn2">In a
                                    memorandum dated March 27 <persName corresp="#p_BW1">William
                                        Belton</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> that attacks on Protestants in Colombia
                                    continued despite U.S. Government protests and that President
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RRAIF1">Rojas</persName> and the
                                    Minister of Government, Lucio Pabon Nuñez, had “fanned the
                                    flames of religious hatred by public statements linking
                                    Protestants with Communists and subversives.” <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Belton</persName> recommended that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> call in the
                                    Colombian Ambassador to discuss the situation. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 821.413/3–2756)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Colombian Ambassador Dr. <persName corresp="#p_UHF1">Francisco
                                    Urrutia Holguin</persName></item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_OSA1">OSA</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMM1">Bernbaum</persName></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_OSA1">OSA</gloss>—Mr.
                                    <persName>Gerberich</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName> handed the Ambassador
                            an aide-mémoire<note n="3" xml:id="d448fn3">Not found in Department of
                                State files.</note> on the religious problem, and outlined the main
                            points with him. He emphasized that we are concerned because things
                            improved so greatly for a year or so after the <persName corresp="#p_RRAIF1">Rojas</persName> Government took over in 1953
                            and now seem to have deteriorated again. He hoped the Ambassador would
                            find the aide-mémoire helpful in his discussions of this question with
                            the President and other officials of the Colombian Government. He urged
                            that the utmost be done to find a solution to this question that will
                            guarantee U.S. Protestants the enjoyment of their fundamental rights,
                            and said he was pressing the Ambassador to do the utmost, not in a
                            spirit of rancor, but in an earnest desire to eliminate what is possibly
                            the most troublesome problem in Colombian-American relations.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said he understood Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHF1">Holland</persName>’s viewpoint perfectly. He said he had to admit
                            that in the outlying districts of the country the clergy practically
                            rule the actions of the people, and the clergy are ignorant. Most of the
                            country priests have no better education than a fifth-grade pupil in the
                            United States. The average Colombian priest has had no more than three
                            years’ seminary training. They can get the peasants and police in their
                            parishes to testify to almost anything they say, and they may have done
                            this in the deGruyter case and other cases.</p>
                        <p>Nevertheless, he had a feeling that the situation had improved in the
                            last month or two. He asked Mr. <persName>Gerberich</persName> if he had
                            heard of any incidents in that time. Mr. <persName>Gerberich</persName>
                            said he knew of but one, <pb facs="0932" n="898" xml:id="pg_898"/> when
                            an attempt was made to set fire to a Protestant Church at La Cumbre in
                            Valle and the Catholic inhabitants of the village had seen it and
                            themselves put out the flames. The Ambassador said that reminded him of
                            an incident not far away, at La Tejada, where he has a ranch, and where
                            many of the laboring people are Protestants. He said in this case some
                            of the Catholic laborers actually blew up the small parish church
                            because the priest refused burial in consecrated ground to a man who had
                            not lived in wedlock with his wife.</p>
                        <p>He said he would do what he could to improve the situation and intended
                            to make a special effort in the deGruyter case, in which he hopes to
                            interview the witnesses himself. He said the Protestants would help
                            their own lot considerably if they would agree not to operate in
                            “mission territory”. In any case, he thought the situation would
                            certainly improve within a few more months.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>