<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>452. Memorandum From Albert H. Gerberich of the Office of South American
                    Affairs to the Director of the Office ( of the Office of South American Affairs
                    to the Director of the Office (Bernbaum))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d452</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">452</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-04-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-04-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="452"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d452">
                <head>452. Memorandum From <persName type="from">Albert H. Gerberich</persName> of
                    the Office of South American Affairs to the Director of the Office (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BMM1" type="to">Bernbaum</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d452fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 821.14/4–2656.
                        Confidential. Also addressed to <persName corresp="#p_DBC1">Bainbridge C.
                            Davis</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BW1">William
                            Belton</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-04-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 26, 1956</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Banco Popular and its Difficulties with U.S. Banks</item>
                </list>
                <p>On Tuesday, April 24, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CJC2">Corliss</persName>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d452fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJC2">James C. Corliss</persName>, adviser and
                        alternate to the U.S. Representative to the Inter-American Economic and
                        Social Council of the United Nations (IA–<gloss target="#t_IAECOSOC1"
                            >ECOSOC</gloss>).</note> and I had lunch with Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_WF2">Francis</persName>. Scafuro, Vice President of Bank of
                    America, and Mr. <persName>Henry Grady</persName> of the same institution. Mr.
                        <persName>Scafuro</persName> told us he is flying to Bogotá on Thursday and
                    will discuss with the Minister of Finance, with the Chief of the Office of
                    Exchange Control,<note n="3" xml:id="d452fn3">
                        <persName>Enrique Gamboa</persName>.</note> with <persName>Luis Morales
                        Gomez</persName> (President of the Banco Popular), and probably with
                    President <persName corresp="#p_RRAIF1">Rojas</persName> himself the debts owed
                    to eight U.S. banks by the Banco Popular. He said he is very much disappointed
                    with <persName corresp="#p_VMR1">Morales</persName>’ actions, and is definitely
                    of the opinion that there is bad faith in his dealings.</p>
                <p>He said that the eight banks were recently paid a total of some $700,000 on
                    account, but these payments were insufficient, were not allotted in proportion
                    to the amount of the balance due each bank, and were made in such a manner that
                    it was impossible to ascertain just what items were being paid off. The Bank of
                    America also knows that exchange was obtained from the Office of Exchange
                    Control to make additional remittances but was not used by the Banco Popular for
                    the purpose. At one time, Scafuro says, the entire indebtedness to the Bank of
                    America was authorized, but <persName corresp="#p_VMR1">Morales</persName> never
                    made payment.</p>
                <p>The total amount owed the eight U.S. banks is still well in excess of $4,000,000,
                    U.S.C. Over $3,000,000 is still owing the two largest creditors. During the past
                    month Bank of America received a remittance of $250,000 and Banco Popular still
                    owes it about $920,000. It has examined the balance sheet of the Banco Popular
                    and cannot make head or tail of it. An arrangement had been agreed upon whereby
                    Banco Popular was to remit it $100,000 monthly, but this has not been followed.
                        <persName>Morales Gomez</persName> was recently in New York and gave a big
                    party while he was there, carefully excluding all representatives of Irving
                    Trust Company and Bank of America. He has now set up between 55 and 60 branches
                    of the Banco Popular in <pb facs="0951" n="917" xml:id="pg_917"/> half a dozen
                    countries and has evidently over-extended himself. The big question in the Bank
                    of America’s mind is whether the Banco Popular is solvent.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Scafuro</persName> also referred to the drop of the peso to the
                    neighborhood of 4.80 to the dollar last week-end and said he would not be
                    surprised if Finance Minister Villaveces would have to swallow his words and
                    consent to devaluation very shortly, perhaps even this week.</p>
                <p>He said he expected to call on Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BPW1"
                        >Bonsal</persName> and Acting Commercial Counselor Hammond while he is in
                    Bogotá and keep them fully informed of his activities.</p>
                <p>On Wednesday morning, April 25, Mr. <persName>August Maffry</persName>, of the
                    Irving Trust Company,<note n="4" xml:id="d452fn4">In a memorandum of
                        conversation dated March 2, Gerberich reported that Maffry, a Vice President
                        of Irving Trust, had stated that relations between the Banco Popular of
                        Colombia and Irving Trust had deteriorated to the point that all business
                        transactions between the two banks has ceased. (Department of State, Central
                        Files, 821.14/3–256)</note> called at my office and left with me a letter
                    from the Vice President of his firm, Mr. <persName>Michael
                    Sieniawski</persName>, which he asked me to send by pouch to Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName>. He also asked me to make an
                    appointment for him to talk with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BPW1"
                        >Bonsal</persName> when the latter gets here, saying it is known in New York
                    that he will be coming up on May 5. I glanced through the letter and noticed
                    that it concluded by asking the Ambassador if he could use his good offices in
                    correcting the situation. I told Mr. <persName>Maffry</persName> that we could
                    promise him lots of sympathy but I did not see how we could promise any formal
                    intervention at this stage. Mr. <persName>Maffry</persName> made no comment, but
                    shrugged his shoulders.</p>
                <p>He told me he had had a conversation with <persName corresp="#p_NAF1"
                        >Albert</persName> Waterston of the International Bank, and that Mr.
                        <persName>Waterston</persName> was very pessimistic about the Banco Popular
                    case and believes it will hurt the good name of Colombia and may affect
                    Colombia’s chances of getting all the credits it desires this year.</p>
                <p>I happened to speak with Mr. <persName>Russell Lutz</persName> of W.R. Grace
                    &amp; Co. later this morning and asked him if he was au courant regarding the
                    status of the dispute between the Grace Bank and the Banco Popular. He said he
                    was not, but would be shortly talking to New York. I asked him if he would let
                    me know the amount owing the Grace Bank if it is not confidential, as I already
                    know the amount owing the other banks.</p>
                <p>This afternoon Mr. <persName>Lutz</persName> gave me the interesting information
                    that one month ago the Banco Popular owed the Grace Line [Bank?] half a million
                    dollars or a trifle more, but recently one of its Vice Presidents made a trip to
                    Colombia and came back with $250,000, reducing their debt approximately by half.
                    Mr. <persName>Lutz</persName> added that the <pb facs="0952" n="918"
                        xml:id="pg_918"/> Grace Bank is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> interested in
                    having the State Department get into the picture on its behalf, if we are
                    contemplating any such action. He said it is true that it has been working
                    conjointly with the other seven creditors in keeping each other informed on what
                    is happening and coordinating their efforts to effect payment, but his company
                    does not want any pressure brought by the U.S. Government at this time, and the
                    President of Grace Bank told the Irving Trust Company representatives exactly
                    that two days ago. He says his firm is well aware that <persName>Morales
                        Gomez</persName> is very close to President <persName corresp="#p_RRAIF1"
                        >Rojas</persName> and that <persName corresp="#p_RRAIF1">Rojas</persName>
                    and the Government have an interest in the Banco Popular, and it is believed the
                    difficulties can be ironed out without using straight-arm methods.</p>
                <p>On Wednesday afternoon Mr. <persName>Scafuro</persName> phoned me again to tell
                    me all his arrangements have been made and he would be off in the morning. He
                    said Ambassador Urrutia has injected himself into the proceedings, had discussed
                    the Banco Popular with Waterston, and had called Finance Minister Villaveces
                    suggesting a meeting of the latter, President <persName corresp="#p_RRAIF1"
                        >Rojas</persName> and the head of the Banco de la Republica with Scafuro if
                    it can be arranged. In the meantime Scafuro had talked with Martin del Corral,
                    President of the Bank of Bogotá, an old friend who advised him to see Villaveces
                    first of all and get his advice when he arrives in Bogotá; del Corral later made
                    an appointment for him to see Villaveces at 9:00 A.M. on Saturday, April 28.
                    Scafuro then got in touch with Waterston, who advised him to see the President
                    in any case. He agrees with Maffry that Waterston is quite upset about the Banco
                    Popular’s handling of its debt problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Scafuro</persName> has heard that dozens of army officers are said
                    to be indebted to <persName>Morales Gomez</persName>’ bank, and for this reason
                    he fears the President will be fearful of taking any strong action—<persName
                        corresp="#p_VMR1">Morales</persName> may have too much support in the armed
                    forces. For this reason he is a little hesitant about going to the President in
                    the matter.</p>
                <p>Scafuro also told me that the Consulate General in New York wrote in ink
                    alongside his visa the words “Always on the understanding that passport is
                    valid”, something that was not done last year when he went to Colombia. I asked
                    Mr. <persName>Castello</persName>
                    <note n="5" xml:id="d452fn5">Edmundo Castello Nieto, First Secretary of the
                        Colombian Embassy.</note> of the Colombian Embassy about this, and he said
                    it is nonsense, and he is going to inquire into the reason for such an
                    inscription. In the meantime he told me to tell Scafuro to proceed to Colombia
                    at the Colombian Embassy’s risk, and get in touch with it if he should have any
                    trouble on landing at Bogotá.</p>
                <p>I have collected the following figures (approximate) on the total amount still
                    owed by the Banco Popular to U.S. banks: <pb facs="0953" n="919" xml:id="pg_919"/>
                    <table cols="2" rows="9">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Irving Trust Company</cell>
                            <cell role="num">$1,328,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Bank of America</cell>
                            <cell role="num">920,000<note n="6" xml:id="d452fn6">This includes
                                    original principal of $845,000 plus interest and some smaller
                                    items. [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Marine Midland</cell>
                            <cell role="num">450,000<note n="7" xml:id="d452fn7">The indebtedness to
                                    the Marine Midland Bank is “substantial”; I do not think this
                                    figure is too high. [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Colonial</cell>
                            <cell role="num">450,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Schroeder</cell>
                            <cell role="num">375,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Grace</cell>
                            <cell role="num">250,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Philadelphia National</cell>
                            <cell role="num">250,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>A Miami bank</cell>
                            <cell role="num">130,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="underline">Total</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell role="num">$4,253,000</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
