<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>460. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, March 28,
                    1957</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d460</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">460</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recsYFoT63bBb3A5N" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107724"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Protestants</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="460"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d460">
                <head>460. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, March 28,
                        1957<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d460fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Central Files, 821.413/3–2857. Confidential. Drafted by Gerberich.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1957-03-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 28, 1957</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Religious Problem in Colombia</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_UHF1">Francisco Urrutia Holguin</persName>,
                        Colombian Ambassador</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName>Ricardo Anaya</persName>, Minister Counselor of
                        Colombia</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">R. R. Rubottom, Jr.</persName>, Acting
                        Assistant Secretary of State</item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_OSA1">OSA</gloss>—Mr. <persName>Gerberich</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> said he is disturbed that no
                    steps seem to have been taken to work out a solution to the problem of the
                    closed churches in Mission Territory.<note n="2" xml:id="d460fn2">In telegram
                        652 from Bogotá, March 23, <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName>
                        informed the Department of State of a conversation he had with Foreign
                        Minister Rivas on March 21 concerning Protestant missions in Colombia. After
                        describing this conversation, the Ambassador stated:<p>“Only further step I
                            can suggest is to have Secretary call in Urrutia and express his
                            profound concern at this situation and imperative necessity in view
                            interest of US public opinion for Secretary to make public statement at
                            early date deploring fact that American interests and rights as well as
                            general human rights have thus been trampled upon by Colombian
                            Government. It is possible that threat such statement might bring about
                            prompt action. Otherwise we can anticipate only continued delay and
                            evasiveness since elements in this government which brought about
                            closing of churches are stronger than more liberal elements at this time
                            and since Foreign Minister noninfluential even granting intentions
                            good.” (Ibid., 821.413/3–2357)</p>
                    </note> He said he supposed the Ambassador realized that the subject has been
                    brought up on the Senate floor and that Senator <persName corresp="#p_MTD1"
                        >Morse</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d460fn3">
                        <persName>Wayne Morse</persName> (D.–Ore.), Chairman of the American
                        Republics Affairs Subcommittee of the Senate Foreign Relations
                        Committee.</note> had warned that this long unsolved problem is damaging the
                    otherwise good relations between our two countries, and that he intends to
                    follow future developments closely. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1"
                        >Rubottom</persName> added that he himself had been called before four
                    members of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee and had been quizzed regarding
                    the problems of the Protestants in Colombia and he knew that there would be more
                    questioning if there is no change for the better. It has come to be the most
                    discussed subject in our relations with Colombia at the present time.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said he has been hard at work on this problem for the last fifteen
                    days and has been in frequent touch with Bogotáon it. He said the Government is
                    very sensitive toward this attempt to influence it to take steps favoring the
                    Protestants and does not look kindly upon that sort of pressure campaign the
                    U.S. Protestants <pb facs="0967" n="933" xml:id="pg_933"/> have been carrying on
                    by letters to U.S. Senators and Representatives.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> said he thought the U.S.
                    Protestants were exercising their rights as citizens in doing this, for they
                    feel that under a democratic form of government this is an effective way to let
                    the sentiment of the people be known. In view of the large number of Protestants
                    in the U.S., it is not surprising that there has been such an inflow of letters
                    to Congress.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that regardless of this, there seems to be a tendency on the
                    part of the Protestants and others to blame all this trouble over the Mission
                    Territories exclusively on the Government of Colombia and to absolve the Roman
                    Catholic Church from any responsibility or interest in the problem. He said he
                    himself has heard expressions from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BPW1"
                        >Bonsal</persName> and from U.S. Protestant leaders that neither Cardinal
                    Luque nor the Papal Nuncio in Bogotá is interested in closing churches in
                    Mission Territories and have brought no influence to bear in having this done.
                    This is quite contrary to his own understanding. It was the present Subsecretary
                    of State of the Vatican, <persName>Monsignor Antonio Samore</persName>, who as
                    Nuncio at Bogotá signed the Mission Territory Agreement with Colombia, and he
                    has always kept himself carefully informed regarding this problem. The
                    Government is now planning to address the present Papal Nuncio in Bogotá and ask
                    him whether he favors or condemns the action taken to implement the provisions
                    of the Agreement.<note n="4" xml:id="d460fn4">In telegram 615 from Bogotá,
                        February 28, Pigott reported that the Papal Nuncio in Bogotá had stated that
                        the Vatican “did not intend and does not consider 1953 agreement provides
                        basis closing Protestant churches and prohibiting Protestant worship in
                        mission territories.” (Department of State, Central Files,
                        821.413/2–2857)</note> The Ambassador then read Section 9 (c) of the
                    Agreement of January 29, 1953, which provides that the Colombian Government is
                    obligated to hear the views of the Catholic Hierarchy regarding the conduct of
                    education in Mission Territory. In answer to a remark by Mr.
                        <persName>Gerberich</persName> the Ambassador said this provision applies to
                    church services as well as educational activities.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> said his initial reaction to
                    this proposal is that we were not inquiring what the Cardinal or the Nuncio
                    think about what has been done: what we want to know is what the Colombian
                    Government thinks, and what it intends to do about the question.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that it seems apparent there is a conflict between the
                    language of the Mission Territory Agreement and that of the Treaty of 1846. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> said if he remembered
                    correctly, our Legal Division has expressed the view that there is no conflict
                    in regard to the right of the Protestants to hold services. The Ambassador said
                    he would like to see a copy of such an opinion; he <pb facs="0968" n="934"
                        xml:id="pg_934"/> thinks the language of Article XIV of the Treaty is vague
                    on this point and does not guarantee Protestants the right to hold religious
                    services everywhere in Colombian territory. In fact, he thinks that the
                    provisions of the Colombian Constitution give the Protestants greater protection
                    than the Treaty does. He suggested that it might be well to ask an international
                    court to rule on Article XIV of the Treaty.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, he said, the Protestants always come with complaints to the U.S.
                    Embassy or to one or other of the Ministries. They have never tried a test case
                    in the courts of Colombia. If they would do this, they could get a clear ruling
                    on a concrete case. That is the course that would be followed in the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> said he hoped it would not
                    be necessary to submit the Treaty of 1846 to an international court for an
                    interpretation or for the Protestants to fight out this issue in the courts of
                    Colombia. Assurances have been given repeatedly by the Minister of Foreign
                    Relations of Colombia and by President <persName corresp="#p_RRAIF1"
                        >Rojas</persName> himself that a formula would be found to permit the
                    Protestant churches to reopen, and that is what we have been waiting for. The
                    Ambassador agreed that this is so, and that the delay has been caused by the
                    Colombian Government trying to come to an understanding with the leaders of the
                    Church in regard to the issues involved. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1"
                        >Rubottom</persName> said he could only repeat that the question is becoming
                    every day more serious and the Department is under pressure to find a solution
                    which is daily becoming more insistent. He said he hoped the Ambassador would
                    emphasize this in reporting this conversation to his Government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
