<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 106The Ambassador in Italy (Luce) to the President’s Special Assistant
                    (Jackson)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_JCD1">Jackson</persName> papers</note>
                <head>No. 106<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy (<persName type="from"
                        >Luce</persName>) to the President’s Special Assistant (<persName
                            corresp="#p_JCD1" type="to">Jackson</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-09-07">September 7,
                            1953</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear C. D.</hi>: You will remember how profoundly concerned
                    I was about Trieste in Washington six months ago. Since that time, the situation
                    has progressively worsened.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_THR1">Harry</persName>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d106fn1">Presumably a reference to <persName>Henry R.
                            Luce</persName>.</note> will be leaving here on Wednesday<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d106fn2">Sept. 9.</note> and will carry voluminous footnotes on this
                    current “Message to Garcia” to you, for your further clarification …<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d106fn3">Ellipsis in the source text.</note> and concern.</p>
                <pb facs="0299" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/>
                <p>Meanwhile I’d like to make a few observations in what now seems (in G.O.P. season
                    and out) to be my role of Cassandra.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>An adverse decision for Italy on Trieste would be a moral blow to
                            <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s foreign policy.
                            <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> has pitched his whole
                        approach to world questions on a high moral and spiritual note. On moral and
                        spiritual grounds, in a world of the relative virtue of nations, no one can
                        choose <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName>, the Communist Dictator
                        in preference to still Democratic Italy. The loss of Italian friendship for
                        the U.S. which must inevitably follow an adverse decision for Italy on
                        Trieste, would divest <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s
                        foreign policy of much moral coherence.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>It would be a diplomatic blow. British foreign policy scoffed at the
                        Tripartite Declaration from the beginning warning of the danger of promising
                        what we couldn’t probably deliver. Since that time they have made their own
                        position clear in Italy. We never really have. Our failure since 1948, to
                        settle a question which we have increasingly helped to complicate by our aid
                        and support to <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName>, has fortified
                        the view in many chanceries that we are amateurs in diplomacy. To win a weak
                        Italy in 1948 with a promise we refuse to live up to, even partially, is to
                        lose a stronger Italy in 1953, when—as is now happening—the chips are being
                        put down.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>It would be a strategic blow. For the present Italian pro-<gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> government could no more survive the
                        Trieste issue if it went against Italy than <persName corresp="#p_DGA1">De
                            Gasperi</persName>’s did. The next government would go Left—towards
                        Nenni neutralism (this is what the British hope!) and eventually Communist.
                        However great a case the Pentagon can make for <persName corresp="#p_TJB1"
                            >Tito</persName>’s divisions in the event of a war with the Kremlin, a
                        greater case can be made for the wisdom of <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
                        letting Italy check out of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>It would be a political blow. Many of Connecticut’s (and other States’)
                        hundreds of thousands of Catholic and Italian voters would begin to go back
                        to the Democrat fold. One of the greatest reasons why Catholic voters in the
                            <gloss target="#t_USA2">USA</gloss> left the Democratic Party was their
                        deep-seated suspicion that the <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName>
                        buildup of <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> was the effort to
                        further anti-Kremlin Communism, and that Ike would reverse this
                        policy.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I have every reason to believe there is a solution to Trieste, that will lose to
                    us neither Italy’s pro-American government nor Yugoslavia’s divisions. The
                    Department is fully informed of it.<note n="4" xml:id="d106fn4">Presumably a
                        reference to the views which <persName>Luce</persName> expressed in <ref
                            target="#d104">Document 104</ref>.</note> But it is one that can only be
                    achieved now—quickly, and in the present context. Will the Secretary act
                    swiftly? I know and sympathize with the terrible pressures on him—but time is of
                    the essence in this matter.</p>
                <p>Naturally, C.D., I do not cheerfully face the fact that if the Trieste issue goes
                    sour I must bear the onus in Italy, as Ike’s Ambassador. But that is only as it
                    should be. I would proudly endure the failure of my mission here if I believed
                    that I had failed because <pb facs="0300" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/> the Italians
                    would not cooperate with sound American policy—in short, if we were on the right
                    track about Ital-Yugo relations. But my heart is heavy indeed when I consider
                    that we may be on the wrong one. Indeed, I fear we are.</p>
                <p>Believe me, the Democrats will be well within their rights to attack me and the
                    policy I represent with everything they’ve got if it loses Italy to <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. When before could Democrats rightfully claim
                    that Republican policy was appeasing totalitarian dictatorship, scuttling
                    freedom in Europe, selling Democracy down the river to the Commies?</p>
                <p>If <persName corresp="#p_PG1">Pella</persName> falls (which, as I say, he will
                    probably do if the Trieste issue is decided against Italy) the pro-<gloss
                        target="#t_Cominform1">Cominform</gloss> Socialists will probably triumph in
                    the next election—and with them neutralist-socialist views in international
                    affairs. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_MGM1">Malenkov</persName> between them will then decide Europe’s
                    foreign policy.</p>
                <p>What makes all this particularly painful is that no question of dollar handouts
                    is involved here, or Congressional action. What is involved is statesmanship,
                    and resolution, foresight, and fast diplomatic footwork.</p>
                <p>Do we then only know how to pursue dollar diplomacy? Must we always lose in the
                    international field the minute sheer diplomacy is put to the test? If that is
                    true, we may do better frankly to abandon world leadership and revert to
                    isolation which will make much less strain on the purse of our people, and the
                    brains of their leaders.</p>
                <p>I wish I were in Washington now, or Denver. I would feel I could then thrash all
                    this out vigorously with <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Foster</persName> and Ike.
                    Frankly, I never know how much of what is sent to the Department gets through to
                    the top, without being watered down or sold short on the way up. Moreover,
                    cablese seldom conveys the real urgency of these matters.</p>
                <p>State Department cablese is an especially ineffectual and inappropriate idiom in
                    which to tell the President that if he doesn’t settle Trieste in the next few
                    weeks, he may lose his next Congress.<note n="5" xml:id="d106fn5">
                        <persName>Luce</persName> added the following handwritten postscript: “I
                        wrote the enclosed letter to you June 30—two months ago, when the new gov’t
                        was being formed. I did not send it because the Korean pot was boiling, and
                        I felt it was one thing more to harass the President. I wish I had sent
                        it!”</note>
                </p>
                <p>All best</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Clare</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0301" n="267" xml:id="pg_267"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Enclosure]</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy (<persName type="from"
                                >Luce</persName>) to the President’s Special Assistant (<persName
                                corresp="#p_JCD1" type="to">Jackson</persName>)</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-30">June 30,
                                1953</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear CD</hi>—I know the President likes to have even
                        the most urgent matters summed up on one page. The following is a brief if
                        unorthodoxically phrased estimate of the situation in Italy, based on the
                        assumption that nothing ever will be done to bring about a satisfactory
                        solution to the Trieste question.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Estimate of the Situation:</hi>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>For the want of Trieste, an Issue was lost.</p>
                            <p>For the want of an Issue, the Election was lost.</p>
                            <p>For the want of the Election, <persName corresp="#p_DGA1"
                                    >DeGasperi</persName> was lost.</p>
                            <p>For the want of <persName corresp="#p_DGA1">DeGasperi</persName>, his
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> policies were lost.</p>
                            <p>For the want of his <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> policies,
                                Italy was lost.</p>
                            <p>For the want of Italy, Europe was lost.</p>
                            <p>For the want of Europe, America . . . . . . .?<note n="6"
                                    xml:id="d106fn6">The first seven lines of
                                        <persName>Luce</persName>’s “Estimate of the Situation” were
                                    quoted in <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s
                                        <hi rend="italic">Mandate for Change</hi>, p. 409.</note>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">And all for the want of a two-penny town.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>That something be done to save <persName corresp="#p_DGA1"
                            >DeGasperi</persName>’s policies—<gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>,
                        and the Facilities Program—which can be done by giving <hi rend="italic">in
                            exchange</hi> a satisfactory solution of Trieste to the next Italian
                        government.</p>
                    <p>Can you, CD, bring this to the attention of the President at an opportune
                        moment?</p>
                    <p>Cordially,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Clare Boothe Luce</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
