<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-09-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="113" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d113">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">Secretary’s Memoranda of
                                    Conversation, lot 64 D 199, “Trieste”</note>
                                <head>No. 113<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by
                                        the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs
                                            (<persName corresp="#p_BJCH1">Bonbright</persName>)</hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-09-29">September 29, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <list type="subject">
                                    <item>Subject: Trieste</item>
                                </list>
                                <list type="participants">
                                    <head>Participants:</head>
                                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                                    <item><persName>Henri Bonnet</persName>, French
                                        Ambassador</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJCH1">Bonbright</persName>,
                                            <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss></item>
                                </list>
                                <p>M. <persName>Bonnet</persName> raised the Trieste problem with
                                    the Secretary on his own initiative. He began by saying that
                                    because this problem had not been solved the <persName corresp="#p_PG1">Pella</persName> Government was completely
                                    paralyzed and unable to take necessary decisions in other
                                    fields. The French therefore felt that we must come up with a
                                    solution of the Trieste problem which he rather implied could be
                                    imposed. Their thinking was that the solution should be along
                                    the lines of the present boundary between Zone A and Zone B,
                                    perhaps to be followed by a five-power conference. His specific
                                    suggestion was that a tripartite working group be set up to come
                                    up with a proposed solution.</p>
                                <p>The Secretary agreed with the necessity of solving the problem.
                                    He pointed out that on previous occasions we had tried, and
                                    failed, to get a solution based on modifications of the Zone A,
                                    Zone B boundary. The difficulty with this was that refusal of
                                    Italy and Yugoslavia to agree on minor details, involving border
                                    rectifications of only a few miles, had prevented the reaching
                                    of an agreement on the whole problem. He therefore thought it
                                    was questionable whether such details should be discussed in a
                                    larger group such as a five-power conference. His inclination
                                    would be to let the Italians and Yugoslavs work these out.</p>
                                <p>With regard to the Ambassador’s suggestion of a tripartite
                                    working group the Secretary said that he would take it under
                                    advisement but would not attempt to comment now.</p>
                                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> I obtained the distinct
                                    impression from M. <persName>Bonnet</persName>’s attitude during
                                    the discussion that he at least suspects we are working on a
                                    plan for a solution of the Trieste problem and that the French
                                    suggestion for a tripartite working group was intended to smoke
                                    us out and get the French in on the ground floor.)</p>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>