<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-10-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="132" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">Secretary’s Letters, lot 56 D 459,
                                    “T”</note>
                                <head>No. 132<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by
                                        the Director of the Office of Eastern European Affairs
                                            (<persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName>)</hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-10-13">October 13, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <list type="subject">
                                    <item>Subject: Trieste</item>
                                </list>
                                <list type="participants">
                                    <head>Participants:</head>
                                    <item>Yugoslav Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_PCGK1">Koca Popovic</persName></item>
                                    <item>Yugoslav Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Vladimir
                                            Popovic</persName></item>
                                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BM2">Mirko Bruner</persName>,
                                        First Secretary, Yugoslav Embassy</item>
                                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Livingston T.
                                            Merchant</persName>, Assistant Secretary for European
                                        Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Walworth
                                        Barbour</persName>, Director, Office of Eastern European
                                        Affairs</item>
                                </list>
                                <p>The Secretary resumed the conversation interrupted yesterday (see
                                    memorandum of conversation of October 12<note n="1" xml:id="d132fn1"><ref target="#d131"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note>). He stated he had been
                                    reading cables regarding the violent speeches, demonstrations
                                    and attacks on Americans, involving the burning of the portrait
                                    of President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>,
                                    etc., which had been taking place in Yugoslavia. These actions
                                    make a distressing impression when friendship and cooperation,
                                    which has been fostered so many years, blows up for a cause
                                    which is without substance. One wonders how genuine the
                                    friendship is. If real, it does not disappear over-night. The
                                    Secretary asked the Foreign Minister to inform his government
                                    that we take a serious view of these demonstrations which gave
                                    the appearance of being organized and indicated that the
                                    population was not acting spontaneously but being incited to
                                    anti-American acts and worse. As the Secretary had previously
                                    told the Foreign Minister, we have taken action which we believe
                                    to be acceptable to Yugoslavia and designed to allay a
                                    troublesome problem. Without the Yugoslavs making any effort to
                                    understand or appreciate our motives, there have developed
                                    attacks on the US and Britain which prejudice years of effort to
                                    restore mutually advantageous relations. Whatever the intention
                                    of the Yugoslav Government, the violence of its leaders and the
                                    fact that the mobs are not effectively controlled is
                                    incompatible with the relationship we have tried to create.
                                    Between friendly nations there are inevitably differences. We
                                    never expect to find fully acceptable solutions to everything.
                                    However, if on the first occasion when some action is not <pb facs="0343" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/> liked it leads to such
                                    violent outbreaks, it is difficult to see the future since there
                                    will always be differences. We have sometimes to accept
                                    solutions which are not 100% perfect, although in this case we
                                    believe this solution is almost 100% in Yugoslavia’s interest.
                                    The US-UK decision was a basic component of a more tolerant
                                    understanding. We were not in the slightest motivated by
                                    animosity to Yugoslavia, but, on the contrary, felt that the
                                    decision would make for better relations which we desire. As for
                                    Italy, it is anticipated she would have difficulty with the 1948
                                    Declaration.</p>
                                <p>The Foreign Minister stated that on behalf of his government he
                                    regretted the excesses and did not wish to justify them.
                                    However, as the question of the violence of these attacks had
                                    been raised in a context which qualified them as a
                                    discontinuance of friendly relations, he wished to remark that
                                    the bitterness in Yugoslavia and the Yugoslav Government’s
                                    reaction merely are the result of strong feelings and they
                                    believe that through this unilateral decision, relations have
                                    received a blow which has caused the bitterness. On the other
                                    hand, although the Secretary accompanied his remarks by
                                    reservations, there is no basis for the assertion that the
                                    demonstrations were staged or stimulated by the Yugoslav
                                    Government. Even the US press correspondents in Yugoslavia have
                                    reported that the demonstrations were spontaneous and that the
                                    government had taken all suitable measures. As to the
                                    Secretary’s last point the Foreign Minister agreed that it is
                                    difficult to reach fully satisfactory settlements. This, he
                                    said, is obvious. There is another element involved in the
                                    Yugoslav reaction, namely, the equality of nations. Yugoslavia
                                    considers the decision both in substance and form as
                                    constituting a precedent very hard to accept in the conduct of
                                    relations generally, and particularly US-Yugoslav relations. It
                                    is difficult for any nation, no matter how much political
                                    maturity or wisdom it may have, to decide what is best for
                                    another nation. The best motives do not guarantee the results.
                                    It is important to emphasize this since another undesirable
                                    development has taken place, namely, that the Soviets have
                                    started to use the developments for their own and different
                                    purposes.</p>
                                <p>The Secretary noted that, as the Yugoslavs are aware, we have
                                    sought for seven or eight years an agreed solution of this
                                    problem. Meanwhile, US and UK forces have remained indefinitely
                                    responsible for the discharge of functions which were intended
                                    to be temporary and which we are not prepared to continue. As a
                                    result of discussions with the Yugoslav and Italian Governments,
                                    we concluded that the only solution to be adopted was a <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> solution—Zone A to Italy and
                                    Zone B to Yugoslavia. This is not ideal, but it brings this
                                    problem to a conclusion so that we can go forward. If the
                                    Italians do not own Zone A, so far at least Zone B does not
                                    belong to <pb facs="0344" n="310" xml:id="pg_310"/> the
                                    Yugoslavs. It is not right that we remain in Trieste forever. We
                                    have rights which we have exercised, and we see no damage
                                    therefrom to Yugoslavia. The Secretary expressed confidence, in
                                    all seriousness and solemnity, that as the Yugoslav Government
                                    thinks over the matter it will conclude that this is a sound
                                    solution. Yesterday the Yugoslavs expressed concern that the
                                    Italians would go beyond Zone A. We do not believe that they
                                    have such ambitions and we would take affirmative measures with
                                    the Yugoslavs to counter such ambitions if they exist. As far as
                                    we are concerned, this is the end of such ambitions, subject
                                    only to minor mutually agreeable adjustments.</p>
                                <p>The Foreign Minister asked the Secretary to permit him to reply
                                    frankly. The Yugoslavs recognized that the US motives may have
                                    been as set forth but it is hard for them to accept the
                                    motivation as justification for the decision either as to its
                                    substance or its form. He agreed that US troops should not have
                                    to stay indefinitely in Trieste, but he also could say that the
                                    US did not have the right to take decisions affecting the rights
                                    of the Yugoslav Government and the Yugoslav people for the
                                    purpose of removing US troops. Concerning US exercising efforts
                                    to counter further Italian ambitions, is it possible for the
                                    Yugoslavs to consider that sufficient? This decision, if
                                    implemented, already effectively settles the main part of the
                                    issue we are discussing in favor of Italy. To direct the
                                    conversation toward a way out of the situation we are in, the
                                    Foreign Minister said he would like to refer to the Yugoslav
                                    proposal for a four-power meeting.</p>
                                <p>The Secretary said that he could not reply concerning the
                                    four-power proposal today because of the necessity for
                                    coordination with the UK. In response to a further question from
                                    the Foreign Minister as to whether the issue of a four-power
                                    conference should be decided urgently, in view particularly of
                                    the note now received from the Soviet Government,<note n="2" xml:id="d132fn2">Reference is to the Soviet note delivered
                                        to the Embassy in Moscow the afternoon of Oct. 12, the text
                                        of which was transmitted to the Department of State in
                                        telegram 461 from Moscow, Oct. 12. The note contained the
                                        Soviet Government’s protest that the U.S.-U.K. decision on
                                        Oct. 8 constituted a violation of the Italian Peace Treaty.
                                        (750G.00/10–1253)</note> the Secretary agreed on the
                                    urgency, but added that it could be better dealt with if the
                                    Yugoslavs dropped their talk of the use of force and violence,
                                    which is out of keeping with relations between our two
                                    governments. As I understand it, he continued, <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> says that as soon as any
                                    Italian sets foot in Zone A, the Yugoslavs will march in. At
                                    that point there will still be British and US troops there. The
                                    Secretary said that he was not necessarily asking the Foreign
                                    Minister to reply, that the latter could if he wanted to, but
                                    also, if he should so wish, his question <pb facs="0345" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"/> could be treated as a rhetorical one,
                                    carrying its own answer. The remarks made by <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> indicate a forceful
                                    intent.</p>
                                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_PCGK1">Popovic</persName>
                                    replied that he could answer the question with full
                                    responsibility. He said he thought it would be incorrect on the
                                    part of his government to make statements which could be
                                    interpreted as bluff. The Yugoslav Government has stated that it
                                    will react “by corresponding means against an action which, if
                                    it comes about, could be characterized only as the forcible
                                    introduction of Italian troops into Zone A”. If that should
                                    happen, it would be unfortunate as American troops would act as
                                    a shield for such introduction. Precisely to avoid such
                                    consequences, which would be unavoidable if the decision is
                                    implemented, the Foreign Minister requested urgent consideration
                                    of their four-power conference proposal.</p>
                                <p>The Secretary said he would carefully consider the suggestion and
                                    added, in response to a further question as to whether in the
                                    Secretary’s personal view the suggestion appeared appropriate to
                                    the interest and prestige of various countries involved, that he
                                    had made it clear he would have to consult the UK and he could
                                    not express a personal view.</p>
                                <p>Yugoslav Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Popovic</persName>
                                    interjected at this point to inquire whether, in view of the
                                    Soviet action in raising the matter in the Security Council, on
                                    which discussions could take place within 48 hours, it could be
                                    stated in the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> that
                                    conversations between the US, UK and Yugoslavs had already
                                    begun.</p>
                                <p>The Secretary declined to answer except to reiterate that he
                                    would consider the proposal as a matter of urgency and let the
                                    Foreign Minister know. He inquired whether the Foreign Minister
                                    had thought of returning to Belgrade to report to his government
                                    on these conversations or whether he would stay in New York. The
                                    latter replied that he expected to stay in New York in view of
                                    the Security Council development.</p>
                                <p>The Secretary expressed the hope that he could make it very clear
                                    to Marshal <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> that we
                                    cannot take a very favorable view of the threat to use force in
                                    areas outside Yugoslav territory. The Foreign Minister said that
                                    he would fully convey everything that has been said and
                                    particularly the foregoing remark, but he would like to comment
                                    that while the territory is not Yugoslav, it is not Italian, and
                                    to express, in the interest of calming the situation, regret
                                    that he had only received a reserved response in respect to the
                                    four-power conference.</p>
                                <p>The Secretary concluded that the Yugoslavs will have seen the
                                    announcement that he is flying to London tomorrow, that he will
                                        <pb facs="0346" n="312" xml:id="pg_312"/> confer with Mr.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> on Friday<note n="3" xml:id="d132fn3">Oct. 16. Regarding the meeting in
                                        London, Oct. 16–18, see <ref target="#d137">Document
                                            137</ref>.</note> in connection with the foregoing, and
                                    that in the circumstances we might postpone expression of our
                                    views in the Security Council by obtaining a recess for a few
                                    days following the presumed Soviet presentation on Thursday.</p>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>