<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 154The Chargé in the United Kingdom (Butterworth) to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d154</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">154</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-12-18T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-12-18T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-18T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-18T16:00:00-05:00" n="154"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d154">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">750G.00/12–1853: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 154<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom (<persName corresp="#p_BWW1"
                            type="from">Butterworth</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department
                            of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-12-18T21:00:00+00:00"
                            >December 18, 1953—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2696. Limited distribution. <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> and I
                    discussed Trieste plan with <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>.
                    Kirkpatrick, <persName corresp="#p_MRM2">Makins</persName>, Selwyn Lloyd and
                    others were also present.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that French scheme reported Belgrade’s 798 to Department<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d154fn1">
                        <p>Telegram 798 quoted as follows a summary of a proposal <persName
                                corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> made to <persName
                                corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> on Dec. 16 which had also been
                            furnished the Embassy in Belgrade:</p>
                        <p>“Before a conference and with the agreement of the two parties <gloss
                                target="#t_AMG1">AMG</gloss> would transfer to the Italian
                            authorities for the City of Trieste only the contemplated administrative
                            posts. On the other hand it would abrogate Fascist legislation still in
                            force, proclaim an amnesty for Slovenes sentenced on the basis of this
                            legislation and would guarantee freedom of teaching in Slovene.</p>
                        <p>“This step taken, a five-power or two-power conference should be
                            organized with the purpose of seeking a definitive solution. Italy would
                            give up claims to Zone B, Yugoslavia would give up claims to the City of
                            Trieste, territorial exchanges between Zone A and Zone B would take
                            place.</p>
                        <p>“The three powers would emphasize that the settlement in order to be
                            definitive should include a regional autonomy for the two zones,
                            reciprocal guarantees in favor of minorities, a privileged position for
                            Yugoslavia in the Port of Trieste through arrangements similar to those
                            which operated in Salonika between the two wars.” (750G.00/12–1853)</p>
                    </note> was quite impractical. Also agreed, in light of results of <pb
                        facs="0385" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>’s discussion with <persName
                        corresp="#p_PV1">Popovic</persName> (Belgrade’s 797 to Depart-ment<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d154fn2">Telegram 797 reported a conversation between Foreign
                        Minister <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Popovic</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName> on Dec. 17, during which
                            <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>, acting on
                        instructions from the Department of State, had proposed certain
                        modifications to the conditions for convening a five-power conference on
                        Trieste. <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Popovic</persName> had said that the
                        Yugoslav Government insisted on a balanced implementation of the Oct. 8
                        decision, that is, that guarantees for the rights of the Slovene minority in
                        the city of Trieste would have to be decided upon at the same time that
                        Italian officials were introduced into Zone A. (750G.00/12–1753)</note>), it
                    would be inadvisable to pursue present effort any further with <persName
                        corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName>. To do so might only irritate him, obtain
                    nothing acceptable to Italians, and jeopardize chances of getting any agreement
                    from him later on. We should move immediately into second phase of plan, i.e.,
                    ascertain final Italian position. Preliminary five-power meeting without
                    conditions. It was felt we should simultaneously inform Yugoslavs this being
                    done in order to be able to assure both sides they are being kept fully informed
                    of our efforts. British instructing their Washington Embassy to propose
                    foregoing to tripartite group suggesting that instructions be sent Ambassadors
                    Belgrade and Rome to take this step.</p>
                <p>Assuming this does not succeed we should proceed to make United States-UK
                    approach to <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> as outlined in plan.
                        <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> was heartily in favor of this
                    phase of plan, as we believe all others present were, and characterized it as
                    excellent.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> would not agree, however, to
                    statement of numbered paragraph 7 that in last resort <persName
                        corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> could be told he could have choice between
                    our proposal or implementation of October 8 decision. He stated it would in
                    first place require reversal of Cabinet decision, which he is not prepared to
                    request at this time, and secondly we all feel that chances of settling problem
                    have now improved and that both Yugoslavs and Italians genuinely want an agreed
                    settlement. He was unwilling to commit himself now to enforcement of October 8
                    declaration, saying that we should make decision at time it becomes necessary
                    and in light of situation then obtaining. Although <persName corresp="#p_ESA1"
                        >Eden</persName> unwilling to give firm commitment or to put question now to
                    Cabinet, it was clear that he was impressed by the necessity of a solution
                    without retreat from October 8 and by our firmness in this regard.</p>
                <pb facs="0386" n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/>
                <p>With regard to possibility of letting question go to <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> (i.e., Assembly, not Security Council), <persName
                        corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> said “we once favored <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> but it is now at bottom of list.”</p>
                <p>It was agreed that for present no reference to question of “last resort”
                    statement to <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> re October 8 would be
                    made outside Foreign Office and Department. Any discussion of this point and
                    consequent possible leakage might jeopardize chance of putting proposal across.
                    Minutes on this will be drafted and telegraphed Washington when agreed between
                    Foreign Office and Embassy.<note n="3" xml:id="d154fn3">No copy of the agreed
                        British-U.S. minutes of this meeting has been found in Department of State
                        files.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It was also agreed that negotiations with Yugoslavs could best be carried out in
                    either Washington or London, because this would be only way secrecy could be
                    maintained and possibility of final appeal to <persName corresp="#p_TJB1"
                        >Tito</persName> would be left open if necessary. It was tentatively agreed
                    that Yugoslavs would be given choice of Washington or London for
                    discussions.</p>
                <p>Recommend that Department inform Paris, Belgrade and Rome of plan on basic <gloss
                        target="#t_Noforn1">noforn</gloss> except British.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d154fn4">In telegram 754 to Belgrade (2121 to Rome, repeated to
                        London, Paris, and Trieste), Dec. 23, the Department of State outlined the
                        new plan regarding Trieste. (750G.00/12–1753)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWW1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Butterworth</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
