<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-01-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="163" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                                <head>No. 163<lb/><hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi></head>
                                <p>Preparations for the conference on Trieste between the United
                                    Kingdom, the United States, and Yugoslavia began almost
                                    immediately after the Yugoslav Government’s acceptance of the
                                    idea on January 11.</p>
                                <p>In a letter of January 12 to <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Julius
                                        C. Holmes</persName> of the Bureau of European Affairs,
                                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>
                                    said that he hoped <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName>
                                    was going to head the United States negotiating team if the
                                    talks were to take place in London, although he said he was
                                    curious as to how secrecy could be maintained if the “well-known
                                    face of <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> appears in
                                    that city.” <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>
                                    indicated that the Yugoslav Government was very interested in
                                    knowing whom the United States was sending as the negotiator,
                                    because, in addition to Yugoslav sensitivity concerning rank, it
                                    wished to find out if the United States wished to make a real
                                    negotiation of the talks. <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName> also remarked: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“I think the Yugoslavs are vastly pleased with the
                                            proposal and want to get down to business as soon as
                                            possible. Therefore, I hope we shall come prepared to
                                            discuss with them a final solution to Trieste. They are
                                            not being sticky about the form, although they realize
                                            perfectly well that at some point we must go back to the
                                            Italians with a proposal.” (750G.00/1–1254)</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>On January 12, Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> wrote to the Ambassador in Austria,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Llewellyn E.
                                    Thompson</persName>, and apparently raised with <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> the possibility of his
                                    heading the United States negotiating team in the Trieste talks.
                                    No copy of this letter was found in Department of State files,
                                    but in telegram 2039 to Vienna, January 15, <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> asked <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> to stand by for a
                                    possible urgent request to return to Washington for consultation
                                    and the “special temporary assignment about which I wrote you
                                    Jan. 12.” On January 16, the Department of State requested
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> to return to
                                    Washington for consultation as soon as possible. He left Vienna
                                    on January 22 and arrived in the United States the following
                                    day.</p>
                                <p>In a letter of reply to <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>, January 19, <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> said that Secretary
                                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> thoroughly
                                    concurred in <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>’s opinion <pb facs="0400" n="366" xml:id="pg_366"/> that <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> was too familiar a figure in London to
                                    conduct the secret negotiations on Trieste and in view of the
                                    need to maintain secrecy, it had been decided to send <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>. He also said that,
                                    because a number of Department of State officials would soon
                                    leave for the Berlin Conference, it was felt that <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> should remain in
                                    Washington and cover that end of the Trieste negotiations.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> mentioned that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> was being
                                    called back to Washington ostensibly for consultation on
                                    Austrian matters and would use the cover story that he was
                                    stopping over in London to get some new clothes and to talk with
                                    the Foreign Office regarding Austrian matters on his way either
                                    to Berlin or Vienna. (<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/RA
                                    files, lot 54 D 514, “Trieste, 1954”)</p>
                                <p>Another reason that <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName>
                                    was not selected as the chief United States negotiator in the
                                    talks is that Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> was aware, as early as September 1953,
                                    that the Justice Department was contemplating legal action
                                    against <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> on charges
                                    of defrauding the United States Government in surplus ship
                                    transactions. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>,
                                    however, was able to persuade Attorney General
                                        <persName>Brownell</persName> to delay taking action against
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> until early
                                    1954. Memoranda of telephone conversations between <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> and Brownell regarding
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName>, on September
                                    11, October 5, and November 2, 3, 19, and 20, 1953, are in
                                        <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> papers,
                                    “Telephone Memoranda—General.” On February 23, 1954, the
                                    Department of Justice announced that <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName>, along with 17 other persons and 7
                                    corporations, were being charged with defrauding the United
                                    States Government in surplus ship deals. <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> had been given advance
                                    notice that he was to be indicted and had written to Under
                                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> on
                                    February 18 saying that he had done nothing illegal or improper.
                                    However, he expressed his belief that it was not in the interest
                                    of the United States Government for him to continue at his post.
                                    On February 23, the Department of State announced that <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Holmes</persName> had been granted a leave
                                    of absence. (<hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, February 24,
                                    1954, pages 1, 15)</p>
                                <p>There was also considerable discussion among the three
                                    participating countries as to which city would be the best
                                    location for the talks. The Department of State preferred to
                                    hold the talks in Washington rather than in London because it
                                    believed that there was a better chance for secrecy in
                                    Washington, the Yugoslav Ambassador in London held extreme
                                    personal views on the Trieste issue, and an agreement worked out
                                    in Washington would be easier to present to the Italian
                                    Government than one worked out in London. (Telegram 811 in
                                    Belgrade, January 12; 750G.00/1–1154) The British Government
                                    agreed with this preference. However, the Yugoslav Government
                                    indicated its preference for London because of practical
                                    considerations of proximity and travel, its belief that <pb facs="0401" n="367" xml:id="pg_367"/> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VV1">Velebit</persName> was better informed on
                                    the Trieste issue than Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Vladimir Popović</persName> in Washington, and the fact
                                    that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Popović</persName>
                                    was planning to leave Washington in March as a result of his
                                    election to the Federal Assembly. (Telegram 863 from Belgrade,
                                    January 15; 750G.00/1–1554) On January 16, in telegram 825 to
                                    Belgrade, the Department of State expressed its approval for
                                    London as the site of the talks and suggested February 2 as the
                                    opening date. (750G.00/1–1554) On January 18, in telegram 870
                                    from Belgrade, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName> said that the Yugoslav Government
                                    had accepted the February 2 date. (750G.00/1–1854)</p>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>