<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 173Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of Protocol (Simmons)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-03-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-03-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="173"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">601.6811/3–1154</note>
                <head>No. 173<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of Protocol
                            (<persName corresp="#p_SJF1">Simmons</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-03-11">March 11,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Farewell Call of the Yugoslav Ambassador on the President</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>The Ambassador of the Federal People’s Republic of Yugoslavia</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJF1">John F. Simmons</persName>, Chief of
                        Protocol</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BM2">Mirko Bruner</persName>, First Secretary of
                        the Embassy, Interpreter</item>
                </list>
                <p>His Excellency <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Vladimir Popović</persName>, Ambassador
                    of the Federal People’s Republic of Yugoslavia, called, by appointment, on the
                    President at 2 p.m. today for the stated purposes of (1) saying goodbye and (2)
                    presenting to the President a bronze equestrian statue, an original of the
                    larger one to be given later to the United Nations. Certain aspects of the
                    conversation, as set forth below, seem to be worthy of particular note.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador’s first point was an assurance of a continuation of the feeling of
                    friendship by the Yugoslav Government and people toward the United States. He
                    emphasized the point that this feeling is a very real one. He then stressed the
                    gratitude of Yugoslavia for all the assistance, material and moral, which the
                    United States had given to his country at a time of dire need. This, he said,
                    would never be forgotten.</p>
                <p>The President said that, although Americans do not favor Yugoslavia’s form of
                    Government, the Ambassador must realize, from his four years here, that the
                    American people are truly friendly and that this feeling applies in strong
                    measure to Yugoslavia. He said that we appreciate particularly the brave action
                    of Yugoslavia in showing its independence of the Soviet Sphere.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then said that this was true and that we could view with the
                    utmost confidence the very real break from the Comintern which occurred in 1948.
                    He described this as a real people’s movement, and said that the whole nation
                    was solidly behind Marshal <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> in this
                    action. He said that a recent manifestation of Yugoslavia’s being in the
                    anti-Comintern group was its action in signing pacts of friendship and
                    cooperation with Turkey and Greece. He then said that Yugoslavia would like to
                    continue this policy further by taking similar action with Italy. Here the
                    stumbling block had been the difficult Trieste question. At this point he <pb
                        facs="0415" n="381" xml:id="pg_381"/> somewhat emotionally described the
                    efforts for conciliation on the part of his own country and the intransigeant
                    attitude of Italy. He asked what could be more fair than Yugoslavia’s conceding
                    the whole City of Trieste to Italy and only demanding certain areas and towns of
                    pure Slavic population in Zone B. Yugoslavia, he said, places great importance
                    on the amicable settlement of this thorny problem. He asked the President to
                    mediate, if possible.</p>
                <p>The President said that solving the Trieste problem is vital. If that could
                    occur, he said, we would have a solid defense ring, starting with Turkey and
                    Greece, and carried forward without a break through Italy. This, he said, would
                    be a tremendous deterrent to Soviet aggression and would thus have great
                    stabilizing influence on the world situation. He stood ready, at any time, to do
                    anything he properly could to bring about a solution. He added that the problem
                    is a two-way affair, and that both sides must approach it in a spirit of
                    conciliation. We in America could not be expected to judge the rights and wrongs
                    of each contentious point, but we could and would lend our good offices, where
                    possible, to effect a solution through fair compromise. Such a solution, the
                    President said, is very close to his heart and he hopes fervently that it can be
                    reached through frank and conciliatory discussions by both parties.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then said that he had to bring up one more question, although he
                    did so with some embarrassment. This was the continuance in the future of our
                    aid to Yugoslavia in the form of two things (1) military assistance and (2)
                    grants of wheat. These two questions were as important now as they ever were
                    before, he said, and he hoped that they would be acted upon by us in the same
                    generous spirit as previously.</p>
                <p>The President said that the Ambassador could count on our continued friendship
                    toward his country. The last question was of an intricate technical nature and
                    would of course be studied sympathetically. The Ambassador mentioned that he
                    would take this question up in more detail in his forthcoming conversation at
                    the Department with General <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName>.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d173fn1">This conversation has not been further
                        identified.</note> The President said that after this conversation had
                    occurred he would call upon General <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName>
                    for a full discussion of it and that then the question of how to meet
                    Yugoslavia’s wishes would be worked out with all possible regard to our wish to
                    adopt both friendly and reasonable solutions.<note n="2" xml:id="d173fn2">No
                        record of such a conversation between <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName>
                        has been found in Department of State files or at the <persName
                            corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Ambassador expressed himself as deeply appreciative of the President’s
                    friendly reception and as a devoted friend of the American people as he returned
                    to his own country.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
