<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="198" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source"><persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> papers, Whitman file</note>
                                <head>No. 198<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d198fn1">A draft of this memorandum by
                                            <persName>Hooker</persName> was an attachment to
                                            <persName>Hooker</persName>’s memorandum of June 2 to
                                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                                        through <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>.
                                            <persName>Hooker</persName> wrote that in view of the
                                        President’s interest in the Trieste problem, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> might wish to call
                                        his attention to the successful completion of the first
                                        phase of the negotiations. (750G.00/6–254)</note></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                        secret</hi></seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-03">June 3,
                                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <list type="subject">
                                    <head>Subject:</head>
                                    <item>Successful completion of first phase of Trieste
                                        negotiations.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p>For your information, the “Agreed Record of Positions Reached”
                                    between the US, UK, and Yugoslavia was initialed in London on
                                    Monday, May 31 (copy attached<note n="2" xml:id="d198fn2">The
                                        copy was identical to the Agreed Record of Positions, <ref target="#d197"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>.</note>).</p>
                                <p>The Yugoslavs agreed to a territorial settlement which amounts
                                    practically to acceptance of October 8, i.e., Zone A which
                                    includes the city of Trieste to Italy and Zone B to Yugoslavia.
                                    The only difference is that they ask for a small strip of Zone A
                                    at the western end of the interzonal boundary and are willing to
                                    give up a smaller segment of Zone B at the eastern end. (See map
                                        attached.<note n="3" xml:id="d198fn3">Not found attached to
                                        the source text.</note>) The changes proposed could
                                    accurately be described as a “minor rectification” of the
                                    boundary. This contrasts with the initial Yugoslav demand for
                                    the entire hinterland of Zone A, leaving only the city of
                                    Trieste and a coastal strip to the Italians; and with their
                                    later demand for a port area on the outskirts of the city with a
                                    connecting corridor.</p>
                                <p>The Yugoslavs have also given up their insistence that the
                                    territorial settlement be contingent upon a settlement of their
                                    financial, mostly World War II reparations, claims against
                                    Italy.</p>
                                <p>Other features of the contemplated settlement are a reciprocal
                                    statute for the protection of minorities, arrangements for
                                    maintenance of a free port in Trieste and for some measure of at
                                    least lip-service to the idea of local autonomy, and a
                                    reciprocal declaration <pb facs="0473" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/>
                                    of non-prosecution for political activities in connection with
                                    the settlement.</p>
                                <p>The US, UK, and possibly France would issue a statement of
                                    non-support for further territorial claims by either side and
                                    would in fact make it clear that they consider the settlement
                                    final, although it will not be so described in explicit
                                    terms.</p>
                                <p>The US is granting Yugoslavia $20 million additional aid in
                                        <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1954 and the British
                                    $5,600,000, which is required on the basis of Yugoslavia’s
                                    current balance of payment deficit. The Yugoslavs may use a
                                    major portion of the local currency counterpart funds generated
                                    by this aid for the construction of a port and transportation
                                    facilities in the Capodistria–San Nicolo area. It will also be
                                    proposed to the Italians that we grant them a similar amount of
                                    aid to assist them in reaching a financial settlement with the
                                    Yugoslavs.</p>
                                <p>The US and UK negotiators in London, after informing the French,
                                    opened the second phase of these negotiations with the Italians
                                    on June 1.<note n="4" xml:id="d198fn4">In a brief memorandum to
                                            <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, June 7,
                                            <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                                        thanked the Secretary for the report on Trieste and said
                                        that if it became apparent that an agreement was to be
                                        reached, plans for the release of the information should be
                                        carefully made. He concluded, “If properly handled, it
                                        should strengthen our position immeasurably, particularly
                                        abroad.” (750G.00/6–754)</note></p>
                                <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">John Foster
                                    Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                            </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>