<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 282The Ambassador in Italy (Luce) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d282</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">282</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-09-22T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-09-22T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-22T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-22T07:00:00-05:00" n="282"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d282">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">750G.00/9–2254: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 282<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy (<persName type="from"
                        >Luce</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d282fn1">Repeated for information to London for <persName
                            corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> and Paris for <persName
                            corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> and to Belgrade and Trieste.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-22T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >September 22, 1954—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1140. Limit distribution. As stated in Embtel 1133<note n="2" xml:id="d282fn2">
                        <ref target="#d281">
                            <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> Casardi and <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> Balzo met
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> at airport early this morning
                    to discuss government’s decision on two alternatives for frontier rectification.
                    They did not give any definitive answer but stated that the following procedure
                    would be followed: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>Instructions would be sent to <persName corresp="#p_BM1"
                                >Brosio</persName> to conclude immediately all aspects of proposed
                            agreement with exception of territorial question.</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>Entire agreement containing two alternatives on frontier rectification
                            would then be presented by <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName>
                            for Cabinet decision.</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>Cabinet would decide whether alternative one or alternative two would
                            be accepted (as described in Embtel 1113 September 20<note n="3"
                                xml:id="d282fn3">
                                <ref target="#d279">Document 279</ref>.</note>) and final agreement
                            could then be completed in very short time.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Foreign Office officials said that this procedure was necessary in view of
                    political problem faced by <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> since
                    territorial settlement was least attractive aspect of agreement from Italian
                    point of view. Territorial provisions however are counter balanced by other
                    favorable aspects which Italy would derive from Trieste settlement. They believe
                    that <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> could then present entire
                    package with choice of territorial alternatives in much better light than if he
                    presented solely problem of frontier rectification without being able to stress
                    the advantages of agreement to Italy. They reiterated <pb facs="0590" n="556"
                        xml:id="pg_556"/> importance of timing as outlined in Embtel 1133 and stated
                    that instructions would be sent to <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Brosio</persName>
                    to proceed on foregoing basis immediately.</p>
                <p>Casardi and <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> Balzo pointed out two problems
                    which still disturbed them: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>On question of cultural houses they repeated that raising their figure
                            of 150 million lire by 25 or 30 was all that could be done at present
                            time. <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> Balzo suggested that land and
                            an “equitable” sum of money be given to Yugoslavs for purpose of
                            constructing a cultural house and that details providing for further
                            payments over a longer period of time be worked out at a later date.
                            They pointed out discrepancy between requirement for providing 500
                            million lire for cultural houses in Trieste and the fact that “no hovel
                            is available in Capodistria for Italian Consulate.” <gloss
                                target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> Balzo stressed that problems of this
                            type might raise difficulties in the ultimate political decision. (We
                            learned from Fracassi today that instructions were sent to <persName
                                corresp="#p_BM1">Brosio</persName> limiting additional Italian
                            financial support to 25–30 million lire.)</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>Italians also disturbed by phrase “regardless of their legal status”
                            in first sentence draft letter on financial settlement. According to
                            Casardi, Yugoslavs responsible for paying for property of optants.
                            However, Yugoslavs have refused recognize right of certain people
                            residing or formerly resident in territory ceded to Yugoslavia by Italy
                            under peace treaty. Yugoslavs refusal based on grounds that persons
                            involved are ethnically not Italians. Italian Treasury estimates that
                            property claims of persons this category amount to ten million dollars.
                            Question apparently involves Article 10 of Annex 14 peace treaty and
                            Italo-Yugoslav agreement of 1949. Casardi promised us memo today
                            substance of which we will telegraph as soon as received.<note n="4"
                                xml:id="d282fn4">Not further identified.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Yugoslavs request for frontier rectification in Gorizia area not raised with
                    Italians. <persName corresp="#p_BA1">Bebler</persName> gave <persName
                        corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> a memo on this question which he has
                    given to Embassy in Rome for action.<note n="4" target="d282fn4">Not further
                        identified.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> was under distinct impression that
                        <persName corresp="#p_BA1">Bebler</persName> did not make frontier
                    rectification in Gorizia a condition for Trieste settlement. We concur with
                        <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>’s recommendation that this
                    problem should be in no way connected with Trieste settlement or made a part of
                    it. We therefore propose subject to instructions to bring gist of Yugoslav memo
                    to attention Italian Foreign Office and follow <persName corresp="#p_TLE1"
                        >Thompson</persName>’s suggestion that Italians be asked to agree to discuss
                    this question promptly. We will make it clear however that it is not connected
                    with Trieste settlement.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Luce</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
