<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 293Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-01-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-01-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="293" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d293">
                <head>No. 293<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Following some minor changes in the wording of the various documents under
                    discussion by the negotiators in London, the Department of State released the
                    following announcement at 10 a.m., E.S.T., October 5: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“At noon today in London a Memorandum of Understanding on Trieste was
                            initialed by representatives of the Governments of the United States,
                            the United Kingdom, Italy and Yugoslavia. <persName corresp="#p_TLE1"
                                >Llewellyn E. Thompson</persName>, United States Ambassador to
                            Austria, initialed the Memorandum of Understanding for the United States
                            and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HGW1">Geoffrey Harrison</persName>,
                            Assistant Under-Secretary of State in the British Foreign Office,
                            initialed for the United Kingdom. The Ambassadors of Italy and
                            Yugoslavia in London, Signor <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Manlio
                                Brosio</persName> and Dr. <persName corresp="#p_VV1">Vladimir
                                Velebit</persName>, initialed the document for their two
                            Governments. The text of the Memorandum of Understanding is being
                            communicated to the Security Council of the United Nations.</p>
                        <p>“Today’s initialing came as a successful conclusion to conversations
                            among the four Governments which have been carried on for eight months
                            in an endeavor to work out arrangements for the Free Territory of
                            Trieste which would be acceptable to the Governments of Italy and
                            Yugoslavia. The United States Government welcomes the understanding
                            reached today which it believes will lead to improved relations and
                            closer cooperation between Italy and Yugoslavia. The United States
                            Government takes this opportunity to declare it will give no support to
                            claims of either Yugoslavia or Italy to territory under the sovereignty
                            or administration of the other. The United States Government is
                            confident that it will be possible for the two countries to resolve any
                            outstanding problems by friendly negotiations in a spirit of mutual
                            understanding.</p>
                        <p>“Arrangements are being made for the early termination of Allied Military
                            Government, the withdrawal of American and British forces from the area
                            under their occupation and the assumption by Italy and Yugoslavia of
                            responsibility in the areas as defined by the agreement initialed
                            today.” (Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October
                            18, 1954, page 555)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Also released at this time was the following text of the Memorandum of
                    Understanding between the Governments of Italy, the United States, the United
                    Kingdom, and Yugoslavia regarding the <pb facs="0605" n="571" xml:id="pg_571"/>
                    Free Territory of Trieste (printed in Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bulletin</hi>, October 18, 1954, pages 556–558): <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <list>
                            <item>“1. Owing to the fact that it has proved impossible to put into
                                effect the provisions of the Italian Peace Treaty relating to the
                                Free Territory of Trieste, the Governments of the United Kingdom,
                                the United States and Yugoslavia have maintained since the end of
                                the war military occupation and government in Zones A and B of the
                                Territory. When the Treaty was signed, it was never intended that
                                these responsibilities should be other than temporary and the
                                Governments of Italy, the United Kingdom, the United States and
                                Yugoslavia, as the countries principally concerned, have recently
                                consulted together in order to consider how best to bring the
                                present unsatisfactory situation to an end. As a result they have
                                agreed upon the following practical arrangements.</item>
                            <item>“2. As soon as this Memorandum of Understanding has been initialed
                                and the boundary adjustments provided by it have been carried out,
                                the Governments of the United Kingdom, the United States and
                                Yugoslavia will terminate military government in Zones A and B of
                                the Territory. The Governments of the United Kingdom and the United
                                States will withdraw their military forces from the area north of
                                the new boundary and will relinquish the administration of that area
                                to the Italian Government. The Italian and Yugoslav Governments will
                                forthwith extend their civil administration over the area for which
                                they will have responsibility.</item>
                            <item>“3. The boundary adjustments referred to in paragraph 2 will be
                                carried out in accordance with the map at Annex I. A preliminary
                                demarcation will be carried out by representatives of Allied
                                Military Government and Yugoslav Military Government as soon as this
                                Memorandum of Understanding has been initialled and in any event
                                within three weeks from the date of initialling. The Italian and
                                Yugoslav Governments will immediately appoint a Boundary Commission
                                to effect a more precise demarcation of the boundary in accordance
                                with the map at Annex I.</item>
                            <item>“4. The Italian and Yugoslav Governments agree to enforce the
                                Special Statute contained in Annex II.</item>
                            <item>“5. The Italian Government undertakes to maintain the Free Port at
                                Trieste in general accordance with the provisions of Articles 1–20
                                of Annex VIII of the Italian Peace Treaty.</item>
                            <item>“6. The Italian and Yugoslav Governments agree that they will not
                                undertake any legal or administrative action to prosecute or
                                discriminate against the person or property of any resident of the
                                areas coming under their civil administration in accordance with
                                this Memorandum of Understanding for past political activities in
                                connexion with the solution of the problem of the Free Territory of
                                Trieste.</item>
                            <item>“7. The Italian and Yugoslav Governments agree to enter into
                                negotiations within a period of two months from the date of
                                initialling of this Memorandum of Understanding with a view to
                                concluding promptly an agreement regulating local border traffic,
                                including facilities for the movement of the residents of border
                                areas by land and by sea over the boundary for normal commercial and
                                other activities and for transport and communications. This
                                agreement shall cover Trieste and the area bordering it. Pending the
                                    <pb facs="0606" n="572" xml:id="pg_572"/> conclusion of such
                                agreement, the competent authorities will take, each within their
                                respective competence, appropriate measures in order to facilitate
                                local border traffic.</item>
                            <item>“8. For a period of one year from the date of initialling of this
                                Memorandum of Understanding persons formerly resident
                                (‘pertinenti’-‘zavičajni’) in the areas coming under the civil
                                administration either of Italy or of Yugoslavia shall be free to
                                return immediately thereto. Any persons so returning, as also any
                                such who have already returned, shall enjoy the same rights as the
                                other residents of these areas. Their properties and assets shall be
                                at their disposal, in accordance with existing law, unless disposed
                                of by them in the meantime. For a period of two years from the date
                                of initialling of this Memorandum of Understanding, persons formerly
                                resident in either of these areas and who do not intend returning
                                thereto, and persons presently resident in either area who decide
                                within one year from the date of initialling of this Memorandum of
                                Understanding to give up such residence, shall be permitted to
                                remove their movable property and transfer their funds. No export or
                                import duties or any other tax will be imposed in connexion with the
                                moving of such property. Persons wherever resident who decide to
                                sell their movable and immovable property within two years from the
                                date of initialling of this Memorandum of Understanding will have
                                the sums realised from the sale of such property deposited in
                                special accounts with the National Banks of Italy or Yugoslavia. Any
                                balance between these two accounts will be liquidated by the two
                                Governments at the end of the two year period. Without prejudice to
                                the immediate implementation of the provisions of this paragraph the
                                Italian and Yugoslav Governments undertake to conclude a detailed
                                agreement within six months of the date of initialling of this
                                Memorandum of Understanding.</item>
                            <item>
                                <p>“9. This Memorandum of Understanding will be communicated to the
                                    Security Council of the United Nations.</p>
                                <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>, the 5th of October, 1954.</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Manlio Brosio</persName>
                                <lb/>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HGW1">Geoffrey W. Harrison</persName>
                                <lb/>
                                <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Llewellyn E. Thompson</persName>
                                <lb/>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_VV1">Vladimir
                                Velebit</persName>”</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The map at Annex I, cited in paragraph 3, is not printed here and was not printed
                    in the Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>. A copy of Annex I is
                    in file 750G.00/10–554. Annex II, cited in paragraph 4, is not printed, but see
                    Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October 18, 1954, pages
                    558–561. This Memorandum of Understanding was transmitted to the President of
                    the Security Council on October 5 and circulated as <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >U.N</gloss>. <ref target="#d8">document 8</ref>/3301.</p>
                <p>Also made public on October 5 were the texts of identical letters which <persName
                        corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HGW1"
                        >Harrison</persName> addressed to <persName corresp="#p_BM1"
                        >Brosio</persName>, asking the Italian Government to designate a
                    representative to meet at an early date with General <persName corresp="#p_WGJ1"
                        >Winterton</persName> to formulate arrangements for the transfer of military
                    and administrative authority in Zone A to Italy <pb facs="0607" n="573"
                        xml:id="pg_573"/> which, it was hoped, would be carried out within one
                    month. In his identical letters of reply to <persName corresp="#p_TLE1"
                        >Thompson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HGW1">Harrison</persName>,
                    also dated October 5, <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Brosio</persName> said that the
                    Italian Government had designated General <persName>Edmondo de Renzi</persName>
                    as its representative to conduct the talks with <persName corresp="#p_WGJ1"
                        >Winterton</persName>. The texts of these letters are printed in Department
                    of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October 18, 1954, pages 555–556. A
                    statement by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, dated
                    October 5, regarding the Trieste agreement, is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.,
                    page 556.</p>
                <p>In addition to those parts of the agreement which were made public, there were
                    several confidential parts not made known at the time: (1) an exchange of
                    letters, dated October 4, between <persName corresp="#p_HGW1"
                        >Harrison</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>, on
                    the one hand, and <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Brosio</persName>, on the other,
                    whereby the Italian Government said that it was prepared to approve the
                    establishment in Trieste of a Slovene credit institution and (2) an exchange of
                    several letters, dated October 5, between <persName corresp="#p_BM1"
                        >Brosio</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_VV1">Velebit</persName>,
                    whereby (a) the Italian and Yugoslav Governments agreed to an early meeting with
                    other interested governments to discuss the use of the Free Port; (b) they
                    agreed to negotiate and to conclude within two months a claims agreement; (c)
                    the Italian Government agreed to provide cultural homes for Slovenes in Zone A,
                    furnishing 500 million lire for this purpose; and (d) the Italian Government
                    agreed to the establishment of a Yugoslav Consulate in Trieste and the Yugoslav
                    Government agreed to the establishment of an Italian Consulate in Koper. The
                    texts of all these letters, except for <persName corresp="#p_VV1"
                        >Velebit</persName>’s reply to <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Brosio</persName>
                    regarding the meeting on the Free Port issue, were transmitted to the Department
                    of State as attachments to despatch 971 from London, October 6.
                    (750G.00/10–654)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
