<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 295Memorandum of Discussion at the 216th Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, October 6, 1954</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-10-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-10-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="rec3fxRcXXIdLOFDO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006620"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naval operations</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-10-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-10-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="295"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> papers, Whitman file</note>
                <head>No. 295<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Discussion at the 216th Meeting of the National
                        Security Council, Washington, October 6, 1954</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d295fn1">Prepared by <persName corresp="#p_GSE1"
                            >Gleason</persName> on Oct. 6.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>eyes only</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-10-06">October 6,
                            1954</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Present at the 216th meeting of the Council were the Secretary of State,
                    presiding; the Secretary of Defense; the Director, Foreign <pb facs="0609"
                        n="575" xml:id="pg_575"/> Operations Administration; and the Director,
                    Office of Defense Mobilization. Also present were the Secretary of the Treasury;
                    the Attorney General (for Item 4); the Director, Bureau of the Budget; the
                    Secretary of the Army; the Secretary of the Navy; the Secretary of the Air
                    Force; the Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff; the Chief of Staff, U.S. Army;
                    Admiral <persName>Duncan</persName> for the Chief of Naval Operations; the Chief
                    of Staff, U.S. Air Force; General <persName>Twining</persName> for the
                    Commandant, U.S. Marine Corps; the Director of Central Intelligence; the
                    Assistant to the President; <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Robert Cutler</persName>,
                    Special Assistant to the President; <persName corresp="#p_BRR1">Robert R.
                        Bowie</persName>, Department of State; the Executive Secretary, <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>; the Deputy Executive Secretary, <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>; the Coordinator, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> Planning Board Assistants.</p>
                <p>Following is a summary of the discussion at the meeting and the main points
                    taken.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of matters unrelated to Trieste.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">8. Redeployment of United States Forces in Trieste</hi>
                        (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1203<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d295fn2">See <ref target="#d236">Document 236</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> said that Deputy
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ARB1">Anderson</persName> has suggested that the
                    U.S. units now in Trieste be sent back to the United States, but that most of
                    the men in those units might be sent to Austria as reinforcements.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> expressed the opinion
                    that the Trieste settlement has strengthened our position in Europe. He felt
                    that we should not set a precedent of making up with U.S. forces for British and
                    French withdrawals from Austria. Moreover, reinforcing Austria with our Trieste
                    forces would be out of spirit with the current European situation. In any case,
                    one additional regiment is not enough to hold Austria, but once it is sent it
                    will be hard to withdraw.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> pointed out that the cost
                    of maintaining U.S. forces in Europe is two to three times the cost of allied
                    forces. Redeployment of Trieste units to Austria would require more dependents
                    in Austria and a bigger investment there, including housing. He understands the
                    military point of view of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, but thinks that the
                    decision as to redeployment of our Trieste forces depends primarily on what the
                    Secretary of State thinks should be done from the political viewpoint.</p>
                <p>At Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>’ request, General
                        <persName corresp="#p_KRB1">Ridgway</persName> said that the use of the
                    Trieste forces, even though small, would give a much better chance of defending
                    the key terrain north of the Italian frontier. There would then be a high
                    probability of retaining the mountain passes in Austria. The Trieste regiment
                    would constitute one-third <pb facs="0610" n="576" xml:id="pg_576"/> of a
                    proposed new U.S. division in Europe, one-third of which is already in
                    Austria.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_KRB1">Ridgway</persName> pointed out that the
                    President has recently approved a new plan for the rotation of U.S. divisions
                    overseas, under which career soldiers will serve about 50% of their time outside
                    the United States. They must have their dependents with them or morale and
                    enlistments will suffer.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> said that he wants the
                    men to have their dependents with them, but doesn’t want to go to Congress for
                    additional housing in Austria.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> thought that, on the
                    military assessment of General <persName corresp="#p_KRB1">Ridgway</persName>,
                    the President is the best judge. In general, however, the problem of ever
                    getting our troops out of Europe grows tremendously difficult. The Trieste
                    troops may be redeployed to the United States without such political
                    difficulties. If they are sent elsewhere, however, we may never get them out.
                    Because the risk of war in Europe does not appear imminent, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> felt that it would be better to get our
                    Trieste forces back to the United States.</p>
                <p>Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> and Humphrey believed
                    that this was a question the President will have to decide on the basis of the
                    military requirement for our Trieste forces in Austria.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Discussed the subject in the light of the Trieste settlement, and
                            requested that the discussion be reported to the President for his
                            information.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> The President, after considering the
                    above-mentioned discussion, directed the Secretary of Defense to proceed with
                    the temporary redeployment of U.S. forces in Trieste to Leghorn, Italy, pursuant
                    to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1203, pending a final decision
                    as to their ultimate redeployment after the President can discuss the matter
                    further with the interested officials.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of a matter unrelated to Trieste.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">S. Everett Gleason</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
