<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-05-06T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-05-06T06:00:00-05:00" n="308" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d308">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">681.82/5–652: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 308<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Greece (<persName corresp="#p_PJE1" type="from">Peurifoy</persName>) to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d308fn1">Repeated to Ankara, Belgrade, Rome for
                                        <persName corresp="#p_UL1">Unger</persName>, and Paris for
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MDII1">MacArthur</persName>.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-05-06T13:00:00+02:00">May 6, 1952—1
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>4758. Fol info supplied by <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss>
                                … today.</p>
                            <p>While Grk-Turkish talks (re Embtel 4712 May 2, 52<note n="2" xml:id="d308fn2">Telegram 4712 reported that a visit by a
                                    Turkish Delegation to Athens, Apr. 23–May 2, had resulted, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, in an agreement to explore
                                    joint defense planning with Yugoslavia. (681.82/5–252)</note>)
                                covered practically every subj of interest to both countries
                                relations with Yugos unquestionably main topic discussed. Grks and
                                Turks agreed that close collaboration with Yugo was indispensable
                                for def effort. . . .</p>
                            <p>Grk Govt for some months has striven to better relations with Yugo
                                and hence has purposely ignored number of disagreeable occurrences.
                                For example, five bearers of Grk passports in Skopolje were recently
                                refused exit permits by Yugos on grounds that they were not Grks but
                                Macedonians. Similar incident occurred in Belgrade. Some of 64 Grk
                                children repatriated from Yugo several weeks ago brought their Yugo
                                school books back with them. Grks shocked discover that map of Yugo
                                in children’s geography books showed Salonika as Yugo territory. In
                                these cases, as in constant references by Yugo radio to
                                Aegean-Macedonia, Grks have been careful to protest informally and
                                in most friendly way possible. Officially, Grk Govt has behaved as
                                if it believed such irritating Yugo acts and pretentions were due to
                                various “broiled-heads” whom <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> obliged to pamper. This incidentally was
                                explanation given Grks by Brit Amb Peake. Grks well pleased that
                                their efforts have resulted in exchange of Mil Attachés with Yugo
                                and consider this major step forward.</p>
                            <p>Yugo Mil Attaché recently called on Gen
                                    <persName>Grigoropoulos</persName> to inform him that he had
                                been authorized by Yugo gen staff to state that in time of war Grks
                                could consider their Yugo frontier as covered and protected by Yugo
                                army. (Up to that moment Grk info was that Yugos had decided to
                                concentrate on waging guerrilla warfare from strongholds in
                                Montenegro–Bosnia–Herzegovina and mountains of Istria.) Yugo Mil Att
                                added that Yugo gen staff did not think mil conversations with Grks
                                immediately necessary since it believed there wld be time for such
                                talks in case of real threat. Grigoropoulos logically maintained
                                talks shld be held immediately. Yugo Att answered he not authorized
                                to discuss such questions but <pb facs="0627" n="593" xml:id="pg_593"/> that in any case initiative for mil talks must
                                come from Grks or Turks. (Same view re initiative given Turk <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> by Yugo Amb Ankara. Both Grks
                                and Turks attribute this to <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName>’s uneasiness over his internal <gloss target="#t_POL1">pol</gloss> sit.) Grigoropoulos asked Mil
                                Attaché to transmit Grk desire for immediate staff talks and to
                                consider this as Grk initiative. General added that he wld
                                appreciate direct Yugo answer to his request.</p>
                            <p>On Apr 28 Averoff told Yugo Min here that Grk Govt highly pleased
                                over Grigoropoulos’ conversation with Mil Att. Averoff added his
                                request for early commencement of staff talks, arguing that Russia
                                might strike with scant warning. In this connection he referred to
                                events of 1941 when Yugo-Grk staff discussions were delayed until
                                eight days before German attack to the great disadvantage of both
                                countries. Yugo Min vaguely agreed but remarked that Grks need not
                                be unduly alarmed as they could be sure that Yugo wld act strongly
                                and quickly in their common interest.…</p>
                            <p>From past conversations, both Grks and Turks feel that <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> wants mil talks but fears to
                                begin them because of his delicate internal sit. In fact, Grks
                                believe <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> may be afraid of
                                some of this own men, hence his insistence on Grks and Turks taking
                                initiative. An indication of this is in months Yugos delayed in
                                selecting Mil Att for Greece after agreeing to send one. This, Grks
                                consider, due to difficulty incurred by <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> in finding man sufficiently trustworthy and
                                able.</p>
                            <p>Grks agreed with Turks to take clear initiative with Yugo in urging
                                mil talks and will assure them that conversations will be “top
                                secret” only between officers and that Grks and Turks will not ask
                                for treaty, only definite understanding. In this connection, Turk
                                    <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> agreed that immediately after
                                his return to Ankara <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> wld
                                tell Yugo Amb of Turk desire for discussions to begin.</p>
                            <p>It has been and will be clearly implied to Yugo that without mil
                                understanding it is very doubtful that Turks will be disposed to
                                place strong forces on Eur front but on contrary if clear
                                understanding can be reached, Turks prepared commit formidable
                                forces in Europe.</p>
                            <p>Grks and Turks agreed that atmosphere helpful to it must be created
                                without delay. With this in mind on May 2, Averoff proposed to Yugo
                                Min Athens that group of six to ten members of Grk Parl make good
                                will visit to Belgrade. After this visit he suggested that group of
                                Yugo MP’s pay return call to Athens. Yugo Min liked idea and
                                promised pass to Belgrade adding that it wld be well for Grk Min
                                (read Averoff) to head group.…</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_PJE1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Peurifoy</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>