<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-29T19:17:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-29T19:17:00-05:00" n="347" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d347">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">760.5/6–2854: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 347<lb/><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                        Yugoslavia</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d347fn1">Drafted
                                    by Marcy; cleared in RA, <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>,
                                        <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_GTI1">GTI</gloss>; and signed for the Secretary by <persName corresp="#p_TRL1">Thurston</persName>. Repeated for
                                    information to Moscow, Athens, and Ankara.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-29T19:17:00-05:00">June 29, 1954—7:17
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1385. You may find it useful in following up <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Popovic</persName> information (Belgrade
                                telegram 1357 to Dept rpted separately to Athens and Ankara<note n="2" xml:id="d347fn2">Telegram 1357, June 28, reported that the
                                    Soviet Ambassador in Yugoslavia, <persName corresp="#p_VVV1">Valkov</persName>, had urgently requested an interview with
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName>, which <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Popović</persName> thought might have
                                    something to do with the Balkan military alliance.
                                    (760.5/6–2854)</note>) to express Department’s appreciation and
                                interest in information re Soviet Ambassador. You might if it seemed
                                useful continue to outline two of considerations which prompt
                                Department’s interest: first of course interest in imminent Soviet
                                moves particularly, in present case, as regards Balkan alliance. We
                                agree recent suggestion that pattern of Soviet action suggests
                                logical next counter-move in Balkans might be offer some form mutual
                                non-aggression pact with Balkan <hi rend="italic">Entente</hi>
                                partners and perhaps also Bulgaria Hungary Rumania and Albania. This
                                would also fit in with recent broader moves in Soviet peace
                                offensive designed divide and weaken Western World. Second
                                consideration to US revolves around recent process of
                                “normalization” between Yugoslavia and USSR/satellites. Yugoslavs
                                cannot be unaware that, while we believe we understand their
                                motives, progress this direction gives rise to questions in minds
                                some supporters our policies towards Yugoslavia and furnishes
                                ammunition to opponents. This connection it is reassuring and useful
                                for Yugoslavs keep us as fully informed as possible as regards
                                actual state “normalization” in order that we may in full confidence
                                meet adverse criticism re our Yugoslav policy which is constantly
                                directed toward us. We therefore appreciative this information from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Popovic</persName> as well as
                                information given our mission in Moscow (Moscow telegram 1510 to
                                Department not repeated all addressees<note n="3" xml:id="d347fn3">Telegram 1510, June 1, reported that the Soviets had harassed
                                    the Yugoslav Ambassador. (601.6861/6–154)</note>) and our
                                mission in Budapest (Budapest telegram 703 to Department, not
                                repeated all addressees<note n="4" xml:id="d347fn4">Telegram 703,
                                    June 24, reported that the Soviets had afforded the Yugoslavs
                                    extremely solicitous treatment at a Budapest Danube committee
                                    meeting earlier in June. (940.5301/6–2454)</note>).</p>
                            <p>You may also, should course of any conversation pursuant to above
                                indicate it would be useful to do so, reiterate to <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Popovic</persName> our basic approval of
                                impetus towards Balkan military alliance. In doing so you will of
                                course maintain usual cautions re timing and <pb facs="0693" n="659" xml:id="pg_659"/> Trieste as well as <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> complications: we have impression this connection
                                that while we conveyed this basic approval to Yugoslavs during your
                                    <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> of May 22 (Belgrade telegram
                                1246 to Department not repeated Moscow<note n="5" xml:id="d347fn5">See <ref target="#d340fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                    340</ref>.</note>) we have not been as forthcoming this regard
                                vis-à-vis Yugoslavs as we have vis-à-vis Greeks and Turks.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>