<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-08-26T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-08-26T09:00:00-05:00" n="358" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d358">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">747C.00/8–2653: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 358<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Greece (<persName corresp="#p_YCW1" type="from">Yost</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d358fn1">Repeated for information to London and
                                Nicosia.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-08-26T16:00:00+02:00">August 26, 1953—4
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>614. Foreign Minister has requested United States assistance in
                            dissuading Archbishop Makarios from bringing Cyprus question before
                            United Nations General Assembly.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SSS1">Stephanopoulos</persName> declared that
                            Marshal <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName>, while he has
                            endeavored hitherto to play down Cyprus issue, is becoming more and more
                            concerned, on basis of recent reports, over situation there which
                                <persName corresp="#p_SSS1">Stephanopoulos</persName> qualified as
                            “oppression” and “slavery”. <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName> feels that only method of dealing with problem
                            which has any possibility of success is direct and secret negotiation
                            with British. He proposes during forthcoming <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> visit to Greece to approach British Foreign
                            Minister on personal man-to-man basis alleging that <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> is unknown even to his own Cabinet. He intends to
                            propose that British immediately grant to Cypriots constitution which
                            would accord them certain rights of self-government and which would be
                            followed in two or three years by plebiscite in which Cypriots would be
                            given a choice between independence, incorporation into Greece or some
                            status within commonwealth. For reasons Foreign Minister did not make
                            completely clear he has some hope British might accept this proposal. He
                            believes, however, that under present circumstances Cypriots would not
                            do so.</p>
                        <p>Some time ago <persName corresp="#p_KAA1">Kyrou</persName> approached
                                <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>, urged him to
                            abandon appeal to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> on grounds that
                            without US support it would merely invite failure and work to profit of
                            Soviets, and confided that Greek Government contemplated high level
                            approach to British. <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>
                            rejected <persName corresp="#p_KAA1">Kyrou</persName>’s plea and has
                            since leaked to Cypriot press intimation that high level conversations
                            are being contemplated, thus jeopardizing prospects of their
                            success.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_SSS1">Stephanopoulos</persName> fears that, if
                                <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> goes ahead with
                            appeal lacking support of Greek Government, he may publicly accuse
                                <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName> of betrayal Cypriots,
                            which would have most serious affect upon position <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName> Government in Greece. On other
                            hand if Greek Government should support appeal, negotiation with British
                            would be impossible and probable failure of appeal would undermine
                            confidence of Greek people in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. This
                            would be particularly unfortunate at time when government is increasing
                            Greek forces in Korea.</p>
                        <pb facs="0711" n="677" xml:id="pg_677"/>
                        <p>He therefore urgently requests that US endeavor to persuade <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> to drop his appeal “for the
                            time being” on the grounds that time is not ripe, that appeal would fail
                            under present circumstances and that Communists in United Nations and in
                            Cyprus would profit from this failure.</p>
                        <p>We would recommend that Department accede to Foreign Minister’s request.
                            Whether or not it is likely one of Soviet bloc might sponsor <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> complaint, it would seem to
                            be in interests of United States as well as of <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName> Government and British that
                            Cyprus question not be raised in any form before United Nations at this
                            time. While we do not share <persName corresp="#p_SSS1">Stephanopoulos</persName> optimism about <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>’s reaction to <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName> proposal, it would still seem
                            that confidential bilateral conversations offer best prospect of
                            progress on this problem. It appears likely that, unless <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> can be restrained, <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName> may feel that his posture as
                            Paladin of Greek nationalism obliges him to take over leadership of this
                            campaign. Certainly there are few issues on which the opposition could
                            cause more embarrassment to government than that of “betrayal of
                            Cyprus”.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister would appreciate prompt response so that <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName> might be informed of our
                            position before he speaks with <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> who arrives in Greece August 30.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_YCW1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Yost</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>