<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 368Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs
                    (Merchant) to the Assistant Secretary of State for United Nations Affairs
                    (Key)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d368</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">368</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-06-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="368"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d368">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">747C.00/6–354</note>
                <head>No. 368<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MLT1" type="from">Merchant</persName>) to the
                        Assistant Secretary of State for United Nations Affairs (<persName
                            corresp="#p_KDM1" type="to">Key</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d368fn1">Attached to the source text is a handwritten note
                        by Popper: “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KDM1">Key</persName>: We expected this
                        kind of answer. It will be helpful to us when we get complaints about how
                        useless or harmful <hi rend="italic">GA</hi> discussion of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Enosis</hi> may be.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-03">June 3,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Cyprus.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I refer to your memorandum of May 11<note n="2" xml:id="d368fn2">Not found in
                        Department of State files.</note> regarding the possibility of referring the
                    Cyprus question to the North Atlantic Council in order to avoid the possible
                    disruptive effects of a discussion of the problem in the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> General Assembly next September.</p>
                <p>We had not, prior to receipt of your memorandum, given consideration to referring
                    this question to the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>. No <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> member has suggested such a move, and
                    furthermore the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> has never before, to my
                    knowledge, been called upon to consider problems of this nature (i.e. a
                    territorial dispute between two of its members). In fact the major emphasis in
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> to date has been upon the military
                    alliance and we have deliberately avoided Council discussion of certain issues
                    (e.g. Trieste) in order to avoid any possible break in the all-important <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> solidarity. Political consultation is an
                    important function of the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>, but matters
                    involved in this consultation procedure are matters of common interest to <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> raised with a view to presenting a unified
                    front to problems facing the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> area as a
                    whole.</p>
                <p>It is true Article 1 of the North Atlantic Treaty states that the parties
                    undertake “to settle any international dispute in which they may be involved by
                    peaceful means in such manner that international peace and security and justice
                    are not endangered. …”<note n="3" xml:id="d368fn3">Ellipsis in the source text.
                        For text, see TIAS No. 1964; 63 Stat. (pt. 2) 2241; or United Nations Treaty
                        Series (UNTS), vol. 34, p. 243.</note> This, however, we look upon as a
                    statement of general principle, intended to reconcile this regional arrangement
                    with obligations assumed under the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                        Charter.<note n="4" xml:id="d368fn4">For text, see Department of State
                        Treaty Series (TS) No. 993, or 59 Stat. (pt. 2) 1031.</note> It does not
                    establish a substitute for the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter and its
                    provisions for settlements of disputes. Neither the <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NAT</gloss> nor any subsequent agreement of the parties establish any
                    machinery for the collective handling of disputes between <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> partners.</p>
                <pb facs="0723" n="689" xml:id="pg_689"/>
                <p>Even if one were to assume the problem was an appropriate one for the <gloss
                        target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>, there still remains the question of
                    advisability. Thus far, there has been no indication that the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Enosis</hi> problem has affected UK–Greek cooperation in <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. We believe, on the other hand, there may be
                    a danger that such cooperation would, in fact, be affected if the <hi
                        rend="italic">Enosis</hi> problem were now to be brought to the <gloss
                        target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>. (Incidentally, I presume you are aware that
                    Cyprus was specifically excepted from the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    area by the terms of the North Atlantic Treaty).<note n="5" xml:id="d368fn5">At
                        this point appears a handwritten note by Popper: “Only from the area in
                        which the obligations of <hi rend="italic">automatic defense</hi> exist—not
                        from area about which there may be consultation.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>It is pertinent, of course, to estimate the probability of accomplishing
                    something worthwhile in the <hi rend="italic">Enosis</hi> case in the event of
                    its being submitted to the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>. First of all,
                    the matter should not be put before the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>
                    without the approval of both parties to the dispute. The UK has refused to
                    discuss the matter bilaterally with Greece. It is reasonable to assume the UK
                    would not approve consideration by the Council if the UK expected the Council to
                    find in favor of Greece. Greece on the other hand might well oppose submission
                    to the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>, on the assumption that the colonial
                    powers in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> would side with the UK. A defeat
                    of Greece, express or implied, on this issue in the <gloss target="#t_NAC1"
                        >NAC</gloss> could not help but make <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    still another target for blame by the Greek people. Both <gloss target="#t_BNA1"
                        >BNA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GTI1">GTI</gloss> agree that neither side
                    is likely to change its position in this dispute without strong pressure from
                    some source. The <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> is not in a position to
                    assert such pressure.</p>
                <p>Probably the most that could be achieved by way of Council action would be a
                    recommendation that the two countries settle the matter bilaterally (which the
                    British would resent) or that Greece drop its claims temporarily in view of the
                    exigencies of the present world situation (which the Greek people would resent).
                    Even if only a statement by Greece followed by a UK statement in the <gloss
                        target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> were considered sufficient, there would be
                    certain difficulties. In order to have assurance that other delegations, for
                    example Turkey, would not also speak and set off a general discussion with risks
                    of dissension within the Council, it would be necessary to contact all
                    delegations in advance and “rig” the discussion. RA doubts the advisability of
                    employing this device, which is rare in the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>,
                    for this purpose.</p>
                <p>In summary, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> is unable to foresee any solution
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Enosis</hi> problem in the North Atlantic Council. On
                    the other hand, we foresee possible damage to <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> solidarity if the dispute should be submitted to the <gloss
                        target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> in an attempt to find a solution or to give <pb
                        facs="0724" n="690" xml:id="pg_690"/> the parties an opportunity to state
                    their respective positions. I feel very strongly that the various strains under
                    which <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is already operating at the present
                    time make it extremely inadvisable to submit a problem such as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Enosis</hi> to the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>I might point out in this connection that reports indicate this problem has been
                    very recently discussed in the Council of Europe. We are waiting official
                    reports from the Consulate at Strasbourg<note n="6" xml:id="d368fn6">Telegram
                        7713 from Strasbourg, Sept. 18, reported that Stamatios Mercouris, a Greek
                        Representative to the Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe,
                        announced in the general political debate the intention to bring up the
                        Cyprus question in the near future. (747C.00/9–1854) No further reports on
                        it from Strasbourg have been found in Department of State files.</note> and
                    will revert to this subject after these reports have been received and
                    examined.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>by WB<lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_MLT1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Livingston Merchant</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
