<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="412" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d412">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">747C.00/12–2354</note>
                        <head>No. 412<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the
                                Deputy Director of the Office of Greek, Turkish, and Iranian Affairs
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_KJC1">Kitchen</persName>)</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d412fn1">Drafted on Dec. 30.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-12-23">December
                                    23, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Call of Greek Ambassador re Cyprus (December 23, 1954, 5:00
                                p.m.)</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>Participants:</head>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MGV1">George V. Melas</persName>, Greek
                                Ambassador</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">John D. Jernegan</persName>,
                                Acting Assistant Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KJC1">Jeffrey C. Kitchen</persName>,
                                Deputy Director, <gloss target="#t_GTI1">GTI</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Ambassador commenced by referring to the Secretary’s letters of July
                            28 to the Greek Foreign Minister<note n="2" xml:id="d412fn2"><ref target="#d375">Document 375</ref>.</note> and November 16 to
                            Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Papagos</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d412fn3"><ref target="#d396">Document 396</ref>.</note> He
                            said these letters showed that the United States was willing to assist
                            in seeking a mutually acceptable solution for the Cyprus problem.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador then became rather emotional and asked why the United
                            States had seen fit to go along with the British as far as <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action on the Cyprus issue was concerned.
                            He recalled the American tradition of freedom and expressed the opinion
                            that our <pb facs="0785" n="751" xml:id="pg_751"/> action in this matter
                            was inconsistent with that tradition. He then adverted to recent
                            conversations with his “Turkish colleague” which led him to believe that
                            the Turkish Government had not acted as a free agent in taking a stand
                            against the Greek resolution but had, in fact, been subjected to great
                            pressure. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGV1">Melas</persName>
                            clearly implied the British Government had put such pressure on the
                            Turks.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MGV1">Melas</persName> inquired rhetorically
                            what the British wanted out of this and what they expected the result
                            could be. He had read in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> that
                            the British were again considering offering the Cypriots a parliament
                            with an appointed majority. This, of course, was completely inadequate
                            and unacceptable. In the House of Commons debate, the Colonial Secretary
                            had said the British position was strengthened by the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> vote. If the British intended only to
                            pursue their old course, it would be a great mistake. They couldn’t have
                            everything their way. He stated with great emotional emphasis that
                            international relations were now governed by a set of accepted standards
                            and practices embodied in the Atlantic Charter, the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter, the Potomac Charter, and similar
                            basic agreements to conduct international relations on a just and legal
                            basis. The Greeks, he asserted, could not be treated as “colonials”—they
                            were neither Zulus nor Sudanese. Although he had received much of his
                            formal training in Britain and was an admirer of their institutions, he
                            was at a loss as to how they could realistically and genuinely maintain
                            the position they had assumed in connection with Cyprus.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName> stated that our
                            position with regard to Cyprus, and the reasons why we had pursued the
                            course which had culminated in our <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            vote in favor of deferring consideration for the time being, had been
                            clearly stated in the Secretary’s communications to the Foreign Minister
                            and Prime Minister. It had also been set forth in discussions in
                            Washington, and by our representatives at the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. There was no need to review the history of the United
                            States position at this juncture. In answer to the Ambassador’s
                            question, one could presume that the strategic position of the island
                            and the matter of prestige had played a considerable part in the
                            formulation of the British position. Regardless of whether prestige was
                            a rational or logical consideration on which to base a position it,
                            nevertheless, was a real factor which could not be discounted in
                            international dealings.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador interrupted, seizing on the question of prestige, and said
                            that in the modern world “prestige is not enough” on which to base a
                            course of action on a matter as important as this. He was afraid the
                            United States gave way to outward form. The British could keep a few
                            battalions of fusiliers on the island and <pb facs="0786" n="752" xml:id="pg_752"/> scatter them around the Middle East from time to
                            time to “protect the oil lines” as occasion demanded, but their
                            usefulness was not comparable to the devoted willingness of some 400,000
                            Greeks on Cyprus to defend that soil as part of their homeland. The
                            Ambassador then suggested the military problems involved should be
                            examined by a team of top military men in order to decide on actual base
                            requirements on the island. There could be no doubt that Greece would
                            make the bases available. Greece was on the allied side. They had no
                            Bevan; sent no goods to Red China. Could they be considered less
                            reliable? The United States apparently considered its arrangements on
                            Crete satisfactory, and the Ambassador regarded the United States Sixth
                            Fleet as more of a factor in area defense than “the island” as such.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName> said that while much
                            of what the Ambassador had said was logical, yet he believed one could
                            safely assert prestige constituted approximately 90% of the British
                            position.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador interjected that, with all due respect, the United States
                            should not be “entangled” with this. The Cypriots had all the
                            prerequisites to be free—and no valid reason for not being free. He
                            referred to the recent regrettable “riots” in Athens and Salonika. To be
                            candid, he was distressed, but not astonished. Greece was a peninsula of
                            eroding rocks whose economy had been resuscitated and was now kept going
                            by United States assistance. Although Greece had been a poor country for
                            400 years, her one great contribution had been her love of liberty and
                            her defense of freedom. He reiterated that in modern circumstances
                            prestige and the British concern for “position” was insufficient in face
                            of the overwhelming facts and reasonableness of the proposition that
                            Cyprus should be a part of Greece. He begged the United States to
                            consider not only its history, but the negative effect on its influence
                            which would result from its appearing to defend colonialism. A colleague
                            in the Greek Foreign Service, who had recently written to him after a
                            trip to Southeast Asia, expressed great concern because in that area the
                            United States had been successfully labeled by the communists as a
                            defender of the colonial system and a protector of the colonial powers.
                            The implications in connection with United States world leadership were
                            very great indeed and should be weighed carefully by the United States
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName> replied that all
                            factors had been taken into account in determining the United States
                            position. It was not true that on the Cyprus question the United States
                            was simply defending a colonial position. As we had stated in our
                            communications to the Greeks, our overriding concern was that there
                            should not be an open split between our friends and allies in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. Such a debate at this juncture could not
                            hope to produce a beneficial result. It <pb facs="0787" n="753" xml:id="pg_753"/> was appropriate for the Greek Government to bring
                            to our attention its concern in relation to future developments. We
                            intend to seek ways for a satisfactory settlement. What we can
                            accomplish is another matter. He urged the Greeks not to draw gloomy
                            conclusions from the speech of the Colonial Secretary.<note n="4" xml:id="d412fn4">Not further identified.</note> From his experience
                            in Tunisia he was aware that parliamentary speeches were frequently
                            intended primarily for home consumption and contrasted past statements
                            in the French Assembly to recent favorable developments in Tunisia. With
                            a release of pressure, the Colonial Secretary might be more forthcoming.
                            He strongly urged an attempt at <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi>
                            between the British and Cypriot leaders. The latter should talk with the
                            British even if the initial British proposal is not regarded as good
                            enough. A refusal on the part of the Cypriots even to discuss would be
                            regrettable. The history of other British colonies showed they were not
                            unbending. He differed with the Ambassador in that the United States did
                            not regard it as its responsibility to see to it that all nations lived
                            up to all principles of all charters. It was certainly desirable that
                            they do so, but as a practical matter the United States could not be
                            expected to execute a universal policing responsibility. However, this
                            Government continued to be concerned that a satisfactory solution be
                            worked out between the parties at interest, and we would continue to
                            seek one.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador apologized for calling “on Christmas Eve” but said that
                            his Government and he personally were concerned that the United States
                            should continue to be conscious of the need for a reasonable
                            settlement.</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>