<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 413Statement of Policy Proposed by the National Security Council</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d413</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">413</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046227"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cultural exchange</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="413"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d413">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.57A/2–152</note>
                <head>No. 413<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Statement of Policy Proposed by the National Security
                        Council</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d413fn1">Transmitted as an enclosure to operations
                        memorandum 19 to Helsinki, Feb. 1. For another extract of <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 121, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v06p2#pg_1758">vol. VI, Part 2, p. 1758</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">[Extracts]</note>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 121</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-01-08">January 8,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Position of the United States With Respect to
                        Scandinavia and Finland</hi>
                </p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>With regard to Finland, it is in our interest that she maintain her independence.
                    Although the Finns value highly their independence and are intensely
                    anti-Soviet, this country’s freedom of action in its foreign relations is
                    drastically curtailed by its proximity to Soviet power and by various treaty
                    obligations which Finland has been forced to undertake. The key to U.S. policy
                    is to avoid any steps which would threaten the delicate balance of
                    Finnish-Soviet relations and call forth drastic Soviet measures inimical to
                    Finnish independence.</p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Attachment]</note>
                    <head>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Staff Study on the Position of the United States With
                            Respect to Scandinavia and Finland</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Our relations with Finland differ from those with Scandinavia because of
                        Finland’s special relationship to the Soviet Union. Finland <pb facs="0790"
                            n="756" xml:id="pg_756"/> is not a Soviet satellite. It is a
                        constitutional democracy with unrestricted internal sovereignty wherein the
                        democratic freedoms are guaranteed by law. Although there is a strong
                        Communist Party in Finland, it has had no positions in the Government since
                        1948, and there does not now appear to be a likelihood of the Party’s taking
                        over Finland by internal coup. Nevertheless, Finland’s freedom of action in
                        its foreign relations is drastically curtailed by its proximity to Soviet
                        power and by various treaty obligations which Finland was forced to
                        undertake after the war. Our basic objective is therefore limited to the
                        maintenance of Finland as an independent and democratic state; because it
                        would be extremely dangerous to Finland, it is not in our interest to make
                        any attempt to incorporate Finland into a Western bloc.</p>
                    <p>In view of their position and Soviet sensibilities, the Finns must be very
                        circumspect in their dealings with the West, even though the overwhelming
                        majority of Finns, as in the past, identify themselves with the West. By the
                        same token, we must be careful not to take any action which would disturb
                        Finland’s relations with the USSR. These delicate relations preclude
                        Finland’s participation in the <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>, the
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss>, and make impossible our extending
                        any military assistance or the development of Finnish defense. This
                        situation has not, however, prevented our giving moral support through
                        informational and cultural exchange, or economic support through carefully
                        allotted credits and the maintenance of Finland’s traditional pattern of
                        trade predominantly with Western Europe and the Western Hemisphere, all of
                        which we have been or are seeking to do.</p>
                    <p>We have, however, a particular problem arising from Finland’s trade with the
                        USSR and the Soviet bloc. Though decreasing, this trade is expected to
                        constitute 20–25% of the Finnish total during the next few years. Some of
                        the items Finland traditionally supplies to the Soviets include scarce or
                        strategic materials, for which Finland receives in return other strategic
                        commodities. While it would appear that both for political and economic
                        reasons there is no immediate possibility for Finland to eliminate or
                        substantially reduce the export of strategic items in its trade with the
                        Soviet bloc without serious consequences, we should continue to impress the
                        Finns with our concern over this trade. However, although a careful
                        case-by-case review should be made in order to minimize any contribution
                        which U.S. exports to Finland might make to the Eastward flow of strategic
                        items from Finland, the United States should continue to export available
                        materials which are necessary to Finland’s economy.</p>
                    <p>Unofficial Soviet sources have expressed the thesis that the Baltic is a
                        closed sea. However, there has been no indication that <pb facs="0791"
                            n="757" xml:id="pg_757"/> the Soviet Government proposes to promulgate
                        this as an official doctrine. A closure would be unacceptable to the United
                        States, to the riparian states (Finland, Sweden, Denmark and Germany), and
                        to other Western states which have important interests in the area. Recent
                        Soviet attempts to extend territorial waters in the Baltic have been
                        protested by Sweden and Denmark and these two countries continue their study
                        of means to resist this encroachment. Sweden’s traditional neutrality policy
                        is not reflected in any tendency on the part of the Swedish Government or
                        public opinion to accept Soviet encroachments in the Baltic; on the
                        contrary, there has been a strong Swedish reaction against Soviet attempts
                        to extend its territorial waters, and it is regarded as a very healthy
                        exercise that Sweden continue to wrestle with this problem.</p>
                    <p>A unilateral declaration by the USSR would not in itself effect the closure
                        of the Baltic. However, such a declaration coupled with the use of or
                        display of force aimed at enforcing the declaration could result in closure
                        of the Baltic. If these steps involve military action against merchant or
                        public vessels or aircraft of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss>
                        powers in or over the Baltic, or armed violation of Danish sovereignty or UK
                        occupational jurisdiction in Germany, the provision of Article V of the
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> could be invoked.</p>
                    <p>In our desire to support Finnish independence by the limited means available,
                        we should avoid any steps which would threaten the delicate balance of
                        Finnish-Soviet relations and call forth drastic Soviet measures inimical to
                        Finnish independence. In this connection, so long as Finnish exports of
                        strategic items to the Soviets remain limited, we should in so far as supply
                        considerations permit, and after careful scrutiny on a case-by-case basis,
                        refrain from restrictive action on any exports whose denial would weaken the
                        Finnish economy or which might prompt Soviet action endangering Finland’s
                        independence.</p>
                    <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
