<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="416" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d416">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860E.00/12–1753</note>
                        <head>No. 416<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the
                                Director of the Office of British Commonwealth and Northern European
                                Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RGH1">Raynor</persName>)</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-12-17">December
                                    17, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Finnish Economic Situation—Effectiveness of Possible American Aid
                                as a Solution Thereto.</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>Participants:</head>
                            <item>Minister <persName corresp="#p_NJA1">Nykopp</persName>, Legation
                                of Finland</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RGH1">H. Raynor</persName>, Director,
                                    <gloss target="#t_BNA1">BNA</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Minister <persName corresp="#p_NJA1">Nykopp</persName> called this
                            afternoon at my request. I told him in view of the continuing concern
                            which a number of us in Washington felt with respect to the Finnish
                            economic situation from the point of our view of our concern that
                            Finland remain independent, I wanted, with his permission, to continue,
                            on a personal and informal basis, the conversation which I had had at
                            lunch at his home a month or so back with him and Mr.
                                <persName>Tuomioja</persName>, then the Governor of the Bank of
                            Finland and now Prime Minister of Finland.<note n="1" xml:id="d416fn1">No further record of this luncheon has been found in Department of
                                State files.</note></p>
                        <p>I referred in general to the views expressed by Mr.
                                <persName>Tuomioja</persName> and by him at the lunch and wondered
                            in the light of developments if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NJA1">Nykopp</persName> in general still subscribed to such views. I said
                            a further reason for suggesting this talk was the publication recently
                            of certain stories in our press with respect to the Finnish economic
                            situation which had been rather alarmist in character.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NJA1">Nykopp</persName> expressed the view that
                            while the situation has been and remains serious that in some respect it
                            is not quite so bad now as it was six months or so previously. This
                            improvement is due to a slight firming of prices and some increase of
                            British demand for certain forest products. Also the price of raw timber
                            has declined. The combination of the decline in the price of raw timber
                            and the slight increase in the price of the processed product for export
                            has <pb facs="0804" n="770" xml:id="pg_770"/> resulted in a favorable
                            differential totalling approximately $5.00 per ton has gone a
                            considerable distance to bridge the gap between costs and sales but has
                            not yet gone far enough to put the business back on a profitable basis.
                            He stressed, however, these changes in terms of trade have been in the
                            right direction.</p>
                        <p>I queried him rather hard on his feeling as to the magnitude of the
                            unemployment problem this winter. He seemed to feel that the present
                            level did not bear out the pessimistic prediction that unemployment
                            would be the highest on record. He said as to what the peak would be
                            could not yet be predicted because it would depend on whether the owners
                            of the raw material would begin to sell or not. He said the raw material
                            owners and processers were still playing poker. He felt, however, that
                            inventories of the processers were somewhat below normal and should the
                            increase in demand, say from the British continue, that fairly soon they
                            might feel it necessary to buy. From the other side of the picture, many
                            of the owners of the raw material might begin to run short of money and
                            be more willing to sell. While avoiding any definite prediction, on
                            balance, I gathered the impression that he thought the shutdowns and the
                            consequent unemployment, and this is the area where unemployment would
                            be the greatest, might not be as severe as predicted. I asked him if he
                            was apprehensive as to unfavorable effects of unemployment on the
                            elections now scheduled for March. He did not seem unduly disturbed
                            saying that a majority of those thrown out of work would be given public
                            works jobs by the State. He also said that when the labor force was
                            reduced that the first people to be let out were usually the Communists.
                            He even ventured to say that this might have the effect of some of the
                            Communists wondering if being a Communist paid and might, therefore,
                            vote another way. He thought the workers who were non-Communist would be
                            well enough taken care of either by not losing their jobs or receiving
                            assistance from the State so that there was little danger of a swing on
                            their part to the Communists.</p>
                        <p>I reviewed with him the ground I had covered at the lunch meeting with
                                <persName>Tuomioja</persName>. He said he continued to feel the
                            problem was one of costs and not one which was susceptible to a cure by
                            dollars or for that matter by any foreign exchange considerations. He
                            confirmed that if the Deutsche-Mark loan goes through from the
                            International Bank that the process of modernizing equipment in the
                            forest products industry would be largely taken care of. He said some
                            consideration had been given to requesting a loan in an amount of
                            approximately $3 million for road building which would be highly
                            desirable for the long-range future and even might be necessary in from
                            three to five years should there be a broad increase in the demand for
                            Finnish forest products. He said this <pb facs="0805" n="771" xml:id="pg_771"/> transportation question was not presently an
                            element in cost but could become one should there be a considerably
                            higher demand. He said the Government had decided to defer making this
                            application as they did not want to increase loan obligations except
                            upon a basis of real need.</p>
                        <p>I asked him about the proposal of Mr. <persName>Kahma</persName>, made
                            last summer, with respect to establishing local village industries in
                            the North. He said this question was being worked upon and Finland is
                            now trying to translate it into practical terms and that local capital
                            for the enterprise would be raised. Then a canvass would have to be made
                            as to what equipment from non-Finnish sources would be required. He
                            personally was of the opinion that most of this equipment could be found
                            in Europe and paid for in European currency although he did not
                            completely rule out the possibility that some dollar equipment would be
                            necessary. He did not seem to think, however, that the dollar component
                            of the program would be substantial. In answer to my direct inquiry as
                            to what Finland’s greatest economic need was at the present, he said it
                            was to be able to sell more to the West. He thought the most useful
                            thing the U.S. could do would be to find ways of increasing purchases
                            either privately or publicly in Finland. In this connection he referred
                            to the off-shore procurement problem in terms similar to those he had
                            used in speaking to Waugh the other day.<note n="2" xml:id="d416fn2">The
                                conversation with Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs
                                Waugh has not been further identified.</note>… He said, however, he
                            thought the yards were full in ’54 but could take on such orders in
                            ’55.</p>
                        <p>He also referred to the possibility of working out third country
                            arrangements, perhaps under Section 550. He said, for instance, the
                            Finns liked Virginia tobacco and American cotton. Could these products
                            be made available for sale to the Finns for local Finnish currency under
                            Section 550, the currency then being used to buy Finnish articles needed
                            for aid programs in third countries. He said, for instance, Israel
                            needed building materials. Could the local currency proceeds on the
                            tobacco deal be spent by the U.S. in Finland for building material for
                            Israel. He said this idea was being discussed with <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> by private interests at the moment. He
                            mentioned in this connection the name Culbertson. It seemed likely
                            although not certain from what he said he was referring to Col. William
                            Culbertson. I said that while I couldn’t say what the technicalities
                            might be that I thought plans of this type should be given thorough
                            consideration and that I would see that the one he had just mentioned
                            would be looked into. In this part of the discussion he referred to but
                            did not press the idea he had advanced several <pb facs="0806" n="772" xml:id="pg_772"/> months ago of a loan with Western Germany on
                            wheat. On the subject of off-shore procurement he thought that prefabs
                            which might be needed for military construction in Germany or elsewhere
                            might be a promising avenue.</p>
                        <p>I asked him if a shortage of dollars or other Western currency were a
                            contributing factor on import restrictions to an extent of resulting
                            shortages being an important cause of the present high price level. He
                            did not think so saying that despite import restrictions shortages
                            really did not exist and that coffee was the only product now rationed
                            in Finland. He had previously told me that the sterling shortage had
                            resulted in wool purchases being curtailed to a point where he feared
                            processing operations in Finland would have to be reduced in that
                            industry thus contributing to unemployment. He indicated in today’s
                            conversation that a somewhat better sterling position now prevailing was
                            making it possible to purchase sufficient wool so that he did not now
                            look for shutdowns in this industry.</p>
                        <p>Making it entirely clear that I was talking on a hypothetical basis and
                            that he should not interpret my remarks to mean that we could do one
                            thing or another, although I made it very clear that we were very
                            sympathetic to their problems, I asked if in his opinion his Government
                            would feel it were politically feasible to accept American economic
                            assistance on a grant basis. He pondered this for a moment and then
                            replied, stressing that he was talking personally, that in his judgment
                            the Government could not accept grant aid. He said what he thought could
                            be accepted would be credits at a very low interest rate with the
                            beginning of amortization payments put off for say 20 years. He thought
                            it would be necessary, if anything like this were to be done for it to
                            be “in some such manner as I have just indicated”.</p>
                        <p>I then asked if he thought politically it would be possible for Finland
                            to join the <gloss target="#t_EPU1">EPU</gloss> or the <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss>. He said while he thought it would be
                            necessary for his Government to study very carefully just what the
                            participation of the U.S. now was in these agencies that he thought it
                            might be possible provided the U.S. was not now contributing financially
                            to these organizations. He volunteered, however, the statement it would
                            be disastrous for Finland to take such a step at this time or in fact
                            until their general price level had been stabilized on a lower basis. He
                            said now with high Finnish prices under the trade liberalization schemes
                            everybody would be concentrating on selling in Finland and under such
                            circumstances it would be bad for Finland to join as they would be
                            buying at high prices and selling at low prices and thus possibly
                            running into serious debt.</p>
                        <pb facs="0807" n="773" xml:id="pg_773"/>
                        <p>The Minister seemed rather skeptical of the Russian loan offer. He said
                            while he had been in charge of these matters and again for political
                            purposes the Russians had on one previous occasion offered a loan, that
                            time in the amount of $5 million, the repayment date had turned out to
                            be one year. The Finns, therefore, feeling they could not refuse this
                            generosity had accepted the loan but had immediately placed it aside for
                            repayment purposes and had repaid it as soon as they could politely do
                            so. In other words, it had been no benefit whatsoever to Finland. He
                            said, however, that he could see that it might be useful for Finland to
                            accept another loan if this meant they could get a percentage of their
                            exports paid for in Western currency. He said he understood the offer
                            had been 10% and this might mean the equivalent of $12 million per year.
                            He in no sense challenged the implications of my observations to the
                            effect that entering into a loan arrangement was at best a dubious and
                            perhaps a dangerous step for Finland to take.</p>
                        <p>Finally, I referred to the question of devaluation saying I had not asked
                            Mr. <persName>Tuomioja</persName> about this as it was always a delicate
                            subject to raise. The Minister said that he was under what amounted to
                            standing instructions to deny in the most vigorous terms that
                            devaluation was a possibility. He added personally, however, that he
                            knew it was a matter which had been studied by the Bank of Finland and
                            other Finnish authorities and no doubt would continue to be so studied.
                            The Minister said as he understood the situation it was something the
                            Finnish authorities would regard as a last resort measure should the
                            situation be serious enough to make it necessary. He felt the Finns
                            would want to try other measures such as political steps to reduce costs
                            before coming to this.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RGH1">G.H.R.</persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>