<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 497Memorandum of Conversation, by the Ambassador-designate to the Soviet
                    Union (Kennan)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d497</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">497</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-04-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-04-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-04-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-04-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="497"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d497">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.61/4–352</note>
                <head>No. 497<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the <gloss type="from"
                            >Ambassador-designate</gloss> to the Soviet Union (<persName
                            corresp="#p_KGF1" type="to">Kennan</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d497fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_DRH1"
                            >Davis</persName> and read, corrected, and approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan. Kennan</persName>’s diary (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Memoirs, 1950–1963</hi>, pp. 107–108) contains a brief description of
                        this luncheon meeting.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1952-04-03">April 3,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Luncheon Conversation at the Soviet Embassy</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PAS1">Panyushkin</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Boris I. Karavaev</persName>, Counselor of the Soviet
                        Embassy</item>
                    <item>Ambassador-designate <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">George F.
                            Kennan</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DRH1">Richard H. Davis</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I telephoned Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PAS1">Panyushkin</persName> on
                    April 2 to invite him to have luncheon with me and one other officer of the
                    Department and was met by his counter-invitation that I have luncheon with him
                    today at 1 p.m. at the Soviet Embassy, which I accepted.</p>
                <p>We were met at the door of the Embassy by Mr. <persName>Myshkov</persName> and
                    escorted upstairs to the large reception room facing 16th Street where
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PAS1">Panyushkin</persName> and Mr.
                        <persName>Karavaev</persName> were waiting to greet us. During the five
                    minute conversation before luncheon over a cocktail seated in the reception
                    room, our conversation was devoted to climate and meteorological conditions.</p>
                <p>At the luncheon table at which there were only the four of us, served by a single
                    maid, the conversation took a more natural, practical turn. I had the impression
                    during the course of our conversation at the table and afterwards over coffee
                    that the Soviet Ambassador and his Counselor were pleased at the opportunity to
                    receive us in this informal fashion and to talk in general about things without
                    undue emphasis on political differences. I purposely avoided contradicting or
                    entering into a debate with them upon some of the ideas they expressed.</p>
                <p>Possibly the chief points of interest in our two hours’ conversation, conducted
                    entirely in Russian, were these: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>The Ambassador spoke of the shallowness of understanding in this
                                country which was prevalent not only among average Americans but
                                even among those intellectually above average with relation to the
                                Soviet Union and its purposes. Both he and Mr.
                                    <persName>Karavaev</persName> told stories of how their
                                countrymen when identifying themselves as Russians had encountered
                                on the part of Americans incredulity and expressions of “Impossible,
                                where is your beard?” or <pb facs="1003" n="969" xml:id="pg_969"/>
                                “Why aren’t you black?” The Ambassador stated with obvious feeling
                                that he had heard intelligent Americans refer to his countrymen as
                                “barbarians.”</p>
                            <p>This line of thought among other things which the Ambassador said
                                revealed that they have become aware and sensitive to those
                                reflections of present tensions in the relations between our two
                                countries, which they have personally encountered.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>The Ambassador talked at some length about “correspondents” and
                            “journalists”, the former being defined as those who wrote down without
                            understanding that which they heard and saw and the “journalists” being
                            described as those who observed well and understood the implications
                            behind facts and events which they were able to interpret for their
                            readers. He then went on to refer to <persName>Walter
                            Lippman</persName>, <persName>Arthur Krock</persName> and James Reston,
                            about whom he seemed to have a respectful opinion.
                                <persName>Lippman</persName>, he thought, was experienced and an
                            independent thinker. He was particularly curious about Reston, whose
                            position and qualifications apparently baffled him.</item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>The Soviet Ambassador then brought up the recent replies made by
                                    <persName>J. V. Stalin</persName> to the questions of certain
                                U.S. newspaper editors<note n="2" xml:id="d497fn2">On Mar. 31,
                                        <persName>Stalin</persName> replied to four questions
                                    submitted to him by a group of American editors. In his answers,
                                        <persName>Stalin</persName> indicated that he thought war
                                    was no closer than it had been two or three years earlier and
                                    that a meeting of the heads of the great powers might be
                                    helpful. For text of the questions and answers. see <hi
                                        rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, Apr. 2, 1952; <hi
                                        rend="italic">Documents on American Foreign Relations,
                                        1952</hi>, p. 103; or <hi rend="italic">Documents</hi>
                                    (R.I.I.A.) for 1952, p. 224.</note> and complained that
                                    <persName>Stalin</persName>’s statements were so often brushed
                                aside as mere propaganda in this country. He referred in a serious
                                tone to <persName>Stalin</persName>’s statements as “most
                                authoritative—more so than those of the Ministry of Foreign
                                Affairs.”</p>
                            <p>It may be that, in view of <persName>Lippman</persName>’s recent
                                articles criticizing our reply to the Soviet note on Germany and
                                    <persName>Stalin</persName>’s reply to the effect that he
                                considered this an opportune time for the unification of Germany,
                                the Ambassador was attempting indirectly to draw me out on our
                                attitude toward the German question. He did not press the matter
                                when he failed to obtain any reaction.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>At about this time, Mr. <persName>Karavaev</persName> broke in to
                            remark that there were not any questions which the Soviet Government was
                            not willing to discuss wth us, that the Soviet Government, as it had
                            made clear by repeated statements, was willing at any time to enter upon
                            discussions leading to a settlement of any existing problems.</item>
                        <label>5)</label>
                        <item>The Ambassador spoke of his service in China with evident nostalgia
                            and with warm feeling for the great qualities of the Chinese people. He
                            revealed that his twenty year old son had always had an inclination
                            toward the study of the Chinese and other Siberian languages and was now
                            studying at the Oriental Institute in Moscow. His other son, fifteen
                            years old, had always had, on the other hand, a penchant for mechanical
                            things although still in the 8th year class.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In our conversation I tried and, I think, succeeded in conveying the impression
                    that I had no special proposals to make after my <pb facs="1004" n="970"
                        xml:id="pg_970"/> arrival in Moscow; that the problems between our countries
                    were not easy nor quick of solution and that I saw only a long road ahead if we
                    were to improve the present atmosphere.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Ambassador obviously had had no time to receive instructions from
                    Moscow as to the conduct of his conversation at our luncheon, and it is perhaps
                    for this reason that he himself did not attempt to turn it into a political
                    debate. Nevertheless, I thought there was a note of relief and even genuine
                    cordiality on the part of our Soviet hosts that they could talk with us in this
                    free and informal way. Perhaps it was also noteworthy that our hosts, while
                    pleasant and hospitable, made no effort to ply us with drinks or turn the
                    occasion into one of false conviviality.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
