<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-06-19T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-06-19T12:00:00-05:00" n="511" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d511">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.61/6–1952: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 511<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_KGF1" type="from">Kennan</persName>) to
                                the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-06-19T20:00:00+03:00">June 19, 1952—8
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2044. I called on Vishinsky as scheduled and had conversation with him
                            which, to my mind was extremely interesting and somewhat encouraging. It
                            was my first discussion of any political subject with any Sov official
                            since my arrival here, and I think my long silence and restraint lent a
                            desirable emphasis to it in Sov eyes. He received me courteously but
                            quite seriously, there was no banter or small talk. Since he did not
                            bring up the question of our relations I did so myself, referred to the
                            Secretary’s talk with <persName corresp="#p_PAS1">Panyushkin</persName>,
                            said I would not repeat the Secretary’s remarks but could say that they
                            reflected such reports as I had been obliged to my great regret to
                            render about the violent anti-American propaganda with which I had been
                            greeted on my arrival. I emphasized to him how painful this had been to
                            me and how difficult it had been for me to discover any reasons for all
                            this which could conceivably be compatible with a desire on the Sov
                            inside to improve Sov-Amer relations. I said that I had worked hard up
                            to this time and had done all in my power to bring about an improvement
                            in the atmosphere surrounding the relations between the two governments,
                            that I was not a pessimist and would be glad to continue to use my
                            influence in this direction, but what I had seen here since my arrival
                            really caused me to question whether there was any point in such effort,
                            since it could not be entirely one-way street.</p>
                        <p>I was less surprised by the content of Vishinsky’s reply than by its
                            terms and tone of utterance. He spoke quietly and reasonably, with no
                            trace of vehemence or unfriendliness, and in a manner quite different
                            from that which he uses when he is reiterating propaganda formulas
                            designed for the public record, or when he feels under any pressure from
                            higher authority to be aggressive and unpleasant. He referred
                            immediately to statements made on our side of the water, some of them,
                            he said, by high-placed persons, and also to the Grew diary,<note n="1" xml:id="d511fn1">See <ref target="#d499fn5">footnote 5, Document
                                    499</ref>.</note> the press attacks, etc. He made particular
                            reference, in what seemed to me to be really plaintive terms, to the
                            Gubichev case.<note n="2" xml:id="d511fn2">Valentin Alekseyevich
                                Gubichev, a Soviet citizen and former member of the Soviet
                                Delegation to the United Nations subsequently serving as an engineer
                                with the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N</gloss>. Secretariat in New
                                York, was arrested in New York on Mar. 5, 1949, for receiving stolen
                                government information from Judith Coplon, an employee of the
                                Department of Justice. Gubichev was indicted for having violated the
                                espionage laws of the United States, tried, and convicted. A long
                                prison sentence handed down by the trial judge on Mar. 9, 1950, was
                                suspended on condition that Gubichev be deported from the United
                                States, which in fact occurred on Mar. 20, 1950. For documentation
                                on the Gubichev case, see <ref target="frus1949v05#pg_776"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 776</ref>–<ref target="frus1949v05#pg_805">805</ref>.</note> He did not
                            specifically mention <pb facs="1046" n="1012" xml:id="pg_1012"/>
                                Katyn,<note n="3" xml:id="d511fn3">See <ref target="#d499fn3">footnote 3, Document 499</ref>.</note> but I am certain that it
                            was this he had most prominently in mind. He dwelt at some lengths on
                            these matters and left no doubt about their being the Sov Govt’s
                            official reason for the propaganda.</p>
                        <p>I did not wish to be drawn into an argument with him about propaganda
                            exchanges and incidents of the past, and terminated the conversation by
                            saying to him that I deeply hoped that the anti-Amer propaganda might
                            cease at once and that so far as such things as the Grew diary were
                            concerned, I would ask that we be judged by the present and not by the
                            past. In parting he took occasion, to my surprise, to indicate that the
                            Sov Govt had high regard for my person and that none of the
                            unpleasantness had any reference to myself.</p>
                        <p>By way of comment on the above I would say only this. The past has taught
                            us the need for greatest wariness in dealing with the Sovs precisely in
                            their better moments. Eager optimism is the enemy of all progress at
                            such junctures. We know that when we run across reactions and motives on
                            their part which are at least understandable in normal human terms, they
                            are usually intermingled with other impulses of which this cannot be
                            said. What Vishinsky said to me of the background of the anti-Amer
                            campaign is only part of the story, and the misunderstandings to which
                            his statement points are extremely serious ones, since they have roots
                            in the stubborn Sov refusal to understand the nature of Amer public
                            opinion and its channels of expression. Nevertheless, I have the feeling
                            that this talk was useful and encouraging. It indicated a certain
                            concern for my opinion, and represented at least something like an
                            effort on his part to present an explanation for the campaign—and that
                            in itself was not something to be taken for granted. If nothing occurs
                            in major Amer utterances to rock the boat in these coming days, I think
                            we may soon see a relative decline in the amount of anti-Amer material
                            appearing here. This does not mean that I think there is possibility
                            that the tone of the Sov press will shortly become friendly to us. I
                            merely think it possible, as a result of the Secretary’s helpful
                            statements to <persName corresp="#p_PAS1">Panyushkin</persName><note n="4" xml:id="d511fn4">Reference is presumably to the conversation
                                between the Secretary of State and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PAS1">Panyushkin</persName> on June 6; see <ref target="#d506">Document 506</ref>.</note> and in <pb facs="1047" n="1013" xml:id="pg_1013"/> the light of this talk with Vishinsky,
                            that the abnormal pitch of anti-Americanism may now wane fairly rapidly,
                            if no new factor appears to exacerbate the situation. Its possibilities
                            must have been fairly well exhausted by this time, in any case.</p>
                        <p>In light of above, I hope no major statement or move will now be made by
                            us until I have chance to discuss matter with Secretary in London next
                                week.<note n="5" xml:id="d511fn5">In telegram 1910, May 31,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan</persName> informed the
                                Department that he was planning to visit Berlin and Bonn in late
                                June for consultation with authorities in Germany and to assist his
                                family in travel to Moscow. <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan</persName> planned to leave Moscow on June 21 and return
                                to Moscow on June 30. (123 <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan,
                                    George F.</persName>) In an exchange of messages with and at the
                                suggestion of Secretary <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan</persName> broadened his itinerary to include a visit to
                                London on June 27 for luncheon with <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName>. (123 <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan,
                                    George F.</persName>)</note> For what I feel to be good reason,
                            I have not told local press about this meeting with Vishinsky and hope
                            that news of it may be closely held in Washington.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KGF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Kennan</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>