<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="579" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d579">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Microfilm telegram files, “Moscow <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 53”: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 579<lb/><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the Soviet
                                    Union</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d579fn1">Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SWJJ1">Stoessel</persName> (<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>)
                                and approved for transmission by <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName> (<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>).</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-07">April 7, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>754. For <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d579fn2"><persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> left
                                Washington on Apr. 4 and arrived in Moscow on Apr. 11 when he
                                assumed charge of the Embassy.</note> In presenting credentials<note n="3" xml:id="d579fn3"><persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName>
                                presented his credentials to <persName corresp="#p_V1">Voroshilov</persName> on Apr. 20; see <ref target="#d584">Document 584</ref>.</note> you should use following text of
                            remarks: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Your Excellency: I have the honor to present the letters
                                    accrediting me as Ambassador of the United States of America to
                                    the Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics and to
                                    hand you the letters of recall of my predecessor.</p>
                                <p>In its foreign policy the Government of the United States is
                                    consistently guided by a desire to contribute to the cause of
                                    peace in the world, to enhance respect for international
                                    obligations and to develop friendly relations between all
                                    nations. In conformity with these principles it is the sincere
                                    hope of my Government that all questions requiring adjustment
                                    between our two Governments may be settled amicably. I shall
                                    actively work for the achievement of these aims and I hope that
                                    my efforts will meet with the collaboration of the officials of
                                    the Soviet Government.</p>
                                <p>As Ambassador of the United States I shall endeavor faithfully to
                                    represent the hopes and aspirations of the American people, who
                                    entertain feelings of sincere friendship for the peoples of the
                                    Union of Soviet Socialist Republics.”<note n="4" xml:id="d579fn4">In telegram 1500 from Moscow, Apr. 20,
                                            <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> indicated
                                        his intention to make available to American correspondents
                                        in Moscow this text of his remarks. (Microfilm telegram
                                        files, “Moscow <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    53”)</note></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>