<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 586Special Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d586</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">586</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recZ240W8VG9BDJBE" type="compound-subject"
                        category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        >Soviet foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec589358498c26b52" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="austrian-peace-treaty">Austrian peace treaty</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec_korean_war" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="korean-war" subject="korean-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073119" lcsh-match="exact">Korean War</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="586"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d586">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss>
                    files</note>
                <head>No. 586<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Special Estimate</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d586fn1">
                        <p>Regarding Special Estimates, see <ref target="#d552fn1">footnote 1,
                                Document 552</ref>.</p>
                        <p>According to a note on the cover sheet of this SE, the intelligence
                            organizations of the Departments of State, the Navy, the Air Force, the
                            Army, and the Joint Staff participated in the preparation of this
                            estimate. The note further records that the Intelligence Advisory
                            Committee concurred in this estimate on Apr. 21.</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>SE–42</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-24">24 April
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Current Communist Tactics</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>To estimate the significance of current Communist “peace” tactics.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Estimate</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Since the announcement of the death of <persName corresp="#p_S1"
                            >Stalin</persName> the various gestures and statements by the Soviet and
                        Chinese Communist Governments have followed so swiftly upon each other, and
                        the evidence concerning relations among the men in the Kremlin has remained
                        so obscure, that any estimate of the situation is apt to be quickly
                        outdated. This estimate is a brief presentation of provisional conclusions
                        on the subject as of the present date.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Recent statements and actions of the Soviet and Chinese Communist
                        Governments demonstrate that the Communists have adopted, at least for the
                        moment, a conciliatory posture in their dealings with the West.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>There have also been developments within the USSR which may prove to be of
                        profound significance for Soviet foreign policy. We are unable as yet to
                        estimate the meaning of these developments. It may be that the present
                        Soviet Government is united, securely entrenched in power, and has agreed
                        upon tactics which will be developed with consistency and determination. It
                        is also possible, however, that an intense struggle for power may be in
                        progress in the Kremlin. If the latter is the case, current Soviet tactics
                        may proceed from the regime’s instability, and Soviet foreign as well as
                        domestic policy may fluctuate as one or another faction in the Kremlin gains
                        temporary ascendancy. So far, however, the current Soviet tactics in foreign
                        relations give no indication of infirm purpose in the Kremlin.</item>
                    <pb facs="1195" n="1161" xml:id="pg_1161"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In Korea, we estimate that the Communists are now prepared to make some
                        concessions in order to reach an armistice. However, there are ambiguities
                        in the Communist proposals on the <gloss target="#t_POW1">POW</gloss> issue.
                        These ambiguities may conceal difficulties which would prevent the
                        conclusion of an armistice. Moreover, we believe that, possibly in
                        connection with the armistice negotiations, and almost certainly in
                        connection with negotiations for a political settlement, the Communists will
                        introduce proposals which the US will find extremely difficult to accept but
                        which some members of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> will not be
                        disposed to reject, especially in the atmosphere of hope created by the
                        current Communist tactics. In any case, we believe that the Communist
                        objective to gain control of all Korea will remain unchanged.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>With respect to Germany, we believe that the Kremlin is unlikely to
                        implement courses of action which would jeopardize Kremlin control over East
                        Germany. The Communists may again make dramatic proposals for free
                        elections, for the withdrawal of occupation forces, and for the
                        reunification of Germany. However, we believe that such proposals would
                        contain conditions which the Kremlin would intend to be unacceptable to the
                        West, or that, in making these proposals, the Kremlin would intend to
                        prevent their implementation. These proposals would be designed to frustrate
                        the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> program and the rearmament of West
                        Germany, capitalizing on the atmosphere created by Communist concessions in
                        Korea and by the conciliatory Soviet behavior.<note n="2" xml:id="d586fn2"
                            >The Deputy Director for Intelligence, The Joint Staff, believes that
                            with respect to Germany, the Kremlin may be willing to withdraw its
                            troops from East Germany, if the Soviet Union considered that by doing
                            so, it could force the Western Powers to withdraw their troops from West
                            Germany, frustrate the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> program, and
                            the rearmament of Germany. The Communists may also make proposals for
                            free elections and for the reunification of Germany, in the hope that
                            they would be able to secure a demilitarized and neutral German state.
                            [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Likewise, the Kremlin will probably continue to make proposals for general
                        disarmament, but we believe that these will be made for propaganda effect,
                        and not in the expectation that they would be accepted by the West.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>In many other ways the Kremlin could easily win some temporary advantage
                        and embarrass the West without real disadvantage to the Bloc. For example,
                        the Soviet Government might accede to the Tripartite Declaration of 1948
                        calling for the return of Trieste to Italy. It might offer a peace treaty to
                        Japan containing various attractive economic and even territorial clauses.
                        It might facilitate the departure of Jews to Israel from Eastern Europe and
                        the USSR. The Communists might propose an Austrian peace treaty, <pb
                            facs="1196" n="1162" xml:id="pg_1162"/> or even offer a peaceful
                        settlement of the war in Indo-China, on terms difficult alike to accept or
                        to reject. The aim of such maneuvers would be to impair the political and
                        military strength of the West, and to reap the greatest possible benefits
                        from a decision to end the Korean War.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Our present view is that the purpose of current Kremlin tactics is to
                        create an atmosphere in which resistance to Communism and to Soviet
                        imperialism will be weakened. There is no basis for concluding that the
                        fundamental hostility of the Kremlin toward the West has abated, that the
                        ultimate objectives of the Soviet rulers have changed, or that the menace of
                        Communism to the free world has diminished.<note n="3" xml:id="d586fn3">The
                            Deputy Director for Intelligence, The Joint Staff, believes the last
                            sentence of paragraph 8 should read: “Although there is no basis for
                            concluding that the fundamental hostility of the Kremlin toward the West
                            has abated, that the ultimate objectives of the Soviet rulers have
                            changed, or that the menace of Communism to the free world has
                            diminished; it is possible that the Soviets have adopted courses of
                            action designed for the present to reduce the threat of general war.”
                            [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
