<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 711Memorandum by the Director of the Foreign Operations Administration
                    (Stassen) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d711</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">711</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-11-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-11-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recTdbwPhSPuOaeNu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93000083"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Religious freedom</term>
                    <term ref="recNuUP5FwVBYX7g7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic policies</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="711"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d711">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">33.1100 ST/11–154</note>
                <head>No. 711<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Foreign Operations
                        Administration (<persName type="from">Stassen</persName>) to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d711fn1">Also addressed to the Secretary of Defense, the
                        Special Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs, and the
                        Chairman and Executive Officer of the Operations Coordinating Board.
                            <persName>Stassen</persName> also visited Italy Oct. 26–27 and Spain
                        Oct. 27–29. For memoranda reporting on his visit to Italy and Spain, both
                        dated Nov. 1, see <ref target="frus1952-54v06p2#pg_1707">vol. VI, Part 2,
                            pp. 1707</ref> and <ref target="frus1952-54v06p2#pg_1993">1993</ref>,
                        respectively. <persName>Stassen</persName> summarized the conclusions in
                        each of the three memoranda in a separate memorandum to President <persName
                            corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>, which he personally gave to the
                        President on Nov. 1. (<persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                        Library, <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> papers, Whitman
                        file)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-11-01">November 1,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Yugoslavia Trip—October 24–26, 1954</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <item>From my conferences with Marshal <persName corresp="#p_TJB1"
                            >Tito</persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d711fn2">
                            <persName>Stassen</persName>’s conversation with <persName
                                corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName>, Oct. 26, is summarized in
                            telegram 335 from Belgrade, Oct. 26. (768.11/10–2654)</note> and other
                        officials of the Government of Yugoslavia, which have been reported in
                        Embassy cables from Belgrade, and from my talks with the United States
                        country team in Belgrade, I have the following impressions: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>The Trieste settlement is looked upon as opening the way for
                                cooperation with Italy in economic, cultural, military, and other
                                matters on a mutually advantageous basis, moving step by step
                                beginning with a November economic conference.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>There is a deep conviction in the present government that the
                                break from Soviet domination in 1948 has proven to be in the best
                                interests of Yugoslavia, and that its neighbors, Hungary, Rumania,
                                and Bulgaria, have not fared well under Moscow.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Yugoslavian agriculture is rapidly being de-collectivized and
                                returned to private property, and the regime intends to continue to
                                move in that direction with gradual liberalization of small business
                                employing no more than three employees, and some easing of
                                opposition to religion, all the while maintaining a status as a
                                “Communist regime” working toward a “Socialist system.”</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> looks upon the apparent
                                reversal of Soviet attitude toward Yugoslavia as an admission of
                                error by the Soviet under <persName corresp="#p_S1"
                                    >Stalin</persName> in 1948 and considers that this will increase
                                Yugoslavian influence <pb facs="1449" n="1415" xml:id="pg_1415"/>
                                among the Balkan satellites, which influence he feels is already
                                strong and underestimated by the West.</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item>Yugoslavia has at this time a strong defense position in the
                                mountains of central Yugoslavia, has located new defense industries
                                in these remote areas, and will never adopt any defense plan which
                                does not include the central mountains fortress concept, the area of
                                successful resistance in World War II.</item>
                            <label>F.</label>
                            <item>Yugoslavia will be reluctant to take any step which would be
                                interpreted to the East as reducing Yugoslavian independence and
                                sovereignty and reducing Yugoslavian claimed influence to the
                                East.</item>
                            <label>G.</label>
                            <item>If the Western European Union develops economic objectives or
                                programs, Yugoslavia would support a relationship of the Balkan pact
                                group (Turkey, Greece, Yugoslavia) to this Brussels pact group in
                                such economic matters, but not, at least in the near future, in
                                military matters.</item>
                            <label>H.</label>
                            <item>The Yugoslavian objective might be described as a “Third position
                                through national strength,” which, although different from India’s
                                “Third position through softness,” nevertheless attracts <persName
                                    corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> to visit India and talk with
                                Nehru.</item>
                            <label>I.</label>
                            <item>Tourist travel from the West is expanding and will be increasingly
                                welcomed by the government which now recognizes its foreign exchange
                                earning potential.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>II.</label>
                    <item>From these observations, I suggest informally for such consideration as
                        may be deemed appropriate the following courses of United States action: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>That the United States encourage Yugoslavian-Italian bilateral
                                military talks on joint defense, with United States <gloss
                                    target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> officials of the two countries
                                sitting in, and perhaps with United Kingdom and perhaps French
                                military attachés also present, and that the first such talks should
                                not be under <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> auspices.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>That the joint planning include both the Ljubljana gap defense and
                                the central Yugoslav fortress defense with the development of plans
                                for Italian units to enter Yugoslavia in the gap under certain
                                circumstances and with Italian resupply of the central fortress from
                                the Adriatic by sea and air.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>That those elements of the Yugoslavian economy which are freed be
                                assisted by the United States, through its regular assistance
                                program, in being successful, and that the total Yugoslavian economy
                                be assisted in a successful development in contrast to the neighbors
                                to the East. <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>For this purpose, extend United States good offices
                                            toward the refunding of Yugoslavian debt to Germany,
                                            United Kingdom, France, and Switzerland on a long term
                                            basis, and toward the extending of additional
                                            development credits by these countries on a long term
                                            basis.</p>
                                        <p>(The balance of resources and population in Yugoslavia is
                                            favorable, and an economically sound long term program
                                            can be carried out on a loan basis over a long term of
                                            years.)</p>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <pb facs="1450" n="1416" xml:id="pg_1416"/>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>Steady but not sharp or heavy United States pressure be applied on
                                granting internal religious freedom.</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item>The exchange of persons program for technical information be
                                maintained and be oriented toward the significant leadership
                                potentials within the country.</item>
                            <label>F.</label>
                            <item>Regular visits to Yugoslavia by United States officials such as
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Robert Murphy</persName> for the
                                purpose of continually informing, drawing out, influencing, and
                                satisfying prestige urge, of Marshal <persName corresp="#p_TJB1"
                                    >Tito</persName> and his principal associates.</item>
                            <label>G.</label>
                            <item>Tourist travel should be encouraged.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>III.</label>
                    <item>General Comment. <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>Two major dangers from a United States standpoint are suggested. <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> and his regime
                                        may become overconfident of the strength of their position,
                                        may gradually relax their vigilance and lower their guard,
                                        and a successful violent internal blow may be struck by the
                                        Kremlin in a sudden reversal of their current “sweet words”
                                        tactics.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>A change in Soviet leadership which removes from influence
                                        those responsible for the original policy leading to the
                                        break, and an invitation by such new leadership to <persName
                                            corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> to take one of the top
                                        world Communist leadership positions along with Mao
                                        Tse-tung, and to revise Soviet economic policies along the
                                        lines of Yugoslavian policy, might attract <persName
                                            corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> more than anything the
                                        West would offer.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>There is one major favorable prospect. <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>A successful gradual evolvement of the Yugoslavian
                                        economic, political, social, and religious system in the
                                        direction of freedom, accompanied by increased flow of
                                        information and ideas from Yugoslavia to the Soviet and the
                                        Soviet bloc, might become an important factor in a favorable
                                        evolvement of the entire Soviet system over a period of
                                        years, without a world war.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>The percentage chance of the dangers and of the asset are all
                                considered to be small, but the implications are so far-reaching
                                that they should be kept in mind nevertheless.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">HES</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
