<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 94Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of Eastern
                    European Affairs (Leverich)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d94</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">94</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-09-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-09-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="94"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d94">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">750G.00/9–353</note>
                <head>No. 94<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of
                        Eastern European Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_LHP1"
                        >Leverich</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-09-03">September 3,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject: Trieste, Tripartite Military Talks with Yugoslavia, Wheat for
                        Yugoslavia</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PV1">Vladimir Popovic</persName>, Yugoslav
                        Ambassador</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BM2">Mirko Bruner</persName>, First
                        Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHP1">Henry P. Leverich</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>At his request, the Yugoslav Ambassador, accompanied by his First Secretary of
                    Embassy, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BM2">Bruner</persName>, called on the
                    Secretary this afternoon at 3:30. After exchange of the usual courtesies, the
                    Ambassador took occasion to express not only his own satisfaction but also that
                    of the Yugoslav participants with the outcome of the military talks between
                    Yugoslavia on the one hand and the US, UK and France on the other,<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d94fn1">A summary report of these talks, held in Washington Aug.
                        24–28, is in file 611.68/8–2453.</note> which he believed showed great
                    progress in the <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi> between Yugoslavia and the
                    Western powers. He felt that these talks were of great significance for two main
                    reasons. First, they marked an important step in the development of a mutual
                    concept for the defense of Southeastern Europe, thereby strengthening the common
                    defensive system against Soviet aggression. Second, in these talks with complete
                    sincerity and frankness the Yugoslavs had for the first time given full details
                    of Yugoslav defense plans. The Ambassador understood that the Tripartite
                    representatives in the talks fully appreciated the forthrightness of the
                    Yugoslav participants, and he was glad that this had taken place at this
                    particular juncture in the international situation. The Ambassador said that in
                    the light of these circumstances he was compelled to say that he had been
                    somewhat surprised to see in the American press numerous articles asserting that
                    the attitude of Yugoslavia is “hurting the Balkan defense pact”. He wished to
                    assure the Secretary that Yugoslavia has no intention of weakening the “Balkan
                    defense pact” and on the contrary will continue its efforts to strengthen it
                    since Yugoslavia considers the pact as a contribution to over-all defensive
                    strength against Soviet encroachments. The Ambassador referred in particular <pb
                        facs="0279" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/> to two articles by Sulzberger which he
                    said had appeared recently in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>.</p>
                <p>In response to the Secretary’s inquiry, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHP1"
                        >Leverich</persName> said that he had noted numerous press stories since
                    last weekend which were apparently prompted by the flare-up between Yugoslavia
                    and Italy regarding Trieste, and that these articles had indulged in speculation
                    of all sorts with respect to Yugoslavia’s attitude in this matter. (Subsequent
                    reference shows that the Sulzberger articles dealt not only with the Trieste
                    problem but also with the recent press altercation between Yugoslavia and Greece
                    regarding Greek Macedonia). The Secretary then pointed out that, as the Yugoslav
                    Ambassador was aware, we have a free press in this country and we do not make
                    any attempt to influence it. The current military talks, the Secretary said, had
                    been kept on a Top Secret basis, and hence the press has no factual basis on
                    which to write. Consequently, whatever they do write is purely speculation, and
                    he did not believe that the Yugoslav Government need be concerned by these press
                    articles.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador replied that the press articles were not of primary importance.
                    What is essential, he said, is that cooperation between Yugoslavia and the
                    Western powers should go forward, and in this connection he regretted the
                    Italian attitude with regard to the military talks. Italy, which should be
                    interested in any steps aimed at building up defensive strength, has indicated
                    resentment over the Tripartite talks with Yugoslavia, and it is to be hoped that
                    gradually Italy will realize that such a policy is detrimental to Italy’s own
                    interests.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he had not yet received any detailed report on the
                    outcome of the current military talks but that it was his impression that they
                    had gone well, in an atmosphere of frankness on both sides. He wished to express
                    our appreciation of the Yugoslav Government’s attitude in this respect. Whereas
                    the Secretary did not attach any fundamental importance to press reports, he
                    said that we are concerned over the situation regarding Trieste which flared up
                    so sensationally during the last week. He hoped that the Yugoslav Government
                    would avoid adding any fuel to the flames, which he thought would gradually die
                    down. The Secretary underlined our hope for a solution of the Trieste problem.
                    We cannot go as far in building up common defense as we wish until harmonious
                    relations between Yugoslavia and Italy have been established. The United States
                    is eager to do whatever it can to help bring this about. The Secretary expressed
                    the hope that the Yugoslav Government will maintain an attitude of calm and will
                    do nothing to aggravate the most recent tension between Yugoslavia and Italy
                    over Trieste. This flare-up illustrates the need to move <pb facs="0280" n="246"
                        xml:id="pg_246"/> quickly to eliminate the friction between two governments
                    which in their mutual interests should be working together.</p>
                <p>Responding to the Secretary’s observations, the Ambassador stated that his
                    country had consistently favored a reasonable settlement of the Trieste question
                    and had demonstrated its attitude by deeds and by concrete proposals. The
                    Italians, on the other hand, have consistently blocked any feasible settlement
                    and have turned down all Yugoslav proposals and efforts in this direction. The
                    desire of the Yugoslav Government to cooperate has been demonstrated not only
                    with respect to Trieste but also in other matters, but the Italian response has
                    always been negative. The Italians have manufactured provocations and have
                    endeavored to present events in such a way as to discredit Yugoslavia. The
                    Ambassador expressed the belief that as long as the Italians are given the
                    impression by the Western powers that there is no alternative to the March 1948
                    declaration regarding Trieste, there will be no inclination on Italy’s part to
                    permit reasonable settlement of the issue. In this regard, the Ambassador
                    referred to press reports on the tickers of the Secretary’s press conference
                    this morning, which the Ambassador thought implied reaffirmation of the 1948
                        declaration<note n="2" xml:id="d94fn2">Reference is to the Mar. 20, 1948,
                        announcement on Trieste by the French, British, and U.S. Governments that
                        they favored the return of the Free Territory of Trieste to Italy. For text,
                        see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, Mar. 28, 1948, p.
                        425.</note> and which he was sure would be interpreted by the Italians and
                    built up in the Italian press as such.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that he did not know what the tickers were putting out but
                    that he knew what he had said. He did not think that the reports as described to
                    him just now by the Ambassador were accurate and, in order to set the matter
                    straight, he would read from the transcript of his press conference. The
                    Secretary proceeded to read the following excerpt therefrom: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Q. Mr. Secretary, do we have an official policy position on Trieste that
                            is later than that ’48 statement which would have awarded it all to
                            Italy?</p>
                        <p>“A. I would say that the US, since that time, has been exploring other
                            alternatives and has been open-minded to other alternatives. In other
                            words, we do not necessarily regard that like the laws of the Medes and
                            the Persians which stand forever. So far, we have not come up with any
                            official alternative proposal.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The Ambassador listened attentively and stated smilingly that the Secretary’s
                    remarks were entirely different than had been reported and he was indeed glad
                    that this was the case. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BM2">Bruner</persName> read
                    through the transcript himself and jotted down notes, presumably for
                    transmission to his government.</p>
                <pb facs="0281" n="247" xml:id="pg_247"/>
                <p>The Ambassador said that there was one more point upon which he wished to touch.
                    Shortly before leaving for Yugoslavia earlier in the summer he had had a talk
                    with General <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d94fn3">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PV1"
                            >Popović</persName> and Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1"
                            >Smith</persName> briefly discussed a Yugoslav request for wheat on July
                        20. A memorandum of this conversation is in file 768.5 <gloss
                            target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/7–2053.</note> and, as a result thereof,
                    had been able to carry back to his government assurances of substantial United
                    States aid to meet Yugoslavia’s urgent need for wheat. While he was away,
                    however, officials of the Embassy talked with lower ranking officials of the
                    United States Government, and obtained quite a different impression of the
                    amount of aid to which Yugoslavia could look forward, an impression quite
                    contrary to that given by General <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName>.
                    This was a great disappointment to the Ambassador and to his government, and he
                    wondered whether the Secretary had anything to tell him on this point.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that he simply did not have the information at hand to give
                    an answer at this time. He did know that the question of economic aid to
                    Yugoslavia was currently under intensive study, both in the State Department and
                    in other agencies of the Government, and that a decision would be forthcoming in
                    the near future. The Secretary pointed out that it is one thing for the State
                    Department to determine that a certain course of action is desirable as a matter
                    of policy, and quite another thing for other agencies of the Government
                    responsible for action in the matter to find the means of actually putting it
                    into effect. They were often faced with the problem of finding money, and with
                    other practical problems. The Secretary promised to look into this matter, and
                    in the meantime asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHP1">Leverich</persName> if he
                    had anything to add. In reply, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHP1"
                        >Leverich</persName> pointed out that following the appropriation by the
                    Congress, <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> had been engaged in reapportioning
                    the amounts of economic aid which it would be possible to grant to the various
                    countries concerned. This process was still in progress and the Ambassador might
                    rest assured that the Yugoslav position, which had been so ably set forth by the
                    Ambassador on more than one occasion and by other representatives of his
                    Embassy, would be given most careful consideration.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador asked if the Secretary had anything which he might like him to
                    pass on to his government with regard to the general international situation,
                    such, for example, as prospective talks with the USSR. In reply the Secretary
                    said that there were no plans for any talks with the Soviets other than those
                    which were dealt with in the recently published notes regarding Germany and
                    Austria and the prospective conference regarding Korea.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
