<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-08-01T17:37:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-08-01T17:37:00-05:00" n="101" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d101">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.5/7–2752: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy at Saigon</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d101fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_GWM1">William M.
                                Gibson</persName>, Deputy Director of <gloss target="#t_PSA1">PSA</gloss>. Also sent to Paris as telegram 623.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-08-01T18:37:00-04:00">August 1, 1952—6:37
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>241. Eyes only Amb. <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 220 July 27
                        arrived at time when Dept giving particular thought to disturbing question
                        of growing evidences of absence Fr offensive attitude in mil field in <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> as a result indications given in Wash by
                            <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> himself in June and <pb facs="0264" n="232" xml:id="pg_232"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 131 July 17, which was only slightly
                        alleviated by Singapore’s 74 July 17.<note n="2" xml:id="d101fn2">In
                            telegram 74 from Singapore, July 17, not printed, Consul General
                                <persName>Baldwin</persName> reported on the visit of Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> to Singapore, July
                            11–13, referring to British sources. <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> was reported to have emphasized his
                            satisfaction with his conversations in Washington in June.
                            (601.5151G/7–1752)</note></p>
                    <p>You will recall our original concern with this subj during <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> conversations here when Dept
                        contested thesis that offensive action on part of Franco-Viet forces was
                        unwise on the grounds that it wld only provoke further intervention from
                            <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> on behalf Viet Minh. We found
                            <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>‘s statement that he was
                        not prepared to sacrifice more Fr lives in operations for purpose seizing
                        land from Viet Minh until such time as Viet Govt and Natl army were capable
                        of assuring control after liberation understandable but not excuse for not
                        carrying out offensive operations purpose of which was strike at enemy in
                        areas outside present Fr perimeter even if land were not gained thereby and
                        important result of which would be to develop supremely important feeling of
                        confidence in eventual victory our side.</p>
                    <p>Dept agrees with Saigon that any furtherance of impression that Fr are
                        disinclined push war against Viet Minh wld have grave psychological effect
                        on Vietnamese populace as a whole, serve to encourage rather than reduce
                        fence-sitting and otherwise benefit the enemy. Impression cld gather
                        momentum at such a rate as to jeopardize effort into which so much manpower
                        and money have been poured and which is key to overall program for defense
                        of <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>Departmental officer discussed subj including details ur 220 July 27 with
                        responsible officers in Pentagon today. We found considerable degree of
                        agreement on necessity maintain offensive psychology and present continued
                        evidences of will to win in form, for example, airborne operations in enemy
                        territory. Pentagon appreciates difficulties in administering liberated
                        territory but impressed by <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName>
                        theory that Viet Minh now vulnerable and must be hit soon wherever it is to
                        be found. Object is to annihilate enemy not gain land. Pentagon disagrees
                        however with Gen <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName>‘s statements
                        made to you as reported <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> re ability
                        Fr air force airlift sufficient troops for offensive airborne operations
                        (which Pentagon agrees most practical and effective form offensive action).
                        Without detailing differences of opinion (to be done separately) their
                        conviction, which is based largely if not entirely on <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> reports, is that Fr are not now obtaining
                        maximum potential troop lift with existing aircraft. Trouble lies in lack of
                        pilots, crews, maintenance facilities and airfields. They believe for
                        instance that <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName> can now airlift
                        two battalions at a time rather than one They think it is useless to discuss
                        more equipment until the Fr agree to provide the necessary pilots and
                        maintenance crews. There <pb facs="0265" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/> was some
                        talk of possibility of creating a supply and rehabilitation depot in
                        Phils.</p>
                    <p>Pentagon reported that <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName> had
                        been delayed in Paris in order make it possible discuss subj with <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName> and that they wld anxiously await his
                        first report after arriving in Saigon.</p>
                    <p>Dept suggests matter be pursued actively with <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName> who is airborne officer himself and shld have ready
                        understanding situation, to the end that an agreed interpretation of needs
                        can be reached between Fr and <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> and
                        specific recommendations made to Pentagon.</p>
                    <p>Pentagon understands fully danger in allowing sit-tight attitude to be
                        cultivated and is anxious contribute whatever they can within realm of
                        possibility. Dept anxious impress upon Fr folly of giving up offensive
                        strategy so brilliantly launched and carried out by <persName corresp="#p_DLDT1">de Lattre</persName> in favor of a mere holding
                        operation.</p>
                    <p>Aside from using every opportunity to impress imperative need for continued
                        offensive action upon Fr auths in both Paris and Saigon next step wld appear
                        to be to press for ironing out differences between Gen <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName>‘s and <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>‘s analysis of what is needed to deal with problem if
                            <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName>‘s recommendations are
                        accepted in Paris. Paris shld make every effort support <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName>‘s cause and Saigon urge prompt action
                        upon <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName> after his arrival
                        while continuing impress <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>
                        our conviction that offensive must be pursued.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BDKE1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Bruce</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>