<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-12-04T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-12-04T23:00:00-05:00" n="144" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d144">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.5/12–552: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Heath</hi></persName>)
                            <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-12-05T12:00:00+08:00">December 5,
                            1952—noon</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1149. Rptd info Paris 182, Hanoi 127, Manila 114. Re <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1141, December 3.<note n="1" xml:id="d144fn1">Telegram 1141 to Saigon, Dec. 3, read as follows: “Eyes
                            only Amb. In view possibility Fr request, suggest you discuss with
                                <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName> nature possible Fr
                            requirements additional aircraft because of destruction and attrition
                            resulting from current mil operations. We wish to examine possibility of
                            being helpful but can of course make no commitments at this stage.”
                            (751G.5/12–352)</note> The French have not asked for additional
                        aircraft. What they do request and General <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName> is urgently recommending is that the 30 F–8’s
                        already programmed be expedited to arrive here not later than January and
                        that delivery of the 8 B–26’s scheduled to arrive at rate of one a month
                        during calendar year 1953 be accelerated.</p>
                    <p>The French yesterday made, however, urgent request on which in <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName>‘s and my opinion immediately
                        favorable action in some form or other should be taken. The request is that
                        150 American Air Force mechanics be detailed immediately to Nhatrang Air
                        Base for one month to give 50-hour checks to 18 <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>-47’s and 100-hour checks on another 18 <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>-47’s. Nhatrang was chosen presumably because presence
                        mechanics would be less conspicuous than if detailed to a Tonkin base or to
                        Saigon. The French have made the same imperative request of the French Air
                        Ministry, but according local information, French Metropolitan Air Force has
                        only a few if any surplus mechanics for immediate despatch. The French
                        request is entirely legitimate. When <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName> asked for and was granted the 50 additional <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>-47’s late last summer (21 were provided by US),
                        sufficient crews were available for normal maintenance. It was expected
                        these would be used for tactical drops of parachute troops. No sustained
                        airlift operation was or could have been foreseen at that time. With loss
                        Nghialo and the ensuing necessary decision of French command to attempt hold
                        Na San to prevent overrunning that country and Laos, an air lift had to be
                        instituted. As a result, the <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>-47’s are
                        operating at several times the normal rate, entailing urgent increased
                        maintenance.</p>
                    <p>As an alternative to sending American mechanics, <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName> and I have suggested possibility
                        of the 36 planes being sent for repairs and checks to
                            <persName>Clark</persName> Field. Trip to Manila would add extra flying
                        time to the planes, but that might be the more practical operation. I can
                        see no policy objection either to despatching American maintenance crews <pb facs="0341" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/> for a few weeks stay here or
                        providing maintenance at <persName>Clark</persName> Field. On several
                        occasions we have provided mechanical specialists for brief periods for
                        instruction and repair of certain American equipment. This emergency
                        maintenance is vital to holding of Na San and for meeting any other
                        emergency air-borne operations.</p>
                    <p>General <persName>Chassin</persName>, <gloss target="#t_CinC1">CINC</gloss>
                        French Air Force <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, arrives today from
                        Tonkin to consult with <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d144fn2">In telegram 1183 to
                            Saigon, Dec. 8 (repeated for information to Paris as telegram 3241 and
                            to Manila as telegram 1651), the Department of State responded as
                            follows: “Secy of Air and Air Staff giving urgent consideration matters
                            brought up <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> [telegram 1149].
                            Chief of Staff has cabled Gen [<persName>Otto P.</persName>]
                                <persName>Weyland</persName>
                            <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> of <gloss target="#t_FEAF1">FEAF</gloss> for his views. Suggest you make sure detailed info
                            being developed re Fr requirements be made available directly to
                                <persName>Weyland</persName> and rptd here.”
                        (751G.5/12–552)</note></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HDR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>