<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador at Saigon ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-12-12T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-12-12T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-12-12T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-12-12T03:00:00-05:00" n="150"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.5/12–1252: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-12-12T16:00:00+08:00"
                            >December 12, 1952—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1190. Rptd info Paris 187. Eyes only for <persName corresp="#p_AJM1"
                        >Allison</persName>. Re<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1201 Dec
                    10, rptd Paris 3305.<note n="1" xml:id="d150fn1">In telegram 1201 to Saigon,
                        Dec. 10, Assistant Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_AJM1"
                            >Allison</persName> informed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                            >Heath</persName> that the initial reaction of the Department of the Air
                        Force to the proposal for participation in the maintenance of French
                        aircraft was unfavorable. It was thought that such participation would
                        involve a significant change of policy and should be undertaken only as the
                        result of a high-level decision which took into account all implications.
                        (751G.5/12–552)</note> Gen <persName>Hewitt</persName> (see <gloss
                        target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 1187 Dec 12),<note n="2" xml:id="d150fn2">
                        <p>Telegram 1187 from Saigon, Dec. 12, repeated to Paris for information as
                            telegram 186, read as follows: “Brigadier General [<persName>Albert
                                G.</persName>] <persName>Hewitt</persName> in charge of maintenance
                                <gloss target="#t_FEAF1">FEAF</gloss>, arrived in Saigon late
                            yesterday to study overhaul needs of French transport planes. He said
                            that from preliminary observation it was possible and he wld recommend
                            assignment of mobile repair group to Indochina provided there were no
                            policy objections.</p>
                        <p>“Montel, French Secretary of State for Aviation, arrived today. I
                            suggested to General <persName>Hewitt</persName> that he consult with
                            both Montel and French Air Force Commander Gen
                                <persName>Chassin</persName>.” (751G.5/12–1252)</p>
                    </note> after interviews with Fr Secy of State for Aviation Montel and Gen
                        <persName>Chassin</persName>
                    <pb facs="0347" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> Commander <gloss target="#t_FAF1"
                        >FAF</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss>, and study plane maintenance problem, has sent
                    tel to Commandant [<hi rend="italic">Commanding</hi>] Gen <gloss
                        target="#t_FEAF1">FEAF</gloss> Japan stating that in view heavy demands
                    faced by Fr maintenance personnel, we must send Amer maintenance personnel for
                    balance of period of loan to Fr of US transport planes if we expect eventually
                    return of these planes (which are only loaned to French until end Jan next). He
                    has recommended assignment to <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> of mobile
                    maintenance detachment 60 persons which wld provide for major inspection and
                    battle repairs for one squadron of 31 planes, which wld include 21 US transports
                    loaned to French.<note n="3" xml:id="d150fn3">Telegram 1197 from Saigon, Dec.
                        13, repeated to Paris as telegram 189, read as follows: “I have learned that
                        General <persName>Hewitt</persName>, after visit to Nha Trang, has revised
                        his estimate and believes that detachment of 25 or 30 <gloss target="#t_AF1"
                            >AF</gloss> mechanics with a weekly air support run from
                            <persName>Clark</persName> Air Field base direct to Nha Trang will be
                        sufficient to handle <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>–47 overhauls.”
                        (751G.5/12–1352)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Montel indicated to <persName>Hewitt</persName> he wld appreciate Def and State
                    decision on question US despatching maintenance personnel prior his scheduled
                    departure from <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> Dec 21.</p>
                <p>From talk last night with <persName>Hewitt</persName> and Col
                        <persName>Whisner</persName>, acting chief <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                        >MAAG</gloss> (Gen <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName> on trip
                    to Formosa) it is apparent that Fr maintenance facilities are now taxed to point
                    where standard maintenance provided is dangerously below that which Amer Air
                    Force deems adequate. Although 100 technicians arriving from France next week,
                    60 are replacements for equal number leaving on rotation.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Hewitt</persName> favors sending US technicians to <gloss
                        target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> rather than repairing transports at
                        <persName>Clark</persName> Field for long over-water flight unsafe for worn
                    and damaged aircraft and trip to and return from Philippines wld cut into
                    over-all flying hours planes now requiring 50-hour and 100-hour overhauls.</p>
                <p>This sending of technicians to <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> is not an
                    innovation in our relationship to <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> conflict. US
                    Air Force mechanics were sent to <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> several weeks
                    ago to repair planes damaged by typhoon; our <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                        >MAAG</gloss> mission which includes delivery and instruction in use of
                    weapons is scarcely less involvement than repair of planes.</p>
                <p>Shld requirement for transport aircraft remain at present high level or increase,
                    which is quite probable, Fr wld face most critical situation. It is my opinion
                    that our stake in this area is too important for us to jeopardize the tremendous
                    effort we have already made through failure to follow through on action which
                    seems to be clearly called for in the present circumstances and which does not
                    seem to me to be much more than we have already done.</p>
                <p>It is perhaps pertinent to recall that during <persName corresp="#p_LJ2"
                        >Letourneau</persName> conversations last June, Def was interested in
                    sending Amer training mission to expand Vietnamese officer corps to command in
                    this war. This proposal was objected to by Dept official (and myself) not
                    because it wld <pb facs="0348" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> mean further
                    involvement but on the grounds that officer training was a Fr responsibility and
                    language difficulties were involved. If we can consider training men for combat
                    in actual war, we shld be able to send mechanics to repair our own planes, which
                    are to be returned to us in good condition after expiration of a short loan
                        period.<note n="4" xml:id="d150fn4">
                        <p>In telegram 1286 to Saigon (also sent to Paris as telegram 3523), Dec.
                            22, Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>
                            stated the following to Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                                >Heath</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dunn</persName>:
                            “Dept concurs in US participation maintenance <gloss target="#t_C1"
                                >C</gloss>-47s by 25–30 <gloss target="#t_USAF1">USAF</gloss>
                            personnel at Nha Trang on temporary loan basis. Defense notified and has
                            taken similar position.</p>
                        <p>“Defense has directed <gloss target="#t_FEACOM1">FEACOM</gloss> to
                            undertake such support and is informing <gloss target="#t_MAAG1"
                                >MAAG</gloss> Saigon.</p>
                        <p>“Defense additionally queries <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>
                            French intentions on possibility retention mechanics due rotation.”
                            (751G.5/12–1352)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
