<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-02-24T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-02-24T06:00:00-05:00" n="17" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d17">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">601.5151G/2–2452: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Heath</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-02-24T19:00:00+08:00">February 24, 1952—7
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1670. Rptd info Paris 587, Hanoi unn. At special briefing held evening Feb 22
                        at High Commissariat for me, Gen <persName corresp="#p_BBGF1">Brink</persName><note n="1" xml:id="d17fn1">Brigadier General <persName corresp="#p_BBGF1">Francis G. Brink</persName>, Chief of the
                            Military Assistance Advisory Group at Saigon.</note> and
                            <persName>Tobler</persName>, acting director <gloss target="#t_STEM1">STEM</gloss>, Gen <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName> reviewed
                        mil situation and <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>
                        summarized over-all situation Assoc States. <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName>’s comments being transmitted by despatch.<note n="2" xml:id="d17fn2">Despatch 416 from Saigon, Feb. 26, <ref target="#pg_40">p. 40</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>Gist <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>’s remarks as fol:<note n="3" xml:id="d17fn3">Despatch 429 from Saigon, Mar. 3, not printed,
                            contains a memorandum of conversation supplementing the account
                            contained in this telegram. (751G.00/3–352)</note>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Death <persName corresp="#p_DLDT1">De Lattre</persName> had given
                                rise to uneasiness, particularly among Viets regarding Fr plans and
                                intentions. He had come to Assoc States to answer questions with
                                view to allaying doubt as well as get firsthand knowledge present
                                situation. He found mil situation still worrisome but presently in
                                hand. He thanked US for aid which had helped bring this about.</p>
                            <p>Vital question was development Viets army regarding which there are
                                two major problems: (1) source of funds and (2) senior and staff
                                officers and specialists. He had told Viets Govt Fr willing
                                initially shoulder major share Viets mil expenses but Viets Govt
                                must rapidly assume increasing share burden. Viets obviously not
                                anxious assume heavier financial responsibility. No difficulty
                                getting sufficient Viets manpower for ranks and company grade
                                officers but dearth qualified senior and staff officers and
                                specialists serious Lacuna. Reluctance Viets have Fr officers
                                provisionally fill post and their obsession with having Viets occupy
                                all positions is major stumbling block. Fr Commander-in-Chief
                                naturally cld not rely upon inexperienced and untried Viets. Gen
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SGR1">Salan</persName> had expressed
                                willingness give training to promising officers but Viets impatient
                                to have their people in top brackets. On whole, <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> optimistic regarding
                                Viets forces, but time of essence as northern Vietnam campaign
                                proved evidence <pb facs="0069" n="37" xml:id="pg_37"/> of
                                increasing <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> training and material
                                assistance, including heavier armaments.</p>
                            <p>Pacification cannot be accomplished by Fr without energetic
                                cooperation Viets. Especially important, and presently lacking, is
                                strong, efficient Viets admin and police machinery to take control
                                in areas regained from <gloss target="#t_VM1">VM</gloss> and take
                                advantage of population fatigue under <gloss target="#t_VM1">VM</gloss> exactions. This, of course, only one facet larger
                                problem stimulation leadership and vigorousness Viets Govt.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> referred to strong
                                sentiment in France, particularly in parliamentary circles, which
                                questions policy sacrificing Fr manpower and wealth on country which
                                manifests desire expell Fr. Asserted he told <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> willingness France continue
                                mil effort depends on (1) Viets Govt vigorously shouldering its
                                polit, admin, and fin responsibilities and (2) abandoning present
                                carping attitude of demanding ever more concessions.</p>
                            <p>Viets Govt shld devote efforts now expended on building up external
                                prestige to improvement internal admin. <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> considers Fr Union formula valid and
                                major revision inappropriate, altho minor adjustments might be
                                negotiated discretely. He remarked France’s capabilities limited and
                                that when exhausted, France’s “friends” wld have to come to rescue
                                otherwise chaos wld ensue. He did not specify type of “rescue”
                                envisioned.</p>
                            <p>He then made rather surprising statement on which I did not comment.
                                He said even if peace were restored the “presence Francaise” in
                                    <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> shld still be supported by its
                                friends (US) for if Fr were eliminated results wld be anarchy.</p>
                            <p>No polit problem in Laos but in Cambodia elections had stimulated
                                rising tide nationalistic tub-thumpings. He had reminded Cambodians
                                that unless more realistic attitude adopted Cambodians inviting
                                Communist takeover.</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Main theme of <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>’s able presentation was that key to improvement
                        of situation is Viets Govt facing up to its responsibilities. When I
                        enquired in what way US might help in this respect, <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> made no specific suggestions but
                        said that High Commissioner wld naturally keep in closest touch with me.</p>
                    <p>While <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> alluded to Fr
                        weariness with Assoc States mil burden he in general reflected determination
                        France stick to guns both with respect to <gloss target="#t_VM1">VM</gloss>
                        and Viets demands for greater freedom. His reference to validity of Fr Union
                        formula wld suggest he will not recommend significant additional concessions
                        to Viets nationalistic aspirations.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HDR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>