<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé at Vientiane ( (Thomson) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d198</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">198</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-03-19T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-03-19T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-03-19T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-03-19T04:00:00-05:00" n="198"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751J.5/3–1953: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Vientiane</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Thomson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vientiane</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-03-19T16:00:00+07:00"
                            >March 19, 1953—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>17. Repeated information Saigon 155, Paris unn. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName> called on Crown Prince <persName
                        corresp="#p_SV1">Savang</persName> at Luang Prabang March 16 accompanied by
                        <persName corresp="#p_MR2">McClintock</persName> and myself.</p>
                <p>In course conversation regarding problems Lao national defense, Ambassador
                    suggested that Lao Government, to ensure full consideration its point of view
                    during <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> visit Washington and
                    subsequent studies, submit statement its projects for strengthening national
                    forces including some detail regarding needs external aid. After reflection,
                        <persName corresp="#p_SV1">Savang</persName> said he would descend Vientiane
                    March 18 and that statement might be produced within week.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Despite <persName corresp="#p_SV1"
                        >Savang</persName>’s reply, and although I informed both Foreign Minister
                    and Prime Minister of foregoing conversation same evening in Vientiane, I doubt
                    whether Lao Government can quickly produce any statement detailed enough to be
                    of great use. Total lack qualified military planners leaves Lao Government
                    hardly capable drawing up military projects other than those developed by
                    French; and this degree dependence would render Laos cautious about submitting
                    anything this nature to US without prior French clearance. To my knowledge no
                    projects yet considered for Laos parallel recent Dalat decisions for Vietnam.
                    Effort continuing along established lines gradually improving and enlarging
                    existing National Army (now about 12,000 men) and lightly-armed National Guard
                    (about 6,000 men). <persName corresp="#p_SV1">Savang</persName> might use above
                    statement to plug his pet project convert most of existing Lao infantry into
                    paratroops. Legation will of course follow matter and assure speediest
                    transmittal any results to Department.</p>
                <p>Other points of interest conversation with <persName corresp="#p_SV1"
                        >Savang</persName>: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>National defense: <persName corresp="#p_SV1">Savang</persName> much
                            concerned over Chinese intentions, but did not even mention Vietminh
                            threat from Thai country North Vietnam. While not prepared deny that
                            fate of Laos linked to outcome struggle in Vietnam, he continued reflect
                            Lao Government’s hope steer clear any unnecessary involvement in what
                            they call “Vietnamese civil war” (re Saigon tel 1061 November 22), and
                            specifically to avoid use Lao troops outside borders of Laos. He
                            conceded nevertheless that such refusal based “present conditions” of
                            conflict, and that Lao troops might fight beyond frontiers if conflict
                            should become “more generalized”. He was vague about changes in
                            conditions he had in mind.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>French conception of Indochina war effort: <persName corresp="#p_SV1"
                                >Savang</persName> expressed mild irritation at changeability
                                <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>’s declarations,
                            varying from emphasis struggle as common problem free world to most
                            recent shift toward playing up French Union interests. Added, however,
                                <pb facs="0448" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> realization that <persName
                                corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> less than free agent,
                            subjected many different pressures.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Reorganization of French administration in Indochina: Stated that,
                            like rest of Laotians, he would be impressed only by results, not by
                            promises or assignment new titles to same old faces.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Minister to Washington: <persName corresp="#p_SV1">Savang</persName>
                            said that while Lao Government ready establish mission immediately, he
                            did not consider Minister designate fully prepared yet. (Foreign
                            Minister now anticipates <persName corresp="#p_OS1">Ourot</persName>’s
                            arrival Washington perhaps month of May.)<note n="1" xml:id="d198fn1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_OS1">Ourot Souvannavong</persName> presented
                                his credentials on July 13, 1953.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>Personal plans: <persName corresp="#p_SV1">Savang</persName> to travel
                            to France early May, thence to Coronation London. King whose gout still
                            bad may try cure in France during summer.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
