<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (
                    (Allison) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d218</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">218</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-04-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-04-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="218"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d218">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.5/4–353</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_AJM1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Allison</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d218fn1">
                        <p>This memorandum was drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Philip W.
                                Bonsal</persName>, Director of the Office of Philippine and
                            Southeast Asian Affairs. A handwritten notation on the source text by
                                <persName corresp="#p_ORL1">Roderic L. O’Connor</persName>, Special
                            Assistant to the Secretary of State, indicates that the paper was seen
                            by the Secretary on Apr. 7.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName> was appointed Ambassador
                            to Japan on Apr. 2. He was succeeded as Assistant Secretary of State for
                            Far Eastern Affairs by <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Walter S.
                                Robertson</persName> on Apr. 8.</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-03">April 3,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Status of Indochina Problem</item>
                </list>
                <p>In the course of the <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Mayer</persName> talks full
                    recognition of the interdependence of the fight in Korea and in Indochina was
                    expressed. The French <pb facs="0488" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> reasserted their
                    resolve to pursue hostilities in Indochina with a view to “achieving success”.
                    We stated our willingness to study French plans “so as to determine how and to
                    what extent the U.S. may be able to contribute matériel and financial support to
                    their achievement”.</p>
                <p>The two governments also stated that in their view, should there be an armistice
                    in Korea and “should the Chinese Communist regime take advantage of such an
                    armistice to pursue aggressive war elsewhere in the Far East, such action would
                    have the most serious consequences for the effort to bring about peace in the
                    world and would conflict directly with the understanding on which any armistice
                    in Korea would rest”.</p>
                <p>M. <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> remained in Washington for
                    two days after the departure of M. <persName corresp="#p_MR1">Mayer</persName>.
                    M. <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> described to Defense, State
                    and <gloss target="#t_DMS1">DMS</gloss> officials the general Franco-Vietnamese
                    strategic concept looking to the substantial defeat of the enemy in Indochina.
                        <hi rend="italic">M. <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>
                        stressed in the most energetic terms the top secret nature of the plans and
                        other data which he furnished</hi>.</p>
                <p>Stated very briefly, the strategic concept involves over the next two years the
                    training, arming, and equipping of 135,000 additional Vietnamese troops. These,
                    organized in light battalions and officered entirely by Vietnamese, will be used
                    in conjunction with Franco-Vietnamese units to clear up enemy centers of
                    resistance in the south and central portions of Viet-Nam, thus releasing heavily
                    armed Franco-Vietnamese regular units for service against the bulk of the
                    regular organized enemy forces in the north. It is estimated that these latter
                    forces will be brought to a decisive final battle during the first half of
                    1955.</p>
                <p>The French estimate of the additional cost of raising and maintaining the
                    additional Vietnamese troops needed for this strategic plan is, for calendar
                    1954 in the neighborhood of $233 million for pay, maintenance, food, clothing,
                    matériel, etc., and $81 million for additional end-items from the U.S. For
                    calendar 1955 the French estimate the additional cost at over $300 million for
                    pay, maintenance, food, etc., and some $10 million for additional end-items from
                    the U.S. (The present cost to the French and ourselves of the war in Indochina
                    is estimated at well over $1.5 billion.)</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> have been requested by the Secretary of
                    Defense to prepare a military evaluation of the French plan. It is expected that
                    this will be ready on April 8. Meanwhile General <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1"
                        >Trapnell</persName>, Chief of <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>/Saigon,
                    although disappointed at the slowness and expense of the plan sees no
                    alternative to its acceptance. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        >Heath</persName> has expressed <pb facs="0489" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/> a
                    considered view that the program of expanding the Vietnamese national army as
                    well as the military responsibilities of the Vietnamese Government is
                    politically feasible and desirable. He has also endorsed other features of the
                    plan.</p>
                <p>So far as cost is concerned, it is believed that the French preliminary
                    submissions should be and will be carefully screened and that there will be
                    careful examination of the possibility of increasing the financial share of the
                    war effort borne by the people of Viet-Nam.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
