<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of Western European Affairs (
                    (Knight) ) to the Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs (
                    (Merchant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d267</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">267</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-05-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-05-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="267"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d267">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_PSA1">PSA</gloss> files, lot 58 D 207, “French Military
                    Operations in Indochina”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of Western
                        European Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_KRB1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Knight</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MLT1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Merchant</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d267fn1">
                        <p>On May 6, <persName corresp="#p_KRB1">Knight</persName> transmitted
                            copies of this memorandum to Counselor <persName corresp="#p_MD1"
                                >Douglas MacArthur II</persName> and to <persName corresp="#p_BPW1"
                                >Philip W. Bonsal</persName>, Director of <gloss target="#t_PSA1"
                                >PSA</gloss>, with the following note:</p>
                        <p>“I am sending to you herewith some preliminary thoughts concerning the
                            difficult problem of a political solution to the Indochina war.</p>
                        <p>“This is a very rough memorandum for which I request your indulgence. Any
                            and all comments will be deeply appreciated.” (<gloss target="#t_PSA1"
                                >PSA</gloss> files, lot 58 D 207, “French Military Operations in
                            Indochina”)</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-05-06">May 6,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Negotiated Settlement in Indochina</item>
                </list>
                <p>In accordance with your request at a recent Director’s meeting, I am putting down
                    some preliminary thoughts concerning a negotiated settlement in Indochina.</p>
                <p>First, and even though this is not the point to which I wish to address myself,
                    mention should be made of the difficulties which we will encounter in seeking to
                    bring the “other side” to the conference table. Quite obviously <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi Minh</persName> would not fully represent the
                    “other side”, but the Chinese Communists as well as the Soviets can, without
                    doubt, be expected to disclaim any knowledge of or responsibility for the
                    situation in Indochina, “a purely internal affair.”</p>
                <p>Quite aside, however, from the above difficulties and assuming for the purpose of
                    the argument that they have been overcome, it is difficult to visualize what
                    would be the terms of reference which we would suggest for the political
                    discussion of Indochina. From the start we should realize that the Communists
                    would insist on at least the withdrawal of foreign forces and a plebiscite
                    thereafter.</p>
                <pb facs="0577" n="545" xml:id="pg_545"/>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>A plebiscite under present conditions could with certainty be predicted as
                        giving a thumping majority to the Viet-minh in Viet Nam. Under normal
                        conditions it could be expected that Laos and Cambodia would vote
                        anti-communist with a large margin. However, both these people have been
                        long known for their peaceful characteristics bordering on timorousness.
                        What with the recent aggression in Laos by the Communists from Viet Nam on
                        top of a general current of victory running for the Viet Minh, it is to be
                        feared that a plebiscite in these two other countries would also result in
                        Communist victories.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Another possibility which presents itself would be a cessation of
                            hostilities on the basis of the military <hi rend="italic">status
                                quo</hi> with both sides resting on their positions and negotiations
                            between the <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi Minh</persName>–<persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> Governments. As we all know, the
                            situation is radically different from that prevailing in Korea where
                            there exists a continuous battle line with both sides in effective
                            control of all the territory on their side of the line. In Indochina, on
                            the contrary, the picture is one of an infinite series of pockets and
                            pockets within pockets. Because of this complex and confused situation
                            it is difficult to imagine that the Viet Minh would refrain from
                            political consolidation and expansion during the talks.</p>
                        <p>The probable outcome of these negotiations would be the creation of two
                            Viet Namese states—one Communist and the other non-Communist. After
                            complicated exchanges of territories there would result in all
                            probability a Communist Viet Nam in the North and a <persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> Viet Nam in the South. This
                            state of affairs, however, could not be expected long to endure what
                            with the greater dynamics of the Communist elements in Viet Nam coupled
                            with the half-heartedness of <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                                Dai</persName> and his Government. It is believed that it would not
                            be long until the Southern Viet Nam state would have been subverted by
                            the Communists with the result that all of Viet Nam would be Communist.
                            A chain of events leading to Communist domination over most of Southeast
                            Asia could well have been thus set in motion.</p>
                        <p>After having given some thought to the above possibilities and variations
                            thereof (obviously it would be a loss of time to consider a return to
                            the <hi rend="italic">status quo ante-bellum</hi>, because of public
                            opinion in the Associated States, as well as because of the Viet Minh’s
                            inflexible opposition thereto), I am tentatively tempted to conclude
                            that the following would offer us something which might be accepted by
                            both sides and yet not lead inevitably to eventual Communist control
                            over all of Indochina.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Essentially this suggested situation is a variation of the second
                        hypothesis above. There would be two Viet Nam states with this important
                        proviso that most of the French forces in Indochina would remain for a long
                        period in the Southern state. At the same time, the <pb facs="0578" n="546"
                            xml:id="pg_546"/> French would have to agree to encouraging and
                        fostering to a greater extent than heretofore the full autonomy of this
                        state so that it would acquire in a matter of years enough national
                        consistency to resist subversion from the North. To make this solution
                        politically acceptable to the French, such a state could remain within the
                        French Union but this should be much more on the basis of British Dominion
                        status than has been contemplated so far. While the Indochina war is
                        unpopular in France, it is believed that stationing of forces there for a
                        long period of time should be politically possible as long as the drain in
                        blood would have been stopped and the financial burden greatly decreased. A
                        similar arrangement could be worked out for Cambodia. Unfortunately, it is
                        difficult to see how the same could be done for Laos not only because it is
                        now in part overrun by the Communists but also because of its exposed
                        strategic position and weak defense potential, which might make it a
                        permanent liability. At best it would seem that we could only hope for a
                        divided Laotian state or else for the integration of southern Laos into
                        Cambodia. While thus Siam would have a rather long common border with the
                        northern Indo-Chinese Communist state or states, it is believed that as long
                        as a solid non-Communist entity would remain to the east of Siam, Communist
                        intervention therein would not be inevitable.</item>
                </list>
                <p>We should have no illusion that anything much better than the foregoing could be
                    developed in negotiations with the Communists concerning a “political
                    settlement” in the Far East unless a vast improvement in the situation in
                    Indochina is achieved through military operations exceeding those presently
                    envisaged. Whether the foregoing would be acceptable would also depend to a
                    large extent upon what might be considered an acceptable settlement for
                    Korea.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
