<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Embassy in France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d282</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">282</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-05-16T16:32:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-05-16T16:32:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-05-16T16:32:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-05-16T16:32:00-05:00" n="282"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d282">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">330/5–1653: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d282fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MRH1">Robert H.
                            McBride</persName>, Officer in Charge of French-Iberian Affairs.
                        Repeated for information to Saigon as telegram 2265 and to Bangkok as
                        telegram 2175.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-05-16T17:32:00-04:00"
                            >May 16, 1953—5:32 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5651. French Ambassador informed Acting Secretary May 15 he had new instructions
                    from Paris endeavor obtain US support for French position re bringing cases
                    aggression Southeast Asia before UN or at least assurances US was not urging
                    Thailand bring case.<note n="2" xml:id="d282fn2">The meeting of May 15 between
                            <persName corresp="#p_SGWB1">Walter Bedell Smith</persName>, the Acting
                        Secretary of State, and <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Henri Bonnet</persName>,
                        the French Ambassador, was recorded in a memorandum of conversation by
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRH1">Robert H. McBride</persName>, the Officer in
                        Charge of French-Iberian Affairs. (Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation,
                        lot 64 D 199) <persName corresp="#p_SGWB1">Smith</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> had also discussed the question of an
                        appeal to the United Nations on May 12; the memorandum of that conversation,
                        by <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> of <gloss target="#t_PSA1"
                            >PSA</gloss>, is in file 751J.00/51253. <persName corresp="#p_BH1"
                            >Bonnet</persName> discussed the matter further with Assistant Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> on May 21. The
                        memorandum of that conversation, by <persName corresp="#p_HRE1">Robert E.
                            Hoey</persName>, Officer in Charge of Vietnam-Laos-Cambodia Affairs, is
                        in file 330/5–2153. On May 22, <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName>
                        told Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HJD1">Hickerson</persName>
                        that his government was “very upset” at the extent to which the United
                        States had encouraged Thailand to raise the problem at the United Nations.
                        The memorandum of the <persName corresp="#p_HJD1"
                            >Hickerson</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName>
                        conversation, by <persName>Ward P. Allen</persName>, United Nations Adviser
                        in the Bureau of European Affairs, is in file 792.00/5–2253.</note> He
                    indicated possibilities very serious repercussions France were it published that
                    US not only not supporting France but agitating with Thailand to bring case
                    against strong French opposition.</p>
                <p>Acting Secretary stated we were not agitating with Thailand to bring this case
                    before UN but our basic position was unchanged and we would support Thais if
                    they presented case as we had already told them and told French.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d282fn3">In telegram 2210 to Bangkok, May 20, Acting Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_SGWB1">Smith</persName> indicated that the
                        Department of State was gratified to learn that the Government of Thailand
                        had decided to submit to the Security Council the matter of the threat to
                        Thailand arising from the invasion of Laos. The telegram read in part as
                        follows: “Inform Prime Minister foregoing and assure him US Government
                        continues prepared support Thailand’s presentation Security Council and
                        assist in other practical ways in course preparing resolution or other
                        supporting material.” (751J.00/5–1953)</note> He assured <persName
                        corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> we did not wish cause difficulty over
                    this matter and were not now taking initiative though we did not conceal that
                    basic difference of view over question of bringing matter before UN remained. He
                    agreed with <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> we perhaps had <pb
                        facs="0601" n="569" xml:id="pg_569"/> breathing spell now though he stressed
                    we believed it was only temporary.</p>
                <p>In conclusion French Ambassador reiterated importance this matter to French
                    Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGWB1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
