<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador at Saigon ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d313</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">313</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-06-23T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-06-23T22:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-06-23T22:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-06-23T22:00:00-05:00" n="313"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d313">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.5851G/6–2453: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-24T11:00:00+08:00"
                            >June 24, 1953—11 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2552. Repeated information Paris 474. No distribution outside Department. For
                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> (<gloss target="#t_FE1"
                        >FE</gloss>) from <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_OLGJ1">O’Daniel</persName> mission<note n="1" xml:id="d313fn1">
                        <p>The <persName corresp="#p_OLGJ1">O’Daniel</persName> Mission was
                            announced in Department of State Press Release No. 329 of June 20, 1953,
                            which read as follows: “In response to an invitation from the French
                            Prime Minister when he visited Washington last March, a U.S. military
                            mission headed by Lt. Gen. <persName corresp="#p_OLGJ1">John W.
                                O’Daniel</persName>, presently commander, U.S. Army Pacific, will
                            arrive at Saigon on June 20. Its purpose will be to pursue discussions
                            with Gen. <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Henri Navarre</persName>,
                            Commander in Chief, Indochina, on the manner in which U.S. material and
                            financial support of the effort of the French and Associated States
                            armed forces in Indochina may best contribute to the advancement of the
                            objectives of defeating the Communist forces there and of bringing peace
                            and security to Vietnam, Cambodia, and Laos. It is believed essential to
                            insure an increasingly close integration of U.S. assistance with the
                            plans developed by the authorities of France and of the Associated
                            States.</p>
                        <p>“Arrangements are being made for the military leaders of the Associated
                            States to participate in these discussions. The vital role of the
                            national armies of Vietnam, Cambodia, and Laos and the increasingly
                            important assumption of high military responsibilities by the Associated
                            States will make these discussions of particular interest.” (Department
                            of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, June 29, 1953, p. 909)</p>
                        <p>For the terms of reference of the mission, as prepared by the Joint
                            Chiefs of Staff in collaboration with the Department of State, see <hi
                                rend="italic">United States-Vietnam Relations, 1945–1967</hi>, Book
                            9, pp. 59–67. The mission consisted of 12 military officers, including
                            General <persName corresp="#p_OLGJ1">O’Daniel</persName>. <persName
                                corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName>, Director of <gloss
                                target="#t_PSA1">PSA</gloss>, accompanied the group as political
                            consultant.</p>
                        <p>For the report of the <persName corresp="#p_OLGJ1">O’Daniel</persName>
                            Mission, July 15, 1953 (without annexes), see <hi rend="italic"
                                >ibid</hi>., pp. 69–96. A copy of the report, including its annexes,
                            is in file 711.5851G/71553.</p>
                    </note> arrived <pb facs="0649" n="617" xml:id="pg_617"/> twentieth and has been
                    engaged series intensive briefings and discussions with French and Vietnamese
                    military. Group departs for Hanoi today returning about twenty-seventh.</p>
                <p>Cordial working relationships have been established. <persName corresp="#p_OLGJ1"
                        >O’Daniel</persName> has injected a number of fresh ideas and suggestions in
                    discussions particularly with <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName>,
                        <persName>Bodet</persName> (his deputy) and <persName>Bondis</persName>
                    (head of forces in south Vietnam) in stimulating, forthright fashion and
                    apparently without giving offense. Specific reactions as yet undetermined
                    although reasonable suppose at least some of these concepts have fallen on
                    fruitful soil.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> himself gives me impression being
                    offensive-minded. His broad strategic thinking resembles <persName
                        corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>-<persName>Allard</persName> outline
                    with time-table somewhat improved. He contemplates strategic offensive in Tonkin
                    area for September next year preceded by maximum of offensive activity of
                    tactical nature in that area prior to date indicated. He is aware danger heavy
                    enemy offensive capability beginning September this year but hopes throw enemy
                    off balance through limited offensive action.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> proceeding Paris early July to
                    present plans to government. I believe those plans will be favorably influenced
                    by vigorous <persName corresp="#p_OLGJ1">O’Daniel</persName> approach. I believe
                    also that they may include request for additional French Union forces, perhaps
                    in amount equivalent to two divisions.</p>
                <p>My impression is that unless French and Vietnamese can concentrate in Tonkin this
                    fall sufficient mobile forces seriously to hurt the <pb facs="0650" n="618"
                        xml:id="pg_618"/> enemy and to deprive him of the broad capacity for
                    initiative which he has enjoyed over past year, situation may deteriorate
                    irretrievably. Political evolution and developments here and in France, war
                    weariness, continued high prestige of <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho</persName>
                    forces, and other factors with which Department abundantly familiar support this
                    impression.</p>
                <p>It would be my hope that at Bermuda meeting,<note n="2" xml:id="d313fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d303fn3">footnote 3, p. 608</ref>.</note> President could
                    discuss situation with French Prime Minister and encourage his support of prompt
                    positive approach to military situation and discourage wishful thinking as to
                    possibility of a negotiated settlement free world could live with. (Idea of
                    reinforcements from French Union has been advanced by Admiral <persName
                        corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> and by others who have studied
                    situation here. General <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> should of
                    course not be brought into picture by us at Bermuda.)</p>
                <p>It would seem important at Bermuda: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>To combat French illusion that Indochina situation can at this stage
                            honorably be settled by negotiation with Chinese Communists or with
                            Soviets;</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>To give French such indications as may be possible that, if as result
                            of vigorous military offensive by Franco-Vietnamese against Viet-Minh,
                            Chinese Communists should invade Indochina, we would not abandon them
                            but would indeed support them vigorously on sea and in the air;</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>To emphasize need for handling political development of Associated
                            States in manner more consistent with political necessities and with
                            professions of faith made by French in past. Useful tripartite statement
                            could perhaps be made along lines earlier suggested.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName> concurs.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
