<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador at Saigon ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d360</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">360</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-07-30T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-07-30T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec6RPowhBcehiRY8" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Communications lines</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications lines</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-30T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-30T03:00:00-05:00" n="360"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d360">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/7–3053: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-07-30T16:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 30, 1953—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>196. Repeated information Paris 59, Hanoi unnumbered, Phnom Penh unnumbered. I
                    had a long talk with <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> yesterday
                    evening. With regard to Cabinet discussions in Paris, he said that government
                    had agreed to initiate “<persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> plan” but
                    could not undertake to carry it through to completion until financing could be
                    found. <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> would receive a
                    reinforcement of nine battalions from France plus the French battalion now in
                    Korea if UN Command agrees to its departure. The new battalions would leave
                    France—and Korea—on October 1. <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName>
                    would also receive additional cadres, non-coms, and specialists he had demanded.
                    Metropolitan Air Force would send 25 additional <gloss target="#t_C1"
                    >C</gloss>–47s. <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> had been very
                    effective in pressing his demands against great deal of opposition which
                    objected to further building-up French expeditionary forces in Indochina at
                    expense of build-up of Metropolitan Forces. He, <persName corresp="#p_DM1"
                        >DeJean</persName>, thought insistence in France on danger of a Soviet
                    invasion of Europe was unjustified. He did not believe Russia intended or could,
                    in view of its internal difficulties and problems with its satellites, attack in
                    Europe at present time.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> said he was very pleased with
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> whom he had known for a long
                    time. He was not only an intelligent general but he had political sense as well.
                    Even with reinforcements from France and formation of new Vietnamese battalions,
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> would be unable to undertake
                    all-out offensive operations in next few months, but there <pb facs="0737"
                        n="705" xml:id="pg_705"/> would be a stepping-up of limited offensive moves
                    such as raid on Langson and action at <persName>Quang Tri</persName>, Annam,
                    which started two days ago. Hitherto, Viet Minh had been able to put practically
                    their entire force in battle lines leaving almost unguarded communications lines
                    and supply centers. This, they would no longer be able to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> indicated some belief that Korean
                        armistice<note n="1" xml:id="d360fn1">The Korean Armistice agreement was
                        signed at Panmunjom on July 27.</note> signified desire on part of Chinese
                    Communist regime to break away from Russia. To his inquiry I replied that I did
                    not share this opinion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> I took this as an indication that <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> believes some sort of an arrangement can
                    be made with China to cease its support of Viet Minh.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> had just returned from seeing
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> at Banmethuot. He spoke in
                    praise of <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>’s statesmanlike
                    understanding and wholehearted acceptance of French offer of July 3. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> would leave about August 1 for Paris to
                    be followed in a week or so by a delegation headed by President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NVT1">Tam</persName>.</p>
                <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> I thought it very important
                    for him to see Cambodian King as early as possible; that in my opinion King was
                    more reasonable than his advisors. I told him of my conversation of July 25 with
                    King who expressed appreciation and satisfaction with French reply to his note,
                    taking exception only to French statement they intended to exercise temporary
                    military command east of Mekong, instead of requesting Cambodian permission
                    therefor, which King said he would gladly have given. I expressed personal hope
                    that some amicable adjustment of this point would be found; French having gone
                    as far as they had might go a little further and find a formula which would save
                    King’s face. <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> made no reply to this
                    observation. He said he was going today to Phnom Penh to see Prime Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Penn Nouth</persName> and call on Regent, King’s
                    father. He would hand <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Penn Nouth</persName> a letter
                    to King expressing hope that His Majesty would receive him and that he could
                    renew pleasant relations which he had enjoyed with King during latter’s four
                    weeks’ “exile” in Japan. <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> said he
                    had, in fact, enjoyed very friendly contacts with King during latter’s Japanese
                    stay. He had transmitted to King agreement reached in Paris with Cambodian
                    delegates, which King had assured him, since it made substantial concessions to
                    his point of view, was acceptable. King had left immediately thereafter for
                    Phnom Penh and it was great surprise to <persName corresp="#p_DM1"
                        >DeJean</persName> to hear that two or three days later he had gone into
                    “exile” again in Bangkok. I remarked that was probably due to influence of
                    King’s entourage plus possibly that of Buddhist priests. I remarked King had
                    told me he intended to send delegation to Paris, but now it appeared that
                        <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Penn Nouth</persName> had insisted that
                    negotiations <pb facs="0738" n="706" xml:id="pg_706"/> must begin at Phnom Penh.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> replied that in any case France
                    intended to complete negotiations with Vietnam before attempting to come to
                    agreement with Cambodia.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> said he had named
                        <persName corresp="#p_OR1">Offroy</persName>, whom he had known favorably
                    for some years, as his deputy.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
