<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-09-09T19:06:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-09-09T19:06:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-09-09T19:06:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-09-09T19:06:00-05:00" n="398"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d398">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.5 <gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/9–753:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d398fn1">Drafted by <persName>Edgar J. Beigel</persName> of
                        the Office of Western European Affairs and <persName>William J.
                            Galloway</persName>, Special Assistant to the Counselor, <persName
                            corresp="#p_MD1">Douglas MacArthur II</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-09-09T20:06:00-04:00"
                            >September 9, 1953—8:06 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>868. Limit distribution.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Subject to our receiving necessary assurances from French, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> today approved additional aid proposed for
                        Indochina based on substance <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 827,
                        with Presidential approval expected tomorrow. Comments <gloss
                            target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss>s 939, 940, 941 fully taken into account
                        in presentation to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>.<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d398fn2">Telegram 827 to Paris, Sept. 5, containing the text of
                            a draft memorandum to the French Government concerning additional U.S.
                            aid for Indochina, is not printed. (751G.5 <gloss target="#t_MSP1"
                                >MSP</gloss>/9–553) Regarding telegram 939 from Paris, Sept. 7, see
                                <ref target="#d390fn1">footnote 1, p. 758</ref>. Telegram 940 from
                            Paris, Sept. 7, transmitting technical comments on the draft memorandum
                            contained in telegram 827 to Paris, is not printed. (751G.5 <gloss
                                target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/9–753) For text of telegram 941 from
                            Paris, Sept. 7, see <ref target="#pg_758">p. 758</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>On most confidential basis you should therefore now informally advise
                            <persName corresp="#p_LJ1">Laniel</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> above action and indicate assurances
                        desired are to effect that French Government is determined: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>put promptly into effect program of action set forth its
                                memorandum Sept 1;<note n="3" xml:id="d398fn3">For text, see <ref
                                        target="#pg_770">p. 770</ref>.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>carry this program forward vigorously with object of eliminating
                                regular enemy forces in Indochina;</item>
                            <pb facs="0824" n="792" xml:id="pg_792"/>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>continue pursue policy of perfecting independence of Associated
                                States in conformity with July 3 declaration;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>facilitate exchange information with American military authorities
                                and take into account their views in developing and carrying out
                                French military plans Indochina;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>assure that no basic or permanent alteration of plans and programs
                                for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> forces will be made as
                                result of additional effort Indochina;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                            <item>provide appropriate info to US Govt of amount of expenditures for
                                military program set forth in memo of Sept 1.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>We would expect these assurances be embodied in note which US in reply
                        would acknowledge. US reply would go on to make clear that: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>appropriately established financial requirements for military
                                program as indicated in Sept 1 memo from French Govt, not to exceed
                                $385 million or its equivalent in Calendar Year 1954, will be met by
                                US Govt (see para 8 below);</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>amount of $385 million or its equivalent in francs or piasters is
                                deemed to satisfy in full request made by French memo of Sept
                                1;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>no further financial assistance may be expected for Calendar Year
                                1954;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>US Govt retains right to terminate this additional assistance
                                should for any reason French Govt plan as outlined in memo of Sept 1
                                prove incapable of execution or should other unforeseen
                                circumstances arise which negate the understandings arrived at
                                between the two govts.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>You should immediately begin informally to work out language with French
                        covering paragraph 2 above. (We will cable soonest new draft of US reply.)
                        It should be made crystal clear to French that final US Govt agreement will
                        be given only when satisfactory language for exchange notes has been
                        obtained.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>During time you are working out exchange with French, Administration will
                        inform interested leaders both houses Congress since new program involves
                        important change in orientation foreign aid program as enacted by Congress.
                        We have begun and will continue work on this phase of matter with greatest
                        urgency and hope have it completed by time you wind up negotiations with
                        French. Please impress on your French colleagues overriding necessity
                        maintain complete secrecy on all aspects this matter until Congressional
                        leaders informed and negotiations actually completed and notes exchanged
                        between two govts.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>It was agreed by <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> there should also be
                        assurances from French Govt re intention move ahead on <gloss
                            target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>, but that for various reasons such
                        assurances need not necessarily be contained in formal notes exchanged
                        between govts. Would like your current views on how most satisfactory
                        assurances can best be obtained.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>While procedures whereby payments to French or Associated <pb facs="0825"
                            n="793" xml:id="pg_793"/> States will be made will have to be worked
                        out, it is important that French understanding clearly our basic approach to
                        this additional aid—US is agreeing to finance a specific action program up
                        to an agreed dollar figure. Consequently, we will pay or reimburse French or
                        Associated States on basis of agreed franc and/or piaster expenditures as
                        they occur at rates of exchange then current. US should receive benefit any
                        reduced costs resulting from screening, devaluation, or other causes.
                        Appropriate safeguards will be included in US note. <gloss target="#t_FOA1"
                            >FOA</gloss> will forward details of suggested procedures
                        shortly.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>We have very serious problem finding 385 million and unless there are
                        compelling reasons to contrary we would plan to release counterpart accruing
                        Calendar Year 1954 (now estimated $70–80 million) to help meet total.
                        Realize French may be counting on this counterpart for other purposes but
                        trust you will be able reach agreement along these lines. This connection,
                        would like to know lines French thinking on how they would present US aid
                        figures to parliament, whether as separate amount outside regular French
                        budget for 1954 or as item only on resources side as shown
                        heretofore.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Will expect you keep us currently informed regarding negotiations on
                        language of note.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Copy memo submitted <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> being pouched
                            <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. Copy <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> action paper will follow soonest. Will inform <persName
                            corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName> separately of developments.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>, current planning envisages following <gloss
                        target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss> sources for $385 million: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>$70–80 million <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> counterpart
                            accruing in Calendar Year 1954;</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Rescreening of Fiscal Year 1954 French <gloss target="#t_MDAP1"
                                >MDAP</gloss> program;</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Rescreening of Fiscal Year 1954 Indochina <gloss target="#t_MDAP1"
                                >MDAP</gloss> program;</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Transfer of Title I and possibly II <gloss target="#t_MDAP1"
                                >MDAP</gloss> funds from Defense to <gloss target="#t_FOA1"
                                >FOA</gloss> (thereby possibly reducing amount of regular <gloss
                                target="#t_OSP1">OSP</gloss> that <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                                >NATO</gloss> countries including France could otherwise have
                            received).</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
