<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Dillon) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d432</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">432</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-10-23T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-10-23T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rec3b4QX8ohh76TF3" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004886"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Journalist</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-10-23T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-10-23T02:00:00-05:00" n="432"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d432">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/10–2353: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dillon</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-10-23T08:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 23, 1953—8 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1593. Repeated information Saigon 159. Embassy officer saw Vietnamese High
                    Commissioner Prince <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Buu Loc</persName> yesterday at
                    latter’s request. Had hour interview just before <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Buu
                        Loc</persName> proceeded to Matignon receive French “note” from <persName
                        corresp="#p_LJ1">Laniel</persName> for <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName> and Government.<note n="1" xml:id="d432fn1">On Oct. 21,
                        following a meeting of the Council of Ministers, the French Government
                        issued a communiqué announcing that a note would be transmitted to the
                        Vietnamese Government asking for an explanation of its position in light of
                        the resolutions passed by the Vietnamese National Congress. The text of the
                        communiqué was transmitted to Washington in telegram 1574 from Paris, Oct.
                        22. (751G.00/10–2253) A summary of the main points of the French note was
                        transmitted in telegram 296 from Hanoi, Nov. 19. (651.51G/11–1953) The
                        Vietnamese Government replied on Nov. 16, stating that it reaffirmed its
                        wish to maintain the ties of free association between France and Vietnam,
                        but insisted on full sovereignty and a relationship of equals. A translation
                        of the Vietnamese reply was sent to Washington in telegram 906 from Saigon,
                        Nov. 23. (651.51G/11–2353)</note> He will take note to Cannes today and
                    discuss action to be taken with <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>
                    before latter’s departure for Saigon October 26.</p>
                <p>It was immediately evident that <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Buu Loc</persName> is
                    very seriously worried about present atmosphere Paris concerning Indochina and
                    he repeatedly <pb facs="0875" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/> asked officer if Embassy
                    could exert its influence on French to preserve their “sangfroid” stand and not
                    take any action which might extend present crisis. Described reaction French
                    officials with whom he had conferred since his return from Saigon (presumably
                    including <persName corresp="#p_LJ1">Laniel</persName> and Jacquet) as being
                    unexpectedly severe. He sympathized entirely with their reasons but regretted
                    vehemence their attitude and attributed it to failure appreciate political
                    immaturity Delegates of National Congress. He himself had been equally shocked
                    at resolution advocating break with French Union “in its present form”. He
                    believes it to be immature, unwise and deplorable in its effect. He had had no
                    forewarning of it else he should have tried stave it off. His efforts counteract
                    its effects later had only been partially successful.</p>
                <p>Vietnamese is as much as individualist as Frenchman but lacks latter’s political
                    sophistication. When for first time he found himself in democratically
                    representative assembly, he lost his balance and indulged in emotional
                    extravagances import of which he did not understand. <persName corresp="#p_BL1"
                        >Buu Loc</persName> was convinced most delegates, with possible exception
                    recent Viet Minh converts who may have purposely set out sabotage Congress, now
                    realized what they had done and would undo it if they could without losing
                    “face”. He quoted last night’s <hi rend="italic">France-Soir</hi> article by
                    Lucien Bodard (“best journalist in Indochina”) to effect he had interrogated
                    numerous delegates of Congress and had failed discover single one who would now
                    declare he wished either break with France or replace <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                        >Bao Dai</persName> as being entirely accurate. He regretted French public
                    opinion had not paid sufficient attention favorable declarations which had been
                    made to Congress. He quoted opening and closing speeches Tran Trong Kim and his
                    own first speech as examples.</p>
                <p>When questioned about <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Tam</persName>’s role in
                    Congress, <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Buu Loc</persName> was especially bitter.
                        <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Tam</persName> was so concerned with his own
                    doubtful political future, he did little hold Congress in line. He was convinced
                        <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Buu Loc</persName> wished replace him as Foreign
                    Minister which was absurd.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Buu Loc</persName> hoped terms French note he was
                    about receive would not be too severe. If it attempts force Vietnamese “retract
                    publicly and lose face” it will fail and all will be lost. Neither must French
                    open juridical argument which could go on for months. If this deplorable
                    “incident” could be glossed over by mere understanding, tact and diplomacy both
                    sides, he is convinced mutually satisfactory solution can be found. French Union
                    should not pose an unsurmountable problem. There is nothing in French
                    Constitution which prevents Vietnam <pb facs="0876" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/>
                    from exercising its full independence while retaining its association with
                    France on free and equal basis in French Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Buu Loc</persName> was hopeful <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>’s presence Saigon would do much ease
                    tension and bring dissidents down to earth. “<persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName> has both his feet on ground while most of delegates appeared
                    have theirs in air”. He took particular pains compliment Ambassadors <persName
                        corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De
                        Jean</persName> for their role influencing delegates to be moderate. They
                    both had outstanding appreciation of issues involved and “true friendship both
                    Vietnam and France”.</p>
                <p>In answer our question about effect all this would have on planned negotiations,
                    he replied <persName corresp="#p_LJ1">Laniel</persName> wanted <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> name Vietnamese delegation immediately
                    but it was impossible him do so under present circumstances referring
                    particularly assembly debate and French “note”.</p>
                <p>We were deeply impressed throughout by <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Buu
                        Loc</persName>’s air of gravity which we had never seen present in him
                    before. There is no doubt this time he believes French have been pushed too far
                    and something must be done quickly make amends. As Department knows, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BL1">Buu Loc</persName>’s reactions are usually reflection
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dillon</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
