<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title>Memorandum of Discussion at the 179th Meeting of the National
                                        Security Council, Friday, January 8, 1954,</title>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d499</bibl>
                                <bibl type="frus-document-number">499</bibl>
                                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <settingDesc>
                                <setting>
                                        <date notBefore="1954-01-08T00:00:00-05:00"
                                                notAfter="1954-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                                </setting>
                        </settingDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                                        <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic"
                                                category="politico-military-issues"
                                                subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                                                lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                                        <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic"
                                                category="science-and-technology"
                                                subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                                        <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic"
                                                category="politico-military-issues"
                                                subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                                        <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic"
                                                category="politico-military-issues"
                                                subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                                                lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                                        <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic"
                                                category="foreign-economic-policy"
                                                subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                                                lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                                        <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic"
                                                category="politico-military-issues"
                                                subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                                                lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                                        <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic"
                                                category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                                                lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                                        <term ref="recuSPZDcCd8RkSsx" type="topic"
                                                category="politico-military-issues"
                                                subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002736"
                                                lcsh-match="exact">Aircraft carrier</term>
                                        <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic"
                                                category="politico-military-issues"
                                                subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                                                lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                                        <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                                                category="politico-military-issues"
                                                subcategory="national-security-council">National
                                                Security Council</term>
                                        <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic"
                                                category="information-programs"
                                                subcategory="general"
                                                lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                                                lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>
                        <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="499"
                                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d499">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library,
                                                <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                                        papers, Whitman file</note>
                                <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Discussion at the 179th
                                                Meeting of the National Security Council, Friday,
                                                January 8, 1954,</hi>
                                        <note n="1" xml:id="d499fn1">Prepared by <persName
                                                  corresp="#p_GSE1">S. Everett Gleason</persName>,
                                                Deputy Executive Secretary of the National Security
                                                Council, on Jan. 11.</note>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                        <seg rendition="#left">
                                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>eyes only</hi>
                                        </seg>
                                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-01-08">January
                                                  8, 1954</date>
                                        </dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">[Extracts]</note>
                                <p>Present at the 179th meeting of the Council were the President of
                                        the United States, presiding; the Vice President of the
                                        United States; the Secretary of State; the Secretary of
                                        Defense; the Director, Foreign Operations Administration;
                                        the Director, Office of Defense Mobilization. Also present
                                        were the Secretary of the Treasury; the Attorney General
                                        (for Item 2); the Director, Bureau of the Budget; the
                                        Chairman, Atomic Energy Commission (for Items 1 and 2); the
                                        Deputy Secretary of Defense<note n="2" xml:id="d499fn2">
                                                <persName corresp="#p_KRM1">Roger M.
                                                Kyes</persName>.</note> (for Item 3); the
                                        Secretaries of the Army, the Navy, and the Air Force, and
                                        the Joint Chiefs of Staff (for Item 3); the Chairman, Joint
                                        Chiefs of Staff; the Director of Central Intelligence;
                                                <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Sherman Adams</persName>,
                                        the Assistant to the President; <persName corresp="#p_CR2"
                                                >Robert Cutler</persName>, Special Assistant to the
                                        President; <persName corresp="#p_JCD1">C. D.
                                                Jackson</persName>, Special Assistant to the
                                        President; Gen. <persName corresp="#p_PMGW1"
                                                >Persons</persName>, Deputy Assistant to the
                                        President; the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                        Representative on Internal Security; the Assistant White
                                        House Staff Secretary; the Executive Secretary, <gloss
                                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>; and the Deputy
                                        Executive Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                        >NSC</gloss>.</p>
                                <p>Following is a summary of the discussion at the meeting and the
                                        chief points taken.</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Significant world
                                                developments affecting U.S. security</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The Director of Central Intelligence first briefed the Council on
                                        the military situation in Indochina. The French garrison at
                                        Dien Bien Phu, consisting of ten battalions, was now
                                        surrounded by approximately three Vietminh divisions. It was
                                        not yet clear whether the Vietminh would launch a frontal
                                        attack on the French position or invest it and move south
                                        toward the Thai frontier. Though in no immediate danger, the
                                        French were somewhat disturbed. While Dien <pb facs="0980"
                                                n="948" xml:id="pg_948"/> Bien Phu was a strong
                                        position, the French were actually locked up in it, and
                                        fresh Vietminh battalions were en route.</p>
                                <p>In the center, where the Vietminh made their first thrust, the
                                        situation was still fluid. New French reinforcements were
                                        coming, and they should be able to clean up the Vietminh
                                        column.</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> commented
                                        that General <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName>
                                        had told him that the Vietminh might well be able to take
                                        Dien Bien Phu if they were willing to commit the three full
                                        divisions and take the resulting heavy losses. Admiral
                                                <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> did
                                        not believe, however, that the Vietminh force was large
                                        enough both to besiege Dien Bien Phu and also move forces
                                        south into Laos. Accordingly, Admiral <persName
                                                corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> believed that
                                        the Vietminh would probably avoid an all-out assault on Dien
                                        Bien Phu.</p>
                                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> went on
                                        to point out that the only purpose to be served by a
                                        Vietminh attack on this fortress would be the psychological
                                        damage which they could do the French will to continue the
                                        war in Indochina. This political and psychological advantage
                                        might seem to the Vietminh to be worth the military loss
                                        that they would suffer.</p>
                                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">United States objectives
                                                and courses of action with respect to Southeast
                                                Asia</hi> (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 177
                                        and Special Annex to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                                177)<note n="3" xml:id="d499fn3">See <ref
                                                  target="#d497fn2">footnote 2, p. 944</ref>.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName>, in
                                        introducing the report on Southeast Asia, stated that in
                                        accordance with his discussion of the paper with the
                                        President, there would be no reference to the Special Annex
                                        as such. The contingencies referred to in the Special Annex
                                        would henceforth be discussed only orally, and all copies of
                                        the Annex would be recalled for destruction. General
                                                <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName> also
                                        stated that the Joint Chiefs of Staff had not yet been able
                                        to reach a final decision as to their views on <gloss
                                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 177 or on the problem
                                        set forth in the Special Annex. They would therefore prefer
                                        that the Council make no decision on <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                                >NSC</gloss> 177 at this meeting.</p>
                                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName> then
                                        proceeded to read to the Council many of the most important
                                        sections of the report and to summarize such portions as he
                                        did not read. He also referred to the courses of action in
                                        the two contingencies envisaged in the Special Annex: One,
                                        courses of action in the event that the French insist that
                                        they will pull out of Indochina unless we participate
                                        militarily in the war; and two, courses of action if the
                                        French state that they will pull out of Indochina in any
                                        event.</p>
                                <p>After General <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName> had
                                        finished his briefing of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                        177, the President stated that he wanted to ask a few basic
                                        questions. First, why did the French persist in their
                                        unwillingness to allow the Associated States to put the case
                                        of Communist aggression against any <pb facs="0981" n="949"
                                                xml:id="pg_949"/> of them before the UN? He had
                                        understood why the French were originally opposed to this
                                        move, but he could not understand why French objections
                                        persisted now that France had declared the Associated States
                                        to be independent.</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> explained
                                        that French reluctance stemmed from French sensitivity with
                                        regard to the French position in North Africa. If the
                                        Associated States were to go to the UN, the Moroccan issue
                                        would almost certainly be raised.</p>
                                <p>The President commented that this seemed to be yet another case
                                        where the French don’t know what to do—whether to go it
                                        alone or to get assistance from other nations clandestinely.
                                        They want to involve us secretly and yet are unwilling to go
                                        out openly to get allies in their struggle. For himself,
                                        said the President with great force, he simply could not
                                        imagine the United States putting ground forces anywhere in
                                        Southeast Asia, except possibly in Malaya, which we would
                                        have to defend as a bulwark to our off-shore island chain.
                                        But to do this anywhere else was simply beyond his
                                        contemplation. Indeed, the key to winning this war was to
                                        get the Vietnamese to fight. There was just no sense in even
                                        talking about United States forces replacing the French in
                                        Indochina. If we did so, the Vietnamese could be expected to
                                        transfer their hatred of the French to us. I can not tell
                                        you, said the President with vehemence, how bitterly opposed
                                        I am to such a course of action. This war in Indochina would
                                        absorb our troops by divisions!</p>
                                <p>As to the build-up of the native forces, said the Vice President,
                                        one must realize that the French talk one way but feel
                                        another. What he had seen when he was in Indochina had given
                                        rise to the gravest doubts as to the likelihood of any
                                        really strong Vietnamese national army, at least any army
                                        built up to the levels contemplated in the <persName
                                                corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> Plan. General
                                                <persName corresp="#p_DLDT1">de Lattre</persName>
                                        had certainly favored such a build-up, and the Vietnamese
                                        had liked him. But Generals <persName corresp="#p_NGH1"
                                                >Navarre</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CGR1"
                                                >Cogny</persName> actually believe that the
                                        Vietnamese cannot really fight unless led by French
                                        officers. The Vietnamese, on the other hand, doubt that the
                                        French really want to train them in large numbers.
                                        Essentially, continued the Vice President, the French are
                                        fighting in the hope of keeping Vietnam in the French Union,
                                        whereas the Vietnamese really want independence outside the
                                        French Union. These objectives are incompatible, and when
                                        you pin General <persName corresp="#p_NGH1"
                                                >Navarre</persName> down he admits that the great
                                        issue as to the success of the war in Indochina is not one
                                        of matériel but, rather, of men. He does not indicate very
                                        much confidence in the training program for the native
                                        forces. This, said the Vice President, was of course a
                                        pessimistic view, but the indigenous forces are the key to
                                        success or failure. While at present plans call for the
                                        building up of the Vietnamese forces to a point <pb
                                                facs="0982" n="950" xml:id="pg_950"/> where they can
                                        take over the defense of their own country, there was
                                        considerable question whether the French would really prove
                                        willing to allow us to assist them with this training
                                        program. In short, the situation was not as good as it
                                        looked on paper.</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> said he
                                        was prepared to grant the Vice President’s point, but that
                                        at least the French had agreed to receive two U.S. officers
                                        to assist with the training program.</p>
                                <p>The President then inquired whether General <persName
                                                corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> could be
                                        induced to agree to let us take over some considerable
                                        number of their training camps, with perhaps several hundred
                                        U.S. officers instead of two. Admiral <persName
                                                corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> replied that
                                        in any case the French had certainly resisted such proposals
                                        in the past, as they have also been reluctant to share any
                                        of their planning for the conduct of the war with U.S.
                                        officers.</p>
                                <p>The essence of the problem, said the Vice President, was
                                        political. The French certainly want to win the war in
                                        Indochina, but they want to win it without building up the
                                        Vietnamese to the point where they could win it alone.</p>
                                <p>The President commented that in view of the fact that Frenchmen
                                        back at home were so thoroughly sick of the war in
                                        Indochina, one would imagine that the French would be glad
                                        to have the Vietnamese bear the brunt.</p>
                                <p>The trouble was, answered the Vice President, that French are
                                        aware that if the Vietnamese become strong enough to hold
                                        their country alone, they would proceed to remove themselves
                                        from the French Union. To this the President commented that
                                        if the French had been smart they would long since have
                                        offered the Associated States independence on the latters’
                                        own terms. We had made such an offer to the Puerto Ricans
                                        recently, and they had all run to cover. In any event, said
                                        the President, if the United States could take over a good
                                        part of the training of the native forces in Indochina, it
                                        would relieve the French non-coms for combat.</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> agreed
                                        with this judgment on the need for additional French
                                        non-coms, but pointed out that the real reasons why the
                                        French were still fighting this war after seven years was
                                        their earlier reluctance to train any of the Vietnamese.</p>
                                <p>The President said that one of the outstanding failures of the
                                        Western world in Asia was its inability to produce good
                                        fighting material in the Asian countries for which Western
                                        powers were responsible. The Communists were more effective.
                                        They got hold of the most unlikely people and turned them
                                        into great fighters.</p>
                                <p>The Vice President said that in the course of a discussion he had
                                        had with General <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1"
                                                >Trapnell</persName>, the point had been made that
                                        what was lacking to induce the Vietnamese to fight was a
                                        “cause”. General <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1"
                                                >Trapnell</persName> had <pb facs="0983" n="951"
                                                xml:id="pg_951"/> argued against this view, and
                                        insisted that if the native soldiers were well led, well
                                        equipped and well trained, they would fight. No “cause” was
                                        so important as these considerations. This, said the Vice
                                        President, was of course a controversial view, but it was an
                                        interesting observation, which made the Vice President feel
                                        that the President’s idea of assisting the Associated States
                                        with a large training mission might be a very effective
                                        measure.</p>
                                <p>At this point General <persName corresp="#p_CR2"
                                                >Cutler</persName> stated that <gloss
                                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 177 had reached the
                                        conclusion that there was no danger of a French military
                                        defeat in Indochina except in the event of overt Chinese
                                        aggression. Moreover, Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1"
                                                >Radford</persName>, in a conversation with him, had
                                        expressed the opinion that the French could not possibly get
                                        out of Indochina, since most of them would be murdered in
                                        the process of trying to get out. Accordingly, said General
                                                <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName>, wasn’t
                                        the real question before the Council whether we propose to
                                        give in if the French turn to us and request the
                                        participation of U.S. forces in the war in Indochina?</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> pointed
                                        out that the French had not asked us for any combat forces,
                                        but General <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName>
                                        said that he understood that they had asked for additional
                                        U.S. aircraft together with pilots to fly them, and was not
                                        this the camel getting his head through the door?</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> broke in
                                        to say that there was a certain amount of history in this
                                        issue. He pointed out that when he was Commander-in-Chief in
                                        the Pacific he had been given orders to draw up plans to
                                        assist the French in the air. He had done just this,<note
                                                n="4" xml:id="d499fn4">At Admiral <persName
                                                  corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName>’s direction,
                                                a planning team from <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1"
                                                  >CINCPAC</gloss> headquarters had visited
                                                Indochina from Nov. 10 to 18, 1952. See
                                                  <persName>Edwin Bickford Hooper</persName>,
                                                  <persName>Dean C. Allard</persName>. and
                                                  <persName>Oscar P. Fitzgerald</persName>. <hi
                                                  rend="italic">The United States Navy and the
                                                  Vietnam Conflict</hi>, vol. I, <hi rend="italic"
                                                  >The Setting of the Stage to 1959</hi>, Navy
                                                Historical Division, Department of the Navy
                                                (Washington, Government Printing Office, 1976), p.
                                                190.</note> and he now felt that the United States
                                        should do everything possible to forestall a French defeat
                                        at Dien Bien Phu. Indeed, if necessary we should send an
                                        aircraft carrier to assist the French if they appear to be
                                        in danger of losing this strong point. The French Air Force
                                        had fought well, but its upkeep and maintenance was
                                        poor.</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName> said he
                                        simply did not see how we could talk of sending people, as
                                        opposed to money, to bail the French out. When we start
                                        putting our men into Indochina, how long will it be before
                                        we get into the war? And can we afford to get into such a
                                        war?</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> said that
                                        of course we already had a lot of men in Indochina now,
                                        though none of them in combat operations. Nevertheless, he
                                        insisted, we are really in this war today in a big way.</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName>
                                        repeated his arguments against sending American troops to
                                        Indochina, and said that although he appreciated how serious
                                        the loss of Dien Bien Phu could be, it could not be, he <pb
                                                facs="0984" n="952" xml:id="pg_952"/> thought, bad
                                        enough to involve the United States in combat in
                                        Indochina.</p>
                                <p>The President commented that even if we did not send pilots we
                                        could certainly send planes and men to take over the
                                        maintenance of the planes.</p>
                                <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> queried
                                        whether this would be enough to stave off the loss of the
                                        Dien Bien Phu base. Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1"
                                                >Radford</persName> explained that the French
                                        situation at the base was serious because the Vietminh had
                                        succeeded in moving up heavy anti-aircraft support. The
                                        French feel that they are not capable of destroying these
                                        antiaircraft guns, whereas Admiral <persName
                                                corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> was convinced
                                        that our pilots could destroy them.</p>
                                <p>The President commented that if any of our people were to get
                                        into this jungle fighting, they should certainly be given
                                        the proximity fuse or VT fuse bombs, not just ordinary
                                        bombs. Let’s hurry up and give them some.</p>
                                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName> again
                                        pointed out to the members of the Council that there was
                                        nothing whatever in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 177
                                        which authorized the introduction of U.S. combat forces into
                                        Indochina at this time.</p>
                                <p>The President replied that Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1"
                                                >Radford</persName> was, of course, not referring to
                                        general policy but to a specific action with reference to
                                        the Indochina war. It was certainly going to be necessary to
                                        work out some way by which our planes could be used.
                                        Obviously we couldn’t just fly them into combat off the
                                        carrier.</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName> again
                                        expressed his great concern lest this move involve the
                                        United States in the war, and General <persName
                                                corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName> asked the
                                        Secretary of State if this might not well be the first step
                                        by which the French would proceed to unload their military
                                        responsibility on the United States. Did not the Secretary
                                        of State fear this consequence?</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> said that
                                        he did not believe that Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1"
                                                >Radford</persName>’s proposal would have this
                                        consequence, and the President added that while no one was
                                        more anxious than himself to keep our men out of these
                                        jungles, we could nevertheless not forget our vital
                                        interests in Indochina.</p>
                                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName> expressed
                                        his strong opposition to this course of action, and
                                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName>
                                        asked the question, “Suppose the French were to give up and
                                        turn the whole country over to the Communists. Would the
                                        United States then interfere?” The President replied no, we
                                        would not intervene, but that we had better go to full
                                        mobilization. Speaking to the Secretary of the Treasury, the
                                        President said what you’ve got here is a leaky dike, and
                                        with leaky dikes it’s sometimes better to put a finger in
                                        than to let the whole structure be washed away.</p>
                                <pb facs="0985" n="953" xml:id="pg_953"/>
                                <p>But, said General <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName>,
                                        how about the alternative of making the French do it? To
                                        this both the President and Admiral <persName
                                                corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> replied, in
                                        effect, what else have we been doing all these years?</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> went on
                                        to speculate that if we could put one squadron of U.S.
                                        planes over Dien Bien Phu for as little as one afternoon, it
                                        might save the situation. Weren’t the stakes worth it? We
                                        were already in this thing in such a big way that it seemed
                                        foolish not to make the one small extra move which might be
                                        essential to success.</p>
                                <p>The President thought … [of ] a little group of fine and
                                        adventurous pilots. … Then, continued the President, we
                                        should give these pilots U.S. planes without insignia and
                                        let them go. That, said the President, was the right way to
                                        use the planes from the aircraft earlier, and this all could
                                        be done without involving us directly in the war, which he
                                        admitted would be a very dangerous thing. Admiral <persName
                                                corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> also believed
                                        that some such arrangement as this could be worked out.</p>
                                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> then
                                        inquired whether we proposed to give the French the extra
                                        planes for which they had asked as an emergency measure. He
                                        thought we could do at least this much for them.</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> replied
                                        to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>
                                        by pointing out that the obstacle in this situation was
                                        financial. To provide the French with these additional
                                        planes would cost more than the allocated funds.</p>
                                <p>The President turned to the Secretary of the Air Force, who sat
                                        behind him, and asked whether we would not be glad to get
                                        rid of some of these B–26’s. When Secretary
                                                <persName>Talbott</persName> replied in the
                                        affirmative, the President inquired whether we could not
                                        write down the cost of the B–26.</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> added
                                        that if we did provide the French with this additional
                                        emergency aid, we might use it as a lever to secure a more
                                        active part in the plan of campaign with General <persName
                                                corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName>.</p>
                                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cutler</persName> then asked
                                        the President what form the Council action on this item
                                        should take. The President summed it up by stating that in
                                        point of fact the French were at present unable to get out
                                        of Indochina, so the problem was to see what additional
                                        measures the United States might take to assist them.</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> responded
                                        to the President’s point by suggesting that one of the
                                        things that could be done would be to keep General <persName
                                                corresp="#p_OLGJ1">O’Daniel</persName> continuously
                                        in Indochina, and if necessary give him another star.</p>
                                <p>The President said that he felt this would be a fine move, and
                                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>
                                        thought that General <persName corresp="#p_OLGJ1"
                                                >O’Daniel</persName> should also be provided with
                                        greater flexibility in the delivery of matériel to the
                                        French, a point which the Vice President also thought of
                                        great importance. The <pb facs="0986" n="954"
                                                xml:id="pg_954"/> President and Admiral <persName
                                                corresp="#p_PAAW1">Radford</persName> also agreed
                                        that while we have provided military assistance in large
                                        amounts to the French in Indochina, we had been rather
                                        inflexible about certain specific items.</p>
                                <p>The President then suggested that after the responsible Council
                                        members had studied what additional measures could be
                                        undertaken to assist the French, there be a presentation
                                        before the National Security Council. The object was to get
                                        down to concrete proposals and measures.</p>
                                <p>The Vice President commented that one of the most disappointing
                                        features in Indochina was the failure of French propaganda
                                        to convince the people of Vietnam that they were on the road
                                        to independence. Our own <gloss target="#t_USIS1"
                                                >USIS</gloss> program in this area was also very
                                        weak. The Vice President wondered if it would not be worth
                                        while if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JCD1">C. D.
                                                Jackson</persName> were to look into the situation
                                        and see what could be done.</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">
                                        <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                                        <note n="5" xml:id="d499fn5">Points <hi rend="italic"
                                                  >a-d</hi> below constituted <gloss
                                                  target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1005.
                                                  (<gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss
                                                  target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files, lot 66 D 95,
                                                  “<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                                Actions”)</note>
                                        <list>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                                <item>Discussed the reference report on the subject
                                                  (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 177) and
                                                  deferred action until the next Council meeting,
                                                  pending the receipt of the views of the Joint
                                                  Chiefs of Staff thereon.</item>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                                <item>Noted the President’s directive that all
                                                  copies of the Special Annex to <gloss
                                                  target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 177 should be
                                                  recalled for destruction.</item>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                                <item>Agreed that Lieutenant General <persName
                                                  corresp="#p_OLGJ1">John Wilson O’Daniel</persName>
                                                  should be stationed continuously in Indochina,
                                                  under appropriate liaison arrangements and with
                                                  sufficient authority to expedite the flexible
                                                  provision of U.S. assistance to the French Union
                                                  forces.</item>
                                                <label>
                                                  <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                                <item>Requested the Department of Defense, in
                                                  collaboration with the Central Intelligence
                                                  Agency, urgently to study and report to the
                                                  Council all feasible further steps, short of the
                                                  overt use of U.S. forces in combat, which the
                                                  United States might take to assist in achieving
                                                  the success of the “<persName corresp="#p_LJ1"
                                                  >Laniel</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_NGH1"
                                                  >Navarre</persName>” Plan.</item>
                                        </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> The action in <hi rend="italic"
                                                >c</hi> above subsequently transmitted to the
                                        Secretary of Defense for appropriate implementation. The
                                        action in <hi rend="italic">d</hi> above subsequently
                                        transmitted to the Secretary of Defense and the Director of
                                        Central Intelligence for appropriate implementation.</p>
                                <p>. . . . . . . .</p>
                        </div>
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
