<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-01-08T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-01-08T01:00:00-05:00" n="5" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/1–852: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Heath</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-01-08T14:00:00+08:00">January 8, 1952—2
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1344. Repeated Paris 512, London 23, New Delhi 11. On Pres <persName corresp="#p_TVH1">Huu</persName>’s orders govt-owned news service
                        excised for obvious reasons from its bulletin today the following passage in
                            <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s<note n="1" xml:id="d5fn1"><persName corresp="#p_SR1">Robert Schuman</persName>,
                            French Foreign Minister.</note> exposé before <gloss target="#t_MRP1">MRP</gloss> meeting at Toulouse Jan 6: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“In Indochina our policy is a policy of peace. It is not preoccupied
                                by any spirit of imperialism or conquest. Without wishing to abandon
                                Fr interests in this country nor those who have placed confidence in
                                us, nor open the door to communism we do not refuse there either any
                                agreement which might be susceptible to bringing to an end the
                                dolorous conflict which for five years has torn this country apart.
                                If an armistice can be concluded under honorable conditions France
                                will not hesitate to make peace.</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>If <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s statement contained
                        additional passages on Indochina we wld appreciate pertinent text by cable.
                        We note this may be first occasion on which Fr <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> has invited political negotiations.</p>
                    <p>Local centers of neutralism and appeasement which had remained quiescent
                        through recent <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> parliamentary statements have
                        reacted very quickly to what they regard as <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s lead. For past several days local press has
                        carried series stories re Fr-Brit insistence on <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>
                        <hi rend="italic">détente</hi>, on linking Indochina to Korean negotiations
                        in over-all <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> “settlement” which wld admit
                            <gloss target="#t_ChiCommie1">Chi Commies</gloss> planning liquidate
                        Formosa, and bring peace in our time. Press has suggested <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> wld exert all his influence along
                        these <pb facs="0046" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/> lines and Stalin’s<note n="2" xml:id="d5fn2">Iosif Vissarionovich Stalin, President of the Council of
                            Ministers of the Soviet Union; Secretary General of the Central
                            Committee of the Communist Party.</note> reported willingness to meet
                        Big Three in Stockholm to discuss <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> solution
                        has had due attention along with Vishinsky’s<note n="3" xml:id="d5fn3">Andrey Yanuaryevich Vyshinsky, Soviet Foreign Minister.</note> proposal
                        to move Korean talks to UN.</p>
                    <p>If these Fr initiatives had been discussed with US we assume we wld have been
                        advised. If they have not they represent at least a portentious lack of
                        coordination. In Indochina the <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName>
                        series threatens the Vinh Yen program of psychological mobilization and may
                        work grave injury to <persName corresp="#p_DLDT1">De Lattre</persName>’s
                        patient attempts to build Vietnamese confidence and to convince the listless
                        and the careful that this is their war.</p>
                    <p>In these muddied waters the Indians have begun to fish. Our first news of
                            <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s declaration and our
                        first info that it had been censored came from an exalted Kamath, the Indian
                            <gloss target="#t_ConGen1">ConGen</gloss> here, who had heard of
                        statement on Indian broadcast early this morning and who had received its
                        cabled text few hours later. This surprising Indian forehandedness echoes
                        Indian UN del statement Jan 4 that India was certain <gloss target="#t_ChiCommie1">Chi Commies</gloss> would not invade “Fr
                        Indochina” unless Americans first attacked Manchuria or <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> mainland, and, as if in reply to
                        suggestions that Indochina conflict be “internationalized”, volunteered
                        opinion it was “normal practice” for Peking to send administrators to <gloss target="#t_VM1">VM</gloss> and train <gloss target="#t_VM1">VM</gloss>
                        units in <gloss target="#t_Chi1">Chi</gloss> terr. No doubt Kamath, whose
                        views on Indochina are as unchanging as <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName>’s<note n="4" xml:id="d5fn4"><persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru</persName>, Prime Minister
                            of India.</note> is busy on the wires to Delhi. We may soon be
                        confronted with Indian or Indian-backed proposal to mediate Indochina or to
                        submit Indochina war to UN with all the trappings of a cease-fire, a
                        plebiscite, or UN-sponsored, observed elections, coalition govt and the
                        other devices which wld only result in the surrender of Indochina to the
                            <gloss target="#t_ChiCommie1">Chi Commies</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>We assume Paris is ascertaining Fr intentions and anticipations re <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>’s latest gambit and that we shall
                        coordinate our responses to possible Asian attempts to produce Asian
                        Munich.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HDR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>