<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador at Saigon ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d574</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">574</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-02-21T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-02-21T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007242"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Defense budget</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recJwYAJf2vdRiALq" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039539"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Mobility</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recRywIrZWsI9yUJ7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-02-21T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-02-21T20:00:00-05:00" n="574"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d574">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.5/2–2254: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d574fn1">This telegram was transmitted in two parts.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-02-22T09:00:00+08:00"
                            >February 22, 1954—9 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1506. Eyes only <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_SGWB1">Smith</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_WCE1"
                        >Wilson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KRM1">Kyes</persName> and
                        Rand<note n="2" xml:id="d574fn2">
                        <persName>William M. Rand</persName>, Deputy Director of the Foreign
                        Operations Administration.</note> from <persName corresp="#p_SHE1"
                        >Stassen</persName>. At <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName>’s
                    request, accompanied by Ambassador <pb facs="1097" n="1065" xml:id="pg_1065"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName>, I had a two-hour conference with
                        <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName>—and <persName corresp="#p_DM1"
                        >DeJean</persName> at Dalat this morning February 21.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> and General <persName
                        corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> joined conference for the final
                    half-hour.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName> has been in Indochina two weeks and
                    intends to remain another week. There were a number of plus and minus factors
                    disclosed and I would characterize the total as encouraging but requiring
                    highest priority continuing attention and including some points of major danger
                    to objectives.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName> emphasized that there must be no
                    leak of what he told me as it would make more difficult his task.</p>
                <p>The following is a summary of major points: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Upon <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName>’s return to France
                            he will report to the Cabinet and subsequently, either through a policy
                            motion in the House during the first 10 days of March or through the
                            consideration of the defense budget beginning the middle of March the
                            issue of the Indochina war will be tested.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>He will make a strong case. We reviewed the many factors involved. The
                            difficulties of French public and parliamentary opinion will be very
                            great. He referred to Naegelen’s<note n="3" xml:id="d574fn3">
                                <persName>Marcel</persName>-<persName>Edmond Naegelen</persName>,
                                Socialist member of the French National Assembly.</note> recent
                            adverse address on the subject. It will be necessary to exert
                            extraordinary efforts of persuasion. A program of the way out over the
                            next two years involving increased commitments and efforts of the
                            Vietnamese Government, follow-through commitments of matériel and
                            finance from the US Government, and a see-it-through policy of the
                            French Government will be the trilateral essentials.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>French casualties in recent weeks have been severe, in their view,
                            including excessive casualties caused by a new plastic mine of Chinese
                            make which cannot be detected by present methods and which the Viet Minh
                            sow liberally in the immediate path of French Forces and French
                            vehicles. General <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1">Trapnell</persName> will
                            obtain samples for analysis by US technicians for countermeasures.
                            Presume we may have Korean experience with the same mine. This is high
                            priority.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The top Vietnam leadership is weak and <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                                Dai</persName> failed to come up to the Hanoi Delta area for an
                            agreed trip there with <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName>.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> has also broached an
                            unsound mass evacuation plan from the delta area. But the new Vietnam
                            Cabinet has a number of members with intelligence and spark and drive
                            including the Minister of Defense and this is a real asset.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName> and the French here are now
                            convinced that they can build a real Vietnam Army and their views on
                            this have changed in the past six months from experience. The
                            difficulties are still great but there is now a confidence that an
                            effective fighting force of Vietnam can and will be built.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> is completely confident
                            of his position for the remainder of this fighting season in his
                            principal installations including Dien Bien Phu and the delta and Luang
                            Prabang. Dien Bien Phu is a veritable jungle Verdun which he hopes will
                            be attacked as it will <pb facs="1098" n="1066" xml:id="pg_1066"/>
                            result in terrific casualties to the Viet Minh and will not fall. His
                            concentration now is on the French-Vietnam offensive to start in
                            October.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>In this respect <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName> speak of long delays in
                            essential US equipment. It would appear to me that US procedures have
                            not been adapted to the fact of war and that the back-up of the war
                            should be placed in <gloss target="#t_CinC1">CINC</gloss> Far East who
                            has on hand practically everything needed and could supply it promptly
                            with subsequent payment by <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> funds
                            and subsequent replacement to his stocks from the States. The delays of
                            requisitioning to Washington, or San Francisco, or Pearl when the
                            equipment is all out here in the Japan, Okinawa, Korea area cannot be
                            accepted for the offensive war contemplated by <persName
                                corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> beginning in October.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>The Vietnam Government needs further economic and technical assistance
                            especially in the care of the displaced villagers and urgently in the
                            case of those who desert or flee from the Viet Minh side of war who then
                            need resettlement as a matter of top importance in the winning of the
                            support of the people. I concur in this view and suggest that a fund of
                            $7,000,000 for this purpose be transferred from general reserve and be
                            placed at Director <persName>McReynolds</persName>’ call for these
                            purposes without detailed Washington advance approval of projects. The
                            fact of war should also be recognized in <gloss target="#t_FOA1"
                                >FOA</gloss> Washington and top priority on recruitments of
                            necessary technicians for this new and inexperienced government should
                            be given.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> contemplates a change in
                            his <gloss target="#t_TO1">TO</gloss> for greater mobility and fire
                            power. He wants to increase the automatic arms of his battalions from 45
                            to 65. Long rifles are too slow and useless in the jungle where enemy
                            fire opens up at 10 meters distance. His special request now is for
                            light armor, amphibious light armor, light observation planes and a new
                            request which he will soon make for more automatic arms are considered
                            by <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName> to be of top
                            importance.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>They urgently wish to expand the counter-guerrilla effort and for
                            these and other mobility purposes request early action on their
                            helicopter requests and will want by September 1 an American ground crew
                            of 80 to help initial maintenance and to train their technicians.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Washington statements at high level if first coordinated precisely
                            with Paris which would express attitude of confidence in French and
                            back-up of their requests for material, and would note the affection for
                            France of millions of loyal Vietnamese would be helpful. Washington’s
                            statements can be harmful in Paris if the wrong things are said or the
                            right things in the wrong way.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName> anticipates agreement on
                            final negotiations on Vietnam independence to take place in Paris
                            beginning early March and no serious obstacle to satisfactory
                            completion.</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>Relations of France with Cambodia are improved and internal security
                            in Cambodia is good with only 8,000 Viet Minh remaining in remote areas
                            and the recent surrender of two bands of 1,000 each.</item>
                        <label>14.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pleven</persName> understands that
                            qualification of subject to Congressional approval will apply to all
                            Executive Branch commitments for future follow-through and this is not
                            an obstacle as he has confidence in President <persName
                                corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s effective
                            leadership.</item>
                        <pb facs="1099" n="1067" xml:id="pg_1067"/>
                        <label>15.</label>
                        <item>He further explained that both time and political psychology made it
                            impossible for him to return to Paris via Washington. He hoped I would
                            report his discussion with a strong cautionary note against leaks to the
                            press and that I would convey the background thoroughly on my return. My
                            response was one of broad encouragement, pledge of prompt report to
                            Washington, personal belief that essential action for expediting
                            deliveries and for future follow-through in matériel and finance would
                            be forthcoming, and confidence that his incisive informed leadership
                            would carry this significant case in Paris and that the break-through to
                            a clear victory next year was in the making with deep value for France
                            and the free world.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>My comment now to Washington is limited to these points: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>There is no real danger in Indochina of major reverse during this
                            fighting season.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Top priority is the political issue in March in Paris.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Second priority is getting our matériel back-up reorganized in the Far
                            East to prepare for an offensive in October.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Third priority is expanded high caliber technical assistance to the
                            new government of Vietnam particularly for those ministers who show
                            spark and spirit and in mass methods of economic action which will win
                            the Vietnam people.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>All Washington statements on the Indochina war should be cleared in
                            Paris especially between now and the parliamentary test.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName> has read this message and
                    may send supplementary reactions. General <persName corresp="#p_TMTJH1"
                        >Trapnell</persName> has read the military portions and Director
                        <persName>McReynolds</persName> the economic and technical portions.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
