<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-04-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="723" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d723">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/4–854</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy Assistant
                            Secretary of State for European Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BJCH1"><hi rend="italic">Bonbright</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>eyes
                            only</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-04-08">April 8,
                                1954</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>Subject:</head>
                        <item>Indochina</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>Participants:</head>
                        <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Henri Bonnet</persName>, the French
                            Ambassador</item>
                        <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MD1">MacArthur</persName></item>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJCH1">Bonbright</persName></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> came to see the Secretary at
                        10 this morning to give the preliminary reaction of his government to our
                        proposal for united action in Indochina. The Ambassador began by stating
                        that he feared the Secretary would not regard the first answer from Paris as
                        being completely satisfactory. M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> wished the Secretary to know that he was very happy
                        with this indication of increased solidarity between the United States and
                        France in connection with a struggle which the French have been carrying on
                        for over seven years. It was most encouraging to the French Government to
                        know of our desire to be of even further help and the French Government in
                        return wished us to know that they have no intention of delivering Indochina
                        to the “Bolsheviks”.</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador stated that our proposal had been debated in the Cabinet where
                        it was regarded as an initiative of very great importance but one which
                        required further study. The French view is that there is time for this
                        further study and the immediate problem is the outcome of the battle for
                        Dien Bien Phu. He went on to say that no French government could neglect
                        even the slightest chance for bringing about peace in Indochina and it was
                        felt that nothing should be done which would jeopardize in advance the
                        chances of obtaining peace at Geneva. M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> had talked along this line to the Secretary at
                        Berlin and it was their present belief that the formation of a powerful
                        coalition would give the impression to China and the world that we do not
                        want peace. They believed that “an honest warning” was a good thing but in
                        their view this is what the Secretary had done in his talks with <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName><note n="1" xml:id="d723fn1">Reference is to discussions during the Berlin Conference.</note> and in
                        his speech of March 29. Before going <pb facs="1323" n="1291" xml:id="pg_1291"/> further than that there is time to study various
                        aspects of our proposal, including the important ramifications which it
                        might have for peace in the Pacific.</p>
                    <p>M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> then referred to reports out
                        of London which indicated that there was reluctance on the part of the
                        British Government. He also thought there would be reluctance in Thailand
                        and the Philippines to join a coalition against Communism.</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador then repeated that in the view of the French Government our
                        proposal should be considered in connection with a possible second step in
                        the event that it appears that things are not going well at Geneva. In the
                        meantime, we could study a number of factors in our proposal, including what
                        US forces would be involved and what would be the commitments of the other
                        parties. This could be studied by the Far East staff agency. Other questions
                        to be answered were the nature of the mutual guarantees and how and when the
                        coalition would go into action. He said it was M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>’s hope to discuss some of these questions with the
                        Secretary in Paris at the time of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            meeting.<note n="2" xml:id="d723fn2">The North Atlantic Council was
                            scheduled to meet at Paris on Apr. 23.</note></p>
                    <p>The Secretary then interposed to inform the Ambassador that there was a new
                        development since last night. The British Government had asked the Secretary
                        to come over right away to discuss the problem and the Secretary planned to
                        be in London on Monday.<note n="3" xml:id="d723fn3">Apr. 12.</note> He had
                        sent word to M. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> last night
                        that we did not wish to talk just in London and that he would be glad to
                        proceed on to Paris if that were convenient. He added that the French
                        reaction had been to recommend this but that for internal reasons the French
                        Government had wished to keep the visit quiet for a day or two in order to
                        avoid a debate in the Assembly prior to the Easter recess.<note n="4" xml:id="d723fn4">In telegram 3778 from Paris, Apr. 8, received in
                            Washington at 7:44 a.m., Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> reported that he had conveyed to Foreign Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> the message from
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> regarding the
                            desire of the latter to visit Paris for talks on Apr. 14 (see telegram
                            3535 to Paris, Apr. 7, <ref target="#pg_1286">p. 1286</ref>). <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> expressed agreement, but asked
                            that the announcement of the visit be withheld until the evening of Apr.
                            10, Paris time. (751G.00/4–854)</note> With regard to this point M.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> pointed out that he had
                        already received press reports of press leaks out of London to the effect
                        that the Secretary is leaving immediately for London and Paris on his own
                        initiative because his proposal had not been accepted. (Later in the
                        conversation, in response to a direct inquiry from the Ambassador concerning
                        the initiative for the visit the Secretary explained that in the course of
                        the exchange of views with the British on the proposal, we had indicated
                        that if further clarification were needed and it would be useful, we would
                        be glad to send someone to London and Paris. The British had replied that
                        they would be glad to have the Secretary come over and he had agreed to do
                        so.)</p>
                    <pb facs="1324" n="1292" xml:id="pg_1292"/>
                    <p>The Secretary then stated that the fallacy in the French attitude is that the
                        French Government apparently thinks that in order to get peace in Indochina
                        we must go to Geneva in a weak position and that if we go there in a strong
                        position we won’t get peace. In other words, they are afraid that the
                        Chinese won’t like it. M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName>
                        stated that he could not agree with this interpretation as he had indicated
                        before that the French Government regarded the Secretary’s public statement
                        of March 29 as good. M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName>
                        regretted that the French reply was disappointing to the Secretary but his
                        government believed that if we went too far the Geneva Conference would be a
                        farce. The Secretary replied that he would not put it that he was
                        disappointed. Our belief was that the dangers to South East Asia will not be
                        met without unity of will and unity of action. If we meet the threat, one by
                        one all will be lost. Indochina will go, Thailand will go, Malaya will go,
                        or will be held only by very costly operations. Indonesia will almost surely
                        be lost. The dangers to Australia and New Zealand will be greatly increased.
                        He pointed out again that the danger was further from us and if others would
                        not go along with us, we would know where we stood. If it became necessary
                        for the US to base its defenses on the shores of this country—all right. The
                        French were apparently afraid if we all stood together. But it was “crazy”
                        to think that the US would be drawn into a war without any political
                        prearrangements of any kind or description in order to save one outpost such
                        as Dien Bien Phu and when we were not attacked and were without Allies. He
                        pointed out that we did not have an alliance with France in regard to
                        Indochina. M. <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bonnet</persName> concluded by
                        saying that he knew our country and Congress well enough to know our
                        position in this regard.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>