<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in India ( (Allen) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d800</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">800</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-04-25T06:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-04-25T06:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic reform</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-04-25T06:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-04-25T06:30:00-05:00" n="800"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d800">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G. 00/4–2554: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_AGV1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Allen</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-04-25T17:00:00+05:30"
                            >April 25, 1954—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 7 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1596. Repeated London 298 Geneva 7. I had hours talk with Prime Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> yesterday April 24 following
                    his statement in House of People on Indo-China.<note n="1" xml:id="d800fn1">For
                        the proposals made by Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1"
                            >Nehru</persName> in the course of an address before the Lower House of
                        the Indian Parliament on Apr. 24, see Folliot, ed., <hi rend="italic"
                            >Documents on International Affairs, 1954</hi>, pp. 123–124.</note>
                    Although purpose my visit was to discuss US economic aid to India prior to my
                    departure for Washington, and his for Ceylon, he had Indo-China chiefly in mind
                    and went to considerable length to explain his statement which included
                    declaration that fighting there is in origin and essence “a move of resistance
                    to colonialism”. He said his experience in fighting Communist Party in India had
                    shown him conclusively that he could appeal to voters only by showing that CIP
                        [<hi rend="italic">CPI</hi>] was controlled from outside India and therefore
                    unpatriotic. Whenever Communists were able to attach themselves to a
                    nationalistic issue, as they had succeeded in doing in Indo-China, they carried
                    public with them. Speaking of Indian electorate he said that whereas in Britain
                    and perhaps United States, eighty percent of voters were definitely committed to
                    one party, with twenty percent uncommitted and therefore decisive in swinging
                    elections, in India and perhaps other South Asian countries, percentages were
                    reversed. He had to keep eighty percent fluid sector constantly in mind, to
                    convince it that he was dedicated to Nationalism and not tool of western
                    colonialism as his Communist opponents alleged. Hence his statement on
                    Indo-China would have carried no conviction <pb facs="1439" n="1407"
                        xml:id="pg_1407"/> in India and South Asia if he had not come out solidly on
                    behalf of independence and had not recognized unequivocably that Viet Minh were
                    on Nationalist side. He did not want Peking to dominate Indo–China any more than
                    for Paris to do so. He believed Indochinese felt same way and that <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi-Minh</persName> had been forced reluctantly to lean
                    on Chinese help just as Western Powers had been glad to have <gloss
                        target="#t_Commies1">Commie</gloss> help in fighting Hitler. He reviewed at
                    some length Congress Party refusal to associate with Indian Communists during
                    post war because CPI under orders from Moscow did not support immediate
                    independence for India. He remarked with smile: “you were hand in glove with
                        <gloss target="#t_Commies1">Commies</gloss> when I despised them as
                    traitors”.</p>
                <p>I referred ‘to press reports that French and Vietnamese were about to sign
                    agreement in Paris guaranteeing full independence for Viet Nam and asked
                        <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> whether he thought this would
                    enable Viet Nam to regain Nationalist support. He said he thought it might, but
                    pointed out that part of revolutionary movement in South Asia was social and
                    economic as well as political. For example, even though French might grant full
                    independence to Viet Nam, <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>’s
                    Government would not achieve great popular support unless it also convinced
                    people it would achieve social and economic reform.</p>
                <p>Krishna Menon, who drafted <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName>’s
                    statement on Indo-China, says first half was for domestic and South Asian
                    consumption and that Western Powers need concern themselves only with second
                    half. He has drawn attention of United Kingdom High Commissioner to fact that
                    statement makes no attack on Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                        >Dulles</persName>’ concept of collective security in southeast Asia, nor
                    does it claim that security of this area should be left to nations of area. In
                    fact it recognizes that collective security is required to maintain peace. Only
                    difference between Indian proposal and American, he says, is that under
                        <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> concept, China and Russia
                    should join with US and UK in guaranteeing nonintervention. This would result,
                    he believes, in more or less neutralizing Indo-China and create buffer zone to
                    prevent any further Chinese expansion towards South Asia and India. Krishna
                    Menon claims he able to guide <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName>
                    statement in this channel only because of Indian membership in Commonwealth. He
                    pointed this out to UK <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> as dramatic proof
                    of value of Commonwealth connection.</p>
                <p>During talk with <persName>Pillai</persName> yesterday (April 24) latter told me
                    Krishna Menon was quite pleased with himself over fact that he had drawn factual
                    parts of statement on Indo-China “straight out of Judd report”.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d800fn2">See <ref target="#d464fn1">footnote 1, p. 892</ref>.</note>
                    Final sentence, quoting Pope Pius plea for peace, was further evidence of
                    Menon’s “fine Italian hand”.</p>
                <p>I told <persName>Pillai</persName> obvious weakness of statement was that its
                    recommendations, if accepted, would result in control of Indo-China by <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi-Minh</persName>, <pb facs="1440" n="1408"
                        xml:id="pg_1408"/> whose attachment and obligation to Peking were too close
                    to be broken. I pointed out that stopping of aggression in Korea, at cost of
                    severe fighting and casualties, had nevertheless made Japan much safer from
                        <gloss target="#t_Commies1">Commie</gloss> expansion than it would be if
                        <gloss target="#t_Commies1">Commies</gloss> controlled Korean Peninsula.
                    Similarly, hard fighting was necessary to give <gloss target="#t_Commies1"
                        >Commies</gloss> bloody nose in Indo-China in order to protect South Asia
                    and India. <persName>Pillai</persName> agreed but said <persName
                        corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> hoped both sides had let sufficient blood
                    in Indochina to make them ready for cease-fire. If psychological moment had
                    arrived, as it had in Korea last year, proposal “just might provide the out both
                    sides are looking for”.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGV1" type="from">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Allen</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
