<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador at Saigon ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-07-30T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-07-30T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-30T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-30T04:00:00-05:00" n="99"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d99">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.11/7–3052: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d99fn1">This telegram was transmitted in two parts.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-30T17:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 30, 1952—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>248. Rptd info Paris 58. From info obtained from <persName corresp="#p_NHT1"
                        >Huu</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> and other
                    sources, I am finally able to estimate cost of <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName> to Viet budget (as yet unpublished) and to Viet people.</p>
                <p>Under the govt of <persName>Nguyen Phan Long</persName>,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d99fn2">Premier of Vietnam, January-May 1950.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> recd from govt 4 million piasters
                    monthly or roughly, at par of exchange, $200,000 a month. After <persName
                        corresp="#p_NHT1">Huu</persName> became <gloss target="#t_PriMin1"
                        >PriMin</gloss>, he raised <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>‘s
                    allowance to <pb facs="0260" n="228" xml:id="pg_228"/> 7 million piasters per
                    month ($350,000). According to Phan Long, <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName> also receives from Binh Xuyen organization a “gratification”
                    of from 2–2½ million piasters per month out of profits for gambling in
                    Saigon-Cholon for which Binh Xuyen now hold the concession. Binh Xuyen are also
                    reported to have paid a similar monthly “gratification” to <gloss
                        target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_TVH1">Huu</persName>. Govt of South Viet receives fixed
                    percentage of these gambling profits, govt’s share amounting to around 200
                    million piasters (roughly $10 million) per annum. Binh Xuyen is reported to
                    receive other certain revenues since until fairly recently it controlled and
                    maintained order in Cholon by Fr permission. They were ousted from their
                    overlordship of Cholon in November 1951 by Fr and Viet mil forces working
                    together. Binh Xuyen are still understood, however, to receive some protection
                    money from establishments in Cholon altho their mil and police duties are now
                    limited to guarding the waterways and outskirts of Cholon. For latter service
                    they are paid by Fr and Viet Treasuries.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> is, therefore, apparently
                    receiving from govt and Xuyen together from 110–120 million piasters a year
                    (roughly $6 million).</p>
                <p>In 1951, <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> tells me <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> remitted abroad total of 800 million
                    francs equivalent to 47 million piasters or roughly $2,350,000. An unknown but
                    presumably relatively small portion these transfers went to upkeep of Empress
                    and children who live well but with no imperial pomp in Cannes. On occasion,
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> helps out Prince <persName
                        corresp="#p_BL1">Buu Loc</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d99fn3">Representative of Bao Dal in Paris.</note> for
                    extraordinary entertainment or propaganda expenses in Paris but I believe the
                    amount of such assistance is very small. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName> bought an old four-motor Liberator plane a few months ago but
                    probably paid less than $200,000 for it. The bulk of <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                        >Bao Dai</persName>‘s transfers are understood to have gone to Fr and Swiss
                    banks, to real estate purchases and investments in France and Morocco. I have no
                    info as to size of his bank accounts and investments but <persName
                        corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> tells me that <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>, who was practically penniless in Hong
                    Kong before 1949, now has respectable fortune abroad. I assume it now totals
                    several million dollars.</p>
                <p>If he transfers abroad something approaching 50 million piasters a year, he still
                    has from his revenues some 60–70 million piasters to spend in Vietnam. His
                    allowance of 7 million piasters from Viet Treas is not given as salary according
                    to <persName corresp="#p_NHT1">Huu</persName> but to cover his “social” and
                    charitable program. While he is known to give fin assistance to his friends and
                    members of imperial clan such expenditures according to <persName
                        corresp="#p_NHT1">Huu</persName>, are not an important item. <persName
                        corresp="#p_NHT1">Huu</persName> claims that in 1951 Viet Govt made
                    contribution from govt funds to enable Queen Mother to live on more “adequate”
                    basis at Hue. There is little staff in old Imperial Palace at Hue which was
                    partially destroyed.</p>
                <pb facs="0261" n="229" xml:id="pg_229"/>
                <p>There are only a few servants in Hanoi Palace. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName>‘s residence at Dalat is smaller than thousands of homes in
                    New York area altho it does have extensive stables and an indoor tennis court.
                    At Ban Me Thuot he lives in modest cottage altho he has recently built guest
                    house and office quarters there for imperial cab. These last items may have come
                    out of his own pocket but it is doubted they have cost more than two or three
                    million piasters ($100 to 150 thousand). <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName> has one hunting lodge not far from Ban Me Thuot. We have no
                    reports of large charitable donations by <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName>. He gave Catholic Bishops in north, once he told me, out of
                    his own pocket some two or three million piasters. On one occasion <persName
                        corresp="#p_PVG1">Giao</persName>, then Gov of Central Vietnam showed
                    Counselor <persName corresp="#p_GEA1">Gullion</persName> a check for six million
                    piasters which he had received from <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName> presumably for extraordinary expenses in connection with
                    admin in Annam. Tho upkeep of <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>‘s
                    four planes is undoubtedly expensive but even allowing for charitable and
                    quasi-governmental grants which we do not know about it is difficult for me to
                    see how he is spending locally from 60 to 70 million piasters which are
                    apparently available to him after banking abroad the better part of 50 million
                    piasters. He receives a grant from govt for salaries and expenses of imperial
                    cab and two million piasters month for admin of crown lands in southern
                    plateau.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> tells me during 1951 he
                    remonstrated with <persName corresp="#p_DLDT1">De Lattre</persName> over the
                    amounts of monetary transfers <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> was
                    allowed to make. <persName corresp="#p_DLDT1">De Lattre</persName> replied that
                    after all <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> was chief of state and
                    altho the amounts were excessive he did not think Fr cld object. It now appears
                    that the seven million piasters ($350,000) transfer which <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> requested for his forthcoming trip to
                    France (see <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 61, July 8)<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d99fn4">Not printed.</note> was not to be from his own funds but was
                    a demand on <persName corresp="#p_T1">Tam</persName> for an extraordinary travel
                    grant over and above his regular stipend of seven million piasters. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> says he thinks that <persName
                        corresp="#p_T1">Tam</persName> cut down the amount to six million piasters
                    but neither <persName corresp="#p_T1">Tam</persName> nor Fr are willing to
                    refuse transfer or travel grant. The only action taken by Fr was to refuse an
                    additional request for transfer of one million piasters made by four members of
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>‘s entourage who will accompany
                    him to France.</p>
                <p>This was turned down flat with the suggestion that they appeal to His
                    Majesty.</p>
                <p>His Majesty’s 84 million piasters a year from Viet treas approaches five percent
                    of central govt receipts but if we add the “gratification” from the Binh Xuyen
                    as income which might otherwise go into govt treasury it approaches about six
                    percent of natl receipts. <persName corresp="#p_T1">Tam</persName> is having
                    difficulties in finding 20 million piasters for initial capital of his <pb
                        facs="0262" n="230" xml:id="pg_230"/> agrarian reform land bank. Three
                    months of His Majesty’s reg allowance from the trees wld finance this
                    project.</p>
                <p>To my inquiry as to what action might be taken to persuade <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> to reduce his expenditures—and transfers
                    abroad—to a level seemly to circumstance that Vietnam was at war, bankrupt and
                    maintained essentially only thru the mil and finan sacrifices of France and US
                        <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> cld only suggest that I
                    remonstrate with <persName corresp="#p_NEA1">Nguyen De</persName>, chief of
                    imperial cabinet.</p>
                <p>This I intend doing and wld welcome the Dept’s suggestions or instructions.</p>
                <p>Apparently <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> fears that if he
                    remonstrates <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> will threaten to
                    abdicate since he now has sufficient fortune to live comfortably abroad.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LJ2">Letourneau</persName> said to me in this
                    connection the “<persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> solution” was the
                    only one but qualified the statement by adding “for time being” and remarking
                    that if the monarchy fell it wld be <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName>‘s own fault. Disclosure of <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName>‘s stipend and investments abroad wld have a critical effect
                    on prestige of monarchy and regime.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
