<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-09-01T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-09-01T01:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-09-01T01:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-09-01T01:00:00-05:00" n="258"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01 Inner Mongolia/78: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-09-01T14:00:00+08:00"
                            >September 1, 1936—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received September 1—11:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>429. Reference Embassy’s 427, September 1, noon.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <item>Information has been obtained with regard to conditions in Inner Mongolia
                        in Chahar and eastern Suiyuan under Japanese control from two
                        Mongol-speaking foreigners who have just returned from that area after a 3
                        months’ and 1 month’s visit respectively. <pb facs="0373" n="278"
                            xml:id="pg_278"/> Their information, which is contained in paragraph 2,
                        is not conflicting and it substantiates information submitted by the Embassy
                        in previous telegrams.</item>
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <item>There are apparently not Japanese troops in the area in question, but
                        there are Japanese officers and some thousands of Manchukuo and Mongol
                        forces. The Mongols do the bidding of the Japanese only and admit their fear
                        of the Japanese and because Prince Teh is heavily in debt to them as the
                        result of purchases of military supplies. Chinese renegades and bandits,
                        together with some Mongols of similar character, continue to gather in the
                        vicinity of Shangtu in the extreme west of Chahar northeast of Pingtichuan
                        and are allegedly and presumably receiving arms and money from Japan.</item>
                    <label>(3)</label>
                    <item>An American resident of Suiyuan states that residents of Suiyuan are
                        apprehensive of the allegedly impending westward movement of the
                        above-mentioned elements and that definite preparations are being
                        pushed.</item>
                    <label>(4)</label>
                    <item>The attitude of Fu Tso Yi, however, is not known. The Chief of Staff of
                        the Kwantung army visited Fu at Kueihwa on August 25 and 26. The purpose and
                        outcome of the visit are not known. Itagaki also visited Yin Ju Keng but did
                        not see Sung Che Yuan. His visit to Yin has aroused speculation in
                        connection with the Japanese Ambassador’s alleged statement to the Chinese
                        press that East Hopei and North Chahar should be united. By mail to
                        Tokyo.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
