<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-09-19T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-09-19T06:00:00-05:00" n="283" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d283">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/8157: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-09-19T19:00:00+08:00">September 19, 1936—7
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received September 19—5:29 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>455. 1. Japanese authorities have stated to the press that as their
                            troops stationed at Fengtai were returning from maneuvers last night
                            about 6 o’clock the Chinese sentry in front of the Chinese barracks made
                            an insulting remark or gesture to one of the Japanese officers
                            commanding the troops. An altercation immediately ensued and the Chinese
                            barracks which are situated near the railroad station and house 120
                            troops or 1 company of the 37th Division of the 29th Army and constitute
                            all of the Chinese troops stationed in Fengtai itself were kept under
                            siege without shooting during the night and early morning. Meanwhile
                            negotiations were carried on between Chinese and Japanese authorities
                            and according to good authority the following agreement was reached at
                            10 this morning when the siege was raised: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>A public apology before the troops of both countries to
                                    Colonel Mutaguchi of the Japanese Embassy Guard by the Chinese
                                    general in command.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The immediate withdrawal of all Chinese troops in Fengtai to a
                                    point 2 miles south of railroad.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The eventual withdrawal of all Chinese troops in Fengtai
                                    region to Nanyuan or Hsiyuan.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Reliable American informants say the first two requirements being carried
                            out this week. They were informed by Chinese officers on the spot that
                            they were unable to resist the Japanese in view of General Sung Che
                            Yuan’s standing instructions that they were not to fight in any
                            event.</p>
                        <p>2. According to the press, precautions were taken throughout China
                            yesterday to avoid unfortunate incidents on the fifth anniversary of the
                            Mukden incident. No such incidents have been reported.</p>
                        <p>By mail to Tokyo.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>