<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-01-31T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-01-31T08:00:00-05:00" n="32" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">761.9315 Manchuria/35: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-01-31T16:00:00+03:00">January 31, 1936—4
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received January 31—2:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>39. The usual emissary of the Kremlin who in past conversations has been
                            in the habit of minimizing the importance of Soviet-Japanese dissensions
                            in the Far East stated to me yesterday substantially as follows:</p>
                        <p>The feeling which had hitherto prevailed in the Soviet Union that Japan
                            would be too deeply occupied with completing its conquest of North China
                            to attempt any aggressive action against the Soviet Union in the near
                            future was being replaced with an uneasy feeling that on [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] the outbreak of a Japanese-Soviet conflict
                            in the spring or summer of the present year was quite within the realms
                            of possibility. The desertion into Soviet territory on January 29th (as
                            reported in the <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> of January 30th) of a
                            whole company of Manchurian soldiers, together with a Manchurian
                            lieutenant and several non-commissioned officers, was the very type of
                            an incident which the Soviet Government feared might serve the Japanese
                            as a pretext for opening of hostilities. It seemed that the company
                            after having killed its Japanese officers fled into the Soviet Union
                            with a considerable amount of military equipment. It was disarmed and
                            sent into the interior for internment. The Soviet Government was
                            concerned lest a number of such incidents might result in insistence on
                            the part of the Japanese Government that the deserters be extradited and
                            charges that the disturbances were the result of the activities of the
                            Comintern.</p>
                        <p>The anxiety of the Soviet governmental circles was sharpened by the fact
                            that they were inclined to believe reports recently published to the
                            effect that Germany and Japan had entered into an alliance directed
                            against “the activities of the Comintern”. They feared that if Japan
                            should launch an attack under the pretext that it was crusading against
                            the Comintern this alliance might serve as a basis for a simultaneous
                            German attack from the West. They also felt that it was possible that
                            influential groups in other countries which otherwise would have no
                            sympathy for Japanese or German aggression might be inclined because of
                            their dread of the spread of Communism [to support such attacks.]</p>
                        <p>The Soviet Government believed that of all the great powers Great Britain
                            was in the best position to exercise restraint upon Germany. Undoubtedly
                                Litvinov<note n="56" xml:id="d32fn56">Soviet Commissar for Foreign
                                Affairs.</note> while in London would discuss the matter with the
                            British Government.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>