<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-12-21T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-12-21T04:00:00-05:00" n="441" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d441">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/13808: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lockhart</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-12-21T17:00:00+08:00">December 21, 1936—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received December 21—11:35 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>629. 1. The Shensi revolt has had the effect, perhaps temporarily only,
                            of suspending the agitation of students at Peiping, although it is
                            understood that rather pronounced differences have arisen among them on
                            the question of the advisability of despatching a punitive expedition to
                            Shensi. Although professing to believe that a more aggressive policy
                            towards Japan is needed, the sympathy of the students on the whole
                            appears to be with Chiang Kai-shek notwithstanding the huge
                            demonstration staged at Peiping on December 12 (see Embassy’s No. 604,
                            December 13, 1 p.m.)</p>
                        <p>2. There are signs that Yen Hsi Shan may emerge from the present trouble
                            with increased power and prestige. If Chiang Hsueh-liang is finally
                            ousted from authority there would seem to be a good prospect for the
                            expansion of Yen’s authority since it is believed that he might be
                            satisfactory to both factions if a drastic reorganization of the
                            military establishment in the northwest area should become necessary as
                            now seems inevitable. The defection of Yu Hsueh Chung from Lan-chow,
                            reports of which are persistently reported but not yet confirmed, are
                            most disturbing as he has long been one of Chiang Kai-shek’s most
                            steadfast adherents.</p>
                        <p>3. Reports, apparently well-founded, continue to circulate that
                            defections from the “irregulars” in Suiyuan to the Government side are
                            occurring almost daily.</p>
                        <p>By mail to Tokyo.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lockhart</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>