<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d460</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">460</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-01-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recdTuobyjHNvXKhT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011601"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bankruptcy</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="receNc7LQFkxnPn2F" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                    <term ref="rec7wEECiiCfq0TDz" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123713"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Smuggling</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recmU3mkCMXw0nKe9" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Foreign nationals</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-01-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="460"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d460">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/13989</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 975</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-01-12">January 12,
                            1937</date>.<lb/>[Received February 20, 1937.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Embassy’s
                    despatch No. 552 of July 3, 1936,<note n="20a" xml:id="d460fn20a">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_231">p. 231</ref>.</note>
                    reviewing the political, military, economic, and financial developments in China
                    during the first six months of 1936, and to submit a similar review of the last
                    six months of the year just ended.</p>
                <p>Whereas the outstanding developments during the first half of 1936 increased the
                    precariousness of China’s position, the significant events of the second half,
                    in their larger aspects, have had the opposite effect. The following factors
                    have definitely tended to unify and strengthen the Republic and even to cause
                    the Japanese, at least temporarily, to adopt a decidedly less aggressive policy
                    towards China: the <hi rend="italic">dénouement</hi> of the Southwestern crisis
                    whereby recalcitrant Kwangtung and Kwangsi Provinces were taken into the Central
                    Government’s fold and the scope of Chiang Kai-shek’s authority accordingly
                    widened; the abortive attack on Suiyuan by Japanese directed and supported
                    Mongol “irregulars” under the leadership of General Li Shou-hsin, the bandit
                    Wang Ying, and Prince Teh, which brought practically the entire nation
                    enthusiastically to the support of the Suiyuan defenders and evoked an amazing
                    manifestation of nationalism; and the outcome of the detention at Sian of Chiang
                    Kai-shek by Chang Hsueh-liang from December 12 to December 25 which fostered
                    another spontaneous outburst of nationalism throughout the country and caused
                    universal rejoicing when the Generalissimo was released on Christmas day. Each
                    of these crises at their inception gave promise of disastrous results for the
                    progress of China; in the end each in turn, with the possible exception of the
                    aftermath from the Sian affair, proved a political asset to the country and an
                    enhancement of the power of Chiang Kai-shek.</p>
                <p>There continued to exist during the first days of July the pessimism which had
                    deepened during the last days of June because of the fear that the difficulties
                    between Nanking and the Southwest, whose primary purpose was to overthrow the
                    Generalissimo and perhaps, secondarily, to wage war against Japan, could not be
                    settled without resort to civil war. If the rebellion could not be quashed there
                    was the possibility of a complete breakdown in authority with attendant <pb
                        facs="0549" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/> political impairment of Nanking’s
                    authority and economic bankruptcy and consequent encouragement to Japan for
                    further aggression. However, at the Second Plenary Session of the Fifth Central
                    Executive Committee of the Kuomintang (July 10 to 14), which had been called in
                    an endeavor to place the Southwestern leaders in the position of traitors if
                    they should disobey the Session’s mandates and to open the way for conciliation,
                    decisions were made which constituted a decided political victory for Chiang
                    Kai-shek. The Executive Committee abolished the legality of the semi-independent
                    political organs in the Southwest and removed General Ch’en Chi-t’ang from his
                    position. They offered the Southwestern leaders a means of obtaining absolution
                    by cooperating with the Central Government. The decisions made also confirmed
                    the Generalissimo’s policy toward Japan and enabled him to continue to avoid
                    taking an open and definitive stand regarding armed resistance to Japanese
                    aggression and interference in political affairs in China. General Chiang,
                    through his skill in political maneuvering and the threat of military action,
                    succeeded in bringing Kwangtung under his control.</p>
                <p>During July and August General Chiang was unable to liquidate the Kwangsi
                    situation. Negotiations and military preparations went on simultaneously. During
                    the first half of September, however, after protracted negotiations an agreement
                    was reached whereby Kwangsi also came under the control of the Central
                    Government. The Southwestern rebellion was thus ended, leaving the country more
                    completely unified than it had been at any time since the establishment of the
                    Nanking Government.</p>
                <p>The threat against Suiyuan, although existent for some time, was late in
                    materializing. The situation in Northern Chahar, where General Sung Che-yuan
                    appeared reluctant to interfere, remained obscure even throughout October, but
                    there seemed little doubt that “pro-Manchukuo” Mongol and bandit forces based on
                    Shangtu, Changpei, Pailingmiao and Chapsur were continuing preparations for an
                    attack on East Suiyuan, in which preparations Japanese planes and armaments
                    formed a part. General Fu Tso-yi, Chairman of the Suiyuan Provincial Government,
                    had been endeavoring for many months to perfect the defense of his Province. In
                    October Central Government troops were despatched to his support. Hostilities
                    were finally opened by the “irregulars” on November 15, and by November 24 the
                    Suiyuan forces had successfully repulsed the invaders and had taken Pailingmiao,
                    the strategically important base of the “irregulars” and the capital of the
                    Inner Mongolian Autonomous Political Council. This caused national rejoicing.
                    Great popular support was given the defenders of Suiyuan as a fresh wave of
                    patriotism swept the country. The failure of the “irregulars’”drive became
                    obvious in December with the unsuccessful attempt to retake Pailingmiao, the
                    defection of <pb facs="0550" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> some of the “irregular”
                    leaders and troops, and the capture by Suiyuan forces of Tamiao, the principal
                    “irregular” base some 60 miles northeast of Pailingmiao.</p>
                <p>On December 12 General Chang Hsueh-liang and General Yang Hu-cheng, the
                    Pacification Commissioner of Shensi, revolted against Nanking and forcibly
                    detained Chiang Kai-shek and other important Central Government officials who
                    were in Sian with the Generalissimo. The leaders of the rebellion issued a
                    statement demanding a reorganization of the Government to include all factions,
                    presumably even the Communists, and for a united front against Japan. Shensi and
                    Kansu responded to the plea, but the rest of the country loudly proclaimed its
                    adherence to the Generalissimo and voiced the bitterest contempt for Chang
                    Hsueh-liang and the revolt. The Generalissimo’s release on Christmas day was
                    greeted with enthusiasm throughout the country which had again become more
                    closely knit through common patriotic zeal.</p>
                <p>A very regrettable aftermath of the Sian coup was the reported alliance between
                    the mutineers and the communists who had been concentrated for some time in the
                    vicinity of Sian. At the end of the year, in the absence of knowledge as to what
                    agreement, if any, had been made for the release of Chiang, the Central
                    Government was at a loss to know whether further trouble was to be expected from
                    that source. Chang Hsueh-liang who requested punishment was sentenced by court
                    martial to ten years’ imprisonment but was pardoned. His civil rights, however,
                    have not been restored.</p>
                <p>Other less important occasions which also fostered Chinese nationalism were the
                    celebration of the National holiday on October 10, with a diplomatic reception
                    (for the first time since the Mukden incident) and of the anniversary of Chiang
                    Kai-shek’s birthday on October 31 at which time a large number of airplanes
                    bought with funds publicly subscribed were presented to the Generalissimo.</p>
                <p>It would appear that, at least partially due to the above indicated expansion and
                    strengthening of the Chinese national consciousness, and to the failure of the
                    Sino-Japanese negotiations at Nanking, the Japanese have lessened their pressure
                    on China. Since the large October military maneuvers and the founding in October
                    of the Hui T’ung Aviation Company, whose planes now furnish through service
                    between Manchuria and Tientsin and Peiping with Japanese pilots and Japanese
                    planes, the Japanese have been relatively quiescent in North China. Whereas
                    smuggling in this region has continued on a vast scale and is still causing a
                    great loss in revenue to the Chinese Government, the Japanese authorities have
                    recently shown less ardor in endeavoring to protect Japanese and Korean
                    smugglers when their activities are interfered with by Chinese officials.</p>
                <pb facs="0551" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/>
                <p>The replacing of General Matsumuro last month by Colonel Matsui as the Japanese
                    resident officer of the North China Garrison in Peiping is also believed to be
                    of considerable political significance, as indicating the gradual recession of
                    Japanese influence in North China which became particularly noticeable during
                    the last half of December. A further indication of this recession is the
                    reported decision of the Hopei-Chahar Political Council to enter upon a general
                    program of retrenchment.</p>
                <p>There are also indications that the East Hopei Anti-Communist Autonomous
                    Government presided over by Yin Ju-keng may be on its descendency. Rumors of
                    serious dissension within the administration of the bogus regime continued to
                    circulate during December. It is becoming more apparent that Yin’s hold is
                    highly tenuous, and it is altogether possible that the elaborate and costly
                    celebration of the regime’s first birthday on November 25 and its reported
                    donation of $1,600,000 to the support of the “irregular” forces attacking
                    Suiyuan may be the harbingers of its demise.</p>
                <p>The improvement of China’s position vis-à-vis Japan developed despite ill feeling
                    which sometimes was brought to a dangerous pitch through a long series of
                    Sino-Japanese incidents varying from murder to trivialities. This improvement
                    developed notwithstanding the failure of the negotiations held in Nanking
                    between the Japanese Ambassador and the Minister for Foreign Affairs and their
                    subordinates during the last four months of the year. The negotiations were
                    disrupted by China’s conviction, allegedly, that Japan had been aiding the
                    “irregular” forces in their attack on Suiyuan. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                    on December 6 issued a statement outlining the present position of the Chinese
                    Government relative to the subjects which had been under negotiation. This
                    release has been briefly summarized by the Embassy at Nanking as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <list>
                            <item>“1. The Chinese Government is prepared to inaugurate a civil air
                                line between Shanghai and Fukuoka as soon as the unauthorized and
                                illegal flights of Japanese airplanes over Chinese territory are
                                stopped.</item>
                            <item>“2. The revision of China’s tariff is a domestic affair. When
                                tariff readjustment is studied the suppression of smuggling and the
                                freedom of the Customs Preventive Service will be the first
                                questions studied.</item>
                            <item>“3. With reference to the unlawful anti-Japanese activities of
                                Koreans in China, the Chinese Government does not like to see these
                                acts committed on Chinese soil. At the same time the Japanese
                                Government should suppress the other unlawful activities of its
                                subjects, Koreans, Formosans and others, committed on Chinese
                                territory under Japanese protection.</item>
                            <item>“4. The employment of foreign advisers depends upon their ability,
                                not their nationality. Should Sino-Japanese relations improve, it
                                would not be impossible for China on its own initiative to employ
                                Japanese technical experts.</item>
                            <pb facs="0552" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                            <item>“5. Orders have repeatedly been issued stressing the necessity of
                                maintaining friendly relations with foreign nationals. However,
                                cognizance must be taken of the fact that much cause exists inciting
                                the people against Japan.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Other unfavorable circumstances were: (1) the presence of the Communist troops in
                    the Northwest against whom the Government troops confined their offensive mainly
                    to “pushing”; (2) the wholesale North China smuggling by Japanese and Koreans;
                    and (3) the Japanese cotton mill strikes in Shanghai and Tsingtao and the
                    landing of Japanese forces at the latter port, against which action the Chinese
                    Government protested.</p>
                <p>At a meeting on October 15 the Standing Committee of the Central Executive
                    Committee decided to postpone indefinitely the convocation of the National
                    People’s Congress which was to have met on November 12.</p>
                <p>Economic and financial conditions in Kwangtung began to improve in August under
                    the direction of General Chiang Kai-shek. In the same month resumption of
                    service was offered on the Lung-hai Railway loans and Canton–Kowloon Railway
                    bonds.</p>
                <p>In September decision was made to revise the law governing the encouragement of
                    shipbuilding. Through train service was inaugurated on the Canton–Hankow
                    Railway, and definite plans were made to construct a modern port at Whampoa.</p>
                <p>During October it was announced that the British Government in order to promote
                    British exports to China had decided to guarantee credits advanced by British
                    firms to Chinese importers. Chinese officials and business leaders publicly
                    expressed gratification on this decision. It was believed that this action was
                    intended to demonstrate Great Britain’s desire to advance its commercial
                    relations with China and to serve as a warning to Japan that Great Britain was
                    not disinterested in China’s future. China also expressed her approval of the
                    monetary agreement recently concluded between the United States, France and
                    Great Britain. The Ministry of Finance viewed the accord as a stabilizing
                    influence in international exchange which would tend further to strengthen
                    China’s currency. He pointed out that China had profited by more than U. S.
                    $1,000,000 through the sale of a part of its gold reserves abroad, and that
                    China would be assisted in the discharge of its foreign loan obligations.
                    (Chinese currency remained stable during the period under review except for
                    slight and brief fluctuations at the time of the Sian coup).</p>
                <p>During November it became obvious that the continuation of the shipping strike in
                    the United States was injuring trade relations with the United States and
                    adversely affecting American prestige and good will. The service of the China
                    National Aviation Corporation was <pb facs="0553" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/>
                    extended to Hong Kong, a Pan American Clipper having made its first call at Hong
                    Kong the month before.</p>
                <p>A number of loan operations in connection with the financing of the construction
                    of the Nanking–Kiangsi Railway, which will link Nanking with the Canton–Hankow
                    line and thus make a direct connection between Nanking and South China, were
                    concluded during December. It was announced on December 16 that a loan contract
                    for Yuan $34,500,000 for the construction of the Chengtu–Chungking Railway had
                    been signed by the Szechuan–Kweichow Railway Corporation and a French banking
                    syndicate. Indications at the end of the year were that the United States,
                    notwithstanding the American shipping strike, would continue to enjoy the
                    largest share of Shanghai’s foreign trade, with Germany showing the greatest
                    gain over 1935.</p>
                <p>During the period under review there were no marked changes in the relations
                    between China and the western nations. There were indications, however, of an
                    increasing <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi> between China and Great Britain.
                    Great concern, moreover, was shown by Chinese officials and the public regarding
                    the conclusion of the anti-Communist pact by Japan and Germany and the reported
                        <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> recognition of “Manchukuo” by Italy. Chinese
                    officials and the Chinese press expressed gratification over the election of
                    China to a non-permanent seat on the Council of the League of Nations. The
                    reelection of President Roosevelt was accepted by the Chinese newspapers and
                    public with great enthusiasm.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">F. P. Lockhart</hi>
                    </signed>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Counselor of Embassy</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
