<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="598" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d598">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.114 Narcotics/1473</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Davis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>)<note n="49" xml:id="d598fn49">Copy transmitted to the Department by the Consul
                                General at Shanghai in his despatch No. 126, February 1; received
                                February 24.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 115</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-01">February 1, 1936</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit for the
                            confidential information of the Embassy a copy of a report prepared by
                            the Municipal Advocate’s office of the Shanghai Municipal Council
                            concerning the opium and narcotics regulations promulgated by the
                            Chinese authorities under date of October 28, 1935. For convenient
                            reference a translation of the first set of regulations referred to is
                            also enclosed.<note n="50" xml:id="d598fn50">Enclosures not
                                printed.</note> This translation has been obtained from the Shanghai
                            Municipal Police but a copy of the Chinese text could not be obtained in
                            time to accompany this despatch. It will be noted that the Municipal
                            Advocate calls attention to the serious and drastic punishments
                            prescribed, expresses the view that the regulations in question are not
                            applicable to the International Settlement under the provisions of the
                            Rendition Agreement of February 17, 1930,<note n="51" xml:id="d598fn51"><ref target="frus1930v02#pg_333"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1930, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p.
                                    333</ref>.</note> and Chinese law and recommends that the
                            Council protest to the Consular Body against any steps that may be taken
                            by the Chinese authorities to enforce the regulations in the Settlement.
                            Particular attention is called to the statement that the regulations are
                            an attempt “to create an opium monopoly under the supervision and
                            control of the Military Affairs Commission rather than an endeavor to
                            suppress opium and narcotics.”</p>
                        <p>The Secretary General of the Shanghai Municipal Council is said to fear
                            that the long prison sentences provided by the new regulations, if
                            applied in the International Settlement, would place an unduly heavy
                            burden on the taxpayers and result in congestion in the jails, and to be
                            apprehensive lest the Chinese authorities attempt to license
                            establishments in the foreign settlements. Although not disposed to
                            raise any question regarding the legality of the regulations in so far
                            as the Chinese are concerned, he does intend to ask that persons
                            convicted under them serve their sentences in Chinese prisons and that
                            no opium establishments be licensed in the Settlement.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Monnett B. Davis</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>