<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-01-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-01-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="608" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d608">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.48/1040</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far
                                Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-01-30">January 30, 1936</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Chinese Ambassador called and stated that he regretted having to say
                            that the Chinese Minister of Finance, H. H. Kung, after much effort on
                            the Ambassador’s part, had decided that the Chinese Government could not
                            adopt the plan which the Ambassador had been urging for the handling of
                            the payment of the Chicago Bank Loan.</p>
                        <p>I said that I received this news with great regret.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said that Kung takes the position that he must handle this
                            obligation in the same manner in which he is dealing with <pb facs="0672" n="577" xml:id="pg_577"/> “the others”. I made the
                            observation that, with regard to most of “the others”, this meant “doing
                            nothing about them”, whereas, with regard to some of “the others” the
                            Chinese Ministry of Finance has been making special arrangements of
                            particular character. I said that Kung’s reported position amounted to a
                            refusal to be responsive to the request which the Department had
                            communicated in the form of the suggestion which I had made to the
                            Ambassador in conversations held in December, our request having been
                            occasioned by and having been made in response to the Chinese
                            Government’s request made to this Government in relation to the FCA and
                            the EFC obligations of the Chinese Government. I said that it amounted
                            to a “no” by the Chinese Government. The Ambassador said that he felt
                            that I was putting it a little too strongly.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said that he had informed Mr. Abbott, of the Chicago Bank,
                            of Kung’s position and that Mr. Abbott would be passing through
                            Washington tomorrow and would confer with the Ambassador about the
                            situation. It was assumed that Mr. Abbott while here would call on me. I
                            said that if the Ambassador would explain to Mr. Abbott what the method
                            was by which Kung was contemplating dealing with “all” of the
                            obligations in some one manner, Mr. Abbott might be able to explain the
                            matter to me.</p>
                        <p>I said that, so long as it remained Kung’s position that he would not be
                            responsive to the suggestions which we had made, I hoped “that the
                            Chinese Ambassador would make no further move toward requesting
                            concessions in connection with the FCA and the RFC payments”. The
                            Ambassador said that this would put him in a difficult position. I said
                            that I realized that he himself had been doing everything possible to
                            move his Government in the right direction and that the last thing that
                            I would wish to do would be to put him in an embarrassing position, but
                            that nevertheless the hope which I had expressed was a hope which I
                            entertained.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that the Ambassador would try to make clear to Mr. Abbott
                            points which thus far I had been unable to understand.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ornbeck</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>