<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d680</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">680</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-09-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-09-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="680"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d680">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.79690 Pan American Airways/76</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 697</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-09-11">September 11,
                            1936</date>.<lb/>[Received October 5.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to previous
                    correspondence relative to the Pan American Airways, Inc., and to report that a
                    member of my staff was informed confidentially by Mr. Harold M. Bixby, chief
                    American executive of the China National Aviation Corporation, in Shanghai on
                    September 3 last, that negotiations for facilities for the Pan American Airways,
                    Inc., at both Macao and Hong Kong making possible the linking of that company’s
                    service with that of the China National Aviation Corporation would culminate
                    favorably within a short time.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bixby said that due to British pressure the contract which the Pan American
                    Airways had submitted to the Portuguese Government, which had been approved by
                    the Governor of Macao, had been rejected at Lisbon, and that the proposal made
                    by the Portuguese authorities in return contained so many unacceptable
                    provisions that it was impossible to revise it into a compromise draft. Mr.
                    Bixby had assisted in drafting an entirely new contract when he arrived in New
                    York recently after a seven-day flight from Manila, and that contract had been
                    submitted to the Portuguese Government with virtually no hope on the part of the
                    Pan American Airways officials that it would be accepted. They feared that an
                    impasse in the negotiations with Portugal had been reached. Much to their
                    astonishment, however, the British pressure apparently having been relinquished,
                    possibly due to the British authorities’ decision to invite China to send planes
                    to Hong Kong and to Great Britain’s preoccupation with the situation in Spain,
                    the draft was accepted <hi rend="italic">in toto</hi>. This action was
                    particularly gratifying to the Pan American Airways since the draft included
                    provisions for rights in the Azores even more important to the trans-Atlantic
                    service than the rights in Macao to the trans-Pacific <pb facs="0741" n="646"
                        xml:id="pg_646"/> service. Mr. Bixby said that it only remained now for the
                    Portuguese authorities to invite the Chinese Government to send planes to Macao
                    to connect with the service of the Pan American Airways, Inc. He understood that
                    such action would be taken.</p>
                <p>The Pan American Airways, Inc., are glad to have this link as an auxiliary or
                    reserve and so as to maintain a stronger position vis-à-vis the British. Mr.
                    Bixby said, moreover, that the China National Aviation Corporation would
                    probably establish some sort of service with Macao despite the fact that its
                    main terminus would be in Hong Kong.</p>
                <p>The British in their negotiations with China had held out for three privileges:
                    most-favored-nation treatment, the right to fly over China, and permission to
                    land in Chinese territory in case of emergency. The Chinese authorities had
                    finally been persuaded to grant the first and last of these privileges but were
                    not willing to grant permission in writing for British aircraft to fly over
                    Chinese territory in view of their reluctance to grant the same right to the
                    Japanese. Upon an intimation from an American source, however, that the Chinese
                    authorities would in fact have no objection to the flight of British planes over
                    Chinese territory provided the right to do so did not have to be stated publicly
                    or in writing, the new Governor of Hong Kong consented to relinquish this point
                    in the negotiations, and arrangements have already been made for the
                    inauguration of the China National Aviation Corporation service with Hong
                    Kong.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bixby felt, moreover, that as soon as the Governor, who is ill at present, is
                    able to give consideration to the final details of the agreement providing for
                    air facilities for the Pan American Airways, Inc., in Hong Kong the whole matter
                    would be satisfactorily concluded.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bixby remarked incidentally that trans-Pacific passenger service between
                    Manila and San Francisco would be inaugurated on or about November 1, 1936.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nelson Trusler Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
