<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Shanghai ( (Gauss) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d729</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">729</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-12-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-12-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-12-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-12-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="729"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d729">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.102S/1433</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 507</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-12-03">December 3,
                            1936</date>.<lb/>[Received January 5, 1937.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my despatch No. 496 of November
                    28, 1936,<note n="2" xml:id="d729fn2">Not printed.</note> concerning the
                    Japanese demand for control of the police of the northern and eastern districts
                    of the International Settlement at Shanghai, I have the honor to report that Mr.
                    Stirling Fessenden, the (American) Secretary General of the Shanghai Municipal
                    Council, informed me this morning that he had been invited to attend a meeting
                    at the British Consulate General yesterday at which were present the British
                    Ambassador, the British Consul General, the British Consul, the Chairman of the
                    Shanghai Municipal Council (Mr. H. E. Arnhold, a British subject) and the
                    Commissioner of the Shanghai Municipal Police (also a British subject), who
                    discussed the situation which has arisen in connection with these Japanese
                    demands.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fessenden tells me that the British Ambassador expressed himself as in
                    agreement with the proposal that the officials of the Council should discuss
                    this matter with the Japanese consular authorities with a view to seeking some
                    arrangement which might meet the Japanese in a reasonable measure.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fessenden said that he had expressed the opinion, which is in accord with my
                    own, that an effort should be made to arrive at some compromise arrangement with
                    the Japanese; the object of the discussions to be a reduction of the Japanese
                    demands and an arrangement which will not disrupt the police administration of
                    the Settlement.</p>
                <p>He told me, however, that the British Consul General appears to be very much
                    concerned over the Japanese demands, and seems to feel that they must be met in
                    large measure. Sir John Brenan has also told me recently that he feels that the
                    Japanese are determined to accomplish their ends. He seems to feel that any
                    opposition to the Japanese demands will be charged principally to the British
                    since the police organization of the Settlement is largely British and the
                    municipal administration principally under officials who are British
                    subjects.</p>
                <p>I am of the opinion that my British colleague takes too serious a view, at
                    present, of the Japanese demands. My impression from my discussions with the
                    Japanese Consul General is that the Japanese will accept very much less than
                    they have demanded; and I believe that my proposal for the appointment of
                    “co-officers” would go a long way toward meeting the Japanese wishes. The
                    authority of the Japanese “co-officer” should, so far as possible, be
                    restricted, and confined to Japanese affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0800" n="705" xml:id="pg_705"/>
                <p>I do not believe that the anxiety of the British Consul General is fully shared
                    by the British and American members of the Council, who are likely to seek to
                    reduce the Japanese demand to a minimum. While it is not possible to say at this
                    time what course will be followed in event a compromise arrangement cannot be
                    made with the Japanese, it seems—if I interpret correctly the attitude of the
                    officials of the Council as explained to me by the Secretary General—that the
                    whole question of the Japanese demands and the attitude of the police
                    administration in regard to them, will be exposed to the full membership of the
                    Council, including the Chinese. I have emphasized with my Japanese colleague
                    that if the Japanese demands should become known to the full Council—and they
                    must become known if the Municipal authorities are unable to make some mutually
                    satisfactory arrangement with the Japanese—there will likely be strong Chinese
                    opposition to the Japanese demands, and the present difficult situation in
                    regard to Sino-Japanese relations at Shanghai will not be improved.</p>
                <p>In his telegram to me of November 22, 12 noon, the American Ambassador, in
                    expressing agreement with my views as set out in my telegram No. 604 of November
                    21, 4 P.M., to the Department and the Embassy, stated that he believed that the
                    secrecy imposed by the Japanese should be combated. I have held that suggestion
                    in mind, and believe that it should be followed in event that no satisfactory
                    compromise arrangement can be reached with the Japanese to continue substantial
                    foreign (non-Japanese) control of the police in the eastern and northern
                    districts of the Settlement. I am not disposed, however, to urge that any
                    publicity be given to the Japanese demands so long as there exists any
                    possibility of a reasonable and satisfactory arrangement. I feel that if the
                    Japanese demands were given publicity at this time, there might be serious
                    repercussion amongst the Chinese, particularly in the northern and eastern
                    districts, and, perhaps, a renewal of attacks on Japanese in those areas. It
                    seems to me desirable that the matter should take its natural course between the
                    officials of the Council and the Japanese, and then, if there is a breakdown
                    that it should be referred formally to the full Council, with probable resulting
                    publicity.</p>
                <p>My British colleague has said nothing to me of the meeting held by the British
                    Ambassador; my information comes confidentially from the (American) Secretary
                    General of the Council who says that he was invited to attend the meeting in
                    that capacity.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">C. E. Gauss</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
