<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d747</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">747</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-02-27T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-02-27T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-27T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-27T10:00:00-05:00" n="747"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d747">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">894.00/583: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-28T00:00:00+09:00"
                            >February 28, 1936—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received February 28—3:15
                        p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>46. Embassy’s 45, February 28, 6 p.m.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>A friendly Japanese in high position has informed me that an ultimatum
                        “from the highest source” was delivered the insurgents at 3 o’clock this
                        afternoon ordering them to disband and return to barracks and that the
                        insurgents have chosen to disregard the order. Our informant states that in
                        these circumstances the Government has decided to proceed with military
                        measures early tomorrow morning probably at daybreak and that in view of the
                        determination of the insurgents this may mean fighting until the last man
                        has been wiped out.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>It is reported that the insurgents demand that General Masaki shall be
                        named Prime Minister; that a portion of the revenues of the big financial
                        interests such as Mitsui and Mitsubishi shall be given to the Government;
                        and that Colonel Aizawa (the murderer of Nagata) shall be freed. They
                        indicate that having drawn the sword for these principles they must carry
                        through to the end.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Subsequent to my receipt of the foregoing communication, three radio
                        announcements were made this evening to the effect that the Tokyo Garrison
                        would take “a certain step” against the three or four hundred insurgent
                        troops now stationed in Kojimachi. These official announcements would seem
                        to corroborate the report of my informant.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Embassy’s observers find that the disposition of the Government troops
                        in this vicinity and near the British Embassy this evening are precisely the
                        same as when the General Staff officer this <pb facs="0826" n="731"
                            xml:id="pg_731"/> morning predicted that fighting might take place as
                        set forth in paragraph 2 of my 44, February 28, noon.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>All of the foregoing information indicates that unless a last hour
                        surrender occurs or unless the insurgent officers adopt the classic way out
                        by suicide there will be fighting in Tokyo early tomorrow morning. It is
                        believed that the number of insurgent troops are at present considerably
                        greater than the number mentioned in the radio announcements.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Repeated to Peiping.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
