<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-01-14T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-01-14T21:00:00-05:00" n="787" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d787">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">894.6363/243: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-01-15T11:00:00+09:00">January 15, 1936—11
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received January 15—1:27 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>12. Embassy’s 253, December 28, noon.<note n="67" xml:id="d787fn67"><ref target="frus1935v03#pg_939"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p.
                                    939</ref>.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>At a recent conference of the representatives of the foreign oil
                                companies with Kurusu<note n="68" xml:id="d787fn68">Saburo Kurusu,
                                    Chief of the Commercial Affairs Bureau, Japanese Foreign
                                    Office.</note> the latter stated that the Vice Minister for <pb facs="0882" n="787" xml:id="pg_787"/> Commerce and Industry<note n="69" xml:id="d787fn69">Shinji Yoshino.</note> agrees in
                                principle with the plan of giving the oil companies governmental
                                guarantees covering quotas over an extensive period, reasonable
                                profit and maximum stock holding obligation as well as equal
                                treatment with Japanese refiners should the oil companies desire to
                                refine in Japan. Kurusu therefore requests the oil companies to
                                propose definite terms upon which they will comply with the stock
                                holding provision of the law and the question has been referred to
                                New York and London for consideration.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The Embassy and the local representatives of the oil companies are
                                of the opinion that the Japanese authorities are now sincerely
                                endeavoring to find some solution of the problem which will permit
                                opposing oil companies to continue in business in Japan although it
                                appears highly improbable that they will be able to allow stock
                                holding obligation. It, therefore, appears desirable that the
                                Japanese proposal outlined above be carefully considered.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>