<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="837" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d837">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.943 Gloves/18</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Japanese Embassy</gloss></hi><note n="33" xml:id="d837fn33">Handed to the Third Secretary of the Japanese
                                Embassy by Mr. Veatch, February 18.</note></head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Wool-Knit Gloves</hi></p>
                        <p>The suggestions presented to the Department today regarding details of
                            the proposed agreement have been given careful consideration. It would
                            be impossible for the President to withhold action on the report of the
                            Tariff Commission if voluntary restriction assumed by Japanese exporters
                            should offer less adequate safeguards to the American industry than the
                            arrangement set forth in the Department’s statement of February 15.</p>
                        <p>This Government made the most liberal offer it could possibly make with
                            respect to the period between March 1, 1936 and January 1, 1937. To
                            shift to shipments from Japan during this period as a substitute for
                            arrivals in the United States would have the effect of increasing
                            considerably and to an indeterminate amount the total volume of imports
                            of wool-knit gloves into the United States during this year. It is
                            essential that arrivals in the United States of all wool-knit gloves
                            manufactured in Japan for the period March 1, 1936 to January 1, 1937
                            shall be limited to 200,000 dozen pairs provided that arrivals of such
                            gloves between January 1 and March 1, 1936 shall not exceed 150,000
                            dozen pairs, any excess over 150,000 dozen pairs during this two-month
                            period to be subtracted from the limit of 200,000 dozen pairs during the
                            ten months following.</p>
                        <p>It is essential also that the agreement cover at least three years and
                            that it should definitely limit arrivals in the United States of all
                            wool-knit gloves and mittens manufactured in Japan to 225,000 dozen
                            pairs for each of the calendar years 1937 and 1938, and that definite
                            announcement of this agreement and its terms should be made if the
                            President is to be justified in refraining from the action recommended
                            in the report of the Tariff Commission.</p>
                        <p>Should the circumstances determining the position of the American
                            industry develop subsequently in such a way as to warrant increased
                            importation consistently with the welfare of the American industry, and
                            should the Japanese Government then wish to propose in the light of this
                            situation that the voluntary limitation on arrivals in the United States
                            for the subsequent calendar year be made more liberal, this Government
                            would, of course, give consideration to any such proposals.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">[<placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-18">February
                                    18, 1936</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>