<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Eugene H. Dooman of the Division of Far Eastern
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d898</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">898</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="rec7iuGEudoprgvdN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048668"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fishery</term>
                    <term ref="recd8LWcmLbIIZh8o" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85116821"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Salmon</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recUxK0PiRCnqTXts" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000044"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Farming</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="898"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d898">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.008 North Pacific/1</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Eugene H. Dooman of the Division of Far
                        Eastern Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-12-16">December 16,
                            1936</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Canadian Minister, Sir Herbert Marler, called at the Department this morning
                    accompanied by Mr. Hume Wrong, Counselor of Legation, and Mr. Charles Ritchie,
                    Third Secretary of Legation.</p>
                <p>The following officers of the Department were present: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Mr. Dooman (FE) [Far Eastern Affairs]</p>
                        <p>Mr. Hickerson (WE) [Western European Affairs]</p>
                        <p>Mr. Keating (TD) [Treaty Division]</p>
                        <p>Mr. Bonbright (WE)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1043" n="948" xml:id="pg_948"/>
                <p>The Canadian Minister stated that his Legation had received from the Canadian
                    Department of Fisheries a memorandum setting forth views with regard to certain
                    fishing problems, and that he thought that it would be helpful to him and to his
                    Government if there could be had an informal discussion on these problems.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wrong distributed copies of the memorandum referred to by the Minister (copy
                        attached),<note n="96" xml:id="d898fn96">Not printed.</note> the purport of
                    which he outlined and amplified by certain observations. He said that the
                    methods of catching fish and distributing fish had been revolutionized by the
                    development of the so-called “mother” ships and by improvements in
                    refrigeration. He understood that it was now possible for fish to be immersed in
                    brine and frozen without injuring the cell structure of the fish and without
                    materially altering its flavor. It was thus possible for ships now to be sent to
                    all parts of the world to engage in fishing and also to distribute catches in
                    widely separated markets. He thought that there was reason for reviewing the
                    whole problem, with a view to determining new principles calculated to conserve
                    the fishery resources of the various countries.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wrong then referred to the specific question of Japanese fishing vessels
                    operating along the coast of North America, and to the fear that operations of
                    this kind would eventually deplete the salmon and halibut of the Pacific.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dooman then gave in strict confidence an account of the discussions which
                    have been held between this Government and the Japanese Government over the
                    possibility of action being taken by the Japanese Government to prohibit
                    Japanese nationals from fishing for salmon in the waters of Bristol Bay. He
                    referred to the informal conversations which were held at Tokyo in 1930 and
                    1931, to the plan which was formulated at that time and which fell through, to
                    the investigations carried out during the last four or five years by vessels of
                    the Japanese Government with regard to the salmon resources of Bristol Bay, and
                    finally to the inquiry made by this Government last year with regard to the
                    possibility of a convention to provide for the exclusion of Japanese fishing
                    vessels from operating in Bristol Bay. The Japanese Government expressed
                    inability to consider any such convention until certain studies which were being
                    conducted of the salmon resources of Bristol Bay were concluded. The Japanese
                    Government had given assurances, however, that Japanese fishing vessels would
                    not be licensed to operate in that area for the time being, and so far as this
                    Government was aware there had been no cases of Japanese packing salmon in the
                    waters of Bristol Bay.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dooman went on to say that the studies which were being made by the Japanese
                    Government would, he understood, continue for another <pb facs="1044" n="949"
                        xml:id="pg_949"/> two or three years, and that he thought it unlikely that
                    the question under consideration would come to a head, either by the conclusion
                    of a convention such as we have in mind or by Japanese operating in Bristol Bay,
                    for several years to come. In the meantime, private suggestions had been put
                    forward by Japanese officials to the effect that it might be desirable for the
                    United States, Canada and Japan to conduct a survey of the fishery resources of
                    the north Pacific with a view to the eventual conclusion of a fishery convention
                    along the lines of the Fur Seals Treaty of 1911.</p>
                <p>So far as halibut is concerned, Mr. Dooman did not believe that the possibility
                    is imminent of Japanese being interested in halibut on an extensive scale,
                    although it is true that a few Japanese fishing vessels had been catching
                    certain types of ground fish for reduction into fertilizer and oil.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hickerson expressed the thought that problems arising in the Pacific appear
                    to be somewhat less difficult than those arising in the Atlantic, for the reason
                    that in the former area only the salmon appear to be involved—and that only
                    because of the possible interest of one other country—whereas in the Atlantic
                    many types of fish and many countries were involved.</p>
                <p>The Canadian Minister pursued that thought and said that it seemed to him that it
                    would be wise to explore the possibility of a convention being concluded between
                    the United States, Canada and Japan. If such a convention were concluded, a
                    precedent and an example will have been created for the setting up of an
                    agreement of the widest possible compass.</p>
                <p>It was suggested to the Canadians that our approach to the Japanese might be made
                    easier if it were possible for us to show that we on this side of the Pacific
                    were making an effort to solve our own salmon difficulties through the Sockeye
                    Salmon Convention of 1930.<note n="97" xml:id="d898fn97">Signed at Washington,
                        May 26, 1930, <ref target="frus1930v01#pg_505">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1930, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 505</ref>.</note> The Canadian Minister
                    agreed and Mr. Wrong expressed the opinion that in the course of the next ten
                    days we would probably know the decision of the Canadian Government regarding
                    the acceptance or rejection of our Senate’s reservations to the Convention,
                    which is not yet in operation.<note n="98" xml:id="d898fn98">For protocol of
                        exchange signed at Washington, July 28, 1937, see <ref
                            target="frus1930v01#pg_512">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 512</ref> (bracketed insertion).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Dooman said that it did not seem to him that a pessimistic view with regard
                    to the conclusion of a three-power agreement such as that suggested by Sir
                    Herbert was called for at the present time: the salmon resources of Kamchatka
                    were being rapidly depleted, due in large part to the policy of the Soviet
                    Government in farming out the so-called “fishing stations” and the importance of
                    canned salmon in <pb facs="1045" n="950" xml:id="pg_950"/> Japan’s foreign trade
                    are two reasons which should dispose the Japanese toward cooperating in
                    conserving the salmon resources of the eastern Pacific. It would have to be
                    realized that the conclusion of such a convention would require the making of
                    sacrifices by both Canada and the United States to permit Japanese participation
                    in salmon fishing, and that the uncompromising attitude of the salmon interests
                    on the west coast would have to be taken into consideration.</p>
                <p>There then ensued a discussion among the Canadians of the likelihood of the
                    Japanese threat to the salmon resources of Canada being raised in the Canadian
                    Parliament, and there seemed to be a consensus among them that the question
                    would be raised. The Americans made the comment that it also seemed likely that
                    some resolution, probably espousing the view of the American salmon interests
                    that the red salmon found in Bristol Bay are property of the United States,
                    would be introduced at the next session of Congress.</p>
                <p>The Canadian Minister observed that the discussion had inclined him to the view
                    that the course to be pursued by Canada and the United States should be to seek
                    with Japan a solution of the Pacific problem, leaving the wider problems
                    presented in the memorandum of the Canadian Department of Fisheries to be
                    resolved at some later date. He added that he would recommend that the Canadian
                    Government endeavor by appropriate means to support and reenforce whatever the
                    American Government might seek to do by way of representations to the Japanese
                    Government. Mr. Dooman said that an instruction to the Embassy at Tokyo is in
                    the course of preparation, and that upon completion he would be glad to confer
                    further with members of the Canadian Legation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
