<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-06-19T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-06-19T21:00:00-05:00" n="921" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d921">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.3362i/11: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-06-20T11:00:00+09:00">June 20, 1936—11
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received June 20—6:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>130. Department’s 79, June 18, 6 p.m.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The Department has made perfectly clear the purposes of its
                                suggestion as well as the method of approach desired.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>While still believing that the chances of a favorable response
                                from the Japanese tending to alleviate situation and improve
                                relations are small, I do concur in the desirability of the step on
                                the basis of all the considerations now clearly set forth.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The risk of premature publicity can be reduced but not necessarily
                                eliminated by my seeing the Minister at his residence instead of at
                                the Foreign Office.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>It would be helpful to learn just how urgent the matter is
                                regarded so that I may determine whether to seek some ostensible
                                reason for seeing Arita immediately or whether a natural and
                                therefore more favorable occasion for broaching the subject may be
                                awaited. In Japan an Ambassador’s visit to the Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs is regarded as a matter of prime importance and periodical
                                calls merely for the purpose of discussing the general situation are
                                seldom understood. The tendency is to look for “the nigger in the
                                woodpile.” I see no reason for minimizing the importance of the
                                subject under reference but shall nevertheless be glad to know
                                whether the delay if any <pb facs="1083" n="988" xml:id="pg_988"/>
                                should be a matter of days only or whether it may be a matter of
                                weeks.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Obviously I can and shall advance a very strong and logical
                                argument in making the suggestion as on my own initiative.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>