<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>178. Intelligence Memorandum</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d178</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">178</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recIMQA43VbepP2FZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Anti-communism</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recejJYhXicNE4KKw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005020174"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Archipelago</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="178"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d178">
                <head>178. Intelligence Memorandum<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d178fn1">Source:
                        Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Indonesia, Vol. VI,
                        11/65–5/66. Secret; No Foreign Dissem; Background Use Only. Prepared by the
                        Office of Current Intelligence, Central Intelligence Agency.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">OCI No. 2943/65</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-11-22">November 22, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">INDONESIAN ARMY ATTITUDES TOWARD COMMUNISM<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d178fn2">The Office of Current Intelligence prepared related
                        intelligence memoranda including: <gloss target="#t_OCI1">OCI</gloss> No.
                        2940/65, November 8, a biographic assessment of <persName
                            corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName> and analysis of his role during
                        and after the September 30 coup; <gloss target="#t_OCI1">OCI</gloss> No.
                        3041/65, November 12, entitled “The Indonesian Army: Objectives and
                        Problems”; <gloss target="#t_OCI1">OCI</gloss> No. 2395/65, November 17,
                        examining the Army’s concern about the rice situation in Indonesia; and
                            <gloss target="#t_OCI1">OCI</gloss> No. 3096/65, December 2, which
                        examined the “Leadership Prospects in Indonesia” and concluded that Sukarno
                        would remain chief of state with the army playing a strong national
                        political role for the foreseeable future. (All ibid., Vol. V, 10/65–11/65
                        and Vol. VI, 11/65–5/66)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>For six weeks the Indonesian Army has been engaged in a major campaign
                        against the Communist Party of Indonesia (<gloss target="#t_PKI1"
                            >PKI</gloss>). Party members and sympathizers are being rounded up and
                        interned by the military; others are being purged from local government
                        positions; and in Central Java <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> adherents
                        are reported to be shot on sight by the army. The army has risked much of
                        its prestige and political future on this campaign. It wants to ban the
                            <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> and to cripple the party
                        permanently, but its attitude toward Marxism is far more complicated than
                        simple anti-Communism.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The army has a long record of opposition to the <gloss target="#t_PKI1"
                            >PKI</gloss> as a political force. In addition, some army leaders
                        undoubtedly view Communism as an ideology which is essentially evil,
                        totalitarian, and alien to the “Indonesian way of life.” But this view is by
                        no means universal. Army officers and enlisted personnel, like Indonesians
                        in all other walks of life, have for the past several years been subjected
                        to a fairly constant barrage of pro-Communist propaganda. This propaganda,
                        echoed and often initiated by President Sukarno, has had its effect. While
                        some <pb facs="0414" n="376" xml:id="pg_376"/> army officers’ beliefs are
                        firmly rooted in a fundamentalist and essentially anti-Communist Moslem
                        tradition, many others, particularly in the lower ranks, equally firmly
                        consider themselves to be Marxist socialists. Nearly all army leaders,
                        however, are united in regarding the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> as
                        a rival for power within Indonesia. They are at present engaged in a power
                        struggle, not an ideological struggle, with the party.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>A well-placed army source recently told the US Embassy that the army was
                        anti-Chinese and anti-<gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>, but not
                        anti-Communist. This is a good capsule summary of the military’s position,
                        for clearly a large segment of the army is by no means opposed to Marxism
                        per se. Indeed, officially the army gives full assent to the frequently
                        stated proposition that the Indonesian revolution is a socialist revolution.
                        Probably few army leaders would oppose some sort of state-controlled Marxist
                        party, even one calling itself Communist, if this party were clearly
                        nationalistic—that is, wholly oriented toward Indonesian national interests.
                        The Yugoslav model is instructive in this regard.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The army leadership at present finds itself opposed to the <gloss
                            target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> on a variety of grounds. First, the murder
                        of a number of high-ranking officers in the course of the insurrection on 1
                        October has made it clear to the army leadership that its very survival may
                        be at stake in the present struggle. Second, the <gloss target="#t_PKI1"
                            >PKI</gloss>, with its high degree of political motivation and
                        discipline, has developed an independent power structure that is not
                        necessarily responsive to the organs of government. Finally, the army
                        believes the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>’s ties to Peking make it in
                        effect the agent of a foreign power. For all these reasons the army finds
                        the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> a threat to its own power position.
                        But it also finds in these factors useful arguments in the propaganda war it
                        is now waging against the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>. It is
                        claiming the party is out of phase with Indonesian ideals and a “traitor” to
                        the Indonesian revolution, and is emphasizing Chinese Communist involvement
                        in the 1 October uprising. This last argument is particularly effective,
                        given the Indonesians’ general antipathy to the numerous Chinese merchants
                        living in their midst.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In pressing this campaign against the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>,
                        however, the army has had to tread a delicate path with respect to President
                            <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>, who is not only
                        emotionally committed to Marxism, but is also convinced that the <gloss
                            target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>, with its high degree of discipline, is a
                        unifying factor on the Indonesian political scene, where centrifugal forces
                        have plagued the government from its inception. In addition, the army must
                        consider Moscow’s attitude. The Indonesian military establishment is almost
                        totally Soviet-supplied, and the army is well aware of its dependence on the
                        Soviet Union for spare parts, replacements, and ammunition.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Whatever its feelings about Peking, the army certainly wants no break with
                        Moscow. It has been careful to exclude the Soviet Union <pb facs="0415"
                            n="377" xml:id="pg_377"/> from its recent denunciations of the <gloss
                            target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> and of the Chinese Communists. A recent
                        report suggests that Defense Minister <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1"
                            >Nasution</persName> has worked out an understanding with the Soviets
                        whereby Soviet arms would continue to reach Indonesia while the army
                        attempted to eradicate pro-Chinese influence within the <gloss
                            target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1"
                            >Nasution</persName> is said to have promised that Indonesia would adopt
                        neither a policy of hostility to Communism as an ideology at home nor to the
                        Soviet Union and its satellites in international affairs. Such an
                        understanding, either formal or informal, seems likely, although it is
                        probable that the Soviets would also be willing to assure <persName
                            corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> that relations with Indonesia
                        would remain firm should he, rather than the army, emerge the victor in the
                        present tug-of-war.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Moscow has been playing the recent events in Indonesia in a low key in its
                        current propaganda. It has been making the minimum noises necessary when
                        Communist Party members are being harried and shot by government
                        forces—criticism far milder, for example, than that directed at Iraq in 1963
                        when similar conditions obtained in that country. Arms deliveries have
                        continued to reach Indonesia without interruption over the past six weeks.
                        There is no indication that they will be cut off.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> is reported to have told
                            <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> of his arrangement
                        with the Soviets. He undoubtedly hopes to cut the ground from under any
                        potential <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> allegation that
                        the army, in its anti-<gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> campaign, is
                        exhibiting reactionary tendencies and is tied to “neocolonialism.” The army
                        leaders may also feel that continued evidence of Soviet good will, as
                        expressed in uninterrupted arms shipments, may infuriate the Chinese
                        Communists and lead to recriminations that the army could then use to
                        advantage in its attempt to orient Indonesia away from Peking.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>The embassy suggests that in reaching an understanding with the Soviets on
                        the arms shipment question the army may leave itself open to Soviet pressure
                        to resuscitate the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> along pro-Moscow
                        lines. While this is possible, it is by no means likely. The army would not
                        be happy at the appearance of a revivified Communist Party with strong ties
                        to a foreign power, even if this power were Moscow rather than Peking.
                        Furthermore, it is likely that the Soviets themselves do not particularly
                        wish to become entangled in the thickets of Indonesian politics. They have
                        before them the clear example of Peking’s involvement in this manner—an
                        involvement which has led to a diminution of Chinese influence in Indonesia.
                        Moscow is primarily interested in close government-to-government relations
                        with the Indonesians, and may well feel that its virtual arms-supply
                        monopoly affords it greater influence on Indonesian policies than would a
                        Moscow-oriented <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>, which the army may at
                        some future date come to consider to be as great <pb facs="0416" n="378"
                            xml:id="pg_378"/> a threat to it as it does the present party.
                        Government-to-government relations supplemented by the leverage of continued
                        arms shipments and the training of middle-grade Indonesian officers in the
                        USSR, gives the Soviets the same sort of influence they enjoy in
                        Egypt.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Indeed, even the rehabilitation of the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>
                        as a “national Communist party” would prove difficult in present
                        circumstances. While the army might have no ideological difficulties in
                        accepting such a party, it has the present <gloss target="#t_PKI1"
                            >PKI</gloss> on the run and almost certainly would like to destroy the
                        party’s organizational structure while it has the chance. It has made no
                        attempt to cultivate the less militant element of the <gloss
                            target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> that might be expected to form the core of
                        a new party. In practice it has made no distinction between those elements
                        directly involved in the 1 October insurrection and other “safer” party
                        members when making arrests and purging local government machinery.
                        Moreover, the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>, like other traditional
                        Communist parties, is organized from the top down, and its members are
                        inclined to follow the lead of its constituted leadership. These leaders
                        have international considerations as well as Indonesian interests in mind,
                        and if forced underground would probably take a large portion of the more
                        dedicated rank-and-file with them. On the other hand, the <gloss
                            target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss> has a strong nationalist coloration, and
                        some lower level party members may eventually be induced to join a tame,
                        government-organized and sponsored party professing Marxism. The army would,
                        however, attempt to see that such a party did not have a real voice in
                        governmental policy making.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Even a development along this line, however, presupposes a victory for the
                        army in its present attempt to influence <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                            >Sukarno</persName> to accept its view of the <gloss target="#t_PKI1"
                            >PKI</gloss> as a threat to the Indonesian state. This outcome is by no
                        means certain; the army may yet be outmaneuvered by the politically astute
                        President. In the end, the army may be forced by <persName
                            corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> to acquiesce in a
                        rehabilitation of the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>, or to accept the
                        party almost whole but reconstituted under a different name. For that which
                        worries the army most—the <gloss target="#t_PKI1">PKI</gloss>’s tight
                        organizational structure—is precisely what makes it so attractive to
                            <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>. And while it is true
                        that the army has gone further in present circumstances in pursuing its own
                        ends, it has retreated in the face of presidential pressure before and may
                        do so again.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>Whatever the outcome of the present scramble for power, it is unlikely
                        that there will be a major change in Indonesian foreign policy. Should the
                        army emerge on top, Indonesian policies would probably be more genuinely
                        neutral in balancing between East and West, and the tendency to follow
                        Peking’s lead in international affairs certainly would be reduced. However,
                        no break with Moscow is in the cards, and the army would find it difficult
                        to extricate itself from present foreign policy attitudes to reach a genuine
                        rapprochement with the <pb facs="0417" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> West. In
                        part this is true because the army itself believes these policies to be
                        correct, and in part because to reach an accommodation with the West would
                        expose the army leaders to charges of “selling out to the neocolonialists”
                        from leftist Indonesian elements independent of the <gloss target="#t_PKI1"
                            >PKI</gloss>. Specifically, the army is deeply involved in confrontation
                        with Malaysia and, despite some indications that its leaders are having
                        second thoughts about this policy, it is unlikely that they can stand down
                        on confrontation without a considerable loss of face. Furthermore, the army
                        leadership, like <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>, would
                        probably find confrontation a useful symbol around which to unify the many
                        divisive forces at work in the archipelago.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
