<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>199. Telegram From the Embassy in Indonesia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d199</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">199</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-03-10T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-03-10T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recFzikmNCJDCCGBL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade unions</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-03-10T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-03-10T04:00:00-05:00" n="199"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d199">
                <head>199. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d199fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 23–9 INDON. Secret; Immediate. Repeated to Taipei for
                            <persName>Bundy</persName>. Passed to the White House.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Djakarta</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-03-10T09:00:00+00:00">March 10, 1966,
                        0900Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2536. 1. Minister <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Adam Malik</persName>, who seemed to
                    be in higher spirits than I’ve ever seen him before, told me at rendezvous last
                    night that situation is explosive, with army prepared to move at any moment
                    using 22 army battalions loyal to Generals <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1"
                        >Nasution</persName> and Soeharto in and around Djakarta area.</p>
                <p>2. I said I understood <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> was
                    planning to dismiss Soeharto. Was this true? He said President was planning to
                    dismiss either or both Soeharto and Adjie; and <persName corresp="#p_MA1"
                        >Malik</persName> hoped <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>
                    would do so because this would be precisely the action which would incite armed
                    forces to move physically against Presidium and bring about long-needed
                    changes.</p>
                <p>3. I remarked that on past occasions when army seemed united in its resolve,
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> was able to recapture
                    initiative by calling in all the military brass including regional commanders
                    and putting on one of his performances which seemed to leave military commanders
                    uncertain as to how each other stood and therefore they wavered at the crucial
                    hour. <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> has called for such
                    meeting this weekend; will history repeat itself?</p>
                <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> replied that he did not think it
                    would. All the Panglimas are behind Soeharto only awaiting his order. However,
                    army will not take initial step against <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                        >Sukarno</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName> to
                    avoid chances of being the aggressor, but army action will be in the form of a
                    counter-action. Thus students and laborers will continue their demonstrations
                    until <pb facs="0453" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_SSD2"
                        >Subandrio</persName> provoked into taking some action which will justify
                    army counter-moves. This could be touched off by a dismissal of Soeharto or
                    Adjie or Sarwo Edhie or Mokoginta or by Tjakrabirawa troops shooting students.
                    An example of how close <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> is to
                    triggering army move was when he and <persName corresp="#p_SSD2"
                        >Subandrio</persName> inspected ransacked Foreign Ministry March 9.
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> so angry that he ordered
                    Tjakrabirawa troops to shoot at students.</p>
                <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> continued that even young air
                    force officers are now organized into teams supporting anti-Presidium movement
                    and have plans to sabotage any aircraft engaged in escape of leftist cabinet
                    ministers from Djakarta.</p>
                <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> said that by far the most
                    important new element in situation since last we met a month ago was student
                    movement against <persName corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName> and other
                    leftist cabinet ministers. These students more powerful than all parties put
                    together and command much wider sympathy and support. In fact, all previous
                    anti-government movements here have lacked this kind of popular support. Student
                    demonstrators include sons and daughters from most prominent families including
                    those who are in pro-Sukarno camp and they naturally exert considerable
                    influence on their parents. Moreover, soldiers and policemen most reluctant to
                    shoot at student demonstrators. As example, he cited dilemma of one policeman
                    charged with protection of Foreign Office on March 8. When he pointed his gun at
                    a student, he discovered this was son of his superior officer. Policeman so
                    shocked he disappeared from scene. Same has happened to members of Tjakrabirawa
                    battalion, a number of whom have deserted.</p>
                <p>7. Additionally, trade unions are getting into the act. Most of trade unions will
                    be supporting students actively by joining in demonstrations and by strikes
                    beginning this week.</p>
                <p>8. I asked <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> whether dismissal of
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> had been serious setback
                    for anti-Subandrio forces. He said not at all; <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1"
                        >Nasution</persName>, who continued to command nationwide respect, could now
                    operate more effectively behind scenes than from office in Defense Ministry.
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> and Soeharto remained close
                    but it was better to have Soeharto the front man. I inquired about position of
                    General Machmud (Kodam V Commander in charge of Djakarta area). <persName
                        corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> said he was completely with Soeharto.</p>
                <p>9. Finally and most importantly, I asked <persName corresp="#p_MA1"
                        >Malik</persName> about general security situation as it affected Americans
                    and American property. I pointed out that <persName corresp="#p_SSD2"
                        >Subandrio</persName> reaction to attacks by students on his Foreign Office
                    and against him personally seemed almost certain to result in his trying to
                    retaliate as well as divert attention. He could not target the army or the
                    students, so it was quite probable he would incite his goon squads against our
                    Embassy. We’ve already had two examples of that in past <pb facs="0454" n="416"
                        xml:id="pg_416"/> two weeks.<note n="2" xml:id="d199fn2">On February 23 and
                        March 8 small, well-organized groups of leftists attacked the U.S. Embassy.
                        There were no injuries and no attackers penetrated the Embassy building.
                        (Telegram 2509 from Djakarta, March 8; ibid.)</note> I also had some rather
                    disturbing reports from unevaluated sources that Sukarno has indicated in his
                    anger that he would do to the Americans what he had done to the British several
                    years ago. This meant danger to our residences as well as the Chancery. What did
                        <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> think of that?</p>
                <p>10. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> replied that undoubtedly
                    Subandrio will attempt anti-US actions. However, this will receive no support
                    from overwhelming elements here, and the army will definitely step in to protect
                    the Americans. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> felt there was no
                    need to evacuate members of American community from Djakarta but suggested that
                    they remain out of sight as much as possible, particularly during next week or
                    so when things likely to be hyper-tense.</p>
                <p>11. I told <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> once again that I hoped
                    for a new relationship between our governments, one that was productive and
                    helpful from Indonesia’s viewpoint, and that meanwhile it was absolutely vital
                    that nothing occur, such as anti-American actions, which would gravely, if not
                    permanently, injure our relations and eliminate future possibilities for
                    fruitful friendship and cooperation. He said he fully understood my point. He
                    felt the same way. He said he was more assured than ever that things would work
                    out the way we both wanted. Certainly his mood reflected this assurance.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d199fn3">In telegram 2564 from Djakarta, March 12, 0150Z, the
                        Embassy reported that a reliable source indicated that the Army was in the
                        process of arresting 20 cabinet ministers. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>12. I asked <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malik</persName> to feel free to share the
                    burden of our conversation with <persName corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName>
                    and Soeharto. He said he would do so.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="p_GM3">Green</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
