<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>23. Telegram From the Embassy in Indonesia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-01-23T04:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-01-23T04:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recdbjtxjnHuY2yic" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ministerial meeting</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="rec1GiKVfLPrlIGzK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">C–130</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-01-23T04:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-01-23T04:30:00-05:00" n="23"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                <head>23. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d23fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 32–1 INDON–MALAYSIA. Secret; Immediate; <gloss
                            target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>. Received at 6:25 a.m. and repeated
                        to Bangkok, Kuala Lumpur, London, Manila, Tokyo, and <gloss
                            target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1"
                            >POLAD</gloss>. Copies were passed to the White House and <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Djakarta</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-01-23T16:30:00+07:00">January 23, 1964, 4:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1510. From Atty General. <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1502.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d23fn2">In telegram 1502 from Djakarta, January 22, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName> reported from Djakarta that
                            <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> was not prepared to
                        call a cease-fire unless the United States convinced the Malaysians to state
                        they were ceasing hostilities. <persName corresp="#p_KRF1"
                            >Kennedy</persName> stated he would not associate himself with any move
                        which equated Malaysian military moves with Indonesia guerrillas and troops
                        in Malaysia. <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName> agreed to issue
                        a general statement that all sides agreed that talks were desirable and a
                        cessation of hostilities was required to provide the necessary calm.
                        (Ibid.)</note> Following summarizes Atty Gen’s (<gloss target="#t_AG1"
                        >AG</gloss>) talks with <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>
                    (First Dep <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>/FonMin <persName corresp="#p_SSD2"
                        >Subandrio</persName>, Second Dep <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LJ9">Leimena</persName>, Third Dep <gloss target="#t_PM1"
                        >PM</gloss> Chairul Saleh, Dep FonMin <pb facs="0084" n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SK1">Suwito</persName>, Army C/S Gen <persName
                        corresp="#p_JY1">Jani</persName>, Min Defense Gen <persName
                        corresp="#p_NGAH1">Nasution</persName> also present) evening Jan 23: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>At <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>’s invitation
                                    <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> outlined results discussions
                                in Manila and <gloss target="#t_KL1">KL</gloss>, stating that
                                procedures discussed in Tokyo were acceptable in both capitals. He
                                said both <persName corresp="#p_MD5">Macapagal</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName> believed situation
                                was deteriorating in way which involved threat to entire area and
                                that they were interested in peaceful, Asian solution. AG had told
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName> that if the
                                tripartite meeting was arranged <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                    >Sukarno</persName> would put out statement ordering cessation
                                hostilities and that organized military activities would take day or
                                so to halt while guerrilla activities would take perhaps seven days
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> interjected
                                “at least”) to control.</p>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> said he had talked about dates and
                                calculated that assuming week required to call off military
                                confrontation, i.e., military activities would cease around end of
                                January, ministerial meeting could take place in Bangkok Feb 5–6.
                                    <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> said the arrangements for this
                                meeting would be up to Thanat Khoman who it was understood was
                                acceptable to all three parties to dispute. AG would go to Bangkok
                                to fill him [in] personally over dinner Thursday night, Jan 24;
                                after that go to London.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> discussed designation of
                            observer-investigator mentioning that there was some reluctance on part
                            both Phils and Malaysians to accept Japanese but that Thai acceptable to
                            both. <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> said Malaysians would like UNSYG
                            to name Thais. <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>
                            worried this matter two or three times with questions but in end
                            accepted proposal.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> mentioned Manila’s thought that
                            political confrontation should also cease and discussed desirability of
                            stopping controversial radio broadcasts. Both <persName
                                corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and <persName
                                corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName> indicated they were
                            interested in this aspect and agreed to stop anti-Malaysian radio
                            broadcasts and knock off political confrontation if other side would do
                            same.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> concluded this part presentation by
                            stating that as result his talks with all three parties he convinced
                            that each interested in peaceful settlement, that Malaysians and Phils
                            both feel situation deteriorating and that in his judgment all parties
                            willing to enter talks in good faith. He said he had left Jim Bell in
                                <gloss target="#t_KL1">KL</gloss> and that if reports from him there
                            and from Ambs in other countries involved should indicate any change in
                            necessary atmosphere of good faith, he would tell this to <persName
                                corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> questioned <gloss
                                target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> closely whether <persName
                                corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName> would come into conference as
                            “Prime Minister of Malaysia.” <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                >Sukarno</persName>’s first reaction was that it would be impossible
                            for him to meet with <persName corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName> as
                            Prime Minister of Malaysia. <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> explained
                            that he had discussed this issue with <persName corresp="#p_TAR2"
                                >Tunku</persName> and had stressed to him that recognition could not
                            be pre-condition of <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>,
                            and that each side could hold its own standpoint on this matter, i.e.,
                                <persName corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName> could come as <gloss
                                target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss> of Malaysia and <persName
                                corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> could meet with him,
                            regarding <persName corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName> in any way he
                            wanted. <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> also <pb facs="0085" n="47"
                                xml:id="pg_47"/> stressed that issue should be minimized by both
                            sides and not allowed to ruin chance for talks. <persName
                                corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> finally accepted. (Indos
                            were perhaps somewhat persuaded by fact, which was spelled out to them,
                            that US reps regularly talk to ChiCom reps without involving recognition
                            question.)</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and <persName
                                    corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName>, with some assistance
                                from Gen <persName corresp="#p_JY1">Jani</persName>, made strong
                                attempt revise talks in Tokyo to provide for withdrawal of troops
                                along border in Kalimantan by both Indos and British. They pressed
                                hard on necessity British issuing cease fire order at same time they
                                would do so. “I can only give order to my troops to cease fire if
                                British give order to theirs,” <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                    >Sukarno</persName> said. There was extended argument about this
                                in which <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> made clear that he
                                regarded Indos major offenders in this matter and it was hardly
                                possible to ask Malaysians or British to announce cease fire. It was
                                Indos who were making most of incursions although there might have
                                been few incidents by other side. It was Indos who were out to crush
                                Malaysia not vice versa. <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> said he
                                would not be party to equating Indo military activities with those
                                defensive activities by other side.</p>
                            <p>
                                <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> argued that in
                                Tokyo “two times I said ‘both sides.’” Amb Zain interjected
                                unhelpfully “We Indonesians all understood there would be cease fire
                                on both sides.” Gen <persName corresp="#p_JY1">Jani</persName>, too,
                                said he had understood that if Indonesia withdrew their troops
                                British would also withdraw theirs. <gloss target="#t_AG1"
                                    >AG</gloss> said withdrawal of troops was impractical and was
                                not what had been agreed in Tokyo. <persName corresp="#p_JY1"
                                    >Jani</persName> said there were two groups of fighters:
                                regulars and “Kalimantan freedom fighters.” He said latter would
                                cooperate only if they thought that what Indo did would benefit
                                them. If British did not cease mopping up activities against them
                                they would defend themselves. <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss>
                                repeatedly reminded <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                    >Sukarno</persName> it was Malaysians not British who required
                                make commitments on military activities in Malaysia.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> said arrangement would not be ideal
                            but there was no alternative. He said he would do what he could and that
                            US Ambassadors in capitals concerned would also do what they could do to
                            help keep incidents from getting out of hand. Main thing was to get
                            talks going. Surely guerrillas could protect themselves for few weeks.
                            If there were incidents they could be investigated. <gloss
                                target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> had proceeded to other capitals on basis
                                <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>’s commitment to
                            him in Tokyo that he would issue cease fire order to Indo troops.
                            Without that there could be no talks.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>After extended argument on this point, <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                >Sukarno</persName> switched discussion to his problem of selling
                            cease fire to Indo people. <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                >Sukarno</persName> asked <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> whether
                            he would ask British “Are you willing silently or otherwise to order
                            cease fire”? <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> said he had already asked
                            this of Malaysians and that their answer was affirmative. <gloss
                                target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> again stressed <pb facs="0086" n="48"
                                xml:id="pg_48"/> that it was Indo military activity which was
                            causing trouble and which had to be stopped before talks could proceed.
                                <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> said it was clear to him that
                            Malaysians and those in support of them would welcome Indo cease
                            fire.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and others finally
                            abandoned their attempts alter Tokyo agreement. <persName
                                corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and <persName
                                corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName> pressed <gloss
                                target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> earnestly, however, for general statement
                                <gloss target="#t_AP1">AP</gloss> press conference scheduled noon
                            Jan 23 that parties concerned all agreed on desirability of talks and
                            necessity cessation military activities to provide period of calm that
                            would make talks possible. <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> agreed try
                            to make some general statement to this effect stressing however that he
                            wished to save most of this for announcement he would make in Bangkok.
                            (See operative para <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss>’s statement to
                            press Jan 24—<gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>.)</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> agreed ministers
                            meeting should be held Bangkok but insisted that venue for summit be
                            decided at ministers meeting and not beforehand. <persName
                                corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> indicated he had promised
                            Japanese that summit might be held Tokyo but assured us there would be
                            no shift to Phnom Penh.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Min Chairul Saleh asked whether <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss>
                            would talk with British about causes of tensions between them and
                            Indonesians. He referred particularly to British impounding C–130 spare
                            parts in <gloss target="#t_HK1">HK</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_AG1"
                                >AG</gloss> agreed consider discussing with British any thoughts on
                            Indo-British relationship which Indos could give him in memo form but
                            promised nothing. <persName corresp="#p_SC2">Saleh</persName> indicated
                            he would provide <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> with memo on <gloss
                                target="#t_HK1">HK</gloss> situation prior <gloss target="#t_AG1"
                                >AG</gloss>’s departure. Later, after dinner, <persName
                                corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName> raised this matter with
                                <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> again stressing difficulties
                                <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> having with labor because of
                                <gloss target="#t_HK1">HK</gloss> situation. <persName
                                corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName> was particularly insistent
                            that engines for C–130s which Indos had acquired from Lockheed had been
                            “confiscated” by British.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                        >Sukarno</persName> is frequently different man in Djakarta where he is
                    subject to and conscious of domestic political pressures than he is outside
                    Indonesia. This fits <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss>’s impression on this
                    occasion. At times during this talk it was almost as if agreement reached Tokyo
                    didn’t exist. However, <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> (with
                    some help from <persName corresp="#p_SSD2">Subandrio</persName>) came around at
                    end and agreed to stand by Tokyo agreement. This was obviously difficult for him
                    in face situation here. In <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss>’s and my judgment
                    situation is most delicate one which will require utmost in effort and
                    coordination to hold. Repeated Indo reference during these talks to British
                    “divide and rule” tactics and to <persName corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName>’s
                    alleged inclination exploit any concessions by <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> for domestic political purposes were two striking examples
                    depth Indo suspicions. Nevertheless, <gloss target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> secured
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>’s agreement to give cease
                    fire order and to otherwise proceed on basis agreement reached Tokyo. I think
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> wants to resolve this
                    matter although whether his terms for substantive settlement <pb facs="0087"
                        n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> would be acceptable to other side remains, of
                    course, to be seen. <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>’s
                    announcement of cease fire order to press as he stood beside <gloss
                        target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss> and his favorable reference to <gloss
                        target="#t_AG1">AG</gloss>’s efforts (see separate report on press
                        conf)<note n="3" xml:id="d23fn3">Telegram 516 from Djakarta, January 23.
                        (Ibid.)</note> would appear to underline impetus <gloss target="#t_AG1"
                        >AG</gloss>’s talks here have given possibility negotiated settlement.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="p_GFJ2">Galbraith</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
