<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>253. Airgram From the Embassy in Indonesia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d253</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">253</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-02-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-02-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="reciuru9i20NCuS5s" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                    <term ref="recNuUP5FwVBYX7g7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic policies</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recAGfEAY7QRgUk1G" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092233"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Non-aligned nations</term>
                    <term ref="recNBOveCHYDHbAqL" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recUsSXH96nnonu86" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Agricultural development</term>
                    <term ref="rectduqNv1b6cCQCB" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001184"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Magazine</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Information programs</term>
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                    <term ref="association-of-southeast-asian-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="association-of-southeast-asian-nations" subject="asean">ASEAN</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-02-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-02-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="253"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d253">
                <head>253. Airgram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d253fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 1 INDON. Secret. Masters and Philip F. Gardner, political
                        officer at the Embassy, were the “coordinating drafters” of this airgram
                        which was approved by <persName corresp="#p_GM3">Green</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">A–423</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Djakarta</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-02-21">February 21, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>U.S. Policy Assessment</item>
                </list>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>REF</head>
                    <item>CA–6014.</item>
                    <item>CA–5400.<note n="2" xml:id="d253fn2">Neither found.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Country Team Message.</p>
                <pb facs="0582" n="544" xml:id="pg_544"/>
                <p rend="center">I. Indonesian Setting</p>
                <p>In March 1967 <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> was totally
                    removed from power, and a “New Order” under the leadership of Acting President
                        <persName corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName> assumed full
                    responsibility for governing the nation. The transition from <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_Suharto1"
                        >Suharto</persName>, which took a year and a half of patient and effective
                    effort by the latter, did not produce the internal upheaval many had felt was
                    inevitable. The ease with which the transition was accompanied was, in fact, a
                    reflection of <persName corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName>’s excellent
                    sense of timing and his understanding of at least the dominant Javanese segment
                    of Indonesian society.</p>
                <p>At the same time, removal of <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>
                    took away a convenient scapegoat with the result that since March 1967 all of
                    Indonesia’s pent up expectations have centered on the new government. With the
                    departure of <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>, the “New Order”
                    also lost the unifying force of a common enemy, and social, cultural and
                    religious frictions have increased markedly during the past nine months.</p>
                <p>These problems will continue to press in on the <persName corresp="#p_Suharto1"
                        >Suharto</persName> government during the coming year, as will the desperate
                    shortage of trained personnel, Indonesia’s critical economic situation, the
                    increasing expectations of the people, revival of serious political in-fighting,
                    and others.</p>
                <p>Despite the problems and shortcomings which were accentuated during 1967, we
                    believe Indonesia has embarked on the long road toward modernization. It is
                    following sound economic policies and moderate foreign policies, although
                    progress in creating a domestic political base for the present government is far
                    slower than it could or should be. The present year will be crucial to the
                    success of these efforts, for during 1968 trends will be set in motion which
                    will determine the course of this important nation for many years to come.
                    (These problems are spelled out in detail in a companion report—Djakarta
                        A–358.)<note n="3" xml:id="d253fn3">For the summary, see <ref target="#d251"
                            >Document 251</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">II. Our Dilemma</p>
                <p>Following the removal of <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>, our
                    bilateral relations with Indonesia improved markedly. During 1967, American
                    owned businesses, previously taken over under the <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> regime, were returned to their
                    original owners, and several American firms, taking advantage of the present
                    government’s liberal economic policies, concluded agreements for new investments
                    in Indonesia. The bilateral air agreement between Indonesia and the United
                    States in late 1967 was one of the most favorable we have concluded in recent
                    years. The United States has become the pace setter for aid to Indonesia within
                    the Inter-Governmental <pb facs="0583" n="545" xml:id="pg_545"/> Group (<gloss
                        target="#t_IGG1">IGG</gloss>), and an increasing number of US officials
                    visited Indonesia during 1967, highlighted, of course, by the visit in November
                    of Vice President Humphrey, who established a new benchmark in our bilateral
                    relations.</p>
                <p>As a result of these and other factors, the US has become closely identified with
                    the goals and efforts of the <persName corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName>
                    government. Such an identification is in fact inevitable since we have a heavy
                    stake in the success of the “New Order” not only for obvious reasons related to
                    Indonesia’s size, strategic importance, resources and potential strength but
                    also because it is the latest test case of whether liberal economic policies
                    combined with free world assistance offer a more solid path to modernization
                    than communism or other totalitarian solutions.</p>
                <p>In seeking to advance our national interests in and regarding Indonesia, the
                    United States Government faces two fundamental problems, one deeply rooted in
                    Indonesian cultural norms and the other in our own tendency as a government to
                    become too deeply involved in the affairs of other nations. Our dilemma, simply
                    put, is this: we cannot and must not let the “New Order” fail, but we also must
                    not become so active that we conflict with Indonesia’s cultural heritage or
                    substitute our initiative for theirs. We have faced the problem ever since
                    October 1965 of treading this narrow line, but the increasing importance of the
                    US to Indonesia’s hopes for recovery means that the margin for error and for
                    misjudgment has become even more critical.</p>
                <p>While our stake in the “New Order” is large, our ability to assist it is
                    circumscribed. The experience of the United States Government in Indonesia over
                    the past 15 years clearly shows that the injection of our assistance into the
                    Indonesian economy does not provide a directly corresponding stimulus to growth
                    but will often be rejected, deflected or transformed by basic features in the
                    Indonesian social structure. Economic development through the infusion of
                    foreign skills and assistance apparently requires parallel development in other
                    sectors of the society. For this reason, it is perhaps best to regard our
                    ultimate aim in Indonesia not as economic development alone but as
                    modernization.</p>
                <p>Needless to say, we would run grave risks if we attempted directly to initiate or
                    even counsel reform in the social structure, where are moored the individual
                    Indonesian’s sense of security and identity. (<persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                        >Sukarno</persName> mobilized the nation behind his policies by pointing to
                    a Western threat to the “Indonesian way of life” and the anti-communist campaign
                    after the October 1, 1965 events was powered with similar fuel.) Our problem,
                    therefore, is to choose from among the priority needs, programs which are
                    compatible with the Indonesian social structure and yet active stimulants for
                    change. The overall process must in the Indonesians’ eyes appear as
                    “modernization,” not “Westernization” and least <pb facs="0584" n="546"
                        xml:id="pg_546"/> of all “Americanization.” If the process appears as
                    “Americanization”, we will not only waste our funds and incur blame for failures
                    but, more importantly, will trigger long acting rejection devices within the
                    Indonesian society to what is falsely identified as foreign intrusion rather
                    than internal development.</p>
                <p rend="center">III. Criteria for American Programs</p>
                <p>To date we believe U.S. policy has avoided the worst dangers of this dilemma and
                    has successfully advanced U.S. interests. Our timely economic assistance has
                    strengthened the hands of Indonesia’s “modernizers” and the U.S. has also been
                    successful to date in supporting Indonesia’s efforts to obtain substantial aid
                    from other donors. Our small but important <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>
                    has made a major contribution to encouraging the Indonesian military to move
                    into Civic Action projects which not only contribute to economic stabilization
                    but also help to enhance the local image of the Armed Forces. Our informational
                    and cultural programs have expanded modestly during the past year, with
                    particular emphasis being placed on distribution of one-half million American
                    books to Indonesian educational and other institutions. We have also had
                    continued success in our efforts to quietly influence Indonesia’s top
                    leadership. Indonesians not only seek our aid but privately they also seek our
                    advice and this has enhanced our ability to influence some, but by no means all,
                    developments. Finally, we have succeeded substantially in convincing Indonesia
                    to do business “through channels” and to cease sending visitors to Washington
                    armed with open-ended “hunting licenses” seeking aid and special favors.</p>
                <p>These past experiences and our estimate of the problems we will soon face in the
                    mounting urgency of the stabilization efforts and in the implementation of the
                    development plan lead us to suggest the following broad criteria for American
                    policy in Indonesia.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">A. Regionalism</hi>
                </p>
                <p>We must continue to encourage Indonesia to join in Southeast Asian cooperation.
                    In addition to the material and political benefits, closer regional ties will
                    encourage Indonesia to see itself as a partner and participant in a world-wide
                    process of modernization rather than a sick patient in the hands of Western
                    doctors. Indonesia’s neighbors, however, must be responsive. While suspicion on
                    the part of some of Indonesia’s neighbors is historically understandable, we
                    should encourage these nations to realize that a “New Order” has taken over in
                    Indonesia and that, even if they fail to accept this fact, the best and most
                    pragmatic way to guard against the possibility of future Indonesian adventurism
                    is to embrace Indonesia’s new government and interweave it inextricably in
                    responsible regional activities.</p>
                <pb facs="0585" n="547" xml:id="pg_547"/>
                <p>Our own expressions of support for regional organizations such as <gloss
                        target="#t_ASEAN1">ASEAN</gloss> should be decidedly low-key. The Soviets,
                    from whom the Indonesians hope to receive additional aid, are already charging
                    that <gloss target="#t_ASEAN1">ASEAN</gloss> is a “Western puppet” and the
                    Indonesians fear that too close an embrace by us would not only complicate their
                    relations with Moscow but also add substance to these allegations and perhaps
                    make it more difficult for <gloss target="#t_ASEAN1">ASEAN</gloss> to enlist the
                    support of additional non-aligned nations.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">B. Multilateral Approach</hi>
                </p>
                <p>We remain convinced of the necessity of setting our programs into a multilateral
                    framework, with the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>, <gloss
                        target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_IGG1">IGG</gloss>
                    nations assuming together a position well in advance of any individual foreign
                    government. This is both a more forceful method of persuading Indonesia to make
                    the tough decisions that will be required and a better guarantee against
                    Indonesia sluffing off responsibility to others’ shoulders. The multilateral
                    approach may, however, prove too slow or inflexible to meet certain problems of
                    exceptional urgency and we must recognize the need for flexibility in applying
                    this criterion.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">C. Adaptations to the Indonesian Social Structure</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There are three broad attributes of the Indonesian culture which will constitute
                    impediments to much-needed technical and project assistance and which we should
                    take into account in developing our programs: (1) a predominantly traditional
                    (as contrasted to rational) mode of thought which resists change, stresses human
                    adaptation to rather than manipulation of environment and recommends avoidance
                    rather than resolution of conflict; (2) particularistic (or personalized) rather
                    than universalistic values, emphasizing loyalty to kin or, more particular to
                    Indonesia, to a protector (Bapak) rather than to institutions or abstract codes
                    of behavior; and (3) a decentralized and compartmentalized organization of the
                    society with relatively little coordination exerted laterally and relatively
                    little authority exerted vertically.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the best single way of ensuring that an American program will be adjusted
                    to the Indonesian environment is to work through the so-called “third culture,”
                    that is Indonesians who have gained a broad knowledge of our culture and yet
                    retain accredited membership in their own. This type of person, most prominently
                    represented by General <persName corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName>’s team
                    of economic advisors, can serve as invaluable mediators between the two
                    cultures. Every assistance request should consequently by evaluated on the basis
                    of whether the Indonesians controlling or staffing the offices connected with
                    the program include a sufficient number of “third culture” persons.</p>
                <p>A second prerequisite for evaluating the prospects for an assistance program is
                    to identify the “Bapak” or “Bapaks” into whose spheres <pb facs="0586" n="548"
                        xml:id="pg_548"/> the project falls. If these are corruptionists, solely
                    political operators or pure traditionalists, the project will probably be
                    deflected from its economic as well as political aims. In this respect, we
                    should continue to promote the modernizer-staffed Bappenas as the agency most
                    directly responsible for economic development.</p>
                <p>It is much more difficult to propose criteria to meet the problem of
                    compartmentalization and decentralization. For the immediate future, however, we
                    should probably concentrate our attention within particular compartments and
                    resist the temptation to place technicians in coordinating roles between
                    compartments where they are more likely to replace than develop Indonesian
                    initiative in central coordination and supervision. (What we diagnose as lack of
                    “managerial skill” is often inability to move beyond the society’s structure, a
                    deficiency which cannot be rectified with instruction in American management
                    methods.) It may prove more fruitful to work outward from individual
                    compartments than to attempt to build up prior or simultaneous coordination and
                    supervision between them.</p>
                <p>The criteria in the immediately preceding paragraphs should not be regarded as
                    binding prerequisites but as safety precautions. They can and undoubtedly must
                    be set aside in certain instances. When it is deemed necessary to provide
                    technical assistance which will involve coordination and supervision of separate
                    Indonesian compartments, we should first seek to have the <gloss
                        target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> or
                    other multilateral bodies take on this task. Where the U.S. must assume this
                    role, the program should be designed with exceptional care and flexibility.
                    Advisors who run a clear risk of being drawn into coordinative or supervisory
                    roles must be carefully selected on the basis of personality and understanding
                    of the local culture. They might in many instances also be placed on TDY status
                    so as to appear as temporary trouble shooters rather than semi-permanent
                    replacements for roles the Indonesians are unwilling or unable to fill.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">D. Restricting the American Presence</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The criteria listed above all argue for continued restrictions on the American
                    presence in Indonesia. Although some growth in the size of the mission must
                    occur as we move into development projects, we would rule out for the
                    foreseeable future personnel from any U.S. Government agency serving in
                    sensitive fields such as community development, manpower planning, much of
                    public administration and some phases of local agricultural development.
                    Cultural programs should be concentrated in binational centers in Djakarta and,
                    if possible, Surabaya. (Savings in personnel in this sector would pay high
                    dividends if invested in magazine subscriptions and more books for donation to
                    key institutions and individuals.) Finally, those personnel who are assigned to
                    Indonesia to work closely with Indonesians must be <pb facs="0587" n="549"
                        xml:id="pg_549"/> carefully selected. (We have already had several minor
                    problems of adjustment.)</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">E. Working from the American Social Structure</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Moving Indonesians to an outside vantage point is undoubtedly the best way to
                    show them the deficiencies in their own social structure and stimulate a desire
                    for this change. For this reason, the participant training program is perhaps
                    the single most valuable component of a modernization program and must be
                    expanded.</p>
                <p>In order to ensure that this program results in the transfer of modernizing
                    attitudes as well as technical skills, we should consider: (1) emphasizing
                    training programs of at least two years in length for adults; (2) concentrating
                    on youth, whose attitudes are more flexible—we should welcome the revival of the
                        <gloss target="#t_AFS1">AFS</gloss> program if the <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> officially asks for it, although we cannot prompt the <gloss
                        target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> on this issue; and (3) “team training” in which
                    five or six Indonesians are trained in related fields at the same time and at
                    the same institution. Upon return to Indonesia these teams should be so grouped
                    in their occupational fields as to provide mutual reinforcement against the
                    social forces which lead to a reversion to a traditionalist framework of
                    thinking. (<persName corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName>’s economic team of
                    advisors is testimony to the success of this method.)</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">F. Building Indonesian Confidence</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Perhaps the foremost requirement of any American assistance program is that it
                    serve to build Indonesian confidence in the modernization process. This
                    criterion is now most pertinent to the stabilization program. Aside from causing
                    important segments of the population to lose faith in and withhold cooperation
                    from the <persName corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName> government, failure
                    of the stabilization program would also perhaps cause <persName
                        corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName> to lose confidence in pragmatic
                    policies and those who have recommended them (the <gloss target="#t_IMF1"
                        >IMF</gloss>, Western governments and his own team of economic advisors). It
                    may, in fact, be useless to talk of economic development if <persName
                        corresp="#p_Suharto1">Suharto</persName> is unable to surmount the inflation
                    hurdle within the next eighteen months.</p>
                <p>We are now clearly faced with the probability that <gloss target="#t_IGG1"
                        >IGG</gloss> nations at their March meeting will not pledge the full $325
                    million of assistance requested of them by the Indonesian Government and the
                        <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>. Such a result will risk losing the
                    confidence which both the Indonesian public and leadership have placed in the
                        <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> and the multilateral approach, and this
                    confidence is perhaps a more important determinant to the success of the
                    stabilization effort than the sums left unsubscribed. If the United States moves
                    to make up this deficit, on the other hand, we risk setting an undesirable
                    precedent for a larger American role in and responsibility for the stabilization
                    program and perhaps the <pb facs="0588" n="550" xml:id="pg_550"/> development
                    program which will follow. For the Embassy the last risk is clearly the lesser.
                    In the final analysis, of course, the extent and nature of our aid must be
                    measured against Indonesia’s own performance. Our long-term interests in this
                    important country require that we not substitute our initiative for theirs or be
                    so responsive to Indonesia’s requests that pressures for self-help measures are
                    weakened.</p>
                <p rend="center">IV. Conclusion</p>
                <p>U.S. policy towards Indonesia must address two broad problems, the relatively
                    short-term task of economic stabilization and the long-term task of
                    modernization. The approaches we have outlined above apply to both problems but
                    with different intensity.</p>
                <p>Our role in economic stabilization is a relatively simple one because it involves
                    minimal contact with the Indonesian social structure: multilateral agencies
                    provide advice and supervision, an outstanding group of “third culture” persons
                    serve as capable intermediaries, and a large American presence is not required.
                    Our decisions in this sector are nevertheless difficult ones as they are couched
                    in urgency and must weigh American resources against possible Indonesian loss of
                    confidence in pragmatic measures.</p>
                <p>In defining our role in Indonesia’s modernization, there is perhaps less need for
                    speed than caution. We are fortunate to be starting off with virtually a clean
                    slate as regards technical and project assistance and information programs.
                    Unlike Vietnam, Laos and Thailand, the urgency of the Indonesian problem is not
                    such as to preclude us from setting up careful test procedures. With a
                    cooperative government, a classically traditionalist society and a good measure
                    of material resources, Indonesia constitutes a good test subject.</p>
                <p>The Embassy consequently recommends that we treat our role in Indonesia as a
                    controlled experiment in modernization. We should begin to apply the criteria we
                    have set out above and develop new criteria as experience is gained. The
                    development of our assistance programs must from the outset be geared to
                    Indonesian performance. In this respect, we will want to keep a careful watch
                    not only on economic measurements but also on the incidence of corruption, on
                    the abuse of authority and on the tendency towards militarism, all of which are
                    relatively good gauges of the progress towards modernization in the social
                    structure.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>MG</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
