<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-09-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-09-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                        <head>346. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="from">Rostow</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d346fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Memos to the President, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>, Vol. 13, 9/15/66–9/30/66.
                                Confidential.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-09-16">September 16, 1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>U.S. Aid to the Philippines</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Whenever the United States agrees to help a country in need, it is
                            easy—and all too common—to ascribe a cynical motive to that action. It
                            is easy, too, too put a price tag on the action and to believe that
                            thereby you have described a policy. It is all too simple—and generally
                            superficial—to take an action by Government A and an action by
                            Government B and make one the “pay off” for the other.</p>
                        <pb facs="0803" n="765" xml:id="pg_765"/>
                        <p>This has been the approach in some of the reporting of your decision to
                            lend new assistance to the Government of President <persName corresp="#p_MFE2">Marcos</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Much of the reporting ignores several fundamental points involved in this
                            decision. Among these fundamental points, I would note the
                            following:</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The assistance program just announced in outline is
                                a determined effort to help a friendly country that is in
                                trouble.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Philippine economy has become almost a model of unstructured,
                            unbalanced, and stunted growth. The late 1950’s were boom years. Gross
                            National Product was growing at more than 5% a year. Industrialization
                            was proceeding at a fast pace. But the rapid growth was unstable. The
                            peso was over-valued. Import prices were artificially low. There were
                            virtually guaranteed markets for the main exports.</p>
                        <p>In 1962, exchange controls were eliminated. The peso suffered almost 100%
                            devaluation. Many marginal industries were in trouble. World prices for
                            Philippine exports fell. Growth rates declined. The economy began to
                            stagnate. The agricultural sector (employing between 70 and 80 per cent
                            of the population) failed to expand. The Philippines, a rich farming
                            country, finds itself importing 90% of its milk and dairy products and
                            10% of its total food needs. The population continues to rise
                            dramatically (about 3.3% a year) as <gloss target="#t_GNP1">GNP</gloss>
                            stagnates at about 4%.</p>
                        <p>Our Filipino friends frankly admit that their operations are plagued by
                            bureaucratic ineptness and nonperformance. Tax collections are
                            inefficient and graft-ridden. Smuggling robs the federal treasury of
                            $100 million or more a year.</p>
                        <p>In the last half of 1965, credit restraints were largely ignored with the
                            result that there was a 5% increase in the money supply since June 1955.
                            A 10% rise in living costs occurred in the same period.</p>
                        <p>In part as a reflection of deepening economic trouble, Communist
                            insurgents have increased their activity; propaganda efforts,
                            recruitment and terrorism are all on the rise.</p>
                        <p>So here is a country in deep trouble, and we are trying to help.</p>
                        <p>The cynical can assert that we are merely “repaying” Filipinos for their
                            decision to send troops to Viet-Nam. The fact is that we would have
                            helped them in any case—indeed, most of the programs now going forward
                            were being considered long before the Philippines’ courageous decision
                            to help their Vietnamese neighbors.</p>
                        <p>Needless to say, we are not providing economic aid to our Australian and
                            New Zealand friends—who also have sent troops to Viet-Nam.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">In working with President <persName corresp="#p_MFE2">Marcos</persName>, we are cooperating with a
                                new and active administration, one that has clearly recognized its
                                country’s fundamental problems and a chief executive who is fiercely
                                determined to move his country forward.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0804" n="766" xml:id="pg_766"/>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_MFE2">Marcos</persName> is not a man to
                            ask for handouts or gifts without strings. He is a proud man. He is a
                            man who wants progress for his people. He believes—and we share the
                            belief—that the development and prosperity of his country is good, not
                            only for the Philippines, but for Asia and for us.</p>
                        <p>He has taken steps to improve the efficient operation of his government.
                            He has searched for men of capability and devotion and put them in
                            positions of responsibility. He continues that search. He has moved
                            actively against smuggling. He is trying to improve his country’s tax
                            collection system. He has worked out a Four-Year Development Program
                            which underlines his goals, and we are working with his specialists to
                            refine that program and to outline workable and feasible projects.</p>
                        <p>And his principal goal is to improve the agriculture of his country. He
                            wants to expand productivity. He wants to build new roads that will
                            bring the countryside into contact with the towns—and therefore with the
                            markets. He wants to provide electric power for his people in the
                            countryside, and to give them the water they need for irrigation.</p>
                        <p>An important element in President <persName corresp="#p_MFE2">Marcos</persName>’ plan is his concentration on 10 of his country’s
                            provinces. These are areas where the need for improvement is
                            greatest.</p>
                        <p>Beyond meeting the present urgent problems in his economy, President
                                <persName corresp="#p_MFE2">Marcos</persName> wants his country to
                            move proudly forward over the frontiers of science and technology. He
                            wants to share in the exploration of space and of the ocean depths, to
                            improve the technical and scientific training of his young people, and
                            to provide for both training and research in the area of economic
                            development.</p>
                        <p>We are cooperating with him in these ambitious enterprises—not to help a
                            man but to help a man who wants to help his people.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">A careful look at the proposed forms of our
                                assistance shows that each one is designed to help President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MFE2">Marcos</persName> and the
                                Philippines to meet some of the specific problems they
                                face—particularly in the agricultural sector.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To be specific: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>A $4.5 million loan</p>
                                    <p>This is for irrigation. It will make possible the
                                        reconstruction and extension of existing irrigation works,
                                        providing much-needed water for the farmers.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Feasibility study loan—$2 million</p>
                                    <p>This will permit the Filipinos to conduct engineering and
                                        economic studies, with our help, which will tell them
                                        whether proposed new projects, including additional
                                        irrigation works, make sense. These studies will follow up
                                        surveys already conducted in the Water Resources survey.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>PL–480 (Title II)</p>
                                    <pb facs="0805" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/>
                                    <p>A grant of food grains and other agricultural products.</p>
                                    <p>This will provide: <list>
                                            <label>(a)</label>
                                            <item>Partial payment (in the amount of $3.5 million) to
                                                some 30,000 workers who will be digging and
                                                renovating irrigation ditches and building or
                                                repairing local roads.</item>
                                            <label>(b)</label>
                                            <item>$.5 million in grains, returns from which will
                                                help to capitalize livestock cooperatives.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                </item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>
                                        <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>–480 (Title IV)</p>
                                    <p>Sale of between $20 and $25 million worth of needed cotton,
                                        feed grains and tobacco.</p>
                                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">Note</hi>: This is repayable in dollars at
                                        3.5% interest.)</p>
                                    <p>The peso proceeds from sale of these products will provide
                                        increased capital for the Agriculture Credit
                                        Administration.</p>
                                    <p>They will also be used: <list>
                                            <item>—for local costs of irrigation rehabilitation
                                                projects;</item>
                                            <item>—for feeder road construction;</item>
                                            <item>—possibly for some capital for the Land
                                                Bank.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>There may also be some small grants to government agencies
                                        for such things as: agricultural research, technical
                                        training in agriculture; pest and crop disease control; land
                                        classification studies in connection with land reform.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Engineering equipment ($1.8 million)</p>
                                    <p>This is equipment from surplus military stocks. It will be
                                        renovated by use of <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>
                                        funds. Value of the repaired equipment is estimated at $10
                                        million and it will be given to provincial governments (in 8
                                        of the 10 critical provinces). The equipment is to be used
                                        in the road-building program and for irrigation and other
                                        agricultural development projects.</p>
                                    <p>We will also be supplying some spare parts and technical
                                        training on operations and maintenance.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Other technical assistance (about $1 million)</p>
                                    <p>To be used for such things as providing for a team from the
                                        U.S. Farmers Union to advise on agricultural credit, and for
                                        a team from the Rural Electric Cooperative Association to
                                        help work up projects for establishing new rural
                                        electrification cooperatives.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>(7)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>
                                        <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>–480 (Title III)</p>
                                    <p>This is a continuing program. It provides food products to
                                        U.S. voluntary agencies, such as the Catholic Relief
                                        Service, for their programs of aid to needy Filipinos.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>(8)</label>
                                <item>In view of the need for better performance in the tax
                                    collection field, we have sent several specialists from the
                                    Internal Revenue Service to the Philippines. This is a small
                                    project which represents about 2 1/2 man-years of labor on our
                                    part annually.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0806" n="768" xml:id="pg_768"/>
                        <p>Even our assistance in the military field is related closely to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_MFE2">Marcos</persName> desire to help his
                            farmers. The five engineer battalions we have agreed to support this
                            year with equipment will be used by him in civic action
                            projects—primarily road-building in rural areas.</p>
                        <p>This, we see when we look beneath the titles and the amounts, that the
                            assistance program that we are working out with the Philippines is
                            designed to meet specific needs, and primarily those needs in the field
                            of agriculture which the Philippine Government and we recognize as most
                            urgent.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Finally, it should be clear that the kind of program
                                outlined in this memo and which we hope to carry out with the
                                Philippines Government is a reflection of your consistent—and often
                                repeated—concern with the problem of food production in a world
                                where the population is rising steadily.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>For example, on March 19, 1964, in your foreign aid message, you noted:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Funds for educational and technical cooperation—to help start
                                    schools, health centers, agricultural experimental stations,
                                    credit services, and dozens of other institutions … But they
                                    will be used by selected projects to raise the ability of less
                                    fortunate peoples to meet their own needs.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>A year later, on January 14, 1965, you said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In the years ahead, if the developing countries are to continue
                                    to grow, they must rapidly enlarge their capacity to provide
                                    food for their people. Up to a point, they can and should
                                    improve their ability to buy some of their food from abroad. For
                                    the most part, however, they must expand and diversify their own
                                    production of food.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>On February 10, 1966—in your <hi rend="italic">Food for Freedom—you
                                said:</hi>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“We will launch a major, new attack on worldwide hunger. We will
                                    present this year a new food aid program designed around the
                                    principle of intense cooperation with those in all hungry
                                    countries who are ready to help themselves. We will direct our
                                    assistance program toward a cooperative effort to increase
                                    agricultural production.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>And again this year—on June 30, 1966 in your <hi rend="italic">Food for
                                Peace Report— you said:</hi>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In simplest terms the task of bringing food and population into
                                    balance—while maintaining progress in health, education and
                                    economic growth—is the most critical challenge many countries
                                    are facing today. It will probably remain their most urgent
                                    challenge in the immediate years ahead. The world’s capacity to
                                    respond will dramatically affect the course which individuals
                                    and nations choose in confronting their problems and neighbors
                                    in coming generations.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="strong">
                                    <persName corresp="p_RWW1">W. W. Rostow</persName>
                                </hi><note n="2" xml:id="d346fn2">Printed from a copy that bears
                                    this typed signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>