<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>68. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in the United
                    Kingdom</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d68</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">68</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-09-02T19:48:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-09-02T19:48:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-09-02T19:48:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-09-02T19:48:00-05:00" n="68"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d68">
                <head>68. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d68fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 32–1 INDON–MALAYSIA. Secret; Immediate; Exdis. Drafted and
                        approved by <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> and cleared by
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BWP1"
                            >William Bundy</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_CH4"
                            >Cleveland</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-09-02T20:48:00-04:00">September 2, 1964, 8:48 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1590. For Ambassador from Secretary. You will have seen another telegram about
                    our reaction to Indonesian paratroop drop on Malaysia and our readiness to
                    support Malaysia in the Security Council<note n="2" xml:id="d68fn2">In telegram
                        200 to Kuala Lumpur, September 2, repeated to London, the Department
                        suggested that, if the reports of Indonesia paratroopers landings in Johore
                        and five sites on the west coast between Malacca and Singapore were
                        confirmed, such action would meet the prerequisite of markedly stepped up
                        hostilities necessary for a successful initiative by Malaysia with the
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Security Council. These actions were
                        not the “ambiguous, desultory infiltrations in North Borneo” of the past.
                        (Ibid.)</note> but it is my impression that if the Malaysians come in with a
                    strong case and good evidence, including such things as interrogation results,
                    it will be hard for Security Council members to accept Indonesian action.</p>
                <p>I am somewhat concerned about nature of British discussion of retaliation in the
                    event that Security Council action is unsatisfactory. I am not now referring to
                        Mountbatten’s<note n="3" xml:id="d68fn3">Earl Mountbatten of Burma, Chief of
                        the British Defense Staff.</note> suggestion of a small commando-type raid
                    to capture some prisoners but rather <persName corresp="#p_SDE1">Duncan
                        Sandys</persName>’ discussion of air strikes, etc. A cooling off period
                    would make it more difficult to get support internationally for such
                    retaliation. Further, Thorneycroft’s<note n="4" xml:id="d68fn4">Peter
                        Thorneycroft, British Minister of Defense.</note> comment to Acheson<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d68fn5">Dean Acheson, former Secretary of State, January
                        1949–January 1953.</note> that British will wish to avoid anything that
                    might escalate would seem to impose very severe limitations upon the nature of
                    any such retaliation.</p>
                <p>There is one point you should be very clear about in your discussions of such
                    matters with British Ministers. We cannot give them a blank check and pick up
                    the tab for escalation by the use of US forces without the fullest and most
                    precise understanding between Heads of Government. If this is what they have in
                    mind, they must not take anything for granted in an area where we have our hands
                    full and with a minimum of allied participation. I would suppose that if the
                    British are contemplating overt retaliation involving such things as air strikes
                    or the shelling of shore installation in Indonesia that would necessarily mean
                    the movement of substantial additional British forces into the area. Even though
                    the Gulf of Tonkin is not a parallel to this particular problem, I remind you
                    for use with British Ministers that the US immediately sent powerful
                    reinforcements to the Far East to <pb facs="0188" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> deal
                    with the consequences of any effort by Hanoi or Peiping to escalate. In other
                    words, the US cannot accept the idea that the British handling of this problem
                    is on the basis of a limited liability. They must back up their actions with a
                    readiness on their part to meet the consequences. If they want us involved, they
                    must find out whether that is possible and, again, take nothing for
                        granted.<note n="6" xml:id="d68fn6">In telegram 1082 from London, September
                        3, Bruce reported that he talked to British Secretary of State for
                        Commonwealth Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_SDE1">Duncan Sandys</persName>,
                        who appreciated U.S. support of Malaysia in the Security Council, did not
                        expect a blank check from the United States, and was not thinking of
                        retaliation unless there was another aggression by Indonesia. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SDE1">Sandys</persName> stated that even if there was
                        retaliation, it would be limited. <persName corresp="#p_SDE1"
                            >Sandys</persName> suggested that it was hardly necessary for the United
                        States to warn him not to take the United States for granted since it always
                        took Britain for granted. (National Archives and Records Administration, RG
                        59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 32–1
                        INDON–MALAYSIA)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="p_RD3">Rusk</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
