<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-09-04T14:58:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-09-04T14:58:00-05:00" n="70" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d70">
                        <head>70. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d70fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 32–1 INDON–MALAYSIA. Secret;
                                Immediate. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_IEC1">Ingraham</persName>, cleared in substance by Frank M. Tucker,
                                Jr., of the Office of British Commonwealth Affairs, and approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-09-04T15:58:00-04:00">September 4, 1964, 3:58
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>1648. Following is text of message from FonSec Butler delivered to
                            Secretary this morning:</p>
                        <p>“As you know, we have been urgently considering with the Malaysian
                            Government how best they should react to the landing of Indonesian <pb facs="0190" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/> parachutists in Johore. It was
                            our conviction, which I am glad to say is now shared by the <persName corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName>, that the first step must be to
                            raise the matter urgently in the Security Council.<note n="2" xml:id="d70fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> wrote <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName> a note on September
                                4 indicating that “in light of new Indo-Malaysian flap,” there was
                                “real merit in getting <persName>Jones</persName> back to Djakarta
                                soonest, but perhaps with some strong words from here.” <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> suggested that “the British
                                sound just as hysterical as <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>,” and he stated, “we can’t stop <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and Malaysia going to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> if 30-man paradrop proves to be fact.
                                Indeed <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> would be a good safety
                                valve to get Brits off talk of Tonkin Gulf-style retaliation.”
                                (Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Indonesia,
                                Vol. II, Memos, 9/64–2/65)</note> When this was discussed in the
                            Malaysian Cabinet, however, a strong and understandable demand emerged
                            that as a condition of Malaysia referring her difficulties to the
                            Security Council we should give an assurance of our agreement in
                            principle to take some kind of action against Indonesia on Indonesian
                                soil.<note n="3" xml:id="d70fn3">Also on September 4, Australian
                                Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WJK1">Waller</persName> informed
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CH4">Cleveland</persName> of Malaysia’s
                                request for support of “armed defensive measures on Indonesian soil”
                                in the event the action in the Security Council failed. <persName corresp="#p_WJK1">Waller</persName> stated he was consulting the
                                United States in view of the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                                treaty. <persName>Bundy</persName> stressed the need for close
                                consultation, especially in light of the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> relationship, but warned <persName corresp="#p_WJK1">Waller</persName> that Australia should not
                                assume that the United States would become involved if the
                                escalation took place. (Circular telegram 441, September 4; National
                                Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66,
                                    <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 32–1 INDON–MALAYSIA)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Since our major concern was to persuade Malaysia to go to the Security
                            Council without delay, we had no option but to agree to some assurance,
                            if not exactly on the lines requested, and the High Commissioner has
                            accordingly informed the <persName corresp="#p_TAR2">Tunku</persName>
                            that the British Government agree in principle that any further act of
                            aggression by Indonesia upon the territory of Malaya or Singapore (i.e.
                            excluding confrontation operations in Borneo), should be met by a
                            counter attack against some appropriate objective on Indonesian
                            territory. He added that we consider it absolutely essential that,
                            before any such counter attack is made, the Malaysian Government should
                            take the matter to the Security Council and seek their moral support
                            against Indonesian aggression, and went on to say that, having once
                            raised the matter in the Security Council it would probably not be
                            necessary to do so again in the event of a fresh act of aggression, when
                            counter action could follow.</p>
                        <p>You will observe that although this message sets out in unequivocable
                            terms our willingness and determination to defend Malaya and Singapore
                            in the only practicable way open to us against further attacks of this
                            kind, we have insisted on a reference to the Security Council first. We
                            are not thinking about tactics for this debate and, as you know, our
                            officials are in close touch.”</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="strong">
                                    <persName corresp="p_RD3">Rusk</persName>
                                </hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>