<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by Mr. John C.
                            Ross, Deputy to the United States Representative at the
                        United Nations (
                        Austin
                    ) to the Assistant Secretary of State for United
                        Nations Affairs (
                        Rusk
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d154</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">154</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-04-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-04-25T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" subject="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-04-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-04-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="154" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d154">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>/4–2549</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">John C.
                            Ross</persName>, Deputy to the United States Representative at the
                        United Nations</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State for United
                        Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-25">April 25,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Enclosed is copy of self-explanatory memorandum<note n="2" xml:id="d154fn2">Not
                        printed.</note> setting forth a request by India for United States support
                    in the Security Council elections next fall. For the last two or three years I
                    have been personally very sympathetic to the idea of a place for India on the
                    Security Council, and I think there are a good many reasons why we should
                    support India next fall and undertake at an early date a commitment in this
                    regard with due reservation to protect our position against unforeseen
                    circumstances which might between now and next fall change our view.</p>
                <p>Among the reasons why I feel we should support India are the following: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>I think that India is in a position to make a very substantial
                            contribution to the “maintenance of international peace and security and
                            to the other purposes of the organization” as set forth in Article 23 of
                            the Charter. This ability to contribute derives not only from India’s
                            great population and actual and potential wealth, but also from her
                            geographic location and the fact that she is already clearly in a
                            position of leadership among a very substantial group or Asiatic
                            countries.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The election of India to the Council would further strengthen the
                            principle of equitable geographic distribution while, at the same time,
                            preserving the general idea of having a second British Commonwealth
                            Member on the Council. I heard very vaguely from Sam Atyeo<note n="3" xml:id="d154fn3">S. L. Atyeo, advisory member of the Australian
                                Delegation to the meeting in progress at this time at New York of
                                the second part of the third regular session of the General
                                Assembly.</note> that <pb facs="0251" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/>
                            Australia might be interested in election to the Council next fall to
                            succeed Canada. Australia, of course, has already been on the Council
                            and for other reasons I must say I do not sympathize very much with this
                            idea. Furthermore, it does not seem to me that any other Commonwealth
                            Member at the present time, with the possible exception of New Zealand,
                            is in a position to make as substantial a contribution as India.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>It is still a bit too early to estimate the probable effect on Chinese
                            Membership in the Council of what appears to be the virtually certain
                            Communist domination of China.<note n="4" xml:id="d154fn4">See <ref target="#pg_281">pp. 281</ref> ff.</note> It seems likely,
                            however, that China, as the sole Asiatic representative on the Council,
                            will not be a very strong support. As a counterpoise, not only in the
                            Security Council but generally, I should think that there is a great
                            deal to be said for having India on the Council in addition to
                            China.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>At one time we were hesitant about supporting India for the Security
                            Council because we were not sure just where India stood in relations
                            between the East and the West. It began to be clear at Paris<note n="5" xml:id="d154fn5">This refers to the meeting at Paris, September 21
                                to December 12, 1948, of the first part of the third regular session
                                of the General Assembly.</note> and I believe has become
                            increasingly clear that India’s sympathies lie with the West.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>We seem to be well on the way to solution of the Kashmir problem,<note n="6" xml:id="d154fn6">Documentation regarding the Kashmir question
                                is scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1949v06">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>
                                </ref>.</note> which solution should entail the virtual, if not
                            complete pacification of the sub-continent.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The foregoing are, of course, personal thoughts which I want you and others
                    concerned in the Department to have. I do think that it would be advantageous,
                    if possible, for us to reach a prompt decision on this particular case with due
                    regard, as indicated above, for any reservations we might consider it necessary
                    to make.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
