<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of the Thirty-eighth Meeting of the United States
                        Delegation, New York, December 7, 1949, 9:00 a. m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d16</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">16</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-12-07T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-12-07T09:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-07T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-07T09:00:00-05:00" n="16" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d16">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">IO Files: US/A/M(Chr)/132</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Thirty-eighth Meeting of the United States
                        Delegation, New York, December 7, 1949, 9:00 a. m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-07T09:00:00-05:00">December 7, 1949, 9:00 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows list of names of persons (41) present.]</p>
                <p>Ambassador Austin explained that the purpose of this meeting was to appraise and
                    evaluate the experience of the Delegation at this session <pb facs="0040" n="24" xml:id="pg_24"/> of the Assembly, as well as the achievements of the
                    Assembly itself. He thought the United States should avoid its present habit of
                    often taking the cue for its position from the Russians. He pointed out that
                    many of our decisions had been influenced by the position which the Soviets have
                    taken. The United States should assume an individual initiative in all cases.
                    Ambassador Austin referred to the great temptation to answer the critical
                    remarks made by Mr. Vyshinsky about the General Assembly upon his departure. He
                    hoped that the discussion of the Delegation could be a real “free-for-all” in
                    which all the members could express their impressions of our common experience
                    and thus contribute to the future improvement of the work of the Delegation.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Austin turned first to the liaison officers. He thought it was
                    important for the Delegation as a whole to understand the actions of other
                    delegations and particularly why the United States received their support and
                    whether other members had confidence in the sincerity of our leadership. Mr.
                    Raynor referred to a dinner held the preceding day with representatives of
                    certain European states. These representatives believed the United States was
                    making a sincere attempt to measure up to its responsibilities of leadership and
                    on balance was adequately meeting its responsibilities. These states
                    particularly appreciated our consultations with them, which had made a
                    tremendous impression. They would like to see the consultations extended in the
                    future and kept up during the course of the year. In response to a question from
                    Ambassador Austin as to whether any particular techniques of consultation had
                    been developed, Mr. Raynor explained that the main change had occurred during
                    the negotiations on the “Essentials of Peace” resolution at which time we had
                    actually taken account of the suggestions put forward by other members. One of
                    the weakest spots in his area of responsibility was the trusteeship work.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hickerson noted that as a result of the improved techniques of consultation,
                    all these states wanted more consultation, including a greater degree of
                    preliminary consultation before the Assembly in their capitals, as well as
                    consultation in New York for which they were most appreciative. Mr. Raynor
                    indicated that the only problem cases in his area were really minor ones,
                    although he noted that the French desired to deal directly with the United
                    States and not through the British. The Australians were also temperamental.
                    However, relations with both delegations had improved at this session.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dreier considered that there were many problems involving the Latin American
                    states. One interesting one was illustrated by the experience in the First
                    Committee the preceding day, when three Latin American states completely
                    surprised the United States by introducing a resolution referring the Chinese
                    case to the Interim Committee <pb facs="0041" n="25" xml:id="pg_25"/> without
                    any advance consultation, and then engaged in some first class Latin oratory
                    which defeated the United States position. By and large, he believed, however,
                    that the Latin American states had demonstrated their support for the United
                    States in the general East-West conflict. The reasons for Latin American
                    enthusiasm in our behalf differed. Some Latin American states were
                    pro-democratic, while others were motivated more by the fear of ideas of social
                    and economic change. One element which made these states difficult to deal with
                    was their extreme caution in many instances. Moreover, some had a purely
                    sentimental hope that through some formula or procedure a way would be found to
                    work out all the problems before the United Nations. This was true, for example,
                    of Mr. Stolk of Venezuela who, despite his experiences in attempting to reach an
                    agreement with the Soviets on the Interim Committee, still maintained the dream
                    of some magic formula which would bring the East and West together.</p>
                <p>Turning to the consultation process in general, Mr. Dreier felt that the United
                    States had kept the Latin American countries well informed of our position. This
                    had been appreciated. However, the Latin American states had not come to the
                    United States to find out its point of view as much as he had thought they
                    would. The consistent practice of consultation on our part made more regrettable
                    the Latin American move on China, on which there had been no consultation,
                    although the Latin American states realized that this was a matter of great
                    importance to the United States. He accounted for this move both on the
                    emotional ground which went back to the ardor engendered in the debate on the
                    resolution on the “Essentials of Peace”, and their desire to keep alive the
                    debate on subversive activities of the Soviets. In the Chinese case, there had
                    also been the feeling that United States policy did not provide sufficient
                    emotional appeal, and that it was essentially weak.…</p>
                <p>Mr. Dreier thought one possible reason for their conduct on China was the fact
                    that when the Latin American states did consult with us, they very often had
                    ideas which we did not like, so that we were constantly throwing cold water on
                    their proposals. He wondered if it would not be better in the future to select a
                    few Latin American ideas, … and seek their modification in such a way that the
                    United States could support them.</p>
                <p>There was another problem involving the Latin American delegations which should
                    not be lost sight of. This was the relative freedom of action of many of the
                    Latin American delegates. For example, Alexis (Haiti) had submitted a plan for
                    the control of atomic energy without the head of his Delegation knowing he was
                    going to make such a proposal. Mr. Dreier did not know how this matter could be
                        <pb facs="0042" n="26" xml:id="pg_26"/> effectively handled. Ambassador
                    Austin … asked whether there was any feeling of inferiority among the small
                    states as compared with the great powers. Mr. Dreier did not think this feeling
                    had been particularly evident in this Assembly, although there was of course a
                    latent sentiment among many Latin American countries. This had come out in the
                    Chinese case. Referring back to the developments of the preceding day, Mr.
                    Dreier thought it would be well for the United States to make known to the Latin
                    American countries involved that our policy was one of consultation and to
                    remind them that such consultation on their part was also desirable. Mr.
                    Hickerson felt that there was a single explanation for the fact that the Latin
                    Americans had not consulted us. They regarded the United States delegation as
                    “no-men”. We usually knocked down their ideas as bad. This time there was
                    nothing basically wrong in their position, and Tsiang’s oratory had simply
                    touched off their emotions, which had then run away with them. Ambassador Jessup
                    noted that the Chinese had also put on an excellent social campaign of luncheons
                    and dinners.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hickerson believed that the Delegation should watch more carefully for the
                    irresponsible elements in other delegations. He believed we should try to get a
                    better estimate from our missions abroad, thus giving us the complete “lowdown”
                    on other delegates.… We should watch carefully the attitudes expressed by the
                    various delegates as the Assembly proceeded to make sure that they were really
                    speaking for their countries and not “freewheeling”. Mr. Clark considered that
                    the Latin American intervention in the Chinese case simply illustrated the
                    effects of good campaigning, which had been started early, to line up the Latin
                    American states in favor of China.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cabot said that certain of the senior political liaison officers felt that
                    there could be more integration of the liaison work with other Delegation
                    operations. He agreed we had secured the confidence of other delegates by
                    increased consultations. With the other liaison officers he was preparing a
                    memorandum making certain constructive suggestions for the greater integration
                    of the liaison work. Ambassador Austin suggested that it would be helpful in
                    studying the future procedures of the Delegation if Mr. Cabot could consult with
                    members of the permanent Mission on this matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. Howard referred to the fact that there were different liaison problems in
                    different areas. He thought all the political officers could helpfully
                    contribute to an over-all study of the liaison work of the Delegation. He
                    personally felt that the liaison work of this session had improved over that of
                    the past. There was rather less lobbying, for one thing. In his view, the most
                    important element of liaison work was to establish a relationship of mutual
                    confidence. This year that <pb facs="0043" n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/> relationship
                    was better than ever before with the exception of certain questions, such as
                    Palestine, on which the Arab states, for example, could never be influenced by
                    the United States. In answer to a question from Ambassador Austin, he agreed
                    that in many cases the position of other states was a response based upon their
                    fear of the Russians. This had been the case when Turkey had not spoken in the
                    debate on the “Essentials of Peace” resolution because it feared this would mean
                    it would be singled out for subsequent attack by the Soviets. A number of states
                    preferred not to speak unless they were actually attacked.</p>
                <p>[Here follows description by the delegates of their impressions of the
                    accomplishments of the fourth session of the General Assembly.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
