<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. John
                            Boss, Deputy to the United States Representative at the
                        United Nations (
                        Austin
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d165</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">165</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-09-22T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-09-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="165" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d165">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">IO Files: US/A/1725</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. <persName type="from">John
                            Boss</persName>, Deputy to the United States Representative at the
                        United Nations</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-09-22">September 22,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Trygve Lie<note n="1" xml:id="d165fn1">Secretary-General of the United
                        Nations.</note> called me into his office following conclusion of the
                    morning plenary and said Bebler<note n="2" xml:id="d165fn2">Aleš Bebler,
                        Yugoslav Deputy Minister for Foreign Affairs and Member of the Yugoslav
                        Delegation to the General Assembly.</note> and his associates had come to
                    see him and urged very strongly that he support Yugoslavia’s candidacy for the
                    Security Council. Lie said that he had not given the Yugoslavs an answer one way
                    or the other. He had asked them, however, as earnest of their good intentions
                    whether the Yugoslav Government could not take an active and immediate part in
                    liquidating once and for all their part in the Greek Case. He added to me that
                    this was a very complex matter of world politics which he did not feel competent
                    to express any view on until he had learned our view. I told him this matter was
                    as much of a surprise to us as anyone else. I explained what our position had
                    been and indicated for the moment we had no position one way or the other but
                    were actively considering the question.<note n="3" xml:id="d165fn3">The U.S.
                        Delegation had discussed the Yugoslav matter at its meetings on September 21
                        and 22 (IO Files, documents US/A/M(Chr)/98 and US/A/M(Chr)/99). The
                        Department’s instruction, telegram <gloss target="#t_GaDel1">Gadel</gloss>
                        4, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, was the subject of discussion at the
                        September 22 meeting, one opinion being that the instruction was a fairly
                        strong endorsement of the Yugoslav candidacy and that the U.S. Delegation
                        “should say we were supporting Yugoslavia.”</note> I told him we would try
                    to inform him as promptly as possible as soon as we reached a decision. I
                    emphasized to him very strongly that the United States had no part whatsoever in
                    this initiative by the Yugoslav Government.</p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
