<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-04-15T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="199" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d199">
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>On March 4, 1949 the Security Council, acting on a resolution offered
                                by the United States Representative at the United Nations (Austin)
                                recommended to the General Assembly that Israel be admitted to
                                membership in the United Nations (United Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Records of the Security Council, Fourth Year, No.
                                    17</hi>, pages 8 and 9; hereafter cited as <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">4th yr., No.
                                    17</hi> [or other appropriate number]. The General Assembly, on
                                May 11, 1949, adopted a resolution providing for the admittance of
                                Israel to the United Nations, drafted in its <hi rend="italic">Ad
                                    Hoc</hi> Political Committee and cosponsored by Australia,
                                Canada, Guatemala, Haiti, Panama, the United States, and Uruguay
                                (United Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Records of the General
                                    Assembly, Third Session, Part II, Plenary Meetings</hi>, pages
                                306 ff.). Documentation on these matters as they relate to United
                                States policy is found in the files of the Department of State,
                                501.AA.</p>
                            <p>On April 8, 1949, the Security Council failed to act favorably on a
                                report from its Committee on the Admission of New Members
                                recommending approval of the application for membership submitted by
                                the Republic of Korea, due to the negative vote of a permanent
                                member, the Soviet Union (9–2) (<gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>,
                                    <hi rend="italic">4th yr., No. 26</hi>, page 15). At the same
                                meeting an application for membership submitted by Nepal was
                                referred by the Security Council to its Admissions Committee for
                                consideration, as a matter of normal procedure (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, page 16).</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>