<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador Argentina (
                        Bruce
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d321</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">321</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-06-07T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-06-07T16:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-06-07T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-07T16:00:00-05:00" n="321" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d321">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.503135/6–749: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bruce</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-06-07T18:00:00-03:00">June 7, 1949—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>509. US meat packing companies last night received checks covering losses since
                    January 1 through April. No provision made for profits but decree which is to be
                    published soon, recognizes right to profit. Packers unable as yet say whether
                    settlements entirely satisfactory. However, they are pleased with developments
                    and hope for completely satisfactory solution. Decree provides for monthly
                    payments of losses until situation stabilized. Government wishes keep this <pb facs="0522" n="506" xml:id="pg_506"/> confidential for few days probably
                    pending signature British agreement.<note n="1" xml:id="d321fn1">See footnote 1
                        to the letter from Secretary of Commerce Sawyer, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> Will report more fully.<note n="2" xml:id="d321fn2">
                        <p>Despatch No. 604, September 6, from Buenos Aires gave the following
                            further report on the situation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“… In recent weeks … there has developed new cause for alarm
                                    relative [to] the long-term situation of foreign-owned <hi rend="italic">frigorificos</hi> in Argentina. Although the
                                    government has been paying regularly the monthly deficits, it
                                    has made no effort so far to audit the books or to reach mutual
                                    agreement on the question of reasonable profit. Obviously the
                                    receipt by <hi rend="italic">frigorificos</hi> of payments on
                                    this basis over an extended period of time may expose them
                                    ultimately to disastrous liabilities.…</p>
                                <p>“… The managers of foreign-owned <hi rend="italic">frigorificos</hi> are beginning to fear that in spite of
                                    professed favorable policy and superficially satisfactory
                                    explanations, the actual procedures of the government in paying
                                    deficits, in distributing United Kingdom export quotas, and in
                                    controlling direct export sales, may result ultimately in their
                                    withering on the vine’; that is, causing the gradual liquidation
                                    of their operations through decapitalization and loss of export
                                    position rather than through outright expropriation or
                                    nationalization such as one time was feared.</p>
                                <p>“It is possible, of course, that recent discriminatory action may
                                    be attributed to laxity of administration and preemption of
                                    policy by subordinate officials, rather than to the long-range
                                    intent of the Argentine government. In an effort to clarify the
                                    situation, the chargé d’Affaires is planning to draw the
                                    attention of Minister of Economy Ares as soon as possible to the
                                    present alarm of the packers, and to request that he discuss
                                    directly with them these problems which recently have arisen.”
                                    (835.6582/9–649)</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bruce</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
