<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="407" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d407">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">812.6363/5–2349</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi>
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Webb</hi>)</head>
                            <dateline>[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,]
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-23">May 23,
                                1949</date>.</dateline>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Meeting With President, Monday, May</hi> 23,
                                1949</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">export-import bank loan to <gloss target="#t_Pemex1">pemex</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The President is very anxious that we do something to help with the
                                problem of oil development and production in Mexico. He mentioned
                                    <pb facs="0691" n="675" xml:id="pg_675"/> a figure of 160,000
                                barrels per day as a desirable level to encourage. He feels that
                                unless something is done expeditiously the peso will lose its value
                                and undermine the government, leading to conditions which would be
                                highly undesirable from the standpoint of the United States. He
                                understands the reasons why we cannot accept Mr. Crosser’s view and
                                agrees that we cannot make a loan on an unconditional basis.</p>
                            <p>The President is anxious that we proceed as expeditiously as possible
                                to develop a solution to this problem along the lines we are working
                                and indicated that arrangements under which certain facilities
                                connected with transportation and refining should be financed would
                                probably be satisfactory.</p>
                            <p>The President expressed himself as feeling that the fastest way to
                                get development was to have private companies provide the technical
                                know-how and create the conditions under which they could go in and
                                accomplish the necessary development.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>