<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-09-23T22:39:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-09-23T22:39:00-05:00" n="43" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB/9–2349: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    in New York to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-09-23T23:39:00-04:00">September 23, 1949—11:39 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_DelGA1">Delga</gloss> 19. For [<hi rend="italic">From</hi>] Hickerson. Following preliminary views on possible
                                alternative courses of action for handling new Soviet resolution
                                (Delga 16<note n="1" xml:id="d43fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Supra.</hi>
                                </note>), which were developed in meeting of members of GADel staff
                                tonight, may be of interest to Department.</p>
                            <p>First possibility would be to have <gloss target="#t_GC1">GC</gloss>
                                recommend separate reference for each paragraph of Soviet draft
                                resolution. First paragraph would be referred directly to plenary,
                                where it would be voted down. Second paragraph would go to <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Political Committee for consideration
                                in conjunction with atomic energy item. Third paragraph would go to
                                Committee 1, under new title such as “adoption of additional
                                measures to strengthen the peace,” so as not to perpetuate title of
                                Soviet draft resolution. In first committee this paragraph would be
                                amended so as to recommend measures to strengthen peace such as
                                application of last year’s <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> veto
                                resolution and a recommendation along lines of suggestion in
                                Secretary’s <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> speech that members
                                agree to accept <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> recommendations as
                                binding in certain cases.</p>
                            <p>Advantage of this method of procedure would be that it would
                                fragmentize Soviet resolution and prevent any possibility of Soviets
                                claiming credit for single resolution embodying generalities on
                                subject of peace which Soviets could claim as their own, as in case
                                of 1947 warmongering resolution.</p>
                            <p>Second possible course of action would be to have general committee
                                recommend reference of Soviet resolution to Committee, with an
                                understanding or recommendation if necessary that paragraph 2 be
                                discussed in connection with atomic energy in <hi rend="italic">Ad
                                    Hoc</hi> Political Committee. In first committee we would
                                substitute an acceptable resolution for paragraphs 1 and 3 of Soviet
                                draft which might include material similar to 1948 <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Mexican resolution (190(III))<note n="2" xml:id="d43fn2">For text, see United Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Records of the General Assembly,
                                        Third Session, Part I, Resolutions</hi>, p. 15 (Hereafter
                                    cited as <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (III/1), <hi rend="italic">Resolutions.</hi>)</note> and matter covered
                                in suggested amendment to paragraph 3 of Soviet resolution in
                                preceding paragraph. This would be done by amendment which would be
                                voted upon before Soviet text. Advantage of this course would be
                                that <pb facs="0106" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/> it would avoid giving
                                Soviets opportunity for propaganda effort in several different
                                    <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> forums.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>