<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chargé in Peru (
                        Pierrot
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d469</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">469</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-05-03T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-03T13:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" subject="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="diplomatic-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recFzikmNCJDCCGBL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" subject="trade-unions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073951" lcsh-match="exact">Trade union</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-03T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-03T13:00:00-05:00" n="469" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d469">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.RA/5–349: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Peru</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pierrot</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lima</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-03T13:00:00-05:00">May 3, 1949—1 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>255. <gloss target="#t_refDeptel1">ReDeptel</gloss> 139, May 2.<note n="1" xml:id="d469fn1">Not printed. This telegram was also sent to Montevideo, as
                        telegram 108, and its contents are summarized in footnote 5 to the
                        memorandum by Mr. Rusk, dated June 2, <ref target="#pg_800">p.
                        800</ref>.</note> Foreign Minister Díaz Dulanto summoned me this morning to
                    state that he is informed by Alvardo in Montevideo<note n="2" xml:id="d469fn2">The Fourth Conference of American States Members of the International Labor
                        Organization met at Montevideo from April 25 to May 8, 1949.</note> that
                    great pressure being brought on him including by American Embassy to induce Peru
                    invite commission investigate Peruvian labor conditions similar invitation
                    extended by Venezuela. Foreign Minister wished me convey to Department
                    following: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>That personalities prominent in present <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> conference at Montevideo are unsympathetic to present
                            Peruvian Government and using <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss>
                            conference as vehicle for embarrassing this government.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>That apparent undue influence of members Uruguayan Government in
                                <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> conference partly responsible
                            for present active efforts embarrass Peru since diplomatic relations do
                            not exist between the two countries. Foreign Minister added that
                            Montevideo was poor choice for seat of <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> conference for this reason so far as Peru is
                            concerned.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>That Peruvian Government will not invite investigation and if
                            delegation named by conference to conduct such investigation it would
                            not be admitted to Peru.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>I expressed to Foreign Minister our practice and belief in trade union freedom
                    and abhorrence of deprival freedom of association inherent in <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> Constitution and UN Charter as expressed <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 139. However, since he insisted no
                    prisoners held on charges labor union activities and that union leaders
                    imprisoned are included among large number others who with them are charged with
                    and being tried for <pb facs="0783" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/> complicity in
                    October 3rd revolt<note n="3" xml:id="d469fn3">Reference is to an unsuccessful
                        revolutionary attempt at Callao on October 3, 1948 by naval and civilian
                        elements.</note> I spoke to him along lines of last paragraph <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 139.<note n="4" xml:id="d469fn4">This
                        portion of telegram 139 indicated that it should not be the United States
                        position at Montevideo that the <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> had
                        authority to intervene in domestic affairs, nor that labor leaders were
                        entitled to rights beyond those enjoyed by other citizens
                        (501.RA/4–3049).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Foreign Minister pointed out that arrests for October 3rd revolt including some
                    labor leaders were made by Constitutional Bustamante Government and not by Odría
                        administration.<note n="5" xml:id="d469fn5">Late in October 1948, the
                        government of President José Luís Bustamante y Rivero had been overthrown by
                        an armed forces revolt led by General Manuel Odría, who became President of
                        the Military Junta of Government in Peru. For documentation on U.S.
                        recognition of the Odría regime, see <ref target="frus1948v09#pg_111">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, pp. 111</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In response to specific inquiry as to grounds on which Peruvian Government would
                    refuse to permit <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> investigation of labor
                    conditions in Peru, Foreign Minister replied that Peruvian Government would
                    consider such actions as intervention in Peru’s internal affairs.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister pointed out that Junta’s labor policy is supported by majority
                    of labor in Peru and opposed mainly by professional <gloss target="#t_APRA1">APRA</gloss> organizers and agitators; that country’s interests has
                    suffered from work stoppages resulting from strikes under previous government;
                    that Junta’s legislation has provided means for considering labor demands
                    without resort to strikes and that under present government this system has
                    worked satisfactorily without economic disruption and that in practically all
                    cases government commission investigating labor demands has granted wage
                    increases satisfactory to labor. Minister added that any <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> sponsored investigating group would be prejudiced against Odría
                    administration and that any information on labor conditions here needed by
                        <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> might be obtained from foreign
                    embassies, particularly American, which have ample means for procuring complete
                    and impartial information.</p>
                <p>Sent Department, repeated Montevideo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierrot</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
