<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by Mr. R. Kenneth
                            Oakley of the Division of River Plate Affairs to the Director
                        of the Office of American Republic Affairs (
                        Daniels
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d478</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">478</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-02-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-02-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="diplomatic-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="economic-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="food" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Foodstuffs</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="wheat" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366" lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="478" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d478">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">733.35/2–1649</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">R. Kenneth
                            Oakley</persName> of the Division of River Plate Affairs to the Director
                        of the Office of American Republic Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-16">February 16,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Ambassador Briggs inquired on August 5 concerning possible US assurances to
                    Uruguay in case of an overt action by Argentina. We replied on September 30,
                    1948 that it appeared logical that United States armed assistance would result
                    from an armed attack on Uruguay, although the Rio Treaty of 1947<note n="2" xml:id="d478fn2">
                        <p>For the text of the Inter-American Treaty of Reciprocal Assistance, see
                            Department of State Treaties and other International Acts Series (<gloss target="#t_TIAS1">TIAS</gloss>) No. 1838, or 62 Stat. (pt. 2)
                            1681.</p>
                        <p>The United States had also given Uruguay certain guarantees of support in
                            1944. Department of State telegram 412 to Montevideo, July 12, 1944, not
                            printed, instructed the Ambassador to “… inform the President [Juan Jose
                            Amezaga] and the Foreign Minister [José Serrato] in strict confidence
                            that in the event of attack we are prepared to extend the necessary
                            military and naval assistance. You may, in your discretion, also state
                            that we have consulted the Brazilian Government and have been assured of
                            its cooperation. We are likewise prepared to extend all necessary
                            economic assistance in the event of Argentine reprisals and you may so
                            inform the President and Foreign Minister.” (733.35/7–1144) In telegram
                            676, July 15, 1944, not printed, Ambassador Dawson reported that he had
                            delivered these assurances on July 13 and 14, 1944, but had omitted any
                            mention of Brazil (733.35/7–1544).</p>
                        <p>This question had been raised by Uruguayan officials at a time when the
                            United States was urging the other American Republics to recall for
                            consultation their respective Chiefs of Mission in Buenos Aires. The
                            Department’s instruction was sent after consultation with President
                            Roosevelt and the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</p>
                        <p>Further information on these previous assurances to Uruguay is in files
                            733.35, 734.35 and 835.01 for 1944. For documentation relating to U.S.
                            efforts to enlist the American Republics in a common policy towards
                            Argentina, see <ref target="frus1944v07#pg_288">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, pp. 288</ref>–<ref target="frus1944v07#pg_377">377</ref>.</p>
                    </note> is not binding as to armed assistance.</p>
                <p>In reply to a similar inquiry by Uruguayan Ambassador Domínguez Cámpora on
                    February 10, 1949, Mr. Daniels replied as follows.<note n="3" xml:id="d478fn3">
                        <p>In his memorandum of this conversation dated February 10, 1949 (not
                            printed), Mr. Daniels stated: “The Ambassador had reminded me that the
                            United States, on at least one other occasion, had given a specific
                            commitment, even before the Rio Treaty.” (811.003 Barkley, A.
                            W./2–1049)</p>
                        <p>For further information on the Argentine attitude toward Uruguay, see
                            despatch No. 167 from Buenos Aires, March 8, 1949, <ref target="#pg_483">p. 483</ref>, in the compilation on Argentina.</p>
                    </note> If <pb facs="0797" n="781" xml:id="pg_781"/> Uruguay should be the
                    victim of an armed attack, and if the United States were completely and
                    unquestionably satisfied that such attack came within the provisions of the Rio
                    Treaty, he supposed (“supongo”) that the United States would immediately render
                    armed assistance, without waiting for a meeting of the Organ of Consultation. He
                    added that he would even consider it “probable” that the United States would so
                    act, since he agreed that such action would be within the spirit of the Rio
                    Treaty. However, Mr. Daniels prefaced these statements by pointing out that it
                    might be unnecessary to act unilaterally and even more desirable to take
                    collective action; that he did not wish to make any statement which might be
                    misinterpreted as a threat to a third country; and that he could not commit his
                    government because circumstances at the moment of any attack are difficult to
                    evaluate now and that officials of the United States Government at any such time
                    might have a different point of view.</p>
                <p>On armed assistance, that is about as far as we can go. We cannot bind ourselves
                    to action under unforeseeable and perhaps impossible conditions although we
                    fully intend to live up to the spirit as well as the letter of our commitment
                    “to assist in meeting the attack in the exercise of the inherent right of
                    individual or collective self-defense”. (Article 3 (1))</p>
                <p>Expanding somewhat on Mr. Daniel’s statement that collective action might be more
                    desirable than individual though immediate armed assistance, reference is made
                    particularly to Article 7 of the Rio Treaty. An examination of a report of the
                    American Delegation indicates that this Article was inserted because of the
                    desire of the majority that, in case of a conflict between two or more American
                    states, every effort should be made to avoid having other states take sides and
                    spread the conflict.<note n="4" xml:id="d478fn4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Inter-American Conference for the Maintenance of
                            Continental Peace and Security, Quitandinha, Brazil, August 15–September
                            2, 1947: Report of the Delegation of the United States of America</hi>,
                        Department of State publication 3016 (Washington, Government Printing
                        Office, 1948).</note> The right to immediate action “to assist in meeting
                    the attack” remained unimpaired nevertheless.</p>
                <p>A Uruguayan policy statement, now in draft, but, for all effective purposes,
                    approved (an identical statement re Paraguay already has been approved), states
                    that “the US recognizes that Uruguay naturally lies within the economic orbit of
                    Argentina, and that the two nations have largely identic interests.<note n="5" xml:id="d478fn5">In the Policy Statement for Uruguay adopted November 17,
                        1950, this sentence read: “We recognize Argentine influence in Uruguay as
                        natural and understand the large identity of interests between the two
                        nations.” (611.33/11–1750)</note> Therefore, we do not oppose any natural
                    movement toward greater collaboration between the two countries, either
                    economic, cultural or political. On the other hand, the US would oppose any
                    Argentine action of an aggressive nature.”</p>
                <pb facs="0798" n="782" xml:id="pg_782"/>
                <p>This statement includes [options?] other than armed assistance, to confront
                    aggression, armed or otherwise. In the case of an aggression which is not an
                    armed attack, the Rio Treaty calls only for a meeting of the Organ of
                    Consultation to decide on measures to assist the victim of aggression or
                    measures for the common defense and the maintenance of the peace and security of
                    the Continent.</p>
                <p>Uruguay obviously is not so much concerned with the possibility of armed
                    aggression by an American State as it is with the less remote prospect of
                    political-economic pressure and penetration by one of its more powerful
                    neighbors. Article 6 of the Rio Treaty merely implies (albeit strongly) support
                    for the victim in such cases, and only when the measures are determined to
                    constitute aggression. Furthermore, Article 6 can be effective only if there is
                    agreement on the difficult question of the nature of aggression and on the
                    equally difficult question of whether the actions constitute aggressive acts. It
                    is recognized that, in any case, considerable time might elapse before
                    Inter-American measures might be adopted and put into force for the support of
                    an American nation confronted with aggression not in the nature of an armed
                    attack, particularly should such aggression derive from another American
                    state.</p>
                <p>Although, as mentioned above, Article 6 carries only an implication of support in
                    cases of this nature, the United States considers itself bound to render such
                    support. Although it would not resort to the measures of support against
                    aggression envisaged in Article 8 of the Rio Treaty (recall of chiefs of
                    diplomatic missions; breaking of diplomatic relations; …; partial or complete
                    interruption of economic relations; …;<note n="6" xml:id="d478fn6">Omissions
                        indicated in the source text.</note> and use of armed force) without prior
                    consultation with the other American States, the United States undoubtedly would
                    act unilaterally to support an American State by interim measures such as
                    supplying basic foodstuffs on a temporary basis (for example, the specific
                    problem of wheat mentioned in Amb. Brigg’s despatch<note n="7" xml:id="d478fn7">Despatch No. 745 from Montevideo, November 8, 1948, not printed, included a
                        comprehensive review of Uruguayan economic and other relations with
                        Argentina (733.35/11–48).</note>), provided of course that this Government
                    were convinced that aggression actually were involved. However, again we could
                    not irrevocably bind ourselves for an unforeseeable and perhaps impossible
                    situation.</p>
                <p>In any instance of a claimed aggression, we must needs be absolutely, certain
                    that aggression did exist. In this regard, it must be remembered that public
                    opinion, to say nothing of the press, is too easily excited into hasty judgment
                    of certain actions as aggression. Furthermore, too precipitate action by the
                    United States to support an <pb facs="0799" n="783" xml:id="pg_783"/> American
                    State against actions which might be based only on misunderstanding, might well
                    compound rather than relieve a difficult situation.</p>
                <p>Another problem is that, should US assurances to some State become known to some
                    of its neighbors, the latter might consider themselves offended on the grounds
                    that the assurances imply the existence of a threat where none actually exists.
                    Since this situation invariably is present at some point or other in the
                    Americas, we must limit ourselves to multilateral assurances, although our
                    position is identical with regard to every one of the 20 other American
                    republics, and is entirely nondiscriminatory.</p>
                <p>Recent events in United States-Argentine relations are recognized to have
                    provoked a certain fear among neighbors of Argentina that the United States is
                    cultivating its relations with the latter nation at the possible sacrifice of
                    its good relations with other American nations, especially Uruguay and Brazil,
                    which proved themselves in the recent war to be good friends and allies of the
                    combatant United Nations. The United States indeed is endeavoring to cement
                    better relationship with Argentina. Under no circumstances, however, does it
                    propose to sacrifice its already proven relationship with Uruguay, Brazil and
                    other American nations which exhibited their support for the United Nations war
                    effort before Argentina did. We firmly believe that it is of great and direct
                    interest to Uruguay and other nations that United States-Argentine relations be
                    improved in every possible way, within the concept mentioned above, and that
                    Uruguay and these other nations should not only view with favor but should
                    encourage such a development in their own self-interest and for their own
                    protection over the long period.<note n="8" xml:id="d478fn8">A brief note from
                        Mr. Daniels to Mr. Oakley, dated February 18, 1949, and attached to the file
                        copy of this memorandum, says in part: “Excellent analysis. I agree
                        throughout.”</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
