<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>President Truman to the
                        Former President of Venezuela (
                        Gallegos
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d489</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">489</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="489" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d489">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">831.001 Gallegos, Rómulo/2–749</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">President <persName type="from">Truman</persName> to the
                        Former President of Venezuela</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gallegos</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-03">February 3,
                        1949</date>.</dateline>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Friend</hi>: I have been sincerely moved by your
                    letter of December fifteenth.<note n="1" xml:id="d489fn1">Not printed, but see
                        the summary contained in telegram 810, December 18, 1948, from Habana, in
                            <ref target="frus1948v09#pg_149">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, p. 149</ref>.</note> The overthrow of the
                    Government over which you presided came as a great shock to me, and I have
                    personally concerned myself with this question from the beginning.</p>
                <p>I am happy you have accepted the sincere statements issued by our Department of
                        State<note n="2" xml:id="d489fn2">For the Department’s statement of December
                        10 with regard to this issue, see telegram 511, <ref target="frus1948v09#pg_143">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 143</ref>.</note> regarding the
                    non-participation in the <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> of American
                    interests or of officials of this Government, and I wish to reiterate these
                    assurances to you personally at this time. It was considerate of you to make
                    public your acceptance of these explanation.</p>
                <pb facs="0814" n="798" xml:id="pg_798"/>
                <p>I believe that the use of force to effect political change is not only deplorable
                    but also inconsistent with the ideals of the American peoples. The Government of
                    the United States intends to do everything possible, consistent with its
                    international obligations to strengthen democratic forces in this
                    hemisphere.</p>
                <p>This concern has been brought to the attention of the Governments of the other
                    American Republics and their advice solicited in determining what steps can
                    properly be taken to encourage democratic and constitutional procedures in the
                    Americas. A number of constructive replies have been received. In order that the
                    position of this Government should be made clear to people both in this country
                    and in the other American nations, as already had been done with their
                    Governments, a statement on this subject was made public on December 21,
                        1948.<note n="3" xml:id="d489fn3">Text in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, January 2, 1949, p. 30.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In your letter you suggested that the recognition of the present <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> Government of Venezuela by the United States
                    would undo the work of the Good Neighbor Policy and would constitute
                    acquiescence in the violation of right by force.</p>
                <p>The possibility of withholding recognition was very carefully considered from all
                    points of view, and it was my opinion and that of my advisers that it was not
                    the course best adapted to achieve the ends which you and I both heartily
                    desire. Since the administration of President Jefferson it had been the general
                    policy of this Government, with certain exceptions, to maintain diplomatic
                    relations with whatever Government held control of the administrative machinery
                    of any state, provided it was both able and willing to carry out its
                    international obligations and gave reasonable evidence of stability. It has not
                    been and is not now the intention of this Government to pass judgment upon the
                    internal arrangements of other Governments. We do not intend that resumption of
                    relations with any particular American Republic should be taken as such a
                    judgment. This principle met with wide acceptance among the other Republics of
                    the hemisphere and was incorporated in a resolution unanimously adopted by all
                    the American States at the Ninth Inter-American Conference at Bogotá in
                        1948.<note n="4" xml:id="d489fn4">Reference is to Resolution XXXV of that
                        Conference; text in <ref target="frus1948v09#pg_98">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, p. 98</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>This Government, furthermore, is of the opinion that nonrecognition is seldom, if
                    ever, effective in bringing about the broader aim of strengthening democratic
                    governments. I feel that the United States can make its influence in favor of
                    democratic procedures felt more effectively if diplomatic relations can be
                    maintained with all the governments of the hemisphere. The American Republics
                    probably can <pb facs="0815" n="799" xml:id="pg_799"/> work together most
                    effectively for hemisphere solidarity if they utilize, among other means, the
                    continuing interchange made possible through normal diplomatic channels.</p>
                <p>I have mentioned only a few of the reasons which led to the conclusion that it
                    would be best for the United States to resume diplomatic relations with
                    Venezuela. Instructions were issued to our Ambassador in Caracas to take the
                    necessary steps on January 21.<note n="5" xml:id="d489fn5">See telegram 12,
                        January 13, 1949, to Caracas, <ref target="frus1948v09#pg_151">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, p. 151</ref>.</note> We did not intend by
                    this step to imply approval of the means by which that Government came into
                    existence. I wish to assure you that we will continue searching for ways and
                    means by which we can contribute to the strengthening of democratic institutions
                    which, I firmly believe, embody the aspirations of the peoples of Latin America
                    just as surely as they do those of the people of the United States.</p>
                <p>I realize, of course, that our action in extending recognition to the Junta of
                    Government in Venezuela may have come as a disappointment to you, and I am sorry
                    that this is so. I want to assure you, however, of my continuing friendship and
                    admiration for you and of my desire to act always in the best interests of the
                    Western Hemisphere.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harry</hi> S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
