<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Representative at the United Nations
                        (
                        Austin
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d49</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">49</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-10-04T16:23:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-10-04T16:23:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="alliances" subject="alliance" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="sovereignty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-10-04T16:23:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-10-04T16:23:00-05:00" n="49" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB/10–449: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-10-04T16:23:00-05:00">October 4, 1949—4:23 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DelGA1">Delga</gloss> 54. I have received following views from
                    delegation staff re your Gadel 24 and 25 of October 1 dealing with Soviet
                    resolution.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Staff is inclined in the light of the present tactical situation to agree
                        that our objective should be to defeat the Soviet resolution and to prevent
                        its amendment by presenting, or having presented to the Assembly, a
                        substitute resolution which could be adopted by an overwhelming <pb facs="0111" n="95" xml:id="pg_95"/> vote but which would contain
                        statements or principles so directly opposed to Soviet methods that Russians
                        could not exploit it and presumably would have to vote against it.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>As staff analyzes situation, in Assembly, we will be confronted with group
                        of members desirous of passing vague, high-sounding resolution which can be
                        accepted unanimously as in case of Mexican resolution last year. In this
                        atmosphere Vyshinsky might be expected to put forward superficially
                        attractive idea of mutual nonaggression pact among Big 5 powers foreshadowed
                        by <hi rend="italic">Daily Worker</hi> articles. He might propose that such
                        a pact include a series of simple points such as: agreement not to join
                        alliance directed against other signatories; agreement not to interfere with
                        sovereignty of other powers through use of bases, troops on foreign soil,
                        etc.; agreement not to use atomic bomb against other signatories; agreement
                        to foster trade among signatories.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Should such a proposal be presented, it seems doubtful that resolution
                        suggested by Department <gloss target="#t_GaDel1">Gadel</gloss> 25 will be
                        sufficiently broadly-based or striking to serve as an adequate substitute.
                        Staff would suggest that substitute resolution might appropriately stress
                        steps directly related to attainment of peaceful relations among nations,
                        and not be limited to reformulation of positions we have pushed through
                            <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> on a series of individual
                        problems.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Proposed staff resolution which is now being drafted, will probably
                        include reference to need for observance of charter principles, proposals of
                        the type mentioned in Ambassador Jessup’s memo to Ambassador Austin on
                        procedures for the maintenance of peace,<note n="1" xml:id="d49fn1">The
                            reference is presumably to Jessup’s memorandum of September 30, <ref target="#pg_90">p. 90</ref>.</note> and generalized standards of
                        conduct which could be worked out so as to reflect by inference on Soviet
                        conduct in various areas such as Yugoslavia. One of the points to be
                        included might be a suggestion that peace can best be achieved if all powers
                        will carry out <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> recommendations such as
                        those mentioned in <gloss target="#t_GaDel1">Gadel</gloss> 25.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Reaction to first consultations undertaken pursuant to <gloss target="#t_GaDel1">Gadel</gloss> 24 indicated that most delegations have
                        not yet given serious thought to this question. However, Romulo and a few
                        others appear to be leaning in direction of a resolution which could be
                        passed unanimously, rather than along lines objective set forth in paragraph
                        1 above. Speeches on debate re position of Chinese item on Committee 1
                        agenda indicated some small delegations also leaning in that direction.
                        Therefore, if objective listed in paragraph 1 is to be sought, staff
                        believes it essential it be brought most promptly to attention broad group
                        of delegates. If this is not done, there is danger of repetition 1947
                        warmongering situation.</item>
                    <pb facs="0112" n="96" xml:id="pg_96"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>My personal preference is that we should inform other delegations that our
                        main objective is that the Assembly should denounce the fraud of the Soviet
                        proposal and defeat it without amendment and, if possible without
                        substitute. The staff is inclined to feel that it is probably not feasible
                        under present circumstances to persuade the Assembly to follow this course.
                        In order to move ahead with the consultations which we all agree must be
                        undertaken immediately, would you agree to my talking privately to Romulo,
                        Padilla Nervo and McNeil,<note n="2" xml:id="d49fn2">Hector McNeil, Member
                            of the British Delegation; British Minister of State.</note> exploring
                        the prospects along these lines. If these talks confirm the opinion of the
                        staff, we would then proceed immediately with broader consultations along
                        the line of paragraph 1.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
