<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-08-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-08-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="89" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d89">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB/8–3149</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador at Large</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Jessup</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d89fn1">Addressed
                                    to the Deputy Under Secretary of State (Rusk), the Consultants
                                    on the Far East (Fosdick and Case), the Chief of the Division of
                                    Chinese Affairs (Sprouse), the Acting Director of United Nations
                                    Affairs (Sanders), and the Director of the Policy Planning Staff
                                    (Kennan).</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-08-31">August 31,
                                        1949</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Attached is a draft of a proposed <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> Resolution on the Chinese situation which follows
                                the pattern of the Washington Treaty of 1922 on China.<note n="2" xml:id="d89fn2">Signed February 6, 1922; <ref target="frus1922v01#pg_276">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 276</ref>.</note> This is
                                the step proposed in paragraph 3 of my memorandum of August 29th to
                                the Secretary listing a series of suggested measures in regard to
                                the Far East.<note n="3" xml:id="d89fn3">Attachment not
                                    printed.</note> The draft resolution repeats the substance of
                                each of the subparagraphs of Article 1 of the Washington Treaty as
                                it was felt that the omission of any one of them, even though it
                                might not be completely appropriate to the present situation, might
                                give rise to criticism. There is also attached for purpose of
                                comparison a copy of Article 1 of the Washington Treaty.<note n="3" xml:id="d89fn4">Attachment not printed.</note> Any comments you
                                may wish to make will be appreciated.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Philip</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Jessup</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener rend="inline">[Annex]</opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Prepared by Mr. <persName type="from">Charles W. Yost</persName>, Special Assistant to the
                                        Ambassador at Large</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Jessup</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    </seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-08-30">August 30,
                                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Resolution</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The members of the United Nations agree that they will not take
                                    advantage of the present disturbed conditions in China</p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>to infringe the sovereignty, the independence or the
                                        territorial and administrative integrity of China and,
                                        specifically;</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>to detach, seek to detach or recognize the detachment from
                                        the sovereignty of China of any territories which have been
                                        recognized by international treaty as falling under that
                                        sovereignty; or</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>to create, or to become a party to any undertakings
                                        creating spheres of influence or special regimes or
                                        administrations within the territory of China;</item>
                                    <pb facs="0177" n="161" xml:id="pg_161"/>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>to restrict the opportunity of the Chinese people to
                                        develop and maintain a stable and effective government
                                        responsive to their wishes; and independent of foreign
                                        control;</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>to seek special rights or privileges in China or parts of
                                        China, particularly in regard to trade and the use of ports
                                        and railways, which are not accorded to all other members of
                                        the United Nations; or</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>to take action, or become a party to undertakings,
                                        infringing the principle of equal opportunity for the
                                        commerce and industry of all nations throughout the
                                        territory of China.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p>The members of the United Nations, moreover, solemnly call upon
                                    the Government of China and upon each and every regime or
                                    administration exercising political authority within any part of
                                    the territory of China to refrain from any action directed
                                    against any of Chinas neighbors which might constitute a threat
                                    to or a breach of the peace and hence involve a violation of the
                                    United Nations Charter. Should any such action occur in spite of
                                    this admonition the United Nations will take immediate action in
                                    the premises in accordance with the terms of its Charter.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>