<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting United States Representative at the United Nations ( (Ross) ) to
                    the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d90</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">90</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-08-31T18:22:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-08-31T18:22:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-08-31T18:22:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-08-31T18:22:00-05:00" n="90"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB/8–3149: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting United States Representative at the United
                        Nations</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ross</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-08-31T19:22:00-04:00"
                            >August 31, 1949—7:22 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1027. For Sanders, <gloss target="#t_UNA1">UNA</gloss>. At his request, I called
                    on McNaughton this afternoon and discussed proposed Chinese <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> item fully on basis <gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 436, August 24 and <gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss>
                    1001, August 26. John Holmes,<note n="1" xml:id="d90fn1">Acting Head of United
                        Nations Division of Canadian Department of External Affairs.</note> who is
                    down from Ottawa for general <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> talks with
                    Canadians and British, and Arnold Smith were with McNaughton. They were without
                    instructions, hence were speaking personally, and Department of External Affairs
                    has reached no conclusions. Holmes said, however, that departmental committee
                    has been studying Chinese policy for some time and he felt reasonably sure views
                    they expressed this afternoon were in line with thinking this committee.</p>
                <p>Following is, I think, fair summary of views they expressed: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>They assumed inevitable that item would be put on agenda.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>They regretted this since it impaired our flexibility and crowded us
                            time-wise. (McNaughton said he had hoped Jessup committee<note n="2"
                                xml:id="d90fn2">For appointment of Raymond B. Fosdick and Everett
                                Case to this group on. July 30, see Department of State <hi
                                    rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, August 22, 1949, p. 279.</note>
                            studies would provide us with opportunity thorough examination whole
                            situation before we were forced to make decisions.)</item>
                        <pb facs="0178" n="162" xml:id="pg_162"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We could not, with self-respect, attempt to dissuade Tsiang from
                            putting item on agenda or refrain from positively and firmly supporting
                            inclusion on agenda when question arises. We could not with self-respect
                            refrain from supporting Tsiang’s first objective, namely, <gloss
                                target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> finding Soviet Union guilty of treaty
                            violation.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>They would be very reluctant to support Tsiang’s second and third
                            objectives, namely, nonrecognition of Communist regime and moral and
                            material aid to Nationalist Government. (Smith raised question whether
                            we might possibly attempt dissuade Tsiang from attempting to pursue
                            these two objectives on self-interest grounds, that he would run serious
                            risk not getting necessary Assembly support and thereby damaging
                            position Nationalist Government.)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>General tone their reactions indicated by expressions McNaughton used such as in
                    effect “We must not be cat’s-paw for Chiang Kai-shek<note n="3" xml:id="d90fn3"
                        >President of the Republic of China until his retirement on January 21,
                        1949, in favor of Vice President Li Tsung-jen as Acting President;
                        Generalissimo Chiang was leader of the Kuomintang (Nationalist
                        Party).</note> and let him play all of us for suckers”; “We must not lean on
                    a house of sand (Nationalist Government)”; “Will Chinese delegation at <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> be a mere façade with nothing underneath?” On
                    last point, McNaughton referred to impression he had members Chinese delegation
                    here actively making other plans and Smith inquired if I could confirm
                    information he had received that T. V. Soong<note n="4" xml:id="d90fn4">Former
                        President of the Chinese Executive Yuan; brother of Mesdames H. H. Kung, Sun
                        Yat-sen, and Chiang Kai-shek.</note> had deposited couple billion dollars in
                    gold in US.</p>
                <p>McNaughton felt Nationalist Government had everything to gain and nothing to lose
                    in bringing up item. He and his associates seemed very reluctant to get pinned
                    down by any <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> action concerning recognition of
                    Communist regime which would hamper our ability to deal in future effectively
                    with that regime on any basis we might choose to fit our policies. They seem to
                    have impression that Communist regime is not under Soviet domination. We should
                    not drive them, as McNaughton put it, into arms of Soviets. Even if this regime
                    were under domination of Soviets, our objective should be to split them away.
                    Therefore, we should retain free hand in dealing with them. To extent personal
                    views expressed by them today may turn out to reflect official Canadian opinion,
                    I should judge Tsiang would have very difficult job getting their support for
                    his objective number two. I think I detected at least slight undercurrent of
                    opinion which was not at all explicit in favor recognition of Communist regime
                    at some point.</p>
                <p>There was very little discussion of Tsiang’s third objective concerning moral and
                    material aid to Nationalist Government. McNaughton indicated awareness
                    difficulties our own situation; it is my impression <pb facs="0179" n="163"
                        xml:id="pg_163"/> they were about as strongly opposed to this point as to
                    non-recognition point.</p>
                <p>Making clear I was not expressing views of Department or, so far as I knew,
                    anyone in Department, I raised question nature leadership Western powers might
                    give to peripheral states such as India, Burma, Siam, which will be in very
                    difficult position regarding this question in <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.
                    McNaughton emphatically thought we must be in position give them strong positive
                    leadership and not let Soviet Union carry the ball. In this connection we
                    agreed, for example, there is risk that if Russians are smart, having been
                    forewarned indirectly by Lie, they will see to it that delegation of Communist
                    Government presents itself to Assembly, thus getting debate whole question on
                    ground of recognition or nonrecognition which would be more favorable to Soviet
                    position than question violation, treaty. McNaughton wondered whether we could
                    not develop strategy slanting whole case in <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                    against Soviet Union and avoid taking sides for or against either Nationalists
                    or Communists. Assuming hypothetically that Western Powers might agree to
                    support first Chinese objective, but not second (and third, we discussed very
                    briefly question whether we could develop positive alternative law [<hi
                        rend="italic">to?</hi>] two objectives but no bright ideas emerged.</p>
                <p>McNaughton was very appreciative my call, promised to let us know soon as he
                    heard anything from Ottawa and asked that we keep him posted. He urged earliest
                    consultations also with other delegations, mentioning particularly India. I
                    agreed desirable but reminded him injunction confidence laid down by Tsiang,
                    adding I thought we should tell Tsiang, soon as we know direction our policy, we
                    felt obliged to consult at least certain other delegations reasonably soon.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ross</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
