<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Spain ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1923v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d137</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">137</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1924-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1924-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="137"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d137">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.529/12</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-03-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 4, 1924</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received March 20.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 271</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Department’s unnumbered
                    Instruction of September 10th last directing this Embassy to report in detail
                    concerning the extent of the territorial waters over which the Spanish
                    Government claims jurisdiction in connection with contraband and fisheries and
                    as regards its bearing upon the enforcement of prohibition on Spanish vessels
                    within American territorial waters, I have the honor to report as follows:</p>
                <p>As regards the first section of the Instruction under acknowledgment, a note was
                    sent to the Spanish Foreign Office upon receipt of the Department’s Instruction,
                    setting forth the quotations mentioned by the Department, asking for a statement
                    as to the present practice of the Spanish authorities, their opinion as to the
                    fisheries control and requesting citation of the dates and numbers and any data
                    which might assist the Embassy in looking up Spanish laws, <pb facs="0342"
                        n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/> agreements, treaties or regulations dealing with
                    the extent of Spanish jurisdiction over the territorial waters claimed by Spain.
                    The matter was urged by personal representations at the Foreign Office and a
                    written reminder was eventually sent in. The answer, herewith enclosed in copy
                    and translation, was received at this Embassy on February 28th last. The Royal
                    Decree of November 23rd, 1914 mentioned in the Foreign Office’s aforesaid note,
                    was transmitted to the Department in duplicate in this Embassy’s despatch No.
                    185 of December 8th, 1914.<note n="70b" xml:id="d137fn70b">Not printed.</note>
                    Article 2 of this Decree gives the extent of three miles for Spanish neutral
                    waters in conformity with the 13th Convention of the Hague,<note n="70c"
                        xml:id="d137fn70c">
                        <ref target="frus1907p2#pg_1239">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1907, pt 2, p.
                        1239</ref>.</note> approved by the Decree.</p>
                <p>As regards the second part of the Instruction under acknowledgment, there is
                    enclosed herewith a memorandum written after a careful study of the matter by a
                    member of the staff, and from which it appears that there is only one Spanish
                    citation amongst the footnotes mentioned; this citation does support the
                    statement in the text as far as the <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> side of it is
                    concerned. There is, however, no mention of the neutral zone. The changing of
                    the neutral zone to three miles was sanctioned by the Royal Decree of November
                    23rd, 1914 above mentioned, but the note from the Spanish Foreign Office
                    explicitly states that such reduction was only provisional and until the
                    termination of the war; this leads to the obvious inference that the
                    jurisdiction over territorial waters claimed by Spain for all purposes, now
                    extends to within six miles of the coast.</p>
                <p>As regards the 3rd part of the Instruction under acknowledgment, it has not been
                    possible up to the present to secure any statement or expression of opinion
                    which would carry weight, from any responsible Spanish official on this subject;
                    but the matter is being borne in mind and supplementary information on this
                    point will be forwarded as soon as it is possible to get the concrete and
                    practical views of one or more Spanish officials.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hallett Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Spanish Foreign Office</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">American Embassy</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 22</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Note Verbale</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>With reference to the courteous notes No. 70 and 118 from the Embassy of the
                        United States, the Ministry of State has the honor to inform the Embassy
                        that, after the disappearance of the causes <pb facs="0343" n="227"
                            xml:id="pg_227"/> which brought about the Royal Decree of November 23rd,
                            1914<note n="70d" xml:id="d137fn70d">
                            <hi rend="italic">Boletín de la Revista General de Legislatión y
                                Jurisprudencia</hi> …, Tomo 156, 3° de 1914, Noviembre y Diciembre
                            (Madrid, 1914), pp. 73–75.</note> in which Spain accepted provisionally
                        until the termination of the war and only as regards neutrality, the
                        reduction of the territorial waters to three miles—its jurisdiction over
                        such waters extends to six miles, in conformity with that which has always
                        been its extent.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-02-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 28th, 1924</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Second Secretary of the Embassy in
                            Spain</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Riggs</hi>) <hi rend="italic">on the
                            Department’s Unnumbered Instruction of September 10, 1923 in re the
                            Extent of Territorial Waters Over Which Jurisdiction Is Claimed by
                            Spain</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>There is no Spanish Authority cited in support of the statement in the text.
                        The only Spanish citation is from Vol. 56 of the “Coleccion Legislativa de
                        Espana”, of the year 1852, page 194, article 18, paragraph 10, of which copy
                        and translation are attached and which is an extract from the Spanish Royal
                        Decree of June 20th, 1852, countersigned by Juan Bravo Murillo, Minister of
                        Hacienda, <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="flushleft">“ordering the enforcement, with various changes, of
                                the bill-of-law concerning the jurisdiction of the fiscal and
                                revenue authorities and the repression of contraband and fraud,
                                which has been approved by the Senate.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>It should be noted that the data given in the Department’s above-mentioned
                        Instruction concerning the year and the Article, are erroneous.</p>
                    <p>The Spanish of the above citation is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 18. Se incurre en delito de
                                contrabando …<note n="71" xml:id="d137fn71">Omission indicated in
                                    the original memorandum.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 10. Por andar con buque nacional o
                                extranjero de porte menor que el permitido por los reglamentos e
                                instrucciones, conduciendo generos prohibidos o procedentes del
                                extranjero en puerto no habilitado, o en bahia, cala o ensenada de
                                las costas espanolas, o por bordear estos sitios dentro de la zona
                                de dos leguas, o sean seis millas que se halla senalada, aun cuando
                                lleve su carga consignada para puerto extranjero, a menos que no sea
                                por arribada forzosa en los casos de infortunio de mar, persecucion
                                de enemigos o piratas, o averia que inhabilite el buque para
                                continuar su navegacion.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">and the translation is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 18. The crime of contraband is
                                constituted by …<note n="71" xml:id="d137fn72">Omission indicated in
                                    the original memorandum.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 10. Running a national or foreign
                                vessel of smaller tonnage than permitted by the regulations or
                                instructions, carrying <pb facs="0344" n="228" xml:id="pg_228"/>
                                prohibited or foreign goods, into an unauthorized port, bay, inlet
                                or cove of the Spanish coasts; and by sailing along the coast in the
                                vicinity of these places within the zone of two leagues, or six
                                miles mentioned above, even though the cargo be consigned to a
                                foreign port—unless it is a case of forced landing in distress,
                                attack by enemies or pirates, or disablement preventing the ship
                                from continuing its voyage.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>The “mentioned above” refers to Section 7 of the same Art. 18, which reads as
                        follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 7. Por la extraccion del territorio
                                espanol de efectos de cualquiera especie, cuya exportacion este
                                prohibida por las leyes, reglamentos u ordenes vigentes, y por su
                                conduccion dentro de la zona proxima a las costas y fronteras en que
                                por las mismas leyes y reglamentos este prohibida su circulacion, o
                                por su detentacion en la misma zona sin los requisitos que en
                                aquellas disposiciones esten prescritos.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">and in translation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Sec</hi>. 7. By the exportation from Spanish
                                territory of any kind of goods of which the exportation is forbidden
                                by the existing laws, regulations or orders, and by the conveyance
                                thereof within the zone adjacent to the coasts and frontiers in
                                which the circulation of such goods is prohibited by the same laws
                                and regulations; or by the possession thereof within that same zone
                                without the fulfilment of the prerequisites required by those
                                regulations.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Hence it would seem that the text of the Spanish Royal Decree cited does
                        support the statement cited in the extract from the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Columbia Law Review</hi>, reproduced in the Department’s
                        Instruction.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
