<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (Schurman) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1923v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d349</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">349</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1923-05-04T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1923-05-04T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-05-04T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-05-04T06:00:00-05:00" n="349"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d349">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/4283: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schurman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-05-04T19:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 4, 1923—7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received 9:10 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>130. My 127, April 28, 4 p.m.<note n="12" xml:id="d349fn12">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_539">p. 539</ref>.</note> In
                    view of the multiplying rumors of war between Chihli and Fengtien forces and
                    convincing <pb facs="0623" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/> evidence that troops and
                    supplies were being pushed forward by both sides greatly to the anxiety of
                    civilian population, the American, French and British Ministers and Japanese
                    Chargé d’Affaires had a conference with Prime Minister this afternoon in which
                    we informed him of the position we had taken with regard to Minister of
                    Finance’s proposal for a loan from the Consortium, and declared we should be
                    compelled to withdraw the recommendations we had made to our respective
                    Governments, if fighting was likely to occur in North China. We acknowledged the
                    receipt of assurances from the Chinese Government that the popular anxiety was
                    without foundation, and stated that we had read similar assurances in the
                    newspapers from the highest military authorities on both sides, but we could not
                    reconcile with these declarations the indisputable facts of the advance of
                    troops and the requisition of carts, etc. While we believed that the Government
                    and the leaders on both sides did not desire war, we apprehended an outbreak of
                    hostilities as a mere result of the juxtaposition of armies whose outposts were
                    now in contact with one another. We suggested that, as a guarantee of peace, the
                    forces on both sides be withdrawn and a neutral zone established, and that the
                    Central Government direct that such steps be immediately taken. Prime Minister
                    replied that his emissaries had just returned from Mukden and would go tomorrow
                    to Paotingfu, and that he could now assure us that the crisis was passed. For
                    this reason he had been hopeful of peace, now he was confident of it. He added
                    that he had good ground for believing, not only Chang Tso-lin, as well as the
                    Chihli leaders, would withdraw their troops from their present advanced
                    positions, but that the former would also soon declare his allegiance to the
                    Peking Government.</p>
                <p>Prime Minister thanked us for our benevolent helpfulness to China. We said that
                    our Governments, who would strongly deprecate the outbreak of hostilities, were
                    desirous of helping China in all proper ways to maintain peace for the benefit
                    of the Chinese people. A copy of this message has been mailed to Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Schurman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
