<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Counselor of Legation at Peking ( (Bell) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1923v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d503</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">503</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1923-05-14T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1923-05-14T22:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-05-14T22:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-05-14T22:00:00-05:00" n="503"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d503">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">393.1123 Lincheng/48: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Legation at Peking</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-05-15T11:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 15, 1923—11 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 15—9 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>157. My 156, May 14, 3 p.m. Following text of note handed afternoon 14th by dean
                    to Acting Minister of Foreign Affairs: <pb facs="0754" n="638" xml:id="pg_638"/>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“With reference to my note the recent outrage on the Tientsin-Pukow
                            Railway at Lincheng, I have the honor to inform Your Excellency that the
                            diplomatic body has decided to insist that the Chinese Government should
                            take immediate steps to reenforce the troops and police guarding the
                            principal Government railways, especially the Tientsin-Pukow and the
                            Peking-Hankow lines and the passenger trains running thereon, and to
                            request Your Excellency to inform me at the earliest possible moment of
                            the nature of the steps taken by the Government to this end.</p>
                        <p>Further, the diplomatic body with a view to the protection of their
                            interests and to safeguard the lives and property of their nationals,
                            have appointed a commission of foreign officers who will be entrusted
                            with the duty of investigating the measures taken by the Chinese
                            Government to protect the said Government railways from a recurrence of
                            outrages similar to that which has occurred at Lincheng, and for that
                            purpose require that the Chinese Government should undertake to arrange
                            for the free transport of these officers on the railways and for all the
                            necessary facilities for their comfort, etc., these details to be
                            arranged by the Ministry of Communications in conjunction with the
                            administration of the several railways.</p>
                        <p>I am desired by my colleagues to add that the diplomatic body reserve to
                            themselves the right, on receiving the report of the commission of
                            foreign officers aforesaid to demand in the name of their respective
                            Governments any further increase in the number of troops and railway
                            police or modifications in the measures taken to protect and patrol the
                            railways as may be recommended by the said commission and appear to them
                            to be desirable.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Following also handed at same time by dean to Acting Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Mexican Minister has informed the diplomatic body that an official
                            of the Foreign Office called on Mr. Kolessoff, the interpreter of the
                            Mexican Legation, on the 12th instant and showed him the text of a
                            message received from the Chinese consul general at San Francisco,
                            United States of America, stating that the relatives of Mr. and Mrs.
                            Manuel Ancira Verea are ready to pay any ransom demanded in order to
                            obtain their release by the bandits near Lincheng. The same official
                            observed that it would be difficult to deliver the ransom to the bandits
                            as the Mexican Legation had no representative at Lincheng, and this
                            would appear to indicate that the Foreign Office accepts the principle
                            that the ransom may be paid by the relatives of the captives and is
                            contrary to the attitude which the diplomatic body has adopted on this
                            point. The Foreign Office should be aware that the Chinese Government is
                            responsible for the payment of whatever ransom may be necessary and that
                            they should accept no funds from private sources for this purpose.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Schurman</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Bell</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
