<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (Schurman) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1923v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d547</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">547</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1923-07-16T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1923-07-16T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-07-16T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-07-16T06:00:00-05:00" n="547"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d547">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">393.1123 Lincheng/203: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schurman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-07-16T19:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 16, 1923—7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received July 16—6:43 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>261. My 241, June 29, 10 a.m. Committee met today and completed draft of note to
                    the Chinese Government which will now be reported to diplomatic body for
                    appropriate action. The only important modification since the omission of the
                    Shanghai demands was the raising of the indemnity for loss of liberty and
                    hardships suffered by the captives as follows: $500 silver per captive per day
                    for the first 3 days, $100 a day for the next week, $150 for the next, $200 for
                    the next, $250 for the next, $300 for the next. For the life of the Englishman
                    $20,000 silver was demanded.</p>
                <p>Committee have thought it best to drop altogether the subject of progressive
                    sanctions. This decision was due on the one hand to the impossibility of finding
                    any suitable substitute for the Shanghai demands and on the other hand to a
                    relaxation of feeling in the minds of the Ministers who in early June were most
                    insistent in urging this penalty.</p>
                <p>I brought up at the end the question as to what measures should be taken to
                    insure acceptance of the demands made by the diplomatic body in case the Chinese
                    Government should prove unresponsive thereto as discussed in your number 138,
                        undated,<note n="7" xml:id="d547fn7">July 9, 6 p.m., <hi rend="italic"
                            >supra.</hi>
                    </note> received July 11, 9 a.m. The French Minister thought it would be unwise
                    to elaborate a definite program of action in advance and believed we should be
                    in a better position to deal with the matter when we had learned reaction of the
                    Chinese Government. I ventured the opinion <pb facs="0795" n="679"
                        xml:id="pg_679"/> that the Chinese Government could be brought to the
                    acceptance of the demands contained in our note through ordinary diplomatic
                    pressure and that the real difficulty would be over the problem of the
                    reorganization of the railway police force under foreign officers which is
                    reserved for a future communication. This view was generally concurred in though
                    the opinion was also expressed that the Chinese would not take favorable action
                    without some delay.</p>
                <p>This afternoon Japanese Chargé d’Affaires (the new Minister is to arrive tonight)
                    called on me to discuss further the subject of railway police with respect to
                    which he had hastily indicated to me his Government’s views before the committee
                    meeting this morning. It is clear to me that while not formally opposing in
                    principle the British program, the Japanese Government views it with suspicion.
                    The Japanese representative here will, I venture to predict, be found supporting
                    the French Minister’s proposal of leaving railway police under Chinese control
                    but subject to foreign inspection and report.</p>
                <p>On the merits of the case I must add that this latter program has much in its
                    favor. In the first place it does not relieve Chinese Government of full
                    responsibility for protection of foreigners traveling on railways and, secondly,
                    it does not assume as the British proposal seems to assume that traveling would
                    be safe if only foreign officers were given supreme command of Chinese railway
                    police, whereas, in my opinion, dangers of travel in China will not be greatly
                    reduced till bandits are suppressed in the provinces. In this connection I may
                    report that French Minister some time ago observed to me that in his opinion and
                    that of the Chinese experts in his Legation the plan of sending foreign experts
                    to the provinces to report what the tuchuns are doing for the suppression of
                    bandits which the committee adopted on my recommendation is likely to prove the
                    most helpful and constructive feature of committee’s note.</p>
                <p>Japanese Chargé d’Affaires told me this afternoon that his Government desired
                    that the subject of railway police should be worked out by the diplomatic agents
                    here. I replied that I believed that was also the view of my Government, which,
                    however, favored in principle the British proposal subject of course to the
                    understanding that its application would be limited to the protection of
                    travelers and not embrace any ulterior objects. I had previously cited to him
                    your attitude in the Shanghai matter as proof of your insistence that the
                    diplomatic body should limit itself exclusively to the object under
                    contemplation, namely, the prevention of future Lincheng outrages.</p>
                <p>Committee decided to postpone further consideration of railway police problem
                    till British Minister who [went?] to Pehtaiho a week ago could be present.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Schurman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
