<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-06-09T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-06-09T19:00:00-05:00" n="630" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d630">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.74/313: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Schurman</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-06-09T20:00:00-04:00"><hi rend="italic">June 9,
                                        1923—8 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>103. For the information of the Minister and to be discussed
                            confidentially with Mr. Schwerin.</p>
                        <p>It is a matter of great regret that on account of unavoidable delays
                            incidental to giving consideration to the Federal contract, the
                            Department has not undertaken to inform you currently of the position of
                            affairs, with regard to questions influencing the matter, in such a way
                            that such misconception as seems to be represented by the Legation’s
                            telegram No. 204 of June 7 would have been obviated.</p>
                        <p>Because of persistent delays by the Chinese Government I have been
                            considering for some time the possibility of alternative procedure in
                            case the Chinese Government’s passive attitude should, under
                            circumstances which constitute an absolute bar to progress in the
                            matter, be continued. Apparently the definite refusal of the Japanese
                            Government to discontinue its support of the Mitsui claim to a wireless
                            monopoly was a significant coincidence with the British Government’s
                            very persistent effort to secure a statement of the American
                            Government’s position regarding the recommendations drawn up by the
                            American, British, French and Japanese radio experts on February 4,
                            1922, with regard to wireless activities in China and which those
                            experts submitted for approval to their respective Governments.<note n="12" xml:id="d630fn12"><ref target="frus1922v01#pg_840"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 840</ref>.</note> You are being
                            informed in a separate telegram of the text of these recommendations.
                            They have, so far as this Government knows, received only the British
                            Government’s formal approval. The formation of what may be denominated a
                            radio consortium for China is the apparent object to which their general
                            purport looks. The British, French and Japanese wireless interests would
                            comprise this consortium, with the maintenance by the American interests
                            of a separate entity, the purpose of which would be direct
                            Chinese-American communications, but taking cognizance, for the purpose
                            of necessary traffic and other working arrangements, of the other
                            organizations.</p>
                        <pb facs="0913" n="797" xml:id="pg_797"/>
                        <p>Although my strong preference would be, if only for the tactical
                            advantage it would give in arranging for such working agreements as
                            would later be necessary with the other national interests, to have the
                            arrangements under the Federal agreement independently executed, the
                            possibility has been receiving my consideration of bringing about
                            substantially the same result through an arrangement among the American,
                            British, French and Japanese radio interests employing as a foundation
                            the experts’ recommendations which look to reserving the
                            Chinese-American field for our interests to be developed through the
                            concession granted the Federal company. The difference is tactical
                            rather than essential between the two methods.</p>
                        <p>I have also considered, if concerted action among foreign interests with
                            respect to radio in China is still opposed by the Chinese Government,
                            the possibility of stimulating China to action on the Federal agreement
                            as an independent project by presenting the prospect of cooperation with
                            a British-French-Japanese radio consortium as an alternative which must
                            be considered by us in case Chinese cooperation under the Federal
                            agreement is persistently withheld.</p>
                        <p>The Department has discussed these suggestions tentatively with General
                            Harbord in order to learn whether the Radio Corporation would be ready
                            to do its part, if necessity should arise, with regard to the proposed
                            alternative method. The corporation is still considering the matter and
                            on June 13 its representatives are to consult with the Department
                            further.</p>
                        <p>There is a third possibility, viz, that the American Government should
                            show its willingness, in response to the British Embassy’s insistent
                            solicitations, to have the American radio interests join with the other
                            three national radio interests on the basis of the recommendations of
                            the experts, the arrangement to be conditional upon assurances that no
                            preferential or monopolistic rights should be asserted in regard
                            thereto, and that all opposition should be withdrawn to the carrying out
                            of the Federal contract.</p>
                        <p>The Department will be pleased to receive, by June 13th if possible, a
                            statement of your and Mr. Schwerin’s views regarding the proposed
                            alternatives to the effort which is being made at present to secure the
                            fulfillment, without reference to the interests of other nationalities,
                            by the Chinese Government of the Federal Telegraph agreement as an
                            independent project.</p>
                        <p>It is my hope that Mr. Schwerin, whose position is fully appreciated in
                            the matter, will find it possible to approve my dealing with it
                            according to one of the three alternative methods I have here outlined,
                            in the event it should appear impossible to overcome the Chinese
                            Government’s inertia.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>