<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in the Dominican Republic ( (Russell) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1923v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d747</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">747</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1923-10-10T12:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1923-10-10T12:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-10-10T12:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-10-10T12:40:00-05:00" n="747"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d747">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">839.00/2749: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in the Dominican Republic</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Russell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-10-10T13:00:00-04:40">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 10, 1923—1 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received October 13—1:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>55. With reference to your telegram 39, October 5, 5 p.m., in regard to
                    suspicions [<hi rend="italic">suspension</hi>] alcaldes pedañeos. Conference
                    with Provisional President contained in a letter from the Minister of the
                    Interior to the President and approved by the latter which is as follows: I
                    consider it absolutely unwise to suppress or suspend the alcaldes pedañeos. For
                    some time past the political leaders have complained of imaginary excesses
                    committed by pedañeos. After careful consideration, however, by this party it
                    developed that the only crimes committed by these men was that they were
                    persuading their political friends to register. This was done by alcaldes [in?]
                    all the different parties. There was not one case where it was proved that these
                    acts were committed with force nor that the alcaldes prevented registration of
                    any citizen of politics different from them. The Department of Interior and
                    police in accordance with your instructions <pb facs="1021" n="905"
                        xml:id="pg_905"/> addressed a circular letter to the governors of the
                    provinces in regard to the participation of officials in election matters and in
                    order that there should be no criticism the alcaldes were forbidden to
                    participate. Since then there has been no justifiable cause of complaint against
                    the alcaldes. The suppression or suspension before the elections would surely
                    result in much trouble. The alcalde is the only official that is feared by the
                    country people and with the disappearance of his authority infractions of the
                    law would multiply especially as the Government has not sufficient police to
                    take the place of these rural officials. Three or four months ago the question
                    of alcaldes was discussed at the American Legation and I proposed the issue of
                    Executive order suspending alcaldes for 10 days prior to elections and this was
                    approved by several of the Commissioners. At present I am absolutely convinced
                    that this should not be done not only for the reason of the Commissioners above
                    mentioned but because the purpose that the alcaldes take no part in the voting
                    would be absolutely frustrated as they would still exert their influence with
                    the country people and bring them to polls which is exactly what it is desirous
                    to avoid. The opinion of Colonel Cutts is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The available forces of the Dominican National Police are positively not
                            sufficient to even attempt to police the sections now allotted to the
                            alcaldes except on definite calls for assistance. They are hardly
                            sufficient in numbers at present to perform the extra work called for by
                            the elections. It is not considered that the relieving of the alcaldes
                            would make any difference in political effect unless they are physically
                            removed to [<hi rend="italic">from?</hi>] their districts.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The opinion of the Military Government is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The alcaldes pedañeos will probably carry out their mission as a legally
                            constituted body to make arrests under certain conditions and act as a
                            factor in maintaining peace and order. This body of men were appointed
                            honestly without regard to their political affiliation during the regime
                            of the Military Government which selected them because of reliability.
                            Since the advent of the Provisional Government I am led to believe that
                            they have been carefully selected from those whom the appointing power
                            considers reliable. Should the alcaldes desire to do any electioneering
                            or to practice any undue influence in their sections it is my opinion
                            that a suspension from office cannot prevent it. The suspension from
                            office of this body of men will deprive the country of their services at
                            a time when the Provisional Government will most need them to contribute
                            to the success of the elections in a legal way. There is no replacement
                            body to use during the period of their suspension. I cannot but feel
                            that suspension of the alcaldes from office during this period will
                            weaken the Provisional Government’s power to preserve order.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Russell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
