<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1923-11-09T08:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1923-11-09T08:40:00-05:00" n="753" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d753">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">839.00/2760: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Commissioner in the Dominican Republic</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santo
                                        Domingo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1923-11-09T09:00:00-04:40"><hi rend="italic">November 9,
                                        1923—9 a.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received November 10—5:10
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>62. My number 60, November 5, 11 a.m.<note n="10" xml:id="d753fn10">Not
                                printed.</note> I have had for the last three days almost continuous
                            conferences with the Commission as well as private conferences with the
                            two Presidential candidates. I have placed before the latter the
                            following considerations:</p>
                        <p>1. If the two political parties continue the policy of obstruction which
                            each has consistently followed, no elections can be held.</p>
                        <p>2. If no elections are held, the Dominican signers of the Plan of
                            Evacuation violate one of the chief obligations assumed by them in that
                            instrument and in that contingency the Government of the United States
                            must reserve entire liberty to determine its course of action.</p>
                        <p>3. By reason of developments not foreseen previous to the date upon which
                            the electoral law was promulgated, both parties have been able to secure
                            technical advantages contrary to the spirit of that law and to the
                            spirit of the plan of evacuation.</p>
                        <p>These advantages for the Coalition Party are as follows: By reason of a
                            restrictive interpretation of a faultily worded article of the electoral
                            law the Central Electoral Board has rejected the Alianza ticket in the
                            Province of La Vega and will, in all probability on the same ground,
                            reject the Alianza tickets in the Provinces of Barahona, Monte Christi
                            and Puerto Plata, thus preventing the members of the Alianza Party in
                            these four Provinces from voting in the coming elections because of mere
                            technical errors in the drafting of the party ticket. Fraudulent intent
                            in these cases has not even been charged.</p>
                        <p>The advantages of the Alianza Party are as follows: By reason of the fact
                            that the provincial and municipal electoral boards were constituted
                            before present Alianza Party was formed as the result of a conjunction
                            of the National and Progressive Parties and since these electoral boards
                            were composed of three members divided equally among such three
                            political parties in existence at that time, the Alianza Party has now a
                            majority vote on all of these important boards. Furthermore, since the
                            conjunction of the National and Progressive Parties occurred subsequent
                            to the formation of the Provisional Government, the Alianza Party has
                            twice the representation among the Secretaries of State of the
                            Provisional Government accorded the Coalition Party. Likewise, by reason
                            of the fact that <pb facs="1028" n="912" xml:id="pg_912"/> Señor
                            Velasquez was almost invariably consulted by the Military Government in
                            regard to the appointment of sindicos, fiscales and judges of the courts
                            of first instance, the great majority of these public officials all of
                            whom play an important role in the decision of electoral contests, are
                            at present partisan supporters of the Alianza Party.</p>
                        <p>4. It is a physical impossibility for the elections to be held on
                            November 14, by reason of the complete break-down of the electoral
                            machinery and the nonfunctioning of the Central Electoral Board which
                            has made impossible the decision of pre-election contests and the
                            printing of ballots. Since the decisions reached by the Electoral Board
                            regarding party tickets, etc., had application solely to the present
                            electoral period, such decisions would have no force in the event that
                            new election decree were issued and a new electoral period be
                            established as must now inevitably be the case.</p>
                        <p>I have therefore suggested to the leaders of the two political parties
                            that each relinquish the technical advantages which may have been
                            acquired, as a patriotic duty, and that before November 14, the date now
                            fixed for the national elections, the President be authorized by the
                            Commission to issue a decree postponing the date of the elections for a
                            period of 46 days and amending the electoral law in the following
                            manner: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Permitting both political parties an
                            extension of time to rectify any technical mistakes which have occurred
                            in the drafting of their provincial tickets; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                            reconstituting the electoral boards in such a manner as to give both
                            parties equal representation thereon throughout the Republic; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) granting the Central Electoral Board the right
                            to determine appeals brought by municipal boards from decisions of the
                            provincial boards thus enabling the Central Electoral Board to make its
                            jurisdiction absolute. And that the President be authorized at the same
                            time to give both parties equal representation among the sindicos,
                            fiscales and judges of the first instance.</p>
                        <p>I made it clear that the intent of my suggestion was to give both sides
                            equal treatment and to enable both parties to go to the polls with equal
                            guarantees; that this suggestion was offered only because the elections
                            could not now be held on the date set, and because I deemed it advisable
                            before a new electoral period was entered into to avail ourselves of the
                            experience acquired and reform the evident abuses which lack of
                            pre-vision in the drafting of the electoral law had made possible.</p>
                        <p>I am highly gratified to be able to state that the political leaders of
                            the two parties have finally today reached a definite agreement in
                            accordance with the suggestion above outlined and are now in process of
                            drafting the decrees required by [<hi rend="italic">for</hi>]
                            transmission to the Provisional President. A complete break-down of the
                            execution of the Plan of Evacuation has thereby been avoided. A much
                            improved <pb facs="1029" n="913" xml:id="pg_913"/> feeling already
                            prevails between the leaders of both parties and I apprehend no further
                            difficulties in the future.</p>
                        <p>I desire to call your attention to the fact that a change in the
                            appointments of judges of first instance, sindicos and fiscales so as to
                            give both parties equal representation implies a modification of article
                            2 of the Plan of Evacuation which provides that “the judges and other
                            officials of the judiciary shall not be removed except for due cause.”
                            Since the proposed change is in itself desirable, in view of the
                            extraordinary circumstances existing, and is farther the only way in
                            which both parties can be made to feel that they will obtain equal
                            treatment during the electoral period, I assume that you will have no
                            objection to my consent to the proposed modifications under the
                            limitations above specified.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>