<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Batavia ( (Livengood) ) to the Acting Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-01-17T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-01-17T21:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-17T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-17T21:00:00-05:00" n="124"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC Indonesia/1–1849: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d124fn1">Repeated in telegram 50, January 19, 9 p. m., to
                        The Hague.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-18T10:00:00+08:00"
                            >January 18, 1949—10 a. m. [<hi rend="italic">p. m.</hi>]</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>93. <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 553.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Supomo and Sudjono called late today. Sjahrir has arrived in Batavia and
                        has been permitted to live in own house and told he can see people freely
                        during his stay Batavia. He has explained to Supomo circumstances under
                        which he accepted invitation to come here. Yesterday he was visited by
                        assistant resident in Prapat and asked to come Batavia. He thereupon
                        consulted with Sukarno and Salim. Three of them do not have radio, receive
                        only Aneta news and are very anxious for news of internal situation. They
                        decided that Sjahrir should accept invitation only in order obtain latest
                        information. Sukarno and <pb facs="0181" n="167" xml:id="pg_167"/> Salim
                        received no invitation. As Hatta and other exiles on Bangka had visit from
                            <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> and received latest information,
                        Supomo thinks Hatta will not accept similar invitation. <gloss
                            target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> will probably call on Sjahrir tomorrow as
                        group. Sjahrir assured Supomo that he will not enter into any negotiations
                        with Drees or Federalists unless and until all Repub leaders are free and
                        restored to positions of governmental authority. Sjahrir will have informal
                        talk with Drees tonight. <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> will be
                        kept informed regarding developments.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Riphagen<note n="2" xml:id="d124fn2">Adviser of the Netherlands
                                delegation to the <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>,
                                Batavia.</note> called in response certain inquiries make [<hi
                                rend="italic">made</hi>] by <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>
                            relating to implementation paragraph seven <gloss target="#t_GOC1"
                                >GOC</gloss> report 16 January (<gloss target="#t_Gocus1"
                                >Gocus</gloss> 548). He stated high representative Crown agreeable
                            in principle to visit of local <gloss target="#t_RepubDel1"
                                >RepDel</gloss> to Bangka but that it was believed Hatta and
                            possibly other exiles will be down to Batavia next day or two. Stated
                            anyway Darmasetiawan going to Bangka tomorrow or next day in connection
                            with Federalist negotiations. <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>
                            had heard through private sources earlier today that Anak Agung Gde
                            Agung had called on Darmasetiawan with reference to invitation to Hatta
                            to come down for consultation. Riphagen stated Sjahrir entirely free
                            here and need not go back Prapat unless he desires.</p>
                        <p>All these facts so far consistent with pattern revealed by Supomo
                            yesterday (<gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 551<note n="3"
                                xml:id="d124fn3">Telegram 90, January 17, not printed.</note>).
                            Believe either (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Riphagen may be doing wishful
                            thinking re Darmasetiawan activity as Supomo had not mentioned
                            Darmasetiawan trip or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Darmasetiawan carrying
                            on independent activity apart from <gloss target="#t_RepubDel1"
                                >RepDel</gloss>. Will check further tomorrow but incline to (<hi
                                rend="italic">a</hi>).</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>British <gloss target="#t_ConGen1">ConGen</gloss>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d124fn4">Francis Michie Shepherd.</note> called re two
                        points: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) stated senior British-military observer
                        believed a <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> report of 14 January (<gloss
                            target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 545) reflected too hasty report by
                        British military observer at Soerabaya. <gloss target="#t_ConGen1"
                            >ConGen</gloss> admitted, however, that facts probably true. Assured him
                            <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> will submit general military report
                        with full evaluation as soon as we can obtain it from <gloss
                            target="#t_MilEx1">MilEx</gloss> Board. (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Said
                        he had been asked by his government to comment on US Working Paper but had
                        seen only inadequate summary in <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss>
                        bulletin. Promised to give him written outline basic features tomorrow
                        morning. He said did not believe his government could support commission
                        instead of <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> because it would imply Repub
                        had not been true party. Sought to explain to him inability of committee
                        good offices to function as such under present conditions and will take
                        opportunity tomorrow in delivering summary to explain further special
                        features of American plan. Signed Lisle.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
