<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the Acting Chief of
                        the Division of United Nations Political Affairs (Bancroft)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v07p1</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d126</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">126</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-01-18T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="126" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d126">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC Indonesia/1–1849</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the Acting Chief of
                        the Division of United Nations Political Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bancroft</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-18">January 18,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Scott<note n="1" xml:id="d126fn1">Joseph W. Scott, of the same Division, was at
                        New York with the U.S. mission at the United Nations.</note> called to bring
                    me up to date on the latest developments after Mr. Rusk’s conversation with Dr.
                    Jessup. He said they had a meeting with Norway and China and had gone over the
                    resolution in detail agreeing on certain drafting changes. The principal change
                    was to provide that the Commission in making its recommendations should take
                    into account the economic well-being of the population of Indonesia. In general,
                    Mr. Scott said that drafting changes were such as to be more palatable to the
                    French point of view and to the Dutch.</p>
                <p>Scott reported that they plan to talk to the Cubans this afternoon to go over the
                    resolution and have a meeting set up with the United Kingdom and Canada jointly.
                    Thereafter if there was time today, or if not, early tomorrow morning they were
                    going to go over the resolution with the Egyptian.</p>
                <p>Scott also reported that after deBeus<note n="2" xml:id="d126fn2">Member of the
                        Netherlands delegation at the United Nations.</note> had brought in the
                    9-page Dutch memorandum,<note n="3" xml:id="d126fn3">January 17, <ref target="#pg_157">p. 157</ref>.</note> Scott had a chance to talk to him
                    further about the working paper. He told deBeus that we were interested in
                    knowing exactly what parts of the resolution the Dutch objected to and pointed
                    out that we were proceeding on a basis whereby we had not introduced a
                    resolution in the Council, but were using the device of a working paper in order
                    to get the suggestions of the Council members and of the Dutch. Scott said that
                    apparently deBeus reported this conversation to Helb in Washington because a
                    little later Helb called him from Washington and said that he would like to come
                    to New <pb facs="0184" n="170" xml:id="pg_170"/> York to discuss the working
                    paper with him. Scott suggested that this might mean that the Dutch point of
                    view was changing slightly and becoming less intransigent.</p>
                <p>Scott reported that pursuant to Rusk’s conversation with Jessup they were going
                    to talk to McNaughton about the possibility of postponing Wednesday’s meeting.
                    He said that there was a good chance of this although China had indicated that
                    they did not believe that the meeting should be postponed beyond Thursday
                    because of the conference in New Delhi.</p>
                <p>Noyes<note n="4" xml:id="d126fn4">Charles P. Noyes, of the U.S. mission at the
                        United Nations.</note> called me later in the afternoon to say that they
                    were sending down by telegram tonight the modifications in the resolution agreed
                    upon with Norway and China this morning and would report on the British and
                    Canadian reactions. He specifically raised the question whether the treatment of
                    the Cochran plan in paragraph (3) of the resolution (NY Tel. #56<note n="5" xml:id="d126fn5">January 17, <ref target="#pg_163">p. 163</ref>.</note>) was
                    satisfactory to Mr. Cochran.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harding</hi> F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bancroft</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
