<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Batavia ( (Livengood) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d197</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">197</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-02-28T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-02-28T22:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-28T22:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-28T22:00:00-05:00" n="197"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d197">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC Indonesia/3–149: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d197fn1">Repeated in telegram 175, March 2, 7 p. m., to The
                        Hague, and 233 to Brussels.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-01T11:00:00+08:00"
                            >March 1, 1949—11 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>211. <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 609. Schuurman addressed <gloss
                        target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> February 28 letter enclosing Hamid radio
                    speech (<gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 608<note n="2" xml:id="d197fn2"
                        >Telegram 210, February 28, 4 p. m., not printed.</note>). Letter concluded,
                    “from contents of speech it appears <gloss target="#t_BFO1">BFO</gloss> has
                    accepted invitation extended by Netherlands Government to participate in round
                    table conferences Hague”. I told Schuurman by phone I had read speech and
                    thought it indicated Hamid favors Netherlands proposal but constituted no <gloss
                        target="#t_BFO1">BFO</gloss> acceptance. He said Beel found acceptance in
                    following Paragraph 17: “Now however we have been offered new opportunity and
                    initiative taken by Netherlands Government to hold round table conference for
                    transfer sovereignty has our wholehearted approval”.</p>
                <p>8 p. m. received as <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> chairman telegram
                    filed Muntok 9:40 a. m. signed Roem, chairman Republic delegation, reading:
                    “Latest decision Netherlands Government as in Beel’s letter handed Saturday
                    night to Sukarno in Muntok by Gieben, inviting Republic leaders join round table
                    conference Hague with other representatives Indonesia on March 12, cuts across
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> resolution and moreover explicitly rejects
                    said resolution. In verbal elucidation Gieben made perfectly clear that on no
                    account Netherlands Government will comply with condition to restore actual
                    government of Republic in its power over any part its territory. In particular
                    Gieben explained that, contrary to wording his government’s statement on
                    abrogation remaining restrictions concerning liberty movement of Republic
                    leaders, we shall in no case be allowed return Jogja. This new move of
                    Netherlands as so often before gives expression to their denial of legality
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> intervention and substitutes different
                    proposal on their own authority. Our government will however never cooperate in
                    any action evading implementation <pb facs="0292" n="278" xml:id="pg_278"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> resolution. We particularly deem it urgent
                    counteract any confusion which this move is apt to create in international
                    circles.”</p>
                <p>I called informal meeting give <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> this
                    message. With group approval phoned Sudjono. He said received same telegram.
                    Said Republic group still desired go Bangkok [<hi rend="italic">Bangka</hi>]
                    planned. <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> also approved my reading
                    message to Schuurman, He said this obviously despatched by Roem prior any
                    discussions by Republic with Koets who flew Bangka Monday.</p>
                <p>Schuurman phoned 11 p. m., said gave Beel message. Latter said Koets had been
                    instructed telegraph promptly if Republic answer negative. No such message
                    received. On contrary Koets had telegraphed was remaining Bangka overnight and
                    asked special plane bring him Batavia Tuesday evening. From this Beel thought
                    matter not settled. I offered let Koets return <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1"
                        >UNCFI</gloss> plane and promised hold <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1"
                        >UNCFI</gloss> report open until late evening awaiting any word from
                    him.</p>
                <p>I phoned Sudjono recommending his group endeavor influence Republic leaders at
                    least leave matter to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> decision if they not
                    willing accept invitation and had not closed door finally.</p>
                <p>This morning Critchley said he saw Leimena late last night. Even Critchley
                    thought Republic’s answer might have left way open for seeking more concrete
                    information from Netherlands on their proposal or exploring after consultation
                    with <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> some way out before turning down
                    summarily.</p>
                <p>Schuurman reported 10 a. m. today no word yet received from Koets.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> group regrets Netherlands has so badly
                    handled their proposal. By sending Gieben Bangka to deliver proposal even before
                        <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> received it deprived latter any
                    chance it might have found feasible and proper to be helpful without weakening
                    on <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> resolution. By not sending Koets until two
                    days later permitted Republic opposition crystallize before Republicans could be
                    presented by Koets with some of arguments in favor proposal which he had so
                    attractively set forth orally to <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> group
                    Sunday (<gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 607<note n="3" xml:id="d197fn3"
                        >Telegram 207, February 27, <ref target="#pg_272">p. 272</ref>.</note>).
                    Signed Cochran.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
