<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-04-02T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-04-02T08:00:00-05:00" n="252" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC Indonesia/4–249:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d252fn1">Repeated in telegrams 287, April
                                    4, 6 p. m., and 297, April 7, 1 p. m., to The Hague, the latter
                                    to be forwarded to Brussels for Kirk.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-02T21:00:00+08:00">April
                                        2, 1949—9 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>322. <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 649. Leimena and Djuanda
                                called this evening after returning 6 p. m. with others of Jogja and
                                Batavia Republican groups from visiting republican leaders
                                Bangka.</p>
                            <p>Leimena gave me copy reply April 1 Republican Delegation Chairman
                                Roem to <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> chairman text
                                whereof follows:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I have honor refer to your message March 26 and subsequent
                                    conversation between your Commission and our party in
                                    Pangkalpinang on March 28 and beg inform you that it has been
                                    decided to accept your invitation to discussions in Djakarta
                                    under auspices of <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss>.
                                    Since it has not been possible to begin these discussions on
                                    Wednesday March 30 as you originally suggested, I presume you
                                    will let me know at your earliest convenience the proposed date
                                    for opening of talks.</p>
                                <p>My acceptance of Commission’s invitation to discussions with
                                    Netherlands, before latter has agreed to establishment of
                                    Republican Government at Djocja, is likely to create grave
                                    misunderstandings among Republican leaders in other parts of
                                    country and abroad and among Indonesian people generally. Such
                                    misunderstandings could not fail to make eventual settlement of
                                    Indonesian dispute more difficult, I would, therefore, stress,
                                    that my participation must necessarily be limited at least in
                                    early stages of discussions.</p>
                                <p>On 19 December 1948 authority was properly transferred to an
                                    emergency government in Sumatra to act on behalf of Republican
                                    Government until such time as that government is free to
                                    reassemble. As your Commission made clear in paragraph two of
                                    its report to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> of 1 March and
                                    as was emphasized by a number of speakers in recent <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>’s debates, restoration or
                                    Republican Government at Djocja free to take decisions uncoerced
                                    is a prerequisite to ‘any fruitful negotiations.</p>
                                <p>I shall, therefore, only be able to discuss initially practical
                                    details of restoration of Republican Government at Djocja. It is
                                    my hope that Netherlands will agree in principle to this
                                    restoration at outset so that Republican Government can take at
                                    Djocja upon basis of ascertained wishes of its people essential
                                    decisions regarding <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>’s
                                    Resolution 28 January and directive 23 March.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>Supomo and Sudjono joined Leimena, Djuanda and me analyzing this
                                reply. They all assure me Republican Delegation will in <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss>
                                <pb facs="0373" n="359" xml:id="pg_359"/> meetings go beyond
                                discussion restoration Jogja but insist that be given priority.</p>
                            <p>Roem will head delegation at start. Republican leaders say no one
                                else can be appointed to this position except by President Sukarno
                                functioning in Jogja.</p>
                            <p>Djuanda felt visit Bangka helped relieve nervousness of leaders there
                                and his group remaining Batavia until Tuesday morning to have more
                                contact with Republicans here. <gloss target="#t_UNCFIN1">UNCFI</gloss> plane will then take them Jogja.</p>
                            <p>Djuanda considers restoration Jogja entirely feasible with maximum
                                2,000 police mostly civil but insists all Netherlands military must
                                be removed. Republican Ministers making serious studies of problems
                                incidental to restoration from administrative, security and economic
                                viewpoints. Jogja depleted of Republican currency. Need for trucks
                                to supply foodstuffs will be considerable since railway service into
                                Jogja from surplus areas largely interrupted. Signed Cochran.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>