<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Batavia ( (Livengood) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d318</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">318</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-07-12T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-07-12T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recdTuobyjHNvXKhT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011601"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bankruptcy</term>
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-07-12T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-12T10:00:00-05:00" n="318"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d318">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BC Indonesia/7–1249: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d318fn1">Repeated in telegram 607, July 13, 3 p. m., to The
                        Hague.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-07-12T23:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 12, 1949—11 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>602. <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 756. Morning 12th definitely refused
                    go along with Critchley’s idea issuing <gloss target="#t_UNCI1">UNCI</gloss>
                    press release critical of reports by American journalists on military observers,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>Roem returned from Jogja five p. m. accompanied by <gloss target="#t_TNI1"
                        >TNI</gloss> Major Harjono. Am sending <gloss target="#t_UNCI1">UNCI</gloss>
                    plane morning 13th with Harjono and US military observer overnight Medan,
                    proceed 14th Kotaradja to pick up <gloss target="#t_TNI1">TNI</gloss> Colonel
                    Hidayat and perhaps other member Republican military staff Atjen, return Batavia
                    14th and take <gloss target="#t_TNI1">TNI</gloss> officers Jogja 15th.</p>
                <p>Roem asked for eight p. m. appointment. I phoned Van Royen that Roem coming since
                    Van Royen continued perturbed over political situation Hague. I told Van Royen
                    that unless conciliatory statement arranged to be issued Jogja after receipt by
                    Roem my letter this morning (<gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 755<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d318fn2">Not printed.</note>) I would suggest Roem make
                    appropriate statement tonight or morning 13th. Van Royen agreed. He expressed
                    sympathy over loss 13 US press correspondents since crash their plane over India
                    just announced.</p>
                <p>Roem came eight p. m. Had discussed my letter with Hatta. Said Hatta and others
                    all unhappy over speech of welcome made sixth by vice chairman working
                    committee. Said both Hatta and he had subsequently issued statements seeking to
                    offset these unfortunate remarks. They felt, however, that there had been
                    nothing in other Republican speeches or statements Jogja to which Hague properly
                    could take exception. Nevertheless they desired improve atmosphere soonest and
                    most effectively. Roem said first Cabinet meeting scheduled for night 13th and
                    possibility Hatta issuing statement thereafter.</p>
                <p>I told Roem speech after Cabinet meeting would be too late for Van Royen’s need.
                    I suggested Roem himself make press statement Batavia morning 13th reporting
                    first few days at Jogja following restoration Republic. He said atmosphere was
                    good, all political leaders working together and Hatta assured he would have
                    unanimous vote of approval in Cabinet. Furthermore Sjafruddin will turn in his
                    authority at Cabinet meeting and support Hatta. Although date not yet fixed for
                    working committee meeting, Hatta thinks possibly only one dissenting vote
                    therein. Following return General Sudirman to Jogja, Hatta has conferred with
                    him and other military leaders. No objection on their part to cease hostilities,
                    only question being that of arriving at <pb facs="0473" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"
                    /> technical measures to prevent clashes in exceptional circumstances which will
                    obtain after cease hostilities ordered and two forces remain so intertwined.
                    Said Leimena working seriously with Simatupang on compilation manual and
                    remaining Jogja to complete Republican version thereof with <gloss
                        target="#t_TNI1">TNI</gloss> advisors. Roem said progress on all lines
                    moving as quickly and satisfactorily as could be expected and optimistic final
                    and favorable decisions can be taken shortly after 20th which will permit
                    Republicans go Hague for <gloss target="#t_RTC1">RTC</gloss> early in August in
                    same spirit cooperation that has characterized Batavia discussions.</p>
                <p>I asked Roem use in his statement as much foregoing information as he could
                    possibly reveal without hurting Hatta’s cause and also to repeat some sentences
                    from his earlier statement at Jogja well as Hatta’s since these had not been
                    translated and broadcast in entirety. I suggested further he visit Van Royen
                    soon as statement prepared and prior its issuance in order Van Royen could see
                    it and phone text by noon to Hague for use before Parliament. Roem agreed.</p>
                <p>I referred to second part my letter to Roem raising question placing Republican
                    representatives in <gloss target="#t_NEI1">NEI</gloss> Ministries. Roem had
                    discussed this with Hatta. They favored idea provided representatives would be
                    and remain Republican officials having contact and liaison with <gloss
                        target="#t_NEI1">NEI</gloss> Government and not become officials or
                    employees of latter. I said appropriate arrangements and announcements along
                    this line should await finalization agreement Jogja.</p>
                <p>I said foregoing plan might eventually pave way for joint approach by Netherlands
                    and Indonesia for revival <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> aid. I had not
                    mentioned <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> to single Republican since
                    question recently raised by Department. Roem promptly remarked <gloss
                        target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> should not be revived until agreement reached
                    at <gloss target="#t_RTC1">RTC</gloss> and sovereignty transferred. I said under
                    present set up <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> aid could not be given <gloss
                        target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> as sovereign state. I said some special
                    arrangement would have to be made as for Korea or some other source funds
                    sought. Roem looks upon <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> as means obliging
                    parties work together rather than source dollars which could play any important
                    part in Indonesian economy this juncture.</p>
                <p>Reference <gloss target="#t_Usgoc1">Usgoc</gloss> 402,<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d318fn3">Telegram 370, July 11, <ref target="#pg_456">p.
                        456</ref>.</note> received four p. m. Hope arrangement for statement by Roem
                    will meet requirements. Do not favor <gloss target="#t_UNCI1">UNCI</gloss> or
                        <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> statement.</p>
                <p>Reference <gloss target="#t_Usgoc1">Usgoc</gloss> 403,<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d318fn4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> simultaneously received. I do not
                    intend mention <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> revival further to
                    Republicans at this time. Am cooperating with Van Royen as thoroughly as
                    possible in seeking best atmosphere for final settlement. Toward that end, am
                    assuming Netherlands acting entirely in good faith. At same time am convinced
                    present policy <pb facs="0474" n="460" xml:id="pg_460"/> inspired importantly by
                    fact that by end January Netherlands Government discovered second police action
                    doomed to failure and <gloss target="#t_NEI1">NEI</gloss> to bankruptcy by
                    mid-summer. Without regard to various cables from Department envisaging possible
                    escape measures by Netherlands Government, I have been slightly concerned by
                    indication hedging on part both Maarseveen and Van Royen to effect <gloss
                        target="#t_RTC1">RTC</gloss> could not take place unless cease hostilities
                    order effective. I recommend no weakening whatever in <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                        >ECA</gloss> and other US and <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> policies
                    vis-à-vis Netherlands until <gloss target="#t_RTC1">RTC</gloss> actually
                    assembles and is progressing towards desired end. Again I reiterate that if
                    present Netherlands Government which instituted second police action cannot
                    weather current squall no chance it surviving real tempest when genuine transfer
                    sovereignty impends at <gloss target="#t_RTC1">RTC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Roem was to call on Chairman Hamid yet this evening to extend invitation from
                    Hatta to <gloss target="#t_BFO1">BFO</gloss> meet Jogja 20th for
                    inter-Indonesian conference which Roem thinks should take about five days.
                    Anticipates that final Republican decisions may be taken and announced within
                    that period.</p>
                <p>Phoned Van Royen ten-thirty tonight. Summarized Roem’s report to me except that I
                    said nothing about <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> or Republican
                    representatives in <gloss target="#t_NEI1">NEI</gloss> Ministries. Van Royen
                    delighted with idea Roem making statement tomorrow morning<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d318fn5">The text was transmitted in telegram 604, <gloss
                            target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 758, July 13, from Batavia, not
                        printed; it was issued to the press by Chairman Roem the same day (501.BC
                        Indonesia/7–1349).</note> after letting Van Royen see draft and confident
                    this will prove helpful Hague. Signed Cochran.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
