<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in India ( (Henderson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-06-20T22:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-06-20T22:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recULIxJyNgKnvgmt" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-06-20T22:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-20T22:30:00-05:00" n="51"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851<gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>.01/6–2149:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-06-21T09:00:00+05:30"
                            >June 21, 1949—9 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>697. (1) I had long talk with Bajpai<note n="1" xml:id="d51fn1">Sir Girja Shankar
                        Bajpai, Secretary-General of the Indian Ministry of External Affairs.</note>
                    afternoon June 20 regarding Vietnam. I told him frankly your hopes and concern
                    and stressed that failure new regime obtain wide support people of country would
                    almost inevitably result in eventual Communist conquest. Communist control would
                    open way for Communists to Siam and other southern Asian areas. I handed him
                    latest available draft our proposed announcement and said my government
                    sincerely hoped, in view all circumstances, responsible Indian leaders would not
                    for time being make any statements or take any action which would make more
                    difficult success new regime. I said we realized unless French could by acts
                    convince nationalist majority Vietnam that requisite concessions would be
                    forthcoming, present experiment would fail. We were hoping enlightened policy on
                    part of French and Bao Dai would gain support of real nationalists and separate
                    them from present Communist leadership.</p>
                <p>(2) Bajpai replied: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>So far as he knew, there was no intention on part Nehru or other
                            Indian leader to make public statement or take other action regarding
                            present situation Vietnam. An announcement might of course result raise
                            inquiries which must be answered. He would discuss question at once with
                            Prime Minister to ascertain if it would not be possible for <gloss
                                target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> at least to reserve for present its
                            position regarding Bao Dai. He would inform me Nehru’s reaction.<note
                                n="2" xml:id="d51fn2">In telegram 704, June 22, 8 a. m., from New
                                Delhi, Ambassador Henderson reported a note from Sir Girja
                                confirming the oral remarks and advising the French to inform India
                                urgently of their intentions respecting Indochina (851<gloss
                                    target="#t_G1">G</gloss>.01/6–2249).</note>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="0076" n="62" xml:id="pg_62"/>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Difficult for <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> to make decisions
                            since French Government has not enlightened <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                                >GOI</gloss> regarding its plans in Vietnam, and <gloss
                                target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> has no information other than that
                            appearing in press.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>He was afraid such expressions “progressive realization” contained in
                            our proposed announcement would not appeal to Indian public since
                            British in their documents 30 years ago continually used expressions
                            like “progressive steps direction self-government.” There was feeling in
                            India use word “progressive” by colonial powers, unaccompanied by
                            listing of measures and dates, was a rather worn device for doing
                            nothing.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>It might be helpful if in talks with press following issuance of
                            announcement, Department spokesman could stress informally somewhat more
                            explicitly Department’s understanding that there were to be in Vietnam
                            orderly developments which would satisfy legitimate aspirations
                            people.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Regardless attitude <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>, he had grave
                            doubts French would be sufficiently intelligent to follow policy in
                            Vietnam which would gain support of population.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>(3) I referred to elections yesterday in Chandernagore and asked if relations
                    with French had improved. He replied affirmatively, but said French colonial
                    office was nevertheless backward and stubborn. India sincerely wished to
                    maintain good relations with French. However, no Indian Government could afford,
                    for internal or external reasons, take any action which might be interpreted as
                    supporting continued control by colonial powers of Asian peoples.</p>
                <p>(4) Our conversation confirmed my views expressed <gloss target="#t_Embtel1"
                        >Embtel</gloss> 893, June 20.<note n="3" xml:id="d51fn3">Not printed.</note>
                    Unless French really intend take measures progressively place power in hands
                    Vietnam people and convince <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> in Paris or
                    Saigon of their intentions, <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> will probably,
                    at sometime not distant future, condemn Bao Dai regime as fraud.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 697; repeated London, Paris, Saigon.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
