<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in France (
                        Bruce
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v07p1</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d85</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">85</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-12-08T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-12-08T12:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-08T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-08T12:00:00-05:00" n="85" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851<gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>.00/12–849:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bruce</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-08T18:00:00+01:00">December 8, 1949—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5166. Foreign Office note December 6 initialed by Schuman contains answers
                    Department’s October 15 questions to Bonnet. Original by despatch.<note n="1" xml:id="d85fn1">Despatch 1101, December 9, from paris, not printed.
                            (851<gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>.01/12–949)</note> Rough translation
                        follows:<note n="2" xml:id="d85fn2">A text in French was received December
                        22 from the French Ambassador. (851<gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>.00/12–2249)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0118" n="104" xml:id="pg_104"/>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>I. The Franco-Vietnamese, Franco-Laotian, and Franco-Cambodian agreements
                        will be submitted for approval to the Assemblies in the near future.</p>
                    <p>Since the details of the ratification procedure have not yet been decided,
                        they will be communicated to the Embassy later.</p>
                    <p>The ratification of these agreements by Parliament will not imply, however,
                        the “legal creation” of the states with which France has signed them. These
                        states already exist. Ratification will merely confirm (<hi rend="italic">consacrer</hi>) the essential points of the new regime of independence
                        granted to these states.</p>
                    <p>(Embassy comment: While complete information not available Foreign Office
                        when note drafted, Letourneau<note n="3" xml:id="d85fn3">Jean Letourneau,
                            French Minister of Overseas France.</note> tells me decision now reached
                        submit Parliament three agreements under cover single bill and in interest
                        speed not wait to include supplementary accords to March 8 document.)</p>
                    <p>II. The supplementary agreements presently being negotiated are to be signed
                        at Saigon by the chief of the Vietnamese Government and the High
                        Commissioner of France for Indochina. These agreements must, in principle,
                        be signed at the same time and before the end of the year. It is possible,
                        however, that if a delay occurs in the conclusion of one of them, the
                        accords already agreed upon will be signed first.</p>
                    <p>III. The agreement of March 8, 1949, refers to qualified Vietnamese
                        authorities without specifying what authorities will be called upon to act.
                        The decision as to who these authorities shall be constitutes in effect a
                        domestic Vietnamese problem whose solution will derive from the constitution
                        of that country which at the present has only provisional institutions.</p>
                    <p>Under the circumstances, it appears that the French Government cannot inform
                        the US Government of the rules which will result from the free determination
                        of Vietnam. However, the general tendencies of political and constitutional
                        order allow one to suppose that a representative assembly of Vietnam will be
                        called to pronounce itself on these agreements.</p>
                    <p>IV. The territory of Cochin-China has been part of the associated Vietnam
                        State since the law of June 4, 1949, and by virtue of its text.</p>
                    <p>The law of June 4, 1949, was passed pursuant to Article 75 of the
                        constitution of the French Republic which provides for changes of status
                        within the French Union as the result of a law passed after consulting the
                        territorial assemblies and the Assembly of the French Union. The territorial
                        assembly of Cochin-China was organized by the law of March 14, 1949.</p>
                    <p>V. The character of the consultation which took place can only be appreciated
                        in the light of the disturbed situation which then prevailed in
                        Cochin-China.</p>
                    <p>The French Government did not wish to use the state of disorder in
                        Cochin-China as a pretext for delaying the reuniting of this territory to
                        Vietnam. On the one hand, in fact, the demand for Vietnamian unity
                        constituted such a grounds for agitation that one risked never achieving
                        pacification if the unity question was made a condition previous. On the
                        other hand, the sentiment for Vietnamese unity seemed strong and unanimous
                        enough for the French Parliament to draw the proper <pb facs="0119" n="105" xml:id="pg_105"/> conclusion, regardless of the imperfections of the
                        representation charged with its expression in the territorial assembly.</p>
                    <p>VI. In the interest of reestablishing normal conditions in Vietnam, the
                        French Government is dealing with H. M. Bao Dai, as the most qualified
                        Vietnam representative in the present situation, to reestablish peace in
                        that country under the authority of a government of its own and whose
                        interests are truly national.</p>
                    <p>The political regime of Vietnam organized under the authority of H. M. Bao
                        Dai is still only provisional and holds itself out as such. The working out
                        of definite institutions for Vietnam will keep pace with the progress in the
                        task of pacification and unification to which this provisional government
                        has set for itself. It will be the concern of the future constitution of
                        Vietnam, after the population has been able freely to express itself, to
                        decide on a monarchical or republican form of government. At that moment Bao
                        Dai will be invested with such titles (<hi rend="italic">qualités</hi>) as
                        the Vietnamese nation may confer upon him after it emerges from its
                        difficulties.</p>
                    <p>VII. Article 4 of the Charter of the United Nations provides that all
                        peaceful states which accept the obligations of the Charter and, in the
                        judgment of the organization are capable and disposed to fulfill them, may
                        become members of the United Nations.</p>
                    <p>Without doubt the disturbances in Indochina and the delays necessary to draft
                        treaties have not, so far, permitted the French Government to consider that
                        the Associated States of Indochina can fulfill all the conditions set forth
                        in the above-mentioned Article 4.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, the solutions already reached in Laos and Cambodia, as well as
                        the Franco-Vietnamian settlement concluded by the agreement of March 8 and
                        its expected consequences, give the French Government great hopes of being
                        able to present the candidacy of the three Associated States of Indochina to
                        the UN Organization in the near future.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Sent Department 5166; repeated London 907.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bruce</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
