<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Document Prepared in the Division of Far Eastern Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recIMQA43VbepP2FZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Anti-communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="123"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Pacific War/3549</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Document Prepared in the Division of Far Eastern Affairs</hi>
                    <note n="89" xml:id="d123fn89">In a memorandum of November 8 the Chief of the
                        Division of Far Eastern Affairs (Ballantine) addressed this document to the
                        Adviser on Political Relations (Hornbeck), the Assistant Secretary of State
                        (Long), the Assistant Secretary of State (Berle), and the Under Secretary of
                        State (Stettinius).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-03">November 3,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Japan–Wang Regime “Pact of Alliance” of October</hi> 30,
                    1943</p>
                <p>The “Pact of Alliance” which was signed by Japan and the Wang regime on October
                    30 provides in part that the “treaty” of November 30, 1940<note n="90"
                        xml:id="d123fn90">
                        <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_117">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 117</ref>.</note> “together with all
                    instruments annexed thereto” is terminated. A comparison of the texts of the new
                    “pact” and the “treaty” of 1940 suggests that the new “pact” represents a
                    gesture on Japan’s part toward the Wang regime and also possibly toward the U.
                    S. S. R.</p>
                <p>In comparison with the “treaty”, the “pact” shows a far greater effort on Japan’s
                    part to appeal to Chinese good-will. In the phrasing of the “pact” there is an
                    emphasis on the apparent equality between the two parties, all the commitments
                    being assumed by “Japan and China”. A protocol accompanying the “pact” contains
                    on Japan’s part a commitment to withdraw Japanese forces from China “when
                    general peace between the two countries is restored and a state of war ceases to
                    exist.” Japan also renounces the right of stationing troops under the Boxer
                        Protocol.<note n="91" xml:id="d123fn91">Signed at Peking, September 7, 1901,
                            <ref target="frus1901China#pg_312">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1901, Appendix, (Affairs in
                            China), p. 312</ref>.</note> On the surface these commitments with
                    regard to the withdrawal of Japanese troops go much farther than the commitments
                    contained in the 1940 “treaty”. (The 1940 “treaty” contained provision for the
                    indefinite stationing of Japanese forces in certain parts of China and for the
                    gradual withdrawal of the remainder over a period of two years after the
                    restoration of peace between the two countries.) At the same time the “pact” as
                    a whole is phrased in very general terms and provision is <pb facs="0168"
                        n="158" xml:id="pg_158"/> made that the necessary details for carrying out
                    the “Pact” are to be decided upon subsequently. The door is thus left open for
                    the obtaining by Japan of any concessions which it may desire from “China.”</p>
                <p>The absence of any mention in the new “pact” of anti-Communism—a subject which
                    held a prominent place in the “treaty” of 1940 and which has long been stressed
                    by Japan as one of the ideological bonds linking Japan and the Wang regime—is
                    notable. This omission may indicate a gesture on Japan’s part toward the U. S.
                    S. R. It certainly shows a determination on Japan’s part not to give offense to
                    the U. S. S. R. at this time.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
