<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="124" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Pacific War/3559</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 1780</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-05">November 5,
                            1943</date>.<lb/>[Received November 27.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose a translation of
                        a confidential report<note n="92" xml:id="d124fn92">Not printed.</note>
                        written by a Chinese correspondent of the <hi rend="italic">Ta Kung Pao</hi>
                        in regard to the military, political and economic phases of the battle in
                        the Lake District of Western Hupeh in May 1943. This report was printed on a
                        single sheet by the <hi rend="italic">Ta Kung Pao</hi> at Chungking for very
                        limited distribution and none of the material has been published in the
                        paper’s regular edition.</p>
                    <p>The correspondent spent a month and a half in the battle area during June and
                        July where he talked with military personnel, with government officials and
                        with the country people. As a result of his observations, he feels that the
                        battle was a military defeat, a serious economic failure and a grave
                        political defeat.</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>. Although the Chinese military
                            authorities had prior knowledge of the enemy’s retreat, the Chinese
                            counter-offensive did not begin until some days later and in its attacks
                            the Chinese encountered only a small number of enemy rear guard units.
                            Chinese troops engaged in the campaign totaled 20 divisions while the
                            enemy forces were estimated at one and a half divisions or between
                            20,000 to 30,000, two-thirds of which were puppet troops. Chinese losses
                            were approximately 70,000 to 80,000 men while enemy losses were from
                            3,000 to 4,000 men. The Chinese soldiers in this campaign were as well
                            equipped as those of the enemy but the poor physical condition and
                            training of the Chinese troops were largely responsible for the
                            defeat.</p>
                        <p>Causes of Chinese military weakness are said to be: (1) false reports on
                            operations by military commanders of all grades; (2) lack of cooperation
                            among commanding officers; (3) remoteness of high <pb facs="0169" n="159" xml:id="pg_159"/> commanders from their troops; (4)
                            insufficient trained officers; (5) lack of food and medical attention
                            for the soldiers; (6) enmity of the common people toward the Chinese
                            troops; and (7) treachery of Chinese who aid the enemy.</p>
                        <p>Under present conditions, which are believed to exist generally
                            throughout the National Government’s armies, a division of soldiers may
                            be entirely wiped out by disease, starvation and desertions within two
                            years’ time without ever having participated in military operations.</p>
                        <p>Large towns and small villages in the battle area were reduced to ashes
                            and most of the people were killed or taken away by the enemy, who also
                            carried off or destroyed all movable property, broke dikes and burned
                            boats in the area affected. The population was greatly reduced and the
                            destruction effected by the enemy will require twenty to thirty years to
                            repair.</p>
                        <p>The harsh treatment of the common people by the Chinese troops and the
                            Japanese policy of apparent friendliness to them has resulted in making
                            the common people hostile toward their own soldiers. In one town the
                            Chinese garrison, prior to the arrival of the enemy, ordered the local
                            populace to evacuate the city but would not permit them to take their
                            possessions. Following the evacuation the garrison completely looted the
                            city and killed those who had refused to depart. In another place the
                            garrison was guilty of looting, rape, murder and burning of houses and
                            of charging the populace large sums of money for permits to enable them
                            to return to their homes. Local government organizations were in league
                            with the enemy and smugglers and members of secret societies deceived
                            the people into thinking the Japanese would be friendly to them. This
                            was true during the enemy’s advance, but when they retreated they burned
                            villages and killed the people on a vast scale. These same traitors,
                            however, continued to work for the local governmental and party
                            organizations after the campaign. <hi rend="italic">End of
                            summary</hi>.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>The foregoing description of the Hupeh campaign and of the destruction
                        resulting therefrom has been heard from other sources and is believed to be
                        accurate. It represents a damning indictment of the Chinese military
                        authorities responsible for the conditions existing among Chinese troops and
                        gives an indication of the meager extent to which the Chinese armed forces
                        can be expected to contribute to the United Nations war effort unless
                        drastic reorganization takes place. It is not believed that the man in the
                        street is aware of the degree of ineffectiveness of Chinese military
                        strength and many Chinese observers are of the opinion that President Chiang
                        Kai-shek himself is not aware of the extent to which the Chinese army has
                        deteriorated. They state that no one dares tell him the truth and that if
                        anyone did attempt to give him a true picture of the situation those close
                        to the President would prevent such action. It is generally agreed that the
                        higher military authorities are aware of these conditions but are unable
                        effectively to remedy the situation because of economic, financial and
                        political considerations.</p>
                    <pb facs="0170" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/>
                    <p>Most observers agree that the distressing conditions found among Chinese
                        troops in the Hupeh area are not confined to those forces but generally
                        exist throughout every area. Even the troops of General Hu Tsung-nan, Deputy
                        Commander of the 8th War Zone, which are said to be the best equipped and
                        trained of all the Chinese forces, are reported to require monthly
                        replacements at the rate of 600 men a division. Numerous reports have
                        reached the Embassy of the general ill-health among Chinese troops
                        throughout free China because of lack of sufficient food and medical
                        attention. Many critics state that honest and efficient military
                        administration alone would go far toward solving the problem in that the
                        troops would then receive the food and medical supplies intended for them
                        and the elimination of the present practice of padding the rolls indulged in
                        by military commanders would enable the government to save a considerable
                        sum. There seems, however, little or no hope that any effective steps will
                        be taken by the Chinese authorities to relieve the present situation and the
                        only positive and effective Chinese military contribution will likely come
                        from American-trained and equipped Chinese forces who may be expected to be
                        given decent rations and medical attention.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">C. E. Gauss</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>