<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Gauss) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d159</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">159</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-01-31T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-01-31T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recIMQA43VbepP2FZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Anti-communism</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-31T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-31T23:00:00-05:00" n="159"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d159">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/14927: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-01T11:00:00+07:00"
                            >February 1, 1943—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 1:25 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>176. Replying to your 137, January 25, midnight. Please refer to Embassy’s
                    telegrams 1005, September 5, 9 a.m.; 1070, September 21, noon; and 1486,
                    December 12, 10 a.m., 7th and 10th paragraphs, and to its despatches 408, May
                        14;<note n="15" xml:id="d159fn15">
                        <ref target="frus1942China#pg_232">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. 1942, China, pp. 232</ref>,
                            <ref target="frus1942China#pg_241">241</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1942China#pg_260">260</ref>, and <ref
                            target="frus1942China#pg_197">197</ref>, respectively.</note> 468, June
                        18;<note n="16" xml:id="d159fn16">Not printed.</note> 501, July 7; 515, July
                    14; 613, September 20 [<hi rend="italic">10</hi>]; and 800, December 16, 1<note
                        n="17" xml:id="d159fn17">
                        <ref target="frus1942China#pg_98">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, China, pp. 98</ref>,
                            <ref target="frus1942China#pg_206">206</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1942China#pg_235">235</ref>, and <ref
                            target="frus1942China#pg_264">264</ref>, respectively.</note> all
                    1942.</p>
                <p>With regard to points numbered 1 and 2, there has been a clear and disturbing
                    deterioration, as the Embassy had repeatedly reported, in the general economic
                    situation in unoccupied China and in the condition of the Chinese armies due to
                    undernourishment, disease and <pb facs="0214" n="204" xml:id="pg_204"/> inaction
                    but it is unlikely and unreasonable that the Chinese Government under present
                    circumstances would find in this state of affairs a pretext for initiating
                    repressive measures that might lead to civil war.</p>
                <p>With regard to point 3, the Embassy’s information does not indicate that there
                    has been any appreciable growth in the strength of the Communist army. There
                    have been no large defections of national troops and individual defections have
                    not materially affected the situation. It is understood that Communists now have
                    more men than they can adequately arm and are encouraging soldiers to return to
                    farms because of labour shortage. Embassy is informed that in order to avoid
                    irritating the Kuomintang the Communists discourage defection of national troops
                    or purchase of arms from them.</p>
                <p>Although relations between the Communists and the Kuomintang are far from
                    satisfactory, it is believed that the conclusion drawn is [<hi rend="italic"
                        >in</hi>] the report that has reached the Department is not warranted.</p>
                <p>In this connection particular attention is invited to my recent despatch number
                    800. Anti-communism continues to be cornerstone of Kuomintang policy but the
                    leaders, notably the Generalissimo, consider it politic and practical to refrain
                    from repressive action at this time. Liquidation of the Communists by the
                    present Kuomintang leadership is a question of “when” rather than “whether”. The
                    time has not arrived. It may never arrive. Russian entrance into the war against
                    Japan would make such a move inadvisable. Liberalization of Kuomintang
                    leadership after peace under pressure from dissatisfied popular and official
                    elements would render conflict improbable. While the war against Japan
                    continues, civil war is not likely to occur. Conversations with informed
                    Kuomintang and Communist leaders here, including Chou En-lai who is mentioned in
                    the Department’s telegram, confirm this opinion.</p>
                <p>Hall of the National City Bank who recently travelled through Communist territory
                    and stayed some time in Yenan reports that morale there is good, that Communist
                    forces have fair equipment of small arms but need mountain guns and that they
                    are carrying on guerrilla warfare but are impatient of situation which prevents
                    them from collaborating with national armies in attacking Japanese in force. He
                    says that whereas commodities are limited, people seem to have a fair quantity
                    of necessities including medicines. He observes that morale of national troops
                    he saw in south Shensi was not so good, that economic conditions were
                    disturbing, and that corruption among military and civil officials was
                    relatively common compared with apparent absence thereof in Yenan. Incidentally
                    he states that he was well and courteously treated by Chinese throughout his
                    long journey.</p>
                <pb facs="0215" n="205" xml:id="pg_205"/>
                <p>In conclusion probably the most encouraging comment that can be made regarding
                    Kuomintang-Communist relations is that they are now much the same as they were
                    when the Embassy described them at some length in its dispatch number 95 of
                    August 20, 1941.<note n="19" xml:id="d159fn19">
                        <ref target="frus1941v05#pg_533">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 533</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
