<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-04-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.408/1</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Troy L. Perkins of the Division of Far
                            Eastern Affairs</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-04-24">April 24, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Reference Chungking’s strictly confidential despatch no. 1001, March 17,
                        1943.</p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> It is believed that the future activities of
                        the San Min Chu I Youth Corps will deserve fairly close attention. While
                        there are numerous morale and propaganda agencies in China (New Life
                        Movement, National Spiritual Mobilization Movement, etc.), the dynamic
                        character of the Youth Corps contrasts strongly with the moribund condition
                        of nearly all the others. This movement receives the serious attention of
                        some of the most influential Chinese officials and it appears to be growing
                        rapidly in strength.</p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                    <pb facs="0236" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/>
                    <p>While many of the above affirmations doubtless spring from an understandable
                        Chinese desire to further social consciousness, pride in China’s past,
                        economic independence and scientific progress, it is believed that the
                        highly nationalistic and mechanistic ideology of the German “state
                        philosophy” can be detected in them.</p>
                    <p>As the Embassy has frequently indicated, the San Min Chu I Youth Corps is a
                        “seed-bed” for future Kuomintang leadership. Its present vitality indicates
                        that it may be able to provide badly-needed new life blood (youth) for the
                        Party. However, its leadership and support would appear to assure that its
                        activities will have a reactionary character. Kang Tze, active leader of the
                        Corps, is known to be strongly influenced by German models. Chu Chia-hua
                        (German returned student and Vice President of the Examination Yuan), Chen
                        Li-fu (Minister of Education), Ku Cheng-kang (Minister of Social Affairs)
                        and Chang Tao-fan (Minister of Information) are all reactionary and are all
                        influential in the direction of the Youth Corps. Several of the leading
                        military figures, including Generalissimo Chiang, are vigorous supporters of
                        the Corps. The apparent reluctance of the better student type to join the
                        Corps is understandable but it also has its disturbing aspect, as this
                        situation would indicate eventual control of the movement (and later of the
                        Party) by half-educated rowdies and place-seekers, to the submersion of the
                        humanistic element which has been the strongest force in Chinese
                        civilization at its best.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>