<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="271" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d271">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/15124: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Atcheson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-09-17T12:00:00+07:00">September 17,
                                1943—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 11:09 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1741. 1. A usually well informed and reliable Chinese source has commented to
                        us on the recently concluded CEC session as follows: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>From the beginning of the session on September 6 until the 10th
                                feeling against the Communists ran high, Kuomintang die-hards
                                demanding their liquidation by armed force. Successful
                                counter-influences included (1) a telegram from T. V. Soong (which
                                became generally known among the delegates) emphasizing the adverse
                                effect in the United States of civil war in China and (2) advice to
                                Chiang Kai-shek by Chang Chun who pointed out that the Szechuan
                                militarists Teng Hsi-hou, Lui Wen-hui and Pan Wen-hua had not
                                accepted invitation to attend the session and that in the event of
                                civil war their forces would lie astride the line of communications
                                between Chungking and the Communist areas, thus giving them
                                opportunity to capitalize on their opposition to the Central
                                Government. Fu Tso-yi and Ma Hung-kuei, chairmen of the Suiyuan and
                                Ninghsia Provincial Governments respectively, also opposed military
                                action.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The session revealed China’s dependence upon the United States:
                                (1) need for financial assistance to which Chiang referred in his
                                speech describing the uses to which part of the American credits to
                                be put; (2) need for military equipment under Lend-Lease; (3)
                                dependence upon the United States to defeat Japan.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The election of Chiang as President now makes him more independent
                                of the CC clique and his power to make decisions without reference
                                to others long exercised in some degree is thus reinforced.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>2. The informant’s description of the anti-Communist feeling prevailing at
                        the CEC sessions corroborated by a statement made on September 10 by another
                        well-informed reliable Chinese who spoke of the “war spirit” of the CEC and
                        expressed fear that a manifesto might be issued tantamount to a virtual
                        declaration of war against the Communists.</p>
                    <p>3. We feel that the informant’s comments offer additional evidence both of
                        the extent to which the United States is in a position to influence Chinese
                        Government policy and of the Kuomintang’s intention to liquidate the
                        Communists if and when direct action can be taken without too adverse an
                        effect upon China’s international relations and the party’s internal
                        position.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Atcheson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>