<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Gauss) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="303"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d303">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/15199</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1827</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-17">November 17,
                            1943</date>.<lb/>[Received December 10.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the Embassy’s despatch no. 1675 of
                    October 14, 1943, in regard to Kuomintang-Communist relations, I have the honor
                    to enclose a copy of an editorial from the <hi rend="italic">Liberation
                        Daily</hi> (Communist newspaper published at Yenan) of October 6, 1943,
                    together with a digest of the editorial,<note n="91" xml:id="d303fn91">Not
                        printed.</note> commenting on the 11th Plenary Session of the Central
                    Executive Committee of the Kuomintang and the 2nd Session of the Third People’s
                    Political Council, both of which were held in September 1943. The English
                    translation of this editorial was received from Communist representatives at
                    Chungking.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Summary of Editorial:</hi> Realizing that the United
                        Nations’ strategy prevents the realization of Kuomintang aims to have Soviet
                        Russia weakened through a Japanese attack or through American and British
                        transfer of their full strength to the Pacific, leaving Russia to fight
                        alone, the Kuomintang has three possible courses of action: (1) to surrender
                        to the Japanese; (2) to delay the fundamental solution of the Communist
                        problem while preparing for civil war; and (3) to alter its political
                        direction. The first course is advocated by defeatists who wish to surrender
                        to Japan and initiate civil war; thinking the Kuomintang armies can easily
                        defeat the Communists. The second course is that favored by those who
                        camouflage their real intentions of destroying the Communists by emphasizing
                        the C.E.C. and P.P.C. resolutions on constitutional government and the
                        solution of the Communist problem by political means. The third course is
                        favored by some Kuomintang members, by the Communist Party and by all the
                        people, for it means a just solution of the Communist problem, the abolition
                        of the fascist dictatorship and the establishment of a democratic form of
                        government. Demands are presented to “Mr. Chiang” for continued resistance
                        to Japanese aggression, the cessation of the civil war crisis and the
                        anti-Communist movement, the withdrawal of the Chungking troops now
                        blockading the Communist areas, the abolition of one party dictatorship and
                        the secret service organs, the calling of the national congress prior to the
                        end of the war and freedom of speech, assembly and organization. <hi
                            rend="italic">End of Summary.</hi>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <p>This editorial is believed to represent the “official” views of the Chinese
                    Communist Party and its tone is a continuation of the critical and unyielding
                    attitude of most of the articles written by Communist Party members during
                    recent months which have been received by the Embassy. One Chinese Communist
                    stated recently that an agreement had been reached between the Communists and
                    Dr. Wang Shih-chieh, acting for the Kuomintang, for a cessation of the bitter
                    propaganda campaign which has been conducted by the two parties during the <pb
                        facs="0389" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> past few months (Embassy’s despatch
                    no. 1651 of October 6, 1943). While there has not yet been any direct evidence
                    of such an agreement, there has been a cessation of articles in the local
                    Government-controlled press enumerating the “Communist crimes,” a large number
                    of which appeared in September.<note n="92" xml:id="d303fn92">Augustus S. Chase
                        of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs in a memorandum dated December 30
                        commented on the “evidence—encouraging if true—that the Kuomintang and
                        Communists may have reached an agreement to cease their bitter propaganda
                        campaign.” (893.00/15199)</note>
                </p>
                <p>The statement in regard to the Communist problem made by the newly appointed
                    Minister of Information, Liang Han-tsao, at his first press conference
                    (Embassy’s telegram no. 1995, October 21) was not published in the vernacular
                    press although it was carried by the Central News Agency English Service. When
                    questioned at a later press conference as to the reason for the failure of the
                    Chinese press to publish the statement (all other statements made by the
                    Minister at this press conference were published in the Chinese press), the
                    Minister said that it was unnecessary to publish such a statement for Chinese
                    consumption as informed Chinese are fully aware of the true situation in regard
                    to the Communist problem. The Foreign Office spokesman at this conference added
                    that it was necessary to let foreign countries know the real situation.
                    Apparently the Kuomintang is endeavoring to play down the possibilities of civil
                    war and the seriousness of the situation in order to reassure foreign observers,
                    and a cessation of the propaganda campaign would be consistent with that
                    policy.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">C. E. Gauss</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
