<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="318" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d318">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.131/49</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 1966</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-27">December 27,
                            1943</date>.<lb/>[Received January 12, 1944.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose a copy of a
                        memorandum dated December 21, 1943,<note n="13" xml:id="d318fn13">Not
                            printed. Mr. Clubb’s final paragraph was as follows: “It is suggested
                            that, in the interests of a common humanity, the Department of State
                            might wish to bring to the attention of the Chinese Ambassador at
                            Washington the circumstance that it has received reports of this general
                            nature and that in the opinion of the Department, in the light of
                            China’s purported adherence to the democratic principles for which the
                            United Nations are now fighting, it would inevitably react to China’s
                            disadvantage should the present reprehensible state of affairs be
                            permitted to continue.”</note> prepared by Second Secretary Clubb,
                        recently on detail as Consul at Tihwa, in regard to prison conditions in
                        Sinkiang.</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi> As the Sinkiang authorities maintain
                            strict secrecy in regard to prison conditions in that province little
                            detailed information on the subject is available. It is known, however,
                            that of the 200 to 300 <hi rend="italic">émigré</hi> Russian army
                            officers in Sinkiang in 1934 all but a handful are now in prison.
                            Large-scale arrests of <hi rend="italic">émigré</hi> Russians took place
                            in 1934 and in 1938 and one well informed Russian <hi rend="italic">émigré</hi> believes that easily one-half of the adult male <hi rend="italic">émigré</hi> population of Sinkiang is now in prison
                            (perhaps as many as 3,500 persons out of the total <hi rend="italic">émigré</hi> population of approximately 14,000). One informed
                            Chinese estimated that 20,000 persons were arrested in the 1937–38
                            period alone. In addition to <hi rend="italic">émigré</hi> Russians,
                            many Chinese (even youths of high-school age), members of the Turki,
                            Kazak and other Sinkiang racial groups, members of scientific
                            expeditions, and even British and other European missionaries have
                            served terms in Sinkiang prisons. Prison conditions are described as
                            “medieval” and torture, solitary confinement in rooms without light, et
                            cetera, are common practices. Persons are sentenced to prison by
                            “special courts” sitting <hi rend="italic">in camera</hi> and once
                            confined are rarely released. The most important prison center in
                            Sinkiang is Tihwa, where there are said to be between 10 and 15 prisons.
                                <hi rend="italic">End of Summary</hi>.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">C. E. Gauss</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>