<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Alger Hiss, Assistant to the Adviser on
                    Political Relations ( (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943China</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d336</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">336</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-03-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-03-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="336"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d336">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.5151/915</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. <persName type="from">Alger
                            Hiss</persName>, Assistant to the Adviser on Political Relations</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-03-11">March 11,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. J. B. Brigden, Financial Counselor of the
                            Australian Legation;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Hornbeck;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Hiss.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Mr. Brigden called on Mr. Hornbeck and said that his Legation had received a
                    somewhat garbled or ambiguous message from London which indicated that the
                    United States was discussing with the Chinese <pb facs="0424" n="414"
                        xml:id="pg_414"/> the problem of exchange rates and of relief for American
                    officials in China.<note n="20" xml:id="d336fn20">For further correspondence on
                        the problem of exchange rates in relation to reverse Lend-Lease
                        negotiations, see <ref target="#pg_515">pp. 515</ref> ff.</note> Mr. Brigden
                    said that as we were all aware the present exchange situation worked severe
                    hardship on foreign official representatives in China.</p>
                <p>Mr. Brigden was told that Mr. Playfair of the British Treasury had been in some
                    weeks ago as a result of a telegram which had been received from the British
                    Military Attaché in Chungking and that it seemed likely that the Australian
                    Legation’s information stemmed from this same source. Mr. Brigden was further
                    told that we had for some time been giving consideration to the problem of our
                    official representatives in China in connection with exchange matters but that,
                    unless General Stilwell<note n="21" xml:id="d336fn21">Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell,
                        Commanding General, United States Army Forces in China, Burma, and
                        India.</note> has discussed the matter informally with the Chinese, we do
                    not believe there has been any direct discussion between American and Chinese
                    officials on this matter. We understand that the Chinese desire that there be no
                    change in the exchange rate and that they further are opposed to the granting of
                    special exchange rates. It was suggested to Mr. Brigden that he might wish to
                    talk to the British Embassy or to Mr. Playfair about the matter or that he might
                    wish to take up with the War Department the question of what arrangements
                    General Stilwell had made on an <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> basis. Mr. Brigden
                    said he was interested only in the Australian Legation’s staff in Chungking, not
                    in problems of the British or American military forces in China. Mr. Brigden was
                    told that if things developed in such a way that there appeared to be likelihood
                    that we could work out some satisfactory arrangement with the Chinese
                    authorities we should be glad to notify the Australian Legation. Mr. Brigden
                    expressed his appreciation for this offer.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
