<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-10T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-10T21:00:00-05:00" n="427" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d427">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.24/1527a: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-10T22:00:00-04:00">February 10,
                                1943—10 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>211. 1. A radio transmitter requested by the Chinese in November 1941 under
                        Lend Lease and approved by the appropriate agencies of this Government has
                        been completed and is ready for shipment. During the latter part of 1942 the
                        question of diverting this transmitter for the use of agencies of this
                        Government arose. At that time inquiry was made of Dr. Alfred C. Sze,<note n="21" xml:id="d427fn21">Sao-ke Alfred Sze, former Chinese Ambassador in
                            the United States.</note> in the absence of Dr. Soong, in regard to the
                        importance attached by the Chinese Government to this equipment. Dr. Sze
                        informed the Department that the transmitter was intended for use partially
                        for broadcasting within China and also to maintain continuous communication
                        with the United States and that the need for the transmitter was both
                        important and immediate. These and other factors were given careful
                        consideration by the appropriate departments of this Government, including
                        the War Department, and it was unanimously agreed that this equipment should
                        not be diverted but be shipped to Chungking with as little delay as
                        possible. The Department has now been informed that in a message dated
                        January 26 received by the War Department, General Stilwell stated that
                        shipment of this equipment, which he referred to as a psychological warfare
                        radio transmitter, would mean the abandonment of various vital projects and
                        he strongly recommended, in view of air transport limitations, the
                        indefinite postponement of the shipment until such time as land
                        communications are reopened.</p>
                    <p>2. While the Department is fully aware of the limitations imposed on the
                        shipment of supplies by air and of the consideration that other supplies may
                        be more vital and necessary, it believes, in view of the delicacy at the
                        present time of the question of the shipment of supplies to China, that it
                        would be advisable, if the Embassy perceives no objection, to bring to the
                        attention of Dr. Soong or to a member of the Generalissimo’s staff the
                        difficulty of shipping this transmitter into Chungking in the immediate
                        future in view of the considerations mentioned by General Stilwell. It is
                        also suggested that the Embassy ascertain whether the transmitter is
                        urgently needed, the relative importance attached by the Chinese authorities
                        to this equipment and, having in mind the Embassy’s 845, July 16, 1942, 10
                            a.m.,<note n="22" xml:id="d427fn22">
                            <ref target="frus1942China#pg_584">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, China, p.
                            584</ref>.</note> the purpose for which the Chinese intend to use
                        it.</p>
                    <p>3. It is suggested that before taking this matter up with Dr. Soong or other
                        Chinese officials you discuss it with General Stilwell and <pb facs="0509" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/> that he be informed of the history of the
                        matter here, the effort made, the decision arrived at, and the Department’s
                        present suggestion and the reasons therefor.</p>
                    <p>Please report developments and make such comment as you may desire.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>