<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="430" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d430">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.24/1581</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-20">February 20, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>In his report of January 25, 1943 to the Congress of the United States, the
                        Lend-Lease Administrator, Mr. Stettinius, made this statement: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="flushleft">“<hi rend="italic">Aid to China</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>“Lend-lease aid to China in 1941 was aimed especially at improving
                                transport over the Burma Eoad. It resulted in more than doubling
                                monthly tonnage carried over the route. Even then, however,
                                transportation difficulties kept total shipments comparatively
                                small. Following the loss of Burma, shipments to China were reduced
                                to a trickle, carried principally by cargo planes from India. We
                                have now taken measures which are considerably increasing these
                                plane shipments and we shall also find other means to get to China
                                the arms she needs.” What, in the light of the fact that at the time
                                when lend-lease program include some planes, most of them fighters
                                and trainers, several thousand trucks and some ordnance, ammunition,
                                gasoline, medical and miscellaneous supplies.”</p>
                            <p rend="center">(<ref target="#pg_39">Pages 39</ref>–<ref target="#pg_40">40</ref> of the official text.)</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Attention is called especially to the
                        statement: “We have now taken measures which are considerably increasing
                        these plane shipments and we shall also find other means to get to China the
                        arms she needs.” What, in the light of the fact that at the time when those
                        words were published and ever since, the American Government was and is
                        still declining to send additional transport planes for service into China
                        and to allocate trucks for service into China, are Americans and Chinese who
                        are concerned with “deeds rather than words” and who know the facts to infer
                        from these words?</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>