<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="548" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d548">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00 Tibet/77</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <persName type="from">Dalai Lama</persName> of Tibet
                            to President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: We received with the greatest
                        gratification your letter and the tokens of goodwill (your autographed photo
                        and an exquisite gold watch showing phases of the moon and the days of the
                        week) through your Envoys, Capt. I. Tolstoy and Lieut. Brooke Dolan, who
                        arrived here safely for the purpose of visiting the Pontificate and the city
                        of Lhasa.</p>
                    <p>We are happy to learn that you and the people of the United States of America
                        take great interest in our country and it is of special significance that
                        the people of the United States of America, in association with those of 27
                        other countries, are now engaged in a war for the preservation of freedom,
                        which has been thrust upon them by nations bent on conquest who are intent
                        upon destroying freedom of thought, of religion, and of action
                        everywhere.</p>
                    <p>Tibet also values her freedom and independence enjoyed from time immemorial
                        and being the great seat of the Buddhist religion I am endeavoring, in spite
                        of my tender age, to uphold and propagate our religious precepts and thereby
                        emulate the pious work of my predecessors. I earnestly hope and pray for a
                        speedy termination of hostilities so that the nations of the world may enjoy
                        a lasting and righteous peace, based on the principles of freedom and
                        goodwill.</p>
                    <p>As a token of my regard I am sending herewith a scarf of honour, three
                        Tibetan coins of the first precious metal (gold), my photo, and three hand
                        sewn thangas (depicting the sextet blessed with long existence, the 4
                        dutiful brothers (friends), and the 8 lucky signs, all framed in blue
                        brocade silk, etc.).</p>
                    <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dalai Lama</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <date calendar="tibetan-phugpa gregorian" when="1943-02-24">Dated 19th
                                Day of the 1st Tibetan Month, Water Sheep Year, corresponding to
                                24th February 1943.</date></dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>