<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-04-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-04-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="715" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d715">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">150.06/831</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of
                            State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-04-16">April 16, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Sir Arthur Salter<note n="13" xml:id="d715fn13">Of the British Merchant
                            Shipping Mission.</note> came in to see me, at my request.</p>
                    <p>I said that he doubtless was aware of the state of the record in connection
                        with the amendment to the Immigration Act. This permits deportation of
                        deserting Chinese seamen, as well as other aliens, who cannot be deported to
                        the country of which they are nationals.</p>
                    <p>I said, as he knew, the bill having been passed by the House and the Senate
                        was now lying over on a motion to reconsider by Senator LaFollette.</p>
                    <pb facs="0815" n="805" xml:id="pg_805"/>
                    <p>Sir Arthur said that he had followed the bill closely and knew the
                        situation.</p>
                    <p>I then said that the Chinese Ambassador had presented a protest—a rather mild
                        one to me, and a stronger one to the Secretary. We had this before us. I
                        said that the ground for this protest was that Chinese seamen ought not to
                        be deported, under these circumstances; and that the real issue was equality
                        of treatment as between Chinese seamen and British seamen, serving on
                        British boats. The actual difference in treatment between the two seemed not
                        to be great; and I wished to inquire whether steps could not be taken
                        quickly to equalize the difference.</p>
                    <p>I said that this seemed to me the only way of avoiding debate on the bill,
                        which probably would consist in airing Chinese grievances against the
                        British, and so forth—which would not be helpful in the general
                        situation.</p>
                    <p>Sir Arthur said that he likewise had been considering the matter. He said
                        that he had an opportunity to approach T. V. Soong<note n="14" xml:id="d715fn14">Chinese Minister for Foreign Affairs, temporarily in
                            the United States.</note> on the matter; and that he proposed to do so
                        in conjunction with Lord Halifax.<note n="15" xml:id="d715fn15">British
                            Ambassador in the United States.</note> He outlined a strictly personal
                        idea as to how the matter might be handled, which, however, he asked me not
                        to record, because he said that it was merely his personal idea and he had
                        not cleared it with his Government.</p>
                    <p>I told him that I thought that the bill would lie in its present stage for
                        ten days or two weeks, but probably not longer than that.</p>
                    <p>Sir Arthur said that he would keep me advised. I told him likewise that I
                        would give him, for his confidential information, a copy of the protest
                        which the Chinese had presented to us. I said that, plainly, we were in
                        between, in a problem chiefly between the British and the Chinese.</p>
                    <p>Sir Arthur said that he realized this. He said, further, that they were
                        concerned about two aspects of the matter. One was that the Chinese were in
                        the position of having broken their contract and then asking for
                        negotiations to revise it. Nevertheless, Sir Arthur was prepared to
                        recommend waiving this feature and entering into negotiations with Soong.
                        The other aspect was that while they were prepared to equate with the
                        Chinese, they did not wish this to be used as forcing the British to equate
                        their pay to the pay of all other United Nations seamen. He said that
                        practically every nation when it came into the war had more or less frozen
                        seamen’s pay. The rates of pay largely reflected the date when the various
                        countries had come into the war; since, between the time when Britain
                        entered the war and the time when the other nations were attacked, their
                        shipping had had the <pb facs="0816" n="806" xml:id="pg_806"/> benefit of
                        very high wartime earnings, which were reflected somewhat in the seamen’s
                        rate. He hoped it would be understood, therefore, that by endeavoring to
                        equate with the Chinese this would not be used as a lever to force them to
                        bring the British wage standard up to the standard of other countries.</p>
                    <p>He explained in some detail the technical difficulties about equating the
                        British pay scale with the Chinese. The Chinese seamen get two months’ bonus
                        at the end of each year; whereas the British do not. The British pay
                        insurance and otherwise pay for their own medical treatment; the Chinese pay
                        no insurance and get free medical treatment. The British pay their expenses
                        while ashore; the Chinese have their expenses paid for them. These, he said,
                        would take more than ten days’ time to work out; but he thought that a
                        method might be worked out which would resolve the present debate.</p>
                    <p>I said I was glad he felt he could tackle it.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A[<hi rend="smallcaps">dolf</hi>] A. B[<hi rend="smallcaps">erle</hi>], <hi rend="smallcaps">Jr.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>