<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="771" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d771">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/7690: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Vincent</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-04-30T12:00:00+07:00">April 30,
                                1943—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received May 1—12:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>629. To Secretary of Treasury from Adler. Reference my TF–115.<note n="17" xml:id="d771fn17">Not printed; it submitted a summary of press comment
                            on schemes for international monetary stabilization.</note> It will be
                        noted that the articles summarized are somewhat vague which is partly due to
                        fact that Ministry of Information has issued instructions for newspapers not
                        to take any definite stand until further notice. Nevertheless, these
                        articles reflect the two dominant and conflicting trends in the Chinese
                        approach to postwar problems, both in the monetary sphere in particular, and
                        the economic in general; namely, a strong and assertive nationalism on the
                        one hand and recognition of the need for external assistance on the other.
                        The trend towards an assertive nationalism receives support from the very
                        highest quarters—I understand that in the draft of the new book the
                        Generalissimo is writing on economic policy he favors high protective
                        tariffs, strict exchange control, et cetera (the article summarized from the
                            <hi rend="italic">China Times</hi> was written by Chu Ping-nan, member
                        of the Generalissimo’s so-called brain trust). There is a sufficient body of
                        realistic opinion in the Government to make it likely, however, that China
                        will cooperate with friendly powers whenever specific questions involving
                        such cooperation arise of which a clear instance is afforded in the
                        discussion reported in TF–114.<note n="17a" xml:id="d771fn18">Telegram No.
                            621, April 29, 5 p.m., from the Chargé in China, <ref target="#pg_850">p. 850</ref>.</note> [Adler.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vincent</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>