<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-05-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="773" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d773">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.50/302</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Vincent</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 1175</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-05-12">May 12,
                            1943</date>.<lb/>[Received May 31.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose two memoranda by
                        Mr. J. Bartlett Richards, Commercial Attaché, as well as a summary of the
                        conclusions reached at a recent forum of college professors and economists,
                        all on the subject of post-war reconstruction.<note n="20" xml:id="d773fn20">None printed.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>This is a subject that has been receiving a good deal of attention in China,
                        officially as well as academically. So far, however, official interest has
                        been confined within the limits of individual ministries and there has been
                        no attempt to formulate a comprehensive and unified project for
                        reconstruction that would embody the ideas of those in charge of
                        agriculture, industry, transportation, social affairs, education, finance
                        etc. it is perhaps natural that individual ministries should desire to
                        formulate their own ideas and reach internal agreement on them before trying
                        to fit them into a comprehensive project. In the case of the Reconstruction
                        Conference recently concluded, to which reference is made in the enclosed
                        memorandum dated May 7, it does not appear that the officials and economists
                        of the Ministry of Economic Affairs and the closely-allied National
                        Resources Commission, who comprised the delegates to the conference, were
                        able to draw up anything very clear or definite in the way of a plan of
                        reconstruction.</p>
                    <p>The National General Mobilization Council is planning to call a comprehensive
                        conference for the first week in June on the more urgent question of
                        increasing wartime production. It is believed <pb facs="0864" n="854" xml:id="pg_854"/> that some attention may also be given to post-war
                        reconstruction projects. The Ministries of Economic Affairs and Agriculture
                        will share in the direction of the Production Conference, as it will be
                        called, and there will be representatives of the Ministries of War, Finance,
                        Communications, Social Affairs, Food, Education, the National Health
                        Administration, the Joint Board of the Four Government Banks, the National
                        Conservancy Commission, the Commission for the Control of Liquid Fuel, the
                        Chungking Municipal Government, the various provincial governments, and
                        industrial and mining organizations as well as experts invited by the
                        government.</p>
                    <p>The Supreme National Defense Council is planning to hold a conference toward
                        the end of May, to discuss a number of major political and administrative
                        questions. It is believed that post-war reconstruction will receive some
                        attention, as one of the principal units of the Council, the Central
                        Planning Board, is preparing a 5-year post-war national defense and economic
                        reconstruction plan and a 10-year plan for the development of the
                        Northwest.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John Carter Vincent</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>