<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Emilio G. Collado of the Division of the American Republics
                    to the Under Secretary of State ( (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1060</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1060</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recR6pcxcU9pXbBvw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002427"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Agricultural production</term>
                    <term ref="recez5uVgqvmr6Nwm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006268"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Irrigation</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rechrPce7erABw7F0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067245"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Interest rate</term>
                    <term ref="rec2qYX3T6ktEaSsg" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85087216"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Moratorium</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="1060"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1060">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">838.51/4119</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Emilio G.
                            Collado</persName> of the Division of the American Republics to the
                        Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-10-11">October 11,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Welles</hi>: M. Dennis came to the Department by
                    appointment originally made with Mr. Duggan and spoke with Messrs. Bursley,<note
                        n="44" xml:id="d1060fn1">Herbert S. Bursley, Assistant Chief of the Division
                        of the American Republics.</note> Barber<note n="45" xml:id="d1060fn2"
                        >Willard F. Barber, of the Division of the American Republics.</note> and
                    Collado. He stated that he had just been appointed Minister of Finance<note
                        n="45a" xml:id="d1060fn3">Fernand Dennis became Haitian Minister for Foreign
                        Affairs and Finance on October 29, 1940.</note> and that he was leaving
                    Washington Monday evening for New York, to sail for Haiti on Thursday. He
                    requested that an appointment be arranged, if possible, with Mr. Welles prior to
                    his departure.</p>
                <p>M. Dennis stated that before leaving he wished to ascertain the status of the
                    items brought up in the memorandum presented to Dr. Berle<note n="46"
                        xml:id="d1060fn4">Adolf A. Berle, Jr., Assistant Secretary of State.</note>
                    at Habana by the Haitian delegation. There followed a brief discussion in which
                    M. Dennis was informed that study of the possibility of revising the trade
                    agreement was moving forward and that the Department had recently requested the
                    Legation at Port-au-Prince to obtain additional information regarding the
                    particular types of a number of products in which Haiti might be interested. M.
                    Dennis was also informed that with respect to coffee financing the problem was
                    being actively considered both in the Inter-American Financial and Economic
                    Advisory Committee as respects a coffee arrangement, and by this Government. Any
                    plan for coffee would be worked out on a general basis rather than with any
                    particular country. M. Dennis indicated that he understood this and merely hoped
                    that the coffee arrangements, both the coffee agreement and a financing plan,
                    could be speedily worked out. With respect to M. Dennis’ inquiry regarding
                    development credits, reference was made to the agreement <pb facs="0928" n="916"
                        xml:id="pg_916"/> recently entered into to continue J. G. White operations
                    in Haiti through the present fiscal year. With respect to the possibility of
                    refunding the Haitian debt at a lower interest yield, M. Dennis was informed
                    that the present situation of the United States money markets was not such as
                    would make such a refunding practicable, and that such operations were not
                    within the scope of the activities of the Export-Import Bank. There followed
                    some discussion of the rate of interest. At the conclusion of the conversation
                    M. Dennis was informed that we would quickly look further into all of the
                    matters which he had brought up and would discuss them with him again Saturday
                    morning.</p>
                <p>The memorandum handed to Dr. Berle brought up six points:</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Development of agricultural production</hi>. The Haitian
                    memorandum speaks of the advisability of irrigation and technical assistance.
                    Irrigation is being provided under the J. G. White contract, and technical
                    assistance is being provided by the loan of Mr. Fennell of the Department of
                    Agriculture.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Public works</hi>. The memorandum speaks of continued public
                    works as being essential. The Export-Import Bank has agreed to continue to
                    finance J. G. White expenditures through the end of the present fiscal year,
                    September 30, 1941.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Modification of the trade agreement with the United
                        States</hi>. This is being actively pushed. The Department on October 8 sent
                    an instruction to Port-au-Prince for additional information regarding a number
                    of the minor commodities mentioned by the Haitians.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Loan for repurchase or conversion of the 1922 debt and
                        reduction of the interest rate on the loan for public works</hi>. The
                    conversion of the 1922 debt in the money market is of course impossible. A loan
                    by the Export-Import Bank to permit the repurchase of this debt might be within
                    the terms of the recent amendment, but in any case would be contrary to the
                    policy of the Bank. I do not believe that the Department should sponsor such a
                    loan. With respect to the present external debt, the Department has already
                    entered into an exchange of notes for a continuation of the moratorium on
                    amortization, this time not even requiring a token payment. We have already
                    approached Mr. Francis White with a hint that a reduction in the rate of
                    interest from 6% to 4% may be essential, and Mr. de la Rue has so stated in a
                    letter to the Council. The matter of this reduction should be pursued at
                    once.</p>
                <p>With respect to the rate of interest on the J. G. White contract, the Haitian
                    memorandum requests a reduction to 3%. The Export-Import Bank has already agreed
                    to reduce the rate of interest to 4% as of July 1. The Bank has sent such a
                    modification of its contract to the J. G. White Corporation which has not yet
                    replied. Mr. Arey told me this morning that he would request an immediate
                    confirmation from the J. G. White Corporation. The Bank meanwhile is accruing
                    interest on its books at the rate of 4%, but no further interest payments are
                    due until January 15, 1941. Mr. de la Rue has been informed of the Bank’s action
                    in the matter. It is not evident from the reports submitted whether Mr. de la
                    Rue has taken this reduction into account in compiling a budget although it is
                    assumed that he has. In <pb facs="0929" n="917" xml:id="pg_917"/> the latter
                    case the Haitian Government must have been informed. In any case there would
                    appear to be no reason why they should not so be informed.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Sugar</hi>. The Haitian Government has requested an increase
                    in the United States import quota on sugar. This is of course impossible.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Coffee</hi>. The question of coffee is only touched on in
                    the Haitian memorandum. As mentioned above, we have informed M. Dennis that the
                    problem is being considered actively, and that the Haitian request for coffee
                    financing, which was made subsequent to the memorandum in question, is being
                    considered in conjunction with the general problem.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
