<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to Diplomatic Officers in the American
                    Republics</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-09-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="11"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d11">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/39a Supplement</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to <gloss
                            type="to">Diplomatic Officers in the American Republics</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-25">September 25,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: Reference is made to the Department’s circular
                    of June 15, 1940 (File no. 810.20 Defense/39A) on the purchase of armament from
                    the United States Government.</p>
                <p>There is enclosed a photostatic copy of a chart<note n="23" xml:id="d11fn1">Not
                        printed; this chart showed that requests would be forwarded from the field
                        to the Department of State, where the requests would be reviewed before
                        being sent on to the Army or Navy.</note> which has been approved by the
                    Secretaries of State, War and of the Navy setting forth schematically the
                    procedure for handling requests made by the American republics of this
                    Government for assistance in the purchase of armament.</p>
                <p>It will be noted that in the future lists for military and naval matériel should
                    be submitted separately, and that these lists should be in quintuplicate in both
                    languages, duly authenticated by the authorities of the government making the
                    request.</p>
                <p>It is believed that the later steps in the procedure after submission of the
                    requests through the Department of State are clearly set forth in the diagram.
                    It is hoped that by submitting copies of future requests to the appropriate
                    officials of the War and Navy Departments at the same time that they are
                    submitted to the Clearance Committee of the Army and Navy Recommendations Board,
                    some time will be saved in obtaining action on these requests.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/>
                <p>For your own confidential information it may be added that an informal committee
                    of the liaison officers of the State, War, and Navy Departments has been
                    constituted which will act as a steering committee in obtaining prompt action on
                    the requests. The functions of this committee do not appear on the chart.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
