<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="1162" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1162">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711F.1914/160</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The American Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Panamanian Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">De Roux</hi></persName>)<note n="11" xml:id="d1162fn1">Copy transmitted to the Department by the
                                Ambassador in Panamá in his despatch No. 804, December 7; received
                                December 11. The substance of paragraphs 4 and 5 was in accordance
                                with instructions sent to the Ambassador by the Acting Secretary of
                                State in telegram No. 172, November 23, 3 p.m. (not printed). The
                                instruction was read and approved by Gen. George C. Marshall, Chief
                                of Staff, United States Army. (711F.1914/157a)</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 427</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Panamá</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-25">November 25, 1940</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my
                            note No. 426 of today regarding the defense problem and negotiations for
                            the leasing from the Republic of Panamá of certain tracts required for
                            defense purposes.</p>
                        <p>As Your Excellency will have observed, it is suggested in my note that
                            the term of occupancy shall be for ninety-nine years.</p>
                        <p>In this connection, I desire to be permitted to explain that General Van
                            Voorhis and I are not unmindful of the circumstance that His Excellency
                            the President proposed in the course of our recent interview that leases
                            be concluded for the term of office of the Panamanian Administration
                            negotiating them. This proposal was communicated to my Government and
                            has received its careful consideration.</p>
                        <p>In directing that a term of 99 years (instead of 999 years as
                            contemplated in the original draft) be suggested, the Department of
                            State points out that the proposal to renew the leases with each
                            succeeding Administration would mean in practice that every four or
                            every six years it would be necessary to reopen the whole matter with
                            new officials who could not be expected to be familiar with what had
                            transpired previouslv. In addition, with short term leases, our
                            authorities would naturally be reluctant to undertake the important work
                            required on certain tracts, such as Río Hato, inasmuch as there would be
                            no definite assurances that the leases would be renewed.</p>
                        <p>I trust that His Excellency the President will appreciate the reasons
                            making longer term leases essential; and I may add that the Department
                            of State calls attention to the fact that, as indicated in my note No.
                            426, it will be expressly stipulated in the leases that the United
                            States will continue to use only such lands as are actually <pb facs="1095" n="1083" xml:id="pg_1083"/> needed for defense purposes
                            and that, irrespective of the term of occupancy, the lands will revert
                            to the Republic of Panamá, whenever they are no longer needed.</p>
                        <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William Dawson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>