<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-07-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="116" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/81<hi rend="superscript">6/12</hi></note>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi></persName>)
                                        <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                            State</gloss></hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 567</seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-07-16">July 16, 1940</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                        July 19.]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                                    the receipt of the Department’s strictly confidential circular
                                    telegram to Chiefs of Mission, dated July 11, 4 p.m.,<note n="37" xml:id="d116fn1"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_19">p. 19</ref>.</note> with reference to
                                    the recent informal conversations undertaken by officers of the
                                    United States Army and Navy in various capitals of the American
                                    Republics.</p>
                                <p>I called on the President of Cuba on July 13, and brought to his
                                    attention the contents of the Department’s telegram under
                                    reference and did not fail to convey to him an expression of the
                                    gratification of our Government that the preliminary
                                    conversations with Cuba and the other American States so fully
                                    conform to the spirit of solidarity existing among the American
                                    States.</p>
                                <p>The President, Dr. Laredo Brú, expressed his appreciation of the
                                    information which my Government had transmitted to him with
                                    respect to these conversations and his gratification that the
                                    conversations had been found in every case successful. He
                                    indicated that the appropriate Cuban authorities would be
                                    prepared to continue the conversations whenever we took the
                                    initiative which, I informed him, would be after the end of the
                                    Habana Conference of Foreign Ministers and most likely early in
                                    August.</p>
                                <p>I asked the President whether he wished me to communicate the
                                    information in this telegram to other officers of the Cuban
                                    Government, and he suggested that I communicate it to Dr. Ramos,
                                    the Secretary of National Defense, and to Secretary of State,
                                    Dr. Campa, and, if I so wished, to Colonel Pedraza, the head of
                                    the Army. As Dr. Ramos happened to be in the Palace at the time
                                    I saw the President, the President called him in and I conveyed
                                    the contents of the telegram under reference to Dr. Ramos in the
                                    presence of the President. It so happened that the Secretary of
                                    State, Dr. Campa, was also in the Palace at the time and I
                                    conveyed to him later the same afternoon the information in this
                                    telegram. All of them expressed <pb facs="0110" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/> themselves as gratified with the results of
                                    the conversations here and elsewhere, and the desire of the
                                    Cuban Government to continue them when we took the
                                    initiative.</p>
                                <p>As Colonel Pedraza, the head of the Cuban Army, had been present
                                    during the conversations which were held with the
                                    representatives of the Army and of the Navy when in Habana, and
                                    as Colonel Pedraza was most helpful in his attitude during these
                                    conversations, I shall, as a matter of courtesy, seek an early
                                    opportunity to convey the contents of the telegram under
                                    reference to him.</p>
                                <p>I did not fail in bringing this telegram to the attention of the
                                    above-mentioned members of the Cuban Government to convey our
                                    desire and hope that the arrangements for, and proceedings of,
                                    these bipartite conversations should be maintained in the
                                    strictest confidence. They assured me that they shared this
                                    desire and that the confidential character of the conversations
                                    would be maintained.</p>
                                <p>I shall, at any time, on the receipt of appropriate instructions
                                    be very glad to facilitate the continuance of these
                                    conversations between the officers of our Army and Navy and the
                                    appropriate officials of the Cuban Government.</p>
                                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">George S.
                                        Messersmitii</hi></signed></closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>