<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Panama ( (Dawson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-11-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="1173"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1173">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">819.00/2090</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 777</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Panama</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-20">November 20,
                            1940</date>.<lb/>[Received November 23.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi> …</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>When I called on the President this morning (after my telephone conversation with
                    Mr. Duggan) I explained briefly my reasons for requesting the audience, adding
                    that the President had no doubt already been apprised of the circumstances by
                    Dr. De Roux. [Here <pb facs="1107" n="1095" xml:id="pg_1095"/> follows account
                    of conversation given in telegram No. 199, November 20, 1 p.m., <hi
                        rend="italic">supra</hi>.]</p>
                <p>Dr. Arias told me that in the preliminary discussion of the draft of the new
                    constitution the question of the recognition of jurisdictional limitations had
                    come up on several occasions, and that it had been held by the jurists who
                    participated in the work that the references to existing treaties found in the
                    original draft covered the situation adequately. He said that some time last
                    week the question had come up for reconsideration and that out of abundant
                    caution and in order to leave no room for doubt it had been decided to
                    incorporate a clause expressly recognizing jurisdictional limitations. He gave
                    me distinctly to understand that the addition of the clause approved yesterday
                    by the Assembly had been decided upon before my interview of November 16 with
                    the Secretary of Foreign Relations.</p>
                <p>In view of this statement, I did not consider it advisable to make any attempt to
                    inquire as to the reasons for the omission of the provision from the original
                    draft. I may point out that the same omission is observed in the draft of a new
                    constitution discussed in 1938 (Page 6 of Mr. Flexer’s despatch No. 491 of
                    September 23, 1938<note n="36" xml:id="d1173fn1">Not printed.</note>). I am
                    inclined to ascribe the omission primarily to the nationalistic tendencies
                    animating the authors of both the 1938 and 1940 drafts. The two projects follow
                    the same general lines and are supposed to represent in the main the aspirations
                    of the Partido Nacional Revolucionario, whose leader was in 1938 and is now Dr.
                    Arnulfo Arias.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William Dawson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
