<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-12-04T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-12-04T15:00:00-05:00" n="229" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d229">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/410:
                                    Telegram</note>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                            State</gloss></hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-12-04T17:00:00-03:00">December 4, 1940—5 p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 8:50
                                        p.m.]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>289. Guani tells me that his talk with Roca<note n="45" xml:id="d229fn1">Julio Roca, Argentine Minister for Foreign
                                        Affairs.</note> will take place probably Monday next,
                                    December 9. He said that he has known Roca for years and that
                                    the talk will be of an informal nature “without documents”.</p>
                                <p>He said that he would seek at the outset to place the
                                    conversation on a “national basis” (his conception is that
                                    Uruguay is entering upon this conversation with Argentina
                                    because of the friendly, good neighborly relations existing
                                    between the two countries, and not because of recognition of any
                                    right on the part of another state to be consulted regarding
                                    Uruguayan action in matters within Uruguayan competence and
                                    sovereignty). With this in mind he would explain what Uruguay
                                    considers it desirable and possible to do as regards
                                    developments of facilities in certain Uruguayan ports, would
                                    discuss Uruguayan practice as regards use of her ports by
                                    belligerent vessels, such as cases in which Uruguay has allowed
                                    British war vessels to stay longer in port than is permissible
                                    under the Hague Convention, et cetera.</p>
                                <p>Having laid the basis for the talks, he would then proceed to
                                    discuss the conversations with United States officers on
                                    continental defense, and the obligations in this field which
                                    Uruguay has assumed as a result of inter-American
                                    agreements.</p>
                                <p>With further reference to “national basis” he remarked that he
                                    was glad that the conversation would take place on Uruguayan
                                    territory.</p>
                                <p>He added that he had various other questions to discuss with
                                    Roca, such as Argentina’s delay in replying to the Uruguayan
                                    draft proposal for a commercial agreement.</p>
                                <p>Guani again said that he wanted to express his regrets for the
                                    publicity given to confidential documents in the Senate and
                                    Chamber debates. He said “There will be no more publicity so far
                                    as I am concerned.”</p>
                                <p>Copy to Buenos Aires.</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi></signed></closer>
                            </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>