<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-07-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-07-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="451" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d451">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">561.333D3/45</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Paul C. Daniels of the Division of
                                the American Republics</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-07-08">July 8, 1940</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Third Pan American Coffee
                                Conference</hi></p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">report on activities from july 4, 1940
                                to july 6, 1940</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">closing date</hi>)</p>
                        <p>In continuation of my report of July 3, 1940, reporting on the activities
                            of the Third Pan American Coffee Conference up to July 3, 1940, there
                            are reported below further developments up to and including July 6,
                            1940, the closing date of the Conference.</p>
                        <p>As indicated in section 8 of the report of July 3, a plenary session of
                            the Coffee Conference was held on July 6 in the offices of the Pan
                            American Coffee Bureau, 120 Wall Street, New York. At this meeting the
                            quota plan of July 2 was discussed and argued at great length. The
                            delegates of a number of the countries stated that the plan was
                            acceptable. Among the remaining delegates, the following reservations or
                            points of view merit specific mention:</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Brazil</hi></p>
                        <p>In accepting the plan, Sr. Penteado said that it should not be for more
                            than one year, and that Brazil felt that its percentage of the United
                            States market should subsequently be increased to 60 per cent from the
                            58 per cent (approximately) participation provided for in the plan. He
                            added that Brazil wished the United States to cooperate effectively in
                            making the plan successful.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Cuba</hi></p>
                        <p>The Cuban delegate, Sr. Alberto Ortega, said that under his instructions
                            he was unable to accept the plan for the reason that the Cuban quota of
                            80,000 bags represented a decrease of 26,000 bags from Cuba’s 1939
                            exports to the United States, while the quotas for many other countries
                            were larger than their 1939 shipments to the United <pb facs="0401" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/> States. He said Cuba wanted last year’s
                            shipments to the United States as a quota.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Nicaragua</hi></p>
                        <p>Nicaragua has consistently sought a quota of not less than 200,000 bags,
                            but will accept the quota of 195,000 bags provided under the plan if all
                            the other governments accept the plan.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Ecuador</hi></p>
                        <p>The delegate had received no instructions, but thought that Ecuador would
                            probably accept the plan.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi></p>
                        <p>No instructions had been received.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></p>
                        <p>No instructions had been received.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Puerto Rico</hi></p>
                        <p>Puerto Rico expressed no views on the plan, considering that it was a
                            question to be determined by the other delegates since Puerto Rico is
                            within the customs territory of the United States and therefore the
                            quota plan does not apply to it.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Venezuela</hi></p>
                        <p>The Venezuelan delegate was not present at this meeting of July 6.</p>
                        <p>After a lengthy exchange of views among the delegates, a resolution was
                            introduced reading as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Third Pan American Coffee Conference</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Resolves</hi></p>
                                <p>“To ratify in all its parts Resolution No. 7<note n="7" xml:id="d451fn1"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>
                                    approved at the plenary session on July 2, 1940, which
                                    establishes a system of export quotas for the United States, and
                                    to charge the Pan American Coffee Bureau with its regulation and
                                    execution.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Two difficulties arose in connection with the foregoing draft resolution.
                            In the first place, since some of the delegates lacked instructions, it
                            was deemed necessary to insert the phrase “ad referendum” after the word
                            “ratify”. In the second place, the Brazilian delegate insisted that the
                            resolution contain some indication that the Government of the United
                            States would be involved in the execution of the plan. However, the
                            Colombian delegates (Sr. Manuel Mejía and Dr. Rafael Parga) said that
                            they had no instructions to agree to any plan <pb facs="0402" n="390" xml:id="pg_390"/> contemplating Governmental intervention. After a
                            lengthy discussion of this point, the resolution was amended to read as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Third Pan American Coffee Conference</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Resolves</hi></p>
                                <p>“To ratify <hi rend="italic">ad referendum</hi> in all its parts
                                    Resolution No. 7 approved at the plenary session on July 2,
                                    1940, which establishes a system of export quotas for the United
                                    States, and to charge the Pan American Coffee Bureau with its
                                    regulation and with establishing contacts with all the
                                    interested governments or entities to obtain their approval and
                                    execution.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>The Brazilian delegate approved the resolution in that form, with the
                            expressed understanding that the United States Government was an
                            “interested” Government and that therefore the Pan American Coffee
                            Bureau would establish contact with it to obtain its approval and
                            cooperation in executing the plan.</p>
                        <p>On the other hand, because of the reference to “government” contained in
                            the resolution, the Colombian delegation refrained from voting on it.
                            Sr. Mejía stated, however, that he would consult his principals in
                            Bogotá with a view to seeing if the resolution could be accepted by
                            Colombia in its present form.</p>
                        <p>The other delegates approved the resolution, with the exception of Cuba,
                            which abstained from voting for the same reason set forth above. It was
                            agreed that the Pan American Coffee Bureau would continue discussing the
                            matter during the coming week, and Sr. Aguilar told me that the Pan
                            American Coffee Bureau would thereupon get in touch with the State
                            Department.</p>
                        <p>Before the Conference adjourned a number of other resolutions were
                            passed, covering the following subjects: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Requesting increased contributions from the producing
                                    countries to the Pan American Coffee Bureau for advertising and
                                    propaganda;</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Requesting the Pan American Coffee Bureau to establish contact
                                    with the interested governments and to inform them of the
                                    results of the Conference;</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Charging the Pan American Coffee Bureau with continuing its
                                    efforts, through the Inter-American Financial and Economic
                                    Advisory Committee in Washington, to bring about a restriction
                                    on the imports into the United States of coffees of inferior
                                    quality;</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Expressing thanks to the Associated Coffee Industries of
                                    America and other representatives of the trade for their
                                    cooperation; and</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Expressing appreciation for the sympathetic attitude of the
                                    United States Government towards the Conference.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>After the adjournment of the meeting on July 6 and the closing of the
                            Conference, I discussed in further detail with Sr. Mejía and Dr. <pb facs="0403" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/> Parga the question of the
                            Colombian attitude regarding cooperation by the United States Government
                            in making the quota plan effective. Following this discussion Sr. Mejía
                            indicated that he would explore further the possibility of an
                            international agreement on coffee to which the United States would be a
                            party, such agreement to be of an emergency character (possibly for the
                            duration of the war) and subject to termination on suitable advance
                            notice whenever any participating government desires to withdraw. When I
                            last left Sr. Mejía on July 6 he seemed to think that some such formula
                            might be acceptable, and said the matter would be examined very
                            carefully. Dr. Parga, who plans to return to Bogotá on July 11, seemed
                            the more doubtful of the two.</p>
                        <p>Sr. Mejía said that he planned to remain in New York so long as there was
                            any chance of an agreement being reached.</p>
                        <p>Since the Pan American Coffee Bureau, 120 Wall Street, New York, has been
                            charged by the Conference with further activities in connection with the
                            proposed quota plan, further information on the general subject can
                            doubtless be obtained from that source. At the same time, as indicated
                            above, Sr. Aguilar of the Coffee Bureau told me that he planned to
                            communicate with the Department in the course of the next week, and
                            would be prepared to come to Washington if necessary.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>