<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in the United Kingdom (
                    (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d468</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">468</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-12-06T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-12-06T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-12-06T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-12-06T20:00:00-05:00" n="468"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d468">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">561.333D3/262: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-12-06T20:00:00-05:00"
                            >December 6, 1940—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>For Achilles.<note n="18" xml:id="d468fn1">Theodore C. Achilles, Chargé
                        d’Affaires near the Governments of Poland, Belgium, Norway, and the
                        Netherlands, established in the United Kingdom.</note> Netherlands Series
                    No. 9. Please discuss the following immediately with the Netherlands
                    authorities:</p>
                <p>Under the terms of the Inter-American Coffee Agreement signed here on November 28
                    by representatives of the United States and <pb facs="0418" n="406"
                        xml:id="pg_406"/> 14 other American Republics (see Radio Bulletin 283), this
                    Government undertakes to limit imports for consumption of coffee from countries
                    not participating in the agreement to a basic annual quota of 355,000 bags of 60
                    kilograms in any quota year beginning October 1. Coffee entered subsequent to
                    October 1, 1940 will be charged against the first year’s quota. The figure of
                    355,000 bags is larger than the average imports, approximately 338,000 bags,
                    supplied by non-participating countries in the 2-year period preceding October
                    1, 1940.</p>
                <p>If this Government allocates the 355,000 bag quota among non-participating
                    countries, the share for the Netherlands (including colonies) would be
                    approximately 68,000 bags, that for the United Kingdom (including colonies)
                    160,000 bags, and the share for all other countries, 127,000 bags. These figures
                    are based on the percentage shares supplied in the 2-year period preceding
                    October 1, 1940, which are 19, 45, and 36 percent respectively.</p>
                <p>Members of the Netherlands Legation, shortly before the signature of the Coffee
                    Agreement, expressed concern to the Department regarding the size of the quota
                    for non-participating countries, indicating a desire for an increase in view of
                    their colonial coffee situation. Although no action can be taken to increase the
                    basic total quota of 355,000 bags for non-participants in relation to the share
                    for participating countries, Netherlands colonial coffee producers could compete
                    for that entire quota, if allocations were not made to individual
                    nonparticipating countries.</p>
                <p>It is the Department’s belief that Netherlands coffee producers could probably
                    market more coffee in this country if the quota for nonparticipants were not
                    allocated, particularly in view of possible shipping difficulties affecting
                    other non-participants.</p>
                <p>Under the circumstances, it is believed that the Netherlands Government, in
                    accordance with the provisions of paragraph 7 of Article VI of the trade
                    agreement with the Netherlands,<note n="19" xml:id="d468fn2">Signed at
                        Washington, December 20, 1935; for text, see Executive Agreement Series No.
                        100, or 50 Stat. 1504; see also <ref target="frus1935v02#pg_579">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 579</ref> ff.</note> will agree to
                    dispense with an allocation of the coffee quota. Please request a written
                    expression of such agreement from the appropriate officials.</p>
                <p>Please expedite this matter as much as possible and inform the Department of the
                    results by telegraph.</p>
                <p>For administrative and other reasons the Department would prefer not to make
                    specific allocations to non-participating countries.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
