<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on International Economic Affairs
                    ( (Feis) ) and the Assistant Adviser on International Economic Affairs (
                    (Livesey))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d679</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">679</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-03-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-03-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="679"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d679">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.51/1777</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on International
                        Economic Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Feis</hi>) <hi rend="italic">and
                        the Assistant Adviser on International Economic Affairs</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Livesey</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-03-05">March 5,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Francis White, President, Foreign Bondholders
                            Protective Council, Inc.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">The Secretary of State</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Assistant Secretary Berle</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Feis</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Livesey</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Briggs</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Collado<note n="19" xml:id="d679fn1">Emilio
                                G. Collado, of the Division of the American Republics.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The circumstances of Mr. White’s seeking an interview with the Secretary are
                    stated in other memoranda.</p>
                <p>Mr. White, starting from the circumstances under which the original Niemeyer
                    proposal of about October 1933<note n="20" xml:id="d679fn2">Apparently plan
                        proposed by the Brazilian Government for adjustment of the national, state,
                        and municipal debts after consultation with Sir Otto Niemeyer of the Bank of
                        England. See telegram No. 82, September 16, 1933, 5 p.m., and despatch No.
                        58, September 27, 1933, from the Ambassador in Brazil, <ref
                            target="frus1933v05#pg_75">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1933, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 75</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1933v05#pg_76">76</ref>, respectively.</note> had been
                    discussed <pb facs="0597" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/> by Mr. Reuben Clark at Rio
                    de Janeiro in January 1934<note n="21" xml:id="d679fn3">See <ref
                            target="frus1934v04#pg_602">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1934, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 602</ref> ff.</note> and qualified
                    somewhat to the advantage of various American bond issues before it was issued
                    as the Aranha Plan of 1934, expounded the unsatisfactory allocation of funds as
                    between the sterling and dollar issues, and notably the treatment given the São
                    Paulo Coffee Realization Loan, as the reasons why the Council could not
                    recommend the present Aranha proposal.</p>
                <p>Mr. Berle and Mr. Feis reminded Mr. White that it was not at present a question
                    of the Council recommending the proposal. The Brazilian Government had been
                    giving serious study to the possibility of making a four-year offer to the
                    holders of its external bonds; the Council, though the suggestion had been put
                    before it by the Department,<note n="22" xml:id="d679fn4">This suggestion was
                        presented to Mr. White by Mr. Feis in a conversation at New York on December
                        30, 1939. Memorandum of conversation dated January 2, 1940, not
                        printed.</note> had no one present in Brazil to represent the bondholders—a
                    fact which Mr. White explained on the score of the limited resources of the
                    Council; the American Ambassador therefore had been endeavoring in discussion
                    with the Brazilian authorities to secure for the American bondholders as
                    favorable terms as it was possible to secure. In these endeavors the Department
                    and the Ambassador had been moved by concern for the interests of the
                    bondholders, who had not received payment for some years, and by the fact that
                    the longer the debt remained in complete default the dimmer the prospect of
                    resumption of payment might become; the Ambassador had reported to the
                    Department three times in the past week that he felt he had achieved everything
                    that was possible at the present time in the way of improving the terms of
                    settlement. He had conveyed to the Department several times the statement of
                    Aranha that he hoped that the Brazilian offer would not be opposed by the
                    Council, and that he would not go forward with any offer if the Council were
                    going to make adverse comment; the situation thus created was that the Council
                    had the choice of refraining from adverse statement or of assuming the
                    responsibility of preventing any offer being made at the present time, in which
                    event, according to the opinion of Ambassador Caffery, the whole matter of
                    resumption of payment might be deferred until after the end of the war. The
                    Department’s own judgment of the best course for the bondholders was that their
                    best interests would be served if the offer could be placed before the
                    bondholders; of course there was no way of being sure that this would in fact
                    prove to be the best course for the bondholders but the Council would obviously
                    be assuming a heavy responsibility if it should veto a proposal <pb facs="0598"
                        n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/> to make payments in the amount of about
                    twenty-five million dollars to American bondholders over the next four
                    years.</p>
                <p>Mr. White went into a very long and critical analysis of the offer both on the
                    score of the total amounts to be paid and on the distribution of the amounts as
                    between the different grades of bonds. His criticism, however, centered chiefly
                    on the fact that certain preferences, which he deemed unjustified, established
                    in the Aranha Plan of 1934, would be retained in this offer, and in his judgment
                    they represented much more favorable treatment to the holders of sterling bonds
                    than to the holders of dollar bonds. (The Brazilian Government had transmitted
                    through Mr. Caffery its estimates that the percentage of total payments going to
                    the holders of dollar bonds was greater by several percent than the proportion
                    of the total bonds which are dollar bonds; this is probably roughly correct as
                    to proportions based on principal amounts; however, the Council takes as its
                    basis of criticism not percentages of principal but percentages of contractual
                    service, and on this basis the amounts paid on the dollar bonds are several
                    percent less than their proportion of service on the original bond contracts.)
                    Mr. White went on to present the situation as one in which the Council had a
                    trustee relationship to the bondholders and to interpret the Department’s
                    presentation as a request to the Council to refrain from disclosure of pertinent
                    facts. In various forms he gave the impression of a belief that the Council’s
                    duty to the bondholders lay in denouncing the offer, and that requests were
                    being made of him to neglect that duty. This made it necessary repeatedly to
                    make counter-assertions and clarifications to the effect that the question
                    before the Council was simple. The Brazilian Government stated it would make an
                    offer to the bondholders on condition that the Council would not comment
                    adversely upon it. Our Ambassador reported that this was the best offer
                    obtainable at the moment. It would represent a payment to American bondholders
                    of a total amount of about twenty-five million dollars over four years. The
                    question, emanating from Mr. Aranha, therefore, was whether the Council would
                    veto Mr. Aranha’s proposal for such payments by taking the position that it must
                    make an adverse statement if the proposal were made. Mr. White never squarely
                    met that simple question. He tried repeatedly to treat the matter as a request
                    from the Department that the Council refrain from disclosing facts, or to elicit
                    a request from the Department. Thus he suggested that if the Department, which
                    is concerned with national policy, should request the Council, which is
                    concerned solely with bondholders’ interests, to take action or to refrain from
                    action because of considerations of national policy, the Council would
                    cheerfully comply, since it never wishes to oppose the national policies of the
                    Government.</p>
                <pb facs="0599" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/>
                <p>Finally the Secretary of State pointed out to Mr. White that the Government’s
                    interest in our bondholders was as great as that of the Council and similar to
                    that of the Council. Both should be moved by the same desire to work things out
                    to the best interest of the bondholders. Our steady purpose along this line was
                    shown by our activity in a score of situations in which the Department had
                    backed the Council and extended every effort to assist the Council’s endeavor.
                    Therefore it seemed to him that we were all working for the same purpose and
                    what the situation called for was the best cooperative efforts of all in the
                    interests of the bondholders and not for a sharp dispute and long discussion
                    among ourselves as to the respective duties and endeavors of the Council and of
                    the Department. It was not a question as to loyalty to bondholders but as to how
                    to make the Council’s loyalty to bondholders effective.</p>
                <p>Mr. White agreed with these general ideas without, however, substantially
                    modifying his position. Finally—it then being after six o’clock and Mr. White
                    having stated that he had to catch a seven o’clock train to New York, the
                    Secretary suggested that the situation might be met if the Council would merely
                    limit itself to a statement that it was putting before the bondholders an offer
                    of the Brazilian Government transmitted through the Department of State. The
                    suggestion was agreed to by Mr. White, who said he would bring it before his
                    Executive Committee in a meeting the following day.</p>
                <p>After the meeting had left the Secretary’s office, Mr. White in Mr. Briggs’
                    office drafted the following statement as embodying Secretary Hull’s suggestion,
                    and as the statement which he would submit to the Executive Committee: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Without passing in any way on the merits of the Brazilian proposal,
                            which was not negotiated by it, the Council limits its comment on the
                            proposal of the Brazilian Government, received through the Department of
                            State, to the remark that negotiation at present would seem to hold no
                            favorable prospect of obtaining any better offer. The Council must leave
                            it to the bondholders to determine whether or not they will accept what
                            is now offered.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>During the meeting with the Secretary, Mr. White at one time had suggested that
                    the Council might refrain from making a public statement but might circularize
                    bondholders transmitting the Brazilian proposal, commenting thereon in these
                    letters of transmittal and in ensuing correspondence with bondholders. In
                    discussion of this, however, it was brought out that such letters to bondholders
                    would inevitably come to the attention of the press and be reported in the press
                    and that the result would hardly be different from that of a public
                    statement.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
