<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-02-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="808" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d808">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.2531/665</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. H. Gerald Smith
                                of the Division of Trade Agreements</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-02-23">February 23, 1940</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Señor Gazitúa called again at the Department to continue the discussion
                            of the general provisions of the proposed trade agreement.</p>
                        <p>Resuming consideration at Article XI, it was agreed for the present to
                            pass over the differences between the Chilean and United States
                            proposals, in as much as it might not be necessary to include the
                            Article in the agreement. All the products on which the United States
                            had requested concessions of Chile are dutiable on a specific basis and
                            only one Chilean product included in the United States offers is
                            dutiable upon an ad valorem basis. If the Chilean Government did not
                            particularly desire the inclusion of the Article, the possibility
                            existed of eliminating it from the provisions.</p>
                        <p>With regard to Article XII on quotas on products included in the two
                            schedules, no comment in addition to that made by Mr. Fowler appeared
                            necessary, in as much as there had been an erroneous idea in the minds
                            of the Chilean Treaty Commission regarding the schedules referred to in
                            the Article.</p>
                        <p>Article XIII required no comment.</p>
                        <p>Regarding Article XIV, it was indicated to Señor Gazitúa that this
                            Government would probably agree to the inclusion of an escape clause, as
                            requested by the Chilean Government, although this was one of the points
                            which would have to be taken up with the Trade Agreements Committee.</p>
                        <pb facs="0691" n="679" xml:id="pg_679"/>
                        <p>On Article XV no particular comment was necessary, except that the same
                            question arose here as in certain other Articles, with respect to the
                            use in the Chilean draft of the words “natural or fabricated products,
                            originating in and coming from” as compared with the language in the
                            United States draft “articles the growth, produce or manufacture …,<note n="16" xml:id="d808fn1">Omission indicated in the original
                                memorandum.</note> imported from or exported to”.</p>
                        <p>With respect to Article XVI, on exceptions to most-favored-nation
                            treatment, the comments made in Mr. Fowler’s memorandum were pointed out
                            to Señor Gazitúa who was requested to indicate the reasons for the
                            position taken by the Chilean Government in requesting that trade with
                            contiguous countries be excepted from the provisions for
                            most-favored-nation treatment. He indicated that there were three
                            principal points: (1) the question of geographic proximity; (2) as an
                            offset for the Cuban exception on the part of the United States; (3) the
                            fact that in the Finnish and Swedish trade agreements,<note n="17" xml:id="d808fn2">50 Stat. (pt. 2) 1436, and 49 Stat. (pt. 2) 3755,
                                respectively.</note> the United States had permitted exceptions in
                            the case of trade between those countries and neighboring nations.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Gazitúa also pointed out as a practical matter that the exceptions
                            for Argentina, Bolivia and Peru which were desired by Chile would have
                            no actual significance in view of the fact that Chile had a number of
                            trade agreements or treaties at the present time with various countries
                            which did not provide for those exceptions. Señor Gazitúa agreed to
                            present our point of view once more to his Government and at the same
                            time he was informed that the proposal of the Chilean Government would
                            be brought to the attention of the Trade Agreements Committee.</p>
                        <p>Regarding Article XVII, it was mentioned to Señor Gazitúa that it was
                            believed that Mr. Fowler’s memorandum contained all the comments that
                            were necessary on the Chilean draft. Señor Gazitúa expressed a desire to
                            have a brief memorandum on the scope of the “constitutional limitations
                            on the authority of the Federal Government” in the case of the United
                            States and it was agreed that he would be provided with such a
                            memorandum.</p>
                        <p>On Article XVIII it was pointed out that although the second Paragraph of
                            the United States draft did not appear to be absolutely necessary, this
                            Government believed that its inclusion would be desirable.</p>
                        <p>There was no discussion of Articles XIX or XX in view of the fact that
                            these Articles might be considered more or less “open” until such time
                            as a definite agreement had been reached on other and more important
                            Articles of the agreement.</p>
                        <pb facs="0692" n="680" xml:id="pg_680"/>
                        <p>Señor Gazitúa stated that he would prepare a report for submission to his
                            Government on the basis of the present conversations and it was agreed
                            that we would have another meeting within a few days.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>