<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-01-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="875" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d875">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/8632</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Beaulac</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 2692</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-01-11">January 11, 1940</date>.<lb/>[Received January
                                12.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Supplementing my despatch No. 2689, of
                            January 10, 1940,<note n="3" xml:id="d875fn1">Not printed.</note> I have
                            the honor to report that the Senate last night approved the del Pozo
                            bill to postpone general elections from February 28 to March 28.
                            However, so much time has elapsed and so much remains to be done before
                            the Constituent Assembly can really begin to function (the coalition
                            forces continue to contest the elections in several provinces, and
                            considerable mechanical preparations will have to be made) that it is
                            now believed that the suggested date does not represent a sufficient
                            postponement.</p>
                        <p>President Laredo Brú’s suggested solution of the impasse created by the
                            controversy over the date of general elections and the terms of present
                            members of Congress is as follows: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>General elections will be postponed until May or June; and he
                                    will consent, if asked by both parties, to the extension of his
                                    term of office for a few weeks, provided that be
                                    necessary.</item>
                                <pb facs="0751" n="739" xml:id="pg_739"/>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The constitution will be drafted freely by the Constituent
                                    Assembly, which will not resort to any device to eliminate
                                    Colonel Batista as a candidate.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>If the Constituent Assembly decides that the structure of the
                                    present Congress shall be changed, a separate column will be
                                    inserted in the ballots at the general elections in which the
                                    voters will have the opportunity to say whether or not they wish
                                    the terms of the longperiod Senators and Congressmen cut down.
                                    If the vote is affirmative, the terms of these members of
                                    Congress will expire when the present Government goes out of
                                    office, and the new Congress will be composed entirely of newly
                                    elected members. If the vote is negative, the longperiod members
                                    of Congress will remain in the Congress, as additional members,
                                    until their terms expire. Any present member of Congress, of
                                    course, is free to become a candidate in the general
                                    elections.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The Department will have noted that the coalition, which originally
                            supported the idea of such a plebiscite, has now taken the position that
                            it is no longer a possibility because the opposition has turned it down.
                            The opposition, on the other hand, states that it not only has not
                            turned down the suggestion, but that it has never been officially
                            advanced by the coalition.</p>
                        <p>The truth appears to be that the coalition favored the idea of a
                            plebiscite until the opposition gave indications that it would agree to
                            it. At this point the coalition backed down and is now endeavoring to
                            place the onus for the failure of the plan upon the opposition, which,
                            however, declines to accept it.</p>
                        <p>It is reported on excellent authority that Colonel Batista, himself, is
                            responsible for the present attitude of the coalition in this respect,
                            and that he was persuaded to take this attitude principally by Senators
                                Casanova<note n="4" xml:id="d875fn2">José Manuel Casanova, member of
                                the Liberal Party.</note> and Hornedo.<note n="5" xml:id="d875fn3">Alfredo Hornedo, president of the Liberal Party.</note> It is
                            reported that Colonel Batista is fully prepared to insist on his
                            attitude and to prolong the present impasse indefinitely.</p>
                        <p>In contradiction to the attitude assumed by the coalition, the President
                            takes the point of view that the matter of the plebiscite has not yet
                            definitely been turned down, and he has expressed his intention to
                            continue his efforts at mediation. He is reliably reported to have said
                            that, rather than consent to continue indefinitely in the present
                            situation, he will resign his office. The possible effect upon the Cuban
                            situation of such a development is not difficult to conjecture. A
                            condition would be created in which Colonel Batista, with the Army
                            behind him, would be greatly tempted to impose himself upon the country
                            by force. If this occurred, it is almost certain that some effort at
                            reprisal would be made, and it is possible that the country would drift
                                <pb facs="0752" n="740" xml:id="pg_740"/> into a situation
                            resembling—in some measure, at least—that which pertained prior to the
                            downfall of President Machado.<note n="6" xml:id="d875fn4">August 12,
                                1933; for correspondence, see <ref target="frus1933v05#pg_270"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1933, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 270</ref>–<ref target="frus1933v05#pg_361">361</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>In this connection, Ambassador Martínez Fraga is being quoted as having
                            said that he participated in a conference in Washington between the
                            Under Secretary of State, Mr. Welles, the Assistant Secretary of State,
                            Mr. Messersmith, and Senator Zaydín,<note n="7" xml:id="d875fn5">Ramon
                                Zaydín, member of <hi rend="italic">Acción Republicana.</hi></note>
                            in which the possible effect upon Cuba’s future relations with the
                            United States of a failure to solve Cuba’s problems was pointed
                                out.<note n="8" xml:id="d875fn6">No record of conference was found
                                in Department files.</note> Ambassador Martínez Fraga is quoted also
                            as having said that he had an interview with President Roosevelt before
                            returning to Habana, in which the latter made it clear that unless the
                            revolutionary cycle which began with the downfall of Machado was
                            completed at this time in a satisfactory and legal manner, the
                            Government of the United States would not be in a position to defend
                            Cuba when sugar legislation should be under discussion in the American
                            Congress. It is believed that these reports have impressed President
                            Laredo Brú, who continues to be the most powerful factor working toward
                            an adequate solution of the present very unsatisfactory situation.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Willard L.
                            Beaulac</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>