<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to Diplomatic and Consular Officers in the American
                    Republics</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="9"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/39a</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to <gloss
                            type="to">Diplomatic and Consular Officers in the American
                            Republics</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-06-15">June 15,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: The President approved on June 15, 1940, a joint
                    resolution to authorize the Secretaries of War and of the Navy to assist the
                    Governments of the American Republics to increase their military and naval
                    establishments, and for other purposes. The text of the joint resolution is as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>[Here follows text of joint resolution printed in 54 Stat. 396.]</p>
                <p>The Department desires that, so far as possible, all negotiations between this
                    Government and the Government of any American Republic desiring to avail itself
                    of the facilities offered by this Joint Resolution be conducted in Washington
                    between the diplomatic or other authorized representatives of the American
                    Republic and the appropriate authorities of this Government. Since the ultimate
                    decision must of necessity rest with our War or Navy Department, it is obviously
                    preferable that negotiations of this character be carried on directly with those
                    Departments. Should the Government to which you are accredited, therefore,
                    approach you with a view to opening such negotiations, you are requested to
                    recommend, after answering as fully as possible inquiries in regard to the scope
                    and purport of the law, that an authorized representative of that Government in
                    Washington be authorized to carry on the necessary conversations there. These
                    should be initiated with the Department of State, which will arrange for the
                    representatives of the American Republic to confer with appropriate officials of
                    the War and Navy Departments.</p>
                <pb facs="0024" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/>
                <p>Should circumstances arise, however, which in your judgment render it desirable
                    that a particular inquiry from the Government to which you are accredited be
                    transmitted through you, you are authorized to forward the inquiry to the
                    Department. That provision of the Department’s Circular Instruction of November
                    21, 1935<note n="21" xml:id="d9fn1">
                        <ref target="frus1935v01#pg_354">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 354</ref>.</note> which states that
                    American diplomatic and consular officers should decline to use official
                    channels for the communication of inquiries or offers between prospective
                    purchasers and sellers is hereby modified to exempt from its scope inquiries
                    from the Government of an American Republic relating to a purchase authorized by
                    this Joint Resolution. The remaining provisions of the Circular Instruction
                    shall continue in effect and American diplomatic and consular officers shall,
                    while responding in every proper way to requests for assistance and information
                    originating with the Government to which they are accredited, continue to
                    refrain from attempting to create trade opportunities for arms, ammunition, and
                    implements of war of United States origin and from undertaking on their own
                    initiative to expand the sales of such articles.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
