<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Ecuador ( (Long))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d990</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">990</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recA365XAlFrgaB1r" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft Convention</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86005172"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific research</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recOzoeUb5OaUz29X" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Laboratory</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="990"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d990">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">822.623/25</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Ecuador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Long</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 313</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-08-26">August 26,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: There is enclosed a copy of the “Draft Convention
                    and Report of the Governing Board of the Pan American Union on Nature Protection
                    and Wild Life Preservation in the American Republics”, published by the Pan
                    American Union in June 1940. The report of the Committee of Experts contained
                    therein was approved by the Governing Board of the Pan American Union at its
                    meeting on June 5, 1940, and the Governing Board decided to have the convention
                    opened for signature at the Pan American Union on October 12, 1940.<note n="32"
                        xml:id="d990fn1">For test of convention signed at Washington, October 12,
                        1940, see Department of State Treaty Series No. 981, or 56 Stat. (pt. 2)
                        1354.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0866" n="854" xml:id="pg_854"/>
                <p>The draft convention has aroused interest among scientists and scientific
                    institutions in this country as offering a basis for cooperative action among
                    the American Republics in taking practical measures for the preservation of wild
                    life in the western hemisphere. Among the species of animal life of particular
                    interest to scientists are those which are found on the Galápagos Islands. It
                    appears that many of the animal species found on these islands are unique in
                    that they exist nowhere else in the world, and that their extinction would be an
                    irreparable loss to science. Among the interesting fauna now found on the
                    islands mention may be made of the tortoises, land iguanas, marine iguanas, sea
                    lions, Galápagos finches, mocking birds, doves, Galápagos hawks, owls,
                    albatrosses, flamingos, and the Galápagos ducks.</p>
                <p>In view of the rarity of these and other species found on the Galápagos Islands
                    the Smithsonian Institution has manifested an interest in conducting further
                    research with regard thereto, and has expressed a desire to cooperate with the
                    appropriate authorities of the Ecuadoran Government in pursuing this important
                    scientific research. If the Government of Ecuador is agreeable to this proposal,
                    the Smithsonian Institution on its part would be prepared to finance the
                    establishment of a small scientific laboratory on the Galápagos Islands, to
                    acquire and maintain there proper laboratory equipment and supplies, and to
                    assign to this work two or three scientists and laboratory assistants at its own
                    expense.</p>
                <p>Please inquire of the appropriate authorities of the Ecuadoran Government if a
                    cooperative undertaking of this character would be of interest to it, and
                    whether it would be prepared to accord facilities in order that the project
                    might be carried out successfully. If the proposal is agreeable in principle to
                    the Ecuadoran Government, the Department will gladly assist in working out
                    further details between the Ecuadoran Government and the Smithsonian
                    Institution.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>A. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Berle, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
