<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-02-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="106" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                        <head>106. Memorandum From the Secretary of Defense’s Deputy Assistant for
                            Special Operations (<persName corresp="#p_LCEG1" type="from">Lansdale</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                            International Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_IJNII1" type="to">Irwin</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d106fn1">Source:
                                Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 63 A 1803:
                                Lansdale Papers, Vietnam Correspondence 1960. Confidential.
                                Sensitive.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-02-19"><hi rend="italic">February 19,
                                    1960</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Counter-Guerrilla Training, Vietnam</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In State message from Saigon, 2446, of 18 February,<note n="2" xml:id="d106fn2"><ref target="#d105"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DE1">Durbrow</persName> strongly recommends that U.S. Army Special
                            Forces be assigned to <gloss target="#t_USARMA1">USARMA</gloss>, Saigon,
                            to give “anti-guerrilla” training to the Vietnamese Civil Guard. He
                            indicates that the Vietnamese Government is agreeable to this extension
                            of <gloss target="#t_USARMA1">USARMA</gloss> activities and regards this
                            type of training as an urgent need.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> concurs in this recommendation. While
                            this is an action for <gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss>, it does touch
                            upon matters of concern to <gloss target="#t_OSO1">OSO</gloss> and we
                            will be happy to assist you in this as fully as desired. We believe this
                            is a real opportunity to assist the Vietnamese meet a Communist threat
                            and to gain valuable experience in a type of warfare which is still
                            too-little understood by Americans.</p>
                        <p>As a foot-note to this memo, it might help if my use of
                            “counter-guerrilla” instead of “anti-guerrilla” is explained.
                            “Anti-guerrilla” has come to mean operations which protect rear areas
                            from guerrilla harassment during combat against regular forces; thus,
                            there is emphasis on how to get truck convoys through ambushes and
                            simple punitive actions. “Counter-guerrilla’, in my opinion, more
                            accurately expresses operations against an enemy force which is entirely
                                <pb facs="0319" n="289" xml:id="pg_289"/> guerrilla, and who
                            combines political subversion with his paramilitary actions. This enemy
                            is “everywhere”, not just in the rear areas. This is the type of warfare
                            we need to understand more thoroughly than we do today.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>