<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-03-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-03-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="122" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d122">
                        <head>122. Memorandum From the Chief of Staff, United States Army (<persName corresp="#p_LGLL1" type="from">Lemnitzer</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d122fn1">Source: National Archives and Records Service,
                                    <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Records, <gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> 99, 9155.3/4060 (15 Feb 60).
                                Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1992/791 <lb/>
                                <gloss target="#t_CSAM1">CSAM</gloss> 103–60</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-03-24"><hi rend="italic">March 24,
                                1960</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">ANTI-GUERRILLA TRAINING FOR VIETNAM (U)</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>I have noted in messages that the security situation in South
                                Vietnam has deteriorated markedly during the last few months. The
                                North Vietnamese-controlled Communist dissidents have extended their
                                reign of terror in the rural areas and have shown an increased
                                capability to mount raids and ambushes against selected targets near
                                the capital. The boldness and frequency with which the dissidents
                                have been operating clearly indicate that their capability has been
                                reinforced with additional cadres and possibly materiel from North
                                Vietnam by land and sea. Communist dissidents, numbering no less
                                than 3,000, have demonstrated an increased capability to mount
                                attacks, raids, ambushes, and other terrorist incidents in southern
                                and central South Vietnam. Such actions plus intimidation of local
                                villagers have caused rural populations to lose confidence in their
                                Government, and will, unless checked, cause the nation’s stability
                                to deteriorate even more rapidly.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>President <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> of Vietnam
                                considers his country engaged in an all-out guerrilla war with the
                                Viet Cong which will last a long time and has requested<note n="2" xml:id="d122fn2">U.S. Embassy Saigon message to Secretary of
                                    State, No. 2622, dated 10 March 1960; on file in Joint
                                    Secretariat. [Footnote in the source text. <ref target="#d114">Document 114</ref>.]</note> additional assistance in both
                                matériel and training. To achieve over-all U.S. objectives in South
                                Vietnam, it is considered necessary that the U.S. render timely and
                                reasonable support.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>In order to reduce and eventually to eliminate the terrorist
                                activities of the Viet Cong, the populace of South Vietnam must be
                                physically and psychologically separated from the terrorists and
                                then the terrorists must be ruthlessly hunted down. These actions
                                require a coordinated effort by the Vietnamese in the fields of
                                psychological warfare, civil affairs, intelligence and
                                counter-intelligence, and counter-guerrilla military operations by
                                the armed forces, Civil Guard and police.</item>
                            <pb facs="0376" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> feels<note n="3" xml:id="d122fn3"><gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>
                                    message to Office of the Secretary of Defense (and info
                                    addressees), <gloss target="#t_DTG1">DTG</gloss> 142355Z March
                                    1960 (<gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss> IN 43393); on file in
                                    Joint Secretariat. [Footnote in the source text. <ref target="#d115">Document 115</ref>.]</note> that an
                                anti-guerrilla capability can be developed within the regular armed
                                forces by changing the emphasis in the training of selected elements
                                of the Vietnamese Army and other security forces from conventional
                                to anti-guerrilla warfare. The Department of the Army agrees with
                                the <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> concept, but feels
                                that additional support in specialized fields is warranted and can
                                be introduced overtly in Vietnam as a result of current developments
                                with respect to the <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_TERM1">TERM</gloss> ceiling.<note n="4" xml:id="d122fn4"><p>(1) <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>
                                        message to Commander in Chief, Pacific, <gloss target="#t_DEF1">DEF</gloss> 973757, <gloss target="#t_DTG1">DTG</gloss> 120010Z March 1960; on file
                                        Joint Secretariat.</p>
                                    <p>(2) Department of State message to American Embassy Saigon
                                        and other addressees, No. 1687, dated 17 March 1960; on file
                                        in Joint Secretariat. [Footnote in the source text. <ref target="#d118fn6">Document 118 and footnote 6</ref>
                                        thereto.]</p></note> The Department of the Army is,
                                therefore, prepared to augment the <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> capability by furnishing the Chief, <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>, with special forces mobile
                                training team personnel, including operational detachments and
                                command and communications elements, psychological operations
                                advisors, civil affairs advisors, and a language qualified
                                counter-intelligence and combat intelligence training team.<note n="5" xml:id="d122fn5">Enclosure “B” hereto. [Footnote in the
                                    source text.]</note></item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Additional matériel support to the Vietnamese forces, or
                                acceleration of deliveries of matériel currently programmed, as
                                considered necessary by <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>
                                should receive the full support of the Department of Defense.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>In view of the critical situation in Vietnam, I believe that the
                                Joint Chiefs of Staff should take definite action to assist the
                                Vietnamese in their effort to combat the insidious guerrilla warfare
                                being conducted against them. I therefore recommend that the message
                                in Enclosure “A” hereto, be dispatched to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>, offering additional
                                training support to <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>, Vietnam,
                                as one means of coping with this increasingly threatening
                                    situation.<note n="6" xml:id="d122fn6">Enclosure A is a draft
                                    message to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>,
                                    subsequently sent unchanged on March 30 as <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 947802 following <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> approval of <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1992/791 at their meeting held
                                    on March 29. This message set forth in the name of the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> the substance of paragraph 4 of
                                        <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1992/791, and requested
                                        <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>’s views on
                                    training assistance and on any additional requirements necessary
                                    to insure the internal security of Vietnam. (National Archives
                                    and Records Service, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                                    Records, <gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> 99, 9155.3/4060 (15
                                    Feb 60)) <p>Subsequent messages in the file cited above and in
                                        Center of Military History, <persName corresp="#p_WLGST1">Williams</persName> Papers, <gloss target="#t_TWXS1">TWX</gloss> s 1960 (71), between <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>, and Chief of
                                            <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> Vietnam during
                                        April indicate that agreement was reached to send to Vietnam
                                        three special forces training teams of ten men each, three
                                        intelligence officers, and three “<gloss target="#t_PSYWAR1">psywar</gloss>” experts, to arrive in time for training
                                        to begin June 1. “Civilian clothes should be worn on arrival
                                        in Saigon. Standard U.S. combat and khaki army uniforms will
                                        be worn during duty hours in Vietnam. Calibre of all
                                        personnel should be best possible since this first time U.S.
                                        will instruct <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>
                                        directly.” (<gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>
                                        message 210017Z to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>,
                                        April 21; National Archives and Records Service, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Records, <gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> 99, 9155.3/4060 (15 Feb
                                        60))</p></note></item>
                            <pb facs="0377" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>It is recommended that copies of this paper be forwarded to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>In consonance with the provisions of <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Memorandum of Policy No. 83,<note n="7" xml:id="d122fn7">Not printed.</note> it is recommended that
                                copies of this paper NOT be forwarded to U.S. officers assigned to
                                NATO activities.</item>
                        </list>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Enclosure “B”</head>
                            <p rend="center">SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION</p>
                            <p>Department of the Army can provide the following additional personnel
                                to USCINCPAC for <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>, Vietnam: <list>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">a.</hi></label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">U.S. Army Special Forces</hi>. U.S. Army
                                        Special Forces are considered well qualified to conduct and
                                        train small unit indigenous forces for anti-terrorist
                                        operations. Twelve special forces detachments totaling 116
                                        personnel can be made available to <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>, Vietnam, to assist the Vietnamese forces
                                        in counter-terrorist operations. Three of these teams have
                                        previously been targeted for South Vietnam. In addition, a
                                        command, control and communication element comprising 50
                                        personnel can, if warranted, be furnished to Chief, <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> in order to provide a
                                        communications system capable of high speed communications
                                        with each element of special forces operating with a
                                        Vietnamese unit. Any special forces units so provided would
                                        be assigned to Chief, <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>,
                                        Vietnam.</item>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">b.</hi></label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Psychological Operations</hi>. Based on
                                        experience factors gained from Philippines anti-<gloss target="#t_HUK1">HUK</gloss> operations and more
                                        recently from Laotian activities, it is considered that a
                                        minimum of six (6) psychological operations personnel may be
                                        required to assist the efforts of <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>, Vietnam. These personnel would have the
                                        mission of advising and assisting the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> in obtaining the
                                        cooperation of the indigenous population and reducing or
                                        eliminating its support of Viet Cong guerrilla elements. It
                                        is believed that <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>
                                        possibly has sufficient resources available to him to
                                        provide these personnel. If not, some of these personnel can
                                        be provided by DA.</item>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">c.</hi></label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Civil Affairs</hi>. As in psychological
                                        operations, experience in the Philippine anti-<gloss target="#t_HUK1">HUK</gloss> operations and more
                                        recently in the Laotian situation definitely demonstrated
                                        that Civil Affairs operations can effectively contribute to
                                        the separation of civilian support from the guerrilla
                                        activity and thus deny the guerrillas a base of operations.
                                        The development of this capability requires a local Civil
                                        Affairs organization <pb facs="0378" n="348" xml:id="pg_348"/> which is a thoroughly integrated part of the local Armed
                                        Forces. A minimum of three well trained Civil Affairs
                                        officers could be made available to the <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> in order to develop the
                                        indigenous Civil Affairs capability required. These officers
                                        would be utilized not only to train and indoctrinate the
                                        indigenous personnel but also as an advisory group to the
                                            <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> for CA aspects of
                                        the counter-guerrilla operation which is presently being
                                        conducted. The indigenous Civil Affairs capability should
                                        include a Civil Affairs focal point within the military
                                        establishment and a <gloss target="#t_G51">G5</gloss> staff
                                        organization at all levels to include the division, suitably
                                        trained and indoctrinated Civil Affairs units and an
                                        aggressive civic action program which this Civil Affairs
                                        organization could carry out.</item>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">d.</hi></label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Intelligence and
                                            Counter-Intelligence</hi>. A training team of 10
                                        individuals, comprising both counter-intelligence and combat
                                        intelligence personnel, all of whom would be
                                        language-qualified. This team would assist and train the
                                        Vietnamese in counter-intelligence and counter-subversion
                                        activities, individual and unit combat intelligence, and
                                        techniques and control of clandestine intelligence
                                        operations against insurgent elements.</item>
                                </list></p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>