<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-08-23T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-08-23T04:00:00-05:00" n="197" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d197">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">741.9411/212: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-08-23T18:00:00+09:00">August 23, 1934—6
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received August 23—6:48 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>188. Department’s 145, August 22, 7 p.m. 1. Kato, who covers the Foreign
                            Office for Rengo, told Fleisher today that when he and other Japanese
                            newspaper correspondents asked Hirota concerning the rumors of a renewal
                            of the Anglo-Japanese alliance Hirota said that in 1902 when the
                            alliance was formed<note n="76" xml:id="d197fn76"><ref target="frus1902#pg_514"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1902, p. 514</ref>.</note> he had advocated
                            the inclusion of the United States and that his views in this respect
                            had not changed. He added that in case the United States should be
                            prevented by its traditional policy from now joining such an alliance no
                            such alliance should be formed against the United States because the
                            Minister felt that Anglo-American-Japanese friendship and cooperation
                            were essential to the peace of the world and he wished to take no step
                            which would alienate American friendship. The Minister apparently sent a
                            direct reply to the questions of the correspondents regarding present
                            Anglo-Japanese negotiations. No foreigners were present at the
                            interview.</p>
                        <p>2. From reliable evidence I am convinced that the British Embassy in
                            Tokyo knows nothing whatever concerning any current Anglo-Japanese
                            negotiations or agreement.<note n="77" xml:id="d197fn77">The Counselor
                                of Embassy in Great Britain, in a letter dated August 22, stated:
                                “Although the Foreign Office had informed the press it was all
                                nonsense, I thought it was worth while to make a <hi rend="italic">pro forma</hi> inquiry of the Far Eastern Department today, and
                                was told that the only matter under discussion between the Japanese
                                Embassy and the Tokyo Foreign Office now was the Manchukuo oil
                                question …” and that the rumored accord “was without the faintest
                                horizon of foundation.” (741.9411/214)</note></p>
                        <p>Repeated to Peiping by mail.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>