<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Mukden ( (Myers) ) to the Minister in China (
                    (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recg3iRrscBAKUZil" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="narcotics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85095095"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Opium</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="22"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d22">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01 Manchuria/1029</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Mukden</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Myers</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Minister in China</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="33" xml:id="d22fn33">Copy transmitted to the Department by
                        the Consul General at Mukden in his unnumbered despatch of February 3;
                        received March 9.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 892</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mukden</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-02-03">February 3,
                            1934</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As of possible interest, I have the honor to
                    report on the gradual change in the sentiment of the people toward the new
                    regime. Although no extensive survey of this matter has been attempted, the
                    information on which these observations are based was obtained from competent
                    and presumably unbiased observers, both Chinese and foreign. The situation
                    described herein pertains primarily to this province.</p>
                <p>Generally speaking, it may be safely said that the sentiment of the people living
                    in cities has become noticeably more favorable to the new regime than a year or
                    more ago. The increasing stability of the new order and the progress made in
                    bandit suppression during the past year have resulted in the practical
                    disappearance of the feeling of uncertainty which prevailed for at least one and
                    one-half years following the “incident” of September 18, 1931. Business,
                    especially in the interior, has greatly improved. Although it may be said that
                    the above generalization is true, it does not mean that the intelligent people
                    of “Manchukuo” do not realize that their country is dominated by Japan nor
                    indicate that they welcome or like this alien domination; rather it seems that
                    this sentiment denotes a philosophical acceptance of an altered status which is
                    bringing in its wake many material benefits and which there appears to be little
                    or no prospect of changing. An unbiased Chinese briefly summarized the situation
                    as follows: No one believes that any change in the existing situation can be
                    effected internally by force; no one has faith in China doing anything; no one
                    desires a return of the former regime; there is a growing appreciation of what
                    the present regime is doing for the people. A foreigner in close touch with the
                    Chinese expressed the opinion that they are beginning to realize that they are
                    better off than under the old regime. Among the reforms which are widely
                    understood and appreciated may be mentioned the stabilization and unification
                        <pb facs="0115" n="25" xml:id="pg_25"/> of the currency, increased official
                    probity and public works, extensive road building being possibly the best
                    known.</p>
                <p>Among the country folk there has been little or no change of feeling according to
                    available information. Chinese propaganda and fear of Japanese troops, instilled
                    by insurgents and bandits in the minds of the country people who are
                    subconsciously hostile to anything foreign, have undoubtedly been factors in
                    keeping alive an anti-“Manchukuo” feeling. Ignorance—a farmer replied to a query
                    of a missionary that his thoughts did not go beyond his two acres—and low grain
                    prices must have a similar effect. Observers believe, however, that increasing
                    security and good roads are beginning to be appreciated. But it is the
                    establishment of the monarchy with P’u Yi as Emperor which is being widely
                    heralded throughout the country that seems likely to influence opinion of the
                    country folk in favor of the new regime more than anything else. (Reference my
                    confidential despatch No. 888 of January 24, 1934,<note n="34" xml:id="d22fn34"
                        >Not printed.</note> entitled “P’u Yi to be Enthroned as Emperor of
                    ‘Manchukuo’ on March 1, 1934.”)</p>
                <p>A few instances indicating this changing sentiment may be of interest. From a
                    reliable source it has been learned that the graduates of mission schools who
                    for at least one year after September 18, 1931, planned only on going to China
                    in search of employment are now seeking and accepting positions in the new
                    government. At the outset public opinion would have condemned this step but now
                    it is accepted as a matter of course. A well-educated Chinese professional man
                    who has no Japanese associations and who is looked upon as having good judgment
                    and much common sense returned some time ago from a visit to his home in the
                    interior of Shantung. He stated that Manchuria is a tabooed subject in Shantung
                    by official order and expressed the opinion that as far as China is concerned it
                    is a closed issue and that Chinese residing in Manchuria should govern
                    themselves accordingly.</p>
                <p>In the opinion of a well-informed observer there is a fairly large body of
                    educated Chinese in Manchuria who are extremely critical of the new regime’s
                    policy regarding opium<note n="35" xml:id="d22fn35">See also <ref
                            target="#pg_349">pp. 349</ref> ff.</note> and education. They are said
                    to condemn the opium monopoly which has greatly increased opium smoking and
                    regard with serious misgivings the small amount of money devoted to education
                    and the failure to reopen the higher middle schools and other higher schools of
                    learning. It has been learned that with the exception of the First Higher Middle
                    School at Mukden (it has only one class with 58 students), the higher technical
                    middle schools and normal schools no schools above the lower middle schools have
                    been reopened in Fengtien Province. The total <pb facs="0116" n="26"
                        xml:id="pg_26"/> attendance at the 41 provincial schools in Mukden was
                    recently reported in the press as 20,231—the city’s population is approximately
                    400,000. That the Japanese have not overlooked the important part played by
                    schools in moulding public opinion is indicated by the promptness with which
                    text books were revised and by the sending of selected youths from time to time
                    to Japan—about 300 Manchurians are reported to be studying in Japan—for further
                    training. According to a recent “Manchoukuo News Service” report a new
                    educational program will be inaugurated at the time of the establishment of the
                    monarchy which “will lay emphasis on the exaltation and propagation of the
                    spirit of national founding among the younger generation.” My informant
                    expressed the view that the reactions of this body of Chinese are of some
                    potential importance especially as they have close connections in China.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>M. S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Myers</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
