<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-05-29T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-05-29T01:00:00-05:00" n="465" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d465">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">493.11/1870: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-05-29T14:00:00+08:00">May 29, 1934—2
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received May 29—11:40 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>225. Legation’s 186, April 21, 11 a.m. and Department’s 128, April 26, 5
                            p.m.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Legation has completed preparation of a list of some 650 claims
                                from data in its files. In going through this list with the idea of
                                preparing a “selected list” for presentation to Chinese Foreign
                                Office the Legation has been more and more persuaded of
                                impracticability of such a method, (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                                because presentation of such a selected list <pb facs="0645" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> might cast doubt upon subsequent lists, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) we want the establishment of a claims
                                commission. Such piecemeal presentation would merely serve to delay
                                decision in this matter.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>With the Department’s approval Legation proposes to make a list of
                                entire 600-odd claims arranged alphabetically showing amount of
                                claims as of date filed or presented and a very general statement as
                                to the nature of claim for presentation to the Foreign Office with a
                                statement that the claims listed have been [taken?] from the records
                                of the Legation but that the list cannot be considered as complete
                                and consequently it is submitted without prejudice to other American
                                claims against the Chinese Government.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Legation believes this would be better tactics in that
                                presentation of such a list might be helpful in persuading Foreign
                                Office to accept idea of Claims Commission.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>