<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Group of the China Consortium to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d474</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">474</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLVtmipNOLIF0A1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="474"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d474">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/5934</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Group of the China
                            Consortium</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-10-25">October 25,
                            1934</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: We beg to acknowledge receipt of your letter of
                    October 11th<note n="16" xml:id="d474fn16">Not printed.</note> (FE 893.51/5928)
                    enclosing a copy of the text of the joint memorandum, under date of August 10,
                    1934, which was transmitted to the Chinese Minister of Foreign Affairs by the
                    representatives in China of the United States, Great Britain and France,
                    together with a copy of the Minister of Foreign Affairs’ memorandum in reply,
                    under date of August 21, 1934.</p>
                <p>In the latter memorandum, the Minister of Foreign Affairs quotes certain
                    authorities concerned with respect to the alleged insufficiency of the present
                    customs revenue to meet demands, while at the same time recognizing the
                    government’s obligation to secure the Hukuang Loan upon the customs as a
                    substitute for the likin abolished.</p>
                <p>At the time of the abolition of likin in 1931, there was a substantial surplus of
                    customs revenues above the service of all loans charged thereon. As you are
                    aware, large amounts of money were borrowed in China by the Chinese Government
                    on the strength of surrendered or remitted portions of the Boxer Indemnity
                    annuities, the government ignoring completely the obligation to secure the
                    Hukuang Loan. Other indebtedness has also been incurred, secured on the surplus
                    of the customs.</p>
                <p>In Sir Arthur Salter’s paper “China and Silver” published in the spring number of
                        <hi rend="italic">Economic Forum</hi>, he states on page 71 that after all
                    charges were met out of customs there remained for that year a surplus of
                    $70,000,000 Chinese. It is exceedingly difficult for us to understand how the
                    Chinese Government can steadily maintain, in its replies to the various protests
                    made by the American, British and <pb facs="0652" n="562" xml:id="pg_562"/>
                    French Governments, as well as by the three Groups, that there are no customs
                    revenues available to implement the obligations of Articles VIII and IX of the
                    Hukuang Loan Agreement when such revenues, as stated by Sir Arthur Salter, do
                    produce a surplus of this amount. Allowing for the annual remittance which China
                    has made in recent years of an amount equal to one coupon per annum, the loan
                    requirements laid down in the contract for the remainder of the interest and for
                    sinking fund annually aggregate only $3,800,000 Chinese; and if the entire loan
                    service were transferred to customs and no salt funds used, the annual
                    requirements would be increased only to $6,000,000 Chinese. (These figures, of
                    course, take no account of existing arrears.)</p>
                <p>It must be the conviction of the Department as it is of the group banks, that
                    China, while using surplus customs revenues for her general needs, is
                    deliberately avoiding the clearly defined obligation to substitute a charge upon
                    customs for the abolished likin pledged under the Hukuang Loan. May we hope that
                    the Department will see fit to request the other interested governments to make
                    even stronger representations than before, in the light of the figures obtained
                    by Sir Arthur Salter from what we understand to be official sources, so that
                    China should use some part of the customs revenues which appear to be available
                    for the purpose of carrying out the obligations which the Chinese Minister of
                    Foreign Affairs in his memorandum recognizes, before such surplus customs
                    revenues are subjected to any further pledges.</p>
                <p>Yours very truly,</p>
                <closer>J. P. <hi rend="smallcaps">Morgan</hi> &amp; Co.<lb/>For the American
                    Group</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
