<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-04-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="550" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d550">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.9411/5</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far
                                Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-04-13">April 13, 1934</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Italian Ambassador asked for an appointment and called on me this
                            morning. He read me a telegram which he said he had just received from
                            Rome in which his Foreign Office informed him that it had received a
                            telegram from the Italian Ambassador in Moscow stating that information
                            was in circulation in Moscow to the effect that the Japanese Government
                            had proposed to the American Government a non-aggression pact and the
                            American Government had replied that it would not be agreeable to a
                            bilateral pact but would be agreeable to a four-power pact (United
                            States, Japan, Soviet Union and China). The Ambassador asked whether I
                            could give him any information.</p>
                        <p>I replied that I doubted whether the Department would wish to make any
                            statement but that I could say to him for his confidential information
                            and the confidential information of his Foreign Office that no proposals
                            had been received here and no such project is, on our part, under
                            discussion. I requested that, if the Ambassador reported this to his
                            Government, he especially ask them not to circulate or to make public
                            any statement with regard to the matter. The Ambassador said that our
                            confidence would be respected.</p>
                        <p>The conversation there ended.</p>
                        <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ornbeck</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>