<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-01-21T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-01-21T21:00:00-05:00" n="8" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d8">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01 Manchuria/988: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-01-22T11:00:00+09:00">January 22, 1934—11
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received January 22—7:05 a.m.<note n="7" xml:id="d8fn7">Telegram in two sections.</note>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>12. Publicity has been given here to Dr. Hornbeck’s speech on January
                                18<note n="8" xml:id="d8fn8">Address delivered by Stanley K.
                                Hornbeck, Chief of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs, Department
                                of State, on “Principles of American Policy in Relation to the Far
                                East,” before the Ninth Conference on the Cause and Cure of War,
                                Washington, D. C. For text, see Department of State publication No.
                                567 (Washington, Government Printing Office, 1934).</note> in which
                            he is reported to have said that “the nonrecognition of government made
                            by swords” is still the policy of the United States. In view of the Far
                            Eastern context of the speech the Japanese interpret Dr. Hornbeck’s
                            remarks as referring to Manchukuo. The spokesman of the Foreign
                                Office<note n="9" xml:id="d8fn9">Eiji Amau.</note> has issued the
                            following statement to the press: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“It is most regrettable that the Chief of the Far Eastern Bureau
                                    of United States State Department should at this particular
                                    moment, when the Japanese authorities are exerting their utmost
                                    efforts for the promotion of friendship between Japan and
                                    America, deliver a speech in which he reviews the argument of
                                    the much-contested Stimson doctrine, and further suggests the
                                    application to East Asia of America’s traditional policy toward
                                    the Latin American countries. His utterances convey an
                                    impression of wilfully ignoring the existence of a great power
                                    bearing the responsibilities for the maintenance of <pb facs="0097" n="7" xml:id="pg_7"/> peace in East Asia. It
                                    should not be forgotten that the Empire of Japan exists in the
                                    Far East as much as does the United States on the Continent of
                                    America.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>It is still too early to foresee the extent of the repercussion from this
                            publicity although it is certain to have a temporarily disturbing effect
                            on Japanese-American relations.</p>
                        <p>I appreciate of course that the Department had good and sufficient
                            reasons for the delivery of Dr. Hornbeck’s speech. The following points
                            are therefore respectfully submitted without any thought of caviling at
                            a step which might have been given mature consideration but rather in
                            the hope that they may be weighed in determining future procedure.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>So far as we can maintain unimpaired, but without public
                                reiteration, the position of our Government regarding the
                                nonrecognition of the fruits of armed aggression, published and
                                compiled at the commencement of the present administration,<note n="10" xml:id="d8fn10"><hi rend="italic">Conditions in
                                        Manchuria</hi>, Senate Document No. 55, 72d Cong., 1st sess.
                                    (Washington, Government Printing Office, 1932).</note> just so
                                far shall we avoid inflaming public opinion in Japan at a time of
                                acute sensitiveness.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>The controversies which are certain to arise in the Naval
                                Conference of 1935,<note n="11" xml:id="d8fn11">See <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_277"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 277</ref> ff.</note> if it
                                takes place, will inevitably subject Japanese-American relations to
                                a strain in which we shall need every asset of which we can avail
                                ourselves.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>If we can even partially overcome the antagonistic attitude
                                prevailing in Japan towards the United States, or at least avoid
                                rendering it more acute, the dangers of that coming strain will be
                                correspondingly lessened and we shall be in a better position to
                                work out our policies effectively. I have, therefore, been working
                                steadily, and not without some favorable result in spite of many
                                local handicaps and setbacks, to improve that attitude.</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>Public reiteration of our determination not to recognize Manchukuo
                                will inevitably tend to undo that work and will render it more
                                difficult for Hirota<note n="12" xml:id="d8fn12">Koki Hirota,
                                    Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note> to carry out his
                                prime policy of improving Japanese-American relations, a policy
                                which I believe to be genuine and which in the long run may prove to
                                be decidedly helpful to American interests if allowed to bear
                                fruit.</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>If and when further reiteration of our policy concerning Manchukuo
                                is considered necessary, less disturbance of our relations with
                                Japan will be caused by doing so in diplomatic conversations than in
                                public speeches.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Please let me make it perfectly clear that I staunchly support the Far
                            Eastern policy of our Government and that the foregoing considerations
                            have to do purely with matters of procedure and not of principle.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>