<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">86</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-04-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-04-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-04-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-04-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="86"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d86">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/6648</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 751</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-04-20">April 20,
                            1934</date>.<lb/>[Received May 5.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: [For first two paragraphs of this despatch, see
                    extract printed in <ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_223">
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, volume I, pages
                        223</ref>–<ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_224">224</ref>; <pb facs="0208"
                        n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/> for the enclosed “Unofficial statement” by the
                    Japanese Foreign Office on April 17, 1934, see <ref
                        target="frus1931-41v01#pg_224">
                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, page 224</ref>.]</p>
                <p>The Embassy’s impression is that the statement as issued conveys the true policy
                    of the Japanese Government toward activities by other countries in China, but
                    that the Foreign Office is somewhat fearful of the effect of the statement
                    abroad and therefore is carefully maintaining a position where it can deny that
                    such a statement was ever officially issued. This view is borne out by a
                    conversation which a member of the staff of the Embassy had with an under
                    official of the Bureau of Asiatic Affairs of the Foreign Office on the 19th.
                    According to this official, the essential basis of the announcement, namely,
                    that the Japanese Government feels that it should be consulted by other
                    governments before they take any action in China, is the actual opinion of those
                    in chargé of Japan’s relations with China. The official stated that the
                    statement of policy should be interpreted in a negative rather than a positive
                    way; that Japan did not contemplate any single-handed action in China but only
                    wanted the other powers to recognize Japan’s right to be consulted when they
                    contemplated any activity in China. The official did not state how this policy
                    could be reconciled with Japan’s recognition, in the Nine-Power Treaty, of the
                    administrative integrity of China.</p>
                <p>It has been apparent for some time that the Japanese Government has been
                    developing such a policy as is outlined in the statement unofficially released
                    by the Foreign Office on April 17th. There was considerable resentment, official
                    and unofficial, of the American wheat and cotton loan to China, and for months
                    past the Japanese have viewed with a suspicious and resentful eye the activities
                    of American airplane companies in China. Even the activities of Dr. Rajchman, of
                    the Health Bureau of the League Secretariat, in China have called forth
                    considerable criticism in Japan. On April 9th, in commenting on rumored plans
                    for international cooperation in giving economic assistance to China, the
                    spokesman for the Foreign Office stated that such attempts have always ended in
                    failure in the past; that the repercussion from failure in Japan was much
                    greater than in other countries; and that for these reasons Japan would not only
                    not join in such international cooperation but would definitely oppose any plans
                    for international cooperation.<note n="34" xml:id="d86fn34">For additional
                        correspondence on this subject, see <ref target="#pg_371">pp. 371</ref>
                        ff.</note> The statement issued on April 17th is undoubtedly an elaboration
                    and elucidation of the policy mentioned on the 9th, but the question which has
                    been agitating foreign circles in Tokyo is not why the Government issued such a
                    statement, but why the Government issued the statement at the present time, when
                    everything possible is being done to conciliate foreign countries. <pb
                        facs="0209" n="119" xml:id="pg_119"/> The under-official of the Foreign
                    Office with whom a member of my staff conversed stated that he knew of no reason
                    for issuing the statement of policy at the present time, but seemed to be
                    inclined to ascribe the move to a desire on the part of Mr. Amau to create a
                    sensation, such as Mr. Shiratori, when in the same position in the Foreign
                    Office, was inclined to create. This interpretation, however, seems somewhat
                    strained. Baron Shidehara, when questioned by one of the newspaper
                    correspondents, expressed surprise that the statement should be issued just at
                    the moment when Japan’s relations with other nations appeared to be improving.
                    An explanation which most observers agree seems to be the most reasonable is
                    that the Japanese suspect that Dr. Rajchman, of the League Secretariat, now on
                    his way to Geneva from China, where he has been conducting investigations for
                    some months past, is carrying with him some plan for international technical and
                    economic assistance supervised by the League of Nations, to China, and that the
                    Japanese Government wishes to forestall any such move by the League.</p>
                <p>There are various reports, some of which seem to be reliable, regarding the
                    impelling force behind the issuing of the statement. One is that the action was
                    taken at the instigation of the military, who have always advocated a strong
                    attitude toward China and who induced Amau to issue the statement without the
                    authorization of Mr. Hirota, thereby placing him in a most difficult position,
                    as the policy enunciated in the statement is not in accord with his conciliatory
                    policy, and as he cannot withdraw the statement without incurring the enmity of
                    the military. On the other hand, Mr. Shigemitsu, the Vice Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs, according to most reliable information, thoroughly endorses the
                    statement, asserting that it forms a part of Japan’s fixed policies, and that it
                    will be carried out regardless of the opposition of other nations of the world.
                    Mr. Amau himself, in a private conversation, asserted that the statement was
                    issued as a sort of preliminary to the forthcoming naval conference, which would
                    be a success if Japan’s thesis regarding assistance to China is accepted by the
                    other powers and which would fail if the thesis is not accepted.</p>
                <p>Amau, in the press conference of the morning of April 20, made an impromptu
                    translation of a typewritten document. According to his translation of the
                    document, Japan has no intention of interfering with the legitimate interests of
                    other powers in China; Japan will object only when the action of a third power
                    threatens Japan’s position; Japan has no intention of interfering with the
                    independence of China or of infringing on the interests of China; and Japan has
                    no intention of deviating from the established policies of the Open Door and
                    equal opportunity, or of infringing existing treaties. This statement <pb
                        facs="0210" n="120" xml:id="pg_120"/> was apparently issued after it was
                    seen that the original statement had excited much adverse comment abroad, and
                    was intended to calm the fears of other nations. It will be observed, however,
                    that while it modifies the tone of the original statement somewhat, it does not
                    alter the basic policy.</p>
                <p>According to the <hi rend="italic">Tokyo Nichi-Nichi</hi> of April 19, 1934
                    (Japanese Edition), the Army authorities unqualifiedly support the stand
                    envisaged in the statement issued by the Foreign Office in regard to
                    international assistance to China. Since the outbreak of the Manchurian incident
                    in 1931, the military authorities have viewed all attempts at or consideration
                    of political and economic assistance to China as being injurious to the
                    maintenance of peace and order in East Asia. This was demonstrated by Japan’s
                    refusal to accept the conclusions of the Lytton Report,<note n="35"
                        xml:id="d86fn35">League of Nations, <hi rend="italic">Appeal by the Chinese
                            Government, Report of the Commission of Enquiry</hi> (Geneva, October 1,
                        1932).</note> which contemplated assistance to China. The Japanese military
                    authorities believe that European and American nations should not endeavor to
                    interfere in Oriental affairs, because of their lack of adequate knowledge of
                    conditions and factors making for the maintenance of peace in the Orient. The
                    maintenance of peace devolves only upon Japan and China, and there can be no
                    argument on this point. They hold that it is shown by actual developments that
                    the Nine-Power Treaty aiming to bring about peace and order in China has no
                    practical value in its application to actualities, and that it is reasonable to
                    conclude that it has practically been invalidated. Under these circumstances,
                    they say, Japan should refrain from participating in the next naval conference
                    if it is proposed that the conference touch upon Oriental problems in addition
                    to matters directly concerned with naval limitation, and if the conference
                    should proceed to consider the political problems of the Orient, Japan should
                    immediately withdraw from the conference, as Japan’s policy in this regard is
                    settled and unshakable and no discussion can be permitted. Therefore Japan
                    should object to any agreement which will hamper cooperation between Japan and
                    China, if any such agreement is proposed at the next naval conference, according
                    to the military authorities.</p>
                <p>In regard to the statement issued by the spokesman of the Foreign Office, the
                    Embassy desires to invite the attention of the Department to the fact that the
                    term “Toa” (Eastern Asia) is used in the statement. As a rule, the Japanese
                    formerly used the term “Toyo” (Eastern Seas, or the Orient, as distinguished
                    from “Seiyo”, Western Seas or the Occident) or “Kyokuto” (Extreme or Far East)
                    in designating the Far East generally. The term “Eastern Asia” has a somewhat
                        <pb facs="0211" n="121" xml:id="pg_121"/> different and more precise
                    connotation and is probably meant to include parts of China.</p>
                <p>So far four vernacular newspapers, the <hi rend="italic">Tokyo Asahi</hi>, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Jiji</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Chugai Shogyo</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Hochi</hi>, have published editorials on the subject of
                    the statement issued by the Foreign Office. They all endorse the principles
                    contained in the statement, although the <hi rend="italic">Asahi</hi> doubts
                    that cooperation between Japan and China will be possible for some time to come,
                    because of opposition among some elements in China. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hochi</hi>, while not disapproving of the statement, believes that the
                    phraseology was too abstract, resulting in misunderstandings abroad, and was
                    issued at the wrong time, before an understanding had been reached through
                    diplomatic channels with other nations. The <hi rend="italic">Japan
                        Advertiser</hi> of April 19th published an editorial on the subject,
                    expressing doubt that other nations will be prepared to subscribe to the
                    Japanese thesis regarding assistance to China. Newspaper clippings containing
                    these five editorials are enclosed herewith.<note n="36" xml:id="d86fn36">None
                        reprinted.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In my opinion, the implications contained in the Foreign Office statement are
                    very serious. If the policy as therein outlined is adhered to and carried out
                    strictly, it will constitute an element in international affairs as important
                    as, if not more important than, the Monroe Doctrine of the United States. It
                    goes much further than the Monroe Doctrine and places China in a state of
                    tutelage under Japan. In view, however, of the declared policy of the present
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs to use every means in his power to better Japan’s
                    relations with other nations, I do not believe that any attempt will be made at
                    the present time to enforce the policy outlined in the Foreign Office statement
                    in a provocative manner.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
