<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d115</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">115</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-10-21T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-10-21T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090254"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Natural resources</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recJqlMttIxR5nnOr" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Nonaggression</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-10-21T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-10-21T23:00:00-05:00" n="115"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94 Conference/88: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-10-22T12:00:00+08:00"
                            >October 22, 1937—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 5:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>846. 1. Yesterday afternoon I held a conversation with Wang Ching Wei, former
                    President of the Executive Yuan, now occupying extremely important positions in
                    the Party and Government. Peng, Vice Minister of Communications, interpreted and
                    Peck was present.</p>
                <p>2. Wang said telegram received from Hu Shih<note n="24" xml:id="d115fn24">Chinese
                        professor of philosophy.</note> reported that the President in recent
                    interview had offered the following advice, (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) that
                    after stating China’s case at the Brussels Conference the Chinese <pb
                        facs="0111" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/> delegates withdraw and (<hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi>) that China be prepared at the Conference to state
                    China’s position in regard to the desire of Japan to cooperate in developing
                    China’s natural resources. Commenting, Wang said that the Chinese Government
                    appreciated this thoughtful advice and would be guided by it. He supposed that
                    the first item was based on the supposition that Japan would it [<hi
                        rend="italic">sic</hi>] not be represented and on feeling that participation
                    by China in the discussions without Japan would impart an air of partiality and
                    would antagonize Japan. There now appeared to be hope that Japan would be
                    represented. In regard to the second he said that China would welcome
                    cooperation from Japan as from all nations in the development of natural
                    resources in accord with the spirit of the Nine-Power Treaty and in ways not
                    harmful to but advantageous to both China and the nations concerned.</p>
                <p>3. Wang said the Chinese Government thoroughly understood the motive which
                    prompted the powers to show scrupulous regard for the sensibilities of Japan as
                    exemplified in the wording of the invitation to the Conference extended by the
                    Belgian Government and in the President’s advice to Hu Shih. At the same time he
                    wished to point out that there was a moderate party in Japan which disapproved
                    of the present ruthless hostilities conducted against China by the military
                    faction. This moderate party was suppressed and lacked arguments with which to
                    oppose the war policy which appeals to the Japanese public on grounds of Japan’s
                    national welfare and need of self-defense. Wang urged that if other nations
                    would exert some form of pressure on Japan to desist from attempted military
                    conquest of China making it evident that the continued use of armed force would
                    be seriously detrimental to Japan’s international position the moderate party
                    would be strengthened in its efforts to demonstrate that the use of warlike
                    methods would be prejudicial to Japan. A too conciliatory attitude on the part
                    of other nations on the other hand would encourage the Military and weaken the
                    moderate party. I replied that one school of thought in the United States
                    sympathized with this line of reasoning but another school felt that combined
                    pressure on Japan would support the contention of the Japanese military faction
                    that Japan was fighting for her existence and that Japan’s only hope lay in
                    demonstrated military supremacy.</p>
                <p>4. Continuing his discussion of underlying principles, Wang refuted the Japanese
                    contention that China had been obdurate and refused to settle outstanding issues
                    through diplomatic negotiation. He recalled that in the face of repeated
                    invasions and provocations China had continued to negotiate with Japan and that
                    Chang Chun when Minister for Foreign Affairs had even discussed Hirota’s “three
                    principles” with the Japanese Ambassador for more than 2 months, <pb facs="0112"
                        n="104" xml:id="pg_104"/> which discussions had failed partly because Japan
                    insisted on acceptance in blank and refused to divulge what the “principles”
                    would mean in actual application. He said that China had thus been conciliatory
                    in the extreme but he felt that much good would now be accomplished if the
                    friendly powers would warn Japan that the present policy was driving the Chinese
                    people to fight in desperation to the bitter end and would moreover leave Japan
                    with a heritage of international ill-will. I observed that I concurred in the
                    views expressed but it must be accepted as a fact that Japanese policy is at
                    present dictated by the military mind which seems to know only the two facts of
                    victory or indivisible defeat.</p>
                <p>5. On the subject of the Brussels Conference, Wang told me in great confidence
                    that the British Minister for Foreign Affairs had assured the Chinese Ambassador
                    in London that whatever plan the participating powers might evolve for the
                    proposed settlement of the conflict would first be submitted informally to China
                    and Japan in order to sound out their views. He inquired whether it would not be
                    possible for the American Government at the present time to ascertain privately
                    what terms of settlement would be accepted by Japan and he added that while the
                    Chinese Government was prepared to go a long way to effect a settlement it was
                    of great importance to China to learn whether the Japanese Government was
                    intending to treat China as Italy treated Ethiopia, because China was not in
                    fact a second Ethiopia and would fight for its independence. I returned an
                    evasive reply.</p>
                <p>6. Wang asked me whether I had any inkling of the nature of the plan which the
                    President had in mind for possible adjustment of the controversy between China
                    and Japan and I said I had no information on this point. He asked what I thought
                    was the attitude of the Soviet Union toward a settlement of the controversy and
                    he remarked that it was absurd for Japan or anyone else to infer that the
                    Nonaggression Pact concluded between the Soviet Union and China in August meant
                    that there was a military alliance between the two countries; the pact was in
                    that respect negative in nature. I said I thought the Russian attitude was one
                    of extreme caution not to become embroiled in the present hostilities and that
                    while Russia was probably convinced that sooner or later there must be war
                    between Russia and Japan, Russia wished to choose the location of the
                    battlefield. Wang asked me what I thought was Germany’s position and I said I
                    saw a change in Germany’s position from that which one would infer from the
                    German-Japanese joint understanding against Communism.<note n="25"
                        xml:id="d115fn25">Agreement signed at Berlin, November 25, 1936, <ref
                            target="frus1931-41v02#pg_153">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 153</ref>; see also <ref
                            target="frus1937v01#pg_605">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1937, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 605</ref> ff.</note> This change was
                    indicated somewhat by the press comments appearing <pb facs="0113" n="105"
                        xml:id="pg_105"/> in German newspapers and might indicate both that the
                    difficulties experienced by the Japanese Army in China lessened in German
                    opinion the supposed value of Japan as an ally and also that German commercial
                    interests did not relish the prospect of Japanese interference with Germany’s
                    encouraging recovery in trade with China and Germany’s increasingly friendly
                    relations with China.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Peiping and Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
