<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State ( (Welles) ) of a Trans-Atlantic
                    Telephone Conversation With the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Bingham))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d149</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">149</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-11-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-11-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="149"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d149">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94 Conference/161</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Welles</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Trans-Atlantic Telephone
                        Conversation With the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Bingham</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-01">November 1,
                            1937</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Welles</hi>: We are very much concerned by both
                    Associated Press and United Press reports of Mr. Eden’s speech in the House of
                    Commons today. He is alleged to have said that the United States took the
                    initiative in convoking the Nine-Power Conference. As you know, the facts in the
                    matter were that on October 6 the British Embassy here, by instruction of the
                    British Government, gave us an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> in which the
                    following statements were made. It referred in the beginning to the action taken
                    by the Advisory Committee of the League which expressed the hope that the other
                    states having special interests in the Far East would be associated with the
                    states who are members of the League in consultation in accordance with the
                    Nine-Power Treaty. Further on in that same memorandum it was stated, I quote,
                    among the points to be considered is the question as to how those invitations
                    should be issued, what form they should take, and where a conference, which is
                    in the view of His Majesty’s Government clearly necessary, should take place,
                    end of quotation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bingham</hi>: Eden has left for Brussels and the
                    evening papers contain no such statement. I cannot tell definitely whether or
                    not these reports are correct because we won’t see them until tomorrow
                    morning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Welles</hi>: The difficulty is, however, that it is
                    obviously very undesirable that our morning papers should carry a statement of
                    that character. Let me remind you of another thing also in that connection—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bingham</hi>: It is now a quarter to ten here and the
                    evening papers that I have looked over say nothing about that and the actual
                    report would be in the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Telegram</hi> tomorrow morning.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Welles</hi>: That does not solve our difficulty here.
                    We do not want our morning papers here to carry a statement of that
                    character.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bingham</hi>: I understand. I will go to work on that
                    immediately and see whether or not that report is correct or incorrect and will
                    get word to you as soon as I can.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Welles</hi>: Let me make this further statement—</p>
                <pb facs="0147" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bingham</hi>: Are you in New York?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Welles</hi>: I am in my office at Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bingham</hi>: I will get a message to you there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Welles</hi>: I want to make another statement to you. I
                    want to remind you that the invitation of the Belgian Government specifically
                    states “At the request of the British Government and with the approval of the
                    Government of the United States, the Royal Belgian Government proposes the
                    meeting at Brussels” et cetera. I have just been talking to the President and he
                    feels that you should obtain a correction, or at least a clarification, if the
                    reports are untrue, so that our press here will not carry any statements of the
                    character which I have read in the morning papers. If Mr. Eden has left perhaps
                        Vansittart<note n="55" xml:id="d149fn55">Sir Robert G. Vansittart, British
                        Permanent Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.</note> could do
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bingham</hi>: Eden has already left but I will try to
                    obtain a correction of that statement and communicate with you as soon as
                    possible. It is a little more difficult at this time of night here but at any
                    rate I will get the whole staff going and will report to you as promptly as we
                    can.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
