<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-24T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-24T19:00:00-05:00" n="223" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94 Conference/302: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the American Delegation</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Davis</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Brussels</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-25T00:00:00+00:00">November 25,
                                        1937—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received November 25—10:30
                                    p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>56. The British are strongly in favor of a joint Anglo-American offer
                                to mediate between Japan and China. They admit that the time is
                                probably not yet opportune but think it may come in the near future.
                                They also think that as long as Japan is unwilling to make a
                                constructive or reasonably just settlement she would discourage
                                mediation by the two of us and perhaps try to work it around for
                                Germany and Italy to mediate believing that she would thus put the
                                other interested powers in an embarrassing position and be able to
                                effect a settlement more favorable to herself than if other powers
                                were the mediators. I have told the British in substance that I
                                would be glad for us to see the thoughts of our two Governments
                                working along parallel lines as to methods of approach and possible
                                terms of settlement which would be a <hi rend="italic">sine qua
                                    non</hi> to safely attempting mediation, but that we should then
                                be guided by developments and I would want to confer with Washington
                                before reaching any conclusion or making any tentative commitment.
                                The British evidently feel as we do that Japan will jockey on the
                                question of mediation. The Japanese Ambassador here sent me word
                                that he was confident his country would be glad to have American
                                mediation particularly if we would act through Grew. He told the
                                British that he was sure that his <pb facs="0238" n="230" xml:id="pg_230"/> Government would be favorable to British
                                mediation alone. He told the Italians that he was prepared to
                                recommend to his Government on his responsibility that they accept
                                mediation by the Shanghai Committee. Aldrovandi has in conference
                                approached me several times here and suggested that Great Britain,
                                France, Italy and the United States mediate as members of the
                                Shanghai Committee and said he believed that they could induce Japan
                                to accept this. That is quite possible. On the other hand the
                                British are opposed to this because they feel satisfied that the
                                problem of composing the difference between the members of such a
                                mediating committee would be about as great as that of bringing
                                Japan and China together. We suspect that the strong opinion
                                expressed by the Japanese and reported by Craigie and Grew against
                                joint Anglo-American cooperation was in line with Japanese strategy
                                of trying to keep us apart just as in the preliminary naval
                                negotiations they tried to drive a wedge between us by playing one
                                off against the other. They unquestionably feel that as long as they
                                can keep us from standing together they are safe from outside
                                pressure. I feel that the more the Japanese think that the British
                                and ourselves are cooperating closely and earnestly for a fair and
                                peaceful solution and are not making threats the greater are the
                                chances of success. I realize, however, that it is important to
                                avoid giving any erroneous impression that we are playing the
                                British game or committing ourselves to join in coercive
                                measures.</p>
                            <p>The Chinese are standing off Italian proffers of mediation and
                                probably also German.</p>
                            <p>We suggest that you take no moves and make no commitments on the
                                subject of mediation until we shall have had an opportunity to
                                discuss it with you in Washington.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>