<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in China ( (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d296</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">296</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-08-26T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-08-26T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Consular offices</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-26T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-26T18:00:00-05:00" n="296"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d296">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">493.11/2055a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-26T19:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 26, 1937—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>184. In view of the present Sino-Japanese disturbances in China it would seem to
                    be desirable that notification be sent to American nationals and concerns in
                    China in relation to steps to be taken by them to obtain and put on record
                    evidence of losses and damages suffered during the disturbances. It is suggested
                    that such notification should be substantially as follows:</p>
                <p>While the American Government cannot in advance and without examination of their
                    respective merits undertake to espouse or to present claims against the Chinese
                    and Japanese Governments which may be presented to the American Government by
                    its nationals for losses, damages or injuries to life or property resulting from
                    present military operations in China, nevertheless, with a view to making clear
                    the essential requirements of the procedure for and the steps which claimants
                    would be well advised to take with a view to possible eventual presentation of
                    such claims,<note n="79a" xml:id="d296fn79a">In a written exchange of views
                        (September and December 1937), the British Embassy and the Department of
                        State presented their ideas on the subject of possible claims against Japan
                        (493.11/2062, 2076).</note> suggestions are offered as follows:</p>
                <p>Evacuated Americans should file with the Consulate inventories of property and
                    best possible evidence as to exact location, quantity, and value of destroyed,
                    looted, abandoned, or occupied property for which they may desire indemnity. In
                    the case of those nationals and concerns who expect to remain on the ground
                    unless forced to abandon their properties, it is of essential importance that
                    they take immediate steps to make a careful inventory of their properties and
                    that this inventory be supported by competent corroborative evidence, if
                    procurable, and sworn to before the American Consulate. Where possible,
                    corroborative evidence of eyewitnesses as to the destruction, looting, or forced
                    abandonment, or occupation of property should be obtained and especially should
                    effort be made to identify the persons or forces occupying or responsible for
                    the losses or damages. Bills of sale, receipts, or other documents tending to
                    establish the quantity <pb facs="0295" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/> and value of
                    the property should be obtained or if already in the possession of claimants
                    should be retained for future reference. Particular stress should be laid upon
                    the necessity for first-hand evidence to establish the identity of the force or
                    forces or individuals who caused the losses, and the extent of the losses. Where
                    any goods or properties are taken over under requisition by either Japanese or
                    Chinese authorities, requisition receipts should be obtained wherever
                    possible.</p>
                <p>In personal injury or death cases, evidence should be obtained whenever possible
                    as to the identity of the persons or forces that caused the injury or death, and
                    the sworn statements of persons, including attending physicians, who can testify
                    of their own knowledge as to the injuries or their effects, or as to the death
                    and its causes, should be obtained.</p>
                <p>Please inform Peiping and consular offices in China, exclusive of Manchuria.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
