<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commander in Chief of the United States Asiatic Fleet ( (Yarnell) ) to
                    the Chief of Naval Operations ( (Leahy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d335</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">335</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-09-06T08:31:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-09-06T08:31:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recb140a4efc2e771d" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Warships</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-09-06T08:31:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-09-06T08:31:00-05:00" n="335"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d335">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/9934: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief of the United States Asiatic Fleet</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Yarnell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Chief of Naval Operations</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Leahy</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="8" xml:id="d335fn8">Copy transmitted to the Department by
                        the Navy Department.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-09-06T21:31:00+08:00"
                            >September 6, 1937—9:31 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received September 6—7:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>0006. The following letter was received from Admiral Hasegawa yesterday addressed
                    to American, British and French Admirals: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“My Dear Admirals: I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your
                            letter of September 4th in which you jointly draw my attention to
                            serious consequences of the artillery duel of September 3d and suggested
                            the removal of both Japanese and Chinese forces to certain points in
                            order to safeguard the foreign lives and property.</p>
                        <p>I wish to state in reply that in view of the possibility of renewed
                            attacks by the Chinese forces from outside the proposed demilitarized
                            zone, and the defensive measures our warships will have to take in such
                            event, the withdrawal of the Japanese and Chinese forces from the area
                            such as you suggest will in no way effectively avoid the danger to which
                            lives and property of the foreign area are exposed.</p>
                        <p>However, should you see your way to exert your influence to get the
                            Chinese to agree to the complete evacuation of their armed forces
                            (including the plain clothed snipers) from the undermentioned zone which
                            I suggest, I shall be ready on my part to consider the nonbombardment of
                            Pootung and Nantao by our men-of-war stationed above section 7.</p>
                        <p>I have the honour to be, your obedient servant, (signed) Kiyoshi
                            Hasegawa, Commander in Chief, the Imperial Japanese Third Fleet.</p>
                        <p>Suggested area.</p>
                        <p>Those parts of Pootung and Nantao within a radius of 6 kilometers from
                            the Pootung point starting from the neighborhood of the International
                            Dockyard (Wo Foong) on the right bank of the Whangpoo, extending as far
                            as the southern border of the French Concession.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The following reply will be sent: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Dear Admiral Hasegawa: We have the honor to acknowledge receipt of your
                            letter of 5 September in answer to our note of 4 September, recommending
                            and requesting that Japanese naval forces withdraw below section 7 of
                            the river and that Chinese forces in Pootung withdraw to the eastward of
                            Pootung Road and south of Changkaou Creek. The senior Italian naval
                            representative in Shanghai would like it understood that he approves the
                            recommendation and request contained in our note of 4 September and
                            would like to be considered as having signed that note.</p>
                        <p>We have considered your letter and would like to make the following
                            observations: Whereas you on your part are proposing that the Chinese
                            withdraw from a large area, you, yourself, are not offering any
                            corresponding withdrawal of your forces. Moreover, it is not clear to us
                            why you consider that our proposal would in no way effectively avoid the
                            danger to which lives and property in the foreign <pb facs="0320"
                                n="312" xml:id="pg_312"/> area are exposed. We would draw your
                            attention to the fact that in our letter of September 4th we referred to
                            that part of the International Settlement south of Soochow Creek and the
                            French Concession to which we are endeavoring to prevent hostilities
                            from spreading.</p>
                        <p>We therefore request once more that you earnestly consider our original
                            proposal.</p>
                        <p>We have the honor to be sir, very sincerely yours, H. E. Yarnell, Admiral
                            U. S. Navy; Charles Little, Admiral British Navy; LeBigot, Vice Admiral
                            French Navy; V. Bacigalupi, Capitano di Frengata Italian Navy.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
