<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-19T00:41:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-19T00:41:00-05:00" n="540" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d540">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/9492: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief of the United States Asiatic
                                Fleet</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Yarnell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-19T13:41:00+08:00">August 19, 1937—1:41
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 7:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>0019. Following received from American Consul General, Shanghai: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Japanese Consul General has notified the Senior Consul that the
                                    Commander in Chief of the Third Japanese Fleet has ordered the
                                    closing of section 6, 7 and 8 of the river to Chinese vessels
                                    between 1900 and 0500 and that other vessels should notify the
                                    Japanese of their movements in advance in order to avoid any
                                    misunderstanding.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Following reply made to Japanese Commander in Chief via American Consul
                            General: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The American Naval Commander in Chief has considered the oral
                                    message received by the American Consul General from the
                                    Japanese Consul General through the Senior Consul, stating that
                                    sections 6, 7 and 8 of the Whangpoo will be closed from 1900 to
                                    0500 daily to Chinese vessels and that other vessels should give
                                    due notice.</p>
                                <p>The Commander in Chief observes that Vice Admiral Hasegawa,
                                    Japanese Commander in Chief, has not conferred with him in
                                    regard to this matter.</p>
                                <p>He has guards of marines and blue jackets at properties below
                                    this area to which access is required at any time at short
                                    notice. He must also have free communication with his ships,
                                    both men-of-war and merchants at Woosung at all times of the day
                                    and night.</p>
                                <p>The Commander in Chief will therefore be unable to comply with
                                    the proposal that he should notify the Japanese Commander in
                                    Chief of any movement between 1900 and 0500. In order to
                                    facilitate identification, however, he will arrange [that] any
                                    United States man-of-war, ship, boat or merchant vessel
                                    proceeding after dark will burn her navigation lights and fly
                                    her ensign or national flag as the case may be and will pass as
                                    close as practicable to the first Japanese man-of-war
                                    encountered up or down stream, reducing speed while passing
                                    her.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>British and French Commanders in Chief have sent identic messages.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>