<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d627</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">627</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-12-13T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-12-13T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-12-13T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-12-13T08:00:00-05:00" n="627"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d627">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">394.115 Panay/28: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-12-13T13:00:00+00:00"
                            >December 13, 1937—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received December 13—9:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>767. Newspaper accounts of the bombing of the United States gunboat <hi
                        rend="italic">Panay</hi> and of British ships adjacent to Nanking appeared
                    in late editions of this morning’s newspaper. I have just seen Mr. Eden<note
                        n="57" xml:id="d627fn57">Anthony Eden, British Secretary of State for
                        Foreign Affairs.</note> at his request and, after expressing his deep
                    concern and regret over what has taken place, he said that both he and the Prime
                        Minister,<note n="58" xml:id="d627fn58">Neville Chamberlain.</note> with
                    whom he had been in consultation this morning, were naturally deeply concerned
                    as they felt from their information that these attacks could not possibly have
                    been the result of accident. He said that <pb facs="0499" n="491"
                        xml:id="pg_491"/> a somewhat lengthy telegram of instruction and guidance
                    had been prepared to be sent to Sir Ronald Lindsay<note n="59" xml:id="d627fn59"
                        >British Ambassador at Washington.</note> and would be sent as soon as it
                    had received the approval of the Prime Minister in whose hands the draft now is.
                    He asked me to convey to you the Prime Minister’s and his earnest desire that
                    before any action is taken by the United States as a result of the attack on the
                        <hi rend="italic">Panay</hi> you will see Sir Ronald Lindsay and hear what
                    he has to say. Both Mr. Eden and through him, the Prime Minister also, expressed
                    themselves as being fully aware of the difficulties of our Government in making
                    any move which might be interpreted as “joint action” with the British or any
                    one else. They attach great importance, however, to being consulted before the
                    United States takes any action in this specific instance and they feel strongly
                    that the more closely the action taken by the American and British Governments
                    is synchronized the greater would be its effect on the Japanese Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
