<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-09-20T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-09-20T03:00:00-05:00" n="788" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d788">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.48/1202: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-09-20T16:00:00+08:00">September 20, 1937—4
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received September 21—5 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>735. Red Cross Society of China invited a number of foreign residents to
                            a meeting on 18th September for announced purpose of establishing at
                            Shanghai a regional committee on Chinese and foreigners. I am informed
                            that the proposals discussed would have left the foreign participation
                            without any substantial influence or supervision over the funds from
                            foreign sources. It was therefore pointed out that a representative of
                            the International Red Cross Committee was represented to be en route to
                            Shanghai and that the matter should be studied here by a small group
                            before action is taken.</p>
                        <pb facs="0638" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>While I am unable on account of pressure of official business to
                                take any active part foreign [<hi rend="italic">in this?</hi>]
                                matter, I am in close touch with responsible interested Americans
                                who have consulted me. I hold the view which they share that in
                                preference to direct foreign association with the Chinese Red Cross
                                it would be desirable to establish either an international or an
                                American advisory committee or auxiliary which might be entrusted
                                with the allocation of funds under suitable guarantees and which
                                might also give assistance to the Chinese Red Cross in those
                                activities which are considered worthy of support.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>I would be glad if the foregoing might be put before Admiral
                                Grayson and his views obtained as to the desirability of directing
                                American support to some form of advisory committee or auxiliary,
                                either American or international. It would also be helpful to know
                                the name of the International Red Cross Committee representative en
                                route to Shanghai, when he will arrive, and for my confidential
                                information whether we should be guided by him in determining the
                                form of foreign participation or assistance in the Red Cross
                                organization for this area.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>