<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-10-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="93" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d93">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94 Conference/73c</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Norman H.
                                        Davis</persName></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-10-18">October 18, 1937</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: A conference having been called of the
                                parties signatory to the Nine Power Treaty signed at Washington
                                February 6, 1922, and the Government of the United States having
                                received and accepted an invitation to participate in this
                                conference, you are to represent the United States.</p>
                            <p>You will recall that the invitation extended to this Government by
                                the Belgian Government states that the purpose of the conference is
                                “to — examine the situation in the Far East and to study peaceable
                                means of hastening the end of the regrettable conflict which
                                prevails there”.</p>
                            <p>You will in your participation in this conference be guided in
                                general by the outline of principles made public on behalf of this
                                Government by the Secretary of State on July 16, 1937, and the
                                further statement of policy made by the Secretary of State on August
                                23, 1937.</p>
                            <p>You will have constantly in mind the character and scope of this
                                country’s interest in peace in the Pacific and the Far East as
                                evidenced by the Washington Conference treaties, and especially the
                                rights and interests of the United States under the Nine Power
                                Treaty; the substance and purport of the statement of this
                                Government’s position made by the Secretary of State on October
                                    6;<note n="3" xml:id="d93fn3"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_396"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 396</ref>.</note> also
                                statements relating to foreign policy made by the President in his
                                address at Chicago on October 5<note n="4" xml:id="d93fn4"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_379"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                                        p. 379</ref>.</note> and in his broadcast from Washington on
                                October 12.<note n="5" xml:id="d93fn5"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_400"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                                        p. 400</ref>.</note> You will bear in mind that the first
                                objective of the foreign policy of this country is national
                                security, and that consequently we seek to keep peace and to promote
                                the maintenance of peace; that we believe in cooperative effort for
                                the preservation of peace by pacific and practicable means; and that
                                this country has as a signatory of the Pact of Paris of 1928<note n="6" xml:id="d93fn6"><ref target="frus1928v01#pg_153"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 153</ref>.</note> renounced
                                war as an instrument of national policy and pledged itself to resort
                                for settlement of disputes to none but pacific means. You will bear
                                in mind also that public opinion in the United States has expressed
                                its emphatic determination that the United States keep out of
                                war.</p>
                            <p>It is the hope of this Government that the conference may be able to
                                achieve results which will contribute toward permanent stability and
                                peace in the Far East. In the concept of this Government, the
                                primary function of the conference is to provide a forum for
                                constructive <pb facs="0093" n="85" xml:id="pg_85"/> discussion, to
                                formulate and suggest possible bases of settlement, and to endeavor
                                to bring the parties together through peaceful negotiation.</p>
                            <p>Copies of the documents referred to hereinbefore are attached for
                                convenience of reference.</p>
                            <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Cordell Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>