<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-05-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="223" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                        <head>223. Conversation Between President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and the President’s Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d223fn1">Source: National Archives,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, White House Tapes, Conversation 500–10. No classification
                                marking. The editors transcribed the portions of the tape recording
                                printed here specifically for this volume. According to the
                                President’s Daily Diary, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> met <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> in the Oval Office from 9:41 to 10 a.m.
                                (Ibid., White House Central Files)</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-05-18">May 18,
                                1971</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Kissinger: I called <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, Mr.
                            President, and <persName corresp="#p_VYM1">Vorontsov</persName> picked
                            up the phone.<note n="2" xml:id="d223fn2">A transcript of the
                                conversation is ibid., <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry
                                    Kissinger</persName> Telephone Conversation Transcripts, Box 27,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> File.</note></p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: And I put it on the ground that <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> was—I said, “I need your advice as a fellow
                            bureaucrat.” I said, “<persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> is
                            scheduled to get back to <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> tonight.
                            I had to keep him here. What do you think?” He said there’s no problem.
                            He said let him go. He said it’s—he said this is such an important thing
                            that <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> can’t do it on his
                            own, even the announcement. And he’s probably going around Moscow
                            checking with the four or five key people. He says there’s no
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Exactly. No problem. But we don’t know about a date.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: That’s—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Huh?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: He thinks there’s no—he is in the box that, until he gets the
                            word, he can’t say yes. But he just doesn’t think there is an issue. I
                            just don’t want to speculate, Mr. President, because—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Well—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —there may be a hundred reasons why in their bureaucracy—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah. I think—it seems to me—I can’t see why—or I can’t see one
                            reason in a thousand why they aren’t going to do it. But the point is,
                            you see—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: I can’t see any.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: —you’ve got to—I can’t see. As I said, one in a thousand. I don’t
                            know. Except—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: If they had wanted to stop it, Mr. President, the easy way to
                            stop it was last week, to tell us our proposal is unacceptable.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah.</p>
                        <pb facs="0697" n="664" xml:id="pg_664"/>
                        <p>Kissinger: To get an agreed text and then, at the last minute—we’ve got
                            too many things hanging over them: China, Berlin—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: There’s nothing he can do to find out what the hell the story
                            is?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: No, he said he sent a cable last night. He said it—and he said
                            it’s too early for him to have heard today.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah? Too early? Hell.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Well, there’s a two-hour transmission time, because—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: The problem is that we need to go—we need to know, well—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Well, I think—I have canceled—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: —whether we go Thursday<note n="3" xml:id="d223fn3">May 20.</note>
                            or not. That’s the point.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Well, I’ve canceled <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> for now.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: And you might consider canceling—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: I canceled <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —canceling <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: I did.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: But—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: I’m not going to tell him though that we’re, of course, we’re
                            doing this thing.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: In concrete—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: If the son-of-a-bitch [<persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>] should turn back on us, this would be a—we just
                            can’t—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: No, your—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: —let him know. You know what I mean, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry</persName>?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Your one—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Never take such a chance.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Your one thousand—if there’s even—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —one chance in ten thousand—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Sure.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —why make ourselves look bad?</p>
                        <p>Nixon: That’s right. That’s right. Well, because then they’ll think
                            we’re—we give away the game without getting anything for it.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Right.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: So would a—</p>
                        <pb facs="0698" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/>
                        <p>Kissinger: Well, we’ve kept the <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> appointment with you for 3.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: If we haven’t heard, we can say you got locked in the
                            Congressional battle.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: I’d like to get him out of town, quite frankly.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: But you think you can get him out?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Of course, we can get him out of town without telling him
                            anything.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: I think I’d get him out of town without telling him anything and
                            then come back and tell him. You could even—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Or we get Farley in and have him tell.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Why don’t you get Farley in and tell him?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: All right.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: I think it would be better to get <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> out of town.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Right. Then I just—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: It’s too late to react.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Then I just have to make sure that <persName corresp="#p_SVS1">Semenov</persName> doesn’t say anything to him. And I can handle
                            that.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion of the President’s meeting earlier that
                            morning with Republican Congressional leaders.]</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: And I think after the <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>
                            announcement, which—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: If—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —after all, we’ll have within a week—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: If we get it. If we get it.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Oh, Mr. President, I cannot—if they negotiate for four months,
                            make that many concessions, and then kick it over when an agreed text
                            exists, that would be so unconscionable. They paid such a price for it.
                            They also—they have a truck plant they are negotiating with us, and I
                            arranged for <persName corresp="#p_PPG1">Peterson</persName> to see
                            their man on it.<note n="4" xml:id="d223fn4">See <ref target="#d214fn5">footnote 5, Document 214</ref>.</note> And I—we’re holding
                            that.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: [unclear]</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: It can’t fail. This is just a terribly bureaucratic
                            government, Mr. President.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: I know. I think it’s going to come, but my point is—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: No—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: —I’m just taking that extra degree of caution that I know in
                            dealing with this, in dealing with—</p>
                        <pb facs="0699" n="666" xml:id="pg_666"/>
                        <p>Kissinger: You’re a thousand percent right.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: In dealing with <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>, we must never go
                            unless we got them by the balls.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: You couldn’t be more right.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: We got them by the balls, then we go, right?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: You couldn’t be more right.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion of domestic politics, including the
                            President’s meeting with Republican Congressional leaders.]</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Well, I’m inclined to think, Mr. President, maybe we ought to
                            let <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> go tonight, even if we
                            haven’t got an answer. Because if the thing is—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: With all this, haven’t you got a secure telephone line?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Yeah. I’ll get Farley in and let him worry about telling
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName>. Farley won’t give us
                            any—it also gives <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>
                            something to do—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —with Farley.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Well, I’ll tell you what I would do. I would, I’d let—where is
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> going? Helsinki?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: To Vienna.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Let him go. Then, have him come back because of this breakthrough
                            to get new instructions, and so forth and so on. Why not? He’s got to do
                            it. And then he gets in the play. Call <persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> back. Have that as part of the scenario.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: All right. I just don’t want him to stand on the platform with
                            you when you announce it.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Oh, no, no, no. After I make the announcement?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Yeah.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: You’re right. [laughs] No.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Absolutely.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Nobody. I’m going to be alone on that.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Neither <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> nor
                            you—nor me.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: After what I’ve been through? Hell, no. Not <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>. Nobody. I’m going to do it
                            myself. I’m just going to—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Because <persName corresp="#p_SJA1">Scali—as Scali</persName>
                            said to me yesterday, that if you would have put this proposal into the
                            bureaucracy, they would have all accused you of sabotaging the <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> talks.<note n="5" xml:id="d223fn5">According to his Record of Schedule, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> met <persName corresp="#p_SJA1">Scali</persName> on May 17 from 6:05 to 6:45 p.m. (Library of
                                Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 438, Miscellany, 1968–76) No
                                record of the conversation has been found.</note> It would have
                            leaked <pb facs="0700" n="667" xml:id="pg_667"/> all over town. Because
                            we really did something on these negotiations. We pulled away from our
                            own proposal on <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> and got the
                            offensive link. Well, it’s—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: It’s a hell of a job. I read the, your memorandum. It’s a hell of
                            a job.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Well, Mr. President, if it fails—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: And I know the hours that went into it.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Oh, God, but—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Well, if it fails, we—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: It cannot fail.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Eight years [unclear]—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: It cannot fail.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: If it fails, listen, we’ll burn the house down ourselves. If it
                            fails, I don’t see anything else to do but to fight on everything. I
                            mean, then we’ll have to go out and—and if the Russians turn this, we’re
                            going to have to go out and say, “To hell with elections and the rest.
                            Let’s build up American forces.”</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: It can’t fail.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: “There has to be more taxes—”</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: They’re not that stupid, Mr. President. If they wanted it to
                            fail, after having made six major concessions, for them to let it fail
                            now, would be nuts. It—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Did they make them? Or did <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> make them?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Oh, no. They are—<persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> always has a note. This is why I’m so
                            confident, because <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, if
                            he had the slightest doubt about the date—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Hm-hmm.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —would tell me there’s a problem. All he is telling me—what he
                            says is, <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>—he says
                                <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> was out of town,
                                <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> can’t set the date
                            alone, and he’s now going around town talking to the senior government
                            officials because they don’t want to call a new government meeting. That
                            would be too time-consuming.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion of domestic politics.]</p>
                        <p>Nixon: By God, if we can get this <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>
                            thing, this will really make these bastards look like a bunch of cheap
                            politicians and cowards—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Oh, that’s why it’s so important, Mr. President, because—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: That’s why we’ve got to get—I wish [unclear]—I know I was the one
                            who wanted that word changed but—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: I don’t think that’s the thing.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: —that’s denial or the—</p>
                        <pb facs="0701" n="668" xml:id="pg_668"/>
                        <p>Kissinger: I think <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>—I
                            don’t think <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> has the—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: It may be that they, however, they could be—the only danger we
                            have is this: they could be looking at the—they have people. Look,
                            they’re Communists. They have an American section analyzing American
                            opinion. They also have American agents over here. You got a fellow like
                                <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Joe Kraft</persName>, who’s a slimy
                            son-of-a-bitch, constantly saying, “<persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> can’t get along with the Russians.” Now, it just
                            may be they decided they could—that is what could move them, those great
                            historical facts.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Yeah, but if they do that, they also know that they won’t get
                            a [Berlin] agreement.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Well, if they know that. That’s—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: If [laughs]—Mr. President, I’m going to do a memo for you
                            summing up what we did on Berlin,<note n="6" xml:id="d223fn6">No such
                                memorandum has been found.</note> because if you think this is—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Do they think—does <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                            know that we’ll flush it?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Oh, yeah.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Listen, don’t worry. There ain’t going to be no doubt about
                            flushing it. I’m not going to—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>—<persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said to me last week that,
                            that I’m the toughest fellow he’s negotiated with since he’s come here,
                            and he says his government is just up a tree, because they’ll—because I
                            fight over every word. Now, basically, you know, I’m sure they’re
                            irritated with me. On the other hand, that’s what they respect.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: That’s what they do. They fight over every word.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: I don’t—it’s that word, Mr. President. Maybe we should have
                            let it go. But I think for them to announce—what I am afraid happened is
                            not the word. Basically, that announcement, which they drafted
                            themselves, is a mistake—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: [unclear]</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —from their point of view. The word is nothing. But the
                            announcement is where they made their mistake. And I am afraid what
                            happened is that <persName corresp="#p_SVS1">Semenov</persName> came
                            back to Moscow from Vienna, saw that announcement, and said, “You
                            idiots, you gave away too much.” That’s what worries me, because that
                            announcement gives us more than we asked for. Even I didn’t have the
                            heart to say—to use the word “agree,” “agree.”</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Hm-hmm.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: That’s the—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Oh, well, I think—I don’t think they can—</p>
                        <pb facs="0702" n="669" xml:id="pg_669"/>
                        <p>Kissinger: But I don’t see—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: I doubt that they can screw around on the announcement.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: But I don’t see how they can pull off from an announcement,
                            which is verbatim the text they gave us. That’s not—I didn’t change a
                            word in the announcement, except put it into English. But I’d worked
                            that out with his own man, with—I mean, with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>. We’ll have it. It’s too far down the
                            track.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion of domestic politics.]</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: By this time tomorrow, we will have heard. No question. They
                            just cannot not do it.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: Well, we will have heard what though? You can’t tell.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: We’ll have heard—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: You’ll hear?</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: —that they want to announce it either Thursday or Friday.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: I think you’re probably right.</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: I just—</p>
                        <p>Nixon: And if they say “No,” though, then we know what we’re up against.
                            We’re up against a hell of a—</p>
                        <p>Kissinger: Mr. President, if they say “No,” then we know that we’re
                            dealing with an insane government.</p>
                        <p>Nixon: That’s right.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>