<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-05-21T16:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-05-21T16:30:00-05:00" n="228" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d228">
                        <head>228. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d228fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 491, President’s
                                Trip Files, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, 1971, Vol. 6 [part 2]. Top Secret;
                                Sensitive. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                                forwarded this memorandum and another summarizing the “main points
                                of the exchange” to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> on
                                May 28. The meeting was held in the Map Room at the White House.
                                According to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s
                                Record of Schedule, the meeting began at 5:45 and lasted until 6:35
                                p.m. (Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 438,
                                Miscellany, 1968–76)</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-05-21T17:30:00-04:00">May 21,
                                    1971, 5:30 p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <item>PARTICIPANTS <list>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A.
                                        Kissinger</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Anatoliy F.
                                            Dobrynin</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I initiated the meeting when I saw a news report that the submarine
                            tender and some submarines were going back to Cuba.</p>
                        <pb facs="0711" n="678" xml:id="pg_678"/>
                        <p>I opened the conversation by showing <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> the <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss>
                                announcement.<note n="2" xml:id="d228fn2">The English text of the
                                    <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> announcement, as published
                                in <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> on May 22 and <hi rend="italic">Izvestia</hi> on May 23, is as follows: “In accordance with a
                                mutual arrangement, a detachment of Soviet warships, consisting of a
                                submarine and an auxiliary vessel that are on a training cruise in
                                the Central Atlantic, will pay a friendly visit to ports of the
                                Republic of Cuba at the end of May and the beginning of June for the
                                purpose of taking on supplies and granting a brief shore leave to
                                the crews.” (<hi rend="italic">Current Digest of the Soviet
                                    Press</hi>, Vol. XXIII, No. 21 (June 22, 1971), p. 19)</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked whether the
                            submarines were nuclear. I said no. I said, nevertheless, I had told him
                            previously that the presence of the tender was all that was needed to
                            make Cienfuegos a base and that we considered it inconsistent with our
                            understanding. I recalled the oral note I had handed to him
                                previously.<note n="3" xml:id="d228fn3">Reference is presumably to
                                the oral note <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> gave
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> on October 9,
                                1970. See <ref target="#d6">Document 6</ref>.</note> I said that to
                            make such an announcement the day after our <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> announcement certainly did not help matters and,
                            frankly, infuriated the President.<note n="4" xml:id="d228fn4">No
                                evidence has been found that <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> mentioned the <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss> announcement to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> before his meeting with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> the afternoon of May
                                21.</note></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that it was not a
                            deliberate move and that I had to understand the Soviet system. In the
                            Soviet system, military movements of this kind are taken by the Defense
                            Department. The Politburo keeps an eye on nuclear submarines, but not on
                            conventional ships. He could assure me that the operations of nuclear
                            submarines in the Caribbean had been severely curtailed. Indeed, when he
                            was in Moscow for the Party Congress, the military had been outraged at
                            the understanding at which he had arrived. The military took the view
                            that once the Soviets circumscribed their military movements at all, we
                            would keep pressing and pressing until there would be no military
                            operations in the Caribbean whatever. He did not understand why this was
                            elevated to the Presidential level.</p>
                        <p>I told him that on a number of previous occasions he had pointed out that
                            matters certain to irritate both sides should be avoided. Of course, if
                            the Soviets serviced nuclear submarines or any submarine carrying
                            offensive weapons from Cuba, it would lead to a show-down, and it is
                            precisely for that reason that I could not understand the Soviet
                            position.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said the position was
                            clear—that nuclear submarines and submarines carrying offensive weapons
                            could not be serviced from Cuba and this was understood, but it would be
                            better if we did not constantly raise military operations since this
                            would just get their back up. He could assure me that there was a
                            massive problem with <pb facs="0712" n="679" xml:id="pg_679"/> the
                            Soviet military about restrictions on any military operations, and the
                            understanding had not been well received in Moscow. He looked at the
                            announcement and said he wanted to assure me he did not know about it
                            and indicated that if it had not already been stated publicly, he would
                            try to reverse it. We left matters at this point.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>