<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-07-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-07-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="287" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d287">
                        <head>287. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for International
                            Economic Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_PPG1" type="from">Peterson</persName>) to the President’s Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d287fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 66, Country Files,
                                Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> Backup (Talkers) [2 of 3].
                                Top Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-07-19">July 19,
                                1971</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>SUBJECT <list>
                                    <item>Economic Items for Use in <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> Discussions</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At San Clemente you asked for alternative piecemeal approaches that might
                            be used in your meeting today with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d287fn2">According to his
                                Record of Schedule, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                                met <persName corresp="#p_PPG1">Peterson</persName> in San Clemente
                                on July 16 from 1:49 to 2 p.m. (Library of Congress, Manuscript
                                Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers,
                                Box 438, Miscellany, 1968–76) No record of the conversation has been
                                found.</note></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">1. Kama River</hi></p>
                        <p>I have pressed very hard again to find a separable item and I think the
                            best possibility we have come up with is the <hi rend="italic">Foundry</hi> portion (see Tab A).<note n="3" xml:id="d287fn3">Tabs
                                A–D are attached but not printed. At Tab A is an undated and
                                unsigned paper entitled “The Kama River Foundry.”</note></p>
                        <p>It is a reasonably discrete element of the total Kama River project. One
                            could argue whether a decision on our part to authorize participation of
                            a foundry is similarly discrete in the minds of <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> business. In other words, <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> businessmen would probably have trouble understanding
                            why the foundry was cleared but nothing else. It may be that we should
                            even consider at some point saying that it is mixed in with other
                            non-economic considerations and we don’t therefore expect it to make
                            economic sense. I am presuming the Russians know the linkage in any
                            event.</p>
                        <p>We now have three foundry applications that have an aggregate value of
                            $175 million but there is undoubtedly redundancy here. Thus, in actual
                            practice if all three were accepted, we would probably find the total
                            volume significantly less than this.</p>
                        <p>Even so, if this kind of number bothers you, you can always try getting
                            some Russian purchases of consumer goods and consumer <pb facs="0874" n="841" xml:id="pg_841"/> goods manufacturing equipment. You will
                            remember the argument to them might be that anything that appears to
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> critics to result in a
                            diminution in defense effort (as consumer goods spending might) helps
                            assuage concerns of segments of <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                            public who might feel the Kama River project by itself has too much
                            potential defense content.</p>
                        <p>In case you have any time for more reading, I show in Tab B<note n="4" xml:id="d287fn4">At Tab B is a draft memorandum for the President,
                                dated July 16, entitled “Proposed Exports of Technology and
                                Equipment for the Construction of a Soviet Truck Manufacturing Plant
                                Located on the Kama River.”</note> the current status of the Kama
                            River inter-agency draft you and I agreed we should try to get done
                            soon, including Defense.</p>
                        <p>Also, included is the latest Mack Truck wire to the Soviets which went
                            out Friday indicating the particular questions they have but keeping it
                            open (Tab C).<note n="5" xml:id="d287fn5">Dated July 16.</note></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">2. Control Data Computer</hi></p>
                        <p>The other significant pending application is by Control Data Corporation
                            for a Model 6400 computer (quite advanced) for the Institute of High
                            Energy Physics at Yerevan.</p>
                        <p>This involves <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> clearance and if
                            you decided to go ahead with it, I would assume you would want to impose
                            the same kind of safeguards we imposed on the British on their recent
                            computer deal with Russia (ICL computers).</p>
                        <p>Also, you should know that this is not too far along in the inter-agency
                            process but I suppose this could be speeded up.</p>
                        <p>This strikes me, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry</persName>, as the
                            kind of item you could offer (a) if you were looking for something quite
                            symbolic in the aftermath of the China move, and/or (b) something you
                            could talk about conditionally (i.e. it would take time for example to
                            work out safeguards) in the event you wanted something positive with
                            stalling potential if later it did not seem appropriate.</p>
                        <p>I have talked to <persName corresp="#p_DEEJ1">Ed David</persName> about
                            this and he has written a very brief memo in Tab D<note n="6" xml:id="d287fn6">Dated July 19.</note> that summarizes the
                            situation. Please read it and note he emphasizes inspection safeguards
                            are required but, on balance, he feels it is a reasonable
                            possibility.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">3. Petroleum-Hydro-Cracker
                                Technology</hi></p>
                        <p>While we have no specific applications on this, we do know there has been
                            general Soviet interest in <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                            technology in this field in the past.</p>
                        <pb facs="0875" n="842" xml:id="pg_842"/>
                        <p>On your desk somewhere, you will probably find a letter for your
                            signature to the President on similar technology to Poland.<note n="7" xml:id="d287fn7"><persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                                signed and forwarded the memorandum and attached letter to the
                                President on August 13; <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                                subsequently approved the issuance of the export licenses to Poland.
                                The memorandum is printed in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi>, 1969–1972, volume XXIX, Eastern Europe; Eastern
                                Mediterranean, 1969–1972, Document 151.</note></p>
                        <p>It might even fit your negotiating plans to offer this to the Russians at
                            the same time or even first, indicating you did not want to appear to be
                            discriminating in favor of the Poles. The difference here, of course, is
                            that the Poles have expressed very specific interest in this technology
                            (to me directly and to Dr. <persName corresp="#p_DEEJ1">Edward
                                David</persName>) whereas the Russian interest has been more
                            general. Thus, its leverage potential with the Russians is
                            conjectural.</p>
                        <p>I hope one or more of these is helpful to you.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>