<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>303. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="303"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d303">
                <head>303. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d303fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 492,
                        President’s Trip Files, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>,
                        1971, Vol. 7 [part 2]. Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. The
                        meeting was held in General <persName corresp="#p_HJD1">Hughes</persName>’s
                        office in the East Wing of the White House. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> forwarded this memorandum and another summarizing
                        its “highlights” to the President on August 9. According to his Record of
                        Schedule, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> met <persName
                            corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> from 6:38 to 8:10 p.m. (Library of
                        Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 438, Miscellany, 1968–76)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-07-29">July 29, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>PARTICIPANTS <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Ambassador Dobrynin</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The meeting was arranged at my request<note n="2" xml:id="d303fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d301">Document 301</ref>.</note> because I wanted to have an
                    opportunity to talk with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> about
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Kama River Project</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I opened the meeting by informing <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    of the decisions with respect to the foundry for the Kama River Project. I told
                    him that the decision had been favorable and amounted to about $170 million.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked what that meant for
                    the rest of the Kama River Project, and I replied that we needed another four to
                    six weeks to make up our mind. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    then said, in the usual ungenerous Soviet way, that he hoped we realized the
                    foundry had already been taken for granted in Moscow. I said that that was their
                    problem; my problem was to inform them of the decisions we had made, and
                    considering that it was a unilateral American gesture for which we didn’t ask
                    reciprocity, it didn’t make any difference whether it had been taken for granted
                    or not. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> then changed tack and
                    rather effusively thanked us for the very positive steps that had been taken on
                    trade since the <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> agreement.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <gloss target="#t_SALT1">
                        <hi rend="italic">SALT</hi>
                    </gloss>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> then reviewed the <gloss
                        target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> situation in Helsinki. He thought we were on
                    a positive course. He said there was still some hesitation in Moscow on the
                    number of Safeguard sites, and of course, an <gloss target="#t_NCA1">NCA</gloss>
                    agreement would be a lot easier. I went over familiar grounds with him and told
                    him that that, in effect, meant zero for us and <pb facs="0927" n="894"
                        xml:id="pg_894"/> Moscow for them. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said they were prepared to examine the zero-<gloss
                        target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> proposal. I told him we would be back to
                        them.<note n="3" xml:id="d303fn3">In a backchannel message to <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> on August 3, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> expressed concern about the
                        “leisurely pace” of the negotiations in Helsinki. As <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName> later recalled, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> also raised the proposal of an
                            <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> ban: “From his talks with <persName
                            corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, [<persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>] had believed that it would never be seriously
                        considered by the Soviets because it would require costly dismantling of
                        assets already paid for. He concluded disingenuously, ‘But I will yield to
                        wiser heads’!” (<persName corresp="#p_SGC1">Smith</persName>, <hi
                            rend="italic">Doubletalk</hi>, p. 259)</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                </p>
                <p>With respect to Berlin, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that
                    he thought that we were on a good course and that things were working out
                    exactly as I had predicted. He said it had made a good impression in Moscow.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Vietnam</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I then turned the conversation to Vietnam. I said we had reason to believe that
                    Hanoi was at a very crucial point in its decision. I knew that <persName
                        corresp="#p_LDT1">Le Duc Tho</persName> was returning to Hanoi. While in the
                    last year and a half I had accepted the proposition that the Soviet Union could
                    not do much about Vietnam, I was now approaching him because I thought there was
                    a useful moment for intervention. If the war in Vietnam continued, it was
                    certain that the bargaining position of Hanoi vis-à-vis us would decline. In
                    fact, Hanoi was in the curious position of threatening us with a continuation of
                    the war, at the end of which—whether Hanoi won or lost—we would not be in a
                    position to do for them what they were asking simply because the number of our
                    troops would have declined too much.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that he had had a full
                    report about my meeting with <persName corresp="#p_LDT1">Le Duc Tho</persName>
                    in Paris on July 12.<note n="4" xml:id="d303fn4">A memorandum of conversation
                        and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s memorandum to
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> on the meeting with
                            <persName corresp="#p_LDT1">Le Duc Tho</persName> are printed in <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v07#d236">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume VII,
                            Vietnam, July 1970–January 1972, Documents 236</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v07#d237">237</ref>.</note> He said I had fooled even
                    him. At first he had thought that of course I was going to meet <persName
                        corresp="#p_LDT1">Le Duc Tho</persName>, no matter what the press said; but
                    then when the China initiative was sprung he thought that maybe I had used
                        <persName corresp="#p_LDT1">Le Duc Tho</persName> as a cover for Peking. Now
                    he did not know whether I was using Peking as a cover for <persName
                        corresp="#p_LDT1">Le Duc Tho</persName> or whether the two were independent.
                    At any rate, he received the telegram about my meeting with <persName
                        corresp="#p_LDT1">Le Duc Tho</persName> just after I had had lunch with him
                    to tell him about the Peking meeting.<note n="5" xml:id="d303fn5">See <ref
                            target="#d288">Document 288</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that Hanoi told them that
                    there were only two issues left—setting a deadline and overthrowing the
                        <persName corresp="#p_T1">Thieu</persName> Government. All other issues
                    Hanoi believed could be settled. I said that I did not think the deadline was an
                    insuperable difficulty; <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said
                    that this was his impression also. But with respect to the overthrow of the <pb
                        facs="0928" n="895" xml:id="pg_895"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_T1">Thieu</persName> Government, I said that this was a
                    condition we could not accept. First, because we did not have the power to do
                    so. Second, because it would be dishonorable even to discuss overthrowing the
                    government of an ally. On the other hand, we had made proposals whose practical
                    consequence had to be to give maximum freedom of choice to the South Vietnamese.
                    I recapitulated the proposals we had offered: to set a deadline after final
                    agreement; to affirm the concept of neutrality for Vietnam; and to accept
                    limitations on military and economic aid after a settlement. It was hard to see
                    how much more we could do. I said this would have a profound impact on the
                    election campaign. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said, yes, he
                    had to admit that.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> then asked me how I proposed to
                    proceed. I said that our idea was that we could sign a statement of principles
                    on the points which we had agreed upon at the private talks and then transmit
                    those to the conference for implementation. He asked how the <gloss
                        target="#t_PRG1">PRG</gloss> and the Saigon Administration were going to be
                    handled. Were they going to associate themselves with these principles? I said,
                    yes, they would have to associate themselves with these principles, but I
                    thought this would not be a major difficulty on our side. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said, well, it should be possible to
                    find some formula to do this.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked whether we were going to
                    set a firm deadline or whether we were going to make it dependent on the final
                    agreement. I said we were going to make the deadline start running on the day
                    the final agreement was signed, because otherwise I was afraid their allies were
                    going to delay forever, and we would still be talking to them about the other
                    point while the last American troops had left Vietnam. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said, well, the trouble with the North
                    Vietnamese is that they want everything signed and delivered. It isn’t enough
                    for them to start a political process. They want to make sure that <persName
                        corresp="#p_T1">Thieu</persName> is overthrown. I said that, short of giving
                    them that assurance, I thought the other points were manageable. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that Hanoi had told them they
                    were willing to continue fighting, but he felt that there was a real desire to
                    come to an agreement this year.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Summit</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> then returned to the Berlin
                    talks. He said it was a pity that the Peking trip had supervened, because he was
                    certain that within five days of the preliminary agreement on Berlin an
                    invitation to a summit in Moscow would have been issued. I said that this was an
                    example of the difficulties in our relationships. The President had given his
                    word that he would work constructively for a Berlin solution. After some initial
                    fumbling about setting up the right channels, we had carried out exactly what we
                    had told him. Yet the Soviet leaders had continually started bringing little
                    pressures on us. I said the President would be as willing to make a big move
                    with Moscow as he was with <pb facs="0929" n="896" xml:id="pg_896"/> Peking; in
                    fact, given the nature of our relationships, he would probably attach higher
                    priority to Moscow than to Peking. However, it was important to put
                    relationships on a level that was worthy of the President instead of this
                    constant nitpicking argument.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> replied that we just didn’t
                    understand. The Soviet leaders had really made a decision to see the President,
                    and had just expressed it in a clumsy way. They couldn’t do it in September;
                    October was taken by the trip to France; so they had picked November as the
                    earliest possible date—and instead we preferred to see <persName
                        corresp="#p_MZ1">Mao Tse-tung</persName>. He had to admit, he said, that I
                    could not believe him if he said they were not concerned in Moscow. But they
                    were willing to retain an open mind. He said that the way to deal with this was
                    to proceed on the basis of the future and to see whether we could work out a
                    more constructive relationship. I told him I agreed, and we departed after some
                    exchange of amenities.<note n="6" xml:id="d303fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> met <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> in the Executive Office Building from
                        8:30 to 8:50 p.m., presumably to discuss his meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>. (National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White House
                        Central Files, President’s Daily Diary) No record of the conversation has
                        been found.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
