<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-08-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-08-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="309" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d309">
                        <head>309. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>)
                            to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d309fn1">Source: National Archives,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 492,
                                President’s Trip Files, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, 1971, Vol. 7 [part 2]. Top Secret;
                                Sensitive; Eyes Only. Printed from an uninitialed
                            copy.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-08-04">August 4,
                                1971</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>SUBJECT <list>
                                    <item>Letter to <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Pursuant to our discussion,<note n="2" xml:id="d309fn2">See <ref target="#d308">Document 308</ref>.</note> I have prepared a
                            letter for your signature to Communist Party Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>. The letter is designed to
                            relieve somewhat the concerns generated by the Peking initiative. It
                            attempts to: <list>
                                <item>—note that our dealings with the Soviets and others have been
                                    conducted on the basis of recognition of the legitimate
                                    interests of both sides;</item>
                                <item>—note that the steps taken to improve contacts with the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> are not based on
                                    hidden—especially anti-Soviet—motives;</item>
                                <item>—endorse further improvement in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> relations
                                    and emphasize that tactical considerations should not detract
                                    from efforts to achieve longer term goals;</item>
                                <item>—urge continuing progress in <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> and Berlin negotiations and register concern
                                    about the dangers of the Middle East situation.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> believes that
                            a letter of this kind will be most helpful in deflecting pique resulting
                            from the Peking initiative and hopes to have a letter at an early
                            date.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi></p>
                        <p>That you sign the proposed letter to Communist Party Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>.</p>
                        <pb facs="0948" n="915" xml:id="pg_915"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Attachment</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-08-05">August 5,
                                        1971</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> to Soviet General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName><note n="3" xml:id="d309fn3">No classification marking. <persName corresp="#p_SH3">Sonnenfeldt</persName> forwarded a draft of
                                    the letter to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                                    on August 3. In an attached note to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SH3">Sonnenfeldt</persName> wrote: “Could you let me know if you
                                    would like me to do any additional work on it in the next day
                                    since I am planning to take my family to the beach for a week on
                                    Thursday [August 5] morning.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HBAMJ1">Haig</persName> revised the text; two substantive additions
                                    are noted below. For his memoir account, see <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, <hi rend="italic">White House Years</hi>, p. 837.</note></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Dear Mr. Secretary:</p>
                            <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName> has reported
                                to me his recent conversation with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>.<note n="4" xml:id="d309fn4">See <ref target="#d302">Document
                                    302</ref>.</note> Of course, I am in close touch with the
                                conversations conducted between Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> and my Assistant for
                                National Security Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry
                                    Kissinger</persName>.<note n="5" xml:id="d309fn5"><persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> inserted this
                                    sentence.</note> I should like, in the light of these
                                conversations, to set forth certain thoughts concerning relations
                                between the United States and the Soviet Union.</p>
                            <p>My Administration has from the outset conducted its policy toward the
                                Soviet Union, and all other states, on the basis of mutual
                                recognition and respect for the legitimate interests of each side.
                                This is particularly important in the relations between our two
                                countries, for our size and power impose upon us a special
                                responsibility to understand each other’s purposes and to deal with
                                care and restraint with those issues that affect our respective
                                security interests.</p>
                            <p>In the numerous negotiations in which, I am pleased to say, our two
                                countries are now engaged in various forums, my premise has been
                                that both of us will approach the issues concretely and in a spirit
                                of mutual accommodation. We do, of course, confront many
                                divergences, some due to misunderstanding or inadequate
                                communication but many the result of differing needs and
                                interests.</p>
                            <p>It is clear that in relations between great powers such clashes of
                                interest will not be resolved by superficial formulae nor by
                                attempts to obtain a unilateral advantage.</p>
                            <p>Experience has clearly shown that unless a genuine effort is made to
                                resolve conflicting views and interests to the satisfaction of each
                                    <pb facs="0949" n="916" xml:id="pg_916"/> party, there will
                                either be no agreement or any agreement reached will not last and
                                may indeed lead to new misunderstandings and tensions. No power, and
                                certainly not a great power, can be expected to abide by
                                arrangements that operate to its disadvantage.</p>
                            <p>It follows from this approach that it is futile to expect powerful
                                nations to be swayed by pressure, exerted either directly, or
                                indirectly, through third parties. I wish to emphasize this point in
                                order to avoid any misinterpretation of my Administration’s efforts
                                over the past two and a half years to normalize and improve
                                relations with a number of countries. Thus, the several steps which
                                I have already taken toward better contacts with the People’s
                                Republic of China and, in particular, my forthcoming visit to Peking
                                have no hidden motives. They are designed to end the hostility that
                                has unfortunately existed between the United States and the mainland
                                of China for over twenty years and to lay the basis for relations
                                which will be mutually beneficial and contribute to peace and
                                stability in Asia and the world as a whole. Such a relationship
                                between two peoples which have had a history of past friendship is
                                not aimed at any third country, including, specifically, the Soviet
                                Union. Indeed, I firmly believe that in restoring contacts that have
                                been so long broken, the United States will be contributing to a
                                wider normalization of international relationships.</p>
                            <p>United States policy with respect to the countries of Eastern Europe,
                                an area which we recognize is historically of special concern to the
                                Soviet Union, is likewise intended to contribute to a broad
                                improvement of international relations, to widen contacts and to
                                stimulate mutually beneficial cooperation in practical matters. In
                                shaping our policies toward these and other countries, we raise no
                                conditions concerning the internal order or the foreign associations
                                of the countries concerned; the only test is whether there is a
                                mutual readiness for good relations on a basis of reciprocity.
                                Friendship with the United States, in my view, does not imply
                                hostility toward any other country.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Secretary, as you are aware, I have maintained a close personal
                                interest in the developing relations between our two countries and
                                particularly in the major negotiations in which both our governments
                                have been involved. I have noted with satisfaction that a
                                businesslike manner, constructive tone and spirit of compromise have
                                been manifest in these negotiations. As Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> has already explained to
                                Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, I have
                                felt there has at times been excessive emphasis on shorter term
                                tactical considerations to the detriment of longer term objectives.
                                Precision about details is, of course, important in any agreement if
                                it is to be viable. But I believe we should never lose sight of the
                                goals to be achieved. American negotiators, acting under my
                                instructions, <pb facs="0950" n="917" xml:id="pg_917"/> will
                                continue to be guided by this general approach and will not engage
                                in bargaining simply for its own sake.<note n="6" xml:id="d309fn6"><persName corresp="#p_HBAMJ1">Haig</persName> inserted the
                                    second half of this paragraph, i.e., the passage on what
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> had
                                    “already explained” to <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>.</note></p>
                            <p>The agreement announced on May 20 represented a commitment at the
                                highest levels of the political leadership of both our countries to
                                achieve a successful outcome in the negotiations for the limitation
                                of strategic armaments. My representatives in Helsinki are under
                                instructions to complete an early equitable agreement on <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>’s as well as a parallel agreement
                                on certain measures with regard to the limitation of strategic
                                offensive weapons. We will then have a basis for a more complete
                                limitation of offensive weapons. The final result will strengthen
                                security, permit valuable resources and talents to be used for
                                constructive purposes and, together with progress in the resolution
                                of other differences, contribute to a stable and peaceful world. As
                                the two countries possessing the most powerful arsenals of
                                destructive weapons, we have, I believe, a unique obligation and a
                                unique opportunity to achieve these goals.</p>
                            <p>I am likewise confident that a successful outcome can be achieved in
                                the negotiations on Berlin in which our two countries are joined by
                                Britain and France. I have always believed that constructive
                                cooperation in Europe and world peace generally will be difficult if
                                not impossible to obtain if Berlin remains a source of tension and
                                crises. Peace will not, of course, be automatic once a satisfactory
                                Berlin agreement is reached; but at least one major threat to it
                                will have been set aside. A foundation will have been laid for
                                removing other long-standing sources of strife and tension in the
                                center of Europe. In this connection, my Administration has welcomed
                                the improvement in relations between the Federal Republic of Germany
                                and its eastern neighbors, including the Soviet Union. I am
                                convinced, and hope you share this conviction, that a successful
                                completion of the Berlin negotiations will further accelerate this
                                trend and strengthen peace between East and West in Europe.</p>
                            <p>I also remain deeply committed to the search for a lasting settlement
                                of the crisis in the Middle East. This will be achieved only if all
                                the parties to the conflict there are confident that their vital
                                interests are safeguarded. The task is complex and requires
                                patience. As great powers we have a special responsibility not to
                                undertake any action that would complicate the situation. The United
                                States seeks no uni-lateral advantages or special position. We
                                believe that this should be the attitude of all outside powers.</p>
                            <pb facs="0951" n="918" xml:id="pg_918"/>
                            <p>In assessing the issues which affect the constructive evolution of
                                our relations, one should not overlook the complications posed by
                                the continuation of the conflict in Southeast Asia. As long as the
                                war persists, it inevitably introduces distortion into the policies
                                of some key countries beyond the basic principles outlined in this
                                letter. As Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> has
                                explained to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, we have made an eminently fair proposal
                                for bringing an end to that conflict on a basis just to all sides. I
                                would hope that the Soviet Union would exercise its influence to
                                achieve peace in that area of the world. Such an action would give a
                                great impetus to the policies of reconciliation we intend to
                                pursue.</p>
                            <p>Without reviewing in detail the other issues on which our Governments
                                are in contact, I wish merely to state my expectation that our two
                                countries can make steady progress in improving bilateral relations
                                and in expanding the numerous areas of practical cooperation—such as
                                trade or the exploration of outer space—where our interests run in
                                parallel, where each of us can learn and benefit from the
                                accomplishments of the other and where resources and experience can
                                be shared.</p>
                            <p>I do not minimize the problems that remain and will persist between
                                us. Differences in social and political systems, in historical
                                background and in geographic position will not disappear. But I
                                believe that if our two countries conduct themselves with restraint
                                and display understanding and tolerance of our respective interests,
                                we of this generation will be able to pass on to our children a
                                better and safer world.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_NRM1"><hi rend="strong">Richard
                                            Nixon</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>