<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-09-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="328" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d328">
                        <head>328. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>)
                            to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d328fn1">Source: National Archives,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 492,
                                President’s Trip Files, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, 1971, Vol. 7 [part 1]. Secret; Sensitive;
                                Eyes Only. Sent for information. A notation on the memorandum
                                indicates that the President saw it.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-09-17">September 17,
                                1971</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>SUBJECT <list>
                                    <item>Brezhnev’s Reply to Your Letter of August 5, 1971<note n="2" xml:id="d328fn2">See <ref target="#d309">Document
                                                309</ref>.</note></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Soviet Party Chief <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s
                            letter to you (Tab A)<note n="3" xml:id="d328fn3"><ref target="#d324">Document 324</ref>.</note> is generally constructive in tone,
                            looks to further progress in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-Soviet
                            relations and is clearly intended to maintain the personal dialogue
                            opened in your original letter.</p>
                        <p>At the same time, <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s
                            treatment of China and, to a lesser degree, Eastern Europe reflects
                            Soviet suspicions of our motives. He reiterates Moscow’s criticism of
                            our Middle Eastern and Vietnam policies. Overall, he again strikes the
                            theme that our foreign policies are uneven and in some respects
                            “puzzling.” Not unnaturally, <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> contrasts this with the constancy of Soviet
                            peace policies. This aspect of the letter is the only one with much
                            ideological content.</p>
                        <p>Following are <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s more
                            significant points: <list>
                                <item>—He repeats the Soviet view that an <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> agreement should be the first order of business
                                    in <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>. He stresses the
                                    “principle of complete equivalence” which in practice has been
                                    reflected in Soviet proposals in Helsinki for precise identity
                                    of what is to be defended and of levels of missiles to be
                                    retained, etc. <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>
                                    fails to mention the offensive side of the May 20 understanding
                                    to which you had referred in your letter.<note n="4" xml:id="d328fn4"><persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> highlighted the paragraph, underlined
                                        this sentence, and wrote in the margin: “<gloss target="#t_K1">K</gloss>—Brace <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> on this.”</note>
                                    This difference, too, has been reflected in Helsinki where
                                    progress has consequently been rather slow.</item>
                                <item>—As regards both the <hi rend="italic">Middle East</hi> and
                                        <hi rend="italic">Vietnam</hi>, <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> asserts a direct Soviet interest in
                                    settlements based on the proposition that “the consequences of
                                    [foreign] intrusions should be eliminated,”<note n="5" xml:id="d328fn5">Brackets are in the original.</note>—in
                                    Vietnam, because it is a Socialist country, and in the Middle
                                    East because the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> has
                                    friends there and the region is close to it geographically. He
                                    denies any intent to infringe on someone else’s (i.e., our)
                                    interests. <pb facs="1021" n="988" xml:id="pg_988"/> While on
                                    Vietnam, <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> in
                                    effect says we should accept the other side’s position, on the
                                    Middle East he makes no particular proposal but expresses dismay
                                    that we broke off earlier direct dealings with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. He leaves the Middle East
                                    with the somewhat ominous point that it would be extremely sad
                                    if developments there led to another aggravation or
                                    explosion.</item>
                                <item>—On <hi rend="italic">China</hi>, as noted, he is cautious and
                                    suspicious, taking a wait-and-see attitude.</item>
                                <item>—On <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe</hi>, he asserts a mild
                                    but unmistakable form of the <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> Doctrine—that it is of principal
                                    importance for the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to
                                    “ensure” that no one threatens the security and political
                                    systems of the countries in the area.</item>
                                <item>—<persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> echoes your
                                    interest in improved <hi rend="italic">direct bilateral
                                        cooperation</hi> in trade and various scientific-technical
                                    areas, although making it somewhat dependent on prior progress
                                    in disarmament. With respect to the latter he stresses paramount
                                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>/Soviet responsibility and
                                    urges that efforts in this field should be multiplied.</item>
                                <item>—As a <hi rend="italic">general approach to negotiations</hi>
                                    between us, he urges that basic understandings be first reached
                                    with you personally (he cites Berlin and <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>) so that practical details
                                    can then be more easily solved.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In sum, this letter is a further direct expression of the line with which
                                <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> personally has
                            become identified since the last Soviet Party Congress: emphasis on
                            negotiations and better bilateral relations with us, and a general
                            posture of conciliation toward the West. On specifics, not surprisingly
                            for this type of letter, <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>
                            foreshadows no particular Soviet move; indeed, he generally holds the
                            line on existing positions, and where he does get into more detail puts
                            the onus of movement on us (e.g., <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>,
                            Middle East, Vietnam).</p>
                        <p>The letter itself sheds no new light on the motives of current Soviet
                            policy. But <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s personal
                            identification with this policy suggests that in his judgment dealings
                            with us can be profitable to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                            and thus to him personally. This judgment originally was undoubtedly
                            based on the premise that the balance of power is moving favorably for
                            the Soviets. But it is now reinforced by more defensive calculations
                            stemming from our China policy.</p>
                        <p>Brezhnev’s letter is at Tab A; yours of August 5 at Tab B.</p>
                        <p>No written response is required for now.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>