<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>113. Telephone Conversation Between President Johnson and Vice President and
                    Vice President Humphrey</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d113</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">113</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-03-18T17:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-03-18T17:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-03-18T17:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-03-18T17:30:00-05:00" n="113"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d113">
                <head>113. Telephone Conversation Between President <persName type="from"
                        >Johnson</persName> and Vice President <persName corresp="#p_HHH1" type="to"
                        >Humphrey</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d113fn1">Source: Johnson Library, Recordings
                        and Transcripts, Recording of Telephone Conversation Between
                            <persName>Johnson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HHH1"
                            >Humphrey</persName>, March 18, 1967, 5:30 p.m., Tape F67.09, Side B,
                        PNO 1 and 2. No classification marking. This transcript was prepared in the
                        Office of the Historian specifically for this volume.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-03-18T17:30:00-05:00">March 18, 1967, 5:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>President: Good speech you made.<note n="2" xml:id="d113fn2">Reference is to
                            <persName corresp="#p_HHH1">Humphrey</persName>’s remarks at the meeting
                        of the White House Conference of Governors on Federal-State Relations, which
                        was held on March 18.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Vice President: Oh, thank you.</p>
                <p>President: I think that you’ve got to cut out a little special niche for
                    yourself. If I were you in these briefings, which we’ll be talking to, the
                    editors, mayors, and the rest of them, I’d get myself a little fresh approach
                    like you did today and just say, “Now here are many things I’d like to add to
                    what the President said to the Secretary of State, Secretary of Defense,
                    agriculture, and economics. I’m interested in every one of those subjects. But,
                    you’ve heard that, and I agree with what’s been said.”</p>
                <pb facs="0303" n="263" xml:id="pg_263"/>
                <p>Vice President: Yeah.</p>
                <p>President: “I’ve made three trips to Asia this year, the most since I’ve been
                    President, and this is a pretty large bloc of people. This is where two-thirds
                    of the world live, and a hungry two-thirds of them.” Then I’d take the <persName
                        corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> line on the Huks in the Philippines, then
                    I’d move into Malaysia, then I’d move into the sixth largest nation in the
                    world, Indonesia.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Yeah.</p>
                <p>President: Then I’d go into China, the largest one in the world with 700 million.
                    I’d just say, “Now, if you think we got troubles because we’ve lost 5,000 men,
                    think about the 500,000 men Indonesia’s lost and she’s lost her Communist
                    system, and we’ve rescued it. Here’s what they’ve lost in Malaya, and she’s lost
                    it and we’ve rescued that. Here’s the Philippines; we’ve rescued that. And we’re
                    going to rescue South Vietnam and the Chinese are in a blood-bath with each
                    other. Now, why are we raising so much hell and crying when we have saved the
                    world from Communism.” I just think that little approach tying it on like you
                    did this afternoon, that’s what they don’t hear, they never see, they can’t draw
                    themselves, and why we don’t want to claim that we brought about the Indonesia
                    thing, if we hadn’t given them the money we did, if we haven’t supported the
                    generals the way we did, if we hadn’t been in South Vietnam the way we were,
                    there wouldn’t be any Sukarno demise.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Yes.</p>
                <p>President: Well, while you may not want to go quite that far, you can certainly
                    say that the ones that are closest to it realize the danger, and we have saved
                    Malaysia, and Indonesia, and the Philippines, and China is in a blood-bath and
                    the North Vietnamese are running. Why in the hell we ought to be hollering
                    “pause” or attacking our own men, you don’t know. Now it’s time to stand up and
                    support our own men. Just get you a little patriotic one-minute ending there and
                    I think you could really wrap it up pretty good.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Well, I thank you, Mr. President. That’s what I’d like to do. I
                    hesitate a little bit to inject myself in on these meetings.</p>
                <p>President: I would always wind it up as kind of like the ranking fellow and let
                    me introduce you there at the end and get you a time limitation. We all talk too
                    long, everyone of us. We ought to quit at four. The reason I didn’t want you to
                    talk at 1:15 was that I was afraid they’d raise hell about us talking too
                    long.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Right.</p>
                <p>President: And I’d already busted in and talked too long on highways, but I, oh
                    boy, you’d get knocked out because they would have made a platform all
                    afternoon.</p>
                <pb facs="0304" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/>
                <p>Vice President: That’s right.</p>
                <p>President: On top of that, they had an agreement they were going to give us
                    hell.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of legislation on Latin America, the space treaty, and
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> issues in the context of the security
                    relationship with West European allies.]</p>
                <p>President: It looks like we have prevented a dismantling of <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and we’re in good shape. Now, I think there
                    ought to be two or three things that you ought to do. The first thing I think
                    you ought to do is get you a little chart and have the Defense Department make
                    it in red, white, blue, and green, and colors like they make their charts, that
                    would show, on a page 8 by 10 where you have a number of copies of it, all of
                    the various pauses we’ve had and the reaction. Right under the first pause, the
                    first Bobby <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName> pause—he came April
                    22 and urged it. In May, we put it on. We told them a week ahead of time, and
                    the first day they pitched it back at us. We ought to show that. And then the
                    second pause, we ought to show what that is—37 days. They assured us it would be
                    12 to 20 days, not 15 to 20, it was 12 to 20. The Soviets put it on; they
                    initiated with Mansfield, then with Fulbright, then with Morse, then with Clark,
                    then with Bobby <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName>, then with Mac
                    Bundy, then with <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, then they all
                    sold <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>. I turned it down two or three
                    times then finally went on with it. Had it go 37 days. And the last pause, 6
                    days. We told them way ahead of time when Tet was coming up, and we said to them
                    directly, “Listen, now if you’ll give us any indication whatever, we will
                    reciprocate anything you give us.” But they said “No, no, no, hell no” every
                    time. Now I think you ought to say that to every one of these leaders and you
                    ought to give them this chart.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Yes, sir.</p>
                <p>President: Before you give them the next chart and say: “Here’s what the
                    seventeen nations did. Here’s what the Indians did. Here’s what the British
                    did.”</p>
                <p>Vice President: Yes sir. Just like we had there today, only I get those in small
                    size.</p>
                <p>President: In an 8 by 10 and leave it with them. And I might just take me one
                    about half as big as this, about the size of my chart over there on inflation,
                    in red, white, and blue, take one on pauses, and take one on peace initiatives,
                    instead of putting them all on one. And get you one about a yard—about half as
                    big as <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s; about the size of <persName
                        corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s—in color. You might take that on
                    the plane so if you speak to any universities, you could show it to them, and
                    say, “Now why is this such a one-sided affair? Why does my President have to say
                    to the seventeen nations, yes, yes, yes, and then wait a week, then get
                    denounced, and then have them say no? Why does he have to say to the <pb
                        facs="0305" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/> British Prime Minister and <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> yes and have them say no? Why does he
                    have to say this yes and them no? Now why in the hell don’t you get Hanoi one
                    time to say yes to anything and then come to us. Why do you always attack us and
                    never attack them? They’re the ones destructing.” I’d just fight the hell out of
                    Hanoi, prosecute the living hell out of them, and prosecute anyone else that
                    won’t make them. If they’re interested in peace, by God, let them deliver their
                    client.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Uh-hmm.</p>
                <p>President: I think it’s a pretty good line to just say in your Democratic
                    speeches, that you said the other night when Bobby gave his pause that some of
                    you think that the administration’s against it. But we’re not at all. And since
                    he’s such a big [inaudible] man, we wish that by God he’d stop his bombing for
                    37 days and give us a pause for a little bit.</p>
                <p>[Here follows continued discussion of <persName corresp="#p_HHH1"
                        >Humphrey</persName>’s European trip.]</p>
                <p>President: Anyway, I’d just try to get me a damn good staff and really, really
                    have a good, personal, dignified trip, but to try to really get some good
                    publicity out of it that will make you look very substantive and working on
                    these things and going at the President’s request, and I wouldn’t apologize for
                    one Goddamn thing. I’d just take the offensive on everything.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Yes, sir. That’s what I want to do.</p>
                <p>President: I’d just say our position is that we don’t want to change <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> at all. That we’d like to stay right where we
                    are, that we think every nation ought to do what it’s agreed to do, and we’re
                    going to do it. But it’s pretty hard when the rest of them haven’t come up for
                    us to keep from rotating one division, and our President doesn’t believe we
                    ought to change it at all. We don’t think we ought to have an invitation for
                    these sons-of-bitches to march. He doesn’t forget what Khrushchev told <persName
                        corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName> at Vienna.</p>
                <p>Vice President: No, sir.</p>
                <p>President: And we don’t want to be encouraging them. But they do encourage them
                    when they jump on us out in Vietnam and all that kind of stuff. And the weaker
                    we are the weaker <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is and they ought to
                    have sense enough to know it. And if they think we’re a bunch of country
                    bumpkins, why, they’re just a bunch of Goddamn fools, and they better quit
                    attacking us. I’d get in. I’d tell <persName>Wilson</persName> to get every
                    Goddamn back-bencher he’s got—he’s got the wildest and the radical.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Yes, sir.</p>
                <p>President: I just talked to him about the Goddamned bombing. They got in there
                    last night and they bombed a bunch of our people there and killed them. But
                    nobody says anything about their bombing. They’d stopped their bombing for
                    awhile. Quit bombing the airport in <pb facs="0306" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/>
                    Saigon. Quit bombing the Embassy in Saigon. Quit bombing our bases everyday with
                    these Russian rockets. Goddamn it, if they quit bombing, we quit bombing.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Well, I think I’ll be able to do a bit of work on them.</p>
                <p>President: I’d just take the back-benchers, just say you’re not going to yield to
                    any liberalism, not a Goddamned one of them, that you had this same fight when
                    you were killing Fascists in Germany.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Yes, sir.</p>
                <p>President: Europe, when you had to go over there when the Battle of Britain was
                    on, that you had the ship status with your state and the United States Senate,
                    were raising hell then, and you’ve got them now. But the time’s come when you’ve
                    got to stand up to people who are trying to provoke tyranny and enslave folks
                    and do it by aggression. You did it in Greece and Turkey, you did it in Berlin,
                    you did it wherever it rears its ugly head. Just because it’s not in their
                    backyard there’s no reason to think that by God they ought to let it go off in
                    their brother-in-law’s yard.</p>
                <p>Vice President: Yes, sir. Very good.</p>
                <p>[Here follows further discussion of <persName corresp="#p_HHH1"
                        >Humphrey</persName>’s itinerary.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
