<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-05-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="175" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d175">
                        <head>175. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian
                            and Pacific Affairs (<persName type="from">Bundy</persName>) to
                            Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="to">Rusk</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d175fn1">Source:
                                National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>. Top
                                Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-05-19">May 19,
                                1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Bombing Policy and Possible Communication with the Soviets</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>On bombing policy, the issue remains whether to cut back to the supply
                            routes, with only enough strikes to the North to keep AA in place and to
                            hit really key targets. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> last night told me that he would define the
                            re-strike situation as applying only to those targets that become newly
                            important or that have come back into operation. No one can say what it
                            would take to keep the AA pinned down; General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> has given the judgment that a
                            move south would start at once if we let our policy become known and
                            even if it emerged only by deeds. I come out that we have a reasonably
                            clear picture of what “limited re-strikes” would mean, and that this is
                            sufficiently clear for any communication we make to the Russians, even
                            though it may need somewhat further refinement among ourselves.</p>
                        <p>The <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> alternative,
                            explained this morning,<note n="2" xml:id="d175fn2"><persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_REV1">Eugene Rostow</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>, <persName>Bundy</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName> met to discuss the
                                cutback as proposed in the <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName> memorandum of May 9, <ref target="#d169">Document 169</ref>. <persName corresp="#p_REV1">Eugene
                                    Rostow</persName> sent a memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> on the same day describing the
                                meeting. (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>)</note> would be as follows: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Much heavier armed reconnaissance in Route Package 6.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Continued attacks on fixed targets, including bridges, road
                                    and rail lines, depots, dumps, and <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>—but not including “marginal fixed targets” such
                                    as chemical and cement plants. General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> does agree that we
                                    have “run out of big targets,” so that to this extent the
                                    hitting of fixed targets would have less dramatic public
                                    impact.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>For both armed reconnaissance and previously struck fixed
                                    targets, <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> would
                                    reduce the present 30-mile circle around Hanoi to ten miles and
                                    the present 10-mile circle around Haiphong to four miles. This
                                    would open up road and rail lines in these areas to armed
                                    reconnaissance attacks, and would permit re-strikes on
                                    previously struck targets without express authorization. Within
                                    the 10- and 4-mile limits, express authorization would continue
                                    to be required. General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> appears to believe that there will not
                                    be many requests for targets within the new “envelopes” and said
                                    at one point that he would not urge re-strikes within these
                                    areas unless there were specific military activity.</item>
                                <pb facs="0458" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>In view of the heavy activity necessarily involved in this
                                    program, General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName>
                                    insists that it must include heavy attacks on all airfields,
                                    including Phuc Yen and Gia Lam.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In addition, as a possible expression of his maximum desires, General
                                <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName>: <list>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item>A combination of mining and bombing against Haiphong. He
                                    stated that the over-all program of attacks on road and rail
                                    lines “makes less sense” unless we also hit Haiphong.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Analysis of <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> Alternative</hi></p>
                        <p>Excluding the Haiphong element (e.), the program would have significantly
                            less dramatic impact than the major target strikes of the past month.
                            Nonetheless, hard attacks on airfields would cancel this out, and create
                            a continuing impression that we were hammering away hard. The program
                            really equates, without Haiphong, to Option B in my previous analysis,
                            which I attach for its listing of factors against that Option.<note n="3" xml:id="d175fn3"><ref target="#d170">Document
                                170</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>The discussion this morning did not sound as though General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> and the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> could quickly be brought to accept the
                            program we have all been considering. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> strongly wants a decision if
                            one can be made. You will wish to talk with him, I think, as to how you
                            and he might present the matter. The major difficulty I see in the
                                <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> alternative, apart
                            from its sheer volume, is that General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> regards attacks on the airfields as absolutely
                            essential, and these are what most of all would contribute to a general
                            impression that we had not cut back at all.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Arguments</hi></p>
                        <p>General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> argues the
                            following: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>A marked cutback would be “an aerial Dien Bien Phu,” tending
                                    away from peace especially in terms of Hanoi’s attitude.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>High losses in attacks on the North are more than compensated
                                    by the value of the targets there.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>AA will move south at once when the program becomes
                                    clear.</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>Any cutdown in <gloss target="#t_LOC1">LOC</gloss> attacks
                                    anywhere increases the flow.</item>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item>The focus is already in the South (7300 out of 9000 sorties in
                                    the past two months), and any increased effort would encounter
                                    dispersal and increased defenses so that it would have marginal
                                    effectiveness.</item>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item>A clear cutdown would have a serious adverse reaction among
                                    our military forces on the ground, and especially among our
                                    pilots, and he believes would have the same effect on the
                                    American people.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In reply, we have pointed out: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Heavy attacks on the road and rail lines (which <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> concedes are now
                                    limited because Sharp and others simply do not think they are
                                    worth it unless we hit Haiphong) simply cannot really cut the
                                    flow of the needed quantities of matériel to the south. At most
                                    such attacks make Hanoi pay a steady price in terms of effort
                                    and dislocation.</item>
                                <pb facs="0459" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Even though a cutback does not have much immediate chance of
                                    producing any move toward peace by the Soviets or Hanoi, it
                                    could at least make less likely any marked additional Soviet
                                    decisions. At some point, the climate would exist for
                                    constructive Soviet effort.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>The generalized costs at home and abroad in terms of
                                    criticism.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The counter-arguments are of course spelled out in clear detail in my
                            earlier memorandum, and the capability factors are covered in Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s memorandum.</p>
                        <p>On timing, we have two new elements. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">George
                                Brown</persName> is delaying his departure from London for at least
                            48 hours (this is from the Embassy this morning). And <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> has told <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> that he might not be back
                            until just before <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>
                            arrives here on June 1.</p>
                        <p>The first of these means that we could hit Hanoi power again tonight, and
                                <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DoD</gloss> seems resolved to do this. The
                            second of these means that we <hi rend="italic">might</hi> have a few
                            more days in which to affect the Soviet decision-making process.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">If a decision is reached on the cutback program
                                today</hi>, we could then foreshadow this to
                                <persName>Brown</persName> in any event, and we could consider
                            whether to tell the Soviets.<note n="4" xml:id="d175fn4">In telegram
                                197662 to Moscow, May 18, the Department requested <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>’s opinion on how to deal
                                with the Soviet reaction to the impending air strikes, noting that
                                it was considering conveying to the Soviets that the intended raid
                                was an anomaly. The United States had held off such attacks in order
                                to give North Vietnam a chance to move closer to negotiations, but
                                since Hanoi’s response to the overtures in April had been negative,
                                the United States felt that it had no choice but to resume. However,
                                the United States afterwards would not launch attacks above the 20th
                                parallel. (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>)</note> On the latter, I find <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>’s cable enigmatic.<note n="5" xml:id="d175fn5"><persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>
                                replied in telegram 5009 from Moscow, May 19, that he agreed with
                                restricting the bombing to south of the 20th parallel, but informing
                                the Soviets while <persName>Brown</persName> was in Moscow would
                                cause them to believe that the attack was “another case of our using
                                initiative for peace to cover escalation.” He advocated a direct
                                letter from the President to <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>, whether or not the power plant was to be
                                hit. <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> questioned
                                whether the target justified the risk. (Ibid., POL 27–14
                                VIET/SUNFLOWER) At lunch with <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> the next day, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> described his inability to explain why the
                                United States had resumed bombing, especially given <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>’s statements in London,
                                which in his opinion were “not made out of thin air.” <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> replied that the
                                concentration of <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> troops at the
                                DMZ was “one important reason.” (Telegram 5015 from Moscow; ibid.)
                                The letter from <persName>Johnson</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> calling on the Soviet
                                Premier to join with the President in addressing pressing issues
                                such as Vietnam, the Middle East, Cuba, deployment of ballistic
                                missiles, and the nonproliferation treaty, is in telegram 198583 to
                                Moscow, May 19. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>)</note> Certainly it argues against putting much
                            emphasis on Soviet action for peace into our message. <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> appears to come out in favor
                            of a simple information message, through a letter from the President to
                                <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, I attach as Tab C<note n="6" xml:id="d175fn6">Not
                                found.</note> a revision of the <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> draft, incorporating your own changes and
                            including additional language stating the new bombing policy.</p>
                        <pb facs="0460" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">If the bombing policy decision is not reached this
                                afternoon</hi>, the <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>
                            letter might still stand, but without the additional material.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">If we hit Hanoi power again tonight</hi>, <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> would say not to send the
                            letter at once. I would think Monday<note n="7" xml:id="d175fn7">May
                                22.</note> was right in this event, and perhaps in any case.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">WPB</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>