<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>195. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d195</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">195</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="195"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                <head>195. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d195fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, <gloss target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> Files: Lot 71 D 88, Memcons of Amb. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName>, 1967. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_HPC1">Philip Habib</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1967-06-13">June 13,
                            1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Report on Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName>’s Visit to
                        Saigon</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>H. E. Bui Diem—Vietnamese Ambassador</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William P. Bundy</persName>—Assistant
                            Secretary—<gloss target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPC1">Philip C. Habib</persName>—<gloss
                            target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> had returned from
                        three weeks in Saigon on the night of Monday, June 12. The Prime Minister
                        had instructed him to come in and “report” to us on recent events in Saigon.
                        The Prime Minister had asked him to get back to Saigon within a week or so.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> was hoping to stay a little
                        longer in Washington before returning.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> commented that the Middle East
                        crisis appears to have ended up in a way which is beneficial to the
                        Vietnamese problem. In his view Hanoi had been in a hurry to back the Arabs,
                        not having expected the Israelis to move so quickly. There may be some
                        inclination to put the blame on the Russians. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> believed that the Middle Eastern crisis had opened the
                        eyes of some of the international critics of American policy who would now
                        have to think things over more carefully. During a stopover in Tokyo he had
                        received the distinct impression from conversations with government
                        officials and Parliamentarians that they now feel that while it is easy to
                        criticize American policy it is not so easy to find a solution. This was
                        related to Middle East developments and many people who are critical of
                        American support for Viet-Nam urged US intervention in Israel. At any rate
                        attention was focused on the Middle East and if the Vietnamese situation
                        didn’t tense up this might provide time for the situation in Viet-Nam to
                        improve. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> clarified this remark by
                        referring to the concentration of official and press criticism on the
                        performance of the Vietnamese Army. Unfavorable remarks about the efficiency
                        of the Vietnamese Army are a cause of concern to Prime Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>, General <persName corresp="#p_CVV1"
                            >Vien</persName> and others. Basically, the criticism has focused on the
                        weaknesses of the 25th, 5th and 18th Divisions. The Prime Minister would
                        like to solve the problem but it is becoming something of a cause celebre
                        which makes it more difficult to move against particularly incompetent
                        officers. Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> asked whether the incompetence in
                        these Divisions was at the command <pb facs="0523" n="483" xml:id="pg_483"/>
                        level or generally throughout the officer group. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> replied that in the case of the 25th Division the
                        problem was to replace General Chinh, whereas in the 5th Division there was
                        a good deal of talk of corruption which was checked out and which turned out
                        to be that the Commander was not so much to blame as were his underlings.
                        The Prime Minister intended to take measures at the proper time. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> had pointed out to the Prime Minister
                        that the international press knows about the inefficiencies of these
                        Divisions which furthers the impression that Vietnamese troops are no good
                        while <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> troops are in the thick of the
                        fighting. Fortunately press attention has moved away from this problem but
                        it can be expected to return.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that in his observation the
                        Prime Minister was not so preoccupied with politics as to forget about the
                        need for improved efficiency in the Government and the furtherance of the
                        pacification program. His desire to push these programs goes beyond,
                        although it is related to, the need for showing improvement before the
                        September elections. Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> asked if there was a
                        feeling of “attentisme” among the Vietnamese officials in light of the
                        coming elections. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said this was
                        unavoidable but the Prime Minister was trying to minimize it. He was well
                        aware of the need to show progress along all fronts, both military and
                        civilian.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that the problems of the
                        National Assembly were occupying the Prime Minister. It was <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>’s firm intention to abide by the
                        decisions of the Assembly and to work in full cooperation with it. At the
                        present time the members of the Assembly are emotional in their attitudes
                        and it is difficult to get a consensus but <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> was going to work with and through the Assembly. There
                        were a number of issues involving strong feelings on the part of the
                        Directorate and the Assembly. On the question of the requirement for a
                        Presidential candidate to be presented by thirty elected representatives,
                        this was no problem for <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> who could
                        get thirty or more. The Directorate, however, opposed the measure as did the
                        Catholics. <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> was trying to be
                        neutral and <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> did not believe this
                        would be a major problem.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>A second issue between the Assembly and the Directorate involved the
                        question of the Presidential candidates going through a run-off procedure
                        unless a minimum percentage of the vote was secured. The Prime Minister
                        understood the U.S. point of view on the desirability of a run-off and he
                        was basically in agreement. However, he believed after careful analysis that
                        if a run-off were to be provided for at this time it would produce
                        maneuvering which would be detrimental to an honest election. At any rate
                        the issue seemed to be resolved and there would be no run-off.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The date of the elections remained a bone of contention. The Directorate
                        wished Presidential and Upper House elections to be held <pb facs="0524"
                            n="484" xml:id="pg_484"/> on the third of September whereas the law as
                        passed by the Assembly provides for Upper House elections on the 17th of
                        December. The Prime Minister has always wanted these elections to be held
                        together and has made his position clear. There will be further examinations
                        and further discussion between the Government and the Assembly.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that all of this debate was
                        in an atmosphere which had generated strong emotional reaction against the
                        Assembly among certain members of the Directorate and in particular he cited
                        Thieu and Chieu. Some people in the Directorate wished to convene the Armed
                        Forces Congress to over-ride the Assembly but <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> had said that this was impossible. The Constitution had
                        been promulgated and the Armed Forces could not be convened for this
                        purpose. He intends to stick by this opinion and abide by Assembly
                        decisions. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> believes that in the
                        end all the Generals will agree and that the problems will be worked out. He
                        thinks <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> is maintaining as strong a
                        hand as necessary to assure continuing functioning of the Assembly. Election
                        laws for the first round of elections will be ready before the filing date
                        which is July 15. (Embassy Saigon reports filing date is June 30.)</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> asked how things were between Thieu and
                            <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> said he would like to tell the whole story. He had had
                        a long conversation with Thieu and many conversations with <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> and other Generals while in Saigon. He
                        was sorry not to be able to bring back a concrete result. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that when he got to Saigon a
                        number of Generals came to tell him of Thieu’s intention to run. He had
                        asked whether this had been by prior arrangement. After discussing the
                        matter with Thieu, Bui <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> discovered
                        that there was considerable misunderstanding between Thieu and the others.
                        According to Thieu he believed that at the time of the promulgation of the
                        Constitution on April 1, the question of his candidacy for the Presidency
                        had been discussed within the Armed Forces Congress and in an “unofficial
                        way” they were prepared to back Thieu. Thieu then went to the hospital where
                        he had a minor operation and was working on his plans for the campaign. A
                        few days later General <persName corresp="#p_NDT1">Thang</persName> came to
                        see Thieu and said that on the authority of the majority of the Generals and
                        speaking on their behalf, mentioning them by name, he wanted to say that
                            <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> had a better chance to win and
                        Thieu would be better off not to run. This was a blow to Thieu who was
                        flabbergasted listening to <persName corresp="#p_NDT1">Thang</persName>.
                        Thieu thought he had the backing of the officers and now he felt deceived
                        and this was the beginning of the trouble. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> had talked to the other Generals who claimed that it
                        wasn’t true that they had told Thieu they would back him. They had just been
                        polite about their attitude toward Thieu. It was not true that they had been
                        deceitful; they just simply thought that <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> had a better chance. Thieu continued to feel deceived, an
                        attitude which was furthered by ill-considered censorship of his statements
                        by General <persName>Tri</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> had gone to see Thieu to convey the feelings of the <pb
                            facs="0525" n="485" xml:id="pg_485"/> others. He told Thieu that it was
                        not his impression that the Generals were against him but that they
                        preferred to back one man who had the best chance and would do anything they
                        could to get Thieu to change his mind. Thieu said it was a matter of
                        prestige. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> had asked what might be
                        done to repair the situation and Thieu said he would think it over but he
                        assured <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> that he would do nothing
                        to harm the unity of the Army nor the stability of the country nor would he
                        do anything to harm <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>. Thieu said he
                        knew he would not have a chance to win but his candidacy was a matter of
                        conscience. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> then talked to
                            <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> who agreed to see Thieu and
                        beg him to withdraw for the sake of unity. It was <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName>’s definite impression that Thieu had been hurt morally
                        and was reacting out of bitterness.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> asked if this bitterness could be reduced.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said yes, that
                            <persName>Tri</persName> had been told to be more careful and that
                            <persName corresp="#p_NDT1">Thang</persName> and the others were asked
                        to make some gestures toward Thieu for the sake of unity. Nevertheless
                        before <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> had left Saigon he was
                        told that Thieu would announce his candidacy by the 15th of June.<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d195fn2">He did so on June 15.</note> This would not necessarily
                        be a final and formal announcement but it would be firmer than hitherto.
                        Thieu’s brother Kieu had been reassuring <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bui
                            Diem</persName> that even a formal announcement wouldn’t mean that there
                        could be no change and a withdrawal later on. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> felt that this was still possible even given Thieu’s
                        bitterness.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> had asked him to report these facts here
                        and to report them even to the President if necessary. <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> felt that he had to run, that he had
                        been urged by people inside and outside the Armed Forces to be a candidate.
                        These people found Thieu indecisive which was the main reason almost all of
                        them prefer <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>. <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> felt compelled to announce and before
                        doing so he had talked to Thieu. He believed that he had Thieu’s tacit
                        agreement. Thieu had told <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> to go
                        ahead with his candidacy. Seeing that this was after <persName
                            corresp="#p_NDT1">Thang</persName> had seen Thieu he went ahead.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that he was sorry that
                        things had developed the way they had. The issues looked personal and petty
                        but unfortunately human beings were involved. Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName>
                        asked what the outlook was. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said
                        that ideally Thieu should withdraw and <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> would be the only candidate. It was not possible for
                            <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> to withdraw. The organization
                        for his election was being set up and the other Generals would be “deceived”
                        if he withdrew. The door is still open to Thieu’s withdrawal. It depends
                        largely on <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> who has “not broken his
                        bridges” to Thieu as had the other Generals. <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> would have to go to Thieu and the two of them make
                        whatever arrangement is necessary to secure Thieu’s withdrawal. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that if Thieu withdraws the
                        tension will ease. However if Thieu goes ahead out of bitterness <persName
                            corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName>
                        <pb facs="0526" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/> thinks the situation is not as
                        worrisome as we might expect. Of course the military vote will be split but
                        he did not believe there would be any danger to the unity of the Army. Thieu
                        had told <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> and asked him to say in
                        Washington that Thieu will do anything for the sake of unity and will do
                        nothing that could be construed as division. He would take no action by arms
                        or words to weaken the unity of the Army and the stability of the country.
                        So <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> has come to the conclusion
                        that it would be unfortunate to have two military candidates but it will not
                        cause unmanageable divisions within the Army.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> asked how it could be kept from doing that.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> replied that General
                            <persName corresp="#p_CVV1">Vien</persName> will keep the Army aside
                        from the controversy and that <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> will
                        agree to the Army being kept out of the machinery of politics. It is true
                        that a candidate from an incumbent administration will find it difficult to
                        keep that administration out of politics but the Prime Minister would be
                        careful to operate “normally” and this would help ward off any divisions
                        inside the Army and civil administration.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that in addition to the
                        problem of military unity there was also a question of how to conduct fair,
                        honest elections. The Prime Minister was well-intentioned but good
                        intentions sometimes do not control men. There were also problems of
                        censorship with the provision of equal facilities for civilian candidates.
                        On censorship the Prime Minister had definite ideas. He did not believe that
                        the campaign should concern itself with issues that should be avoided
                        because they create dangerous dissension. In particular he spoke of
                        religious and regional factors. In his opinion the candidates should reach a
                        consensus on how to conduct the campaign and then abide by it. As far as
                        censorship was concerned <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> was
                        willing to have representatives of the various candidates on the censorship
                        boards so that common approval could be secured. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> felt that <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> was
                        determined to conduct a fair election as he had just recently assured
                        Congressman Dow and Senator Hart<note n="3" xml:id="d195fn3">Representative
                            John G. Dow (D–NY) and Senator Philip A. Hart (D–MI).</note> but of
                        course intention and ability were different things when it came to
                        controlling people down the line.</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>This led <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> to discuss the subject
                        of General Loan with the parenthetical remark that this was an embarrassing
                        subject but there was nothing to hide. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> said that he had met with Loan in the presence of
                            <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> and discussed the problem
                        frankly. He cited the various rumors of Loan’s activities and the consensus.
                        The Prime Minister had agreed with <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> and had asked Loan to re-examine his machinery with a
                        view to controlling the men under him. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> said that Loan was not a bad man but that he had too
                        many hats and could not control <pb facs="0527" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/>
                        all of his men. <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> wanted an honest
                        election and recognizes the crucial importance of Viet-Nam in following a
                        bad path or setting a bad example for the future. Everyone agrees in
                        principle.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> referred to the Thieu-<persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> problem and asked if a real talk had yet
                        taken place between them. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said
                        no, that he had tried to pave the way but when they met they avoided talking
                        about ugly things.<note n="4" xml:id="d195fn4">
                            <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> attempted to continue his
                            mediation of the dispute. In telegram 27182 from Saigon, June 8,
                                <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> reported that he heard
                            from <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> that Thieu and <persName
                                corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> at some point did talk “amicably but
                            without a solution emerging.” They met each other only with other
                            Generals present, and pledged to talk again. Thieu later told <persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> that he would stand by his promise
                            not to split the military. (National Archives and Records
                            Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                            1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 14 VIET <gloss
                                target="#t_S1">S</gloss>) In telegram 27982 from Saigon, June 11,
                                <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> reported that <persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> stated before he left for
                            Washington that the situation was “under control” and that “no untoward
                            steps would be taken by the principals or those immediately around
                            them.” (Ibid.)</note> There was some attempt at trying to reach a prior
                        understanding but he had not succeeded. He had talked to Thieu about his
                        returning to the Army or taking the presidency of the Upper House but had
                        received no reaction. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> said that
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> had asked if there
                        were anything he could do. At the time <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> felt it was preferable to let the matter be worked out
                        among the Vietnamese. He was wondering if that was still valid or whether or
                        not it would be preferable for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE1"
                            >Bunker</persName> to go further. <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                            >Diem</persName> knows that Thieu had been hurt in his conversation with
                        General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> which he
                        understood as a <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> suggestion for
                            withdrawal.<note n="5" xml:id="d195fn5">See <ref target="#d163">Document
                                163</ref>.</note>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> believed that Ambassador
                            <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> should concentrate on
                            <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> at this stage to get <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> to talk frankly with Thieu, making
                        whatever offers were necessary for an amicable settlement. Once <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> had done this then the Ambassador might
                        talk to Thieu.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>Diem feels that Thieu is acting impulsively. He knows he can’t win but
                        nevertheless he goes ahead. However, there was still room for maneuver even
                        if the public announcement took place and the situation could clear up by
                        the day candidacies had to be filed.</item>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName> then referred to a conversation
                        that <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> had had with Tran Van Huong.
                        The two men had mutual respect for each other and had spoken frankly. Huong
                        had told <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> that they could not be
                        running mates in either order but that both should run.<note n="6"
                            xml:id="d195fn6">Huong announced his Presidential candidacy on May
                            26.</note> They did not talk in specific terms but they came out with a
                        general understanding that whoever wins would consider the other for the
                        position of Prime Minister. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName>
                        thought this would be a good combination but he cautioned against any
                        optimism; that there would eventually be a lot of people around each of the
                        men who would be opposed to this. <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Diem</persName>
                        closed by repeating again that the Prime Minister had asked him to report
                            <pb facs="0528" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/> faithfully in Washington and
                        to give his assurances about the conduct of the campaign. Although the
                        Vietnamese people are in a stage of political immaturity and have suffered
                        from communist actions, it is difficult to have normal elections, but he
                        could assure us that as far as the Prime Minister was concerned they will do
                        their best to get the maximum honesty possible and the absence of blatant
                        irregularities. Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> pointed out that it wasn’t
                        only in the interest of international acceptance of the elections but it was
                        terribly important also from the standpoint of the Vietnamese people who are
                        shrewd and who would know what was going on. Bui Diem said there was a
                        question of equilibrium. If the Government was too liberal or if it was too
                        crude there could be a great deal of difficulty. He hoped that <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> would handle it with his customary
                        honesty and sincerity.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
