<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="199" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d199">
                        <head>199. Memorandum From the Deputy for Civil Operations and Revolutionary
                            Development (<persName corresp="#p_KRW1" type="from">Komer</persName>)
                            to the Commander, Military Assistance Command, Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_WGWC1" type="to">Westmoreland</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d199fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency,
                                Colby Files, Job 80–M01009A, Vietnam Phoenix/Pacification. Secret;
                                Eyes Only.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-06-14">June 14,
                                1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>I’ve been pressing <hi rend="italic">a new concept for attack on
                                infrastructure</hi> in hopes of selling it before our visitors
                            arrive. It is based on a long background of my own study and analysis
                            back in Washington. <gloss target="#t_CORDS1">CORDS</gloss>, J–2, and
                            OSA have reviewed it and buy the concept, though many personnel and
                            other details will have to be worked out.</p>
                        <p>The concept is frankly experimental, but it costs us little to
                            experiment. We have no place to go but up. It is essentially a
                            management structure extending right down to district level. Added
                            personnel needs will be minimal at the outset, and probably available in
                            theater.</p>
                        <p>The new organization gives OSA a key managerial role, but with full J–2
                            participation at all levels. I think this sound, because anti-</p>
                        <p>infrastructure intelligence and operations are primarily a police-type
                            matter, and OSA has extensive expertise. Also, I envisage PRU and <gloss target="#t_NPFF1">NPFF</gloss> as chief exploitation arms. Thus, on
                            the principle of choosing the best “project manager,” I chose OSA. But
                            at each level the operation will come under the relevant commander.</p>
                        <p>There is some concern lest we be setting up two intelligence chains, one
                            for tactical intelligence and another for anti-infrastructure. However,
                            I strongly favor this from a management viewpoint, because the necessary
                            and vital concentration of military intelligence assets (<gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>) on tactical needs has partly been at the expense of
                            anti-infrastructure. Moreover, the duplication is so minimal as to be
                            inconsequential.</p>
                        <p>I intend to personally monitor and if necessary manage this experiment.
                            But I don’t want to start till I’m sure I’m on all fours with you.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KRW1"><hi rend="strong">R.W.
                                        Komer</hi></persName><note n="2" xml:id="d199fn2">Printed
                                    from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0544" n="504" xml:id="pg_504"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Saigon</placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-06-14">June 14,
                                        1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="strong">Memorandum From the Deputy for Civil Operations and
                                    Revolutionary Development (<persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName>) to the Commander, Military Assistance
                                    Command, Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>)</hi></p>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECT</head>
                                <item>Organization for Attack on <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                    Infrastructure</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Purpose</hi>: To outline an improved
                                    organization for attack on <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                    infrastructure.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>: <list>
                                        <label>a.</label>
                                        <item>AB–142, the Combined Campaign Plan, highlights
                                            destruction of the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                            infrastructure as a necessary component of revolutionary
                                            development.</item>
                                        <label>b.</label>
                                        <item>MRD and supporting <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                            documents describing concepts for revolutionary
                                            development also focus on destruction of the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> infrastructure as a basic
                                            task.</item>
                                        <label>c.</label>
                                        <item><gloss target="#t_RD1">RD</gloss> teams are instructed
                                            to “root out the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                            infrastructure”.</item>
                                        <label>d.</label>
                                        <item>You have recently emphasized, on several occasions,
                                            the need for a better approach to this key problem
                                            area.</item>
                                        <label>e.</label>
                                        <item>Nevertheless, an integrated, organized attack on the
                                                <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> infrastructure has
                                            not been mounted countrywide.</item>
                                        <label>f.</label>
                                        <item>In contrast to the greatly improved tactical
                                            intelligence which has materially aided anti-main force
                                            operations, results against the infrastructure leave
                                            much to be desired. CT 4, organized as part of Operation
                                            Fairfax, has pulled together at a high level and for a
                                            limited area most of the anti-infrastructure
                                            intelligence organizations. But overall results against
                                            the infrastructure—considering the length of the
                                            operation and size of the troop commitment—have been
                                            limited.</item>
                                        <label>g.</label>
                                        <item>Attack on the infrastructure is not strictly an
                                            intelligence problem, but must include exploitation as
                                            well. While many units and agencies—<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>—are at least partially
                                            involved in the attack on infrastructure, there is as
                                            yet only piecemeal coordination particularly at the
                                            local level. For example, there are only a few District
                                            Operational Intelligence Coordination Centers—modeled on
                                            the Dien Ban experiment. Nor is there adequate tie-in
                                            between intelligence gathering and exploitation.</item>
                                        <label>h.</label>
                                        <item>Because rooting out the infrastructure is an essential
                                            element of the pacification process, I propose to make
                                            it part of Project Takeoff <pb facs="0545" n="505" xml:id="pg_505"/> and to monitor it personally. In
                                            my judgment, attack on the infrastructure is—in both its
                                            intelligence and exploitation aspects—primarily a
                                            police-type measure (see Annex 5 of basic study).<note n="3" xml:id="d199fn3">Tabs A–E and Annexes 1–5 are
                                                attached but not printed.</note> The <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> agency with the
                                            greatest intelligence capability in this field seems to
                                            be the <gloss target="#t_NP1">NP</gloss> Special Branch,
                                            supported by OSA, and the exploitation assets best
                                            suited in the PRV and later a revamped <gloss target="#t_NPFF1">NPFF</gloss>.</item>
                                        <label>i.</label>
                                        <item>Therefore, I had <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                                            in Washington do a study for me on how to mount a more
                                            effective attack on <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                            infrastructure, especially at the critical district and
                                            province levels. I have since personally revised the
                                            study with <gloss target="#t_CORDS1">CORDS</gloss> and
                                            OSA help. It is at Tab E.</item>
                                        <label>j.</label>
                                        <item>A sustained, effective attack on <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> infrastructure requires
                                            primarily better management of already substantial
                                                <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> resources, i.e. pulling
                                            together the multiplicity of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                                            agencies already partly in the business. It must be a
                                            combined civil/military effort, primarily <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> in character, but with
                                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> civil/military
                                            assets in an energizing and advisory role. With the
                                            Mission reorganization, such joint <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> action is now more
                                            feasible than before.</item>
                                        <label>k.</label>
                                        <item>What is chiefly needed is: (1) a joint management
                                            structure extending from Saigon down to district—first
                                            on a “<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-only” basis and
                                            then with full <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                                            participation; (2) a “program manager” at each level to
                                            insure coordinated action; (3) use of <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>’s excellent ADP
                                            system to provide up-to-date target lists to the
                                            provinces and districts and to monitor performance; (4)
                                            machinery to assign these targets to appropriate
                                            exploitation assets at each field level. The
                                            organizational concept proposed to meet these
                                            requirements conforms to the new <gloss target="#t_CORDS1">CORDS</gloss> structure at each
                                            level and to the new integrated chain of command (Tab
                                            A). It is essentially a unified management structure
                                            targeted specifically on infrastructure, but building on
                                            existing assets and organizations.</item>
                                        <label>l.</label>
                                        <item>While the agencies and personnel concerned must be
                                            predominantly Vietnamese, <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> personnel must play the vital catalytic
                                            role. Experience has shown that a small number of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> “advisors” in key
                                            positions can energize much larger <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> operations. By using
                                            existing OSA and MI personnel, added <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> personnel requirements
                                            can be held to a bare minimum of around 164, most of
                                            whom are probably available in theater (Tab B).</item>
                                        <label>m.</label>
                                        <item>The operational concept at the cutting edge is
                                            analogous to a “rifle shot” rather than a “shotgun”
                                            approach. Instead of cordon and search operations, it
                                            will stress quick reaction operations aimed at
                                            individual cadre or at most small groups. Cutting off
                                            the heads of the infrastructure at local levels will
                                            tend to degrade the whole structure. A <pb facs="0546" n="506" xml:id="pg_506"/> three-phase plan for
                                            putting the above concepts into operation is essential.
                                            First concept approval should be obtained. Next the
                                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> side should be
                                            developed. Then the plan should be presented to the
                                            appropriate <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> agencies
                                            (Tab C).</item>
                                        <label>o.</label>
                                        <item><gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> Staff concurs in
                                            importance of revitalized attack on the infrastructure
                                            and in the general concept outlined herein, though it
                                            requests more detailed study of the modest added
                                            personnel required (164 in all—most of whom I believe
                                            are already programmed or could be reprogrammed from
                                            in-country resources) and of the intermediate level
                                                <gloss target="#t_ICEX1">ICEX</gloss>
                                            organization.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Conclusions:</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>a.</label>
                                            <item>As Deputy for <gloss target="#t_CORDS1">CORDS</gloss> I approve this concept in
                                                substance, but wish to see if you have any
                                                objections.</item>
                                            <label>b.</label>
                                            <item>Provided you see none, I will convene the proposed
                                                Saigon-level <gloss target="#t_ICEX1">ICEX</gloss>
                                                Committee, under my chairmanship, to review and
                                                submit firm requirements for personnel, intermediate
                                                structure, and time-phased plans for
                                                implementation.</item>
                                            <label>c.</label>
                                            <item>I further propose to inform Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> by letter of
                                                the action taken. I do not believe that we need his
                                                formal concurrence, though I am confident he will
                                                have no objection.</item>
                                        </list></p></item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KRW1"><hi rend="strong">R.W.
                                            Komer</hi></persName><note n="4" xml:id="d199fn4">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                                    signature.</note></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>