<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>218. Telegram From the Station in Saigon to the to the Central Intelligence
                    Agency</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d218</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">218</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="218"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d218">
                <head>218. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Station in Saigon</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Central Intelligence Agency</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d218fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 14 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>. Secret; Sensitive.
                        A June 26 covering memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_CG1"
                            >Carver</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_RBH1">Read</persName>
                        explained that the reports carried in [<hi rend="italic">text not
                            declassified</hi>] and TDCS DB–315/02242–67 reported <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>’s decision, which was based upon
                        meetings that two of his advisers had with [<hi rend="italic">text not
                            declassified</hi>] of the Saigon <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                        Station. “Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName>, who was
                        of course kept fully conversant with these developments, told Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_HJL1">Hart</persName> he was delighted with the initial
                        apparent result of the advice passed quietly to <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> through the informal channels outlined above and
                        suggested that additional advice to <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> be passed through this mechanism, provided the necessary
                        policy approval is obtained from Washington,” Carver reported. (Ibid.)
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>’s covering note
                        transmitting the telegram to the President, June 26, reads: “Here is where
                            <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> stands on
                            <persName>Loan</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                        >Ky</persName>-Thieu. Could be worse.” (Johnson Library, National Security
                        File, Intelligence File, Vietnamese (South) Elections 1967) A notation on
                        the note indicates that the President saw the telegram.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-06-26"
                            >June 26, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> 8486. Following is the text of a message
                    which Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> approved at 1820
                    hours (Saigon time) 26 June and asked to be passed to the Secretary of
                    State:</p>
                <p>“I have studied the Department’s message of 21 June, received through <gloss
                        target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> channels,<note n="2" xml:id="d218fn2">
                        <gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> Hqs. Message No. 0644. [Footnote in the
                        source text. The cable is printed as <ref target="#d213">Document
                        213</ref>.]</note> in the light of <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                    >Ky</persName>’s decision to rein in <persName>Loan</persName> as first reported
                    in [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                        declassified</hi>].<note n="3" xml:id="d218fn3">TDCS DB–315/022242–67.
                        [Footnote in the source text. The report was not found.]</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>’s proclaimed intentions, which have
                    been reported fairly liberally in the press, will have a salutary effect if he
                    follows through on them in good faith.</p>
                <p>“It appears that, although <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>’s welcome
                    decision to restrain <persName>Loan</persName> was the result of a number of
                    pressures on him, the program which he put forth was in fact one suggested to
                    him behind-the-scenes by some of his close associates. (<gloss target="#t_CAS1"
                        >CAS</gloss> Headquarters has further information on this subject.)</p>
                <pb facs="0593" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/>
                <p>“The fact that <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> was so receptive to
                    constructive advice on this occasion indicates that we would be missing an
                    important opportunity by not insuring that he continues to receive sound advice
                    in the future. What is necessary, in my view, is a more or less continuous
                    consultation with <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> as outlined in the
                    Department’s para 5E.<note n="4" xml:id="d218fn4">i.e., para 5E of <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> Hqs. Message No. 0644. [Footnote in the
                        source text.]</note> This would allow us, for example, to follow up with him
                    to be sure that he actually implements the plans for fair treatment of all
                    candidates to which he has given considerable publicity during the past few
                    days. Unless we do ride herd on him on this matter, however, I regret to say
                    that I have grave doubts that he will in fact live up to his promises.</p>
                <p>“What I have in mind, therefore, is not in any sense an ‘extensive’ program, nor
                    one which is likely to lay us open to embarrassing charges. Within the framework
                    of advising <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> on ways to keep the
                    election honest, we can also give him advice on acceptable uses of his present
                    position in the interests of his own candidacy. If he takes our advice to heart,
                    as I believe he may, we will be much better off having him run a successful,
                    more or less orderly, and reasonably honest campaign on the basis of our
                    behind-the-scenes guidance than we could be if he is left to his own rather
                    unpredictable devices. The latter alternative will almost certainly lead to
                    abuses of power for which, however impartial our position may in fact have been,
                    we will receive rather widespread blame.</p>
                <p>“I agree that part of our continuous consultation with <persName
                        corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> can be carried out via an American <gloss
                        target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> representative, and propose to proceed with an
                    updated version of what the Department has suggested in its para 5. [<hi
                        rend="italic">7 lines of source text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>“As I said in my message of 19 June through <gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss>
                    channels (<gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> Saigon Message No. 8185),<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d218fn5">Sent in <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> telegram
                        7697, <ref target="#d209">Document 209</ref>.</note> I believe we should
                    stand ready to consider giving covert financial help if <persName
                        corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> requests it. However, there is no evidence
                    to indicate at the moment that <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> is
                    actually in need of such help. I suggest, therefore, that consideration of this
                    problem be deferred until the arrangements which I have proposed above have
                    given us a better idea of <persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName>’s thinking
                    about the conduct of his campaign and his plans to support it.</p>
                <p>“On the problem of General Thieu, the passage of time has resulted in the battle
                    lines forming and stiffening, and I rather doubt at this late date that Thieu
                    can be persuaded to retire from the contest. Whatever the effect of his
                    candidacy on military unity, it would probably be counterproductive for us to
                    try to do anything about it. I believe, therefore, that we will be best advised
                    to throw our influence in <pb facs="0594" n="554" xml:id="pg_554"/> the
                    direction of doing everything we can to keep <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                        >Ky</persName>’s campaign reasonably honest and his treatment of other
                    candidates as fair as can be expected. If he then runs the sort of campaign
                    which we would like him to and does not abuse his hold over the national
                    administrative structure, he should increase the respect with which he is
                    already held in many quarters. Given the considerable lead which <persName
                        corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> probably has over any of the other principal
                    candidates, under these circumstances the damage which can be done by Thieu’s
                    rival military candidacy will be held to the minimum and, all in all, we should
                    come out of the affair in September reasonably well.</p>
                <p>“I hope you will agree that, under the circumstances, the modest actions proposed
                    above provide our best hope of realizing full advantage from forthcoming
                    elections. Should the Department disagree with the actions proposed above, I
                    hope you will let me know in the very near future.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
