<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>261. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant (Rostow) to President
                    ) to President Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d261</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">261</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-07-31T09:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-07-31T09:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recakeAztvHvxtY4X" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2013002394"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">MIG</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-07-31T09:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-07-31T09:30:00-05:00" n="261"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                <head>261. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant (<persName type="from"
                        >Rostow</persName>) to President <persName type="to">Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d261fn1">Source: <persName>Johnson</persName>
                        Library, National Security File, Country File, Vietnam, Memos to the
                        President, 6/1–8/2/67, Vol. I. Secret. The notation “L” on the memorandum
                        indicates that the President saw it.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-07-31T10:30:00-04:00">July 31, 1967, 10:30 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Mr. President:</p>
                <p>On bombing and retaliation.</p>
                <p>The Communists are using mortars as their equivalent to our <pb facs="0692"
                        n="652" xml:id="pg_652"/> bombing in the North. Like them, we have hit
                    airfields, barracks, and military installations. These mortar attacks are
                    particularly attractive to them at a time when Viet Cong capabilities have
                    somewhat diminished to make conventional guerrilla attacks.</p>
                <p>The question is, therefore, what additional targets might we add which hurt them
                    and made military sense, in retaliation for their increased use of mortars.</p>
                <p>I surveyed the possibilities over the week-end.</p>
                <p>Here, in order of priority, are some possibilities.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—<hi rend="italic">Phuc Yen and Gia Lam airfields</hi>. These are <gloss
                            target="#t_MIG1">MIG</gloss> bases and Gia Lam is an international
                        airport, similar to the one attacked near Saigon.</item>
                    <item>—<hi rend="italic">Red River bridge</hi>. A mile long. With special care
                        should be attackable without significant civilian casualties. Fits the
                        transport offensive now being mounted.</item>
                    <item>—<hi rend="italic">The three Hanoi radio stations</hi>. The military case
                        is not strong; although they are the source of vicious propaganda throughout
                        Southeast Asia, including Northeast Thailand. They are all out in the
                        country and would involve virtually no civilian casualties. (I, personally,
                        have always thought pretty well of these targets because radio Hanoi is a
                        symbol of the regime’s power and regional pretensions. Some of the
                        Intelligence people say they would miss the broadcasts as a source of
                        information.)</item>
                    <item>—<hi rend="italic">Ministry of National Defense</hi>. They have struck
                        quite close to the <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> compound. We’re not
                        sure they meant to attack. But an attack on the Ministry of National Defense
                        would bring the war home to some of the military bureaucrats.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Hanoi <gloss target="#t_TPP1">TPP</gloss> is ripe for re-attack when other
                    conditions are ripe; but having been attacked before would not be a sign of our
                    upping the ante in retaliation for mortar attacks on us.</p>
                <p>Finally, you should know the Air Force is presenting a plan to Bus Wheeler for
                    cutting the transport lines more systematically around Haiphong and seeking to
                    slow down supply movements more effectively. A quite serious and interesting
                    proposal. No attacks on ships involved.<note n="2" xml:id="d261fn2">According to
                        a July 31 memorandum from Ginsburgh to <persName corresp="#p_RWW1"
                            >Rostow</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName>
                        generally concurred with the Secretary of the Air Force’s plan, SM–519–67,
                        July 26, which called for the increased concentration of bombing on LOCs
                        (Alternative C in <persName>Brown</persName>’s recommendations) and a
                        lifting of restrictions on target areas. (Ibid., Misc. Memos, Vol.
                        2B)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WLGLW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Walt</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
