<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>274. Memorandum From the Deputy for Civil Operations and Revolutionary
                    Development Support, Military Assistance Command, Vietnam (Komer) to the
                    Ambassador to Vietnam () to the Ambassador to Vietnam (Bunker))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d274</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">274</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="274"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d274">
                <head>274. Memorandum From the Deputy for Civil Operations and Revolutionary
                    Development Support, Military Assistance Command, Vietnam (<persName
                        corresp="#p_KRW1" type="from">Komer</persName>) to the Ambassador to Vietnam
                        (<persName corresp="#p_BE1" type="to">Bunker</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d274fn1">Source: Center for Military History, Dep
                            <gloss target="#t_CORDS1">CORDS</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MACV1"
                            >MACV</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> Memos
                        to RWK, 1967–68. Confidential. Copies were sent to Locke, Calhoun, and
                        Zorthian.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-08-09"
                            >August 9, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Our most urgent need is to cope with the abominable <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss> press treatment of the election campaign. As we agreed on the
                    phone, the press is managing to put the worst construction on everything. What
                    is basically sheer inefficiency, endemic in Vietnam, they see as positive
                        evil.<note n="2" xml:id="d274fn2">In telegram 2972 from Saigon, August 12,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> reiterated this theme of
                        “unfair” press criticism of the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>.
                        (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 27 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Last year, to put the best face on the Constituent Assembly referendum, I formed
                    a White House task group with Bill Moyers in the chair. My constant refrain was
                    to emphasize one sensible theme about that referendum and to urge keying all of
                    our press handling to it. We picked my theme that the size of the vote would be
                    the best single indicator of success. We deliberately played down our own
                    expectation of at least a 70 per cent turnout of registered voters (we even
                    exceeded that). Instead, we opined that even a 50 per cent turnout would be
                    regarded by us as a major demonstration of growing popular interest in the
                    political process, and a defeat for the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> (who
                    of course were attempting to disrupt the election). As it turned out, most of
                    the press play was on the impressively large turnout. The result was a big
                    plus.</p>
                <p>Admittedly, it was easier to key the last election to the single theme of turnout
                    than it is this election, where the candidates are predominantly politicians
                    rather than mostly faceless men. But we must again pick a few basic points and
                    keep hammering them home in every way in an attempt to provide the press a
                    realistic appraisal of the election. I suggest the following:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Anything less than a 70-80 per cent vote for
                                Thieu/<persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> is a strong
                            indicator of a reasonably fair election</hi> (if our hunches are
                        correct, Thieu/<persName corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> will probably win
                        with less than a majority—thus we would lay the groundwork for a contention
                        that they had hardly rigged an election in which they didn’t even get half
                        the vote).</item>
                    <pb facs="0722" n="682" xml:id="pg_682"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In focussing almost exclusively on the presidential race, <hi
                            rend="italic">we tend to ignore a potentially far more important
                            development—the diffusion of power between the executive and a new
                            legislature</hi>, which under the constitution will have even greater
                        power than the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Congress. Whoever gets
                        elected president will have to deal with a powerful and independent
                        senate/assembly. If the friskiness shown by the Constituent Assembly is any
                        guide, the man in Independence Palace will have at least as much trouble
                        with his congress as our Presidents do with our Congress. By focussing the
                        issue on the advent of a civilian-dominated National Assembly, we will help
                        diffuse the impact of the military retaining executive power.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">We seem to be applying standards higher than those in the
                            US to a country with no experience of democracy</hi>, and one barely a
                        dozen years old. Incumbent American administrations take every reasonable
                        advantage of their position. Can we expect the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss> to do less?</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Although this is a country where nothing seems to work very well, <hi
                            rend="italic">we ascribe every mistake (such as at Quang Tri)<note n="3"
                                xml:id="d274fn3">According to <persName corresp="#p_BE1"
                                    >Bunker</persName>’s 15th weekly report, telegram 2686 from
                                Saigon, August 9, on August 6 a government-sponsored plane
                                supposedly ferrying the 18 nonmilitary candidates for President and
                                Vice President to the first joint campaign appearance at Quang Tri
                                was instead diverted to a U.S. Marine Corps base at Dong Ha. (Ibid.)
                                This telegram is printed in full in Pike, The <persName
                                    corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> Papers, pp. 111–117.</note>
                            to positive evil intent instead of sheer inefficiency</hi>. Experienced
                        US correspondents should know better.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Themes like the above, constantly played and embroidered upon, would go a long
                    way toward putting the election campaign in perspective. Perhaps there are even
                    better ones. But we are faced with a short-term emergency. We have about three
                    weeks to get our points across. We’d better do so quickly.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">R. W. Komer</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d274fn4">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
