<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>360. Telegram From the Embassy in France to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d360</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">360</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-10-20T18:46:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-10-20T18:46:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recOzoeUb5OaUz29X" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Laboratory</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-10-20T18:46:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-10-20T18:46:00-05:00" n="360"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d360">
                <head>360. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d360fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–14 VIET/PENNSYLVANIA. Top Secret;
                        Priority; Nodis; Pennsylvania. Received at 1:49 p.m. In a covering note
                        transmitting the telegram to the President, October 20, 4:35 p.m., Rostow
                        wrote: “Herewith <persName corresp="#p_KH1">Kissinger</persName> brings M
                        and A closer to the facts of life.” (Johnson Library, National Security
                        File, Country File, Vietnam, Pennsylvania) The notation “L” on the covering
                        note indicates that the President saw the telegram.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-10-20T23:46:00+00:00">October 20, 1967, 2634Z [<hi
                                rend="italic">sic</hi>]</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5507. From <persName corresp="#p_KH1">Kissinger</persName>. A very distraught M,
                    A and I had a long conversation at the airport. I was deliberately very hard in
                    painting the Washington mood. I covered all the points of your 56516.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d360fn2">
                        <ref target="#d358">Document 358</ref>.</note> I dwelled particularly on the
                    situation along the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>. I stressed that the
                    current restrictions were among several that we had imposed on ourselves this
                    year without eliciting a response. The current impatience in Washington was in
                    part due to the fact that we had gone several times through a process where
                    negotiations seemed imminent and then proved futile.</p>
                <p>A replied that he did not think it was quite fair to charge Hanoi with failing to
                    respond completely. They had given up the demand for a public declaration that
                    bombing would stop. Their last message was much soberer than the first and said
                    nothing about the withdrawal of American forces from <gloss target="#t_SVN1"
                        >SVN</gloss>. Nevertheless he thought it urgent that he and M see <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVB1">Bo</persName> as soon as possible. I said that the
                    decision was up to him as long as it was clear that the <gloss target="#t_USG1"
                        >USG</gloss> had nothing to say. If they met <persName corresp="#p_MVB1"
                        >Bo</persName> they should understand that four points were of particular
                    concern to Washington: (A) that a bombing stop be followed by prompt
                    negotiations, (B) that these negotiations not be indefinitely delayed, (C) that
                    no advantage would be taken on the ground, (D) the special situation along the
                        <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>.</p>
                <p>M had to go to his laboratory at this point. A said that perhaps it had been a
                    mistake for him never to see <persName corresp="#p_MVB1">Bo</persName> alone. I
                    said that it seemed to me futile to appeal to <persName corresp="#p_MVB1"
                        >Bo</persName>’s personal good will. He was a professional acting under
                    instructions. He would change his position only if the seriousness of the
                    situation were brought home to him. A replied that he would go to the
                    appointment fifteen minutes early. A then called <persName corresp="#p_MVB1"
                        >Bo</persName>. Unfortunately both <persName corresp="#p_MVB1">Bo</persName>
                    and Sung were away and will not return till 2100. They will try to see him
                    shortly thereafter.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Bohlen</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
