<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>398. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-11-14T01:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-11-14T01:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-11-14T01:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-11-14T01:15:00-05:00" n="398"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d398">
                <head>398. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d398fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_AID1"
                            >AID</gloss> (<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>) VIET <gloss
                            target="#t_S1">S</gloss>. Secret; Nodis. Received at 2:23 a.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-11-14T06:15:00+00:00">November 14, 1967,
                        0615Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>11066. Department literally eyes only for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE1"
                        >Bunker</persName>. Ref: Saigon 10987.<note n="2" xml:id="d398fn2">Telegram
                        10987 from Saigon, November 13, reported separately on the aspect of the
                        discussion between Calhoun and Nguyen Van Kieu, Thieu’s brother, on November
                        11, specifically concerning appointments in the office of the Vietnamese
                        President. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15 VIET <gloss
                            target="#t_S1">S</gloss>)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>In conversation with Calhoun November 11, Kieu made a direct request for
                        U.S. financial assistance to support development of a pro-government
                        political party. As noted in reftel, Kieu seemed to be thinking also of
                        government financial support for a “loyal opposition” party. Although his
                        presentation was rather imprecise and confused he gave the impression that
                        the financial aid they would like from us would be used for the development
                        of political parties in general, thus presumably including any assistance
                        they might give to an opposition grouping. He stressed that the problems of
                        initial organization and facilities were particularly difficult and posed
                        requirements for financial resources which were not available to either a
                        pro-government or a loyal opposition grouping.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In terms of loyal opposition, he seemed to be thinking of relatively tame
                        supporters of Tran Van Huong and the Lien Truong and perhaps some Dai Viets,
                        and not the more vocally critical elements, such as the militant Buddhists,
                        represented to some degree in the lower house. As indicated, Calhoun
                        cautioned against trying to create what may be largely artificial groupings
                        which seem to fit their conception of what should be encouraged, rather than
                        permitting natural political forces and trends to shape the structure to
                        some degree. Kieu seemed to have in mind setting up two favored groups which
                        could in effect take turns being the party in power.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Calhoun was of course non-committal about possibilities of furnishing any
                        financial assistance, pointing out the difficulties posed and saying simply
                        that he would look into the matter.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: It is our assumption that Kieu was speaking
                        on behalf of President Thieu since the latter had designated him as liaison
                        for such matters with us. This approach tends to support the conclusion you
                        reached during your meeting with Calhoun and Lapham last week, namely, that
                        it would be useful to obtain authorization <pb facs="1067" n="1027"
                            xml:id="pg_1027"/> for certain funds to be used selectively in
                        accordance with your own judgments on the spot. We recommend that you pursue
                        this idea in Washington and we can then discuss the answer to be made to
                        Kieu after you return. We will certainly need to know more about their
                        thinking and the form we think it should take before reaching a conclusion
                        on Kieu’s request.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Locke</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
