<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-11-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="414" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d414">
                        <head>414. Memorandum From the Special Assistant to the Ambassador at Large
                                (<persName corresp="#p_SF1" type="from">Sieverts</persName>) to the
                            Ambassador to Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_BE1" type="to">Bunker</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d414fn1">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–7 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/BUTTERCUP. Secret; Nodis; Buttercup.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-11-24">November 24,
                                    1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Just as you left Saigon we sent a State-Defense message (State’s 71461,
                                attached)<note n="2" xml:id="d414fn2">Dated November 18. (Ibid.,
                                    <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–7 VIET)</note> proposing
                            that the release of the three sergeants by the Viet Cong in Phnom Penh
                            should be publicly reciprocated by the release of three <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_PW1">PW</gloss>’s by the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>. Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> believes strongly that this should be done, and
                            that it should be kept separate from Buttercup. (Most of the people who
                            worked on this message are unaware of Buttercup.)</p>
                        <p>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName>
                            suggested I set down a few notes on this subject, with the thought that
                            they may assist you in handling the matter when you return to
                            Saigon.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The first point to note is that, up to now, the Phnom Penh release
                                has not been related to Buttercup. Thomas Hayden, the young American
                                “progressive” who played a role in the release, has told us that
                                preliminary discussions for that release began six months ago. We
                                have an indication that the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                planned to release these men earlier, but delayed because they had
                                not shown the proper attitude. The <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                previously released American <gloss target="#t_PW1">PW</gloss>’s at
                                Christmas and Tet last year and at Christmas, 1965. This month’s
                                release may have been their Christmas release for 1967, with the
                                timing advanced because of Gus Hertz’s death<note n="3" xml:id="d414fn3">Gustav Hertz, an <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> employee in Vietnam, was kidnaped by the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> on February 2, 1965. His
                                    September 24, 1967, death from malaria was suggested in a Radio
                                    Hanoi broadcast of November 2 and confirmed in a November 6
                                    letter from Sihanouk to Hertz’s wife. See <hi rend="italic">The
                                        New York Times</hi>, November 9, 1967.</note> and Mrs.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName>’s visit.<note n="4" xml:id="d414fn4">Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName> visited Cambodia earlier that
                                    month.</note> These are all circumstantial indications that the
                                Phnom Penh release was not considered by the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> to be part of Buttercup.</item>
                            <pb facs="1108" n="1068" xml:id="pg_1068"/>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>If at some future time the VC claim it was part of Buttercup, our
                                position will be much stronger if the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> will have already publicly reciprocated that
                                release. We would have firm grounds for insisting that the release
                                of <persName corresp="#p_SH1">Sau Ha</persName>, et al. be matched
                                by additional releases by the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>There is a considerable amount of interest in the press and among
                                the families of <gloss target="#t_PW1">PW</gloss>’s in the idea of
                                reciprocal releases. Thus there is a degree of pressure for a prompt
                                reciprocal release responding to the Phnom Penh release. While our
                                public statements have avoided a commitment on this subject, we have
                                responded to press questions by indicating that past <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> releases have always been
                                reciprocated by the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>From Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LE1">Locke</persName>’s
                                    message,<note n="5" xml:id="d414fn5"><ref target="#d413">Document 413</ref>.</note> it appears that the main problem
                                is that arrangements for a public reciprocal release could
                                complicate our dealings with the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                                on Buttercup. One way to reduce this difficulty might be to propose
                                to the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> that this public release
                                be handled by a military commander in a province, in a manner which,
                                to the extent possible, avoids involving any of the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> officials seized of Buttercup.
                                Suitable releases could be pulled out of a <gloss target="#t_PW1">PW</gloss> camp and freed, with appropriate public ceremony,
                                either at the place of release, or in their home province where they
                                are to be reunited with their families. Under the circumstances, we
                                could relax our past insistence that the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> to be released be likely to return to their units,
                                and defer to the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s strong
                                preference for picking men who have in effect switched sides and
                                could be expected to return to their families.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The above are no more than suggestions, which I hope may prove useful in
                            your handling of this subject. Needless to say, you have my personal
                            best wishes in this, as in your many other difficult tasks.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SF1"><hi rend="strong">Frank A.
                                        Sieverts</hi></persName><note n="6" xml:id="d414fn6">Printed
                                    from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>