<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-07-10T11:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-07-10T11:50:00-05:00" n="53" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d53">
                        <head>53. Notes of Telephone Conversation Between the Executive Secretary of
                            the Department of State (<persName corresp="#p_RBH1" type="from">Read</persName>) and <persName corresp="#p_CC1" type="to">Chester
                                Cooper</persName> of the National Security Council Staff<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d53fn1">Source: <persName>Johnson</persName>
                                Library, National Security File, Country File, Vietnam, Sunflower
                                &amp; Sunflower Plus. Top Secret; Sunflower Plus. The document is
                                undated but references in the text confirm the date as February 10.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Cooper</persName> was in London;
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RBH1">Read</persName> was in
                                Washington.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1967-07-10T11:50:00">Undated, 11:50
                                    a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>Chet <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Cooper</persName> called to double talk
                            following message:</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Cooper</persName> think that <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> may have indicated “a bite.” He indicated to
                                <persName>Wilson</persName> in talks this afternoon (London time)
                            considerable interest in our Phase A-Phase B proposal and committed
                            himself to send it in cable form to Hanoi with his endorsement.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> is leaving London at
                            10:30 p.m. London time tonight and wants an agreed text ASAP.</p>
                        <p>Suggested text (which will be flashed to us) consists of five short
                            lettered paragraphs.<note n="2" xml:id="d53fn2">A Flash telegram,
                                telegram 6456 from London, February 10, 1900Z, contained these five
                                elements slightly rephrased. (National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–14
                                VIET/SUNFLOWER)</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>The <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> will stop the bombing as
                                soon as it has been assured that infiltration by the North will stop
                                and this assurance can be given privately.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Within a few days to be agreed upon by the parties, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> will stop augmenting its forces in
                                the South and North Viet Nam will stop infiltration.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>What the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> does will of course be
                                immediately apparent but no public rationale will be stated at the
                                time.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>What North Viet Nam does will be more difficult to observe but the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> will not demand a public
                                statement that they have taken the required action.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>These assurances can be given and exchanged by the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> directly or through the Soviets and/or
                                British.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RBH1"><hi rend="strong">Ben
                                    Read</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>