<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Wright to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1907p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1907-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1907-05-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recBTfVgprHsl1J9K" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85047074"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Famine</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-05-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="193"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 6625/10–11.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Wright</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-05-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 15, 1907</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 258.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my dispatch, No. 238, of April 25,
                        last,<note n="b" xml:id="d193fnb">Not printed.</note> I have the honor to
                    transmit herewith translation of the text of the agreement recently signed
                    between Japan and China relating to the Simmintun-Mukden and Kirin-Changchun
                    railways, as published in the Official Gazette of the 4th instant.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Luke E. Wright.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0927" n="777" xml:id="pg_777"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 6625/10–11.</note>
                    <head>[Inclosure.—Translation.]</head>
                    <p rend="center">[Official Gazette, May 4, 1907.]</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs—Notification No</hi>.
                        8.</p>
                    <p>The following agreement relating to the Simmintun-Mukden and the
                        Kirin-Changchun railways was signed on the 15th ultimo by the envoy
                        extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of Japan to China and the Chinese
                        ministers for foreign affairs.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Viscount Tadasu Hayashi</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">May</hi> 4, 1907.</p>
                    <p>Gonsuke Hayashi, envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of Japan to
                        China, and Na Tung, Chun Hungchi, Tuan Chai-kwei, ministers of foreign
                        affairs of China, being duly authorized by their respective Governments,
                        have agreed upon the following articles:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                    <p>In connection with the purchasing of the railway constructed by Japan between
                        Simmin-fu (Simmintun) and Fengtien-fu (Mukden), the Chinese Government shall
                        pay 1,660,000 yen in Japanese currency, which is the price mutually agreed
                        upon, to the Yokohama Specie Bank at Tientsin. The Chinese Government agrees
                        to reconstruct and maintain the said railway on its own account and to
                        borrow one-half of the funds required for the line east of “the Liao River
                        from the South Manchurian Railway Company.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                    <p>In connection with the construction on its own account of the railway from
                        Kirin-fu (Kirin) to Changchun-fu (Changchun), the Chinese Government further
                        agrees to borrow one-half of the funds required for the purpose from the
                        South Manchurian Railway Company.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                    <p>The terms of the loans mentioned in articles 1 and 2 shall be determined
                        according to the terms of the loans of the railways in and out of
                        Shanghaikwan, except the provisions for the periods of redemption. The
                        following are the principal points: All the regulations relating to the
                        conduct of the general affairs of the railways shall be determined on the
                        basis of the present regulations of the bureau of railways in and out of
                        Shanghaikwan.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The periods of redemption shall be eighteen years
                        with respect to the loan for the portion of the Simmintun-Mukden Railway
                        east of the Liao River, and twenty-five years with respect to the loan for
                        the Kirin-Changchun Railway. Prior to the expiration of the periods referred
                        to the whole of both loans shall remain unredeemed.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The property and receipts of the portion of the
                        Simmintun-Mukden Railway east of the Liao River shall be offered as security
                        for the South Manchurian Railway Company’s loan on behalf of the said
                        line.</p>
                    <p>The property and receipts of the Kirin-Changchun Railway shall be offered as
                        security both for future contracts of the Kirin-Changchun Railway bureau and
                        for the South Manchurian Railway Company’s loan.</p>
                    <p>Prior to the redemption of the loans the Chinese Government shall not offer
                        the property and receipts of the above-mentioned railways as security for
                        any other loan.</p>
                    <p>During the periods of the loans the Chinese Government shall maintain in good
                        condition the premises, workshops, rolling stock, land, movables, etc., of
                        the railway east of the Liao River and the Kirin-Changchun Railway, and
                        shall endeavor to replenish the rolling stock from time to time in order to
                        meet the requirements of traffic. Should in future branch lines of the
                        Kirin-Changchun Railway be constructed or the same railway be extended, the
                        Chinese Government shall undertake the construction on its own account. In
                        case there is a <pb facs="0928" n="778" xml:id="pg_778"/> lack of funds an
                        application shall be made to the company<note n="a" xml:id="d193fna">South
                            Manchurian Railway Company.</note> for a loan. In case the Chinese
                        Government should construct any other railways on its own account, it shall
                        not be necessary to consult with the South Manchurian Railway Company.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) The Chinese Government guarantees the payment of
                        the principal and interest of the loans. In case of failure to fulfill the
                        stipulations on the date set for payment of the principal and interest the
                        Chinese Government shall, on receipt of a notification from the company, pay
                        the required sum. In the event of the Chinese Government failing to pay the
                        principal and interest in arrears after receiving the said notification, the
                        railways mentioned above and the whole of their properties shall be held and
                        maintained by the company until the said principal and interest shall have
                        been paid. If, however, the amount of principal and interest in arrears is
                        small, a grace not exceeding three months may be granted.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) During the periods of the loans a Japanese shall
                        be engaged as chief engineer. Should the number of Chinese be insufficient
                        for the conduct of the railway business, Japanese shall be engaged. The
                        change of the chief engineer, if necessary, shall be effected upon
                        consultation with the company. Besides this, an experienced Japanese shall
                        be engaged as railway accountant. He shall have full responsibility for the
                        arrangement and superintendence of all departments of the railway accounts.
                        The business of superintending the railway finances shall be transacted in
                        consultation with the (Chinese) director-general of railways.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) Since the railways mentioned above are public
                        highways of the Chinese Government, troops and provisions belonging to the
                        Chinese Government in time of war or famine shall be transported free of
                        charge.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) All the receipts of the railways mentioned above
                        shall be deposited with Japanese banks. The method of paying in the deposits
                        shall be determined on the occasion of concluding the loan contracts.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                    <p>The Chinese Government shall, after the purchase of the existing
                        Simmintun-Mukden Railway, conclude, as soon as possible, the contract with
                        the South Manchurian Railway Company relating to the loan for the railway
                        east of the Liao River. In order to estimate the expenditure required for
                        the Kirin-Changchun Railway, the Chinese Government shall dispatch Chinese
                        engineers and cause them to survey the route in cooperation with Japanese
                        engineers. Within six months after the conclusions of the said survey the
                        loan contract shall be concluded with the company.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                    <p>Both the Simmintun-Mukden and the Kirin-Changchun railways, which are to be
                        constructed and maintained by China, shall be connected with the South
                        Manchurian Railway. All the regulations relating to this matter shall be
                        determined by commissioners to be appointed by the Tientsin-Linyu
                        (Shanhaikwan) railway bureau and the South Manchurian Railway Company.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6.</p>
                    <p>The actual proceeds of the loans mentioned in articles 1 and 2 shall be
                        equitably determined on the basis of the latest loan contract concluded by
                        China with a third country.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7.</p>
                    <p>The Simmintun-Mukden Railway shall be handed over to the commissioners of the
                        Chinese railway bureau within one month after the payment of the price.</p>
                    <closer>(Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gonsuke Hayashi.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>(Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Na Tung.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>(Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chun Hung-chi.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>(Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tuan Chai-kwei.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <date calendar="japanese-nengō chinese-era gregorian" when="1907-04-15"
                                >Fifteenth day of the fourth month of the fortieth year of
                                Meiji.<lb/>Third day of the third month of the twenty-third year of
                                Kuang-hsu (April 15, 1907)</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
