<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-10-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="212" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d212">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Brussels</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-10-16"><hi rend="italic">October 16,
                                    1907</hi>.</date></dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 241.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith the
                            copy in the English text of the bill for a colonial law offered by the
                            present ministry and which is now being discussed by the special
                            committee of Parliament appointed for that purpose.</p>
                        <p>This commission has been meeting in regular session for some time past,
                            and each article of the proposed law has been subjected to rigid
                            scrutiny and has provoked long debates, numerous amendments being
                            offered, some of which are valuable additions to the law and others of
                            an impractical character.</p>
                        <p>As there is no official report of the proceedings it is difficult to know
                            the amount of progress that has been made and what changes, if any, have
                            been recommended.</p>
                        <p>The principal objection of the opposition is to Article XIX, which
                            contains the provision for a colonial council of nine members, to be
                            nominated by the King.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Lane
                            Wilson.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Belgian colonial project.</hi></head>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article I.</hi> All Belgian colonies
                                    shall be considered as possessing a legal status separate from
                                    that of the mother country, and will be regulated by special
                                    laws.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. II.</hi> All legislative power over
                                    Belgian colonial possessions will be held by the King, according
                                    to the present law and with certain known exceptions.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. III.</hi> Such legislation will be
                                    exercised by royal decrees. With the exception of certain points
                                    named in Articles IX, X, and XIX, the decrees will be signed by
                                    the King on the suggestion of the minister of colonies. No
                                    decree is to be considered as law until after
                                    publication.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. IV.</hi> The executive power will
                                    belong to the King. It will be made known by regulations and
                                    by-laws.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. V.</hi> No act of the King can take
                                    effect until it has been countersigned by a minister, who thus
                                    will be alone responsible.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art VI.</hi>. No customs or taxation may
                                    be established or rescinded except by royal decree.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. VII.</hi> The Belgian currency in
                                    gold and silver is to be available under the same conditions for
                                    the Kongo. Any profit resulting from minting extra Belgian money
                                    for the colony will pass to the colonial budget. The King will
                                    reserve the right to strike billon coins for special colonial
                                    use, which will not be current in Belgium.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. VIII.</hi> The budget of receipts
                                    and expenses will be passed each year by the King. But the
                                    salary of the colonial minister and the expenses of the central
                                    colonial government in Belgium will form a special budget, which
                                    will be annually submitted to the Chambers, according to article
                                    115 of the constitution.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. IX.</hi> The decrees approving loans
                                    chargeable to or under the guaranty of the colony, and the works
                                    on extraordinary supplies, will only be taken on the
                                    propositions of ministers in council.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. X.</hi> All cession or concession,
                                    either made freely or for payment, no matter the length of time
                                    either of domanial possessions or of the enjoyment of such,
                                    situated in colonial possessions, must have the consent or
                                    authorization of royal decree. The act which sets forth the
                                    permission must contain the stipulations made in each case by
                                    ministers in council.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XI.</hi> Both civil and military
                                    justice will be organized by decree.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XII.</hi> The functionaries of
                                    judicial law will be appointed and revoked by the King. Their
                                    revocation can only take place at the demand of the
                                    governor-general, whch shall have for its basis reasons foreseen
                                    by decree, and with the advice of the supreme colonial
                                    tribune.</item>
                                <pb facs="0961" n="811" xml:id="pg_811"/>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XIII.</hi> The King may, for reasons
                                    of public safety, suspend in any neighborhood decided upon all
                                    courts and tribunals of civil justice and confide the exercise
                                    of repressive justice to the military.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XIV.</hi> Justice will be given and
                                    executed in the name of the King. Such will be justified. The
                                    King retains the prerogative to pardon, reduce, or commute
                                    punishments.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XV.</hi> The King may delegate the
                                    executive power to the governor-general of the colony. He may
                                    authorize, when the interest or the safety of the colony
                                    requires it, the momentary suspension of decrees, and himself
                                    pass regulations to be considered as laws. But such regulations
                                    having this object cease to be enforceable after the delay of a
                                    year if they have not been approved by decree before that period
                                    expires.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Chapter II.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XVI.</hi> Each year a report on the
                                    administration of the colonial possessions shall be submitted to
                                    the chambers in the name of the King. This report will contain
                                    all the information necessary to explain the political
                                    situation, the economic, the financial position, and the moral
                                    status of these possessions to the national
                                    representatives.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XVII.</hi> The colonial budget for
                                    the current year, as well as the detailed account of the
                                    receipts and expenses of the last financial year, will be added
                                    as schedules to the annual report.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Chapter III.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XVIII.</hi> A colonial ministry will
                                    be instituted. The colonial minister will be nominated and
                                    revoked by the King, and will form part of the colonial council.
                                    Articles 86 to 91 of the Belgian constitution will be applicable
                                    to him.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XIX.</hi> The colonial council will
                                    be composed of nine members, nominated by the King. They can
                                    only be revoked by a decree of the ministers in council. Five of
                                    these members must have already exercised administrative,
                                    judicial, or military order in the colonies, or have managed for
                                    at least eighteen months an industrial or commercial
                                    establishment. The other members will be chosen from the
                                    superior grades in the army, magistrates of the courts of
                                    cassation or appeal, members of the council of industry or
                                    commerce, members or former members of the diplomatic and
                                    consular corps, and professors of universities. The length of
                                    office in the colonial council will be nine years. One
                                    member—open to reelection—will retire each year. No member of
                                    either House of Parliament may form part of the council.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XX.</hi> The colonial council will
                                    deliberate on all matters submitted by the King. The council
                                    will be consulted in all royal decrees excepting in cases
                                    foreseen by Articles IX, X, XIX. The council will give its
                                    advice in the form of reports, with reasons. Decrees passed in
                                    urgent cases will be submitted to the council within ten days of
                                    their date, with an indication of the reason for urgency. When
                                    the project of decree to be signed by the King is against the
                                    opinion of the colonial council, the decree will be published
                                    with an explanatory report by the minister of the colonies. In
                                    case of urgency this report will be published within twenty days
                                    of its receipt of the communication. The minister will preside
                                    over the seances and will have a casting vote.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Chapter IV.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XXI.</hi> The King will make
                                    treaties concerning colonial possessions. The regulations of
                                    article 68 of the Belgian constitution concerning treaties will
                                    apply to the colonies.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XXII.</hi> The Belgian minister for
                                    foreign affairs will manage the relations between Belgium and
                                    foreign powers concerning the Kongo.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Chapter V.</hi></p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">General regulations.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XXIII.</hi> Judgments passed in
                                    civil and commercial matters in Belgium are to be carried out in
                                    the colonies. Judgments passed by colonial tribunals will be
                                    legally executable in Belgium.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XXIV.</hi> Whoever, having broken
                                    colonial law, has taken refuge in Belgium will be judged by
                                    Belgian law. Whoever, having broken Belgian law, has taken
                                    refuge in the colony will be handed over to Belgian justice and
                                    tried accordingly.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XXV.</hi> Functionaries and military
                                    men authorized to accept engagements in the colony will keep
                                    their rank and right to advancement in their former profession
                                    left temporarily.</item>
                                <pb facs="0962" n="812" xml:id="pg_812"/>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XXVI.</hi> With the exception of the
                                    flag and seal of Belgium, the Kongo colony can make use of the
                                    present Kongo flag and seal as used.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XXVII.</hi> All decrees,
                                    regulations, and other acts now working in the colonies retain
                                    their force, except any which the new laws would make
                                    void.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art. XXVIII.</hi> Any proposal or
                                    modification or addition to this present code will, at the
                                    request of the Government, be submitted to the colonial
                                    council.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>