<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador White to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1907p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1907-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1907-10-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-10-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="223"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 3532/19–20.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">White</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-10-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 4, 1907</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 90.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my dispatch No. 84, of the 27th
                    ultimo, I had the honor of cabling you on the 20th of September that the
                    frontier agreement between France and Liberia had been signed, and that I
                    expected to be shortly in a position to send you a copy of that document, which,
                    thanks to M. Pichon’s courtesy, I transmit herewith, and also a translation of
                    the same.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry White.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">franco-liberian agreement.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister of foreign affairs.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Government of the French Republic and the Government of the Republic of
                        Liberia being desirous of fixing definitively the limits of French West
                        Africa and of Liberia, but recognizing that the clauses of the accord of
                        December 8, 1892, concluded to this end are materially impossible of
                        application, have decided, by common accord, not to have recourse to
                        theoretic lines for the establishment of the frontier, but to utilize to the
                        greatest possible extent the natural topographical lines most appropriate to
                        prevent all possible contestations in the future and to assure an effective
                        domination on both sides, and have to this effect designated as their
                        plenipotentiaries to conclude an arrangement— <list>
                            <item>The Government of the French Republic:</item>
                            <item>M. Gustave Binger, director at the ministry of the
                                colonies.</item>
                            <item>M. Soulange-Bodin, minister plenipotentiary, under director at the
                                ministry of foreign affairs.</item>
                            <item>The Government of the Republic of Liberia:</item>
                            <item>M. Frederic E. R. Johnson, minister of foreign affairs.</item>
                            <item>M. J. P. Crommelin, chargé d’affaires of the Republic of Liberia
                                at Paris.</item>
                            <item>The Franco-Liberian frontier would be constituted by: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The left bank of the river Makona, from the entry of this
                                        river into Sierra-Leone to a point to be determined about 5
                                        kilometers south of Bofosso.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>A line starting from this last-named point, proceeding
                                        southeastward, leaving to the north the following villages:
                                        Koutoumai, Kissi-Koutoumai, Soundebou, N’Zapa, N’Zébéla,
                                        Koiama, Banguédou, and rejoining a source of the river Nuon
                                        or one of its tributaries to be determined on the spot at a
                                        maximum of 10 kilometers to the south and in the vicinity of
                                        Lola. In this section of the frontier the line to be drawn
                                        should avoid separating the villages of a tribe, under tribe
                                        (sous-tribu) or grouping, and utilize as much as possible
                                        the natural topographical lines, such as the course of
                                        brooks and rivers.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The right bank of the river Nuon as far as its confluence
                                        with the Cavalry.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The right bank of the Cavalry as far as the sea.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0981" n="831" xml:id="pg_831"/>
                    <p>In case the river Nuon should not be a tributary of the Cavally, the right
                        bank of the Nuon would form the boundary line only as far as the
                        surroundings of Toulepleu; at and to the south of the suburbs of this
                        village the boundary line would be drawn between the Nuon and the Cavally in
                        the general direction of the parallel of this point, but so as not to
                        separate the villages of the same tribe, subtribe, or grouping, and to
                        utilize the natural topographical lines from the intersection of this
                        parallel with the river Cavally, the boundary line would be constituted by
                        the right bank of the river Cavally as far as the sea.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                    <p>In order to keep up an efficacious police along the frontier, the Liberian
                        Government will assume the obligation of establishing a certain number of
                        posts, which the French authorities will have the faculty of occupying
                        should the resources of the Liberian Government not allow them to maintain a
                        garrison itself at that moment. The number and the position of these posts
                        will be determined on the spot by common accord at the moment of the fixing
                        of the boundary; the force of each will not exceed 40 to 50 men.</p>
                    <p>It is understood that the Liberian Government will give the French
                        authorities notice two months in advance of its intention to occupy the post
                        or posts above referred to and that the post or posts will be handed over
                        within five days following the arrival of the Liberian police forces.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                    <p>Navigation on the waterways forming the frontier shall be free and open to
                        traffic, both to French citizens and to Liberian subjects and citizens.</p>
                    <p>France will have the right to undertake, at its own expense, in the course or
                        on either bank of the rivers in question, works which might be necessary to
                        render them navigable or improve their navigability, it being always
                        understood that this fact will in no way effect the right of sovereignty
                        belonging to the Republic of Liberia on the bank which it occupies. In case
                        the works executed should give rise to the establishment of taxes, these
                        would be determined by a new arrangement between the two governments.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                    <p>The clauses of the arrangement of December 8, 1892, are maintained in all the
                        provisions that are not contrary to the present arrangement.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                    <p>The ratifications will be exchanged before March 1, 1908.</p>
                    <p>The operation of fixing the boundary will be proceeded with within three
                        months following the exchange in question.</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof the undersigned, duly authorized to this effect, have
                        concluded the present arrangement, to which they have affixed their
                        seals.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Paris</placeName> in
                            duplicate <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-09-18">the 18th of
                                September, 1907</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] (Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">G. Binger.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] (Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Soulange-Bodin.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] (Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">T. E. R. Johnson</hi>.</signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] (Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">J. P. Crommelin.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
