<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Gummeré to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1907p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d279</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">279</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1907-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1907-09-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068390"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-09-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="279"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d279">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 2151/109–110.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Gummeré</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tangier</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-09-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 18, 1907</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 268.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Portuguese minister, as dean of the
                    diplomatic corps, has circulated among the corps a letter which he has received
                    in the name of the pretender, Mouley Hafid, a translation of which is herewith
                    inclosed.</p>
                <p>The dean, while thus circulating the said letter, stated that he did not do so in
                    an official sense.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">S. R. Gummeré.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Inclosure.—Translation.]</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Praise to God Alone:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>To the wise and honorable friend who seeks the good of and friendship between
                        the two powers, the minister and doyen of the diplomatic corps at Tangier
                        and representative of the Kingdom of Portugal.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">After Compliments:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Our Lord and Master the Great Sultan and Commander of the Kingdom of Islam,
                        our Lord and Master Abdel Hafid (may God grant to him victory and
                        assistance), has received from the people, of Morocco the investiture of the
                        Sultanate after the deposition of our Lord Abdel Aziz. This deposition has
                        taken place by a decision of the Islamic law, and in the interest of the
                        Moorish Government and the integrity of the Empire.</p>
                    <p>My Master has ordered me to write to you, convinced as he is of your
                        friendship for His Majesty, that he protests against the occurrences at
                        Casablanca.</p>
                    <p>If one regards with humanity and justice what has happened to Morocco,
                        especially at Casablanca, the inhabitants of which were the object of
                        violence and aggression; 6,000 souls of them were killed; the city was
                        bombarded with inflammable explosives, while the inhabitants were without
                        defense. This spectacle, frightful to see, makes the heart burn and cause
                        the most hardhearted to weep. You are not ignorant that this great
                        occurrence, which constitutes an attack upon public rights, is contrary to
                        the international treaties, which forbid the attack of a city without
                        defense by elements of destruction and by mines, etc. Whoever claims that
                        the serious occurrence at Casablanca was caused by any necessity whatsoever,
                        this can not be admitted for several reasons. Moreover, there has never been
                        a precedent for such an occurrence, and such things have never been heard
                        of. Please take note of all this and do all that you can in the way of
                        observations and remarks in order to maintain in their purity the relations
                        of Morocco with the powers.</p>
                    <p>Moreover, no doubt one can count on a man such as you, who possesses such
                        keen intelligence and remarkable sagacity. May God bless you.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rejeb</hi> 7<hi rend="smallcaps">th, Holy, Year</hi>
                        1325 (<hi rend="smallcaps">August</hi> 16, 1907):</p>
                    <p>The minister of the Sultan, fortified by the victory of God.</p>
                    <closer>(Signed) <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mohamed Ben Abdel-Kebir.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>(May God preserve him.)</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
