<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Hill to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1907p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d491</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">491</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1907-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1907-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="491"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d491">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Hill</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Hague</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-04-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 4, 1907</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 206.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of
                    department’s instruction No. 72, of March 18, 1907, inclosing a copy of a
                    circular note to the American nonsignatories, relative to their adherence to The
                    Hague Convention of 1899, and also the following telegram of March 29: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Hague:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Minister to China reports Chinese Government assents Russian proposal
                            adherence nonsignatories and will send telegraphic instructions.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Root.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1270" n="1120" xml:id="pg_1120"/>
                <p>As the circular had not been received when the telegrams of March 27 and 28 were
                    exchanged between the department and this legation, I have thought it expedient,
                    although the purpose of the department’s inquiry regarding the status of Turkey
                    was clearly understood, in order to be certain that no embarrassment would arise
                    regarding the adhesion of the American nonsignatories, to discuss the subject
                    with the Minister for Foreign Affairs of the Netherlands in the light of this
                    new information.</p>
                <p>I may state, therefore, that the Government of the Netherlands shares the view
                    that, as Turkey has not yet ratified The Hague conventions, her assent would not
                    be necessary to the unanimous assent of the powers taking part in the First
                    Conference. If, therefore, as stated, the assent of China has been obtained, and
                    the assent of Belgium is given on condition that the other powers agree,
                    unanimity has already been obtained, unless Turkey should now ratify the
                    treaties, in which case her assent also should be requested. This would
                    naturally be done by the Russian Government; and it is suggested that, in view
                    of the contingency of her ratification at the last moment, Turkey should be
                    requested to take action upon that proposal at the same time that she performs
                    her act of ratification.</p>
                <p>The minister of the Netherlands is of the opinion that no embarrassment is likely
                    to arise with reference to the admission of the nonsignatories invited to attend
                    the Second Conference, provided the delegates of those powers are duly provided
                    with full powers authorizing adhesion to the conventions of 1899 by their
                    respective Governments. It is important, however, that they should possess
                    powers to this effect admitting of no doubt or ambiguity, as adhesion to these
                    conventions will be necessary to admission to the conference.</p>
                <p>The minister informs me that he will expect signatures to the protocol on the
                    part of the assenting Governments and notification of adherence by the
                    nonsignatories, as preliminaries of the Second Conference, and advises that
                    these be promptly produced, in order to avoid embarrassing questions.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">David J. Hill.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
