<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1907-03-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1907-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="58" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 3691/196A.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                Minister <persName type="to">Merry</persName>.</hi><note n="a" xml:id="d58fna">Same to the American legation at
                            Honduras.</note></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.—Paraphrase.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1907-03-15"><hi rend="italic">March 15,
                                1907</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Informs Mr. Merry that in view of the repeated statement in certain
                            quarters that the President has admitted the justice of Nicaragua’s
                            charges against Honduras, it is proper to say that nothing in the
                            President’s telegrams of February 11 and 14 warrants an interpretation
                            so contrary to the declared absolute impartiality of the President. His
                            telegram of the 14th to the President of Nicaragua said: “I shall be
                            glad to render any assistance in my power toward working out a practical
                            solution of the interesting problem in accordance with the ideas in
                            which we so perfectly agree.” This related to the declaration of the
                            President of Nicaragua in his telegram of February 13, in which he said:
                            “I recognize and appreciate the desirability of the American States
                            preserving peace.” Mr. Root further informs Mr. Merry that the President
                            has expressed no opinion as to the merits of the unfortunate
                            controversy, and could not do so consistently with his attitude as the
                            unbiased friend of both and his solicitude to do everything possible to
                            restore peace.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>