<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No. 270
                    The Informal Policy Committee on
                            Germany to the Secretary of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d270</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">270</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-06-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-23T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="war-crimes-and-war-criminals" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="war-crimes-and-war-criminals" subject="war-criminals">War criminals</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="armed-forces" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241" lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="270" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d270">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Austria)/6–2345</note>
                <head>No. 270<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Informal Policy Committee on
                            Germany</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-23">23 June
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum for the Secretary of State</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Directive to Commander in Chief of U. S. Forces of
                        Occupation<note n="1" xml:id="d270fn1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">General Mark W. Clark</persName>.</note>
                    regarding the Military Government of Austria.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">References: <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. <gloss target="#t_IPCOG1">IPCOG</gloss> 9.<note n="2" xml:id="d270fn2">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. <gloss target="#t_IPCOG1">IPCOG</gloss> 9/1.<note n="2" xml:id="d270fn5">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. <gloss target="#t_IPCOG1">IPCOG</gloss> 9/2.<note n="3" xml:id="d270fn3">The enclosure to this memorandum constitutes a
                        portion of <gloss target="#t_IPCOG1">IPCOG</gloss> 9/2.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On 23 June 1945 the Informal Policy Committee on Germany approved the enclosed
                    “Directive to Commander in Chief of U. S. Forces of Occupation regarding the
                    Military Government of Austria”. The Joint Chiefs of Staff have advised the
                    Committee that they perceive no objection to this directive from a military
                    point of view.</p>
                <p>The enclosure is transmitted for your guidance and such implementation as is
                    deemed appropriate. Copies of this directive are being similarly forwarded to
                    the Secretaries of War, the Navy and the Treasury; the Foreign Economic
                    Administrator; and the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>For the Informal Policy Committee on Germany: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWL1">W. L. <hi rend="smallcaps">Clayton</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Directive to Commander in Chief of U. S. Forces of
                            Occupation Regarding the Military Government of Austria</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-23">23 June
                                1945</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <gloss target="#t_IPCOG1">IPCOG</gloss> 9/2</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">References: <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. <gloss target="#t_IPCOG1">IPCOG</gloss> 9</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. <gloss target="#t_IPCOG1">IPCOG</gloss> 9/1</p>
                    <p>1. The enclosure, a revision of <gloss target="#t_IPCOG1">IPCOG</gloss> 9 to
                        incorporate the amendment proposed by the Joint Chiefs of Staff, as approved
                        by the Informal <pb facs="0470" n="338" xml:id="pg_338"/> Policy Committee
                        on Germany on 23 June 1945, is circulated for information and guidance.</p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MCCW1">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles W. McCarthy</hi>
                            </persName>
                            <lb/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RAF1">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Alvin F. Richardson</hi>
                            </persName>
                            <lb/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CRE1">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Raymond E. Cox</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretariat</hi>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure—Extracts]<note n="4" xml:id="d270fn4">An almost complete text of this directive, as transmitted to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CGMW1">Clark</persName> on June 27, 1945,
                                by the Joint Chiefs of Staff, is printed in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, p. 661.</note>
                        </seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Directive to Commander in Chief of US Forces of
                            Occupation Regarding the Military Government of Austria</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">The Purpose and Scope of this
                            Directive:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>This directive is issued to you as Commanding General of the United
                            States forces of occupation in Austria. As such you will serve as United
                            States member of the Governing Body of the Allied Administration and
                            will also be responsible for the administration of military government
                            in the zone or zones assigned to the United States for purposes of
                            occupation and administration. It outlines the basic policies which will
                            guide you in those two capacities after the termination of the combined
                            command in Austria. Supplemental directives will be issued to you by the
                            Joint Chiefs of Staff as may be required.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>As a member of the Governing Body you will urge the adoption by the
                            other occupying powers of the principles and policies set forth in this
                            directive and, pending Governing Body agreement, you will follow them in
                            your zone. It is anticipated that substantially similar directives will
                            be issued to the Commanders in Chief of the United Kingdom, the Union of
                            Soviet Socialist Republics, and French forces of occupation.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>In the event that recognition is given by the four governments to a
                            provisional national government of Austria, such government should be
                            delegated authority in appropriate matters to conduct public affairs in
                            accordance with the principles set forth in this directive or agreed
                            upon by the occupying powers. Such delegation, however, shall be subject
                            to the authority of the occupying powers and to their responsibility to
                            see that their policies are in fact carried out.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Any provisional national government of Austria which is not recognized
                            by all of the four Governments of the occupying powers <pb facs="0471" n="339" xml:id="pg_339"/> shall not be treated by you as possessing
                            any authority. Only individuals who recognize your supreme authority in
                            your zone will be utilized by you in administration.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">part i</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">general and political</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">Basic Objectives of Military Government
                            in Austria:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>You will be chiefly concerned in the initial stages of military
                            government with the elimination of German domination and Nazi
                            influences. Consistently with this purpose, you will be guided at every
                            step by the necessity to ensure the reconstruction of Austria as a free,
                            independent and democratic state. It will be essential therefore that
                            every measure be undertaken from the early stages of occupation with
                            this objective in mind.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>The Governing Body should, as soon as it is established, proclaim the
                            complete political and administrative separation of Austria from
                            Germany, and the intention of the occupying powers to pave the way for
                            the reestablishment of Austria as an independent democratic state. You
                            will make it clear to the Austrian people that military occupation of
                            Austria is intended principally (1) to aid Allied military operations
                            and the strict enforcement of the applicable provisions of the German
                            unconditional surrender instrument in Austria; (2) to eliminate Nazism,
                            Pan-Germanism, militarism, and other forces opposed to the democratic
                            reconstitution of Austria; (3) to cooperate with the Control Council for
                            Germany in the application and enforcement of measures designed to
                            prevent the recurrence of German aggression; (4) to establish Allied
                            control over the use and disposition of German property in Austria; (5)
                            to effect the complete political and administrative separation of
                            Austria from Germany and free Austria from Nazi and German economic and
                            financial influences; (6) to facilitate the development of a sound
                            Austrian economy devoted to peaceful pursuits and not vitally dependent
                            upon German supplies, markets and technical and financial assistance;
                            and (7) to foster the restoration of local self-government and the
                            establishment of an Austrian central government freely elected by the
                            Austrian people themselves. Other objectives of the occupation will be
                            to apprehend war criminals, to care for and repatriate displaced persons
                            and prisoners-of-war who are members of the armed forces of the United
                            Nations, and to carry out approved programs of reparation and
                            restitution insofar as these are applicable to Austria.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
