<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No. 603
                    Memorandum by the Assistant to the
                        President’s Naval Aide (
                        Elsey
                    )Submitted to Leahy July 1 and subsequently forwarded
                        to Truman.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d603</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">603</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States policy</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                    <term ref="reccab053b473a4a56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="world-war-i" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148236" lcsh-match="exact">Councils</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="guerrilla" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="603" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d603">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> Papers</note>
                <head>No. 603<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Assistant</gloss> to the
                        President’s Naval Aide</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_ELGM1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Elsey</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d603fn1">Submitted to <persName corresp="#p_LFAWD1">Leahy</persName> July 1 and subsequently forwarded
                        to <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-01">Undated</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Indo-China</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Indo-China first became a subject in Presidential messages in November 1944.
                        <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">General Wedemeyer</persName>, Commanding
                    General of U. S. Forces in China, on 15 November reported<note n="2" xml:id="d603fn2">Report not printed.</note> that British, Dutch and French
                    interests were making an intensive effort to ensure recovery of their prewar
                    political and economic positions in the Far East. One example of this effort was
                    the establishment of a French <pb facs="1050" n="916" xml:id="pg_916"/> military
                    mission in India which was preparing to infiltrate into Indochina. For his
                    guidance, <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> asked for U. S.
                    policy regarding Indo-China which, by decision of the Combined Chiefs of Staff,
                    is in the Chinese Theater.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> instructed Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> the next day<note n="3" xml:id="d603fn3">See <hi rend="italic">Military Situation in the Far
                            East</hi>, Hearings Before the Committees on Armed Services and Foreign
                        Relations, United States Senate, 82d Congress, 1st Session (Washington,
                        Government Printing Office, 1951), pt. 4, p. 2889.</note> to inform
                        <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> that “United States
                    policy with regard to French Indo-China cannot be formulated until after
                    consultation with Allies at a forthcoming Combined Staff conference.”</p>
                <p>The President also asked <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> to keep
                    him posted on British, French and Dutch activities in southeastern Asia.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> had no information on
                    Indo-China to pass to the President at the time, but on 26 November he sent a
                    short diatribe<note n="4" xml:id="d603fn4">See <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, and
                            <persName>Don Lohbeck</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Patrick J. Hurley</hi>
                        </persName> (Chicago, 1956), p. 322.</note> against the policies of our
                    three Allies which, he said, were directed to the “repossession of their
                    colonial empires and the reestablishment therein of imperial governments.” On
                    New Year’s Day 1945, <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> sent the
                    President a long and unfavorable analysis of British, Dutch and French policies
                    with respect to China<note n="5" xml:id="d603fn5">See
                            <persName>Lohbeck</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Patrick J. Hurley</hi>
                        </persName>, pp. 323–324.</note> but he still had no information regarding
                    Indo-China.</p>
                <p>Nor did the Joint Chiefs of Staff know what our Allies proposed to do there. On
                    21 November, [1944,] by direction of the President, they had informed the
                    Commanding Generals of U. S. Forces in India, Burma and China that: “This
                    Government has made no final decisions on the future of Indo-China, and it
                    expects to be consulted in advance with regard to any arrangements applicable to
                    the future of southeast Asia.”<note n="6" xml:id="d603fn6">Full text not
                        printed.</note> The Joint Chiefs were not consulted by the British or the
                    French, however, and when President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> arrived at Yalta he had no official information on
                    their intentions with respect to Indo-China except that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> had spoken in a general way about
                    sending French troops there.<note n="7" xml:id="d603fn7">This paragraph does not
                        take account of Anglo-American consultations affecting Indochina, in which
                        both the Department of State and the Joint Chiefs of Staff were involved,
                        which had been proceeding for almost a year. The President had been informed
                        of the status of these consultations by the Department of State in December
                        1944, more than a month before the Yalta Conference, and Indochina continued
                        to receive the attention of the Combined Chiefs of Staff during the early
                        months of 1945.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On 8 February, while explaining his views on trusteeships, President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_SMIV2">Stalin</persName> he had in mind a trusteeship for Indo-China. He said the
                    British did not approve and wanted to give it back to the French because they
                    feared that the implications of a trusteeship might affect Burma. He added that
                    the French had done nothing to improve the natives since obtaining the colony.
                    When President <pb facs="1051" n="917" xml:id="pg_917"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> said that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> had asked for ships to transport
                    French forces to Indo-China, <persName corresp="#p_SMIV2">Stalin</persName>
                    asked where <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> would get the
                    troops. The President replied that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de
                        Gaulle</persName> had said he would find the troops when the President found
                    the ships; so far there were no ships.<note n="8" xml:id="d603fn8">See <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_770">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conferences at Malta and
                            Yalta, 1945, p. 770</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In March, <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> were both in Washington. President
                        <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> that he must watch carefully to
                    prevent British and French political activities in the area and that he should
                    give only such support to the British and French as would be required in direct
                    operations against the Japanese.</p>
                <p>On 24 March, President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> had a long discussion on
                    Indo-China. <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> reported this
                    conversation to President <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> on 28
                        [<hi rend="italic">29</hi>] May as follows:<note n="9" xml:id="d603fn9">For
                        another extract from this message, see <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_920">p. 920</ref>. For further extracts, see <hi rend="italic">Military Situation in the Far East</hi>, pt. 4, pp.
                        2890–2892; <persName>Lohbeck</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Patrick J. Hurley</hi>
                        </persName>, pp. 409–411, 413–414.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In my last conference with President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName>, I informed him fully on the Indo-China
                            situation. I told him that the French, British and Dutch were
                            cooperating to prevent the establishment of a United Nations trusteeship
                            for Indo-China. The imperialist leaders believe that such a trusteeship
                            would be a bad precedent for the other imperialistic areas in southeast
                            Asia. I told the President also that the British would attempt, with the
                            use of our Lend-Lease supplies and if possible our manpower, to occupy
                            Indo-China and reestablish their former imperial control. I suggested to
                            the President that for my own guidance and in order to clarify <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName>’s position I thought we
                            should have a written directive on Indo-China. The President said that
                            in the coming San Francisco Conference<note n="10" xml:id="d603fn10">i.
                                e., the United Nations Conference on International
                                Organization.</note> there would be set up a United Nations
                            Trusteeship that would make effective the right of colonial people to
                            choose the form of government under which they will live as soon as in
                            the opinion of the United Nations they are qualified for
                            independence.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>While <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> were in Washington, <persName corresp="#p_CMWS1">Churchill</persName> wired<note n="11" xml:id="d603fn11">Message not printed.</note> that he understood there had been occasional
                    difficulties between <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Lord [Louis] Mountbatten</persName>, British
                    Commander of the Southeast Asia Theater, about activities in Indo-China, and he
                    proposed that he and President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName>
                    direct the Combined Chiefs of Staff to make arrangements for “full and frank
                    exchange of intentions, plans and intelligence between <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> as regards all matters of mutual concern.”</p>
                <p>The President replied on 22 March<note n="11a" xml:id="d603fn11a">Full text not
                        printed.</note> that he understood both commanders were independently
                    conducting air operations and intelligence missions in Indo-China. This was
                    wasteful and apt to <pb facs="1052" n="918" xml:id="pg_918"/> produce dangerous
                    confusion, and President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName>
                    suggested a solution: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“It seems to me the best solution at present is for you and me to agree
                            that all Anglo-American-Chinese military operations in Indo-China,
                            regardless of their nature, be coordinated by <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">General Wedemeyer</persName> as Chief of Staff
                            to the Generalissimo.<note n="12" xml:id="d603fn12">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>.</note>…<note n="13" xml:id="d603fn13">Ellipses and brackets throughout this
                                document appear in the original.</note> If you agree to this
                            proposal, I suggest that you direct <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> to coordinate his activities in Indo-China
                            with <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName>.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMWS1">Churchill</persName> did not reply to the
                    President’s suggestion until 11 April, after <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> had stopped at <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName>’s headquarters on his return to China from
                    Washington. The two theater commanders had discussed operations in Indo-China.
                        <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> was guided by President
                        <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName>’s verbal directive to
                    support only British and French operations directed against the Japanese, and he
                    left <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName>’s headquarters
                    believing he had reached an agreement whereby the British Commander would not
                    carry out operations in Indo-China until they had been approved by him.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> had another understanding of
                    the agreement, however, and the British conception of it was voiced by <persName corresp="#p_CMWS1">Churchill</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> on 11 April.<note n="14" xml:id="d603fn14">Full text not printed.</note> It was apparent that
                    political motives inspired British operations in Indo-China, as the Prime
                    Minister wrote: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Now that the Japanese have taken over Indo-China and that substantial
                            resistance is being offered by French patriots, it is essential not only
                            that we should support the French by all the means in our power, but
                            also that we should associate them with our operations into their
                            country. It would look very bad in history if we failed to support
                            isolated French forces in their resistance to the Japanese to the best
                            of our ability, or, if we excluded the French from participation in our
                            councils as regards Indo-China.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It was also apparent that the British did not consider the <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> agreement as calling for anything more than an
                    interchange of information, for <persName corresp="#p_CMWS1">Churchill</persName> quoted his proposed directive to <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“You may conduct from whatsoever base appears most suitable the minimum
                            pre-occupational activities in Indo-China which local emergency and the
                            advance of your forces require. It is essential, however, that you
                            should keep <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">General Wedemeyer</persName> …
                            continually informed of your operations. …”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> answered <persName corresp="#p_CMWS1">Churchill</persName>’s message on 14 April.<note n="14" xml:id="d603fn22">Full text not printed.</note> He did not make an issue
                    with <persName corresp="#p_CMWS1">Churchill</persName>, but he carefully stated
                    the <pb facs="1053" n="919" xml:id="pg_919"/> American understanding of the
                        <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> agreement, as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“<persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">General Wedemeyer</persName> reports that
                            his conference with <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Admiral
                                Mountbatten</persName> resulted in an agreement that the latter
                            would notify <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> when he
                            desired to conduct an operation in Indo-China and that the operation
                            would not be conducted until approval was given by the Generalissimo.
                                <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName>’s understanding
                            is that the procedure will be for <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> to notify <persName corresp="#p_CLGA1">General Carton De Wiart</persName>, who would inform <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> in his capacity as chief of
                            staff to the Generalissimo. If the proposed operation from <gloss target="#t_SEAC1">SEAC</gloss> could not be integrated with China
                            Theater plans, then <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName>
                            agreed he would not undertake it.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Following different policies and without an understanding on operations in
                    Indo-China, <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> came into open disagreement in
                    May. <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> he intended to fly 26 sorties into
                    Indo-China in support of French guerrilla groups.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> asked for more information
                    because, he said, the French Government had placed all French guerrilla groups
                    in Indo-China under the Generalissimo (<persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> is <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang</persName>’s
                    Chief of Staff) and not under <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName>. He asked the specific question, “What arrangements
                    have been made to insure that the equipment furnished guerrilla units is
                    employed against the Japanese?”<note n="15" xml:id="d603fn15">Full text of
                        message not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> did not answer this
                    question, and after a quick exchange of messages<note n="16" xml:id="d603fn16">Not printed.</note> in which he gave <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> neither the numbers nor the locations of the guerrilla
                    units which he intended to supply, <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> abruptly ordered his planes to carry out the sorties
                    without waiting for the consent or approval of <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> on
                    25 May protested vigorously:<note n="15" xml:id="d603fn20">Full text of message
                        not printed.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“It had never occurred to me that you would presume that you have
                            authority to operate in an area contiguous to your own without
                            cognizance and full authority of the Commander of that area. … Your
                            decision to conduct these operations without the Generalissimo’s
                            approval is a direct violation of the intent of our respective
                            directives.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> informed the Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff of the circumstances, as he saw them, of his misunderstanding with
                        <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName>. He reported his
                        conclusions:<note n="15" xml:id="d603fn21">Full text of message not
                        printed.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have not sufficient information available to coordinate or evaluate
                            the operations <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> is
                            now undertaking and I cannot carry out the explicit instructions of the
                            President. … If lend-lease materials are being made available by United
                            States to British in <pb facs="1054" n="920" xml:id="pg_920"/> support
                            of French Indo-China operations, I believe that these materials should
                            be turned over … [to the China Theater] so that our country at least
                            gets credit for such support and further so that I can carry out my
                            directive in screening the nature of operations in the area.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> summarized his own
                    view of the conflict in British and American policies which underlay the
                        <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName> dispute in a long message to
                    President <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> on 28 [<hi rend="italic">29</hi>] May:<note n="17" xml:id="d603fn17">For another extract from this
                        message, see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_917">p.
                        917</ref>. For further extracts, see <hi rend="italic">Military Situation in
                            the Far East</hi>, pt. 4, pp. 2890–2892; <persName>Lohbeck</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Patrick J. Hurley</hi>
                        </persName>, pp. 409–411, 413–414.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I had been definitely directed verbally by President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> in regard to his policy in
                            Indo-China,” he wrote, “but we in this theater have never received a
                            written directive on the political policy of the United States in
                            Indo-China.</p>
                        <p>“It is in this situation we find ourselves when <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Lord Louis Mountbatten</persName>, the Supreme
                            British Commander in Southeast Asia, informed <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> by cable that he is flying
                            British sorties into Indo-China, which is not in his theater, without
                            the consent of the Theater Commander, the Generalissimo, and without the
                            consent or cooperation of <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">General
                                Wedemeyer</persName>. This military phase of the situation is being
                            submitted to the Joint Chiefs of Staff by <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Lord
                                Louis</persName> is using American lend-lease supplies and other
                            American resources to invade Indo-China to defeat what we believe to be
                            the American policy and to reestablish French imperialism.</p>
                        <p>“Attention is called to the fact that <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Lord
                                Louis</persName> very recently requested <persName corresp="#p_SLGDI1">General Sultan</persName>, United States
                            India–Burma Commander, for a large increase in lend-lease supplies that
                            will enable him to defeat the <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> policy in Indo-China and reestablish
                            imperialism in that area. If you, sir, are opposed to <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Lord Louis</persName>[‘] political objectives in
                            Indo-China, I suggest that our Government stop giving him lend-lease
                            supplies and deny him the use of American Air Forces and other American
                            resources.</p>
                        <p>“The move of the imperialistic powers to use American resources to enable
                            them to move with force into Indo-China is not for the purpose of
                            participating in the main battle against <persName corresp="#p_J1">Japan</persName>. Such a move would have two political objectives:
                            (1) The reestablishment of imperialism in Indo-China and (2) The placing
                            of British forces in a position where they could occupy Hong Kong and
                            prevent the return of Hong Kong to China.</p>
                        <p>“It would clarify the situation in Asia for all of us if we could be
                            given: (1) A definite Indo-China policy, and (2) A definite policy on
                            Hong Kong or if we could be directed to follow the <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> policy in both areas.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>On 31 May, in a personal message to <persName corresp="#p_MGAGC1">General
                        Marshall</persName>,<note n="18" xml:id="d603fn18">Not printed.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WLGAC1">Wedemeyer</persName> endorsed <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName>’s interpretation of British intentions
                    in the Far East. He reported that his information pointed to an increase of
                    British political and economic operations in Indo-China for the purpose of
                    recovering British pre-war prestige and economic preferment in Southeast Asia;
                    and that it was probable the British would <pb facs="1055" n="921" xml:id="pg_921"/> propose, at the next Big Three meeting, extending the
                    boundaries of <persName corresp="#p_MALL1">Mountbatten</persName>’s command to
                    include all former British, French and Dutch colonial possessions.</p>
                <p>There have been no Presidential messages on Indo-China within the past month. The
                    Joint Chiefs of Staff have taken no action on inter-theater disputes in Asia,
                    pending a meeting of the Combined Chiefs; <persName corresp="#p_CMWS1">Churchill</persName> has maintained a careful silence; and President
                        <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> has told <persName corresp="#p_HMGPJ1">Hurley</persName> that this question will probably be
                    discussed at the forthcoming Berlin Conference.<note n="19" xml:id="d603fn19">See <ref target="#d149">document No. 149</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_ELGM1">G. M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Elsey</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
