<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 662 The Ambassador in France ( (Caffery) ) to the Secretary of State ad
                    interim</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d662</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">662</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-07-02T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-07-02T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-02T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-02T11:00:00-05:00" n="662"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d662">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">881.00/7–245: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 662 <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CJ1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State ad
                            interim</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-02T18:00:00+02:00"
                            >July 2, 1945—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3981. <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> rec’d this morning note from
                    Russian Embassy referring to notification regarding Tangier conversations
                    delivered in Moscow Saturday<note n="1" xml:id="d662fn1">See <ref target="#d659"
                            >document No. 659</ref>.</note> and expressing astonishment that such
                    conversations should be called with so little advance notice to Soviet Union.
                    Note then expressed Russian interest in matter of Tangier and requested that
                    opening of conversations be postponed until consultations could be held to
                    arrange for 4 power discussions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MJ2">Meyrier</persName> of <gloss target="#t_FonOff1"
                        >FonOff</gloss>, who conveyed above information to <persName
                        corresp="#p_AGM1">Abbott</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HA1"
                        >Holman</persName> of Brit Embassy said that Russian action had been
                    rendered inevitable by Brit and Amer desire for temporary regime to replace
                    Spanish administration rather than acceptance of French desire to reestablish
                    status existing in 1939. <persName corresp="#p_MJ2">Meyrier</persName> stated he
                    did not see how Russian request to take part in conversations could be refused
                    unless French thesis was adopted. Russians could then be informed that no
                    changes in Tangier administration were contemplated at this time and that Soviet
                    Govt together with other interested powers would naturally be invited to take
                    part in a subsequent conference for revision of Tangier convention. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MJ2">Meyrier</persName> added that this [<hi rend="italic"
                        >the?</hi>] chief objection to admitting Soviets at this time would be
                    endless delays which would follow with result that Spaniards would remain in
                    Tangier for months and years.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Holman</persName> while obviously reluctant to
                    envisage Soviet participation in talks to be held in Paris stated he had not
                        [<hi rend="italic">no</hi>] information as to his govt’s attitude and would
                    have to request instructions.</p>
                <p>The above ground was gone over again this afternoon at a meeting in <persName
                        corresp="#p_MJ2">Meyrier</persName>’s office with members of Amer and Brit
                    delegations. Amer position was stated in accordance with instructions to
                        <persName corresp="#p_VHS1">Villard</persName>,<note n="2" xml:id="d662fn2">
                        <ref target="#d652">Document No. 652</ref>.</note> namely that we favored
                    admission of <persName corresp="#p_R4">Russia</persName> to discussions on an
                    equal basis. Brit delegation stated they would have to ask instructions from
                    London and added that owing to the elections and the dispersal of cabinet
                    ministers it would be difficult to obtain a decision for several days. Privately
                        <persName corresp="#p_PC1">Peake</persName> informed us the Brit delegation
                    had received instructions based on a decision taken by the cabinet to oppose the
                    admission of <persName corresp="#p_R4">Russia</persName> to the conversations.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PC1">Peake</persName> explained also to us that he
                    would not communicate this to the French at this stage inasmuch as since our
                    instructions were different he considered it <pb facs="1126" n="992"
                        xml:id="pg_992"/> inadvisable for the Brit delegation to take the onus of
                    opposing Russian participation and in his view the question would have to be
                    reexamined at the top level.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MJ2">Meyrier</persName> stated that the French Govt
                    prepared to say no to the Russians but it was not prepared to take this stand
                    unless the decision was unanimous on the part of the 3 powers namely the US,
                    France and Great Brit. Likewise in a conversation this morning with the Russian
                        Ambassador<note n="3" xml:id="d662fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BAE1">Alexander Efremovich
                        Bogomolov</persName>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> took the position that any reply
                    to the Russian request for participation in the discussions could not be made by
                    France alone but was a matter which called for a decision representing the views
                    of all 3 powers.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MJ2">Meyrier</persName> stated that there were several
                    alternatives: (1) that the Russians be informed the question of Tangier solely
                    concerned the French and Brit Govts as signatories of the statute of 1923, and
                    that they proposed to restore integrally the 1923 three [<hi rend="italic"
                        >sic</hi>] statute provisionally, and that both the USSR and the US would be
                    invited to participate in the drawing up of a definitive regime; (2) a refusal
                    of the Russian request and the continuance of the present plans for a
                    provisional regime to be followed by the drawing up of a new statute and (3)
                    acceptance of the Russian request, in which case he saw no reason why other
                    interested powers including Belgium the Netherlands Portugal Sweden and Spain
                    should not be invited to participate in the conversations.</p>
                <p>The Brit delegation has expressed itself to us as entirely opposed to the
                    reintegration of the 1923 statute, and they do not wish to see us stand aside.
                    The French stated this afternoon that the Brit draft agreement<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d662fn4">Not printed.</note> involved fundamental changes in the
                    statute and would therefore involve extended discussions.</p>
                <p>Brit have informed Amer delegation privately that if favorable decision should be
                    made to admit Russians they would favor inclusion of the smaller powers in the
                    discussions so that the task may well assume that of drawing up the final
                    statute for Tangier rather than a provisional regime.</p>
                <p>Inasmuch as we were careful not to associate ourselves with the Brit and French
                    Govts in the notification to Moscow <persName corresp="#p_VHS1"
                        >Villard</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CJR1">Childs</persName> feel
                    strongly we should be most careful not to be drawn into associating ourselves
                    with any negative decision by the Brit Govt in respect of the Russian
                    request.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
