<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No. 685 
                    The Ambassador in Turkey
                     (
                        Wilson
                    ) to the Acting Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv01</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d685</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">685</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-06-20T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-20T12:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-20T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-20T12:00:00-05:00" n="685" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d685">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">761.67/6–2045: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 685 <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in <persName corresp="#p_T1">Turkey</persName>
                    </hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WFMSHM1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-20T20:00:00+03:00">June 20, 1945—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>822. I just talked with the Brit <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> who came
                    here this morning from Istanbul. (<gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss>s 817, June
                        18<note n="1" xml:id="d685fn1">
                        <ref target="#d684">Document No. 684</ref>.</note>) He had seen the Acting
                        <gloss target="#t_FonMins1">FonMin</gloss> and given him the views of the
                    Brit Govt along the following lines: The Brit Govt felt the Turks had taken the
                    only position open to them in refusing to discuss <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s proposals. At the same time <pb facs="1157" n="1023" xml:id="pg_1023"/> it would be wise for the Turks not to be entirely
                    negative and they should consider going back at the Russians with a proposal for
                    a discussion of the revision of the Montreux Convention among four or five
                    states instead of only <persName corresp="#p_R4">Russia</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_T1">Turkey</persName>: For instance Britain, <persName corresp="#p_G4">Greece</persName> and the US if willing might participate.
                    Brit Govt felt strongly that it would be advisable for Britain to intervene at
                    Moscow without delay and it was hoped that the US would join in such
                    intervention. The <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> had inquired if the Turk
                    Govt would object to such intervention and the Acting <gloss target="#t_FonMins1">FonMin</gloss> had replied that on the contrary
                        <persName corresp="#p_T1">Turkey</persName> would welcome it and hoped the
                    US would take similar action.</p>
                <p>The Acting <gloss target="#t_FonMins1">FonMin</gloss> had said there were reports
                    of Russian troop movements towards <persName corresp="#p_T1">Turkey</persName>’s
                    eastern frontier and the Turk Govt was considering calling two classes of
                    reserves, about 180,000 men[,] back to the army. <persName corresp="#p_PSMD1">Peterson</persName> said that his <gloss target="#t_mil1">Mil</gloss>
                        Attaché<note n="2" xml:id="d685fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_AMGAC1">Major-General Allan C.
                        Arnold</persName>.</note> reported there was no confirmation the Russians
                    were increasing their troops near the frontier but the mechanization of Russian
                    units in that area had undoubtedly increased the mobility of their forces there.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PSMD1">Peterson</persName> said he felt it unwise for
                    the Turks to call up these reserves as this would make them look jumpy and as if
                    they were feeling the effects of the Russian war of nerves which is just what
                    the Russians want. He thought it unlikely that the Russians would make a move to
                    grab these territories by force and he was considering whether he ought to
                    advise the Turks not to call up these reserves.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PSMD1">Peterson</persName> said his govt had informed the
                    US Govt fully of their views in this matter and had expressed the hope the US
                    would join in intervention at Moscow.</p>
                <p>1 recommend strongly that we express an interest in this matter at Moscow. The
                    Russian proposals to <persName corresp="#p_T1">Turkey</persName> are wholly
                    incompatible with the spirit and principles on which we are seeking with the
                    participation of the Soviet Union to set up a new world organization. While I
                    doubt if the Russians are likely to take military action against <persName corresp="#p_T1">Turkey</persName> at this time, on the eve of the Big Three
                    Meeting I believe that prompt and firm expression of our views at Moscow will be
                    of the greatest importance in keeping this situation from getting out of hand
                    and in contributing to the possibilities of an ultimate solution.</p>
                <p>Sent to <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_rptd1">rptd</gloss> to Moscow as 41.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
