<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-12-19T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-12-19T04:00:00-05:00" n="381" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d381">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.77/2771: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-12-19T17:00:00+08:00">December 19, 1930—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received December 19—9:30 a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>1061. Tokyo’s 249, December 15, 3 [<hi rend="italic">2</hi>] p.m.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The Rengo Japanese Press Agency has lately issued reports at Tokyo
                                that the Chinese are adopting a more aggressive attitude toward
                                Japanese railway interests in Manchuria and that there is reason to
                                fear that the construction of Chinese railways will “envelop” the
                                South Manchuria Railway vitally and adversely affecting its
                                interests (see Mukden’s despatch number 365 [<hi rend="italic">375</hi>], November 28<note n="70" xml:id="d381fn70">Not
                                    printed.</note>).</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I am inclined to believe that the Japanese nervousness in this
                                reputed accusation have [<hi rend="italic">has</hi>] been much
                                accentuated by the recent visit to Nanking of Marshal Chang who
                                acted quite independently of his Japanese advisers. There is no
                                doubt but that the Japanese are opposed to this visit and are much
                                disturbed over the developments which may come from any
                                identification of interests between Mukden and Nanking such as the
                                possible use of a general boycott for the purposes of reenforcing
                                the Chinese position vis-à-vis Japanese in Manchurian
                                questions.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>As far as I can ascertain here the Japanese are disposed to a
                                policy of cooperation in railway matters unless pushed too hard by a
                                Chinese policy which may seek to hamstring the South Manchuria
                                Railway.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Code text to Tokyo by mail.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>For the Minister:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Perkins</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>