<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-06-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="383" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d383">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.9312A/12</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chinese Minister</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">C.
                                    C. Wu</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-06-22">June 22, 1929</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your note of May 28, 1929, on the subject of the arbitration
                            treaty which this Government proposed to the Government of China in a
                            note of December 21, 1928. You inform me that your Government is
                            prepared to accept the text as proposed by this Government with two
                            alterations.</p>
                        <p>The first desired change consists of a definite reference to the
                            Permanent International Commission constituted pursuant to the treaty
                            signed between the United States and China on September 15, 1914. The
                            second desired change consists in having the treaty signed in both the
                            English and Chinese languages, both texts to be of equal force.</p>
                        <p>I am happy to be able to inform you that the first of the changes desired
                            by the Government of China is fully acceptable to the Government of the
                            United States.</p>
                        <p>This Government will, moreover, be glad to sign the treaty with texts
                            both English and Chinese, but feels that the formula used in the treaty
                            regulating tariff relations concluded by the Governments of the United
                            States and China on July 25, 1928,<note n="75" xml:id="d383fn75"><ref target="frus1928v02#pg_475"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p.
                                    475</ref>.</note> should be used also in the present treaty.</p>
                        <p>The pertinent paragraph in the text as submitted by this Government on
                            December 21, 1928, may accordingly be amended to read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In faith whereof, the respective Plenipotentiaries have signed
                                    and do affix their seals to this treaty in duplicate in the
                                    English and Chinese languages; the English and Chinese texts
                                    have been carefully compared and verified but, in the event of
                                    there being a difference of meaning between the two, the sense
                                    as expressed in the English text shall be held to prevail.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>I trust that this will be acceptable to your Government and that you will
                            be in a position shortly to submit to the Department the Chinese text of
                            the treaty. When the English and Chinese texts have been carefully
                            compared and verified, the treaty may be put into final form and we may
                            proceed to signature.</p>
                        <p>I am gratified at the progress which has been made in this matter and I
                            ask you to accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">H. L. Stimson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>