<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Shanghai ( (Cunningham) ) to the Minister in China (
                    (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d416</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">416</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-04-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-04-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-04-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-04-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="416"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d416">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.05/293</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cunningham</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Minister in China</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="10" xml:id="d416fn1">Copy transmitted to the Department by
                        the Consul General in his despatch No. 6868, April 16, 1930; received May
                        8.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-04-16">April 16,
                            1930</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 6458</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to this Consulate General’s despatch
                    No. 6438 of March 28, 1930,<note n="11" xml:id="d416fn2">Not printed.</note>
                    relative to the implementing of the new court agreement, I have the honor to
                    enclose, for the Legation’s information, a copy of a supplemental memorandum on
                    this subject by Consul General J. F. Brenan and Consul J. E. Jacobs,<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d416fn3">Not printed.</note> representing the Legations concerned,
                    the original of which is being sent through the Senior Consul concerned to the
                    Senior Minister concerned. This memorandum is not only supplemental to that
                    transmitted with my despatch above referred to but is the final memorandum of
                    Messrs. Brenan and Jacobs on this subject since all the matters connected with
                    the implementing of the new court agreement have now been concluded.</p>
                <p>In spite of the fear expressed in the last paragraph of my despatch referred to,
                    that there might be some difficulty in connection with the inauguration of the
                    new courts on April 1, 1930, the Chinese authorities appointed the Presidents of
                    the two new courts on March 30th and the inauguration ceremonies took place, as
                    scheduled, on April 1st. Since their inauguration these courts have functioned
                    satisfactorily although the Prosecutor for the Police states that there is still
                    some confusion incident to the necessary readjustments in the personnel and
                    procedure. Two questions, however, did arise in regard to the recording of
                    processes of the new courts served by the Process Servers and in connection with
                    the service of criminal summonses by these officers which were referred by the
                    Senior Consul concerned to Messrs. J. F. Brenan and J. E. Jacobs, the foreign
                    members of the Permanent Committee Constituted under Article IX of the new
                    Agreement. They succeeded in effecting an informal settlement of these questions
                    with the President of the Branch High Court without an actual meeting of the
                    Permanent Committee. The reason for an informal settlement of this kind was the
                    attitude of the Chinese members of the Permanent Committee as regards the proper
                    procedure for referring such questions <pb facs="0443" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/>
                    to the Committee. This difficulty will be the subject of a communication from
                    the Senior Consul concerned to the Senior Minister concerned in order that the
                    procedure may be regularized for the future.</p>
                <p>With reference to the Permanent Committee constituted under Article IX of the
                    agreement, it is not believed that this Committee will be of much assistance in
                    settling disputes which may arise out of the operation of the new agreement. As
                    constituted under the agreement it is nothing more than an advisory board whose
                    recommendations may or may not be adopted by the Chinese and foreign authorities
                    concerned. It would seem, therefore, that the most expeditious way of settling
                    such disputes will be through the medium of formal and informal representations
                    to the Presidents of the two new courts which has already worked satisfactorily
                    as pointed out in the above paragraph.</p>
                <p>Although the new courts have only been functioning for about two weeks, it is
                    believed that the relations between the authorities of these courts and of the
                    International Settlement will be friendly and mutually helpful if the same
                    conciliatory spirit which has characterized their mutual efforts for the past
                    two weeks continues.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin S. Cunningham</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
