<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-03-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="469" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d469">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.003/293</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chief of the Division of Far Eastern
                                Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the British
                                Chargé</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Campbell</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-03-17">March 17, 1930</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Campbell</hi>: Under date February 21,
                            1930, the American Embassy at London telegraphed the Department that the
                            British Foreign Office had expressed a desire to be informed with regard
                            to the attitude of the American Government on the subject of
                            endeavoring, in dealing with the question of extraterritorial
                            jurisdiction in China, to retain criminal jurisdiction and/or to provide
                            for the employment by China of foreign co-judges.</p>
                        <p>In a recent conversation, you mentioned this same matter to me.</p>
                        <p>I am happy to be able to inform you, as per the memorandum hereto
                            attached, with regard to the views of the Department. The text of this
                            memorandum is being telegraphed to the American Embassy at London and to
                            the American Legation at Peiping, with authorization to communicate it
                            to the British Foreign Office and to the British Minister to China.</p>
                        <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Stanley K.
                            Hornbeck</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">British
                                        Embassy</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-03-17">March 17,
                                    1930</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>In reply to the inquiry of the British Foreign Office with regard to
                                the views of the Department on the subject of endeavoring, in
                                dealing with the question of extraterritorial jurisdiction in China,
                                to retain criminal jurisdiction and/or to provide for the employment
                                by China of foreign co-judges, the Department states:</p>
                            <p>It is the opinion of the Department that it would be desirable, if
                                possible, to have provision for both of these features. As between
                                the two, the Department regards provision for the employment of
                                foreign co-judges as the more to be desired. At the same time, the
                                Department believes that the Chinese will resist proposal of
                                co-judges more than proposal that criminal jurisdiction be retained.
                                The Department is willing, in course of its negotiations, to propose
                                to the Chinese both features and to stress desirability of having
                                co-judges. The Department finds it impossible, however, to say in
                                advance which point it would be ready to abandon first, as this
                                would depend on (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) other features of any
                                plan or plans proposed and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the Chinese
                                reaction thereto and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the situation which
                                may develop while discussion proceeds. Department will expect to
                                keep Foreign Office informed of any modification or development in
                                connection with this expression of views.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>