<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Shanghai ( (Cunningham) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d609</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">609</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-07-11T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-07-11T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-07-11T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-07-11T23:00:00-05:00" n="609"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d609">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.5034 Registration/3: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cunningham</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-07-12T12:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 12, 1930—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received July 13—8:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Following telegram has been sent to the Legation: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“July 12, 11 a.m. Referring my July 3, 5 p.m. The view expressed in first
                            paragraph that firms having extraterritorial rights would not be
                            required as condition precedent to force suit in court to be registered
                            is not correct. On the contrary the President of the Shanghai Special
                            District Court upon his return from Nanking stated definitely in
                            conversation that all firms would be required to register before
                            bringing suit in court. Enquiries are increasing in number and I am
                            continuing to express the view cited in the penultimate paragraph of my
                            July 3rd. The Legation’s instructions however are awaited.</p>
                        <p>Singer Sewing Machine Company on June 28th in a case brought up in
                            Kiangsu [<hi rend="italic">Kiangning</hi>] District Court was advised by
                            court to settle case out of court since the company was not registered.
                            The judge called for evidence of registration and since the firm is not
                            registered the case was dismissed. This furnishes a concrete case though
                            it arises in the Nanking consular district but was brought to the
                            attention of this office by the company. The company was requested to
                            appeal to the Nanking Consul for appropriate action on his part. Local
                            inquiry has failed to disclose any definite policy on the part of
                            foreign governments having extraterritoriality. All seem to be awaiting
                            instructions.</p>
                        <p>I desire to stress the importance of early consideration of the question
                            and the enunciation of a policy for the guidance of this office. It is a
                            serious and urgent matter for American concerns.</p>
                        <pb facs="0647" n="549" xml:id="pg_549"/>
                        <p>Copies of provisional regulations for registration of companies and
                            supplemental rules are being forwarded by mail.<note n="62"
                                xml:id="d609fn62">Not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Repeated to Department, copy handed to Minister, copy by mail to
                            Nanking.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cunningham</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
