<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Ethiopia ( (Park))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1930v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recc5wAbpL3cvsf8h" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="883"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d883">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">884.113/43</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Ethiopia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Park</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="2" xml:id="d883fn2">Handed to the Minister to Ethiopia,
                        Southard, while on leave of absence in Washington.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-06-06">June 6,
                            1930</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 131</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has received the Legation’s
                    despatches No. 331 of January 22 and No. 337 of January 27, 1930,<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d883fn3">Neither printed.</note> concerning the efforts of Mr.
                    George T. Wise to sell arms and ammunition to the Ethiopian Government.</p>
                <p>The Department has noted the contents of the enclosures to these two despatches
                    and especially the letters of January 18, 1930, appearing as enclosures two and
                    three of despatch No. 331 of January 22. In the paragraph numbered two of the
                    second enclosure Mr. Wise stated that he would proceed to Paris, and if
                    necessary to London and to Rome, to obtain permission to transship arms at
                    Djibouti. Mr. Wise added that if he did not obtain permission as a result of
                    these visits he proposed to come to Washington to force the issue. In view of
                    this statement it is believed to be desirable to furnish you with information
                    regarding the attitude of the Department with respect to the exportation of arms
                    to Ethiopia.</p>
                <p>As early as January 11, 1892, when the Senate of the United States advised and
                    consented to the ratification of the General Act of Brussels of June [<hi
                        rend="italic">July</hi>] 2, 1890,<note n="4" xml:id="d883fn4">Malloy, <hi
                            rend="italic">Treaties</hi>, 1776–1909, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ii</hi>, p. 1964. For Senate reservation, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >ibid.</hi>, p. 1991.</note> the Senate stated that the United States of
                    America, having neither possessions nor protectorates in Africa, disclaimed any
                    intention, in ratifying the” treaty, to indicate any interest whatsoever in the
                    possessions or protectorates established or claimed on that continent by other
                    powers, or any approval of the wisdom, expediency or lawfulness thereof, and did
                    not join in any expressions in the said General Act which might be construed as
                    such a declaration or acknowledgment.</p>
                <pb facs="0863" n="765" xml:id="pg_765"/>
                <p>Further, in a note of November 6, 1922, to the British Ambassador at
                        Washington,<note n="5" xml:id="d883fn5">Not printed; see the Department’s
                        instruction No. 707, November 7, 1922, to the Ambassador in Great Britain,
                            <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_113">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 113</ref>.</note> the Department stated
                    that this Government had no disposition to interpose any obstacles to the due
                    performance of the obligations assumed under the General Act signed at Brussels
                    July 2, 1890, by the governments whose territories bordered on Ethiopia. In a
                    subsequent note to the British Ambassador the Department stated that it would
                    not facilitate or encourage the traffic in arms with Ethiopia. The policy
                    declared in these notes to the British Ambassador has been consistently adhered
                    to by the Department in replying to communications from private American
                    concerns interested in the exportation of arms. In these replies, except those
                    relating to the exportation of arms to certain Latin American countries and to
                    China, the Department has stated that while it does not encourage the
                    exportation of arms to any country there are no legal restrictions on the
                    exportation of those commodities to the specific country mentioned by the
                    inquirer. A statement of this general tenor was contained in the Department’s
                    instruction No. 27 of November 14, 1928, to Mr. Southard.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d883fn6">
                        <ref target="frus1928v02#pg_802">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                            p. 802</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It may be added that the Department has not agreed to render Mr. Wise any
                    assistance beyond that which is accorded to any other American citizen in
                    similar circumstances. In October 1927, for instance, when Mr. Wise called and
                    asked that the Department request permission from the French Government for him
                    to transship arms at Djibouti, the Department refused to make the request and
                    indicated that he was at liberty to do so if he desired. In that connection Mr.
                    Wise was told that if the French Government should interpose any objections to
                    the shipment this Government would be entirely free to make such representations
                    on behalf of the American exporter as might be considered appropriate.</p>
                <p>On June 12, 1929, a Mr. King, at that time an associate of Mr. Wise, called at
                    the Department and requested some information regarding the exportation of arms
                    to Ethiopia. Mr. King was told that there was no change in the attitude of the
                    Department concerning the matter. Subsequently both Mr. King and Mr. Wise were
                    discouraged in their attempt to export arms to that country.</p>
                <p>It will appear from the foregoing brief statement of policy that the Department
                    has not encouraged Mr. Wise or any other American citizen or concern in an
                    effort to export arms and ammunition to Ethiopia.</p>
                <p>In paragraph numbered three in the second enclosure to despatch No. 331 of
                    January 22 Mr. Wise stated that the material ordered <pb facs="0864" n="766"
                        xml:id="pg_766"/> would be subject to the guarantees required by the United
                    States Government. In this statement Mr. Wise may have had in mind Article 4 of
                    the Convention for the Supervision of the International Trade in Arms and
                    Ammunition, signed at Geneva June 17, 1925,<note n="7" xml:id="d883fn7">
                        <ref target="frus1925v01#pg_61">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1925, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 61</ref>.</note> which provides that a
                    permission to export arms shall be signified by a license or by an export
                    declaration. Since the Convention has never been ratified by this Government the
                    obligations imposed by Article 4 cannot be enforced as a matter of law. However,
                    there are no obstacles to obtaining from the Collector of Customs at the port of
                    exportation a certified copy of the export declaration to accompany the shipment
                    if Mr. Wise so desires.</p>
                <p>In the third enclosure to despatch No. 331 of January 22 Mr. Wise proposed to
                    “have our military authorities release present United States Army equipment” for
                    exportation to Ethiopia. The only condition under which the War Department can
                    sell military equipment to a foreign government is to declare that a surplus
                    exists of the particular articles desired and then proceed with the sale. The
                    United States War Department has, however, on several occasions declared in
                    letters, of which the Department has copies, that it has no surplus equipment of
                    the nature that the Ethiopian Government desires. It is therefore highly
                    improbable that the War Department at this time could consider any request from
                    Mr. Wise on this subject.</p>
                <p>In the last paragraph of the third enclosure Mr. Wise refers to a Major Stack who
                    would be willing to proceed to Ethiopia for the purpose of accepting a
                    commission in the Ethiopian Army to train the military forces of that country.
                    Should an arrangement be concluded between Major Stack and the Ethiopian
                    Government it would be a private agreement between an American citizen and a
                    foreign government in which the Government of the United States could hardly be
                    required to take any part.</p>
                <p>Despatch No. 337 of January 27 encloses a copy of a request for quotations of
                    prices and a statement of the conditions under which the articles mentioned are
                    to be delivered on Ethiopian soil. It would appear that this document is only a
                    renewal of the request for bids which Mr. Wise received from Dr. Martin<note
                        n="8" xml:id="d883fn8">Dr. W. C. Martin.</note> when the latter visited the
                    United States in 1927. It is noted that under the terms of this letter, before
                    the bank in the United States can make any payment for the arms Mr. Wise must
                    submit a permit for the shipment of the arms to a specified city in Ethiopia and
                    a bill of lading, together with a guarantee from the manufacturer that the arms
                    are new and are officially adopted and used by the United States Army. The only
                    one of these conditions which may present any difficulty is the one regarding
                    the <pb facs="0865" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/> permit for transshipment to
                    Ethiopia presumably through Djibouti. It is believed that Mr. Wise would find it
                    less difficult to obtain such a permit if the Ethiopian Government should
                    promptly ratify the treaty relating to the importation of arms into Ethiopia
                    recently signed by representatives of Ethiopia, Great Britain, France and
                        Italy.<note n="9" xml:id="d883fn9">For text of treaty, signed at Paris,
                        August 21, 1930, see <hi rend="italic">British and Foreign State
                        Papers</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cxxxiv</hi>, p. 332.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Department has been informed orally by Mr. Southard that he has carefully
                    explained to King Tafari the policy of the Government of the United States with
                    respect to the exportation of arms.</p>
                <p>In order to complete the information of the Legation regarding the provisions of
                    international conventions and agreements bearing on the exportation of arms to
                    Ethiopia, there is enclosed a copy of a memorandum on that subject prepared by
                    Mr. K. E. Carlson of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs of the
                        Department.<note n="10" xml:id="d883fn10">Dated November 1, 1928; not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. P. Cotton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
