<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Douglas
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d133</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">133</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-03-27T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-03-27T15:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-27T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-27T15:00:00-05:00" n="133" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.20/3–2749: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-27T20:00:00+00:00">March 27, 1949—8 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1220. <gloss target="#t_ECC1">ECC</gloss> discussed principle of “equality of
                    treatment” in <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> request for <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> and has following comments to make:</p>
                <p>We fully appreciate pressures—Congressional, press and public—on Department
                    regarding Indonesian question. It is not intent this message to concern itself
                    with substance of Indonesian problem or Dutch actions. However we believe you
                    would wish us to keep you informed of reaction to be expected in Europe to
                    assertion by US of right to interpret unilaterally our UN obligations by
                    suspending arms shipments under <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> to Dutch.
                    Our comments are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>In asserting that right, we would be acting on assumption that French,
                            British, Luxembourg, and Belgians will be less zealous than ourselves in
                            carrying out our common and identical UN obligations and that common
                            approach to Indonesian problem would be impossible. As matter of fact,
                            closer relations made possible by <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>
                            should <pb facs="0266" n="252" xml:id="pg_252"/> facilitate such
                            approach and the reaching of a common position in which Dutch could
                            cooperate.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>In joining with us in <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> governments are assuming grave
                            responsibilities. They are agreeing to make common contribution to
                            common defense, in which security of all, including US, is indivisibly
                            involved. From point of view of immediate danger of war on own
                            territory, European powers consider risks assumed by them greater than
                            ours. Is it reasonable to expect them to accept a situation in which
                            defense potential of one partner (Netherlands) might be suddenly
                            diminished by American decision involving unilateral interpretation of
                            international engagements to which all partners have subscribed? Can a
                            common strategic concept be built upon such a possible development
                            arising out of unilateral action by US?</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We have been urging integration—both economic and political—on
                            European nations. Some progress is being made. It seems therefore most
                            unfortunate that in case of military integration, where governments
                            concerned are dealing with lives or deaths of their countries, we should
                            foreshadow a refusal to deal with <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> as a
                            unit on this problem, a problem in which we state that our conduct will
                            be governed by our UN obligations which somehow or other, we imply, are
                            not identical with obligations of Britain, France, Belgium and
                            Luxembourg or which we will observe and they will not. Will not this
                            policy be interpreted by European countries as being on [<hi rend="italic">one of?</hi>] keeping a close string on each <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> member separately rather than one of
                            strengthening common organization and promoting common decisions? Is
                            that policy therefore not thoroughly inconsistent with the broad
                            objectices of <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> and the Atlantic Pact?</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>It seems to us that if we insist upon our position, the other
                            members—Britain, France, Belgium and Luxembourg—will be unable to comply
                            with their commitments to each other under <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> will therefore
                            disintegrate to [omission] alternatively, will be unable to enter upon
                            the mutually and collective [apparent garble] undertaking with us on
                                <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> (or possibly the Atlantic Pact).
                            Thus, we are confronted it seems to us, with a dilemma; either we are
                            prepared to admit that all <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> countries
                            and the US are bound equally by their obligations under the charter of
                            UN and should, as a unit, honor them iii accordance with a common
                            interpretation of their meaning, or, alternatively, take a course which
                            may mean either, (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The disruption of <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss>, or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the
                            isolation of US from <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss>, and therefore
                            from the hard military core of the European portion of the Atlantic Pact
                            membership. Either alternative is unpleasant.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>From strategic point of view, defense Western Europe is combined
                            problem not related necessarily with Indonesia. Geography does not
                            permit ignoring any one country. If they do not hang together they will
                            be hanged separately. Dutch mission in common defense is vital. If Dutch
                            forces inadequate in numbers or armament to hold north flank on natural
                            barrier, entire defense could be flanked and objectives and expense of
                                <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> negatived. Continental thinking
                            has not forgotten strategic lessons World Wars I and II. This may help
                            explain great concern <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> countries about
                            US insistence in declaring possible intent unilaterally to refuse arms
                            assistance to one partner of <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0267" n="253" xml:id="pg_253"/>
                <p>Already, under present strategic concept, Dutch would have to concede large part
                    their country to invader in order to make stand on agreed position.</p>
                <p>Disheartening effect US action re arms has further shaken Dutch and may
                    jeopardize <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> and Atlantic Pact.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 1220, repeated Hague 53, Paris 225, Brussels 64.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
