<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d184</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">184</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-09-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3xWCKc8tJ1gyWw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-09-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="184"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d184">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.20/9–1449</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-09-14">September 14,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Bevin</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Sir Oliver Franks</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Sir Gladwyn Jebb</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Sir Roger Makins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Barclay<note n="1" xml:id="d184fn1">Roderick E. Barclay, Principal
                                Private Secretary to the British Foreign Minister.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Acheson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Ambassador Jessup</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. McGhee<note n="2" xml:id="d184fn2">George C. McGhee, Assistant
                                Secretary of State for Near Eastern and African Affairs.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Thompson<note n="3" xml:id="d184fn3">Llewellyn E. Thompson, Jr.,
                                Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Achilles</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Satterthwaite</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Pact</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Bevin opened by saying that the Working Group on the Atlantic Pact has almost
                    made it unnecessary for him to stay in Washington for the council.</p>
                <p>He thought that we should persuade Italy to withdraw its claim to be a member of
                    the standing group. If Sforza made a speech pressing this claim, he might draw
                    some curt replies from some of the other countries. I said we would do our best
                    to prevent Sforza from raising this issue in the meeting. We see no reason why
                    Italy should be in a standing group. We might change the name of the regional
                    group to the “Southern European-Western Mediterranean Group” and give further
                    assurances for full coordination between the groups, if that would help Sforza.
                    Bevin repeated that from the British point of view, it was most important to
                    keep Italy off the standing group. I agreed.</p>
                <p>Bevin then said he had been perturbed about our unwillingness to be full members
                    of the European regional groups. He would like us to be full partners in all
                    their activities. He understood our military and political difficulties but
                    hoped we would take as active a part as possible and be represented by high
                    ranking officers who could speak authoritatively for the Joint Chiefs. The
                    French had tried to get the British to make specific commitments on their
                    contribution of ground forces. The British feared being caught between pressure
                    from the French for commitments in advance of or outside the grand plan and our
                    unwillingness to furnish information on our own plans adequate <pb facs="0340"
                        n="326" xml:id="pg_326"/> to enable the British to make theirs. The British,
                    like us, must pay due attention to global strategy.</p>
                <p>Bevin then stated that he understood from his advisers that, if he submitted two
                    questions on our position he would receive an answer which, while not all that
                    he would desire, would be the best we could give. He handed me the attached <hi
                        rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> and I handed him the attached reply.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d184fn4">This arrangement was worked out by Achilles and Jebb
                        and was approved by British authorities and by the Office of the Secretary
                        of Defense after consultation with representatives of the Director of the
                        Joint Staff. Acheson was briefed on the plan by a memorandum directed to him
                        by Achilles on September 14; not printed (740.5/9–1450).</note>
                </p>
                <p>I went on to say that we also were pressed by various countries for specific
                    commitments which we were not in a position to give. We realized the British
                    problem but believed that such matters could be discussed bilaterally much
                    better than in the regional groups. The Joint Chiefs of Staff could not be
                    expected at this time either specifically to define “participation as
                    appropriate” or to express complete views on the strategic conduct of a war. Our
                    unwillingness to commit our forces on a piece-meal basis did not imply any
                    dodging of responsibility.</p>
                <p>Bevin then said that if Britain fully met the French desire for commitments on
                    the continent, there would be no troops left for the Middle East. I said we
                    could handle that between ourselves. He asked how much pressure the French had
                    recently been exerting on us and was advised that the fact that the French were
                    to be members of the Standing Group had temporarily reduced the pressure but
                    that it would of course be renewed as soon as the organization began to
                    function.</p>
                <p>Bevin then referred to the Economic and Financial Committee. He said Cripps
                    agreed that it was desirable to delay establishing it. I agreed.</p>
                <p>Bevin suggested that there be an Economic and Financial Committee on the
                    ministerial level as well as one on the expert level. I thought that it would be
                    a mistake to have too many committees, a Financial and Economic Committee at a
                    high level with whatever special assistance was necessary would do. Bevin
                    agreed.</p>
                <p>In reply to Bevin’s inquiry as to whether the Council would finish on Saturday
                    Mr. Achilles said the only problems remaining were those raised by Sforza and
                    that the discussions should be finished Saturday.</p>
                <p>I said that if the <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> passed Congress in its
                    present form, a hundred million would be available immediately and four hundred
                    million only when there was a plan. Achilles said we had reminded the other
                    countries of this and hoped that following the October 5th <pb facs="0341"
                        n="327" xml:id="pg_327"/> meeting and the military meeting immediately
                    thereafter, planning would begin at once.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Attachment A</head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Working Party is recommending the setting up under the Atlantic Pact of
                        five regional groups to prepare detailed plans for possible war. Two of
                        these groups, the North Atlantic Ocean Group and the United States-Canadian
                        Group, are regions in which the United States is geographically located and
                        the United States have announced their intention of playing a full part in
                        all their activities. In the other three groups, the North European, the
                        Western European, and the Western Mediterranean, which will probably be
                        located in Europe, the United States provide for their participation in the
                        following terms:—</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The United States have been requested and have agreed to participate
                            actively in the defence planning as appropriate.”</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>The British Chiefs of Staff have not yet been able to find out from their
                        United States colleagues what precise form of participation this formula is
                        intended to embrace and we are therefore still somewhat in the dark. But we
                        feel very strongly that the fullest United States participation in these
                        groups is essential to the success of the Pact both from the military and
                        the political points of view. The United States and British Chiefs of Staff
                        are both agreed that the real work—the work which will make defence under
                        the Atlantic Pact a reality—has got to be done in the regions. The idea that
                        this important work should be carried out with anything less than the full
                        cooperation of the United States seems to us to be quite out of tune with
                        the whole Atlantic Pact conception.</p>
                    <p>As we see it the two essentials are:— <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>that United States representatives be appointed to play an active
                                role in the work of the three European Regional Planning
                                Groups;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>that these representatives should be in a position authoritatively
                                to represent the views of the United States Chiefs of Staff.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>In our view, failure of the United States to associate themselves with the
                        European Regions on the above basis will mean that the existing Western
                        European Organisation will slowly die.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1949-09-14">14th September, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0342" n="328" xml:id="pg_328"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Attachment B</head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The United States will appoint representatives to play an active role in the
                        work of the three European regional planning groups within the limits of the
                        policy of the United States Joint Chiefs of Staff, and it is hoped that
                        their work will lead to the further development of policy by the Joint
                        Chiefs of Staff as may be necessary.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-09-14">September 14,
                                1949</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
