<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom (
                        Holmes
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d193</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">193</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-10-07T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-10-07T05:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-10-07T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-10-07T05:00:00-05:00" n="193" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.20/10–749: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Holmes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-10-07T11:00:00+01:00">October 7, 1949—11 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4023. For <gloss target="#t_FACC1">FACC</gloss> from <gloss target="#t_ECC1">ECC</gloss>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>In view urgency of initiating additional military production program in
                        Europe, and in light of sections 101 and 102, Senate Bill 2388, reference
                        “integrated defense <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> area”, following
                        comments are submitted:</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>It has not been possible, without definite knowledge of stocks to be made
                        available by US, adequately to screen Western Union production program.
                        Further, to our knowledge, <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> production
                        program has never been screened by US as a program to determine: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Desirability of producing items from priority point of view. In
                                other words, does production schedule proposed meet the highest
                                priority of items in which <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss>
                                deficient after deduction of US stocks to be made available, and of
                                items probably to be procured from production in US?</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Items which can best be produced in Italy or by other non-<gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> European pact countries.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Distinction between overall program review, and individual project review
                        should be kept clearly in mind. Project review, without overall production
                        program review, can result only in piecemeal approach to problem.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Recognized, however, that work already accomplished by <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> cannot be scrapped—that present proposed
                        production schedules, in <pb facs="0357" n="342" xml:id="pg_342"/> spite of
                        unsatisfactory nature in many respects, is a basis on which to build a
                        better coordinated program for Europe.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Many projects within <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> program clearly in
                        line with military priorities (reference London’s 3956,<note n="1" xml:id="d193fn1">Telegram 3956, October 3, not printed.</note> repeated
                        Paris 744) and project justification can proceed on these items looking
                        toward their initiation at earliest possible moment.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Certain other items which represent production superimposed on existing
                        military production, which are not of the highest priority, may have to be
                        accepted by US within limits of program as probably the best <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> can do in view of present capabilities. There
                        may be some items, however, even in this area, unjustifiable on a priority
                        or on economic basis. US must make clear will not give dollar support to
                        individual projects which are non-essential and seem to be proposed on
                        nationalist or non military basis.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Where projects require new tooling or represent entirely new production,
                        careful consideration of a coordinated production program for Western Europe
                        is in order.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Where certain production items are not acceptable to US as result of
                        review suggested above, US should be in position to suggest others for
                        consideration of <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> countries, or request
                            <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> countries to initiate such suggestions
                        themselves.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Consideration should be given in overall program review of the
                        desirability of encouraging production for future requirements (including
                        spare parts in Europe) of certain items presently available from US stocks
                        to fill partial <gloss target="#t_WU1">WU</gloss> requirements. Such
                        encouragement, subject to security considerations, would further the
                        principle of self-help.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Request Washington advice on mechanics by which steps along lines
                        mentioned above are to be performed, including integration of non-Western
                        Union production capabilities and net deficiencies of all Western European
                        pact countries.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Sent Department 4023, repeated Paris 763 (for Harriman).</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Holmes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
