<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="206" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">840.20/12–549</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy Under
                                Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-05">December 5, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                <cell>Turkish Ambassador</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Dean Rusk, Deputy Under Secretary</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>
                                    <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>: John D. Jernegan</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>The Ambassador called, at his request, to ask whether I could tell him
                            anything about the security relationships produced by the linking of
                            Great Britain and the United States in the North Atlantic Pact while
                            Britain was in turn linked to Turkey by the Anglo-French-Turkish Treaty
                            of Alliance of 1939. He recalled that he had raised this question with
                            me some time ago.</p>
                        <p>I said that we had been giving considerable study to the whole problem of
                            these interlocking relationships around the world. Right in our own back
                            yard, for example, we had the question of the Rio Pact and the effect on
                            its members of United States participation in the North Atlantic Treaty.
                            However, there appeared to be many ramifications and it was proving
                            extremely difficult and might even be impossible to arrive at a
                            clear-cut juridical picture. Very possibly, we would never be able to
                            give a positive statement as to what automatic obligations would arise
                            out of the various commitments we and our associates had made. This was
                            true even as between the members of the North Atlantic Treaty itself. So
                            much would depend upon the way in which a concrete case might arise,
                            that is, under the circumstances in which we and our associates might be
                            called upon to consider what we should do in the light of our security
                            obligations.</p>
                        <p>We were continuing our studies and, I said, I would be glad to talk to
                            the Ambassador again from time to time as our thinking developed. For
                            the moment, it seemed to me that the adherence of Great Britain to the
                            North Atlantic Treaty, taken in conjunction with the existing UK-Turkish
                            Treaty, had had a positive effect on Turkey’s security position, but I
                            could not say more than that. I could not define precisely what this
                            effect had been in terms of a direct relationship between Turkey and
                            members of the North Atlantic Treaty other than Britain.</p>
                        <p>I asked the Ambassador how he viewed Turkey’s present situation and the
                            attitude of the Turkish people toward security questions. Mr. Erkin said
                            that while there had been no new developments in Turkey’s relationship
                            with the USSR and her international position was therefore relatively
                            calm, he could not say that the Turkish people were satisfied with the
                            existing security arrangements. They were conscious of the lack of any
                            commitment on the part of the United <pb facs="0375" n="360" xml:id="pg_360"/> States to assist Turkey if she were attacked.
                            Until Turkish-American relations were “clarified” by means of a formal
                            mutual defense arrangement the Turkish people would never feel fully
                            satisfied with their international situation.</p>
                        <p>I remarked that Turkey’s Treaty with Great Britain did not obligate
                            Turkey to do anything which might involve her in a war with the Soviet
                            Union. In any new arrangements which she might make with the Western
                            Powers, would Turkey be willing to omit that reservation? The Ambassador
                            hastened to say that conditions had changed since the Treaty of 1939 was
                            drawn up. It was obvious that any aggression at the present time could
                            only come from the USSR. Consequently, Turkey would be quite willing to
                            omit any reservation with regard to the Soviet Union. He added that he
                            understood the British Government did not want at this time to revise
                            the 1939 Treaty, since to do so would be provocative to the
                            Russians.</p>
                        <p>In commenting on a remark of mine, which he appeared to misunderstand,
                            Ambassador Erkin remarked that if the attitudes of the other members of
                            the North Atlantic Treaty should be a stumbling-block in the way of a
                            defense arrangement between Turkey, Great Britain, France and the United
                            States, he was sure the Turkish Government would be willing to make
                            special provision to the effect that the obligations undertaken by the
                            three Western Powers with respect to Turkey would not in any way involve
                            the other <gloss target="#t_NAP1">NAP</gloss> members despite their
                            common association with the US–UK and France in the North Atlantic
                            group. I made it clear that I was not suggesting any new arrangements
                            but was merely trying to explore the interlocking effects of the present
                            arrangements.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>