<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Belgium (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d270</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">270</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-12-02T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-12-02T13:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="jurisdiction" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-02T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-02T13:00:00-05:00" n="270" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d270">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50 Recovery/12–249: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Belgium</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Brussels</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-02T19:00:00+01:00">December 2, 1949—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1624. In accordance with <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1399 November
                        30<note n="1" xml:id="d270fn1">Not printed; it asked Murphy to consult with
                        Van Zeeland with regard to the proposed message from Acheson to the <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> governments, as indicated in telegram
                        4139 to London, November 16, <ref target="#pg_448">p. 448</ref>, the text of
                        which was sent in telegram 1400 to Brussels.</note> accompanied by Nuveen
                    and Bonsal I called on Van Zeeland today and after reviewing Department’s
                    thinking presented him with text of message included in your 1400, 30
                    November.</p>
                <p>After reading it carefully Van Zeeland said he found no difference of substance
                    between Department’s approach and his own plan which was circulated 24
                    November.</p>
                <p>Ockrent<note n="2" xml:id="d270fn2">Roger Ockrent, Secretary General of the
                        Belgian administration for the European Recovery Program.</note> suggested
                    one minor amendment in 6th Paragraph which was agreed to subject Department’s
                        approval,<note n="3" xml:id="d270fn3">The Department of State agreed to the
                        proposed change (Telegram 1419 to Brussels, December 5, 840.50
                        Recovery/12–249).</note> namely the sentence: “to work with Ministers of
                        <gloss target="#t_PCs1">PC’s</gloss> and officials of US Government in
                    coordinating activities developing carrying out policies and measures to
                    establish agreed ends”; would be amended to read: “to work with Ministers of
                        <gloss target="#t_PCs1">PC’s</gloss> and officials of US Government to help
                    coordinate activities and develop policies and measures to accomplish agreed
                    ends;” reason for this was stated be technical, legal one as US language seemed
                    to contemplate transfer of executive authority.</p>
                <p>Van Zeeland gave us outline of his conception of tactics to be pursued. He said
                    invitation should go on out for meeting of Consultative Group to take place 20
                    December. In meantime governments of each of <gloss target="#t_PCs1">PC’s</gloss> would have an opportunity to study suggestions outlined in his
                    paper referred above. They also were aware of additional suggestions which Van
                    Zeeland has made re improvement in practice operation of <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss>. He mentioned establishment offices, monthly
                    meeting and suggestion meetings be reduced in size so Ministers would each be
                    attended by only one assistant; meeting to be held around small table so more
                    effective working atmosphere might prevail, et cetera.</p>
                <pb facs="0471" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/>
                <p>I asked for his opinion re timing of Secretary’s proposed message to <gloss target="#t_PCs1">PC’s</gloss>. He thought that as this was “hoten” message
                    delivery of it should be deferred until 2 or 3 days before proposed meeting 20
                    December, when its leverage would be most effective, but that this would be
                    flexible date depending on interim developments. He expressed view that
                    Secretary’s message would be of greatest value. If he encountered unexpected
                    difficulties in obtaining agreement by all countries to 20 December meeting,
                    delivery of Secretary’s message might be suggested for earlier date.</p>
                <p>I also asked for Van Zeeland’s opinion re necessity of modification of <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> convention and he reaffirmed his previous
                    statement that no modification is necessary. However to make assurance doubly
                    sure he is obtaining opinion of well-known international jurist to support his
                    view. He was aware of Bevin’s and Marjolin’s view that convention would require
                    modification. He thought they could be brought round and mentioned that Cripps
                    agreed modification is not necessary.</p>
                <p>I told Van Zeeland that as I had had no contact with early development of plan
                    and no opportunity for discussion with Spaak personally, I would be grateful for
                    Van Zeeland’s estimate of Spaak’s current attitude toward it. Van Zeeland said
                    Spaak was his candidate now as he had been in beginning; that he thought Spaak
                    would be willing to accept position without being too fussy regarding a
                    definition of his eventual jurisdiction. However, said Van Zeeland, if Spaak in
                    end did not accept, objective should be pursued and next best man selected. He
                    referred in this connection to his own offer to resign as chairman of Council of
                    Ministers if Spaak accepts, and said he believed his offer had helped influence
                    British not to oppose plan. It was apparent Van Zeeland had not recently
                    discussed with Spaak latter’s availability. Spaak has been absent from Brussels
                    almost continuously during past weeks but will call me on his return from
                    Switzerland. It is our opinion Van Zeeland actually favors Spaak for place both
                    because Spaak is ideally suited for it and also because to some degree at least
                    it eliminates Spaak from Belgium domestic politics.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
