<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Political Adviser at Trieste ( (Baldwin) ) to the Secretary
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d291</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">291</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-07-13T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-07-13T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-07-13T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-13T11:00:00-05:00" n="291"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d291">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860S.00/7–1349: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser at Trieste</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Baldwin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Trieste</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-07-13T17:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 13, 1949—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>485. R. J. Routledge ea [<hi rend="italic">E.M.?</hi>] British Royal Army Service
                    Corps killed by gunfire from Yugoslav border guards at 2240 July 10. Yugoslav
                    Army personnel refused release body until <gloss target="#t_AMG1">AMG</gloss>
                    commission made inquiry. Major General Hoge Acting Zone Commander authorized
                    appointment commission comprising British military personnel. Commission
                    conducted inquiry from 2000 to 2115 hours July 11 from 800 to 1200 hours July
                    10. Statements by Yugoslav military personnel indicate British soldier shot
                    inside Yugoslavia after refusing recognize challenge and attempting cross border
                    into Zone A. Yugoslavs admit firing two bursts; first wounded soldier who fell
                    and second was apparently fired very close to soldier’s head. Yugoslavs deny
                    recognizing soldier who was in British uniform. Commission discovered body
                    located approximately 60 meters inside Yugoslavia. When report of commission
                    shown Yugoslav border guard officers they refused release body until certain
                    changes made in report effect of which would have been to partially exonerate
                    Yugoslavs from responsibility. They insisted report indicate commission had
                    established as fact Yugoslav version of incident. Senior officer inquiry
                    commission refused alter report and again unsuccessfully demanded body. Later
                    after consultation with General Hoge he returned to scene of incident and again
                    demanded body in name of Acting Zone Commissioner. Meanwhile Hoge made strong
                    protest to Yugoslav mission here terming Yugoslav refusal release body inhuman,
                    unreasonable, unnecessary and demanding immediate release. Oral reply from
                    mission blamed delay on fact that “report could not be signed owing to reasons
                    not essential being put forward by Allied commission” and said that body would
                    be handed over when report was signed.</p>
                <p>In second note to Yugoslav mission July 13, Hoge stated Yugoslav oral reply
                    contains no satisfactory explanation and expressed amazement at Yugoslav
                    officers’ insistence that Allied inquiry report be worded in manner acceptable
                    to them before body could be released, an act which Hoge termed a form of
                    duress. Hoge again protested strongly against Yugoslav action and said matter
                    was being fully reported to Washington, London.</p>
                <p>Incident has aroused considerable interest here. Local papers playing up story
                    asserting British soldier shot in back by Yugoslavs. Brief <gloss
                        target="#t_AMG1">AMG</gloss> press release merely gives identity soldier and
                    refers to Yugoslavs version of incident but does not mention fact that body
                    still in Yugoslavia although this presumably well known by local press.</p>
                <pb facs="0529" n="514" xml:id="pg_514"/>
                <p>So far as can be determined Yugoslav guards probably within rights in wounding
                    fleeing soldier for purpose detaining him. British doctor on inquiry commission
                    unable determine whether first wounds would have caused death; however, second
                    possibly third firing at close range obviously brutal act completely lacking
                    justification. Yugoslavs persistent refusal release body unless assured inquiry
                    report would virtually exonerate them from all responsibility indicates their
                    anxiety over results more exhaustive investigation which will soon be impossible
                    because of decomposition of body.</p>
                <p>As further efforts here obtain body obviously futile Hoge considers that any
                    further action should be taken by Washington, London, Belgrade.</p>
                <p>British PolAd telegraphing Foreign Office, British Embassy, Washington.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 485; repeated Belgrade 55.<note n="1" xml:id="d291fn">
                        <p>In telegram 495 of July 19, not printed, Baldwin reported from Trieste
                            that the British soldier’s body had been delivered to British officers
                            on July 18 (860S.00/7–1949).</p>
                        <p>In the Department’s telegram 436 of August 5 to Belgrade, not printed,
                            the Ambassador was informed that his British colleague had been
                            instructed to accept the apologies of the Yugoslav Foreign Office but
                            also to advise that the British Government expected the Yugoslav
                            Government to pay compensation and to take all possible action to
                            prevent unnecessary firing on Allied soldiers on the <gloss
                                target="#t_FTT1">FTT</gloss> frontiers. (860S.00/7–1349)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Baldwin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
