<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-07-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="323" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d323">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">865.014/7–2849</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy Under
                                Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d323fn1">Drafted by Joseph N. Greene, Jr.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-07-19">July 19, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell>Ambassador Tarchiani</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Rusk, <gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Greene, <gloss target="#t_SWE1">SWE</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ambassador Tarchiani called by appointment; he said that he is leaving at
                            the end of the week for a month’s leave in Italy, and wanted to be able
                            to report to the Foreign Minister in Rome the views of the United States
                            on the disposition of the former Italian colonies.</p>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador that the Department of State has been considering
                            the question in the light of developments at and since the last session
                            of the General Assembly. I added that the Department felt somewhat
                            handicapped by not having available the current thinking of our friends,
                            or their informal reactions to the views which, I understood, had been
                            informally conveyed to them at a working level.</p>
                        <p>I observed that I would be glad to outline for him the general lines of
                            the Department’s current thinking, and wanted to be sure that it be
                            understood that these views do not necessarily constitute a fixed
                            position and that we would welcome the comments of other interested
                            governments.</p>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador that for Libya we are thinking about independence
                            at an early date, probably not more than three years hence; that the
                            nature of the Libyan state should probably be left to the determination
                            of the inhabitants; and that during the interim prior to complete
                            independence, there should be an advisory council, comprising the United
                            Kingdom, France, Italy, United States and Egypt, to advise the present
                            administration on the development of the area toward independence. After
                            the interim period, all governments desiring to enter into relations
                            with the Libyan Government will of course be free to seek appropriate
                            treaty arrangements.</p>
                        <p>Regarding Eritrea, I said that we continued to favor the cession of all
                            except the western province to Ethiopia with appropriate municipal
                            charters for Asmara and Massawa; we felt that the best disposition of
                            the western province would be its annexation to the Sudan.</p>
                        <p>With regard to Italian Somaliland I said that Italian trusteeship is our
                            preference.</p>
                        <pb facs="0584" n="569" xml:id="pg_569"/>
                        <p>In reply to the Ambassador’s question, I said that the Department has had
                            no indication of the views of the British Government. The Ambassador
                            observed that in his opinion, the French Government might not like the
                            idea of establishing an independent Libya, and he went on to discuss the
                            differences between the social structures in Cyrenaica and Tripolitania,
                            indicating that these differences are not in his view conducive to
                            successfully uniting them into one country. At the same time, he said,
                            he appreciates the difficulties attendant upon the creation of small
                            states in the present world situation as well as the difficulties of
                            determining the disposition of Fezzan if Tripolitania and Cyrenaica are
                            separated.</p>
                        <p>I again assured the Ambassador that the Department would be glad to have
                            a detailed expression of the Italian Government’s views on the whole
                            question.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Rusk</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>