<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-09-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="330" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d330">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">865.014/9–1449</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of
                                State</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d330fn1">Drafted by Livingston Lord
                                Satterthwaite, Deputy Director of the Office of British Commonwealth
                                and Northern European Affairs.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-09-14">September 14, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell>Count Sforza</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Ambassador Tarchiani</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Acheson</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Achilles</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Unger</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Satterthwaite</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sforza said that some of his friends in the United Nations were asking
                            what the status of the Italian Colonial problem was. He said <pb facs="0599" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/> the differences between the
                            British and Italians on Tripolitania were lessening. Bevin had told
                            Sforza that he did not want to stay in Tripolitania indefinitely. I said
                            I thought the problem was working itself out. Sforza said the recent
                            compromise with Bevin adopted for the last <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> session was not satisfactory to either: Although it
                            resulted in the British and Italians subsequently coming out for
                            independence in Tripolitania and Cyrenaica. Sforza said the Italians had
                            a good record in Eritrea and that if the majority there are for
                            independence, and he thinks this is true, independence would be possible
                            and would be consistent with the proposal for Libya. Achilles said our
                            reports from Eritrea are conflicting as to the strength of the sentiment
                            for independence. Sforza said he thought Ethiopia should not get what
                            doesn’t and has never belonged to her.</p>
                        <p>We discussed Tripolitania since Sforza said the British want a longer
                            period of military control than the Italians. I said I thought the
                            British would adjust, but that they want to be there long enough to do
                            something constructive. Sforza said he thought the British want to clear
                            up troubles with Italy and I agreed. Tarchiani said the problem is in
                            the hands of the United Nations. I said if the General Assembly goes
                            along, it should be possible to agree on a commission (advisory
                            council). We would take sympathetic views of Italy’s participation in
                            the life of Tripolitania. Sforza said the Italian policy is to create
                            economic and cultural relations but not political relations. Sforza said
                            Italian parliament realized that the independence of the Arab nations is
                            inevitable. The difficulty is the change-over from military to civilian
                            government. There is no fascism in Tripolitania, but the French are
                            prisoners of the violence of their landowners in North Africa.</p>
                        <p>We agreed that there should be no trouble in securing Italian trusteeship
                            for Somaliland, although Tarchiani thought there might be trouble with
                            some of the Asiatic states who did not realize it was difficult to
                            create a new state overnight. Sforza said that if something comes out of
                            the Point IV Program for Africa, Somaliland would be less of a burden on
                            Italy. Moreover Somaliland would provide a basis for Italian
                            participation in African development. Twenty-five years of trusteeship
                            would be needed, but in 25 years a colony which could be a state might
                            be worked out. This might well include British Somaliland, but the
                            French would probably never agree to relinquish French Somaliland.</p>
                        <p>We next discussed Eritrea and agreed that it might be difficult for
                            Eritrea to become an independent state because of its geographic,
                            economic, ethnic, and religious diversity. I suggested that the General
                            Assembly examine the problem of Eritrea to avoid the creation of an
                            independent state which would be a political and economic vacuum. I
                            asked whether it was the Italian suggestion that the disposition <pb facs="0600" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/> of Eritrea should be held up
                            if solutions to the other problems are found. Sforza agreed that those
                            that can be solved should be solved, and that Eritrea could be postponed
                            if the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> cannot agree at this
                            session.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>