<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Irwin M. Tobin of the Office of European Regional
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recFzikmNCJDCCGBL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade unions</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recjFJIAXOTleIVmh" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85083774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Labor law</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="397"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d397">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">865.5043/11–2249</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Irwin M. Tobin of the Office of European
                        Regional Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-22">November 22,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Norman Thomas has informed the Department that he will come in soon to discuss
                    the Italian labor situation, and particularly the issue of non-Communist labor
                    unification, in which he is deeply interested. In communications to the
                    Department, he has criticized severely what he and some of his American and
                    Italian friends and associates consider to be the United States Government’s
                    position in this matter.</p>
                <pb facs="0722" n="707" xml:id="pg_707"/>
                <p>Officers of the <gloss target="#t_AFL1">AFL</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CIO1"
                        >CIO</gloss>, who are also deeply concerned in Italian labor affairs, are
                    frequently in touch with Department officers on this subject.</p>
                <p>The attached policy statement with accompanying background information has been
                    prepared to serve as a guide and summary for officers of the Department who may
                    discuss this subject with Mr. Thomas and others. It is also being sent to our
                    Embassy in Rome for information and comments.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Policy Statement and Background Data on Unification of
                            Italian Non-Communist Trade Unions</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">i. department’s position on unification of the
                            non-communist labor organizations in italy</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Our objective, with respect to the Italian labor movement, is to
                            encourage the Italian non-Communists to achieve the maximum possible
                            unity of purpose and action, with a view to curbing Communist control
                            over Italian labor. We hope that non-Communist trade unions will find it
                            possible to combine forces, freely and harmoniously, at a time and in a
                            manner most likely to be effective. But, of course, all decisions,
                            including those on timing and method, must be taken only by the Italians
                            themselves. We have no intention of trying to impose any program.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The American Embassy and Labor Attaché in Rome are informed of the
                            Department’s attitude. We rely upon them to carry out our objectives in
                            the light of local circumstances as they see them. The U.S. Labor
                            Attaché in Rome, who also serves as Labor Adviser to the <gloss
                                target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission, is the principal U.S. official
                            in Italy concerned directly with Italian labor developments. He is
                            responsible, as attaché, for keeping the Embassy and the U.S. Government
                            informed on labor developments and, as <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                                >ECA</gloss> Labor Adviser, for seeking the greatest possible
                            cooperation of Italian labor in achieving the purposes of the <gloss
                                target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>In viewing his activities, a distinction should be kept in mind as
                            between his representing the official attitude of the U.S. Government
                            and the assistance he must give to U.S. trade unions and political
                            groups which are in intimate contact with Italian labor and attempt to
                            influence its development. Some of these Americans differ sharply in
                            their approach to Italian labor problems, and in aiding them the U.S.
                            Labor Attaché does not necessarily identify himself with their views or
                            activities.</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0723" n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">ii. attitudes of non-communist italian trade union
                            organizations towards unification</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The elements which would be most likely to join an Italian non-Communist
                        labor federation if the conditions of its formation met with their approval
                        are: the <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss>, whose membership (about
                        1.5 million) is primarily Christian-Democratic (<gloss target="#t_CD1"
                            >CD</gloss>); the <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>, whose membership
                        (about 150 thousand) is mainly right-wing or Saragat Socialist (<gloss
                            target="#t_PSLI1">PSLI</gloss>) and Republican (PRI); the “autonomous”
                        Socialists, composed of ex-left-wing or Nenni Socialist (<gloss
                            target="#t_PSI1">PSI</gloss>) and ex-<gloss target="#t_CGIL1"
                            >CGIL</gloss> labor leaders of high reputation in the labor movement but
                        with little organized following at present; and the “independents”, whose
                        membership (14 unions of unrevealed total membership) is primarily ex-<gloss
                            target="#t_PSI1">PSI</gloss> Socialist. In addition, several other
                        important non-Communist and non-fellow-traveller labor groups and unions
                        both in and out of the <gloss target="#t_CGIL1">CGIL</gloss> might become
                        interested in joining a strong non-Communist labor organization.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> under the leadership of
                            Giulio Pastore has taken the lead for unification, and in an effort to
                            pave the way has tried from the time of its foundation (October 1948) to
                            demonstrate that it is not controlled by the <gloss target="#t_CD1"
                                >CD</gloss>’s or by the Church. Pastore resigned his position in the
                            Catholic labor welfare organization (<gloss target="#t_ACLI1"
                                >ACLI</gloss>) and declared himself independent of the <gloss
                                target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss> party. While remaining a <gloss
                                target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss> deputy in Parliament, he has several
                            times opposed <gloss target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss>-sponsored legislation,
                            such as the proposed Fanfani labor law. Under his leadership the <gloss
                                target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> accepted a <gloss target="#t_PSLI1"
                                >PSLI</gloss> union leader, Alessandro Cappelletti, as head of
                            organization of its agricultural workers’ union (present membership
                            about 250 thousand). Yet, despite all these efforts, the <gloss
                                target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> is still widely regarded as a
                                <gloss target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss>-dominated, Christian labor
                            organization, which is an important obstacle to unification.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The top leadership of the <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>—Giovanni
                            Canini (<gloss target="#t_PSLI1">PSLI</gloss>) and Enrico Parri
                            (PRI)—have favored early unification from the time the <gloss
                                target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss> was founded (May 1949). To this end
                            they have also done their best to demonstrate that the <gloss
                                target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss> is independent of any political party.
                            But some of the lower-ranking leadership (e.g. Alfredo d’Andrea (<gloss
                                target="#t_PSLI1">PSLI</gloss>) and Giovanni Pasqualini (PRI)) and
                            many of the rank and file, especially in the smaller, less well
                            organized unions of the <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>, seem to
                            oppose early unification, on the grounds that the <gloss
                                target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss> should first become stronger so that in
                            joining with the <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> it will have
                            more influence and be less likely to be swallowed up by much stronger
                                <gloss target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss> elements.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The “autonomists”, headed by Romolo Bulleri, Italo Viglianesi and Enzo
                            Dalla Chiesa, ex-<gloss target="#t_PSI1">PSI</gloss> and ex-<gloss
                                target="#t_CGIL1">CGIL</gloss> labor leaders, strongly oppose early
                            unification with the <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> and propose
                            joining the <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>
                            <pb facs="0724" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/> on condition that it postpone
                            unification with the <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> and work
                            for its own strengthening first. The autonomists apparently follow the
                            political leadership of Giuseppe Romita, ex-<gloss target="#t_PSI1"
                                >PSI</gloss> independent Socialist, who favors unification of the
                            various anti-Communist splinters of the Socialist Party before trade
                            union unification with the <gloss target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss>’s. Thus the
                            position of the autonomists is similar to that of some of the lower
                            echelons of the <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>, with the addition
                            that they do not feel that the Socialist trade union organization can be
                            strong until the party is united. However, prospects of Socialist party
                            unification seem to have become less auspicious lately with the
                            resignation from the Cabinet of the three <gloss target="#t_PSLI1"
                                >PSLI</gloss> Ministers—Saragat, Tremelloni and Ivan Matteo
                            Lombardo—and the announcement that they will not meet in December as
                            planned with the Romita and Silone Socialist factions to discuss party
                            unification. In view of the position of the autonomists, this would seem
                            to postpone indefinitely their joining the <gloss target="#t_FIL1"
                                >FIL</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The “independents”, grouped loosely around Paolo Consoni, ex-<gloss
                                target="#t_PSI1">PSI</gloss>, and composed of unions of various
                            political tendencies, do not favor early unification with either the
                                <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> or the <gloss
                                target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>, fearing domination by both groups.
                            They are reportedly advancing the notion that their own group should
                            form the nucleus for eventual unification, as a means of averting
                            political domination.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Several non-Communist unions which have remained in the <gloss
                                target="#t_CGIL1">CGIL</gloss>, regarding the advantages thereof as
                            greater than they would now get by joining the <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1"
                                >LCGIL</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>, are
                            unenthusiastic about <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss>-<gloss
                                target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss> unification at this stage. However,
                            they might be induced to leave the <gloss target="#t_CGIL1">CGIL</gloss>
                            and join a unified non-Communist labor organization once it became
                            strong enough to offer them advantages comparable to those they now
                            enjoy in the <gloss target="#t_CGIL1">CGIL</gloss>.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>To sum up: The <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> and the top leaders of
                            <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss> appear to favor early unification of
                        their two organizations but the lower rank <gloss target="#t_FIL1"
                            >FIL</gloss> leaders and the autonomists seem to fear absorption or
                        domination by the stronger <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss>, still in
                        their view closely tied to the <gloss target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss> and the
                        Church. While not necessarily opposed to unification at some later date, the
                        latter put first Socialist Party unification and strengthening of the <gloss
                            target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">iii. main factors in the italian trade union situation
                            affecting non-communist unification</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The labor groups which now find themselves split into five main groups
                                (<gloss target="#t_CGIL1">CGIL</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1"
                                >LCGIL</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss>, autonomists and
                            independents), were from 1945–48 united in the <gloss target="#t_CGIL1"
                                >CGIL</gloss>. As of November 1949, however, the issue which had
                            caused four of the groups to withdraw from the <gloss target="#t_CGIL1"
                                >CGIL</gloss>—opposition to Communist domination of the labor
                            movement—had not yet proven of sufficient force and urgency to overcome
                            political and other differences between them and enable them to form a
                                <pb facs="0725" n="710" xml:id="pg_710"/> single non-Communist labor
                            federation. One reason for this seems to be that they had learned from
                            their <gloss target="#t_CGIL1">CGIL</gloss> experience that unity is not
                            desirable in itself without basic understanding and agreement.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The intensity of the opposition to early non-Communist labor
                            unification became apparent only in late October 1949, in contrast to
                            earlier indications that it might be achieved by the end of 1949. When
                                <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> brought top leaders of the
                                <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_FIL1"
                                >FIL</gloss>—Pastore (<gloss target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss>), Canini
                                (<gloss target="#t_PSLI1">PSLI</gloss>), and Rocchi (PRI)—to the
                            United States in April 1949, in their capacity of <gloss
                                target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Trade Union Advisory Committee in
                            Italy, it was hoped their visit would serve as a means of helping them
                            through close personal association over a period of weeks to agree upon
                            unification. This it did, and at meetings with leaders of the <gloss
                                target="#t_AFL1">AFL</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CIO1">CIO</gloss>
                            in New York they announced their agreement to complete unification by
                            the end of 1949. After their return to Italy, the first step in this
                            informal agreement, withdrawal of the <gloss target="#t_PSLI1"
                                >PSLI</gloss> and PRI unions from the <gloss target="#t_CGIL1"
                                >CGIL</gloss>, was carried out on schedule in May 1949. The <gloss
                                target="#t_PSLI1">PSLI</gloss> and PRI unions then promptly formed
                            the <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss> as a temporary organizational
                            maneuver to prepare for amalgamation with the <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1"
                                >LCGIL</gloss>. As late as September 8, 1949, when a top level
                                <gloss target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_PSLI1"
                                >PSLI</gloss>–PRI labor conference was held in Rome, it seemed that
                            the entire unification schedule would be carried out. But by late
                            October evidence was mounting that many serious difficulties were
                            arising and that unification might be postponed indefinitely. Apparently
                            there were four main reasons for the change between early September and
                            late October: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>The <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss>, despite all the
                                    efforts of Pastore, had failed to convince the
                                    Socialist-Republican rank and file that it was wholly free from
                                    clerical influence, which the Socialists and Republicans have
                                    traditionally fought in trade union affairs. This failure of the
                                        <gloss target="#t_LCGIL1">LCGIL</gloss> to overcome their
                                    doubts became increasingly important as the time of unification
                                    approached.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>The <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss> Socialists found as
                                    the test approached that their right-wing leadership was not
                                    sufficiently strong to carry even its own following into
                                    unification. This was partly due to the desire of lower echelon
                                        <gloss target="#t_FIL1">FIL</gloss> leaders to strengthen
                                    their organization before amalgamating with the stronger <gloss
                                        target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss>’s, and partly to the influence of
                                    the ex-<gloss target="#t_PSI1">PSI</gloss> autonomists, who
                                    argued, perhaps as pawns of Romita’s political ambitions, that
                                    Socialist trade unions could only be strong if the Socialist
                                    party was first unified. There was also the influence of the
                                    Socialists among the independents, led by an ex-<gloss
                                        target="#t_PSI1">PSI</gloss>, ex-<gloss target="#t_CGIL1"
                                        >CGIL</gloss> labor leader, who feared both <gloss
                                        target="#t_CD1">CD</gloss> and Communist domination and saw
                                    the independents as a possible nucleus for a new, non-political,
                                    non-Communist trade union federation.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Despite all efforts to the contrary, it has so far proven
                                    impossible for Italian trade unionism to divorce itself wholly
                                    from political affiliations. The Italian labor movement has
                                    traditionally been highly political, with the result that
                                    political schisms are bound to accentuate rivalries among the
                                    unions.</item>
                                <pb facs="0726" n="711" xml:id="pg_711"/>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                <item>The … support for unification given by the <gloss
                                        target="#t_AFL1">AFL</gloss> and (to a much smaller degree)
                                    by some elements of the <gloss target="#t_CIO1">CIO</gloss> was
                                    directed to the top leadership only, and had no discernible
                                    influence on the rank and file. The misgivings of some Americans
                                    and Italians aired in the Italian press in late September and
                                    early October found an unexpectedly wide response, showing
                                    plainly that insufficient ground-work had been done to prepare
                                    the way for unification.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
