<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chief of the Division of British Commonwealth Affairs
                        (
                        Satterthwaite
                    ) to the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                        Affairs (
                        Perkins
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v04</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d444</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">444</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-08-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="444" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d444">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.41/8–949</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chief of the Division of British Commonwealth Affairs</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Satterthwaite</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Perkins</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-08-09">August 9,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Subjects Other Than Economic Which Cripps and Bevin Are
                    Likely To Bring up in the September Talks.</p>
                <p>The subjects which Cripps and Bevin will want to discuss in Washington, and their
                    approach to them, will depend to a large extent on the progress of the economic
                    talks.</p>
                <p>We may expect the British to take the offensive in the talks, and in effect say
                    “Here is the spot we’re in, what are you going to do about it”? Nevertheless,
                    their position is sufficiently difficult so that if we have a strong plan which
                    shows some signs of working, and they think we mean to carry it out, they will
                    do almost anything we ask them. If, however, we do not have a strong plan which
                    looks as if it could be a long-term solution to the problem, there is a great
                    danger that the British will make a well thought-out attempt to blame their own
                    and the western world’s ills on the United States. In this case, they will
                    probably formally abandon adherence to multilateralism and do what they can to
                    seal off the sterling area from the dollar world, whether we acquiesce or not,
                    and we will lose some of our ability to control events. A deterioration of
                    military and general cooperation between the United States and Britain, and in
                    our ability to utilize the British to help us protect our world position, would
                    almost certainly <pb facs="0821" n="806" xml:id="pg_806"/> take place if there
                    was a rift in our economic and financial relations. It seems to me that we never
                    have been in a better position to call the turn with the British, if we know
                    what we want and have a plan, nor in a more vulnerable position to absorb
                    needless and unjust blame if we fail to exercise our leadership. The trouble
                    with a short range plan to carry them over a crisis for six months or so, is
                    that the British won’t agree to take sufficiently drastic measures to cure
                    anything fundamental, if they have no assurances as to what will happen when the
                    stimulant wears off.</p>
                <p>Specifically, it is probable that the British will want to give up some of the
                    military commitments which they have all over the world, not only those which
                    involve some out go of dollars but those involving only sterling. This will be
                    aggravated by the failure in recent months of British recruitment for their
                    armed forces. The degree to which the British give up their military commitments
                    will, of course, be influenced by their estimates of the usefulness of whatever
                    help, financial or otherwise, they get from us.</p>
                <p>The British will probably want to discuss the agenda for the September meeting of
                    the General Assembly of the United Nations, as for example, Italian Colonies,
                    India’s membership in Security Council et cetera.</p>
                <p>The British will want to discuss Far Eastern policy. It is probable that their
                    commitments on Hong Kong and elsewhere in the Far East will depend directly on
                    their estimates of their own strength over the next few years, which are in turn
                    dependent on what they think we will do to help.</p>
                <p>We have asked our Embassy in London for a list of subjects, other than financial
                    and economic, which Bevin may wish to discuss with us.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
