<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Fifteenth Meeting of the Washington Exploratory Talks on
                    Security, March 4, 1949</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d87</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">87</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recu0jAoErrAESV42" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002775"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Airlift</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="87"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d87">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.20/3–449</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Fifteenth Meeting of the Washington Exploratory
                        Talks on Security, March 4, 1949</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1949-03-04">March 4, 1949</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that after the last Ambassadors’
                    meeting he had received the expected communication from the Norwegian Ambassador
                    and had given him the reply which had been agreed upon at the meeting. The
                    Norwegian Ambassador would be joining in the discussions later on in the
                    morning.</p>
                <p>A discussion took place on the subject of Italy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> repeated his previous statements,
                    that the Netherlands Government would welcome Italy’s admission if the majority
                    thought it advisable to invite her. The inclusion of Algeria in the Pact, which
                    already covered Corsica, had strengthened Italy’s case.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bonnet</hi> said that it was hardly necessary for him
                    to repeat the views of his Government on this subject. He had received
                    instructions from his Government the previous evening which confirmed everything
                    he had said at the previous meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Oliver Franks</hi> said that the British point of view
                    on Italy was also known to the other representatives at the meeting. The British
                    Government were, however, prepared to modify their view if there was a strong
                    sentiment of opinion on behalf of the other representatives against it. It now
                    seemed that there was a balance of opinion in favour of the inclusion of Italy
                    in the Pact; the balance was made up of opinions varying from a strong to a
                    faint desire; and the British Government were prepared to associate themselves
                    with that general feeling and abandon the position which they had held for so
                    long.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that the Canadian Government were
                    prepared to agree to the participation of Italy as a full member at whatever
                    time might prove most appropriate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Le Gallais</hi> said that the Luxembourg Government had
                    given its agreement that Italy should be included in the Pact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Baron Silvercruys</hi> spoke in the same sense.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that he had been discussing this
                    subject with the President and with the Senators. So far as the executive branch
                    of the United States Government was concerned, he had the President’s authority
                    to agree to the inclusion of Italy in the Treaty at the appropriate time. For
                    purely technical reasons, however, he did not wish to give this formal agreement
                    at the present meeting.</p>
                <p>The United States Government, Mr. Acheson explained, operated two ways in making
                    treaties. The President negotiates them and the Senate advises and consents to
                    their ratification. He had had a certain amount of trouble with the Senators on
                    the subject of Italy. He <pb facs="0166" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/> thought it
                    would be possible to surmount this but it would take a little time and he wished
                    so far as possible to be protected against premature press leaks and
                    discussion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bonnet</hi> said that he hoped Mr. Acheson would
                    succeed in convincing the Senators.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> then raised the question of the moment at
                    which Italy might join the Treaty. As the Treaty was now drafted, other
                    countries could accede to it by the unanimous agreement of the parties. During
                    the debates on ratification the Senate might try to provide that the President
                    of the United States could agree to accessions only with the advice and consent
                    of the Senate. It was necessary therefore to consider carefully whether it might
                    not be best to let Italy come in at the start; there was a risk involved in
                    having countries come in one by one if that would mean having to obtain the
                    advice and consent of the Senate in each case. Mr. Acheson said that he had no
                    final opinion about this but thought that it might be better to admit Italy in
                    one act at the time of signature. He would like to talk with the Senators about
                    this and report again to the Committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bonnet</hi> said that he wished to support strongly Mr.
                    Acheson’s view that it would save difficulty to decide courageously to admit
                    Italy, as well as the other countries, in one blow. He thought that it would be
                    best to be frank and friendly with Italy over such a matter and to put them on
                    exactly the same footing as other nations outside the seven represented at the
                    table which would become original signatories.</p>
                <p>He asked Mr. Acheson to inform President Truman of his gratitude at the decision
                    of the United States Government on Italy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> said that, leaving out of account for
                    the moment the questions of Portugal and Italy about which a decision would
                    probably require more time, he saw three possible solutions for the procedure of
                    admitting Norway, Italy and Denmark. The first possibility was to invite the
                    three countries as original signatories. This solution would prevent communist
                    activities in these countries (especially in Italy) from endangering their
                    participation. The second possibility, which was advocated by the Permanent
                    Commission in London, was accession after the signature of the Treaty by the
                    representatives of the seven countries, now involved in the conversations. It
                    was not quite clear to him whether this accession should, in the view of the
                    Permanent Commission, take place immediately after signature by the original
                    signatories or only after ratification by their parliaments. If Norway, Italy
                    and Denmark were to accede immediately after the signature of the Treaty, he,
                    personally, thought they might as well be invited to become original
                    signatories. If, on the <pb facs="0167" n="153" xml:id="pg_153"/> other hand,
                    these countries had to wait until after the Treaty had entered into force, the
                    delay which this would entail would give the Soviets the opportunity to try to
                    prevent, at the last moment, these countries from acceding. The third
                    possibility was to invite Norway and Denmark as original signatories and to
                    extend an invitation to Italy to accede at a later date. He was not sure whether
                    this was a procedure commending itself. In view of the need for the Secretary of
                    State to consult the Senate Foreign Relations Committee on Italy it might
                    deserve consideration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Oliver Franks</hi> said that at the moment there was a
                    slightly different approach to this question as between the representatives
                    discussing it in London and those discussing it in Washington. He did not think
                    that it was a difference of principle; it flowed from the concern of the
                    representatives in London lest the discussions over the Treaty be prolonged by
                    the participation in them of additional countries which might raise difficult
                    points. These fears might be exaggerated but what these representatives wanted
                    was that all the other countries, apart from those represented round the table,
                    should, if they wished to join the Pact, be invited to accede immediately after
                    signature. That was the interpretation he put upon the telegrams he had received
                    from London.</p>
                <p>Looked at from the standpoint of the time table of the negotiations, he thought
                    that it was more a matter of convenience in arrangement rather than an issue of
                    principle. Now that a decision had been taken on the principle of Italy, the
                    most important business was to get an agreed draft text as quickly as possible.
                    As soon as this was obtained, it could be sent to governments for their views.
                    He hoped that it would be possible to send such a draft to governments by March
                    7. It might therefore be considered to some extent academic at what moment
                    different countries came into subsequent discussions, provided the text had been
                    agreed and sent to governments. Speaking purely personally, he thought that it
                    might be difficult to ask Norway to join the discussions and at the same time
                    request her not to sign with the seven governments in the ordinary way.</p>
                <p>Sir Oliver Franks said that he would concur in any decision which the other
                    representatives thought desirable concerning the moment at which Italy was
                    brought in. But the British Government did not want Italy brought in while
                    active discussion was still going on. They did not think this necessary and they
                    would be glad for it not to happen. But, subject to that, they were prepared to
                    go along with the general sense of things. Everything would be eased enormously
                    on the day when the Committee sent a draft text back to governments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that the Canadian Government had no
                    strong view <pb facs="0168" n="154" xml:id="pg_154"/> on whether Italy should be
                    an original signatory or accede later. He thought that the Canadian Government
                    would probably prefer that Italy should not take part in the drafting
                    discussions; there was a certain apprehension that, if Italy joined the
                    negotiations at this stage, other matters in which Italy had a vital interest
                    might be raised during the final stages of negotiation. He had particularly in
                    mind the questions of the Italian colonies and Trieste. Therefore the view which
                    Mr. Pearson<note n="1" xml:id="d87fn1">Lester B. Pearson, Canadian Secretary of
                        State for External Affairs.</note> had expressed to him was that if, after
                    agreement, Italy was asked to join in the negotiations in the same way as
                    Norway, there should first be a clear understanding reached that none of these
                    issues would be raised which might be used for bargaining purposes and would
                    complicate the procedure of the negotiations. The Irish had made unacceptable
                    conditions for participation in the talks and we should adopt the same attitude
                    towards any other country which tried to set such conditions on their
                    participation.</p>
                <p>On the suggestions made by the Brussels Treaty Permanent Commission regarding
                    accession immediately after signature, he asked whether a country could accede
                    to a Treaty which was not in force. He thought that accession could only take
                    place after the Treaty was in force, which would involve considerable delay.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hickerson</hi> said that he thought the Permanent
                    Commission had meant original signature immediately after the others had signed.
                    He did not think that they could have meant accession owing to the impossibility
                    of acceding to a Treaty not in force.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Oliver Franks</hi> said that there were two time
                    periods which were now under consideration and which had been subject to
                    discussion in the Permanent Commission: the first was the period between
                    publication of the text (following agreement between governments) and the moment
                    of signature; the second was the period between signature and the entry into
                    force of the Treaty. The language used by the Permanent Commission had been
                    “accession” and it had been suggested that this should take place immediately
                    after signature. It did seem that the point raised by the Canadian Ambassador
                    had perhaps not been fully considered in the Permanent Commission.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that the text which would be approved
                    by governments at this stage would be a more or less final one but governments
                    would not be committed to every word and comma of it. If there was going to be a
                    gathering of Foreign Ministers for signature, they would probably wish to talk
                    about it. There was another question of practical importance from the Canadian
                    point of view. After the governments had approved the text, the Canadian
                    Government intended to inform the leaders of the opposition in Parliament. It
                    would be difficult <pb facs="0169" n="155" xml:id="pg_155"/> for the Canadian
                    Government to tell them that this text had been finally agreed to and at the
                    same time say that they would like to have their views upon it. It would be
                    necessary to be able to say that consideration could still be given to any views
                    they might express.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Le Gallais</hi> said that his Government was in favour
                    of the inclusion of Italy as a signatory power. He added that if anything
                    happened all would be in the same boat and he thought it would be preferable if
                    all were united from the beginning. In regard to the time table he agreed with
                    the views expressed by Sir Oliver and hoped that a definite text of the Treaty
                    could be set up today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Baron Silvercruys</hi> pointed out that the question at
                    issue at the moment was the form which Italian participation would take. What
                    had to be decided was whether Italy should be invited to sign the Pact or
                    whether arrangements should be made which would give her the opportunity of
                    acceding later. It was, of course, possible to have the signature in two acts:
                    first the signature of the original members, and then the signature of the
                    others, say half an hour later. But the difference was merely technical and he
                    did not think it worth consideration. Whether Italy signed the Pact or whether
                    she acceded later, it was clear that she would enter the North Atlantic
                    community. Her status through accession would be identical to that as a
                    signatory. The moment Italy acceded she would be in exactly the same position as
                    if she had signed as an original signatory with the other participants. If Italy
                    was only asked to accede, he thought that the position of the Italian Government
                    might thereby be made more difficult. The charge would be made that Italy had
                    been put in an inferior position while assuming the same responsibilities as the
                    other members of the North Atlantic community.</p>
                <p>He had been impressed, Baron Silvercruys continued, by a recent remark of the
                    Secretary of State in connection with one of the Articles of the Treaty. Mr.
                    Acheson had said “If we mean it, why not say it. The Senators will ask us anyway
                    and we will have to make clear what is in our minds”. He thought that the same
                    wisdom might be a guide over this present subject. If it was decided to let
                    Italy in, would it not be as well to make clear what that decision really
                    amounted to? Why not let Italy join at this time as a partner because she was
                    going to be a partner anyway! He thought that the signature of Italy would help
                    to remove a lot of doubts which might be created by accession. The Belgian view
                    therefore was that Italy should be told that she would be given the opportunity
                    to sign as an original signatory with the other participants.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bonnet</hi> said that he would try to dissipate some of
                    the fears which had been expressed around the table. The first one concerned <pb
                        facs="0170" n="156" xml:id="pg_156"/> the possibility that Italy might raise
                    embarrassing questions if she was admitted to the present discussions. From a
                    practical point of view, however, there was little chance that the Italian
                    representative could join the negotiations before the conclusion of the present
                    stage by which time the text would have been agreed. Moreover, he had been
                    informed that the Italian Government had made it clear that its representative
                    would not raise the question of the Italian colonies or of the disarmament
                    clauses of the Peace Treaty or any other clauses of that kind if she was
                    admitted to the discussions. He did not therefore think that this fear was
                    justified.</p>
                <p>As regards the proposals of the Permanent Commission concerning the time at which
                    these other countries should be invited to join the Pact, he thought that there
                    were some obscurities. Nevertheless, he thought that the proposals amounted to
                    this. The seven representatives should agree upon the text as soon as possible
                    and, after securing the agreement of their governments, should initial it. As
                    the next step, the seven powers would undertake to sign the Treaty, it being
                    understood that the five other countries would in the meantime have received the
                    text as well as an invitation to accede the same day during the same ceremony.
                    It could be argued that there was some obscurity arising from the fact that the
                    Permanent Commission had used the word “accede”. He agreed that if the word
                    “accede” was used in its full legal sense, that would mean that the Treaty would
                    have to come into force before the five powers could accede. The representatives
                    at the Permanent Commission had meant, in his judgment, that the five powers
                    should be invited to sign. These would be signatures of accession. He was sure
                    that the French Government intended that all members of the future Treaty should
                    be put on the same footing. That was the origin of the proposal of the Permanent
                    Commission. Thus Norway should be put on exactly the same footing as Italy. The
                    French Government were concerned that the Treaty should cover the Southern flank
                    of the North Atlantic community in the same way as the area in the North of
                    Europe. That was the meaning of the Permanent Commission’s proposal as he saw
                    it, and that was why it had been accepted by the other representatives in
                    London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bonnet</hi> added that he had received instructions
                    from his Government to support this proposal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said he understood that the Permanent
                    Commission had been most anxious that nothing should happen which might drag out
                    the discussions. He did not think that there was any chance of that happening.
                    He confirmed the views of the Italian Government reported by the French
                    Ambassador that the Italians would not raise any difficult points if they were
                    admitted to the discussions.</p>
                <pb facs="0171" n="157" xml:id="pg_157"/>
                <p>The State Department, Mr. Acheson went on, had had indications from the Danish
                    Ambassador that Denmark did not intend to ask to join the discussions in the
                    next day or two. The Foreign Minister wished to come to the United States and
                    discuss the subject. He wanted to go through the same procedure as that followed
                    by the Norwegian Foreign Minister. Mr. Acheson felt that the Norwegian
                    Ambassador would not wish to make any difficulties over the Treaty. He thought
                    therefore that, if the text could be completed early in the following week, the
                    whole matter would become unimportant.</p>
                <p>As regards the point that the Norwegians should not be treated differently from
                    anyone else, that would also become an academic question if it was agreed that
                    all countries should sign at the same time. He did not see what difference it
                    would make whether all signed at once or some at different times from the
                    others. If the text could be agreed soon, Mr. Acheson thought that it could be
                    given to the other governments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Oliver Franks</hi> said that he was not sure whether
                    the analysis given by the French Ambassador was shared by the British
                    representative. He therefore would like to report to his Government on the
                    discussions which had just taken place and find out whether they would agree to
                    the general course proposed by the present meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> asked whether there was any significance
                    in the proposal of the Permanent Commission that the draft should be initialled.
                    Unless there was some special reason for it, it would be an added complication
                    from the American point of view. The French Ambassador suggested that the
                    proposal had been made in order to show that at the moment of initialling the
                    text was final between the seven negotiating governments. It had not been
                    suggested, for instance, that it should be initialled by the Norwegian
                    representative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hickerson</hi> thought that the same purpose could be
                    served by other means. There could be agreement around the table that the seven
                    governments were generally agreed to the text and no changes proposed by other
                    countries could be agreed to except by the unanimous consent of the seven
                    governments who would have to be certain that the proposed changes were good and
                    that their consideration would not delay final signature. He said that
                    considerable public discussion would take place after publication of the text.
                    From this discussion there might arise some suggestions which the seven
                    governments might wish to consider and there might be disadvantages if the
                    document had been completely finalised as a result of initialling.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that it would be a complication from
                    the Canadian point of view if the draft was initialled at this stage. He did not
                    think <pb facs="0172" n="158" xml:id="pg_158"/> that there need necessarily be
                    much difference in the degree of authenticity to be attached to the text whether
                    or not it was initialled.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that he would much prefer to drop the
                    idea of initialling which he would have great difficulty in explaining to the
                    Senate.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> thought that his Government would
                    agree to the trend of the conversation. On instructions he had received, he
                    expressed the hope that it would be possible to come to a conclusion and to
                    finish a text very quickly. There was some danger in delay. The working group
                    could perhaps prepare a text for discussion. He had had information that the
                    Norwegian Ambassador would join the discussions today. He wondered how that
                    fitted into the agreement just reached.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hickerson</hi> said that he thought it fitted in very
                    well. The Norwegian Ambassador would be present when the text was discussed
                    later during the meeting. He went on to say that it would be helpful if about
                    twenty-four hours before publication the text could be communicated, as a matter
                    of courtesy, to the governments of the other American Republics, signatories of
                    the Rio Treaty. He hoped there would be no objection to that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Oliver Franks</hi> said that he thought it would be the
                    wish of the British and Canadian Governments to be able to extend this same
                    courtesy to the other Commonwealth Governments.</p>
                <p>No objections were raised to these proposals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hickerson</hi> asked what the views of the
                    representatives were on the question of the place of signature for the
                    Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Oliver Franks</hi> recalled that the Permanent
                    Commission had suggested Bermuda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that the Canadian Government had no
                    strong views on the subject but would also welcome Bermuda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Le Gallais</hi> thought the Luxembourg Government would
                    be agreeable to the signing to take place in Bermuda in view of the contents of
                    the cable from the Permanent Commission.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Baron Silvercruys</hi> asked whether the place of signature
                    would have any influence on the headquarters of the council or the defense
                    committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that he thought not, certainly not if
                    it was Bermuda. He wondered whether it might not seem somewhat frivolous to go
                    to Bermuda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> concurred in this. If it was
                    envisaged that the ceremony of signature would only be a very short one, he
                    himself did not see why the signature could not take place in Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Baron Silvercruys</hi> spoke in the same sense pointing out
                    that <pb facs="0173" n="159" xml:id="pg_159"/> Washington might be the most
                    appropriate place in view of the very important part which the United States
                    Government had played in the negotiation of the Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that he had assumed, and so had his
                    Foreign Minister, that there would be a really respectable launching ceremony
                    which would involve the attendance of several Foreign Ministers. He did not
                    think that it would be enough if the Ministers were merely to sign their names
                    to a document and then leave. A Treaty making so striking a departure in foreign
                    policy should be launched with rather more ceremony than that, for the purposes
                    of publicity. He also thought that it would be possible to agree finally on the
                    text only at the time of signature. Furthermore, the Canadian Government had
                    made a proposal about the form of a joint declaration which might be made at the
                    time of signature. The purpose of a Declaration of this kind was to explain more
                    fully than could be done in the preamble or the text the reasons why the treaty
                    was necessary at this particular time. The signature of Foreign Ministers to
                    such a Declaration would, of course, give it greater authority. For all these
                    reasons he hoped that, while it might well be short, the conference would be a
                    formal diplomatic gathering. It would only be fair for the countries which had
                    not participated in the negotiations to have the opportunity to state their
                    views publicly at a conference. It did not matter whether signature took place
                    in Bermuda or Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that if matters were to be raised at
                    the last moment it would certainly be easier for him if the signature was in
                    Washington, rather than a long way away from Capitol Hill.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bonett</hi> said that the Foreign Ministers would in
                    any case wash to visit Washington.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Oliver Franks</hi> said that he thought Mr. Bevin would
                    wish to come, wherever the Treaty was signed and would feel that the signature
                    would mark a great event in the history of the North Atlantic area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> agreed and said that the more he thought
                    about it, the more Washington seemed the best place. Perhaps President Truman,
                    rather than himself, would sign the Treaty. This would help a great deal in the
                    presentation of the Treaty to the Senate. If the President could address the
                    conference it would bring the whole matter to public attention in the United
                    States in a way that could not happen if the ceremony was in Bermuda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Le Gallais</hi> expressed the view that should
                    President Truman be willing to sign the Treaty himself, this would be a very
                    convincing argument for the ceremony to be held at Washington. He expressed <pb
                        facs="0174" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/> the hope that a double signature would
                    be considered, as all would wish the Secretary of State to sign it.</p>
                <p>At this point there was a short recess after which Mr. Morgenstierne, the
                    Norwegian Ambassador, joined the meeting and Mr. Acheson welcomed him on behalf
                    of the other representatives.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> thanked Mr. Acheson for his words of
                    welcome. He said that he had been asked by his Government to convey its
                    appreciation and thanks to him, Mr. Acheson, and to the countries represented at
                    the table, for giving him this opportunity to take part in the deliberations.
                    His first task would be to gather information about the present state of the
                    negotiations and about the text itself. When the Norwegian Government had had an
                    opportunity to study these matters, he hoped he would be able to make some
                    contribution to the discussions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> explained the tentative time table for the
                    negotiation and a discussion then took place on the draft Articles of the
                    Treaty.</p>
                <p>As regards Article 2, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> said that his
                    Government regretted that this Article did not go so far as the Canadian
                    proposal. He would welcome a stronger Article.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bonnet</hi> asked that there be some mention in the
                    Article of intellectual or cultural cooperation. Economic collaboration was the
                    only form of collaboration now mentioned in the Article.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that he had secured the agreement of
                    the Secretary of State for External Affairs to the Article as it now stood,
                    subject to the substitution in the fifth line of the words “these institutions”
                    for the word “they”. He recognised that it would cause great difficulty to the
                    United States Government if they had to try and secure the acceptance of an
                    Article more in accordance with the original Canadian proposal, and did not wish
                    to press for any further changes.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Le Gallais</hi> said he had no comments, as the
                    Canadian Government was in agreement to Article 2 as it stood now.</p>
                <p>On Article 3, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> said that he wondered
                    whether the word “endeavor”, which was rather weak, could not for the sake of a
                    uniform terminology be replaced by the expression “will contribute”. This last
                    expression was also used in the preceding Article. He thought that uniformity of
                    terminology was necessary if wrong and undesirable interpretations were to be
                    avoided.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that he was a little worried by the
                    expression “will contribute” which reminded him of some sort of new lend lease
                    operation. He suggested that the subject should be referred to the Working
                    Party.</p>
                <p>The other representatives said that the present phrase was not altogether <pb
                        facs="0175" n="161" xml:id="pg_161"/> satisfactory and agreed that the
                    wording should be considered again by the Working Party.</p>
                <p>On the subject of Article 4, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> asked
                    whether consultation between members had to be limited to instances where one of
                    the parties felt threatened. Could it not also take place in connection with
                    political matters? He thought that under certain circumstances it might be
                    useful to consult on other matters than those especially mentioned in Article
                    4.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> referred to Article 8 and suggested that
                    any matter could be brought up under the council which would be established
                    under Article 8.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> said he wanted to be sure that
                    Article 4 would not be interpreted as to exclude consultation on other matters
                    than those specifically mentioned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> suggested that other matters might be
                    dealt with through the council.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that he had always understood that the
                    parties could consult under Article 8 on any matter which they felt had a
                    bearing on the execution of the Treaty. He did not want to see the area of
                    mandatory consultation expanded.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> wondered whether the Norwegian
                    Ambassador should be informed that this Article, through the word “security”,
                    covered also aggression by subversive action.</p>
                <p>As regards Article 5, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> said that his
                    government hoped that this Article could be made as strong and comprehensive as
                    possible so as to provide that military aid should be given to a country which
                    was attacked with maximum speed and effectiveness.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Bonnet</hi> said with reference to Article 7 that he
                    wished to make it quite clear that it was not the equivalent of an expulsion
                    clause. He did not wish to insist upon having an expulsion clause but wished to
                    emphasize that this Article could not be regarded as one.</p>
                <p>On the subject of Article 8, Mr. Bonnet said that the Permanent Commission had
                    proposed the insertion of the words “prepare plans”. The insertion of these
                    words would make acceptance of the Treaty easier in the French Parliament. The
                    French Government thought that they would add strength and substance to Article
                    8.</p>
                <p>The other Brussels Treaty representatives said that they were prepared to support
                    this proposal if it met with unanimous approval.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> said that he was prepared to accept the
                    Article as it stood.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that the French proposal had been
                    discussed again with the U.S. military authorities and the Secretary of Defense.
                    He regretted to say that the US could not support the inclusion of <pb
                        facs="0176" n="162" xml:id="pg_162"/> these words. They thought it much
                    better to leave the text permissive in the sense that the defense committee
                    could recommend measures which might include the preparation of plans. But the
                    US did not think that it should be bound by Treaty obligations to agree that
                    this committee was the only place in which plans were prepared.</p>
                <p>On the subject of the special Article defining Article 5, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> referred to the preference of the Permanent
                    Commission for the formula “armed forces”. He pointed out that this wording
                    would include U.S. and U.K. forces in Greece. As he understood it, this was not
                    what was meant and he had no authority to commit his Government to what would
                    amount to a guarantee extended to Greece. He had that morning received
                    instructions by telephone from his Government to accept the wording
                    “occupation”.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Oliver Franks</hi> pointed out that the phrase
                    “occupation forces” might not be regarded as including U.S. and U.K. forces in
                    Trieste.</p>
                <p>It was agreed to refer that and certain other matters of definition to the
                    Working Party.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> suggested that the Working Party should
                    consider the question of which islands should be covered by the Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> asked whether aircraft taking part
                    in the Berlin airlift would be covered by the expression “occupation forces” and
                    Mr. Acheson said that they probably would.</p>
                <p>As regards Article 9, it was agreed to insert “the United States Government” in
                    the blank space.</p>
                <p>A discussion took place on Article 10 and Mr. Acheson referred to a suggestion
                    that had been made by Senator George. It was agreed to refer this to the Working
                    Party.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Wrong</hi> also proposed that the last Article should
                    be broken up and made into several Articles, and that provision should be made
                    for equally French and English texts of the Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> asked whether it would be reasonable
                    to include Norway at this time among the countries mentioned in connection with
                    ratification of the Pact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that he did not think so. The
                    original text had said that the Treaty would come into effect when a majority of
                    the signatories had ratified it. The change now made had been put in as a result
                    of proposals by the Senate. If Norway was added to the list of states, it would
                    mean that the Treaty could not come into effect unless Norway ratified it. That
                    was not what was meant. They wanted Norway to ratify it but they also wanted the
                    treaty to come into effect among the other countries even though, for some
                    reason or another, Norway decided not to ratify it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> said it seemed that it would be more
                    natural <pb facs="0177" n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/> to distinguish between
                    countries which had taken part in the discussions and signed the Treaty on the
                    one hand and, on the other hand, countries which acceded to the Treaty
                    afterwards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> did not think that the Norwegian proposal
                    would be acceptable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> added that the Norwegian Government
                    would consider it a great honour to be a charter member of the Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Van Kleffens</hi> said he thought that Norway would be
                    a charter member.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> said that there was no question about
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Morgenstierne</hi> said that there would, however, be a
                    certain distinction between the original and the later charter members.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi> explained that it would only be a
                    distinction arising from the number of ratifications necessary before the Treaty
                    came into effect.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
