<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 1031The Secretary of State to the Secretary of Defense (Lovet)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1031</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1031</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-11-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-11-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-11-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-11-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="1031"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1031">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.74/11–1052</note>
                <head>No. 1031<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Secretary of Defense (<persName type="to">Lovet</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d1031fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_DAB1">Alex B.
                            Daspit</persName>, Politico-Military Adviser in the Bureau of Near
                        Eastern, South Asian, and African Affairs.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-11-21">November 21,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: The situation in Egypt has now
                    developed to a point which makes it necessary for the United States to define
                    more specifically the measures it is prepared to take to assist in promoting a
                    favorable settlement of the Anglo-Egyptian dispute.</p>
                <p>You will recall that in mid-September representatives of General <persName
                        corresp="#p_NGM1">Naguib</persName>, in a secret approach to the United
                    States Embassy Cairo, stated the willingness of the Egyptian Government to
                    cooperate with the United States and to undertake certain commitments, including
                    participation in a Middle East Defense Organization, in return for military and
                    economic assistance. In replying to this overture, the United States declared
                    its willingness to enter into discussions to determine the scope and nature of
                    cooperation between the two Governments and requested the Egyptian Government to
                    define more clearly its views concerning military and economic assistance. We
                    emphasized the importance we attach to Egyptian willingness to participate with
                    the United States, United Kingdom and other free world powers in planning for
                    the common defense of the area and to a settlement of the Canal Zone problem on
                    a basis that would assure the effective maintenance of strategic facilities in
                    the Zone.</p>
                <p>While the Egyptians were formulating their reply to this message, we carried on
                    an exchange of views with the United Kingdom concerning the problem of the
                    Egyptian settlement in relation to the establishment of the Middle East Defense
                    Organization. In an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> presented to the British
                    Ambassador November 5, 1952,<note n="2" xml:id="d1031fn2">For text, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v09p1#d105">Document 105</ref>.</note> we urged that
                    the United Kingdom Government formulate the terms of a base settlement which
                    would be strategically acceptable to the Western powers and at the same time
                    stand a chance of <pb facs="0188" n="1890" xml:id="pg_1890"/> acceptance by the
                    Egyptian Government. We proposed that when this had been done the United States
                    should approach General <persName corresp="#p_NGM1">Naguib</persName> and
                    suggest that the United States, the United Kingdom and Egypt work out in secret
                    a base settlement and Egypt’s adherence to a common defense plan. We also stated
                    our conviction that material assistance by the United States and United Kingdom,
                    including the provision of military equipment, would be essential to the
                    successful conclusion of the proposed negotiations.</p>
                <p>We have now received a reply from the Egyptian and the United Kingdom Governments
                    respectively to the messages cited above. In its reply handed to the Department
                    of State November 10, 1952 (Attachment A),<note n="3" xml:id="d1031fn3">Not
                        printed, but see <ref target="#d1029fn7">footnote 7, Document
                        1029</ref>.</note> the United Kingdom welcomed our offer of assistance and
                    undertook to produce as soon as possible proposals for a settlement of the
                    Anglo-Egyptian dispute which they would discuss with us. The reply of the
                    Egyptian Government is contained in Cairo’s telegram 1167 November 10
                    (Attachment B).<note n="4" xml:id="d1031fn4">For text, see <ref target="#d1024"
                            >Document 1024</ref>.</note> Although it is not as forthcoming as we
                    might have wished, this Department considers that it provides a basis for
                    continuing discussions. Annex I, mentioned in paragraph C of this message, sets
                    forth a detailed list of the military equipment which the Egyptian Government
                    desires to secure. This list, together with analyses and comments by the United
                    States Service Attachés in Cairo, forms Attachment C of this letter.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d1031fn5">Not printed.</note> The Egyptian reply will be completed
                    by a second annex providing details of the economic assistance desired, which is
                    expected shortly.</p>
                <p>As the Department of Defense is aware, this Department considers that a
                    satisfactory settlement of the Anglo-Egyptian dispute will make it possible to
                    secure the participation of the Arab States in the Middle East Defense
                    Organization and that from such a beginning more favorable developments in the
                    entire Near East area might reasonably be expected to flow. This Department is
                    convinced, therefore, that everything possible should be done to assure such a
                    settlement. When the proposed United States-United Kingdom-Egyptian
                    conversations begin, the United States and United Kingdom, ideally, should have
                    their positions fully prepared on three points: 1) the elements of a Suez
                    settlement strategically satisfactory to the West, which would have a reasonable
                    chance of acceptance by Egypt; 2) the mutual defense arrangements and other
                    possible commitments to which it is desired that Egypt should agree; 3) details
                    as to the military and economic assistance which <pb facs="0189" n="1891"
                        xml:id="pg_1891"/> the United States and the United Kingdom would be
                    prepared to provide to Egypt.</p>
                <p>As indicated in their note at Attachment A, the British are now studying the
                    first problem, and we are hopeful that they will inform us of their conclusions
                    at an early date. The general form and structure of a Middle East Defense
                    Organization has been the subject of an exchange of views among the sponsoring
                    powers and a position on the second point can be readily prepared. The remaining
                    problem—the military and economic assistance to be provided to Egypt—requires
                    urgent consideration by the United States and the United Kingdom.</p>
                <p>The Department of Defense has several times stated its willingness to consider
                    favorably a program of military assistance to Egypt, if this were an element in
                    a generally satisfactory solution of the Suez base problem and would assist in
                    the establishment of cooperative defense arrangements in the Middle East. At the
                    same time, the Department of Defense has made clear the difficulties involved in
                    considering any specific program of assistance in the absence of an approved
                    strategic plan and force requirements for the area.</p>
                <p>The Department of State fully appreciates these difficulties. Nevertheless, this
                    Department is convinced that it will be essential to develop for negotiating
                    purposes some estimate of the general character and dimensions of a program of
                    military aid the United States would undertake to supply Egypt in the event
                    satisfactory general arrangements for area defense can be worked out. As a basis
                    for these estimates, we now have not only the statement of Egyptian requirements
                    (Attachment C), but studies of strength and equipment requirements of the
                    Egyptian Armed Forces prepared by the United States Service Attachés in Cairo
                    during October 1952.</p>
                <p>The Department of State would appreciate the Department of Defense undertaking
                    promptly a study of the problems involved in preparing a program of military aid
                    for Egypt, with a view to determining what can reasonably be done in preparation
                    for the United States-United Kingdom-Egyptian negotiations now foreseen. I
                    suggest that after preliminary consideration of these problems within the
                    Department of Defense it would be desirable for representatives of the
                    Department of State, the Department of Defense and the Office of the Director
                    for Mutual Security to discuss the matter informally with a view to deciding
                    upon the most promising course open to us, given the various complicating
                    factors involved. It is our hope that it may be possible through this means of
                    procedure to work out some action that may be taken on the list of requirements
                    at a fairly early date. For example, while a conclusive <pb facs="0190" n="1892"
                        xml:id="pg_1892"/> answer to the total list of requirements should be
                    reached as soon as possible, the time element may dictate accepting a portion of
                    the requirements which appear most reasonable and proceeding upon that portion
                    of their request without completion of the final detailed analysis.</p>
                <p>In this connection, the Department of State invites attention to the reported
                    availability of approximately $45,000,000 of military aid funds found excess to
                    the requirements of the approved programs for Greece, Turkey and Iran. In the
                    view of this Department, serious consideration should be given to the
                    possibility of tentatively programming some portion of these funds for Egypt, on
                    the assumption that negotiations will develop sufficiently rapidly to make
                    definite action possible in the course of this year’s operations. In any event,
                    given the prospects in Egypt described above, it would appear desirable to
                    maintain flexibility with respect to the final use of those funds for the
                    maximum period consistent with efficient operations.</p>
                <p>The limited amount of equipment intended for special Egyptian police units, which
                    was authorized under the terms of Section 408(e) of the Mutual Defense
                    Assistance Act of 1949, as amended, and which is now awaiting shipment, was of
                    course programmed prior to the developments described in this letter. It is now
                    contemplated that upon signature by the Egyptian Government of the appropritae
                    agreement, this equipment will be made available to the Egyptian Army. Most of
                    the items in this program are included by the Egyptian Government in its
                    official request for military assistance mentioned above. Thus, deliveries of
                    this equipment will in effect constitute a part of any general program of
                    military assistance to Egypt which may be authorized. As the Department of
                    Defense is aware, the Department of State considers that the early delivery of
                    this equipment would demonstrate the confidence of the United States in, and its
                    desire to cooperate with the <persName corresp="#p_NGM1">Naguib</persName>
                    Government, and would improve the atmosphere within which the proposed
                    three-power negotiations take place.</p>
                <p>I am forwarding a copy of this letter and its attachments to the Director for
                    Mutual Security.<note n="6" xml:id="d1031fn6">Under Secretary of State <persName
                            corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName> transmitted a copy of this letter
                        to <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Averell Harriman</persName>, Director for
                        Mutual Security, that same day, Nov. 21. (611.74/11–1052)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">H. Freeman Matthews</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Deputy Under Secretary</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
