<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 1061Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1061</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1061</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-09-27T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-27T10:00:00-05:00" n="1061" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d1061">
                <head>No. 1061<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Appendix D of the final agreed version of the “United Kingdom Memorandum on
                    Defence Negotiations with Egypt” contained alternatives, or “Cases” as they were
                    soon to be called, “A”, “B”, and “C”. It reads as follows:</p>
                <p rend="center">Facilities Required in Peace and War</p>
                <p rend="center">Peace</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Case “A”</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Canal Zone would be handed over to Egypt and the base area would be
                        placed under Egyptian control. Within this base existing depots and
                        installations would be retained and would be run and controlled on the
                        analogy of our base in Belgium or the United States base in the United
                        Kingdom.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The depots and installations would act as a working maintenance base for a
                        proportion of the Middle East Land Forces in <pb facs="0230" n="1932"
                            xml:id="pg_1932"/> peace. The <gloss target="#t_RAF1">R.A.F.</gloss>
                        would not, however, carry out any maintenance from installations in Egypt in
                        peace.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The Royal Navy would retain equipment in Egypt for the defence of ports
                        and maintain it under British supervision and have the use of the existing
                        commercial oil storage facilities and pipelines.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Army would retain not more than 5,000 personnel to run these
                        installations and the <gloss target="#t_RAF1">R.A.F.</gloss> not more than
                        2,000 for the same purpose.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>There would be an integrated Anglo-Egyptian Air Defence Organisation,
                        including Headquarters, two British Day Fighter Squadrons and one British
                        Night Fighter Squadron, C. and R. Organisations, &amp;c.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>An Allied-manned staging post would be maintained in Egypt.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Implications</hi>.—If the Egyptians could be persuaded to
                        accept these conditions in peace-time, the Allies would be assured of having
                        a working maintenance base in peace to which they could return and operate
                        immediately in war, and which would be protected by an efficient air defence
                        system.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Case “B”</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The base would remain in Egypt and be placed under Egyptian control. The
                        Egyptians would take over such depots and installations as the Allies wished
                        to retain in Egypt for war, assuming full responsibility for keeping all
                        communications, &amp;c., in working order and for maintaining Allied war
                        reserves and heavy workshops in a state to be reactivated at short notice.
                        There would also be some turnover of stores and equipment for use by the
                        Middle East Land Forces in peace.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>In order to assist the Egyptians in their task a rather smaller number
                        than under Case “A” of Allied supervisory and technical Army and Air Force
                        personnel would be required.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>The Royal Navy would retain equipment in Egypt for the defence of ports
                        and maintain it under British supervision and have the use of the existing
                        commercial oil storage facilities and pipelines.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>There would be an integrated Anglo-Egyptian Air Defence Organisation,
                        including Headquarters, two British Day Fighter Squadrons and one British
                        Night Fighter Squadron, C. and R. Organisation, &amp;c.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>An Allied-manned staging post would be maintained in Egypt.</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Implications</hi>.—Under these conditions there would not
                        be a fully satisfactory working base in Egypt in peace, but it should be
                        possible to reactivate it within 60 days. Some stocks for the initial <pb
                            facs="0231" n="1933" xml:id="pg_1933"/> maintenance of Allied forces in
                        the Middle East in war would have to be located outside the Canal
                        Zone.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Case “C”</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>The base would remain in Egypt and be placed under Egyptian control. The
                        Egyptians would assume the same responsibilities as for Case “B” (paragraph
                        8 above) except that there would be no turnover of stores and equipment for
                        use by the Middle East Land Forces in peace.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>The right of periodic inspections of reserves and installations should be
                        retained. The military personnel to carry out these inspections should, if
                        possible, be stationed in Egypt. However, if the Egyptians were adamant that
                        they would not allow this, agreement might be given to Service personnel
                        wearing plain clothes or to the use of civilians. Failing this it might be
                        necessary to agree that inspecting personnel should be stationed outside
                        Egypt and carry out periodic visits.</item>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>The Royal Navy would retain equipment in Egypt for the defence of ports
                        and place it under Egyptian supervision for maintenance, with the right of
                        periodic inspection. They would have the use of the existing commercial oil
                        storage facilities and pipe-lines.</item>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>No <gloss target="#t_RAF1">R.A.F.</gloss> units would be left in Egypt,
                        but agreement could be given to seconding to the Egyptian Air Force some
                        instructors and advisers. No guarantee of participation in the air defence
                        of Egypt could be given, but agreement might be reached to send units in
                        peace-time to take part in exercises with the Egyptian Air Force.</item>
                    <label>18.</label>
                    <item>The Allies would require the use of an Egyptian-manned staging post in
                        Egypt and the necessary overflying rights for peacetime movements and
                        training.</item>
                    <label>19.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Implications</hi>.—In these circumstances, it is estimated
                        that it would take at least 90 days to reactivate the base. It would be
                        necessary therefore to retain at least 90 days. stocks for the whole of the
                        Middle East Garrison in locations outside the Canal Zone. In addition, the
                        United States use of Abu Sueir and <persName corresp="#p_FI1"
                            >Farouk</persName> airfields in the very early stages of war might
                        become impracticable since the equipment would not be adequately maintained
                        there in peace-time.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">in war</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>20.</label>
                    <item>Under all cases the use of a working base in Egypt in war, together with
                        Egyptian assistance and co-operation, is an essential requirement. In
                        addition, allied Naval Forces will require the use of Alexandria, Port Said
                        and Suez.</item>
                    <pb facs="0232" n="1934" xml:id="pg_1934"/>
                    <label>21.</label>
                    <item>To obtain these facilities is the paramount object of the negotiations.
                        (774.5/1–1453)</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
