<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-02-03T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-02-03T14:00:00-05:00" n="1090" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1090">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">745W.00/2–353: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 1090<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Charge in the United Kingdom
                                        (<persName corresp="#p_HJC1" type="from">Holmes</persName>)
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d1090fn1">Repeated to Cairo as telegram 225 and to
                                    Khartoum as telegram 15.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-02-03T19:00:00+00:00">February 3, 1953—7 p.
                                        m</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>4288. Embassy today discussed Sudan problem with Foreign Office in
                                light <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 5104 February 2. On
                                basis this and other recent conversations, following Embassy
                                comments may clarify specific points raised by Department:</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Department’s understanding “Sudanization” issue essentially
                                    correct as stated Department’s reference telegram. Reasons for
                                    British stand are three-fold: <list>
                                        <label>(a)</label>
                                        <item>They do not feel that situation should be created
                                            whereby Sudanese would be debarred from retaining
                                            experienced British officials at time of
                                            self-determination, even though Sudanese might desire
                                            keep them. To some extent, British position ties in with
                                            problem of south since it is in this area that they feel
                                            there will be greatest need for qualified
                                            personnel.</item>
                                        <label>(b)</label>
                                        <item>British suspect that main reason for Egyptian
                                            insistence on removal all British officials is to pave
                                            way for Egyptian hegemony at time of
                                            self-determination.</item>
                                        <label>(c)</label>
                                        <item>For prestige reasons, British would find it most
                                            difficult to agree to procedure which would in fact be
                                            discriminatory against British nationals by making it
                                            impossible for them to continue service with Sudanese
                                            Government.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>British admit that many and perhaps most Sudan civil servants
                                    would not be willing remain after self-determination. Extent to
                                    which this would be true would depend in large measure on
                                    Sudan’s future status. Closer association to Egypt, less likely
                                    British officials would desire remain. Nevertheless, this
                                    consideration does not destroy in British eyes validity points
                                    set forth (1) above.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>In British minds, Sudanization has always been point of
                                    approximately vital importance to that of south. Main emphasis
                                    has been on south merely because it had appeared earlier that
                                    Egyptians <pb facs="0275" n="1977" xml:id="pg_1977"/> did not
                                    have strong views on Sudanization and that problems could
                                    probably be worked out (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 3164, December 5).<note n="2" xml:id="d1090fn2">Not printed.</note> With re-statement of
                                    hardened Egyptian attitude in recent note, these earlier hopes
                                    have been somewhat dissipated and Sudanization problem now seems
                                    as difficult of solution as south.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item><p>British indicate concern re possibility violence in Sudan
                                        in event breakdown negotiations and have this danger clearly
                                        in mind in studying problem. They are also perturbed re
                                        possibility outbreaks in south if Governor General’s special
                                        responsibilities are given up.</p>
                                    <p>Following additional points also emerged from conversation
                                        today:</p></item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>British encouraged by progress being made in drafting
                                    committee on minor points contained in Egyptian note (Cairo’s
                                    1773, February 2).<note n="2" target="d1090fn2">Not
                                        printed.</note> Stevenson regards this and other indications
                                    as evidence that <persName corresp="#p_NGM1">Naguib</persName>
                                    sincerely desirous of reaching agreement and Foreign Office
                                    inclined agree with Stevenson.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_FBM1">Fawzi</persName> has been most
                                    helpful in connection subcommittee conversations and in number
                                    of other recent problems arising from negotiations. For example,
                                    he recently helped obtain recall Commanding Officer Egyptian
                                    Forces Sudan for statement inciting Sudanese to violence in
                                    event agreement not reached between UK and Egypt.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Howe has now completed first phase his conversations with
                                    Sudanese leaders re Egyptian note and re British position
                                        (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 4242, January
                                        31).<note n="3" xml:id="d1090fn3">In telegram 4242 from
                                        London, Jan. 31, not printed, the Embassy reported that the
                                        Foreign Office reiterated its assessment that Sudanization
                                        and the South Sudan problems represented the two major
                                        obstacles to the Sudan settlement. Moreover, the Foreign
                                        Office repeated that the principle at stake was whether the
                                        Sudanese should be consulted through their own
                                        representative Parliament regarding these two points at
                                        issue, and the Foreign Office felt strongly that they
                                        should. However, the matter was still being studied, no new
                                        instructions had been sent to Stevenson, and it was unlikely
                                        that any would until Sir James Howe had consulted the
                                        Sudanese leaders. (745W.00/1–3153)</note> Foreign Office
                                    says results of consultations are unclear, as expected. SRP
                                    leaders appear have considerable doubts re wisdom Agreement,
                                    UMMA some doubts and pro-Egyptian parties no doubts at all. Most
                                    leaders seem to feel that there would be no problem for Sudanese
                                    to obtain subsequent changes in agreement if present provisions
                                    do not work. Howe pointed out that this might be difficult since
                                    agreement would be between UK and Egypt and Sudanese would not
                                    be parties to it.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Egyptian note has been considered by two recent Cabinet
                                    sessions here and is before Cabinet again today at which time it
                                    will be decided whether send Stevenson new instructions now or
                                    whether await results Howe’s further consultations Sudanese
                                        leaders.<note n="5" xml:id="d1090fn5">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> reported on Feb. 4
                                        in telegram 1784 from Cairo, not printed, that Stevenson had
                                        just received further instructions on the Sudan and had
                                        requested a meeting with the Egyptians. According to the
                                        British Embassy official, Stevenson was “authorized accept
                                        Egyptian version of ‘Sudanization’ with proviso that
                                        self-determination shall take place under ‘international
                                        supervision.’ In return British will insist on Egyptian
                                        acceptance of their proposal on southern safeguards”.
                                        (745W.00/2–453)</note></item>
                            </list>
                            <pb facs="0276" n="1978" xml:id="pg_1978"/>
                            <p>In response our inquiry, Foreign Office official to whom we spoke
                                said in greatest confidence that while he could not speak with
                                certainty prior Cabinet decision, he thought it likely UK would find
                                it possible make some further adjustments toward Egyptian point of
                                view.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HJC1"><hi rend="strong"><hi rend="smallcaps">Holmes</hi></hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>