<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-06-01T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-06-01T12:00:00-05:00" n="1177" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1177">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">641.74/6–153: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 1177<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Egypt (<persName corresp="#p_CJ1" type="from">Caffery</persName>) to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d1177fn1">Repeated to London as telegram
                                810.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/><gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss></hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-01T19:00:00+02:00">June 1, 1953—7
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2513. Further to my telegram 2512 I should like to add by way of
                                general observation that the hour is far later for the West in the
                                    <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> than would seem to be
                                realized. The sentiment of the people in this area is more
                                especially anti-Western and more prepared to be sympathetic to the
                                enemies of the West than we like to believe. The officials of the
                                    <gloss target="#t_RCC1">RCC</gloss> are Egyptian Nationalists of
                                middle class background brought up during a generation of continuous
                                anti–British agitation. They are closely attuned to, and themselves
                                largely reflect, the attitudes of the Egyptian people. They are, at
                                the same time sincerely anti-Communist and desirous of leading Egypt
                                into a firm association with the West. Being honest men and
                                realistic as regards their own internal capabilities, they have
                                consistently rejected and will continue to reject proposals which do
                                not take into sufficient account the complexes created by
                                three-quarters of a century of British occupation.</p>
                            <p>We have an opportunity to do business with a group of men who will
                                not easily give commitments because they believe in keeping their
                                word. If we are going to do business with them, we shall have to
                                take this into account and we shall have to move quickly. Admittedly
                                such a course of action will involve a considerable gamble and a
                                large measure of trust. Nothing breeds confidence like a display of
                                confidence, however, and the vicious circle of Anglo-Egyptian
                                recrimination and distrust must be broken. (<persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s gratuitous pro-Zionist
                                remarks, for example, unquestionably set back the prospects of any
                                Arab-Israel settlement.)</p>
                            <pb facs="0385" n="2087" xml:id="pg_2087"/>
                            <p>It must also be borne in mind that if agreement is not reached with
                                the present regime, the UK will have no alternative but to maintain
                                its position by force. Although the Egyptians have not the
                                capability of expelling the British, they can tie up 80,000 of the
                                best British troops indefinitely and can make life difficult for any
                                Britisher or even any Westerner in Egypt. If matters drag on as at
                                present, no Egyptian leader will dare raise his voice in favor of
                                cooperation with the West. The probable impact of such a development
                                on the Western position in the other Arab states can be
                                surmised.</p>
                            <p>In short, we are playing for big stakes in Egypt. By playing too
                                cautious a game we are sure to lose. The problem is not only to
                                convince the British of that but to help them find a graceful way
                                out of the impasse.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CJ1"><hi rend="strong"><hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi></hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>