<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-22T14:57:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-22T14:57:00-05:00" n="1208" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1208">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">641.74/7–2253: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 1208<lb/><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                        Egypt</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d1208fn1">Drafted and
                                    approved by the Secretary of State.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                        secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-07-22T15:57:00-04:00">July 22, 1953—3:57
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>96. Confidential for <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName>
                                from Secretary. Your 112.<note n="2" xml:id="d1208fn2">Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> in telegram
                                    112, July 21, not printed, reported that General <persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> had told him the
                                    previous evening that the British felt that, as a result of the
                                    Washington talks, the United States was supporting the United
                                    Kingdom. <persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> said,
                                    “British point of view is that as Great Britain stands behind
                                    United States in Korea, United States stands behind Great
                                    Britain in Egypt.” (641.74/7–2153)</note></p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName>’s statement reflects
                                wishful thinking. We are not “backing” either Britain or Egypt. We
                                are anxious to get the result which I specified in my public
                                statement made in Cairo.<note n="3" xml:id="d1208fn3">See <ref target="#d1179fn3">footnote 3, Document 1179</ref>.</note>
                                In certain respects we share the British position. In other respects
                                we share the Egyptian position and in many respects we strongly
                                backed Egyptian viewpoint in our talks here with British.</p>
                            <p>With reference to Department’s 66 it perhaps does not sufficiently
                                make clear that while we are concerned as to “availability” or
                                “duration” this does not mean that we support the British formulae.
                                On the contrary I emphasized to <persName corresp="#p_SLR1">Salisbury</persName> that while we felt that the Egyptian
                                formulae were too restrictive we doubted that a Brit formula should
                                be insisted on and we assume <persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> now has some flexibility on this point. If
                                Egyptians feel we have “let them down” remember British also
                                disappointed we are not fully <pb facs="0423" n="2125" xml:id="pg_2125"/> backing them. Difference is British conceal
                                their disappointment and pretend greater degree of agreement than in
                                fact exists.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF2"><hi rend="strong"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi></hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>