<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-08-25T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-08-25T08:00:00-05:00" n="1213" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1213">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">641.74/8–2553: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 1213<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Egypt (<persName corresp="#p_CJ1" type="from">Caffery</persName>) to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d1213fn1">Repeated to London as telegram
                                84.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-08-25T15:00:00+02:00">August 25, 1953—3
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>253. British Embassy today supplied following re British-Egyptian
                                talks yesterday (Embassy’s 250).<note n="2" xml:id="d1213fn2">Not
                                    printed.</note></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>For Egyptian Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_FBM1">Fawzi</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NCGA1">Nasir</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_ALG1">Hakim
                                        Amir</persName>; for UK Hankey, <persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> and Brig Dove. After unsuccessful
                                    attempt get Egyptians to express their views <persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> advanced substance
                                    new British formula London’s 745<note n="3" xml:id="d1213fn3"><p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AWW1">Aldrich</persName> reported in telegram 745, Aug.
                                            21, not printed, that the British Foreign Office had
                                            just given him a revised Canal Zone base reactivation
                                            formula, which was to be put to the Egyptians at the
                                            next meeting in Cairo:</p>
                                        <p>“In the event of United Nations action to resist an act
                                            of aggression, or in the event of an attack on any Arab
                                            country by an outside power, the base area shall be at
                                            the full disposal of the UK. An attack on Turkey shall
                                            be regarded as an attack on an Arab country for the
                                            purposes of this agreement. In the event of an attack on
                                            Persia, or in the event of a threat of an attack on any
                                            of the above-mentioned countries, there shall be
                                            immediate consultation between the UK and Egypt.”
                                            (741.56374/8–2153)</p></note> without giving text <pb facs="0427" n="2129" xml:id="pg_2129"/> to Egyptians.
                                    Egyptians rejected inclusion Turkey and Iran stating flatly that
                                    on political grounds they could not go beyond “members Arab
                                    League Collective Security Pact”: Egypt would be willing to
                                    “consult” if Turkey attacked and would accept reactivation of
                                    base in case <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> decision calling
                                    for armed action. According British Embassy <persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> believes “we are not
                                    far off on availability” provided London does not insist on
                                    inclusion of Turkey.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> now considers
                                    most serious question to be dealt with is that of duration of
                                    agreement together with numbers and duration of stay of
                                    technicians. UK for first time advanced their ideas on these
                                    matters in detail. UK asked for 10 years agreement with
                                    technicians to stay concurrently. Egyptians refused this. UK
                                    then proposed 10 year agreement with 4000 technicians for 5
                                    years, this number to be tapered off thereafter. Egyptians
                                    suggested 5 year agreement with technicians for 3 years.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> replied
                                    this impossible if base is to have real military value and urged
                                    Egyptians to be forthcoming.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Egyptians were “filled with gloom” when British advanced idea
                                    that all agreement times must start after British evacuation
                                    completed. UK said it was practical impossibility to work out
                                    technician pattern while British forces still there. <persName corresp="#p_RGS1">Robertson</persName> estimated evacuation
                                    would require two years although he hinted this time might be
                                    slightly shortened. (British Embassy states 18 months now
                                    considered absolute minimum.) Egyptians stated that they had
                                    always assumed agreement would run from date of signature and
                                    that 6 months adequate period for evacuation. Both sides agreed
                                    meet August 27.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CJ1"><hi rend="strong"><hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi></hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>