<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="1258" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1258">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">Presidential Correspondence, lot 66 D
                                204, “<persName corresp="#p_EGAD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                                Correspondence with <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>”</note>
                            <head>No. 1258<lb/><hi rend="italic">President <persName corresp="#p_EGAD1" type="from">Eisenhower</persName> to
                                    Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CWS1" type="to">Churchill</persName></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-12-20">December 20, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Winston</persName></hi>: You are so well aware of my
                                convictions as to the necessity for sound and friendly
                                Anglo-American relations that you must keenly realize the concern I
                                feel over the somber tone of your cabled message.<note n="1" xml:id="d1258fn1">Presumably the reference here is to <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s message of Dec. 19,
                                        <ref target="#d1257"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>.</note></p>
                            <p>Because it is a personal communication, I am answering in the same
                                fashion, without waiting to call together the State Department
                                staffs which will be, of course, deeply interested in what you have
                                to say. I shall hope to get this cable off to you the first thing
                                Monday morning so that I may have your further observations on
                                certain delicate phases of this matter.</p>
                            <p>In considering our common interests in various areas, I am, of
                                course, anxious to take into consideration your particular political
                                problems and to adjust our activities so as best to accommodate your
                                position so long as this leads toward a satisfactory solution. We
                                likewise have our political problems. For example, our aid program
                                for the Mid-East was drawn up and was approved by the Congress on
                                the basis that there would be a reasonable division of aid between
                                Israel and Arab countries.</p>
                            <p>Since we have already made allocations to Israel, we have little
                                excuse to avoid moving in the case of the Arab countries, but as you
                                know, at your request we have not only withheld military aid from
                                Egypt, but have likewise postponed several times the initiation of
                                economic aid.</p>
                            <p>You state that the Socialist Opposition would be bitterly resentful
                                of American economic aid to Egypt because of the American objection
                                to trade with Communist China. It has been my understanding that
                                Britain has continued to carry on trade in economic non-strategic
                                items with Red China, and we do not now propose more with respect to
                                Egypt than beginning to help develop its economy. Consequently, I am
                                at a loss to understand the basis on which the Socialists could make
                                a logical attack. You likewise mention that the Opposition would
                                resent any economic aid to Egypt so bitterly <pb facs="0477" n="2179" xml:id="pg_2179"/> that they would urge you to press
                                for inclusion of Red China in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.
                                By implication this would seem to mean that if we do not extend
                                economic aid to Egypt, you are prepared to stand firm with us in
                                opposing the inclusion of the bloody Chinese aggressor into the
                                councils of peaceful nations, at least until Red China withdraws her
                                invading armies, ceases supporting the Indo-China war and begin to
                                act like a civilized government. Could you confirm this to me?</p>
                            <p>I assume, of course, that you are genuinely anxious to arrange a
                                truce with Egypt and that the only remaining obstacles are the two
                                points you mentioned to me at Bermuda, namely availability and
                                uniforms. Now if we continue to press Egypt to accept your
                                conditions on these two points, can we do so with the assurance that
                                they can count on a settlement if they accept your position? You can
                                well understand my anxiety to avoid asking our people to do
                                everything in their power to bring about a settlement of this
                                situation, including another postponement of economic aid, and then
                                discover that we have been operating on a complete
                                misunderstanding.</p>
                            <p>As I told you at Bermuda, I am most deeply sympathetic with your
                                whole problem in the area, even though at times I have believed that
                                different methods might have been more effective. I repeat that in
                                our actual dealings with Egypt, we have gone to great lengths to
                                meet your convictions and opinions. We certainly want to continue to
                                do so. We think we proved that in Persia, and I hope we shall
                                together make that effort seem worthwhile.</p>
                            <p>I know that you realize that there are in this country many people
                                who believe that the United States has treated the Arab countries
                                shabbily and, because parts of the Arab holdings are vital to the
                                Western world, this segment of our citizenry asserts that we should
                                work to improve our relationships with the Arab countries. But this
                                government has always refused to do this at the cost of anything we
                                believe detrimental to Anglo-American best interests. In spite of
                                outrageous and irresponsible criticism of each other on both sides
                                of the Atlantic, American governmental policy and popular sentiment
                                recognize the great value to the free world of keeping
                                Anglo-American relationships coordinated with respect to the rest of
                                the world and friendly as between themselves.</p>
                            <p>[Here follows discussion of the European Defense Community
                                concept.]</p>
                            <p>I hope that you can find it possible to answer this personal cable
                                promptly so that I can assemble the necessary staffs and go over
                                this whole matter in detail. I assure you that I am prepared to meet
                                locally any political difficulty in carrying out whatever
                                arrangements <pb facs="0478" n="2180" xml:id="pg_2180"/> we may make
                                between ourselves for the common good of our two countries.</p>
                            <p>I realize that this is a long and possibly a tedious cablegram. But
                                it is quite necessary that there be the clearest kind of
                                understanding between us if we are at one and the same time to
                                operate together in some of these critical situations abroad and
                                still be able to withstand any kind of political problem and
                                criticism that can arise in our respective countries.</p>
                            <p>I shall look forward to early receipt of your comments.</p>
                            <p>With warm personal regard,</p>
                            <p>As ever,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ike</hi></hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>