<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 1432Memorandum of Conversation, by Robert Sturgill of the Office of Near
                    Eastern Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1432</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1432</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="1432"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1432">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.5886A/1–2152</note>
                <head>No. 1432<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by <persName corresp="#p_SRG1"
                            >Robert Sturgill</persName> of the Office of Near Eastern Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1952-01-21">January 21,
                            1952</date>.<note n="2" xml:id="d1432fn2">This memorandum of
                            conversation was prepared on Jan. 23.</note>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Briefing of Col. H. E. Liebe.</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>U.S. Army—Col. H. E. Liebe</item>
                    <item>Lt. Col. T. R. Davis, Mediterranean—<gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss>
                        Section <gloss target="#t_G31">G–3</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AFH1"
                            >Awalt</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRG1">Sturgill</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Col. Liebe said he had orders to depart for Saudi Arabia February 19 as part of
                    the Advance Technical Group and would remain as Acting Chief in charge of the
                    Army portion of the U.S. Military Training Mission to Saudi Arabia when that got
                        started.<note n="3" xml:id="d1432fn3">For previous documentation on this
                        topic, see <ref target="frus1951v05#pg_1059">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1951, vol. V, pp. 1059</ref>
                        ff.; see in particular the editorial note, <ref target="frus1951v05#pg_1064">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 1064</ref>.</note> Col. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DMB1">Davis</persName> said the fourth member of the Advance
                    Group would probably be an Air Force Major already in Saudi Arabia, although he
                    had not been chosen yet. He also mentioned that it was contemplated that some
                    enlisted personnel would be needed for administrative support of the Group, but
                    that no one had been assigned.</p>
                <p>Col. <persName corresp="#p_DMB1">Davis</persName>’ attention was called to the
                        <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> decision to appoint a Major General
                    Chief of the Mission and to the Department’s understanding that General
                        <persName corresp="#p_DBGE1">Day</persName> was to have been appointed Chief
                    pro tem; and he was asked if orders to that effect had gone out.</p>
                <p>Temporary utilization of the housing facilities at Taif, used by the British
                    Military Training Team recently departed, was discussed. It was pointed out that
                    the Department saw no objection to <pb facs="0708" n="2410" xml:id="pg_2410"/>
                    such use of the facilities if found to be suitable, since that would advance the
                    time for starting our military training operations which would otherwise have to
                    await considerable new construction at El Kharj. It was explained that it was
                    politically desirable to implement our training commitment to Saudi Arabia as
                    soon as possible. It was stressed, however, that initiation of training
                    operations at Taif should have prior Defense approval.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Col. <persName corresp="#p_DMB1">Davis</persName>
                    regarding progress on the <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> agreement, it
                    was stated that an exchange of notes has not yet been effected in Jidda, but
                    that a draft had been sent, upon which the Embassy commented, raising some
                    points. None were major, although the Department’s reply has been held up
                    pending final agreement with Defense on a termination clause desired by the
                    latter.</p>
                <p>Col. Liebe expressed his interest in the Mission and said he considered it a
                    challenging assignment. He was somewhat apprehensive regarding language
                    difficulties, but it was pointed out that there were probably available a number
                    of English-speaking Arabs who had had airport management training at Dhahran and
                    in the US, as well as some who had had military training in this country. It was
                    recommended to him that he make use of Saudi Arabs whenever possible in the
                    training program.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
