<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 992The Secretary of State to the Embassy in Egypt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d992</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">992</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-07-15T18:07:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-07-15T18:07:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-15T18:07:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-15T18:07:00-05:00" n="992"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d992">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">641.74/7–1552: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 992<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Egypt</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d992fn1">Also sent to London as telegram 321. Drafted and
                        approved by <persName corresp="#p_SW1">Stabler</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-15T19:07:00-04:00"
                            >July 15, 1952—7:07 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>83. <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> saw Brit Amb Jul 14 at latter’s
                    request. Amb said he had been instructed reinforce <persName corresp="#p_ESA1"
                        >Eden</persName>’s request contained <gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 41 Jul 8 to Cairo.<note n="2" xml:id="d992fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d991fn1">footnote 1, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> Amb also showed <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> tel
                    from <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> replying to views expressed by
                    Dept Reps on Jul 7 (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 40 Jul 8 to
                        Cairo).<note n="3" xml:id="d992fn3">In telegram 40 to Cairo, July 8, not
                        printed, the Department of State informed Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> not only of the British Embassy’s
                        comments which accompanied the delivery of <persName corresp="#p_ESA1"
                            >Eden</persName>’s request as reported in Department telegram 41 but
                        also provided <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> with a summary
                        of the views expressed to British Embassy officials by the Department’s
                        representatives. The Department’s analysis was that <persName
                            corresp="#p_HAN1">Hilali</persName> fell due to his lack of progress
                        with the British; the Department’s representatives again urged the British
                        to consult with the Sudanese; they said that the United States strongly
                        hoped to avoid a situation whereby the British could maintain their position
                        in Egypt only by using force; and they declared that the Department
                        seriously questioned the wisdom of intervening in Egypt in the fashion
                        suggested by Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>.
                        (641.74/7–852)</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> considered that Brit consultation with
                    Sudanese undesirable and believed it preferable await creation Sudanese
                    legislative bodies.</p>
                <pb facs="0132" n="1834" xml:id="pg_1834"/>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> said he was concerned by strong
                    implications in <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>’s msg that (a)
                    because UK unable make progress with Egypts, responsibility now rests with US to
                    persuade King throw out <persName corresp="#p_AMG1">Sirry</persName> Govt and
                    put title question into “cold storage” and (b) that if US is not successful,
                    full consequences for lack of success wld fall on US. <gloss target="#t_Secy1"
                        >Secy</gloss> emphasized US does not accept these implications. We are not
                    willing be put in such situation. <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> stated
                    that we are bothered by rapid shifts in Brit attitude. When in London <gloss
                        target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> was told all well in Egypt, then <persName
                        corresp="#p_HAN1">Hilali</persName> resigns and UK rushes to US with idea
                    that either US persuade Egypt accept UK-proposed settlement or force must be
                    used maintain position. US cannot take responsibility for these
                    alternatives.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> then went on to analyze request contained
                    in <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>’s msg. Re change of Govt <gloss
                        target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> said <persName corresp="#p_CJ1"
                        >Caffery</persName>’s view which more often right than <gloss
                        target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> is that it not possible bring about
                    change of Govt through intervention, that new Govt wld probably not be better
                    and that <persName corresp="#p_AMG1">Sirry</persName> not doing too badly. We
                    wld not consider advice to King to change Govt good advice.</p>
                <p>Re telling King put title question in “cold storage” <gloss target="#t_Secy1"
                        >Secy</gloss> said that we had tried this before but it has not worked. We
                    are faced with real dilemma which we try to get around by denying one of
                    premises which appears to be accepted by all i.e. it not possible achieve
                    settlement Canal Base without something on King’s title which wld satisfy
                    Egypts. In our view it is difficult if not impossible try to persuade Egypts re
                    putting title in cold storage when they regard title as a matter of right and
                    when they have no real desire for anything except to get Brit out of Egypt and
                    Sudan.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> said that we wld be delighted assist in
                    any way possible to create better atmosphere and that we wld gladly ask
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> go to King if there was some
                    new element, real and concrete, which cld be used. <gloss target="#t_Secy1"
                        >Secy</gloss> added that he fully understood <gloss target="#t_FonOff1"
                        >FonOff</gloss> concern re possible Egypt moves in Sudan and fact one cld
                    not rule out possibility Egypt “skulduggery”. However he thought something might
                    be done which wld not run appreciable risk.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName> expressed great US concern over
                    implications of use of force and effect such course of action wld have on world
                    opinion and Western position in <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Brit Amb indicated that he wld inform London that US unable to do what had been
                    requested. He added that he wld report general tenor <gloss target="#t_Secy1"
                        >Secy</gloss>’s remarks and fact Dept unable to offer any new ideas this
                    stage. Speaking personally, <persName corresp="#p_FSO1">Franks</persName> said
                    he imagined <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> thinking tended toward
                    view that UK shld make no move at this time unless Egypt requested talks and
                    that next action wld be in December when Sudan Parliament installed and cld
                    consider sovereignty question.</p>
                <pb facs="0133" n="1835" xml:id="pg_1835"/>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> expressed belief that if establishment
                    Sudanese Parliament awaited, Sudanese wld be so strongly headed toward policy of
                    no Egypt sovereignty that favorable response to title cld not be expected. It
                    wld then be necessary to deal with Canal Base question in bad atmosphere and
                    this in itself might lead to more rioting. This in turn wld raise use of force
                    to protect base and possibly UK and Fon nationals. <gloss target="#t_Secy1"
                        >Secy</gloss> emphasized that once one gets started on this road it is most
                    difficult to stop.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> ended discussion by saying that we wld
                    continue, in consultation with <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName>, to
                    see if there was any way we cld help do impossible i.e. separate Sudan and Canal
                    Base issues so that somehow Base question which is heart of matter cld be dealt
                    with.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
