<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-08-04T17:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-08-04T17:50:00-05:00" n="998" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d998">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">641.74/8–452: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 998<lb/><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting
                                        Secretary of State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy
                                        in the United Kingdom</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d998fn1">Repeated to Cairo as telegram 236. Drafted by
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SW1">Stabler</persName> and approved
                                    by <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName>.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-08-04T18:50:00-04:00">August 4, 1952—6:50
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>811. 1. Future course events Egypt still remains sufficiently unclear
                                to prevent formulation any firm policy re possible coop with present
                                Egypt regime.</p>
                            <p>2. Such signs as decision not convoke Wafd Parl, statements by Egypt
                                mil officials re desire coop with West, gen restrained atmosphere
                                and continuance constit monarchy (when radical change was possible.
                                are encouraging.</p>
                            <p>3. On other hand, possibility of dissension among junta surrounding
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NGM1">Naguib</persName>, complications and
                                difficulties in formulating and executing anti-graft and corruption
                                program, Wafd attitude as revealed in Party manifesto, civilian
                                versus mil stresses and strains, and other uncertainties wld seem to
                                pt to probable future difficulties tending to make structure present
                                regime shaky.</p>
                            <p>4. Notwithstanding question marks and obscurities re Egypt future, we
                                believe there is possibility that Egypt mil may wish to come to
                                understanding with UK on Canal Base. While polit shibboleths “unity
                                and evacuation” are standard among all groups, there is some reason
                                to believe that Egypt mil coopn with the West involving West mil
                                assistance wld have sufficient appeal so that Sudan problem might be
                                handled separately from Base issue.</p>
                            <p>5. In view potentialities (altho we admit not necessarily
                                probabilities) new sit created by coup, we think UK wld do well lose
                                no time in formulating in detail settlement they wld like achieve
                                with respect to CZ Base, i.e., technicians, phasing of evacuation,
                                etc.</p>
                            <p>6. Reason we make this suggestion is that if new Egypt regime shld
                                appear ready resume negots and adopt reasonable line, UK wld be in
                                position move quickly take advantage favorable atmosphere.</p>
                            <p>7. We hope UK in formulating detailed settlement wld be as
                                forthcoming as possible since important in discussion with Egypt <pb facs="0146" n="1848" xml:id="pg_1848"/> mil wld be initial
                                favorable impact UK offer settlement. We feel Brits wld stand to
                                gain in long run if they decided beforehand what pts they are likely
                                have to concede and offered them in generous spirit, thereby
                                creating climate favorable to successful negots.</p>
                            <p>8. Pls discuss above with <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss>
                                soonest and say that we shld be glad to have oppy study proposals in
                                hope reaching common agreement. This in turn wld enable us if and
                                when time comes to help put them over.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BDKE1"><hi rend="strong"><hi rend="smallcaps">Bruce</hi></hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>