<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-04-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="1096" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1096">
                    <head>Inhabitants of Huntsville, Alabama</head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Huntsville</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1865-04-18">April 18, 1865</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p rend="center">PUBLIC MEETING.</p>
                    <p>Pursuant to previous notice, a meeting of the citizens of Huntsville and
                        Madison county, Alabama, was held in the court-house at 12 m. on the 18th
                        instant, which was very largely attended.</p>
                    <p>On motion of Hon. Nicholas Davis, Hon. D. C. Humphreys was called to the
                        chair. He explained the object of the meeting to be to give expression to
                        the sentiments of the community, and the citizens generally, in regard to
                        the death of the President of the United States by the hands of the
                        assassin. His remarks evinced deep feeling, and were forcible and
                        judicious.</p>
                    <p>On motion of Hon. D. P. Lewis, W. B. Figures was requested to act as
                        secretary of the meeting.</p>
                    <p>Judge P. M. Dox then moved that a committee of fifteen be appointed by the
                        chair to draft resolutions expressive of the sense of the assemblage, which
                        was carried.</p>
                    <pb facs="0737" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/>
                    <p>The chair appointed the following gentlemen as said committee, viz: P. M.
                        Dox, chairman, D. P. Lewis, F. A. Saunders, Smith Adams, Nicholas Davis,
                        Joseph Ward, Britton Frank, B. M. Lowe, jr., Thos. Bibb, A. J. Johnson, C.
                        E. Douglass, S. M. Weaver, Thos. U. Green, Jas. M. Venable, and Theo.
                        Lacy.</p>
                    <p>The committee retired for a short while and then reported the following
                        preamble and resolutions, which were read and unanimously adopted, viz:</p>
                    <p>Whereas official information has been received in this community that Abraham
                        Lincoln, President of the United States of America, has been killed by the
                        hand of an assassin, and that an attempt, by assassination, has been made on
                        the life of William H. Seward, Secretary of State; and whereas civilization
                        and Christianity alike the laws of God and the laws of man, regard such acts
                        with unmixed horror and execration; the citizens of Huntsville, in primary
                        meeting assembled, and without distinction of parties, do resolve— <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>That they can view the acts of assassination of President Lincoln,
                                and the attempt to assassinate Mr. William H. Seward, Secretary of
                                State, only with emotions of unmixed grief and detestation; and that
                                the assassins are the enemies of civilization and humanity.</item>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>That the acts and the actors can find parallels alone in the
                                calendars of the most flagitious crimes and the most fiendish
                                criminals. They can only be classed in infamy with the savage and
                                the cannibal, the guerilla of Spain, the carbonari of Italy, and
                                thugs of India.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>That copies of the proceedings of this meeting be laid before
                                Brigadier General R. S. Granger, commanding the district of northern
                                Alabama. That copies of the same be sent to Andrew Johnson,
                                President of the United States of America; to Mrs. Lincoln, relict
                                of Abraham Lincoln, late President of the United States; and to Hon.
                                William H. Seward, Secretary of State of the United States of
                                America.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>That the proceedings of the meeting be signed by the president and
                                secretary, and that the same be forwarded to the newspapers in the
                                cities of Nashville and Washington, D. C., with the request that
                                they publish the same.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>On motion of Judge Lewis, a committee of three was appointed by the chair,
                        consisting of Messrs. D. P. Lewis, William B. Figures, and J. W. Scraggs, to
                        carry out the wishes of the meeting expressed in the resolutions.</p>
                    <p>In response to loud calls from the multitude, feeling, appropriate, and
                        eloquent remarks were made by Judge Dox, Hon. Nicholas Davis, Judge Lewis,
                        and the chairman of the meeting, which were received with hearty
                        applause.</p>
                    <p>On motion, the meeting then adjourned.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>D. C. HUMPHREY, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>.</item>
                                <item>WM. B. FIGURES, <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi>.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Huntsville</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Alabama,
                                April</hi> 18, 1865.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>