<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inhabitants of Zanesville, Ohio</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-04-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-04-15T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-04-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-04-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="1146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1146">
                <head>Inhabitants of Zanesville, Ohio</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Zanesville, Ohio</hi>
                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-04-15">
                        <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 15, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">in memoriam</hi>.</p>
                <p>Pursuant to adjournment from the spontaneous meeting held in front of the
                        court house at 9 o’clock this morning, an immense assemblage of the citizens
                        of Zanesville and vicinity convened in the Market-house Hall, at 2 o’clock
                        p. m. Mr. Henry Blandy occupied the chair, and C. W. Potwin continued to act
                        as secretary. Rev. D. D. Mather offered an eloquent and impressive
                        prayer.</p>
                <p>The committee appointed at the morning meeting, composed of the Rev. H. K.
                        Foster, Rev. J. M. Platt, Rev. N. A. Reed, A. A. Guthrie, esq., Colonel
                        Granger, and Messrs. V. Best and H. Blandy, reported, through their
                        chairman, A. A. Guthrie, esq., the following resolutions, which were adopted
                        unanimously:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That this community learns with
                        consternation and profound sorrow of the death, by the hands of murderers,
                        of President Lincoln and Secretary Seward.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That in deliberate and cautious wisdom in
                        judging, in steady spirit and unsullied integrity, and sincere and
                        disinterested devotion to his country’s cause, Abraham Lincoln closely
                        resembled him whom a grateful people have named the “Father of his
                        Country.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That in the death of Mr. Lincoln at this
                        juncture of our national affairs the country suffers a loss the magnitude of
                        which we cannot in our present sorrow adequately estimate, and were it not
                        for our knowledge that God reigns over human affairs, our grief would
                        utterly prostrate and overwhelm us.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That, by the death of Mr. Seward, a
                        learned, liberal, and wise statesman has been taken from us; he had ever
                        been a faithful counsellor of his chief, and “in death they were not
                        divided.” He also died for his country.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That in these diabolical murders we have
                        but the fuller development of the spirit of the rebellion and its
                        acknowledged cause, and the consummation of purposes and plans formed before
                        Mr. Lincoln’s first inauguration; and that the teachings and acts of the
                        rebel leaders have all tended to this result; and that they are justly held
                        responsible before God and the world <pb facs="0789" n="717" xml:id="pg_717"/> for these hellish deeds; and in the name of humanity, as well as that of
                        justice, we demand their punishment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That our confidence still rests in the
                        great truth that God lives and governs, and our recourse must be continually
                        unto Him, beseeching him to preserve and direct the Vice-President, who now
                        succeeds to the chief magistracy; to guide the councils of his cabinet and
                        Congress, and sustain the armies and navy in their self-sacrificing devotion
                        to the national cause; to cause the plots of murderous men to recoil upon
                        themselves, and to deliver our nation from all its present peril.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That in this latest development of the
                        spirit and plans of traitors we find an insuperable objection to all schemes
                        of adjustment which ignore the cause of the rebellion, or propose an
                        indiscriminate pardon of its leaders.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That we deem this occasion a fitting one to
                        renew our consecration to our beloved country; and now and here we do
                        solemnly pledge ourselves to our imperilled government to <hi rend="italic">maintain</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sustain</hi> it against <hi rend="italic">all its foes;</hi> trusting in God, “sink or swim, live or
                        die, survive, or perish,” we will stand by our glorious flag.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That in our deep sorrow for our country we
                        would not forget the deeper sorrow of the families who are utterly
                        overwhelmed by this inscrutable Providence; and that we tender to them our
                        deepest heartfelt condolence, and the assurance of a nation’s fullest
                        sympathy.</p>
                <p>On motion, a committee was appointed consisting of A. A. Guthrie, Charles C.
                        Russell, Colonel Gilbert, and General Ball, to make proper arrangements for
                        funeral services to be held in this city at the same time that they occur at
                        Washington.</p>
                <p>On motion, it was</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That the proceeding and resolutions of this
                        meeting be published in the city papers, and in the Ohio State Journal, and
                        a copy thereof be forwarded to the President of the United States and the
                        families bereaved.</p>
                <p>Following the proceedings, eloquent addresses were delivered by Revs. Foster,
                        Piatt, Read, Slather, and by Hons. T. J. Maginnis and T. A. Reamy.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <list>
                            <item>H. BLANDY, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>.</item>
                            <item>C. W. POTWIN, <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi>.</item>
                        </list>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Note</hi>.—It is proper to notice here that since
                            the adjournment of this meeting of citizens the joyful intelligence
                            reaches us that Secretary Seward is still living, and hopes are
                            entertained of his recovery.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
