<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-05-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                    <head>Convener Court of the Seven Incorporated Trades of Aberdeen</head>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-09">May 9, 1865</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolutions by the convener court of the seven
                            incorporated trades of the city of Aberdeen, North Britain</hi>.</p>
                    <p>At Aberdeen, and within the Trinity hall there, the ninth day of May,
                        eighteen hundred and sixty-five.</p>
                    <p>At a meeting of the convener court representing the seven incorporated trades
                        of the city of Aberdeen, North Britain, the following resolutions were
                        unanimously adopted: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>That this court expresses its sorrow and indignation at the act of
                                atrocity lately committed on President Lincoln, of the United States
                                of America, and its sympathy with the government and people of these
                                States in their peculiar circumstances, and its hope that, under
                                Providence, the establishment of peace there, and harmony between
                                them and the whole world will soon be promoted.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>This court cannot separate without expressing its liveliest
                                feeling and sympathy with Mrs. Lincoln and family, and prays that
                                the worthy example of her husband will prove that a straight-forward
                                and honest course is alike honorable and worthy of imitation.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Signed in name and by appointment of the meeting, and the seal of the court
                        appended hereto by me, convener of said court.</p>
                    <closer> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>] <signed>ROBERT THORUSON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>