<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-05-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-05-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="234" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d234">
                    <head>Union and Emancipation Society</head>
                    <dateline>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ashton-under-Lyne Union and Emancipation Society</hi>, <lb/>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 26, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Address of the Union and Emancipation Society of
                            Ashton-under-Lyne to Mrs. Lincoln</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The sorrowful intelligence which has been recently transmitted to us,
                        announcing the death of your much-beloved husband, Abraham Lincoln, has
                        filled our hearts with pain and sadness. We little expected that his
                        valuable life would have been so suddenly destroyed by the treacherous hand
                        of a cowardly assassin, and cannot but lament the irreparable loss which has
                        deprived you of a faithful protector, your children of an affectionate
                        father, and the American people of a thoughtful and sagacious statesman.</p>
                    <p>We consider the death of the late President a world-wide calamity, because
                        the impression made by it seems to be the strongest and most general that
                        has ever appeared upon the death of a fellow-man; and it is for this reason
                        that we desire to convey to you our united expressions of grief in this
                        severe trial of your affliction and bereavement, and also to declare our
                        abhorrence of the brutal and horrible crime by which his life was
                        sacrificed.</p>
                    <p>In contemplating his character we have often felt a just admiration which his
                        many virtues command; but to dwell upon them here, in any particular, is
                        unnecessary, and, upon this occasion, would perhaps be improper. That his
                        loss has been generally lamented cannot be wondered at, for certainly there
                        never was a more just cause for universal sorrow. To lose such a man, at
                        such a critical time, so unexpectedly and so barbarously, must add to every
                        feeling of regret, and make the sense of bereavement more severe and acute
                        to all thinking minds. He was snatched away in the midst of a crisis when
                        America could spare him least; at a time when the people hoped to be
                        especially benefited by his energy, his benevolence, and his wisdom. His
                        ardent desire to promote the welfare of his fellow-men was conspicuously the
                        animating motive of his active life His indefatigable labors to strike off
                        the fetters which have so long bound the down-trodden negro have at length
                        been rewarded by a glorious and triumphant victory. Millions of them are
                        already free—free as the very breath of heaven; and the accursed
                        slave-stain, which has ever soiled the American banner, will now be
                        eradicated, and the fate of the accursed system forever sealed with the
                        martyred blood of a holy Christian man. Never was he known to shirk the
                        onerous duties of his responsible office; in every instance we have found
                        him true to his sacred oath; even in the latest hours of his life kindness
                        to his enemies was the uppermost sentiment of his generous heart, prompting
                        the most considerate arrangements for the happiness and comfort of a great
                        and mighty people.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, permit us to hope that the humble and genuine affection so
                        widely entertained towards him will tend to mitigate in some degree the
                        heavy bereavement of his afflicted family, consoling them with the knowledge
                        that the labors of the departed are truly appreciated by thousands of
                        earnest hearts in far distant lands.</p>
                    <p>Signed on behalf of the members of the Ashton-under-Lyne Union and
                        Emancipation Society.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>JAMES BROADBENT, <hi rend="italic">President</hi>.</item>
                                <item>JOHN HAGUE, <hi rend="italic">Vice-President</hi>.</item>
                                <item>JOHN GLAZEBROOK, <hi rend="italic">Treasurer</hi>.</item>
                                <item>JOB ARUNDALE, <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi>.</item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Mrs. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lincoln</hi>.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>