<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Welsh Residents of London</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d484</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">484</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-05-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="484" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d484">
                <head>Welsh Residents of London</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>London</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-08">May 8, 1865</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolutions passed at a meeting held by the Welsh
                            residents in London</hi>.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">sympathy with america</hi>.</p>
                <p>At a meeting of Welsh residents in London, held at the Young Men’s Christian
                        Association institution, Aldersgate street, on Monday, the 8th of May, the
                        Rev. Owen Thomas Jewin Crescent, in the chair, the following resolutions
                        were unanimously adopted:</p>
                <p>I. Moved by Rev. Henry Richard, seconded by J. Owen, esq., Holloway, and
                        supported by Rev. W. Rees, Liverpool:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That this meeting desires to express its
                        utter abhorrence of the <pb facs="0355" n="283" xml:id="pg_283"/> execrable
                        crime by which Mr. Abraham Lincoln, President of the United States, was
                        stricken down by the hand of an assassin, at a time so inexpressibly
                        critical and momentous in the history of that country, while it cordially
                        joins in the tribute of admiration so universally paid to the many admirable
                        qualities of the deceased statesman, the honesty, simplicity, and firmness
                        of his character, the rare self-control which he showed amid the excitement
                        of conflict and the moderation and mercy with which he was prepared to use
                        the advantages of victory.</p>
                <p>II. Moved by Mr. John Griffith, seconded by Mr. J. Williams, London city
                        mission, supported by Dr. Nicholas, Dr. Reed, Swansea, Rev. W. Lloyd,
                        Aldersgate street, and Thomas Williams, esq., Pendarran:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That the meeting would convey to the people
                        of the United States the assurance of its profound sympathy under the
                        appalling calamity that has overtaken them, and earnestly hopes they will
                        not suffer themselves to be driven, even by the supreme atrocity of this
                        act, from the disposition, so honorable to their national character, which
                        they had previously displayed, to act towards their vanquished brethren in
                        the spirit of true Christian kindness and conciliation.</p>
                <p>III. Moved by Rev. J. Kilsby Jones, seconded by Rev. H. C. Parry, supported
                        by Rev. W. Edwards Aberdare, D. Davies, London, and D. Rowlands, B. A.
                        Lanbrynmair:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That the meeting would further record the
                        expression of its respectful sympathy with Mrs. Lincoln in the midst of the
                        awful affliction that has befallen her, and trusts that she may be enabled
                        to find solace in the thought that the father of the fatherless and the
                        judge of the widow is God in his holy habitation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Signed on behalf of the meeting:</salute>
                    <signed>OWEN THOMAS,</signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>.</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
