<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Stockport Sunday School Union</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d619</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">619</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvFVZiL6ijeo9Lc" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104428"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political rights</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="619"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d619">
                <head>Stockport Sunday School Union</head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Resolutions passed at a meeting held by the Sunday School
                        Union of Stockport</hi>.</p>
                <p>At a meeting of the teachers, superintendents, and representatives of the schools
                    composing the Sunday School Union of Stockport, held on the eighth day of May,
                    1865, Mr. Councillor George Barber in the chair, it was—</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Unanimously resolved</hi>, That the Sunday schools of
                    Stockport, embracing all he evangelical denominations of the Christian church,
                    have heard with feelings of <pb facs="0415" n="343" xml:id="pg_343"/> the
                    deepest horror and the most inexpressible grief of the brutal assassination of
                    Abraham Lincoln, President of the United States of America, by the hand of a
                    vile and reckless murderer.</p>
                <p>That this union, while recording this expression of the most heartfelt sympathy
                    and sorrowful condolence with the bereaved widow and the great American
                    republic, most cordially recognizes the eminent personal worth, the high-toned
                    religious principle, and the noble civic virtues of that large hearted father of
                    the American people, twice elected as Chief Magistrate by the popular voice,
                    beloved by the children of two hemispheres, admired by the vast army of Sunday
                    school teachers in the free countries of Europe and America, and revered by the
                    great and good of every clime, as the heroic emancipator of four millions of
                    abject bondsmen, and the saviour of his country from armed rebellion, anarchy,
                    and ruin.</p>
                <p>That whilst this union cherishes these sentiments with the deepest emotion, it
                    feels most keenly the death, by the hand of a wretched drunkard, of so good a
                    man, whose persistent advocacy of the importance of an education based upon
                    religious principles, and his bright example as a steady and consistent
                    abstainer from intoxicating drinks, afforded strength and encouragement to our
                    bands of hope, and proved that, even under circumstances of the most severe
                    trials ever imposed upon the ruler of a great nation, the late President of the
                    United States of America devoted the full strength of his lofty intelligence and
                    the warmest sympathies of his noble heart.</p>
                <p>While our Sunday schools are bowed with sorrow, feeling that each has lost a
                    friend, the prayer is raised continually that this fearful rebellion may
                    speedily be brought to a close, and that a permanent peace may soon be
                    proclaimed, established on the only righteous basis, viz: That of union,
                    nationality, justice, and freedom, with equal civil and political rights to all
                    loyal men, of whatever creed, race or condition, and the inestimable blessings
                    of a healthy religious education secured to all rising and future generations of
                    the republic.</p>
                <p>Signed on behalf of the Union—</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <list>
                            <item>GEORGE BARBER, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>.</item>
                            <item>JAMES H. MIDDLETON, <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Honorary Secretary</hi>.</item>
                        </list>
                    </signed>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockport</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-08">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 8, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
