<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-07-31T19:42:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-04-14T19:43:00-05:00" n="777" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d777">
                    <head>Hon. H. B. W. Johnson, Secretary of State</head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Monrovia</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-volume-rules" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1865-07-31T23:59:59-00:43" notBefore="1865-04-15T00:00:00-00:43">undated</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p>Whereas the honorable Abraham Lincoln, late President of the United States of
                        America, a ruler ordained of Heaven, has, by the ruthless hand of the
                        assassin, been removed from his sphere of usefulness in this life; and</p>
                    <p>Whereas in the death of that great chief the American nation has sustained a
                        severe loss, in which the interests of nations, as well as those of mankind
                        generally, have participated; and</p>
                    <p>Whereas the government and people of the republic of Liberia, which is
                        legitimately an offspring of the great American republic, fostered during
                        the period of its colonial growth by a society of American citizens, and
                        recently greatly favored and sustained by the United States government,
                        recognized in the late President of the United States one who utterly
                        abhorred slavery—a friend of the negro race and a promoter of the interests
                        of Liberia; and</p>
                    <p>Whereas, by the sudden and lamentable death of this great ruler, not only has
                        a nation been deprived of its head, but a home and a hearth are desolate,
                        and kindred hearts are broken, and tears of grief are shedding by those who,
                        by reason of a foul murder, have been deprived of a companion, a father, a
                        friend: Therefore,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved by the President of the republic of Liberia and
                            his cabinet in council</hi>, That it is with sincere regret and pain, as
                        well as with feelings of horror and indignation, the government of Liberia
                        has heard of the foul assassination of the honorable Abraham Lincoln, late
                        President of the United States of America.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That the government and people of Liberia
                        deeply sympathize with the government and people of the United States in the
                        sad loss they have sustained by the death of so wise, so just, so efficient,
                        so vigorous, and yet so merciful a ruler.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That while with due sorrow the government
                        and people of Liberia weep with those that mourn the loss of so great and
                        good a chief, they are, nevertheless, mindful of the loss they themselves
                        have experienced in the death of the great philanthropist whose virtues can
                        never cease to be told so long as the republic of Liberia shall endure; so
                        long as there survives a member of the negro race to tell of the chains that
                        have been broken; of the griefs that have been allayed; of the broken hearts
                        that have been bound up by him who, as it were a new creation, breathed life
                        into four millions of that race whom he found oppressed and degraded.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That our prayers are also on behalf of him
                        who has been called so suddenly to assume the reins of government, the
                        honorable Andrew Johnson, President of the United States of America; that we
                        trust that the God who controls the destinies of nations will endue him with
                        all wisdom necessary to rule so great a people, and continue to guide the
                        nation in its rapid progress to the consummation of its greatness and
                        glory.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That we express, moreover, our sympathy for
                        the efficient statesman, the profound diplomatist, the honorable William H.
                        Seward, Secretary of State of the United States, who, with the Assistant
                        Secretary of State, had nigh fallen a prey to that horrible conspiracy which
                        has robbed the American nation of its brightest jewel.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That while we are reluctant to invade the
                        sacred precincts of domestic sorrow, we cannot refrain from expressing here
                        our sympathy for Mrs. Lincoln, the estimable widow of the late President,
                        exhorting her to receive to <pb facs="0545" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> her
                        consolation the words of Holy Writ, “Whom the Lord loveth He chasteneth,”
                        and to be sustained by the promises of Almighty God, who will be a husband
                        and a father to the widow and orphans of him who, in his lifetime, was not
                        only the ruler of his own people, but a father to millions of a race
                        stricken and oppressed. That, while wicked men have desolated her home by
                        the perpetration of a crime too horrible to be uttered, the renowned chief,
                        the beloved companion, the tender father, has died to redeem a nation, a
                        race; and, dying in the performance of so noble a work, he has left behind a
                        monument more lasting than brass, and generations yet unborn shall call him
                        the mighty ruler, the great emancipator, the noble philanthropist.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That copies of these resolutions be
                        presented to the United States consul general in Monrovia, with a request
                        that he forward a copy to the proper authority at Washington, and also one
                        to Mrs. Lincoln.</p>
                    <closer>By order of the President: <signed>H. B. W. JOHNSON,</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State</hi>.</closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>