<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Henry Headly Parish</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d853</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">853</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-04-29T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-04-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="853" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d853">
                <head>Mr. Henry Headly Parish</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-04-29">
                        <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 29, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Parish</persName> to the <gloss type="to">American citizens in Rome</gloss>, read at the American
                            chapel</hi>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ladies and Gentlemen, Brethren and Sisters in
                            Christ</hi>: With the kind permission of your excellent representatives,
                        and as having enjoyed as a diplomatic guest the hospitality of the United
                        States during four years, more than forty years ago, I hope I may not be
                        thought presumptuous in mingling <pb facs="0601" n="529" xml:id="pg_529"/>
                        with your sacred grief an expression from the old country, the land of our
                        grandsires, being myself wholly unconnected with politics.</p>
                <p>If my fellow-countrymen at Rome are not present with you this day to manifest
                        their horror at the event which has deprived you of the Chief Magistrate of
                        your choice, of that conscientious spirit who lived and toiled and died that
                        all his fellow-citizens might be united in peace, be assured that the
                        motives of their absence must be reluctance to intrude, uninvited, into the
                        grave of your domestic affections. The profound sympathy of our own
                        sovereign and of her royal family, so often bursting forth in the days of
                        your heavy trials, must guarantee to you the love at such a moment of the
                        many millions who, within so many horizons, own her sway. But while we are
                        all here in spirit to denounce the most odious of crimes, let us acknowledge
                        how hopeful is the dawn of your future life, when he who now rules in the
                        shrine of the pious Washington has given the impress of his power and of the
                        happiness of every transatlantic soul in his first inaugural words, “I am in
                        the hands of God.” Thus may we be all “of one accord” in every place, united
                        in Christ, one in God, and God in us.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HENRY HEADLEY PARISH.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
