<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Duke of Valencia to Mr. Perry..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d858</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">858</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="858"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d858">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Duke of Valencia</gloss> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Perry</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <note rend="inline" rendition="#center" type="source">[Translation.]</note>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Presidency of the Cabinet of Ministers</hi>, <lb/>
                    <placeName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-05">
                        <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 5, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The horrible crimes committed on the persons of
                    the President and Secretary of State of the United States have caused a painful
                    and profound sensation in the Spanish nation, which is united to that great
                    republic by the ties of a true friendship and a cordial sympathy.</p>
                <p>Although at the first moment this sad news reached us I hastened to make known to
                    you, personally, the profound grief of her Majesty the Queen, my august
                    sovereign, and of her government, at that immense misfortune, I have the honor
                    to-day to transmit to you the annexed copies of the declarations made by the
                    Senate and the Congress of Deputies, associating themselves to the great sorrow
                    of that generous nation for the abominable crime perpetrated upon the person of
                    its illustrious and respected President.</p>
                <p>The affliction which the death of that eminent statesman has produced to the
                    government of her Majesty is in part relieved by the welcome news that the life
                    of the Secretary of State for foreign affairs is happily not in great danger,
                    but, on the contrary, that there are well-founded hopes he may obtain a prompt
                    and complete recovery. Please God it may be so, for the good and prosperity of
                    that noble country of which you are the most worthy representative!</p>
                <p>I avail myself of this occasion to renew to you the assurance of my most
                    distinguished consideration.</p>
                <closer>The <signed>DUKE OF VALENCIA</signed>.</closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Chargé d’Affaires</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">of the United States of America</hi>.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
