<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editor of the Bund to Mr. Fogg</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d898</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">898</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="reccab053b473a4a56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="world-war-i" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148236" lcsh-match="exact">Councils</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="898"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d898">
                <head>Editor of the Bund to Mr. Fogg</head>
                <note rend="inline" rendition="#center" type="source">[Translation.]</note>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi>
                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-12">
                        <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 12, 1865</date>.</dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">To the honorable George G. Fogg, minister resident of the
                        United States, Berne</hi>.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">To the hands of his Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Andrew
                        Johnson</hi>, <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">President of the United States, at Washington:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The undersigned has the honor herewith to transmit to you the address of sympathy
                    and condolence to the American Union voted by a meeting of Swiss citizens at
                    Bern, and accompanied by the declarations of accession sent in from all parts of
                    the whole Swiss Confederation.</p>
                <p>It required but the slight impulsion of this address to arouse in Switzerland a
                    lively and most universal movement of sympathy for the American sister republic.
                    After the members of the high Federal Council and of the grand council of the
                    canton of Berne had opened the list of signatures, the governments of Argovy and
                    Soleure gave the signal for the accession also of the cantonal governments, most
                    of whom have, upon the immediate invitation of the address committee, not
                    hesitated to comply either by letters to the Federal Council, or by direct
                    individual signature, and in the names of their cantons.</p>
                <p>In Geneva a meeting of 4,000, and in Chaux-de-fonds one of 2,000 persons was held
                    in order to vote a separate address. The grand councils of Vaud and Tessin also
                    have voted separate manifestations of sympathy. Besides a number of the most
                    prominent citizens of the country, a great many communal authorities and private
                    citizens, particularly from the cantons of Berne, Basle-Town, Neufchatel,
                    Argovy, Zurich, (town of Winterthur,) Fribourg, (town of Murten,) Basle,
                    Campagne, &amp;c., have acceded to our address. The aggregate number of
                    signatures, which at this moment cannot be given quite accurately, may be
                    estimated for the accompanying address alone at about 10,000, if the number can
                    add anything to the value of the testimonials of sympathy from all classes and
                    professions, authorities and private individuals.</p>
                <p>The greatest act of sympathy, however, was the resolution of the Landsgememde of
                    Glaris, an assembly of from 5,000 to 6,000 voters of a Swiss canton of 30,000
                    inhabitants, who in the open air make the laws of their country, and of which
                    occasion they availed themselves, at the suggestion of their Landammann,
                    unanimously to rise, and with uncovered heads to manifest their sympathy with
                    the American Union.</p>
                <p>In accordance with this manifestation, the government of another democratic
                    canton, namely, Grisons, has submitted the question of a demonstration of
                    sympathy and condolence by the people of Grisons, to all the thirty-nine
                    district assemblies, which in that canton are equal to the Landsgememde; and
                    there is no doubt that on Sunday, the 14th May, the voters of a canton of 90,000
                    inhabitants will also unanimously proclaim their sympathy for the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>In view of these tokens it may well be asserted that it is the whole Swiss people
                    who, in this moment, offer to the American people their greeting of brotherly
                    sentiment. Our sole wish is, that it may be received in the same spirit by the
                    citizens of the American Union.</p>
                <p>With the highest consideration, in the name of the address committee,</p>
                <p rend="right">F. GENGEL, <hi rend="italic">Editor of the Bund</hi>.</p>
                <pb facs="0632" n="560" xml:id="pg_560"/>
                <p>P. S.—It will hardly be necessary to explain that the term “democracy” in the
                    address is not synonymous with the party denomination in America. The address of
                    condolence also is directed to Mr. Vice-President Johnson, because it was drawn
                    up before his (known) inauguration as President. And in regard finally to the
                    external appearance of the signatures, the apology may be given that though much
                    may be left to be desired, they are not the less sincere.</p>
                <p>The above undersigned.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
