<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-07-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="12" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d12">
                        <head>12. Memorandum Prepared in the Central Intelligence Agency for Emerson
                            Brown of the Bureau of Intelligence and Research, Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d12fn1">Source: National
                                Security Council, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                                Administration Intelligence Files, Subject Files A–E, Box 25, Angola
                                11 July 1977–18 April 1978. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-07-25">July 25, 1977</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>PERSPECTIVES—Cuban/Soviet Presence in Angola</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>1. Cuban intervention in Angola succeeded in allowing <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Fidel Castro</persName> again to pose as a leader
                            of “international revolution”, enhanced his image as a leader in parts
                            of the Third World, gave him renewed international attention, and served
                            to reinforce his contention that Communist and Third World countries are
                            continuing to gain advantage over the West. The use of the Cubans as
                            surrogates allowed the Soviets to retain a relatively low profile,
                            offsetting possible African fears of neo-colonialism, while they
                            extended their military capability and political influence over a
                            significant part of Africa. The strategic location of Angola on borders
                            of both black-ruled and white-ruled countries gives the Soviets an
                            unusual opportunity to exert influence in this area, particularly in
                            relation to the debate and struggle over the future of Rhodesia and
                            Namibia, and the ultimate problem of South Africa.</p>
                        <p>2. It is estimated that there are 18,000 or more Cubans in Angola, and
                            there have been recent reports citing a growing Angolan unhappiness with
                            this presence. Angolans have referred to the Cubans as arrogant “new
                            colonialists” who tread on African sensibilities, who together with the
                            Soviets monopolize what few luxuries are available in the country, and
                            who contribute little or nothing to the economic progress or internal
                            security of the country.<note n="2" xml:id="d12fn2">See <ref target="#d4fn2">footnote 2, Document 4</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. With the objective of dispelling the aura surrounding the Cuban/Soviet
                            presence in Angola, and of discouraging its spread elsewhere in Africa,
                            we propose to expose Angolan displeasure with the Cuban <pb facs="0057" n="20" xml:id="pg_20"/> presence, and to discourage the continuation
                            of that presence, through the use of our international covert action
                            infrastructure. In general terms, we intend to influence the propaganda
                            content of certain foreign radio broadcasts to parts of Africa; conduct
                            related propaganda and political influence operations elsewhere in
                            Africa, and use the infrastructure for propaganda outside of Africa,
                            particularly in Western Europe and Latin America.</p>
                        <p>4. The following themes, to be used in selective tasking of the
                            infrastructure, are submitted for State Department approval:<note n="3" xml:id="d12fn3">On August 2 the Department responded: “We agree that
                                the Angola government and its Cuban allies appear to be in an
                                increasingly difficult situation, however, we are reluctant to agree
                                that USG covert propaganda in an effort to publicize this situation
                                would be useful to us for the following reasons: 1. We are
                                attempting to normalize relations with Angola and Cuba and a covert
                                propaganda campaign would work against that policy. 2. Moderate and
                                friendly African governments are very aware of the situation in
                                Angola and are already accusing us of failing to block Soviet-Cuban
                                aggression and urging us to take action. Covert propaganda directed
                                towards these governments would be preaching to the converted. 3.
                                ‘Radical’ and ‘progressive’ governments are becoming increasingly
                                aware of the situation. <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Savimbi</persName> of <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss>
                                is attempting to obtain publicity (witness the <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi> reporter who just returned from seven
                                months in the bush and who will be publishing a series of articles
                                in August). The situation is becoming increasingly embarrassing for
                                the Angolans and the Cubans and any involvement on our part raises
                                the risk of compromising the <hi rend="italic">bona fides</hi> of
                                the information now surfacing.” Leon Dash wrote a series of seven
                                articles published in the <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>
                                August 8–13.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>a. Stress that the Cubans and Soviets in Angola are the new breed of
                            colonials who have become arrogant and have continually ignored African
                            sensibilities, and have monopolized those few luxuries that exist in the
                            country.</p>
                        <p>b. Cite instances of frictions created between Angolans and Cubans as a
                            result of Cuban attitudes and actions. These include Angolan charges
                            that the Cubans enjoy conspicuously high standards of living while
                            Angolans experience severe shortages of food and other basic
                            necessities, that Cuban technicians were inadequately trained, that
                            “administrators” know little about administration, and that Cubans
                            confine themselves to garrison towns and do little in pursuit of the
                            enemy.</p>
                        <p>c. Encourage moderate African leaders to express concern about Cuban and
                            Soviet presence in Angola as a threat to the territorial integrity of
                            African states.</p>
                        <p>d. Exploit continuing criticism made by the People’s Republic of China of
                            Cuban/Soviet presence in Angola and domination of the Angolan
                            government.</p>
                        <p>e. Question <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName>’s requests for
                            foreign aid from other governments, and the wisdom of such aid being
                            granted while he is spending so much on continued deployment of troops
                            and equipment in Angola.</p>
                        <pb facs="0058" n="21" xml:id="pg_21"/>
                        <p>f. Call attention to the critical attitude of some Latin American
                            governments toward Cuban foreign adventures, and to beliefs of some
                            Latin American leaders that Cuba cannot expect to assume a position of
                            being a worldwide “revolutionary leader” through continued presence in
                            Angola, and at the same time retain its respectability in Latin
                            America.</p>
                        <p>g. Emphasize that Angola is far removed from Cuba and well beyond
                            reasonable limits of Cuban security interests. Stress that the presence
                            of Cubans in Angola serves to undermine Cuba’s apparent wish to improve
                            relations with the US and other non-Communist nations.</p>
                        <p>h. Cite the need for negotiated political settlement for majority rule in
                            Rhodesia and self-determination for Namibia. Settlement of these issues
                            would negate major pretexts that the Cubans and Soviets have used for
                            their presence in Angola.</p>
                        <p>i. Stress that the Cuban involvement in Angola prolongs a bloody,
                            internecine war, pitting black against black.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>