<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>133. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Zambia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-01-28T19:34:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-01-28T19:34:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-01-28T19:34:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-01-28T19:34:00-05:00" n="133"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                <head>133. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Zambia<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d133fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box 88, Zambia: 1/77–5/78.
                        Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_WFG_1">Wisner</persName>; cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SWE_1">Schaufele</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1"
                            >Habib</persName> and in <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>; approved
                        by <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-01-29T00:34:00+00:00">January 29, 1977, 0034Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>20461. For the Ambassador. Subject: Message to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName>.</p>
                <p>1. Please pass the following message to President <persName corresp="#p_KK_1"
                        >Kaunda</persName>.</p>
                <p>2. “Dear Mr. President: The President has written you to say I would be in
                        touch.<note n="2" xml:id="d133fn2">In telegram 17342 to Lusaka, January 26,
                        the Department transmitted a message from President <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> to President <persName
                            corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName>, in which <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> expressed his commitment to a
                        peaceful resolution of the conflicts in Rhodesia and Namibia. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> also mentioned that <persName
                            corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> would consult with <persName
                            corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> “on future steps we might take, and
                        ways in which we can work together to achieve solutions for Southern
                        Africa’s difficult problems.” (Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                        Brzezinski Material, President’s Correspondence with Foreign Leaders File,
                        Box 22, Zambia: President <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kenneth D.
                            Kaunda</persName>, 1–12/77)</note> I want to take an early opportunity
                    to write you about the Rhodesian situation. I appreciated the message of
                    encouragement you sent me through <persName corresp="#p_CM_2">Mark
                        Chona</persName> and profited from his report of your views.</p>
                <p>3. “Needless to say, <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Ian Smith</persName>’s January
                        24<note n="3" xml:id="d133fn3">See <ref target="#d131fn2">footnote 2,
                            Document 131</ref>.</note> speech came as an unpleasant surprise to us.
                    As you know, we have supported the British proposals on Rhodesia as a basis for
                    further negotiations and had <pb facs="0403" n="366" xml:id="pg_366"/> hoped
                    that <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> and the Zimbabwean
                    nationalists would do the same. Of course I recognize that during the course of
                    negotiations concessions by all the parties will be necessary if a solution is
                    to be reached. We continue to support the framework of a settlement which the
                    British have advanced. We regret that efforts to reach a satisfactory negotiated
                    settlement have, for the moment, at least, been rebuffed. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName>’s attitude has produced a new and more
                    dangerous situation in Rhodesia and Southern Africa.</p>
                <p>4. “<persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName>’s reference in his speech to an
                    internal solution is unacceptable and we have so stated in public. We have told
                    him that if a deadlock is reached, he will be met by stiff American opposition.
                    As an indication of our position, the President has asked me to tell you that
                    the administration will seek the repeal of the <persName corresp="#p_BRC_1"
                        >Byrd</persName> Amendment. We are beginning efforts with the Congress to
                    work towards that end. We have asked the South Africans to communicate our
                    message to <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName>.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d133fn4">See the attachment to <ref target="#d131">Document
                            131</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>5. “I will be making a statement to the press on Monday in which I will reconfirm
                    the United States’ commitment to majority rule, our intention to pursue a
                    negotiated settlement and will restate our opposition to the course <persName
                        corresp="#p_SI_1">Ian Smith</persName> has indicated. We are in close
                    consultations with the British Government and will over the course of the coming
                    days give careful thought to the next steps. As our review of the situation
                    proceeds, I expect to stay in close touch with you and look forward to having
                    your thoughts. I hope all parties will move forward in the period ahead in a
                    manner which will contribute to a renewed search for a peaceful solution.</p>
                <p>6. “I understand you will be in Tanzania at the same time Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_YA_1">Andrew Young</persName> is visiting. I would appreciate
                    your receiving him and providing him with your assessment of what lies
                    ahead.</p>
                <p>7. “I know of your long dedication to the cause of peace in Southern Africa and
                    the independence of Zimbabwe and Namibia. Your vision and courage have long
                    impressed me. The present situation is a difficult one, but I am certain that,
                    if we join together and persevere, a successful conclusion will be reached.<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d133fn5">In telegram 337 from Lusaka, February 4, the Embassy
                        transmitted a reply from <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> to
                            <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>. <persName
                            corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> welcomed the administration’s
                        commitment to majority rule in Southern Africa, but said that <persName
                            corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName>’s announcement left the Frontline
                        States “no choice but to support the Nationalists fully in their
                        intensification of the war of liberation.” (Carter Library, National
                        Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box 88, Zambia:
                        1/77–5/78)</note>
                </p>
                <p>8. “Respectfully, <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Cyrus R. Vance</persName>.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Vance</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
