<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>190. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in the United
                    Kingdom</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d190</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">190</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-02-26T15:59:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-02-26T15:59:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-02-26T15:59:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-02-26T15:59:00-05:00" n="190"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d190">
                <head>190. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in the United
                        Kingdom<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d190fn1">Source: Carter Library,
                        National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Cables File, State
                        Department Out, Box 111, 2/18–28/78. Confidential; Cherokee; Immediate;
                            <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Printed from a copy that was
                        received in the White House Situation Room. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_EWB_1">Edmondson</persName>. (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        P840142–2167)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-02-26T20:59:00+00:00">February 26, 1978, 2059Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>49711. For Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BKJ_1">Brewster</persName> only.
                    Subject: Rhodesia: Letter From <persName corresp="#p_ODA_1">Owen</persName> to
                        <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>.</p>
                <p>Following is text of signed letter from <persName corresp="#p_ODA_1"
                        >Owen</persName> dated 24 February 1978 and delivered to Department for the
                    Secretary on February 26. Response sent <gloss target="#t_septel_1"
                        >septel</gloss>.<note n="2" type="source" xml:id="d190fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d191">Document 191</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Begin text:</p>
                <p>Personal and Confidential</p>
                <p>Dear Cy:</p>
                <p>I have spent about five hours discussing Rhodesia with <persName
                        corresp="#p_MRM_1">Dick Moose</persName> over the last few days and this has
                    been very valuable. I am sorry I was not able to devote more time to it but I
                    leave tonight for Jordan and Israel and I also had to spend some hours this week
                    talking to the Rev. <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sithole</persName>. I think we
                    have stiffened him considerably along agreed lines about our joint concern over
                    the issues of substance still to be decided in the Salisbury talks. I was,
                    however, sorry that <persName corresp="#p_MRM_1">Dick Moose</persName> decided
                    not to meet Rev. <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Sithole</persName>. I attach great
                    importance to demonstrating to the world that we are open to all the parties to
                    the dispute and in my view we would be unwise to underestimate <persName
                        corresp="#p_SN_1">Sithole</persName>’s ability or his toughness as a
                    politician. I believe he could well eventually establish a working relationship
                    with <persName corresp="#p_NJ_1">Joshua Nkomo</persName> and together they could
                    become a formidable combination. Certainly I cannot see how either alone has
                    sufficient electoral strength to beat Bishop <persName corresp="#p_MA_2"
                        >Muzorewa</persName>, although any predictions so far ahead of an election
                    are hazardous.</p>
                <p>For the first time since we started our joint initiative I detect the possibility
                    of a different analysis of the problem. This is potentially serious and is why I
                    write. Let me assure you that I will not take any unilateral decisions. The
                    differences may be exaggerated by having to compress into a short space of time
                    a difficult analysis and I certainly think it is wise for us all to stop and
                    think. I am not so certain about my own analysis that I am not open to argument
                    and could well change my view, particularly if I felt that you and I differed,
                    for to my <pb facs="0585" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/> knowledge that would be the
                    first time we had differed on any significant issue anywhere in the world since
                    we started working together.</p>
                <p>Working backwards, we start, I am sure, from an agreed position. Our long-term
                    objective, besides bringing about a genuine transfer of power and fair and free
                    elections for Zimbabwe, must be to prevent increased Cuban involvement in the
                    Rhodesian situation, which would cause us to lose our current influence on
                    Zambia, and as a lesser, though important, priority to keep Mozambique genuinely
                    non-aligned and if possible with an improving relationship with both our
                    countries. At the same time, we both want to keep good relations with the <gloss
                        target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> and retain the momentum of our African
                    policies. However, we need to be tough-minded about what exactly the <gloss
                        target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> is. For example, Mauritius’ UN Representative,
                    Krishna Ramphul, takes a line with the UN which is frequently at total variance
                    with that of his own government. There is a feeling amongst some African
                    countries that, over the last year, our two countries have tended to respond
                    only to the vocal and radical voices in the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1"
                    >OAU</gloss>. Even the countries fairly close to Rhodesia are not united and
                    their leaders are privately worried that we tend to lean over too much to
                    accommodate the Patriotic Front, for example. This is thought, if not said, by
                    Botswana, Zaire, Kenya, Malawi and Ghana, while further afield the Arab African
                    states and the French-influenced African states are not as solid on the
                    Patriotic Front as one would think from the decisions of Libreville and
                    Tripoli.</p>
                <p>Now, as to the way forward, our initiative always had as its greatest weakness
                    the point on which the Front-Line Presidents not unreasonably focus, namely how
                    we remove <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> or, as President
                        <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> puts it “how to bell the cat.”
                    We were able, by a mixture of confident assertion and letting it be known that
                    we were planning for oil sanctions, to convince most people that we meant
                    business, but this was only ever a credible strategy in a scenario in which we
                    were able to convince all the main Rhodesian Nationalist leaders of our
                    proposals, where they were solidly on board and where we only faced an
                    intransigent <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> holding out for white
                    minority rule. We do not face that situation now. We have not been able to rally
                    all the Nationalist leaders to our proposals, and the world sees Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> as making very significant moves in the
                    direction of a genuine transfer of power in agreement with Bishop <persName
                        corresp="#p_MA_2">Muzorewa</persName> whom the world sees as the most
                    popular Nationalist figure inside Rhodesia. Malta opened a chink of light but,
                    as I said to you in New York, there are still major differences and we for our
                    part have very little room, if any, to make more concessions. Frankly, I believe
                    that even if we managed to get the Patriotic Front to support our proposals, we
                    would be a laughing stock if we proposed that we should apply oil sanctions
                    against a Salisbury agreement in the present situation. We could also be
                    severely attacked for backing <pb facs="0586" n="549" xml:id="pg_549"/> the
                    forces of violence in an attempt to overthrow a genuine democratic settlement.
                    That is certainly how people here would see it.</p>
                <p>I know that most of your people would agree with this analysis but it is
                    important to state this brutally and frankly now because if we can agree on this
                    then we must surely be extremely careful in giving any credence to the view that
                    our main emphasis now should be on trying to get the Patriotic Front to agree to
                    our proposals. Reality dictates that our objective now should be to accept that
                    we will have to somehow widen the area of agreement so that we aim to achieve a
                    settlement at a point, and I do not know where it will be, somewhere between the
                    Salisbury talks and the Anglo/US initiative. Such a settlement may not involve a
                    complete ceasefire but it should aim to minimize the fighting. If you accept
                    this analysis then our task is in a variety of different ways to get the
                    Front-Line Presidents and all the parties to the dispute to recognize that this
                    is the direction in which we are all going to have to go.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, it means that if we are to achieve that point of maximum agreement
                    at least one of the Nationalist leaders, and realism dictates that will probably
                    be <persName corresp="#p_NJ_1">Joshua Nkomo</persName>, must come into some
                    arrangement involving <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_MA_2">Muzorewa</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SN_1"
                        >Sithole</persName>. This does not mean coming in on the basis of the
                    Salisbury talks but widening out from the progress we have made so far and the
                    progress made in the Salisbury talks. How to achieve it is very difficult. I
                    tend to believe, and may well be wrong, that if it were possible by clandestine
                    means to involve <persName corresp="#p_NJ_1">Nkomo</persName> before the
                    Salisbury talks firm up on an agreement, this would be better since I rather
                    doubt that they will be prepared to give much once an agreement has been fixed
                    and it will then be harder to involve <persName corresp="#p_NJ_1">Joshua
                        Nkomo</persName> and prevent him taking the route of violence. I well
                    recognize that to do this without alienating the Front-Line Presidents is
                    extremely difficult. But again we must analyze what the Front-Line Presidents
                    are, in particular the relationship between <persName corresp="#p_NJ_1"
                        >Nkomo</persName> and President <persName corresp="#p_KK_1"
                        >Kaunda</persName> is crucial. My fear is that if we ignore what is going on
                    in Salisbury on the basis of a policy of non-contamination we could find
                    ourselves in a situation where Salisbury reaches agreement but we are identified
                    solely with the Patriotic Front. The only way the Patriotic Front will then be
                    able to influence Salisbury is to increase the violence. This in the short term
                    can only be brought about by reinforcements, probably Cuban, and we, instead of
                    being the negotiators, will become identified with the violence, particularly if
                    we are committed to implementing our proposals through having brought the
                    Patriotic Front to agree to them.</p>
                <p>Now I do not underestimate in any way the difficulty of walking this tightrope.
                    But I detect in the US position, and I hope I am wrong, a slight tendency to
                    want to avoid making some of these choices and <pb facs="0587" n="550"
                        xml:id="pg_550"/> to feel that by sticking only with the Anglo/US initiative
                    and with the <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> we can stay clean and on the
                    right side. I should stress that I am not saying that we should in any way
                    retract our support for the principles of the Anglo/US initiative. It remains
                    the right policy for us to have pursued, for it offered the hope of a ceasefire.
                    But holding resolutely to that now will not, in my view, achieve either a
                    ceasefire or a negotiated settlement, or a reduction in the violence. Yet in
                    order to exert influence on the negotiation we must not be seen to move
                    precipitately off the Anglo/US initiative. I well recognize that if the
                    Patriotic Front came to us genuinely wanting to discuss our initiative, it would
                    be difficult for us not to respond, but again I stress to you as I did in New
                    York that the onus must be on them to indicate what movement they are making in
                    our direction. If they did indicate such movement we should have to be careful
                    to avoid the danger (which I have described) that we should be expected to
                    deliver on our proposals, when in fact it is no longer in our power to do so.
                    Instead we should aim to use any movement on their part towards us [as] a means
                    of paving the way to direct talks between them and the Salisbury Group—and if
                    that meant Joshua separating from <persName corresp="#p_MR_1">Mugabe</persName>,
                    he would be able to do it under the respectable umbrella of our proposals. But
                    in the absence of a clear indication that they are prepared to move towards us
                    in this way (or at least that Joshua is), I do not think that we should have
                    another meeting with them, at any level.</p>
                <p>I am sorry for this long letter but I think we should both be clear. I do not
                    believe the present Salisbury settlement is viable and I am very worried about
                    the situation outside the main centers, particularly in the Tribal Trust lands.
                    There are nearly five million people there and it was there that Bishop
                        <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Muzorewa</persName> rallied support and ensured
                    rejection of the 1971 proposals as being unacceptable to the people as a whole
                    (see the enclosed piece by Xan Smiley). Bishop <persName corresp="#p_MA_2"
                        >Muzorewa</persName> may well start to toughen his demands in the Salisbury
                    talks and we must watch closely his links with <persName corresp="#p_MR_1"
                        >Robert Mugabe</persName>. If the Salisbury talks fail, in part because of
                    our attempt to stiffen the terms, we must ensure that we are in a position to
                    unify all of the four Nationalist leaders behind our proposals, in which case we
                    would then only face Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName>. This is
                    another reason why we must not back off our proposals but, equally, why we must
                    not offend Bishop <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Muzorewa</persName>.</p>
                <p>I enclose a leader [<hi rend="italic">letter</hi>] from the New Statesman which
                    represents my views and mainstream Labour Party views.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d190fn3">Presumably the article by Smiley and letter in the <hi
                            rend="italic">New Statesman</hi> were attached to the original letter
                        delivered to the Department of State on February 26, which was not found.
                    </note> For your amusement, on the other side of the page is an account of what
                    it is like to have <pb facs="0588" n="551" xml:id="pg_551"/> one’s African
                    policy subjected to questions day by day in the House of Commons. We can and
                    will withstand domestic party political pressures.</p>
                <p>I will let you know what happens in the Middle East. With best wishes, yours
                    ever,</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ODA_1">David</persName>
                </p>
                <p>End text.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Vance</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
