<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>2. Memorandum From Henry J. Richardson of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Brzezinski))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-05-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-05-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005651"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monitoring</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recu3GH1ojKcJBA1c" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recAEL6tyPTrEjX4P" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004006618"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offshore oil</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039557"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Drilling</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-05-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-05-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="2"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d2">
                <head>2. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_RH_1">Henry J. Richardson</persName>
                    of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d2fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Staff Material, North/South, <persName corresp="#p_RH_1"
                            >Richardson</persName>, Chron File, Box 105, 4–5/77. Secret. Sent for
                        information.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-05-26">May 26, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">ALERT ITEM:</hi> Cuban Reinforcements Arriving in
                        Angola</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Summary</p>
                <p>Several trends in Angola are conjoining, creating a situation not now alarming
                    but which warrants scrutiny. Increases are now being noted in Cuban men and
                    materiel flowing into Angola, but on current information the purpose of this is
                    unclear. Close intelligence monitoring is underway. The intensity of and success
                    of insurgency activity in the south and in Cabinda has also increased, as has
                    friction between the Soviet/Cuban military-civilian adviser-occupation forces
                    and the Angolan civilian population. The Gulf Oil installation on Cabinda may be
                    in some danger of destruction by the <gloss target="#t_FLEC_1">FLEC</gloss>
                    liberation movement which enjoys local acquiescence among the population. Around
                    200 American and British nationals may be involved, and evacuation may be
                    required. The immediacy of this danger is unclear, however. The Cabinda
                    situation is now public knowledge.<note n="2" xml:id="d2fn2">The <hi
                            rend="italic">Chicago Tribune</hi> reported on the unrest in Cabinda in
                        a May 17 article entitled “Anti-Reds threaten to blow up Gulf Oil rigs in
                        Angola.” (<hi rend="italic">Chicago Tribune,</hi> May 17, 1977, p. 2)</note>
                </p>
                <p>The government is beseiged with serious problems, but cannot be said to now be in
                    danger of falling, notwithstanding dissent (with possible racial overtones) in
                        <gloss target="#t_MPLA_1">MPLA</gloss> ranks, as long as <persName
                        corresp="#p_CRF_1">Castro</persName> continues his current strong support of
                    the <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName> regime.</p>
                <p>This situation may furnish an opportunity for the US, in the context of the
                    present steady but not accelerated process toward normalizing <pb facs="0040"
                        n="3" xml:id="pg_3"/> relations with Angola, to arrive at exercising some
                    influence in Luanda while the Cubans and Soviets pay the freight. It would seem
                    to be in <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName>’s interest to move toward
                    us somewhat to give himself additional options, to open another channel to
                        <persName corresp="#p_MSS_1">Mobutu</persName>, and to lay the basis for
                    requesting badly needed US aid and ultimately technical assistance.</p>
                <p>The Nigerians, by virtue of the time and effort spent in their Angola-Zaire
                    mediating effort, and the Zambians would seem to have immediate interests in
                    maintaining <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName>’s stability, i.e., in
                    urging him to take positive action on the Cabinda and <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1"
                        >UNITA</gloss> situations, and in shoring up the Angolan economy.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Introduction</p>
                <p>There appears to be some dissent within the upper level <gloss target="#t_MPLA_1"
                        >MPLA</gloss> leadership as well as increased insurgency by
                    anti-governmental groups in Angola. Within the past few weeks Cuban flights to
                    Angola have been nzoticeably full and three Cuban convoys of ships have left for
                    Angola in the month of May alone.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Angolan-Cuban Friction</p>
                <p>Angolan dissatisfaction over Cuban and Soviet involvement there has grown in
                    recent months. Although Angolan President <persName corresp="#p_NA_1"
                        >Neto</persName> probably has good relations with top Cuban and Soviet
                    leadership, their substantial and continued presence in Angola has led to
                    increasing frictions at lower levels of the Angolan Government and society.
                    There are an estimated 10,000 to 14,500 Cuban military and civilian advisors in
                    Angola. Several hundred Soviet advisors and sizeable contingents from other East
                    European states are also there. The Cubans and Soviets are criticized for being
                    arrogant, monopolizing luxuries, being incompetent for the salaries paid them,
                    not fostering economic progress, and not eliminating the insurgent threat in
                    southern Angola and the exclave of Cabinda. Reportedly, Cuban troops have been
                    reluctant to actively pursue insurgents, and this has created additional
                    friction.</p>
                <p>While <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName> is undoubtedly aware of the
                    problems caused by continued Cuban and Soviet presence, he simply cannot afford
                    to reduce their role given Angola’s current economic difficulties and his
                    increasing dependence on the Cubans to maintain internal security and keep the
                    government functioning. <persName corresp="#p_CRF_1">Fidel Castro</persName>
                    apparently, however, remains committed to the preservation of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName> regime, and these reinforcements would
                    seem to confirm that. However, they may also be evidence of Cuba’s sinking into
                    a Viet-type quagmire.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Cuban Reinforcements</p>
                <p>The third Cuban convoy on the way to Luanda is currently under very close
                    intelligence surveillance. [<hi rend="italic">4 lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] coverage of the port
                    of Luanda is being arranged and further reports will be made.</p>
                <pb facs="0041" n="4" xml:id="pg_4"/>
                <p>The purpose for these three convoys is uncertain. There is a possibility that
                    this could be part of a large though normal rotation of Cuban troops accompanied
                    by shipments of new equipment.</p>
                <p>More probable is that these men and equipment are related to reinforcing Cuban
                    participation on the side of the <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName>
                    government against the insurgency by <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss> in
                    the South, against the insurgency by <gloss target="#t_FLEC_1">FLEC</gloss> on
                    Cabinda, against any problems generated by the apparent trickling back across
                    the Angolan-Zaire border of defeated Katangese, or Cuban participation in other
                    internal security duties for the Angolan Government, or all of the above. There
                    is tentative evidence, for example, that of the two-ship first convoy, one ship
                    docked in Cabinda and the other in Luanda.</p>
                <p>The ranking probability is that this activity is related to a felt Cuban need for
                    reinforcements in the <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss> and the Cabinda
                    situations. Neither of these have been going particularly well militarily for
                    the Angolans and Cubans recently: <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss> has
                    managed to at least temporarily interdict some food supply routes in the South;
                    and <gloss target="#t_FLEC_1">FLEC</gloss> appears the most disciplined and
                    effective military force on Cabinda, against Cubans, Angolans and Zairians, and
                    evidently controls over half of that territory with the acquiescence of the
                    local population.</p>
                <p>The latter raises a problem for the Gulf Oil installation on Cabinda, from which
                        <gloss target="#t_FLEC_1">FLEC</gloss> has demanded payment of royalties
                    otherwise flowing to Luanda, on threat of destroying the installation.
                    Unconfirmed reports are that some Gulf personnel have felt threatened enough to
                    seek safety on offshore oil drilling platforms, which are now also threatened.
                    It is unknown whether <gloss target="#t_FLEC_1">FLEC</gloss> actually possesses
                    the capability to carry out this threat, or the extent to which the installation
                    is effectively being protected by the Angolan/Cubans. Evacuation may be needed
                    here. Further, it seems important that Gulf have maximum flexibility relative to
                    its royalty payments in this situation. Such flexibility has in the past been a
                    key to the survival of that installation when Gulf was caught between the
                    Portuguese and the growing <gloss target="#t_MPLA_1">MPLA</gloss> liberation
                    movement.</p>
                <p>It must be emphasized that the information on the Cuban reinforcements and the
                    Cabinda situation discussed above is still tentative, and that the situation
                    remains under very close scrutiny.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">An Opportunity for the US</p>
                <p>While I believe it would be too much to say that the <persName corresp="#p_NA_1"
                        >Neto</persName> government is in danger of falling, especially with
                    continued Cuban/Soviet assistance, it is safe to say that he and his regime are
                    beseiged with very serious problems. This is especially the case in Cabinda from
                    which the Gulf installation furnishes a significant part of the country’s
                    revenues, and in the south where the <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss>
                    insurgency represents <pb facs="0042" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/> not only political
                    and military antagonism toward Luanda, but also tribal differences. The
                        <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName> regime has never come to terms
                    with the Ovimbundu peoples who are the mainstay of <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1"
                        >UNITA</gloss> support; there are reports of Soviet pressure on <persName
                        corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName> for him to open serious negotiations with
                        <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss> to stabilize the situation and
                    prevent further economic drain on the country. This apparently has not yet
                    occurred.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName> would not seem in a position to
                    eject the Soviets and the Cubans, even if he wanted to. Other possibilities are,
                    down the line after protracted negotiations, for some kind of shared
                    governmental arrangement with <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss>.
                        <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Neto</persName> still has <gloss
                        target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> and African recognition which would seem
                    unlikely to be withdrawn, especially since there is probably residual South
                    African support for <gloss target="#t_UNITA_1">UNITA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>He probably seeks normalization of relations with the US to, among other reasons,
                    give himself more options in the situation and to lay the basis for future
                    requests for US aid. It would seem profitable for us to continue the process of
                    normalizing relations, though not to accelerate it, and through that process
                    search out small and then larger opportunities for US leverage and influence in
                    Luanda. We would have to tread cautiously, acting positively in a guarded way,
                    while seeing whether the Soviets and the Cubans hang themselves. All of the
                    foregoing indicates that it is increasingly within <persName corresp="#p_NA_1"
                        >Neto</persName>’s interest to begin to slowly counterbalance ‘occupational
                    influence’, and this may be a situation where we can begin to be heard while the
                    Cubans and the Soviets pay the freight.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
