<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>252. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-12-17T10:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-12-17T12:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-12-17T12:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-12-17T10:30:00-05:00" n="252"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                <head>252. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d252fn1"
                        >Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material,
                        Subject File, Box 37, Memcons: President: 10–12/79. Secret. The meeting took
                        place in the White House Cabinet Room.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1979-12-17T10:30:00-05:00" to="1979-12-17T12:30:00-05:00">December
                            17, 1979, 10:30 a.m.–12:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The President’s Meeting with Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1"
                            >Margaret Thatcher</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>The Vice President</item>
                    <item>Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Cyrus Vance</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Zbigniew Brzezinski</persName>, Assistant
                        to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_ADL_1">David Aaron</persName>, Deputy Assistant to the
                        President for National Security Affairs</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BKJ_1">Kingman Brewster</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador at Large <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry Owen</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>George Vest, Assistant Secretary of State</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Robert D. Blackwill</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staff Member</item>
                    <item>Prime Minister of the United Kingdom <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Margaret
                            Thatcher</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Lord Carrington, UK Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth
                        Affairs</item>
                    <item>Sir Nicholas Henderson, Ambassador to the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >U.S.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Sir Robert Armstrong, Secretary to the Cabinet</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PSM_1">Sir Michael Palliser</persName>, Permanent
                        Under Secretary of State, Foreign and Commonwealth Office</item>
                    <item>Sir Frank Cooper, Ministry of Defense</item>
                    <item>Michael Alexander, Private Secretary to the <gloss target="#t_PM_1"
                            >PM</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>George Walden, Principal Secretary to the Secretary of State</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Omitted here is discussion unrelated to Rhodesia.]</p>
                <p>Moving on to Rhodesia, the President congratulated Lord Carrington for his
                    extraordinary success in the Lancaster House negotiation and said he was eager
                    to hear how prospects looked now after a slight interruption over the weekend.
                    We had lifted sanctions at midnight last night which was another indication that
                    the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> would continue to be Britain’s full
                    partner in this effort to bring peace to Southern <pb facs="0768" n="731"
                        xml:id="pg_731"/> Africa. The President added that there should be no
                    hesitation on Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName>’s part to
                    ask us for help in the period ahead, and we would do everything possible to be
                    responsive. (S)</p>
                <p>In reply, Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> said she was
                    delighted to be sitting in the White House; it was a great emotional experience
                    to be in the United States as Prime Minister for the first time. She thanked the
                    President for everything the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> had done on
                    Rhodesia, and especially for its efforts during the last few days. Noting that
                    Lord Carrington had done extremely well in the negotiations, the Prime Minister
                    indicated that the UK had come up against Patriotic Front hesitation at the last
                    moment over the weekend. But she was still hopeful and stressed that prompt
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> action in the last few days had been
                    important in trying to assure the success of the Lancaster House discussions.
                    (S)</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is discussion unrelated to Rhodesia.]</p>
                <p>The President next asked for the UK’s latest reading on the Rhodesian situation.
                    Lord Carrington replied that, as always, the last hurdle was the most difficult.
                    They had brought the Patriotic Front to agreement on a constitution, on
                    transitional arrangements and on the cease fire. The sticking point now was the
                    Patriotic Front’s assembly areas. These areas were around the outside of the
                    country and not in the middle. This seemed to be sensible since the Patriotic
                    Front did not wish to be surrounded by Rhodesian security forces. Britain wanted
                    to leave them where they were—on the outside areas of the country. With 17 or
                    18,000 Patriotic Front guerillas inside Rhodesia, Lord Carrington thought 15
                    assembly areas was about right. He said he was extremely surprised when the
                    Patriotic Front did not agree. Carrington thought that the Front was trying to
                    get a political advantage by putting more of its people in the center of the
                    country. This problem was particularly difficult to deal with since the
                    Patriotic Front argued that it had 35,000 troops inside Rhodesia, which the UK
                    knew to be untrue. (S)</p>
                <p>Nonetheless, and to try to find a compromise, Lord Carrington over the weekend
                    had offered the following: (1) if Britain found that it was wrong about the size
                    of the Patriotic Front force inside Rhodesia, it would reassess the situation
                    with a view to adding more assembly areas; and (2) it would now give the Front
                    an assembly area in the center of the country. Carrington thought these
                    proposals might do the trick. President <persName corresp="#p_MS_1"
                        >Machel</persName> had been particularly helpful by putting pressure on
                        <persName corresp="#p_MR_1">Mugabe</persName>. Carrington said that
                        <persName corresp="#p_NJ_1">Nkomo</persName> wanted to sign, but that
                        <persName corresp="#p_MR_1">Mugabe</persName> really did not want to sign.
                    The last word from London was that it appeared that there would be a majority
                    within the Patriotic Front to initial the final documents. Reflecting on
                    Britain’s negotiating style through the Lancaster House negotiations, Carrington
                    said that they had been forced to issue ultimatum after ultimatum all the while
                    indignantly denying that they were issuing ultimatums. But there was no other
                    way to bring the Patriotic Front around. (S)</p>
                <pb facs="0769" n="732" xml:id="pg_732"/>
                <p>Carrington thought that with a bit of luck we should get a cease fire, but even
                    then, the situation would be messy. Both sides were suspicious and it was
                    doubtful the Patriotic Front would assemble all their forces. We were
                    unquestionably in for a difficult period and it was important, Carrington said,
                    to hold the election as soon as possible. (S)</p>
                <p>The President asked if the <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Muzorewa</persName> group
                    was opposed to giving more assembly areas to the Patriotic Front or whether that
                    was a British position. Carrington replied that it was a bit of both. Salisbury
                    thought that a larger number of assembly areas would endanger their political
                    prospects. Nonetheless, Britain had agreed to give the Front one area in the
                    center of the country and would consider creating more areas if it was wrong
                    about the total number of Patriotic Front troops inside Rhodesia. (S)</p>
                <p>Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> added that, in general,
                    Salisbury had been quite helpful and had accepted the idea that the Patriotic
                    Front have an assembly area in the center of the country. The President asked if
                    the UK would set a deadline for the Patriotic Front’s acceptance of the
                    agreement. Carrington replied that he would not break up the conference although
                    the Patriotic Front might seek to make him do so. Whatever happened, Britain
                    would say that the Patriotic Front could join the process but the election
                    period would begin if the Front did not soon initial the agreement. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> asked if a problem would be
                    created by continued infiltration of Patriotic Front troops into Rhodesia during
                    the transition period. Lord Carrington replied that the Front would certainly
                    try, but that he hoped that <persName corresp="#p_MS_1">Machel</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_KK_1">Kaunda</persName> would stop it. The President
                    said that we were prepared to help Britain as this process continued. Carrington
                    noted that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> had been fair all the way
                    along, and the President responded that we thought so too. (S)</p>
                <p>Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1">Thatcher</persName> opined that <persName
                        corresp="#p_NJ_1">Nkomo</persName> was a natural politician but that
                        <persName corresp="#p_MR_1">Mugabe</persName> was a typical communist
                    obstructionist. The President asked if the Communists had been helpful in this
                    endeavor and Carrington responded that they had provided no help at all. Gromyko
                    had been decidedly hostile in his conversations with Carrington on the subject
                    and both the Soviets and Romanians had been supplying arms to the guerillas.
                    Carrington said there was a good reason for this. Trouble in Southern Africa
                    suited Soviet interests very well. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1"
                        >Brzezinski</persName> observed that it was odd that the Romanians had been
                    supplying arms to the Front. Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_TMH_1"
                        >Thatcher</persName> stressed that Britain would go ahead with the election
                    because that was the right thing to do. It would not be an easy task for
                        <persName corresp="#p_SBACJ_1">Christopher Soames</persName>, but the UK
                    would press on. She <pb facs="0770" n="733" xml:id="pg_733"/> then asked if the
                    President would like next to discuss the Middle East. (S)</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is discussion unrelated to Rhodesia.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
