<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-01-28T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-01-28T10:00:00-05:00" n="261" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                        <head>261. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d261fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                Brzezinski Material, Subject File, Box 33, Memcons: <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>: 1–9/77. Confidential.
                                The meeting took place at the White House.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-01-28T10:00:00-05:00">January 28, 1977, 10
                                    a.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Southern Africa</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">South Africa:</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">R. F.
                                            Botha</persName>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">
                                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>:</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Zbigniew Brzezinski</persName>,
                                        Assistant to the President for National Security
                                        Affairs</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> inquired whether Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> was related to the
                            General <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> of Boer War fame.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> replied that he was.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> related that as a
                            child he had refought the war many times with his toy soldiers, and had
                            always been on the side of the Boers. <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> replied that he was happy to hear it. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> then added: “I’m always in
                            favor of national liberation movements—consistently”. <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> replied “I’m not so happy to
                            hear that”.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> explained that his purpose
                            in coming to see <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> was
                            to tell him that South Africa feels that “we’ve been let down by the <pb facs="0790" n="753" xml:id="pg_753"/> Americans”, and why. Out of
                            last year’s extended conversations in Germany, Switzerland, etc., had
                            come a series of papers which constituted “at least an understanding, at
                            most an agreement”. As far as South Africa was concerned these were not
                            British proposals but were a joint British-American effort. They
                            culminated in the well known 5-Point Plan<note n="2" xml:id="d261fn2">The Five Point Plan is included in Tab 1 to <ref target="#d264">Document 264</ref>.</note> which was “typed on American
                            typewriters”. Two points were not spelled out, and were included in
                            brackets. These concerned the proposal for white ministers in the two
                            security positions, and a white Chairman of the Council of Ministers.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> acknowledged that
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> made no promises
                            on these at the meeting in Pretoria where he, <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> and Volster were all
                                present.<note n="3" xml:id="d261fn3">See <ref target="frus1969-76v28#d206">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol.
                                    XXVIII, Southern Africa, Document 206</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>At that meeting, <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> said,
                                <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> accepted the 5-Point
                            Plan in principle. It was a very painful, solemn, but “touching and
                            sincere” meeting. Upon reading the plan, <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> turned to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and said “so you want me to sign my own death
                            note”. But <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> emphasized that
                            whatever happened later, at that time <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> did accept the 5-Point Plan as the basis for
                            serious negotiations.</p>
                        <p>A few days later, the American Embassy informed the South African
                            government that the plan could now include the two bracketed points, and
                            again according to <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName>, the
                            new version was typed at the American Embassy. The Americans gave the
                            South Africans and the Rhodesians “no warnings, no caveats” that this
                            would be anything other than a bona fide negotiation plan. <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> accepted this and presented the
                            5-Point Plan unchanged in his statement of September 24. But just a few
                            days later the African front-line Presidents met, and started to shoot
                            down these proposals.<note n="4" xml:id="d261fn4">See <ref target="frus1969-76v28#d212">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol.
                                    XXVIII, Southern Africa, Document 212</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> then talked at length of
                            the key South African concern that a plan be developed which would allow
                            for an interim period so that the Rhodesian economy could be kept
                            intact. Otherwise, Rhodesia’s fate would resemble Mozambique’s which is
                            now dependent upon South Africa for food, energy and other forms of
                            support. If the Rhodesian economy is not preserved, then whoever comes
                            to power there—black or white—will simply have to depend on some outside
                            nation for economic help, and there still will not be African rule.</p>
                        <p>Concerning the present status of negotiations, <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> said “there is no way we can get
                            out of this unless an agreement <hi rend="italic">is</hi> an agreement.”
                            He urged that the Americans require all sides to stick to what they
                            agree to. Only in this way can the government of South Africa play a
                            constructive role in holding <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> to his agreement. But if Americans <pb facs="0791" n="754" xml:id="pg_754"/> continue to “tell blacks that you want
                            peace at all costs, they will keep raising the price.” South Africa will
                            not break its word. But now, “you are missing golden opportunities for
                            peace.” <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> closed by
                            emphasizing again that the only way to stop further Russian intrusion in
                            Africa is through economic growth, and therefore through a gradual
                            transition to majority rule that will not damage the Rhodesian
                            economy.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> replied that he was
                            grateful to <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> for sharing
                            his thoughts so openly with him, and emphasized that he cannot engage in
                            negotiations since that is the job of the Secretary of State. However,
                            he wanted to put the conversation in a broader historical context. He
                            sees the problem in the Southern African arc as a case of adjustments to
                            changing political and social conditions coming too late. If you compare
                            Mozambique for example, to Nigeria or the Ivory Coast or Senegal, the
                            difference is that in the latter case historical trends were understood
                            and anticipated, while in Mozambique they were resisted until too late.
                            The lesson for us all, and for South Africa in particular, is that we do
                            live in a world of extraordinary change. The United States cannot afford
                            to become involved in a struggle where objectively or subjectively it
                            would be seen as being against blacks, nor would it accept a position
                            where our policies would force blacks into an alliance with
                            communists.</p>
                        <p>He remarked that we must remember that the aspirations of the Southern
                            African blacks are “fundamentally legitimate” even if certain
                            individuals may seem too radical or ill prepared to govern. The problem
                            with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> is that for years
                            he has resisted these legitimate goals. This is why we have to take into
                            account the mood of the African blacks.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> emphasized that if
                            the black-white struggle in Southern Africa also becomes a red-white
                            conflict “it will be a disaster”. He added that no one in South Africa
                            should be under the illusion that if this happens we will side with the
                            whites against the blacks simply because that would be the anti-red
                            position. <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> answered that
                            “we have no illusions”. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> replied that he understood that, but believed
                            that Salisbury may harbour illusions, and this would be very dangerous.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> emphasized that
                            “the longer this goes on, the greater the chance for the two conflicts
                            to interlock”. There is no opportunity for too many more delays. He
                            closed by adding that <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName>
                            should understand that his position on Southern Africa was “not divorced
                            from the human dimension” or from his personal admiration for the
                            historical role of the South African whites—referring again to his
                            opening remarks.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> remarked that he
                            understood what <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> was
                            saying, but that he did not feel that Americans fully appreciated the
                            South African “fear of domination”. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> replied that that was probably true, but that
                            the South Africans should understand the overriding <pb facs="0792" n="755" xml:id="pg_755"/> need for accommodation. “Once you begin to
                            see the radicalization of your younger black generations it will be too
                            late”. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> added that
                            from his own historical studies, he believes that once an urban working
                            class acquires political consciousness the momentum is too great to
                            stop.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> turned to the subject of
                            Namibia, saying that he believes that there is real hope for peace, but
                            “we won’t be able to turn the territory over to <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss>—no one could survive that in South
                            Africa”.</p>
                        <p>He closed with a very strong appeal to South African nationalism. “In
                            South Africa we have never shared power. We fought the British, and our
                            nationalism now is as strong as ever. We will do it again. We do not
                            fear to fight as long as we don’t have to fight the Russians. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> asked: “But who’s going to
                            keep them out?” <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> replied
                            “if necessary we will raise an army of a million men—black and white”.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> said yes, they
                            could do that, but isn’t it a “grim prospect”. <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> did not reply. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> finished the conversation
                            by urging <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> that his
                            government make sure that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> has no illusions as to American intentions. He
                            urged the need to “make it clear to <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> once and for all” that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> will never intervene in the conflict on the side of a
                            minority white government, even if the communists were involved.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>