<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-12-29T20:26:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-12-29T20:26:00-05:00" n="350" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d350">
                        <head>350. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in South
                                Africa<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d350fn1">Source: Carter
                                Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Cables
                                File, State Department Out, Box 114, 12/15–31/78. Secret; Sensitive;
                                Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Sent for
                                information to the White House. Printed from a copy that was
                                received in the White House Situation Room.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-12-30T01:26:00+00:00">December 30, 1978, 0126Z</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>327068. For the Ambassador. Subject: Further Nuclear Talks. Ref: Pretoria
                                7631.<note n="2" xml:id="d350fn2">In telegram 7631 from Pretoria,
                                December 29, <persName corresp="#p_EWB_1">Edmondson</persName>
                                noted: “With the Namibian question very much up in the air in the
                                next few weeks, I do not believe this is a good time to encourage
                                    <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> to begin further talks on
                                the nuclear issue.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D780538–0524)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>1. It has now been six months since the <persName corresp="#p_SI_1">Smith</persName> talks. While the <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> has come back to us in the meantime for clarifications,
                            which we have supplied, it has avoided giving us a definite response to
                            our proposals for a nuclear settlement.</p>
                        <p>2. [<hi rend="italic">4 lines not declassified</hi>] instituting a
                            safeguards regime with a possible stockpile of HEU of unknown size would
                            present clear political and technical difficulties.</p>
                        <p>3. In these circumstances, we think it important to determine whether the
                                <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> is serious in entertaining our
                            proposals, or whether it is simply stretching out the negotiations for
                            other purposes. Delay also reduces the credibility of our effort to
                            resolve the uncertainties of SA’s nuclear intentions through negotiation
                            and cooperation.</p>
                        <p>4. In light of the above, we are contemplating asking the Secretary to
                            approve an early approach to the <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss>.
                            The purpose of an approach would be to determine to what extent the
                                <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> is willing to cooperate on the
                            nuclear issue and, hopefully, to obtain a clearer indication of its
                            specific intention to adhere to the <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss>
                            and accept safeguards at Valindaba.</p>
                        <p>5. If the <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss>’s response to this
                            approach indicated that our non-proliferation objectives are attainable,
                            we would consider as a second step what steps we might appropriately
                            take to accelerate the settlement process.</p>
                        <p>6. The approach we contemplate would be along the following lines:</p>
                        <p>—You will recall that in June both sides stressed the urgency of
                            resolving the nuclear issues set forth in the Joint Minute<note n="3" xml:id="d350fn3">See <ref target="#d344">Document 344</ref>.</note>
                            and expressed <pb facs="1107" n="1070" xml:id="pg_1070"/> the hope that
                            the necessary decisions could be taken within two months of that
                            time.</p>
                        <p>—The communication we received in September was inconclusive, did not
                            lead to the implementation foreseen in the Joint Minute, and in fact
                            raised issues we thought had been clarified earlier.<note n="4" xml:id="d350fn4">See <ref target="#d348">Document 348</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>—Moreover, since September we have provided a team of your legal experts
                            detailed briefings and documentation on all aspects of the
                            Non-Proliferation Act, ancillary procedures, and administrative
                            regulations. We have also supplied a draft text of a revised nuclear
                            cooperation agreement. We have indicated our willingness to discuss
                            further the technical aspects of an interim safeguards development
                            program at Valindaba.</p>
                        <p>—My government is most concerned that our extensive exchanges over the
                            past year have not brought us to a nuclear agreement.</p>
                        <p>—Continuing delay compounds uncertainties regarding operation of the
                            Valindaba plant. Our concerns will be shared by others familiar with Dr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_RAJ_1">Roux</persName>’s recent statement in
                            the US press that Valindaba is capable of producing highly enriched
                            uranium. (FYI: Reference is to Washington Post article,<note n="5" xml:id="d350fn5">“South Africa’s Pilot Enrichment Plant,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, December 5, 1978, p.
                                A16.</note> pouched to you earlier.)</p>
                        <p>—There is serious question under these circumstances as to whether a
                            nuclear settlement reached only after substantial further delay would be
                            in the interests of the US or would resolve continuing international
                            concern regarding South Africa’s nuclear intentions.</p>
                        <p>—In view of the above and since, as Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SGC_1">Smith</persName> pointed out in the June
                            discussions, time is of the essence in our nuclear proposals, we need
                            very soon (FYI: we would have in mind a couple of weeks) your
                            government’s decision on whether to enter the nuclear settlement set
                            forth in the Joint Minute.</p>
                        <p>7. Reftel reached us as we were preparing the above proposal. In light of
                            your concern regarding timing of further nuclear talks, but also taking
                            into account our concerns enumerated above, we would very much like to
                            have soonest your considered judgment as to whether <pb facs="1108" n="1071" xml:id="pg_1071"/> or not we should go ahead with an
                            approach to the <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> along the lines
                            described in para 6.<note n="6" xml:id="d350fn6">In telegram 7665 from
                                Pretoria, December 30, Edmonson counseled a delay until at least
                                February. He held: “More fundamentally, even taking into account our
                                nuclear concerns, I believe it would be wisest to make our approach
                                after we have a better idea as to whether we have indeed been
                                successful in getting the <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> to
                                move ahead with the implementation of <gloss target="#t_UNSC_1">UNSC</gloss> Resolution 435 on Namibia. If we are having
                                difficulty on Namibia, it may be difficult to get the <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> to focus on nuclear matters
                                rationally and it will be much harder for us to be forthcoming on
                                matters necessary to get a nuclear agreement. If Namibian matters
                                appear to be hanging in the balance, it might be best not to press
                                them on the nuclear issue. On the other hand, if Namibia is going
                                badly and we are concerned at the passage of time, we might decide
                                to take a much harder stand on the nuclear issue, clearly indicating
                                that we cannot hold our offer open if they have not committed
                                themselves to accept it in time for approval by the present session
                                of Parliament (which ends in June).” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                P840139–2128)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1"><hi rend="strong">Newsom</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>