<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>49. Telegram From the Embassy in South Africa to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d49</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">49</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-04-07T13:07:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-04-07T13:07:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec8uqG4zFwFzxdlO" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104422"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Demarche</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-04-07T13:07:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-04-07T13:07:00-05:00" n="49"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                <head>49. Telegram From the Embassy in South Africa to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d49fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D770121–1115. Confidential; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1"
                            >Exdis</gloss>. Sent for information to London, Paris, Bonn, Ottawa, and
                        Pretoria. Sent for information Immediate to <gloss target="#t_USUN_1"
                            >USUN</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Cape Town</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-04-07T18:07:00+00:00">April 7, 1977, 1807Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>521. Subj: Meeting With <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM </gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> on Namibia. Ref: Cape Town
                        0519;<note n="2" xml:id="d49fn2">In telegram 519 from Cape Town, April 7,
                        the Embassy notified the Department that the aide-mémoire was delivered to
                            <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> at 4 p.m. (National
                        Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                        File, D770121–0907) The aide-mémoire is printed as Tab A, <ref target="#d50"
                            >Document 50</ref>.</note> State 076299<note n="3" xml:id="d49fn3">In
                        telegram 76299 to Cape Town, April 6, the Department approved the language
                        for questions and press guidance. (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D770119–0034)</note> and previous.</p>
                <p>1. This message covers the highlights of an hour-long meeting with <gloss
                        target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> at which I handed him aide
                    memoire and made oral points on behalf of the five governments. He was
                    accompanied by <gloss target="#t_FonMin_1">FonMin</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> and <gloss target="#t_DFA_1"
                        >DFA</gloss> Secy <persName corresp="#p_FBG_1">Brand Fourie</persName>. In a
                    separate message there will follow my assessment of the meeting.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d49fn4">In telegram 526 from Cape Town, April 8, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BWG_1">Bowdler</persName> gave his assessment of the
                        meeting. He noted that <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> faced
                        two limitations to “call the tune,” in Namibia: the need for the white
                        population to accept what the Turnhalle does and the awareness that he must
                        retain the cooperation of the non-white delegation. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BWG_1">Bowdler</persName> suggested that it might be better
                        to seek fulfillment of UN Security Council Resolution 385 (see <ref
                            target="#d50fn3">footnote 3, Document 50</ref>) after the interim
                        government was set up. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D770123–0455)</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. After reading the aide memoire carefully and listening to the oral
                        points,<note n="5" xml:id="d49fn5">
                        <p>In telegram 1000 from <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss>, April 2,
                            the Mission provided instructions for the Namibian démarche. The
                            spokesman for the Five was instructed to make the following points
                            orally to <persName corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName>: “The Five
                            Governments are convinced that an internationally acceptable settlement
                            to the Namibian problem must be found urgently.</p>
                        <p>“The Five are prepared to work with South Africa in finding such a
                            solution. The views of the Five Governments on the nature of a
                            settlement are contained in the aide memoire.</p>
                        <p>“The Five Governments urge a prompt response and are prepared as a group
                            to enter into discussions with the South African Government to consider
                            its response and to work with South Africa towards a solution consistent
                            with Security Council Resolution 385.” (National Archives, <gloss
                                target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                            D770114–0052)</p>
                    </note>
                    <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss> reacted by saying that “to put it mildly, he
                    found this approach very strange indeed.” Showing considerable irritation, which
                    continued throughout the meeting, he made these points about the document:</p>
                <p>A) You talk about self-determination through a fully democratic process. After
                    watching the Turnhalle process for two years, now you tell us that it is not
                    good enough.</p>
                <pb facs="0147" n="110" xml:id="pg_110"/>
                <p>B) You speak of supervision of the United Nations. There is the whole history of
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EAM_1">Escher</persName> sent out by the <gloss
                        target="#t_UNSYG_1">UNSYG</gloss> as his representative to work with us on
                        <gloss target="#t_SWA_1">SWA</gloss>.<note n="6" xml:id="d49fn6">See <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v28#d73">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, vol. XXVIII,
                            Southern Africa, Document 73</ref>.</note> After reaching certain
                    understandings with him, he returned to New York but we heard nothing further
                    from the <gloss target="#t_SYG_1">SYG</gloss>.</p>
                <p>C) You call for an end to <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> administration in
                        <gloss target="#t_SWA_1">SWA</gloss>. Our attitude on this is very clear and
                    has been repeated many times. We have said that we want to end our
                    administration of the territory.</p>
                <p>D) Regarding political prisoners, he was not aware of any political prisoners
                    being held in <gloss target="#t_SWA_1">SWA</gloss>. If you refer to people
                    convicted by the courts as common criminals, these fall outside the terms of
                    your note.</p>
                <p>E) With respect to people returning to <gloss target="#t_SWA_1">SWA</gloss>, he
                    found this very strange since there is no hindrance to people coming back,
                    including <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss> people. Why do your
                    governments bring this up? They know this, or don’t they want to know?</p>
                <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> then entered the discussion
                    focusing first on lack of Western recognition for what the <gloss
                        target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> had done and then expressing dismay over the
                    fifth paragraph of the aide memoire which he described as a “veiled threat.” He
                    referred to the <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>-<persName
                        corresp="#p_VBJ_1">Vorster</persName> talks on Namibia in which our position
                    was described as “extremely reasonable.”<note n="7" xml:id="d49fn7">See <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v28#d206fn4">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. XXVIII,
                            Southern Africa, footnote 4, Document 206</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> said <gloss target="#t_SAG_1"
                        >SAG</gloss> willing to be reasonable but will not be hammered. Much of
                    subsequent conversation centered around this paragraph with <gloss
                        target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1"
                        >Botha</persName> referring to it as “obnoxious” and “unnecessary” given the
                        <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> stated position that it was prepared to
                    talk about these matters as reflected in the response to the <gloss
                        target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>–9 demarche and in <persName corresp="#p_BRF_1"
                        >Botha</persName>’s recent conversation with President <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>.<note n="8" xml:id="d49fn8">See <ref
                            target="#d269">Document 269</ref>.</note> At one point <persName
                        corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName> suggested that the paragraph be revised
                    but the <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss> did not support him on this.</p>
                <p>4. In the face of the <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss>’s and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BRF_1">Botha</persName>’s criticisms of the aide memoire, their
                    efforts to draw us into a discussion of substantive points, and questioning of
                    the motive in making a demarche with the “veiled threat,” I made the following
                    points at various stages in the conversation, supported by my colleagues:</p>
                <p>A) The aide memoire represents a sincere effort to open a new stage of
                    discussions looking toward a solution consistent with Resolution 385. Without
                    entering into polemics, the unacceptability of Turnhalle has been known to the
                        <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> for some time.</p>
                <pb facs="0148" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/>
                <p>B) The proposal for discussions should be looked at as part of the effort to
                    avoid confrontation in the UN with adverse effects for South Africa.</p>
                <p>C) We were not in a position to discuss substantive points in a possible
                    settlement, this being a matter better left to the proposed discussions.</p>
                <p>D) We could not tell him how the proposed discussions would be conducted, this
                    being a point on which we expected further guidance from our capitals in the
                    near future. In the meantime, we hoped for a prompt response to the aide
                    memoire.</p>
                <p>E) No one was proposing that <gloss target="#t_SWA_1">SWA</gloss> be turned over
                    to <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss> which my government does not
                    recognize as the sole representative authority of Namibia, but that all
                    political groups should be allowed to participate peacefully in determining
                    Namibia’s future, including <gloss target="#t_SWAPO_1">SWAPO</gloss>.</p>
                <p>6. In the end the <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss> said he was prepared to give
                    his response to the aide memoire right away. He put it in these terms: “We are
                    prepared and have always been prepared to have realistic discussions—as with the
                        <gloss target="#t_UNSYG_1">UNSYG</gloss> and naturally with your
                    governments—but as far as <gloss target="#t_SWA_1">SWA</gloss> is concerned, we
                    are not <gloss target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> not taking any decisions on their
                    behalf. We have not interfered with the Turnhalle Conference and cannot stop its
                    momentum. We cannot and will not prescribe for the people of <gloss
                        target="#t_SWA_1">SWA</gloss>. It is their country and their future. Within
                    this framework I am prepared to enter into discussions with whoever wants to
                    discuss <gloss target="#t_SWA_1">SWA</gloss> in a constructive spirit. It was
                    not necessary to threaten us to come to this point. I shall expect to hear from
                    your governments where and when the discussions will take place.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWG_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Bowdler</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
