<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>162. Memorandum From Gary Sick of the National Security Council Staff to the
                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National Security
                    Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d162</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">162</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-01-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-01-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003007715"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hostages</term>
                    <term ref="rec2ojF1nU3Lvcn3X" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Kurds</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recdZke2uFUGdGg1d" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="rubber" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85115631" lcsh-match="exact">Rubber</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-01-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-01-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="162"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d162">
                <head>162. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SG_1">Gary Sick</persName> of the
                    National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d162fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> Material, Country
                        File, Box 30, Iran 1/11/80–1/31/80. Secret. A stamped notation in the upper
                        right corner of the memorandum reads: “<gloss target="#t_ZB_1">ZB</gloss>
                        has seen.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-01-24">January 24, 1980</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Iran</item>
                </list>
                <p>We are approaching a new point in our relationship with Iran where some
                    fundamental choices must be faced. Our basic dilemma can be defined as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>—With the Soviet threat to Iran growing more explicit (and given our new level of
                    commitment in the area) we will have a greater interest in propping up <hi
                        rend="italic">any</hi> anti-communist regime in Tehran, and there will be a
                    growing inclination to try to fashion a cooperative relationship with the
                        <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName> regime after a new
                    president is elected;</p>
                <p>—But the very presence of the <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName>
                    regime lends itself to continued collapse of the society, the danger of civil
                    war, and the very real risk that the left will capitalize on the foibles of the
                    present leadership to strengthen its position for a takeover from within.</p>
                <p>The questions we must ask ourselves at this point are:</p>
                <p>1. Is the <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName> regime salvageable? Is
                    it capable of evolving over time into a government which provides even the
                    minimal level of internal stability and self-defense capability?</p>
                <p>2. Is the risk of a communist takeover in Iran greater from an actual Soviet
                    intervention, or is the greater risk an internal growth of leftist power?</p>
                <p>3. How can we simultaneously seek to get the hostages back, bolster an
                    anti-communist regime, and strengthen Iran’s capability to resist a possible
                    Soviet intervention?</p>
                <p>In my view, the regime in Iran is perilously close to total collapse. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName> is committed to an unrealistic vision
                    of a pure Islamic society, but he is leaving the organizational work to God. He
                    is an old man, physically unwell, and totally lacking in any practical sense of
                    how to manage anything, let alone a major nation. The people of Iran were
                    thrilled at his leadership in bringing down the Shah, but fundamentally they do
                    not share his vision. As time goes on, the gap between his image and the reality
                    of governmental chaos have become increasingly <pb facs="0477" n="428"
                        xml:id="pg_428"/> apparent, and his support is waning. His hospitalization
                    will reinforce the sense of uncertainty and drift. It will remind everyone of
                    his mortality and the absence of any structure to provide continuity if he is
                    incapacitated.</p>
                <p>The process of seeking alternative to <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                        >Khomeini</persName>’s leadership was already well underway, and it is
                    gaining momentum daily. The Kurds will not be reconciled with him. They have
                    learned they cannot trust him and they are naturally inclined to grasp such
                    moments to assert their own nationalistic aspirations. Azerbaijan is simmering
                    just below the level of full scale rebellion. It is only the uncertainty of
                    Shariatmadari’s status—and the possibility that he might be harmed—which
                    restrains them from even more overt opposition. <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                        >Khomeini</persName> has met their demands with naked force and contempt.
                    They are not going to be wooed back into his fold. The other tribes—<persName
                        corresp="#p_QNK_1">Qashqai</persName>, Baluchi, Khuzistan Arabs—recognize
                    weakness when they see it, and their open opposition to the central regime is
                    the best evidence of how they view the prospects of the present regime.</p>
                <p>The regime itself is a collection of second-rate, venal, power hungry,
                    self-centered, inexperienced and disreputable individuals. There is not a good
                    mind or a good idea in the lot. The power struggles which at first were hidden
                    beneath a superficial unity have now emerged into public view. One of the
                    current rumors in Tehran is that the Forgan assassination group<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d162fn2">Purported to be a religious extremist assassination group
                        that followed the teachings of Ali Shariati. The leader, Akbar Goudarzi,
                        reportedly was arrested January 8. (Report by <gloss target="#t_UN_1"
                            >UN</gloss> High Commissioner for Refugees, February 1, 1999;
                        www.unhcr.org)</note> in fact does not exist at all—it is the invention of
                    the ruling mullahs for their own political assassinations. No one in Tehran
                    today believes that Ayatollah Taleghani died a natural death. Rather, he is
                    considered to have been too much of a rival to <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                        >Khomeini</persName> and was quietly dispensed with. The fact that these
                    rumors have credibility is unmistakable evidence of the decay of the
                    revolutionary elite.</p>
                <p>People have seen mullah rule, and they are appalled. <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                        >Khomeini</persName>’s son-in-law is rumored to be exporting large amounts
                    of money to Swiss accounts. The level of bribery and corruption extends from the
                    lowest level (where the local mullahs and komiteh members “borrow” cars,
                    furnishings and bank accounts of their opponents) to the very top. Nothing in
                    the performance of the present regime has given any basis for encouragement
                    about the future.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName> insists on retaining all power
                    to himself. He makes pronouncements and expects them to be carried out according
                    to his vision. When things go wrong, he fires those most directly involved—or
                    those who have been fingered by the members of his court. As a result, <pb
                        facs="0478" n="429" xml:id="pg_429"/> everyone shuns responsibility and all
                    the “officials” of the government and the Revolutionary Council spend all their
                    waking hours (and probably their nightmares as well) scheming about how to
                    maintain <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName>’s personal support.
                    This is about the best we can expect so long as <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                        >Khomeini</persName> is alive. Ironically, if he dies, the game will return
                    to square one and it will be every man for himself.</p>
                <p>In the meantime, the left is organizing itself. The <gloss target="#t_Tudeh_1"
                        >Tudeh</gloss> Party expects <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                        >Khomeini</persName>’s imminent collapse and is positioning itself to
                    inherit as much of the wreckage as possible. If the present chaos drags on, the
                    left will continue to ingratiate itself with <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                        >Khomeini</persName> as one of the few reliable bastions of support, and he
                    will be forced to rely on them more and more heavily.</p>
                <p>The presidential elections will probably change very little. The election will be
                    boycotted by major sections of the population, and the remainder will probably
                    split according to personalities. Any president, even if elected by a genuine
                    majority, will find himself in the same position as poor old <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_1">Bazargan</persName>—and the new president’s fate is likely
                    to be about the same. <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName> will not
                    brook real independence, so the new president will either have to be a total
                    rubber stamp or he will have to set about building an independent power base.
                    The latter is more likely, but it is also dangerous to the health—politically
                    and otherwise.</p>
                <p>The threat of internal collapse and the emergence of the left as the dominant
                    power strikes me as much more imminent and likely than an actual Soviet military
                    intervention. Any prolongation of <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                        >Khomeini</persName>’s faltering regime only increases that risk. Our
                    objective should be to hasten the downfall of the present regime. We need not do
                    much actively, for it is falling of its own weight. But we should beware of
                    taking tactical steps in the context of the Soviet invasion which artificially
                    breathe new life into the present leadership and give the Iranian public the
                    false impression that there may be more there than meets the eye.</p>
                <p>They are troubled by sanctions. We should use that weapon, and reinforce it with
                    some hype and propaganda. It undercuts the credibility of the mullah rule and it
                    puts pressure on them where they feel it—in their domestic support.</p>
                <p>We should continue with our contacts with dissident groups. Our objective should
                    be to encourage those groups who have real influence—particularly those in
                    Azerbaijan which stand between Tehran and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> and who have the manpower, talent and political determination
                    to provide some kind of alternative regime. They also have an invaluable
                    religious asset in Shariatmadari, and a network of fellow Azeris in key
                    positions throughout the country, including the military.</p>
                <p>We need not delude ourselves into thinking that we can mastermind a countercoup.
                    That would be both infeasible and historically <pb facs="0479" n="430"
                        xml:id="pg_430"/> foolish. But we can quietly promote some degree of
                    cooperation among various key groups and assist them to communicate among
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>We can also help to promote political ideas which promise Iran something more
                    than the obeisance to personality. Where is a program? Who has any political
                    ideas which go beyond just getting themselves elected to the highest possible
                    office? If there are such people or such ideas, we should make sure they get the
                    widest possible exposure.</p>
                <p>We need to build an alternative to the left. Obviously we cannot do this
                    ourselves, but more and more Iranians are thinking exactly this way, and we have
                    some ability to reinforce it through intelligent propaganda and selective
                    support. Although this appears to be a long-term strategy, it may in fact
                    develop much more quickly than we think if the present regime simply folds up—as
                    it may. If nothing else, the clear acceptance of that objective as a policy goal
                    would provide a structure to our thinking about the future of Iran which is now
                    lacking.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
