<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="176" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                        <head>176. Memorandum From the White House Chief of Staff (<persName corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName>) to President <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d176fn1">Source: Carter Library, Office of the Chief of
                                Staff, <persName corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName>’s Confidential
                                Files, Box 34, Iran 2/80. Eyes Only. <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> initialed “C” in the upper right corner of
                                the memorandum.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-02-04">February 4, 1980</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I hope that you will have a chance to review this before our 2:00 meeting
                            on the hostage situation.<note n="2" xml:id="d176fn2">According to the
                                President’s Daily Diary, <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ADL_1">Aaron</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName> from 1:58 until 2:22 p.m. (Carter Library) In
                                his memoir, <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> wrote that
                                the purpose of the meeting was “to get an update on the Iranian
                                response.” “Apparently,” he wrote, “<persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> is sending word to us directly that he
                                wants to proceed with a resolution of the hostage question. His
                                inclination is to wait until after the 26th of February, when he can
                                put his government together. (He also said he wanted to get rid of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>.) He
                                    [<persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>] does not
                                want us to identify him as a friend of the United States or as a
                                moderate. He wants to be known as a revolutionary protecting the
                                interests of Iran against both superpowers’ threats. We decided to
                                maintain our multiple approaches to Iran.” (<persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Keeping
                                    Faith</hi>, p. 485) For <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>’s message, see <ref target="#d175">Document 175</ref>.</note> It may be a bit disjointed, but
                            analyzes frankly the situation that we face.</p>
                        <p>Our objective continues to be to get the hostages out safely at the
                            earliest possible date without having to take risks that are
                            unacceptable. If anything, our objective has been modified since the
                            Afghanistan invasion to include, “and in a way that does not jeopardize
                            the possibility of a reconciliation of US-Iranian relations”.<note n="3" xml:id="d176fn3">The quoted phrase represents <persName corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName>’s perception of how the
                                December 27 Finding had changed. See <ref target="#d110">Document
                                    110</ref>.</note> Politically, I believe that we continue to
                            have some flexibility on what we are able to do in the course of working
                            toward the release of the hostages. The American people will tolerate a
                            good deal more now than they would have before the Soviet invasion of
                            Afghanistan IF we have the successful resolution of the hostage
                            situation.</p>
                        <p>Let me review briefly what we know for a fact and those things that we
                            are not sure of:</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">That in the final analysis, only <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName> can insure the safe
                                release of the hostages</hi>. It is doubtful that <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> can get the militants to
                            release them and very, very doubtful that <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> can get them released.</p>
                        <p>2. That a large number of the Revolutionary Council—possibly all—see the
                            need to resolve the hostage situation, and that this includes the
                            clerics as well as the “European group”.</p>
                        <p>3. That at least among the European group and other members of the
                            Revolutionary Council, a clear consensus is emerging as to <hi rend="italic">how</hi> the <pb facs="0511" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/>
                            situation should be resolved. It recognizes that the Shah will not be
                            returned, but places special emphasis on the international tribunal, the
                            right of Iran to seek extradition of the Shah, to seek the legal
                            recovery of his “stolen monies” and public statements from the United
                            States that suggest that we are willing to develop a relationship which
                            acknowledges both the “equality” of Iran and is based on “mutual
                            respect”.</p>
                        <p>4. That political factors and personal animosity between <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> have possibly resulted in a
                            situation whereby although there is general consensus as to “how”, there
                            is not a consensus as to “who” or “when”. <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> wants to do it quickly and be personally
                            involved for obvious reasons, and <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> prefers to wait until after he takes power (at
                            least that is the message from the Egyptian which we need to
                                confirm).<note n="4" xml:id="d176fn4">See <ref target="#d175">Document 175</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>5. That although <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> is
                            personally unpopular, he probably has the support of Beheshti and other
                            members of the Revolutionary Council who are against <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> for other reasons. It is
                            impossible to discern as to whether the support for <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> reflects a desire to
                            resolve the situation quickly or whether they simply want to deprive
                                <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> of the personal
                            satisfaction of resolving it when he takes over.</p>
                        <p>6. That while <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> might
                            not like <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>, he has let
                            us know through two very direct channels—Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_NAR_1">Nobari</persName> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LE_1">Lang</persName> that we were to continue to deal
                            with <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>, but that he
                            wanted to be kept informed. He probably recognizes the reality of the
                            situation, and while not liking it is reconciled to it.</p>
                        <p>7. That while the Foreign Minister is disliked by almost everyone, those
                            same people recognize that he has a personal relationship with <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName> that cannot be ignored or
                            taken lightly.</p>
                        <p>It seems to me that the following is and should be our posture:</p>
                        <p>—That we should continue to pursue an early release of the hostages
                            through <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>, but not at
                            the expense of our relationship with <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>.</p>
                        <p>—That we should keep <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>
                            informed of our activities.</p>
                        <p>—That if it ever became a choice of having to choose between <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>, we would have to go with
                                <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>.</p>
                        <p>—That we should work to try to avoid that choice by a reconciliation of
                            their views, in this respect the French contacts are invaluable.</p>
                        <p>—That to put <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> on “hold”
                            now has a number of problems for us:</p>
                        <pb facs="0512" n="463" xml:id="pg_463"/>
                        <quote><p>1. We cannot make a conscious decision to wait until after
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> takes office
                                in late February to try to resolve the present crisis.</p>
                            <p>2. The delay also risks the chance that something could happen to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName>, who by all
                                accounts will have to be personally involved in freeing the hostages
                                from the compound.</p>
                            <p>3. That <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> does not
                                know what the political situation will be when he takes office. It
                                could very well be that resolving the hostage situation will be more
                                difficult for him then than it is for <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> now.</p></quote>
                        <p>It might be possible through the French contacts and the political
                            leverage of the Revolutionary Council to create a situation where
                                <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> has no choice but
                            to tolerate/actively cooperate in pursuing a strategy of early release.
                            In fairness to <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>, he
                            may think that only he will have the muscle and the influence to resolve
                            the crisis, and that it is less a matter of who gets the credit but more
                            a matter of who can pull it off.</p>
                        <p>Finally, you should read the enclosed Memcon from <persName corresp="#p_CR_4">Cottam</persName>.<note n="5" xml:id="d176fn5">Not
                                attached.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CR_4">Cottam</persName> says that <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> could not risk direct
                            contact with us without the knowledge of <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>, the Revolutionary Council and even <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName>. He says that if we had an
                            opportunity for direct contact, we would have to take advantage of
                            it.</p>
                        <p>One final comment about our French contacts, particularly Mr. B. They are
                            not the stooges of <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>.
                            One preferred <persName corresp="#p_HH_1">Habibi</persName> for
                            President and the other <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName>. They have been dealing with the Foreign
                            Minister because they have been told to by the Revolutionary Council and
                            by <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>. They told me last
                            weekend that if <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> tried
                            to block them from seeing <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> or the other members of the Revolutionary
                            Council, they would “wash their hands of this matter”.</p>
                        <p>The Iranian experts at the State Department who have seen a flurry of
                            stories and hints coming out of Tehran and the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> think strongly that the French proposal which we were
                            involved in has been seen and is being discussed and debated by
                            different members of the Revolutionary Council. They assume that
                                <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> would have to be
                            a part of any such discussion. All of the various stories coming out
                            which contain precise details are generally compatible with the scenario
                            that we jointly evolved.</p>
                        <pb facs="0513" n="464" xml:id="pg_464"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>Press Guidance<note n="6" xml:id="d176fn6">Secret; Sensitive.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> initialed “C”
                                    in the upper right corner.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian">undated</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">PRESS GUIDANCE</p>
                            <p rend="center">Steps Toward Release of the Hostages</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Present situation: Iranians State Decision to
                                Form a Commission</p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="roman">Iran:</hi></cell>
                                    <cell><hi rend="roman">Revolutionary Council has decided that a
                                            commission of inquiry should be formed.</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="italic">NOTE:</hi></cell>
                                    <cell>The scenario is not triggered until Iran sends
                                        pre-arranged request to <gloss target="#t_SYG_1">SYG</gloss>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName>. The <gloss target="#t_SYG_1">SYG</gloss> therefore has control over
                                        launching the scenario.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="italic">U.S.:</hi></cell>
                                    <cell>—No Iranian decision has been communicated to us nor, as
                                        far as we know, to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>—If a proposal is made, we will state our position.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="italic">U.N.:</hi></cell>
                                    <cell>Provides no substantive response until a formal Iranian
                                        request along agreed lines is received.</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Step II—1 and 2: Iranian Request that a
                                Commission be formed.</p>
                            <p>Iran requests <gloss target="#t_SYG_1">SYG</gloss>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName> establish a
                                Commission of Inquiry “to hear Iran’s grievances and to allow an
                                early solution to the crisis between Iran and the United States” and
                                states Iran’s desire to have the Commission speak to each of the
                                hostages.</p>
                            <table cols="2">
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Alternatively:</hi></cell>
                                    <cell>“. . . to investigate the grievances of both
                                        sides.”</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="italic">NOTE:</hi></cell>
                                    <cell>This would trigger the scenario.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="italic">U.S.:</hi></cell>
                                    <cell>—The U.S. will discuss the Iranian request with the
                                        Secretary General. We will reserve our comments until we
                                        know what the terms of reference of the Commission will
                                        be.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>—You have heard our position many times before. I need not
                                        repeat it.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>—We support any steps by the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> that might lead to the release of the
                                        hostages while protecting essential international
                                        principles.</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>