<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>180. Telegram From the Embassy in Switzerland to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d180</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">180</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-02-10T14:23:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-02-10T14:23:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86002124"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Hostage</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rechzLHEN4lWkdlwk" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">PermRep</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="public-diplomacy" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomacy</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-10T14:23:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-10T14:23:00-05:00" n="180"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                <head>180. Telegram From the Embassy in Switzerland to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d180fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                        Security Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                        Material, Country File, Box 31, Iran 2/80. Secret; Nodis; <gloss
                            target="#t_Cherokee_1">Cherokee</gloss>; Flash. An unknown hand wrote
                        “advance copy” in the upper right corner. <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1"
                            >Carter</persName> initialed “C” in the upper right corner.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bern</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-02-10T19:23:00+00:00">February 10, 1980, 1923Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>781. Eyes only for President, Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"
                        >Vance</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName>,
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> from <persName
                        corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1"
                        >Saunders</persName>. Subject: Scenario for Resolving Hostage Crisis.</p>
                <p>1. S–Entire text.</p>
                <p>2. We met our contacts two hours Saturday midnight and all day Sunday.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d180fn2">February 9 and 10. <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1"
                            >Saunders</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PH_1">Precht</persName>, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName> met with <persName
                            corresp="#p_BC_2">Bourguet</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_VH_1"
                            >Villalon</persName> at the Bellevue Hotel in Bern. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Crisis</hi>, p. 150) <persName corresp="#p_SG_1">Sick</persName> later
                        complained to <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> that he had
                        been cut out of the <persName corresp="#p_BC_2">Bourguet</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_VH_1">Villalon</persName> scenario and his
                        inclusion needed to be clarified in order to maintain his credibility.
                        (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_SG_1">Sick</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>, February 11; Carter Library,
                        National Security Affairs, Staff Material, Middle East File, Box 32, Subject
                        File, Iran [Retained] 2/80)</note> As a result, we believe we have an
                    acceptable revised scenario (text below). The main lines are as you earlier
                        approved<note n="3" xml:id="d180fn3">See <ref target="#d168">Document
                            168</ref>.</note> with one addition—statements by Presidents <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1"
                        >Bani-Sadr</persName>. The changes primarily develop a more exact schedule
                    of steps for establishing the Commission and a more precise description of
                    events surrounding the end of the Commission’s work and the release of the
                    hostages. Although the exact time it will take to play out this scenario cannot
                    be determined now, we have stressed that the period must be short, and it looks
                    to us as if the scenario should be completed in something less than three weeks
                    from today.</p>
                <p>3. One important proposal outside the scenario below is that <persName
                        corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName> (with <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1"
                        >Saunders</persName>) meet secretly with <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1"
                        >Ghotbzadeh</persName> in Paris next Sunday.<note n="4" xml:id="d180fn4"
                        >February 17.</note> He is taking a trip to Athens, Rome, and Paris on
                    official Iranian business of various kinds. The purposes of the meeting would be
                    (a) to demonstrate good faith on both sides; (b) to confirm or refine the last
                    stages of the scenario, hopefully to get <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1"
                        >Ghotbzadeh</persName>’s agreement to direct release of the hostages rather
                    than going through the intermediate stage of moving them to a hospital in
                    Tehran; (c) to reach understanding on the contents of the two Presidential
                    statements now added to the scenario; (d) to review any details on the remainder
                    of the scenario. We recognize there are risks in such a meeting because it <pb
                        facs="0520" n="471" xml:id="pg_471"/> may leak, but we recommend that it
                    take place in order to assure ourselves on the release of our people. It will be
                    in the mutual interest of both parties to keep this secret. Since we have asked
                    for direct contact and they have responded positively, it might be a setback if
                    we shied away now.</p>
                <p>4. We propose the following immediate steps:</p>
                <p>—<persName corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1"
                        >Saunders</persName> would arrive in New York by 0900 Monday<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d180fn5">February 11.</note> and see <persName corresp="#p_WK_1"
                        >Waldheim</persName> as early as possible, with Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> if at all possible. (If this is approved,
                    we hope the Secretary might call <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName>
                    Sunday and arrange this appointment secretly at <persName corresp="#p_WK_1"
                        >Waldheim</persName>’s residence.)</p>
                <p>—<persName corresp="#p_PH_1">Precht</persName> and interpreter would move to
                    Paris as point of communication with our French contacts throughout the week and
                    to arrange the Sunday meeting. Our contacts will be on the phone to Tehran from
                    Paris daily, and direct communication may be essential in keeping this scenario
                    on the tracks.</p>
                <p>—It would be extremely helpful if Hamilton could call around midnight here (1800
                    Washington time) to determine whether or not to proceed on the basis of this
                    message.</p>
                <p>5. We want to emphasize that it is essential to do everything possible to limit
                    knowledge on our side about the meeting next Sunday.</p>
                <p>6. Begin text.</p>
                <p rend="center">Revised Scenario</p>
                <p>I. Principles and Procedures (no change from earlier draft)</p>
                <p>The United States and Iran agree:</p>
                <p>1. To accept the principle of the establishment of a scenario, the first stages
                    of which would be defined precisely, and the subsequent stages would be defined
                    in detail as events evolve;</p>
                <p>2. To manage this scenario with the help of persons agreed to by both sides;</p>
                <p>3. To proceed, within the framework of this scenario, by stages each involving
                    reciprocal actions to be defined in advance;</p>
                <p>4. That these points are intended to allow the earliest possible resolution of
                    the present crisis by peaceful means.</p>
                <p>II. Establishment of a Commission of Inquiry (changes show detailed sequence of
                    events—all times below are New York time)</p>
                <p>1. It is agreed in the approval of this scenario that the Secretary-General of
                    the United Nations should establish a Commission of <pb facs="0521" n="472"
                        xml:id="pg_472"/> Inquiry to hear Iran’s grievances and to allow an early
                    solution of the crisis between Iran and the U.S. and that Iran desires to have
                    the Commission speak to each of the hostages.</p>
                <p>2. Monday night: Secretary-General <persName corresp="#p_WK_1"
                        >Waldheim</persName> sends a message to <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1"
                        >Ghotbzadeh</persName> confirming his readiness to send to Iran within a
                    week the Commission of 5–7 members which he discussed in Tehran early in January
                    “to hear Iran’s grievances and to allow an early solution of the crisis between
                    Iran and the U.S.”<note n="6" xml:id="d180fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName> confirmed to <persName
                            corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> his intention to establish a
                        commission on February 13, reiterating the sentences in this step of this
                        scenario. (Department of State, Records of <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1"
                            >David D. Newsom</persName>, Under Secretary of State for Political
                        Affairs, Subject Files, 1978–1981, Lot 81D154, Box 8, <gloss
                            target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> and Security Channel) A report of <persName
                            corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName>’s trip to Iran in January is in
                            <ref target="#d132">Document 132</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>3. Tuesday: <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> would respond by
                    agreeing that the Commission should come to Tehran within a week and stating
                    Iran’s desire to have the Commission speak to each of the hostages.<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d180fn7">
                        <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName> fulfilled this step of
                        the scenario in two messages. The first, February 12, informed <persName
                            corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName> that Iran would accept the
                        Commission “to make the inquiry about the crimes committed by the deposed
                        Shah and the funds stolen by him and his family. On this basis the
                        Commission will hear the American hostages as well.” In a second note of
                        February 13, he acknowledged that his message had given rise to “erroneous
                        interpretations,” and stated that the Commission “will have as its mission
                        to examine the grievances of Iran and to allow a rapid solution to the
                        crisis between Iran and the United States.” (Department of State, Records of
                            <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1">David D. Newsom</persName>, Under Secretary
                        of State for Political Affairs, Subject Files, 1978–1981, Lot 81D154, Box 8,
                            <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> and Security Channel)</note>
                </p>
                <p>4. Tuesday night: The U.S. would remove its objections to the establishment of
                    this Commission by a direct private communication to the Secretary-General.<note
                        n="8" xml:id="d180fn8">On the basis of the exchange of messages between
                            <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"
                            >Vance</persName> reiterated the sentences in this step of the scenario
                        in a February 13 message to <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName>.
                        (Department of State, Records of <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1">David D.
                            Newsom</persName>, Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs,
                        Subject Files, 1978–1981, Lot 81D154, Box 8, <gloss target="#t_UN_1"
                            >UN</gloss> and Security Channel)</note> In that communication, the U.S.
                    would state importance that Commission look into the grievances of both sides
                    and work for early release of the hostages. At this time, the U.S. would take
                    the following position publicly: The U.S. will discuss with the
                    Secretary-General the concept of a Commission. The U.S. will reserve its comment
                    until it knows what the terms of reference of the Commission will be. The U.S.
                    has stated its position many times before and need not repeat it. While we have
                    opposed the formation of a Commission under past conditions, we would support
                    any steps by the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> that might lead to the
                    release of the hostages while protecting essential international principles.</p>
                <p>5. Tuesday night: Secretary-General <persName corresp="#p_WK_1"
                        >Waldheim</persName> sends a second message to <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1"
                        >Ghotbzadeh</persName> which would (a) state briefly the purpose of <pb
                        facs="0522" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> the Commission as a fact-finding
                    mission (not a tribunal) to help end the crisis and (b) recommend the membership
                    of 5–7 for the Commission. In proposing the membership, the Secretary-General
                    would propose <persName corresp="#p_AA_1">Aguilar</persName> as Chairman plus
                    4–6 members, including (1) M’Bow (UNESCO Director), (2) <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Bedjaoui</persName> (Algerian PermRep at <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>), (3) Petitti (former head of Paris Bar
                    Association and Association of Catholic Jurists), (4) Martin Ennals (Amnesty
                    International Secretary-General), (5) Abu Sayeed Chowdhury (former President of
                    Bangladesh), (6) <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Daoudi</persName> (Advisor to
                    President Assad of Syria) or Sabah el Rikabi (Head of Union of Syrian Bar
                    Associations). If any of the proposed members is not acceptable to Iran, Iran
                    could suggest that one or two be dropped.<note n="9" xml:id="d180fn9">In the
                        right margin, an unknown hand wrote “D’Quello.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>6. Between Tuesday and Friday: Either <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1"
                        >Bani-Sadr</persName> himself would confirm by phone to the
                    Secretary-General or the Imam would issue a statement that he has authorized the
                    Revolutionary Council to resolve the crisis.<note n="10" xml:id="d180fn10"
                        >February 11–15. <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName> received
                        this confirmation on February 13 for the initial go-ahead and also announced
                        publicly on February 19 that <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1"
                            >Khomeini</persName> and the Revolutionary Council had approved the
                        Commission and invited it to Tehran. (<persName corresp="#p_VC_1"
                            >Vance</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Hard Choices</hi>, p.
                        403–404)</note> The Secretary-General would not proceed until he has
                    received confirmation in one of these forms from Iran.</p>
                <p>7. Friday at 1600 hours: The Secretary-General would announce establishment of
                    the Commission and its purposes, including Iran’s desire to have the Commission
                    speak to each of the hostages.<note n="11" xml:id="d180fn11">
                        <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName> made this required
                        announcement at 12:30 p.m. on February 20. (Telegram Tosec 45792/10049 to
                            <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>, February 20; Department of
                        State, Records of <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1">David D. Newsom</persName>,
                        Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs, Subject Files, 1978–1981,
                        Lot 81D154, Box 1, Iran NODIS Cables Feb 1980) The announcement and
                            <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName>’s press briefing were
                        reported in Michael Weisskopf, “U.N. Commission Plans Interviews With All
                        Hostages,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, February 21, 1980, p.
                        A1.</note>
                </p>
                <p>8. After <gloss target="#t_SYG_1">SYG</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName>’s announcement: The President of
                    Iran would publicly present the establishment of the Commission of Inquiry as a
                    success of Iranian diplomacy, would interpret the visit to the hostages as one
                    of the elements in the investigation into Iranian grievances, and would state
                    the desire of the Imam to see the Commission conclude its work rapidly. The
                    Iranian President would instruct government administrations to place their
                    documents at the disposal of the Commission.<note n="12" xml:id="d180fn12">See
                            <ref target="#d189">Document 189</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>9. After the Iranian statement: The U.S. would state that the Commission is going
                    on a fact-finding mission to Tehran, to hear the grievances of both sides, to
                    meet with each of the hostages, and to report to the Secretary-General. The U.S.
                    would object publicly to having the <pb facs="0523" n="474" xml:id="pg_474"/>
                    Commission subject the hostages to interrogation in connection with its inquiry
                    during any of its meetings with them.</p>
                <p>III. Work of the Commission</p>
                <p>1. The Commission would not leave New York for Tehran until the U.S. announcement
                    above has been made. It would aim to begin work in Tehran early next week.</p>
                <p>2. The Commission would hold its meetings in private and will receive evidence
                    and documents to be submitted to it by Iranian authorities.</p>
                <p>3. The Commission would visit the Embassy as soon as possible to meet with the
                    hostages.</p>
                <p>4. As soon as the Commission has concluded its work and drafted its report, it:
                    (a) would tell the Revolutionary Council that the credibility of its report
                    would be seriously limited unless the hostages are released immediately or at
                    least moved from the compound to a hospital; (b) would inform the Revolutionary
                    Council that it is ready to return to New York to submit its report to the
                    Secretary-General.</p>
                <p>IV. Final Stages:</p>
                <p>1. Transfer of the hostages to the protection of the Government of Iran either in
                    a hospital or in the Embassy compound after the “students” have left the
                    premises. (Day number 1.)</p>
                <p>2. Return of the Commission to New York. (Day 1 plus 1)</p>
                <p>3. Submission to the Secretary-General of the Commission’s report which will
                    contain findings and recommendations. Publication of the report as a <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> document. The report would express <hi
                        rend="italic">inter alia</hi> the following principle as a recommendation to
                    all governments:</p>
                <p>—Governments should respect and facilitate within the framework of their internal
                    laws the right of Iran:</p>
                <quote>
                    <p>(a) to file suits against the Shah, his family or associates on the basis of
                        the grave presumption of any serious crimes set forth in the report;</p>
                    <p>(b) to file suits to recover assets which in the report are presumed to have
                        been illegally taken from Iran by the Shah, his family or associates.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>(Day 1 plus 2)</p>
                <p>4. Release of the hostages and their departure from Iran. (Day 1 plus 3).</p>
                <p>5. One hour after their departure, the <gloss target="#t_SYG_1">SYG</gloss> will
                    release statements by President <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1"
                        >Bani-Sadr</persName> and President <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1"
                        >Carter</persName> both previously agreed by Iran and the U.S. and, before
                    the Commission left Iran, deposited privately with the <gloss target="#t_SYG_1"
                        >SYG</gloss>.</p>
                <p>(a) The Iranian statement will admit the moral wrong of holding hostages, express
                    regret, promise to respect international law and affirm a desire to establish
                    normal relations based on mutual respect, equality and international law.</p>
                <pb facs="0524" n="475" xml:id="pg_475"/>
                <p>(b) The U.S. statement will:</p>
                <quote>
                    <p>(1) accept the principle stated in 3 above</p>
                    <p>(2) express understanding and regret for the grievances of the Iranian
                        people, including the widespread perception of U.S. intervention in Iran’s
                        internal affairs;</p>
                    <p>(3) affirm the right of the Iranian people to make decisions governing their
                        political future and the policy of the U.S. to respect that right;</p>
                    <p>(4) affirm a desire for normal relations based on mutual respect, equality
                        and the principles of international law.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>6. Establishment of a Joint Commission to resolve all unresolved bilateral
                    problems. (On a date to be determined by Iran and the U.S. within one month
                    after day 1.)</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Vine</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
