<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>208. Telegram From the Embassy in Switzerland to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d208</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">208</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-03-13T20:25:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-03-13T20:25:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003007715"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hostages</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-03-13T20:25:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-03-13T20:25:00-05:00" n="208"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d208">
                <head>208. Telegram From the Embassy in Switzerland to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d208fn1">Source: Carter Library, Plains File,
                        Box 7. Secret; Immediate; Nodis; <gloss target="#t_Cherokee_1"
                            >Cherokee</gloss>; Special Encryption.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bern</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-03-14T01:25:00+00:00">March 14, 1980, 0125Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1463. For the President and Secretary. Subj: Second Meeting With B and V Revised
                    Scenario.</p>
                <p>1. S–Entire text.</p>
                <pb facs="0594" n="545" xml:id="pg_545"/>
                <p>2. Please pass to the White House Eyes Only for the President and Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>.</p>
                <p>3. In order to focus discussion on how the situation in Tehran can evolve
                    relating to the hostages and the work of the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                    Commission, we developed the middle and final stages of the scenario as a basis
                    for discussions in Washington, Tehran, and New York on how to proceed. You will
                    have an opportunity to study the revised scenario in Washington Friday and
                        Saturday.<note n="2" xml:id="d208fn2">March 14 and 15.</note> V is planning
                    to return to Tehran Sunday. One possible action for Friday is discussed
                    below.</p>
                <p>4. Begin text of revised scenario.</p>
                <p>Scenario—Second Revision</p>
                <p>I. Principles and Procedures</p>
                <p>The United States and Iran renew their commitment to resolve the crisis between
                    them through completion of the previously agreed scenario.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d208fn3">See <ref target="#d180">Document 180</ref>.</note> The
                    following is a suggested development of events in the days ahead:</p>
                <p>II. Transfer of the Hostages (Objective: March 15–25)</p>
                <p>A. March 15 or 16: Election results are announced.</p>
                <p>B. March 16: V returns to Tehran with a personal message from <persName
                        corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani
                        Sadr</persName>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d208fn4">See <ref target="#d209">Document 209</ref>.</note>
                    which would make the following points:</p>
                <p>—President <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> appreciates President
                        <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani Sadr</persName>’s message stating that
                    the transfer of the hostages to the control of the Revolutionary Council would
                    take place no later than March 25.<note n="5" xml:id="d208fn5">See <ref
                            target="#d207fn4">footnote 4, Document 207</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>—President <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> appreciated this direct
                    communication and has asked <persName corresp="#p_JHH_1">Jordan</persName> to
                    discuss with B and V agreed steps that could be taken to make possible an early
                    end of the crisis between the two countries and also ask them to report to
                    President <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani Sadr</persName> steps that the US
                    has taken.</p>
                <p>—The US is prepared to continue restraint in its public posture for a few more
                    days, despite the increase in public pressure for it to adopt stronger
                    measures.</p>
                <p>—The US has urged the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Commission to complete
                    its work and to be prepared to return to Iran to do so in coordination with the
                    Iranian authorities. Until the time is right, we have urged the Commission also
                    to maintain restraint in its public posture.</p>
                <p>—When the hostages are transferred, the US will regard that as a clear indication
                    of President <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani Sadr</persName>’s willingness to
                    continue, <pb facs="0595" n="546" xml:id="pg_546"/> through the series of agreed
                    reciprocal steps, the process to allow an early end to the crisis, including
                    release of all 53 Americans now held in Tehran.</p>
                <p>—The US looks forward to a period beyond the present difficulties when we can
                    build a relationship with Iran and its people based on equality and mutual
                    respect.</p>
                <p>C. March 15–17: The Commission would limit its public statements to an
                    announcement that it is reviewing the material collected. But, in private
                    messages to <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani Sadr</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>, the Commission would recall in
                    particular that it will be unable to complete its report until it has seen all
                    the hostages, and that it will be ready to return to Tehran as soon as the
                    Iranian authorities indicate to it the date and the conditions under which the
                    visit can take place. As the Commission discussed with <persName
                        corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani Sadr</persName>, it would suggest that the visit
                    take place between March 21–25 and could ask the Foreign Minister to place at
                    its disposal all the remaining documents it wishes to submit to the
                    Commission.</p>
                <p>D. Transfer of the hostages to the authority of the Foreign Ministry and of the
                    Revolutionary Council.</p>
                <p>III. The Return of the Commission to Tehran (Objective: March 21–25)</p>
                <p>(The following would be agreed in advance by <persName corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani
                        Sadr</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GQS_1">Ghotbzadeh</persName>, and the
                    Commission.)</p>
                <p>A. On arriving, the Commission would state: It has returned to complete its
                    mission. It has asked the Foreign Ministry to place all remaining evidence at
                    its disposal.</p>
                <p>B. The Foreign Minister, as the Imam requested, would collect all remaining
                    documents and enable the Commission to examine them.</p>
                <p>C. The Commission would meet with the Revolutionary Council to set forth the
                    facts invoked by Iran, to state that it indeed has received elements of evidence
                    relating to these facts, and that within days it will be able to present a
                    report to the Secretary-General giving the findings and recommendations that it
                    has been able to derive from the evidence presented.</p>
                <p>D. The Revolutionary Council would make a statement on its meeting with the
                    Commission.</p>
                <p>E. The Commission would then visit each of the hostages under the conditions
                    which the Commission will prescribe.</p>
                <p>F. The Commission would make another report to the Revolutionary Council on the
                    conditions of the hostages. It would also tell the Revolutionary Council that
                    the credibility of its report would be seriously limited unless the hostages are
                    released. It would ask Iran to set a date for releasing the hostages and would
                    commit itself to publish its report on that date. (The simultaneity indicated in
                    the last sentence is subject to review as the final stages are revised.)</p>
                <pb facs="0596" n="547" xml:id="pg_547"/>
                <p>IV. Final Steps (Objective: Ten days after transfer)</p>
                <p>The previous scenario agreed to by both parties envisioned a final stage of
                    reciprocal steps leading to release of the Americans held in Tehran.</p>
                <p>However, the sequence of steps envisioned then has changed because in the new
                    circumstances the Commission will return to Iran after the Revolutionary Council
                    has taken custody of the American personnel. Because of recent developments, the
                    final steps of the scenario agreed earlier seem no longer to be completely
                    applicable. If that assumption is not correct, the US is prepared to abide by
                    the previously agreed scenario.</p>
                <p>If the final steps of the earlier scenario can no longer be followed, it is
                    necessary for both parties to agree on the steps in a new final stage. In these
                    new circumstances, the United States believes that the components of the final
                    stage—including the report of the United Nations Commission, the statements of
                    Presidents <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani Sadr</persName>, the establishment of an Iran-US
                    joint commission to resolve bilateral issues, and the release of all 53
                    Americans—should be taken simultaneously. It is also the position of the United
                    States that the release of the hostages should take place no later than 10 days
                    after the transfer of the American personnel. End text.</p>
                <p>5. The one possible action the Secretary might wish to discuss with <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG_1">SYG</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WK_1">Waldheim</persName> Friday while members of the
                    Commission may still be in New York is the possible message from the Commission
                    described in para IIC of the scenario above. They could at least talk it over
                    with a view to authorizing the co-chairmen to send it Sunday or Monday to arrive
                    in Tehran shortly after the election results are available and when the US
                    message arrives in Tehran Sunday.<note n="6" xml:id="d208fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> informed <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> that he thought it “doubtful that we
                        can side-step” <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName>’s public
                        declarations against release of the hostages. He found the scenario to have
                        “an unrealistic quality in not factoring in student resistance, the
                        Ayatollah’s, the Parliament, etc.” and added “we will be setting ourselves
                        up for another fall which will leave the hostages still in Tehran and could
                        damage you seriously politically.” He concluded that <persName
                            corresp="#p_BSAH_1">Bani-Sadr</persName> is “stringing us along.”
                        (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> to
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName>, March 14; Carter Library,
                        Plains File, Box 10)</note>
                </p>
                <p>6. A draft of the message mentioned in para IIB of the scenario is being carried
                    back to Washington Friday morning.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Vine</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
