<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>349. Message From Joint Task Delta to 1st Special Operations Wing, 101st
                    Airborne (Air Assault) and 1st Battalion, 75th Ranger Regiment to 1st Special
                    Operations Wing, 101st Airborne (Air Assault) and 1st Battalion, 75th Ranger
                    Regiment</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v11p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d349</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">349</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-09-02T07:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-09-02T07:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receU2jshk3GXzdwQ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Intelligence assessment</term>
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86002124"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Hostage</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recH8UKNUTXoDXkax" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-09-02T07:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-09-02T07:15:00-05:00" n="349"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d349">
                <head>349. Message From Joint Task <gloss target="#t_Delta_1">Delta</gloss> to 1st
                    Special Operations Wing, 101st Airborne (Air Assault) and 1st Battalion, 75th
                    Ranger Regiment<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d349fn1">Source: Department of
                        Defense, Joint Chiefs of Staff Records, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                        218–07–0002, Records of <gloss target="#t_J-3_1">J–3</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_DDSO_1">DDSO</gloss>, Box 2, Iranian Hostage Crisis
                        1979–1984, B270–280 Intelligence Assessment. Top Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <idno type="document-identifier">Nr 002</idno>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-09-02T12:15:00+00:00">September 2, 1980, 1215Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Intelligence Assessment.</item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>REF</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss>/Snowbird/J3 Cite 0288 Subj: 60–90 Day
                        Situation Projection<note n="2" xml:id="d349fn2">See <ref target="#d341"
                                >Document 341</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>1. (<gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss>) This message provides a hardcopy
                    follow-up to the intelligence assessment presented at the 29 Aug 80 <gloss
                        target="#t_JTD_1">JTD</gloss> planning conference and is a supplement to
                    reference.</p>
                <p>A. The American-Iranian hostage situation remains as it did in November and
                    during the intervening months, it is a political problem without a political
                    solution. Political solutions are the product of compromises. In the current
                    situation, the positions of the opposing parties the <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> and the Iranian entities are non-negotiable.</p>
                <p>B. Although a humanitarian solution is possible the political impasse is likely
                    to continue past 4 November before a major change. <pb facs="0967" n="918"
                        xml:id="pg_918"/> After 4 November Iranian options include a release of some
                    hostages while requesting concessions from the new US administration (if there
                    is a new administration), or the continued detention of most of the hostages and
                    the initiation of a grand jury type trial heading to the indictment of the
                        <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> and several of the hostages.</p>
                <p>C. A major unknown in the projection equation is the health of <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAR_1">Ayatollah Khomeini</persName>. He is currently a major
                    stabilizing force; if he were to die of natural causes and his death
                    acknowledged as such no significant change in the hostage situation is likely to
                    occur as the hardline clerics now possess a far greater degree of control than
                    they did prior to the election of the Parliament and naming of the Prime
                    Minister. However, if <persName corresp="#p_KAR_1">Khomeini</persName> were to
                    be assassinated or his death claimed to be the result of an American plot then
                    chaos and confusion would result and within three–five days the lives of the
                    hostages would be at serious risk.</p>
                <p>2. (<gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss>) In reviewing the threat, five entities
                    warrant discussion.</p>
                <p>A. The conventional Iranian military continues to deteriorate due to internal
                    purges of the professional leadership and difficulties in maintaining some of
                    the more sophisticated weapons systems. However the air defense network and
                    associated alert aircraft and point defense <gloss target="#t_ADA_1">ADA</gloss>
                    systems together with the gendarmerie reporting structure provide a persistent
                    potential for detecting and interdicting mission aircraft.</p>
                <p>B. The Revolutionary Guard structure is becoming more structured and is
                    unquestionably a tool of the clerics. In the rural areas the Guard has attempted
                    to replace the army but integration has not occurred. In the larger cities
                    particularly Tehran reports now indicate Guard members have taken to bullying
                    the population at the slightest opportunity and some have established a
                    neighborhood protection payout mechanism.</p>
                <p>C. The composition of the militants seems to have changed somewhat with the hard
                    core radicals, many with Marxist influenced backgrounds, continuing to control
                    the fate of the hostages, although there is no question that they have received
                    assistance from the Revolutionary Guard and hardline clerics such as Ayatollah
                        <persName corresp="#p_BBASM_1">Beheshti</persName>.</p>
                <p>D. The U.S. media and self proclaimed political moralists pose a significant
                    danger to any prospects of a political solution and a tremendous threat to
                    military planning with false leaks and compromises. Their real danger lies in
                    their potential for creating a dangerous degree of instability in both hostage
                    location and security.</p>
                <p>E. The fifth threat entity is the intelligence apparatus of the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and its allies. The Soviet intelligence
                    services were embarrassed by the degree of their ignorance regarding the April
                    attempt. They do not <pb facs="0968" n="919" xml:id="pg_919"/> want to be caught
                    unawares again. In addition the Soviet Union is preparing to take advantage of
                    several possible opportunities regarding Iran. It is preparing to move military
                    forces into Iran if anarchy and chaos erupts. Similarly the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is preparing to react if U.S. military
                    forces are introduced into Iran in any size, and while awaiting the advent of
                    one of these possibilities, the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is busily
                    laying the propaganda groundwork to capitalize on the above and justify a
                    unilateral move on the pretext of countering the alleged presence of counter
                    revolutionary forces operating in Iran against the Government of Iran and the
                    Government of Afghanistan.</p>
                <p>3. (<gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss>) Hostage Situation:</p>
                <p>A. Dispersion outside of the Embassy compound must be accepted as fact; planning
                    must consider multiple targets. Precise locations remain unknown due to tight
                    security and deception measures employed by militants and clerics. During the
                    past month most hostage relatives have received a letter from their loved ones.
                    The letters indicate long periods of small group isolation, very little outside
                    activity, no physical abuse, allowed to receive some mail, and at least three
                    hostages, military and civilian, have implied they plus another 6 to 9 are being
                    held in a prison or prison-like environment.</p>
                <p>B. Current estimates put upwards of a half probably in Tehran as follows: <gloss
                        target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> (3), Embassy compound: Chancery 3–5, warehouse
                    3–5; prison/jail or villa in northern Tehran (16–18). The balance, according to
                        [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] reporting are
                    apparently scattered throughout the country in groups of 3–5. A 25 Aug <gloss
                        target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> assessment listed ten possible locations, this
                    HQ believes the actual number is less than that, probably no more than 3–5
                    locations at any given time. The typical site is probably a 2-story house within
                    a walled compound located in a quiet residential neighborhood.</p>
                <p>4. (<gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss>) Operational Planning. During the review
                    and crosschecking of possible locations we have located at least one potential
                    fixed-wing landing zone within 100NM of each of the more likely hostage
                    detention locations, and at least one active airhead with extraction potential
                    within 12–15 miles. Of all the locations Tehran offers the greatest number of
                    possibilities for insertion and extraction.</p>
                <p>A. In the city proper both Mehrabad and Doshan Tappeh [Airports] hold
                    possibilities with D/T being within 5–6 minutes driving time of the compound and
                    M/B within 20–25 minutes driving time.</p>
                <p>B. In the immediate suburbs at least two additional sites have been identified as
                        <gloss target="#t_C-130_1">C–130</gloss> capable and two others have been
                    identified within 30 <gloss target="#t_NM_1">NM</gloss>.</p>
                <p>C. Farther out Manzariyeh still holds a potential for use. In addition three
                    fixed-wing capable sites (one <gloss target="#t_C-141_1">C–141</gloss>) have
                    been identified in the Semman area.</p>
                <pb facs="0969" n="920" xml:id="pg_920"/>
                <p>D. The search for additional sites is continuing and field survey of the more
                    promising sites is hoped to be started within 3–4 weeks.</p>
                <p>5. (<gloss target="#t_TS_1">TS</gloss>) In summary three points are important to
                    remember during future planning and training.</p>
                <p>A. The situation is not stable and the confirmed locations of today can be
                    invalid tomorrow because of a militant reaction to a news rumor.</p>
                <p>B. The second point is that the Soviets are actively seeking data on U.S.
                    military intentions toward Iran and are preparing their forces in the border
                    area to move into Iran when the opportunity arises. A prolonged widespread
                    rescue operation that carried a large signature before or during the operation
                    could provide them with the rationale to react against an “American
                    invasion”.</p>
                <p>C. The third and final point is that regardless of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_HJLIII_2">Holloway</persName> Board’s inference that <gloss
                        target="#t_OPSEC_1">OPSEC</gloss> was too restrictive during the planning
                    for the last attempt,<note n="3" xml:id="d349fn3">See <ref target="#d321"
                            >Document 321</ref>.</note> it was essential then and an absolute
                    imperative now. Secrecy was paramount to mission success the last time, and the
                    same is doubly true now. Secrecy is essential for mission success and for world
                    peace. The bear is standing in wings anticipating the script and watching for
                    his cue to enter stage north.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
