<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversations, by Mr. Stewart of the Division of European
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941-43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d185</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">185</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-01-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3xWCKc8tJ1gyWw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-01-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="185"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 PW/1576½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversations, by Mr. Stewart of the Division of
                        European Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">strictly confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-01-12">January 12,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Australia and the War in the Pacific</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I have had several talks in recent days with Mr. Alan Watt of the Australian
                    Legation concerning general developments in Australia <pb facs="0396" n="322"
                        xml:id="pg_322"/> and the Southwest Pacific. In this connection Mr. Watt
                    showed me a confidential summary of recent developments which he prepared for
                    the use of the Australian Minister, Mr. Casey, and which covers the main points
                    discussed with me. I asked Mr. Watt if I might have a copy of this summary for
                    my <hi rend="italic">strictly confidential information</hi> and for very
                    restricted distribution to certain other persons in the Department. Mr. Watt
                    agreed that I might have a copy for these purposes. I assured him that it would
                    be treated as strictly confidential. The text of his summary is as follows:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">“January 9th, 1942</p>
                        <p>“1. The Australian Government is gravely concerned over the adequacy of
                            the measures so far taken to maintain in Allied hands vital areas in the
                            southwestern Pacific, including Australia, as a base of operations from
                            which to attack Japan. It believes that Singapore is the key point in
                            this area, and that the Philippines and the Netherlands Indies are also
                            of vital importance. Yet, in its opinion the forces at present available
                            in the southwestern Pacific, together with the additional reinforcements
                            which have so far been allocated to that area, are insufficient to
                            withhold Japanese attacks with any reasonable degree of certainty. If
                            the Philippines, Malaya and the Netherlands Indies are lost to Japan,
                            the consequences will be incalculable—not only directly to Australia
                            itself, but also to Burma and India and to the United States, which may
                            be compelled to fight Japan from Hawaiian bases at great disadvantage
                            and cost in time, men and materials. In view of her own vital interests
                            involved, the Australian Government feels strongly that Australia and
                            also the Netherlands Indies should have a direct voice in policy
                            decisions affecting the southwestern Pacific area so that their views
                            may be given full weight <hi rend="italic">before</hi> decisions on
                            policy are reached.</p>
                        <p>“2. Australia has not been represented at the United Kingdom—United
                            States discussions in Washington. The Government has been compelled,
                            therefore, to put its views from time to time in writing and to address
                            these to Mr. Churchill and President Roosevelt jointly in the hope that
                            they may be considered in time to affect decisions. These views have had
                            to be formulated in the absence of precise information as to the
                            progress of the discussions. Replies to the representations of the
                            Australian Government have been received both from Mr. Churchill and
                            President Roosevelt. The difficulty of carrying on adequate discussions
                            in this way, however, has been very well illustrated by certain major
                            misunderstandings and difficulties which have arisen from some of these
                            replies. The main points involved are referred to below.</p>
                        <p>“3. The Inter-Allied Conference held at Singapore from 18th to 20th
                            December came to the conclusion that the situation was ‘serious’ but
                            need not give rise to ‘undue pessimism’, provided necessary
                            reinforcements were supplied within the time still available. It
                            stressed the fact that time was the essential factor. The Conference
                            agreed on a list of ‘minimum’ reinforcements necessary to withstand a
                            Japanese <pb facs="0397" n="323" xml:id="pg_323"/> attack on the then
                            existing scale. If additional Japanese forces were thrown into the
                            battle, the scale of Allied reinforcements would have to be
                            increased.</p>
                        <p>“4. On 23rd December the Australian Prime Minister sent an urgent message
                            to Mr. Churchill and President Roosevelt<note n="1" xml:id="d185fn1">For
                                text, see <ref target="frus1941v05#pg_390">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 390</ref>.</note> jointly
                            expressing the opinion that British air reinforcements known to be
                            earmarked for Singapore were quite inadequate and asking that urgent
                            additional aid should be given.</p>
                        <p>“5. In his reply, dated 24th or 25th December, Mr. Churchill indicated
                            that he and his advisers did not accept the view that there was danger
                            of an early reduction of the Singapore fortress. He referred to
                            reinforcements which were being sent and stated that commanders in the
                            Middle East had been directed to concert a plan for sending fighters and
                            tanks to Singapore ‘immediately the situation in Libya permits’. Mr.
                            Churchill added that President Roosevelt and his advisers were not only
                            impressed with the importance of maintaining Singapore but were ‘anxious
                            to move a continuous flow of troops and aeroplanes through Australia for
                            the relief of the Philippines’ if that were possible. Should the
                            Philippines fall, the President was agreeable to troops and aeroplanes
                            being diverted to Singapore and he was also ‘quite willing to send
                            substantial United States forces to Australia’, where the United States
                            was anxious to establish important bases.</p>
                        <p>“6. On 1st January, President Roosevelt informed the Australian Prime
                            Minister that he and Mr. Churchill, with their Chiefs of Staff, had
                            given the most urgent consideration to the despatch of reinforcements at
                            the earliest possible moment. He added that the necessary steps were
                            already under way ‘for the flight (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>) to
                            Australia of effective air assistance’.</p>
                        <p>“7. From information subsequently supplied by the United States Army Air
                            Corps it would appear that by the end of January between 200 and 250
                            American fighter planes will have arrived in Australia en route to the
                            Philippines or Singapore or elsewhere. In addition, it is proposed that
                            some 80 heavy bombers will be flown from the United States to the Far
                            East via Africa, their probable dates of arrival being unknown at
                            present.</p>
                        <p>“8. On 29th December Mr. Churchill informed the Australian Government
                            that he and President Roosevelt had ‘agreed’, <hi rend="italic">inter
                                alia</hi>, on the following important matters: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Unity of command in the southwestern Pacific (Mr. Churchill
                                    said the boundaries of the command were not yet finally settled
                                    but would presumably extend southward to the ‘necessary supply
                                    bases, principally Port Darwin and supply lines in Northern
                                    Australia’).</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Wavell would be Commander-in-Chief of all land, sea and air
                                    forces and ‘would receive his orders from an appropriate joint
                                    body’ responsible to Mr. Churchill and President
                                    Roosevelt.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The United States Navy would ‘remain responsible for the whole
                                    of the Pacific Ocean east of the Philippines and Australasia
                                    including the United States approaches to Australasia’. <pb
                                        facs="0398" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/> Mr. Churchill added
                                    that a Letter of Instructions to Wavell was being
                                    drafted.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>On 30th or 31st December the Australian Prime Minister informed Mr.
                            Churchill that the Australian Government assented to the ‘text
                            agreement’. Mr. Curtin added that the Australian Government ‘expect that
                            Australia will be included in the composition of the joint body’ from
                            which Wavell was to receive his instructions.</p>
                        <p>“9. About 3rd January Mr. Churchill forwarded to the Australian Prime
                            Minister Wavell’s Letter of Instructions ‘approved by the President and
                            the Prime Minister’.</p>
                        <p>“10. On 7th January the Australian Minister in Washington was informed
                            that the Australian Prime Minister had telegraphed Mr. Churchill
                            regarding Wavell’s Letter of Instructions along the following lines: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Australia was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> included in the
                                    composition of the ‘joint body’ which was to direct
                                    Wavell.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Dominion views on policy, reinforcements, etc. regarding the
                                    southwestern Pacific were (in accordance with the Letter of
                                    Instructions) to be conveyed merely to London, which would then
                                    inform Washington.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Australia had been totally excluded from the southwestern
                                    Pacific area assigned to Wavell.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>There was nothing at all to indicate that the United States
                                    Navy would assume responsibility for the waters east of
                                    Australia.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>“The Prime Minister expressed his dissatisfaction with the present
                            position and stated that this dissatisfaction was shared by the
                            Australian War Council and the Australian people. Mr. Curtin added that
                            without adequate naval protection, the line of communication with
                            Australia for American supply ships could not be maintained. The
                            Japanese had only to ‘walk into’ New Caledonia, where they would be
                            astride this line and in a position to launch air attacks on the most
                            northern Australian ports which were being used by the United States for
                            unloading aircraft and other supplies for transit to Darwin and the
                            Netherlands Indies.</p>
                        <p>“11. In short, the views of the Australian Government can be summarised
                            as follows: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Singapore, the Philippines, the Netherlands Indies, Australia
                                    itself and points like New Caledonia and Fiji are in grave
                                    danger of falling under Japanese control because— <list>
                                        <label>(i)</label>
                                        <item>insufficient forces are at present in the southwestern
                                            Pacific to repel Japanese attacks, and</item>
                                        <label>(ii)</label>
                                        <item>insufficient reinforcements have been assigned to that
                                            area.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>In view of the fact that vital Australian and Dutch interests
                                    are involved, the machinery set up to control policy in this <pb
                                        facs="0399" n="325" xml:id="pg_325"/> area is unsatisfactory
                                    because there is inadequate provision for Australian and Dutch
                                    participation at the appropriate time and places in policy
                                    decisions affecting the southwestern Pacific.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>For reasons not explained General Wavell’s area of command
                                    excludes the whole of Australia, although according to Mr.
                                    Churchill it had been agreed that this area would include Port
                                    Darwin and supply lines in Northern Australia.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>No adequate provision has been made to ensure the control of
                                    waters east of Australia on the supply line from the United
                                    States or for the defence of important points like New
                                    Caledonia. This is a matter of great urgency as Intelligence
                                    Reports show that it is quite possible a heavy Japanese attack
                                    on New Caledonia or Fiji might develop at any time after January
                                    10th.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
