<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="330" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d330">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Roosevelt Papers: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">President <persName type="from">Roosevelt</persName>
                                to Prime Minister <persName type="to">Churchill</persName>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d330fn1">Sent to the United States Naval
                                Attaché, London, via Navy channels.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-07">January 7, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Personal and secret from the President for the <gloss target="#t_FormerNavalPerson1">Former Naval Person</gloss> No.
                            254.</p>
                        <p>I should like to acquaint you with a message received by me from
                            Generalissimo Chiang Kai Shek.<note n="2" xml:id="d330fn2">The message
                                from Chiang was a telegram dated December 28, 1942 (Roosevelt
                                Papers).</note>
                            <hi rend="italic">Begin brief of Generalissimo’s message:</hi>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Last spring the Prime Minister assured the members of the Pacific
                                    War Council that before the end of the next monsoon season,
                                    eight <pb facs="0601" n="515" xml:id="pg_515"/> battleships,
                                    three aircraft carriers and the usual complement of other
                                    vessels would be in the Indian Ocean to assist in the recapture
                                    of Burma.<note n="3" xml:id="d330fn3">The reference is
                                        presumably to statements made in the Pacific War Council in
                                        London, of which Churchill was the chairman. The United
                                        States was not a member of the London Pacific War Council.
                                        On June 25, 1942, during the 12th Meeting of the Pacific War
                                        Council in Washington (of which Roosevelt was the chairman),
                                        Churchill had stated that the Eastern Fleet would be built
                                        up to full strength by August 1942, and this would allow
                                        positive help to be given to China. For the record of this
                                        Washington Pacific War Council meeting, see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_448">p.
                                            448</ref>.</note> We have been counting on the support
                                    of this naval force, for without it the recapture of Burma will
                                    be impossible. General Stilwell upon returning from a conference
                                    in India informs me that Admiral Somerville stated the British
                                    Navy has at its disposal only a few destroyers and submarines
                                    for operations in the Bay of Bengal. Furthermore, two months ago
                                    General Wavell promised General Stilwell the British could make
                                    seven divisions available to assist in the recapture of Burma.
                                    Now I learn that only three divisions are to be employed in
                                    limited operations with the objective of capturing Akyab and
                                    occupying the line of the Chindwin River. You can rely on the
                                    Chinese force being concentrated and ready for action on time in
                                    accordance with plans already made. I am sure the American air
                                    help for the campaign will be present. However, it is impossible
                                    to undertake the offensive with my troops unless the British
                                    carry out their part of the undertaking. All the principal
                                    United Nations spokesmen have pledged that Burma will be
                                    recovered in 1943. I therefore earnestly ask that you urge our
                                    British Allies to provide the necessary naval, air and land
                                    forces to carry out their part. <hi rend="italic">End of brief
                                        of Generalissimo’s message.</hi></p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>I understand that definite progress is being made not only in
                            preparations of the Chinese troops in India for the Burma Road operation
                            but also of the Chinese troops in Yunnan. Units are being reorganized
                            and equipped. Some of the supply essentials are even being flown in. I
                            feel that we must do something to ensure that the Chinese put their full
                            weight into the operations which are due to start in March. Can you
                            suggest any assurance which we can give Chiang Kai Shek which will have
                            this effect?</p>
                        <p>Offensive action by the Chinese and the timeliness of a thrust into Burma
                            this spring are all important. We also want to get started on our air
                            offensive from China against Jap sea lanes (if not Japan itself), the
                            moment sufficient and dependable communications over Burma warrant such
                            action.</p>
                        <p>That we may forfeit neither the Chinese potential nor the lift to United
                            Nations morale of early action in Burma, I would like to give the
                            Generalissimo the necessary assurances to prevent the Chinese <pb facs="0602" n="516" xml:id="pg_516"/> attack stalling. We might
                            together go over the substance of my reply to the Generalissimo
                                later.<note n="4" xml:id="d330fn4">
                                <p>Roosevelt acknowledged Chiang’s message of December 28, 1942, in
                                    the following message to Chiang dated January 2, 1943,
                                    transmitted through Stilwell in Chungking as telegram <gloss target="#t_AMMISCA1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ammisca</hi></gloss> No. 1942:</p>
                                <p>“The receipt is acknowledged of your message of December 28 in
                                    regard to the proposed Burma campaign.</p>
                                <p>“In view of the existing shortage in shipping and present
                                    difficulties in providing supplies and reinforcements at their
                                    great distance, it is my present thought that an opening of the
                                    Burma Road is more important at the present time to our war
                                    effort than an occupation of Southern Burma.</p>
                                <p>“It is my understanding that the light British naval vessels
                                    needed for operations in the Bay of Bengal are now being used to
                                    hunt Japanese ships in the vicinity of the Cape of Good Hope, a
                                    very necessary employment for them at the present time.</p>
                                <p>“I will definitely take up with the highest allied authorities at
                                    the earliest possible date the matter of opening the Burma Road
                                    without any avoidable delay.</p>
                                <p>“Please accept my warm personal regards and my wishes for great
                                    and final success in the New Year.” (Roosevelt Papers)</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Dill has seen this message.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Roosevelt</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>