<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941-43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-12-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-02-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-12-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="397" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d397">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>No official record of the substance of the discussion at this meeting has been
                    found. The brief accounts in Hopkins’ notes of January 24, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_839">p. 839</ref>, and in Pendar, <hi
                        rend="italic">Adventure in Diplomacy</hi>, p. 152, agree that the meeting
                    was given over to the final revision of the joint messages from Roosevelt and
                    Churchill to Stalin and Chiang. In information supplied to the Historical
                    Office, Harriman recalls that the one significant piece of business during the
                    Conference of which he had personal recollection related to this particular
                    meeting: “In the course of that evening, Hopkins prepared, with some suggestions
                    from me, drafts of joint messages from the President and Churchill which were to
                    be sent to Marshal Stalin and Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek, informing them of
                    the substance of their talks at Casablanca. The President and Churchill made
                    some changes in the text thus prepared and the messages were sent off.” Pendar’s
                    account describes the unusual circumstances in which the revision of the
                    documents was carried out. Hopkins’ account fixes the conclusion of the meeting
                    at 2 a.m. on January 25, while Pendar recalls that the documents were not in
                    final order until 3:30 a.m. For the final texts of the two messages, see <hi
                        rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_805">pp. 805</ref> and <ref
                        target="#pg_807">807</ref>, respectively. It is also probable that at this
                    meeting Roosevelt and Churchill concluded the drafting of their letter of
                    January 25, 1943, to the United States and British Chiefs of Staff, <hi
                        rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_808">p. 808</ref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
