<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-12-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-12-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="42" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d42">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Roosevelt Papers</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">White House Press Release</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d42fn1">Published in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, December 27,
                                1941, p. 573.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">immediate release</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-12-22">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">December</hi> 22, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>There is, of course, one primary objective in the conversations to be
                            held during the next few days between the President and the British
                            Prime Minister and the respective staffs of the two countries. That
                            purpose is the defeat of Hitlerism throughout the world.</p>
                        <p>It should be remembered that many other nations are engaged today in this
                            common task. Therefore, the present conferences in Washington should be
                            regarded as preliminary to further conferences which will officially
                            include Russia, China, the Netherlands and the Dominions. It is expected
                            that there will thus be evolved an over-all unity in the conduct of the
                            war. Other nations will be asked to participate to the best of their
                            ability in the over-all objective.</p>
                        <p>It is probable that no further announcements will be made until the end
                            of the present conferences,<note n="2" xml:id="d42fn2">Earlier on
                                December 22 the White House had released a brief statement to the
                                press, indicating that Churchill had arrived in Washington to
                                discuss “all questions relevant to the concerted war effort.” See
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, December 27, 1941, p. 573. On December
                                23 the White House released to the press a statement indicating that
                                Prime Minister Churchill’s first official engagement after being
                                received by the President was to meet with the representatives in
                                Washington of the British Dominions. See <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 573. Roosevelt issued a general statement on the
                                progress of the conference on the evening of December 27. See <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 578.</note> but it may be assumed
                            that the other interested nations will be kept in close touch with this
                            preliminary planning.</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>