<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>United States Minutes</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941-43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-01-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-01-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="99"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d99">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Defense Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Minutes</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_JCCS1">JCCS</gloss>s–8</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-01-10">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">January</hi> 10, 1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">1. <gloss target="#t_SuperGymnast1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Super Gymnast</hi>
                    </gloss>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Pound</hi> said that the British Chiefs of Staff
                    had made a careful examination of the various factors which affected the timing
                    of this operation, and the earliest date on which the first convoy could arrive
                    at Casablanca. He explained these to the Conference and undertook to let the
                    United States Chiefs of Staff have a note on the subject. So far as the British
                    were concerned, it appeared that if January 7 were taken as the date on which
                    planning really began, the earliest date for D–1 on which the decision to load
                    the first convoy could be given would be February 4. In this event the first
                    convoy would arrive at Algiers and Casablanca on D–28, that is, March 3,
                    depending upon the availability of shipping on that date. He also pointed out
                    that the whole undertaking would depend upon the planning, the shipping, and the
                    availability of troops and matériel. As to details at points of debarkation, <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Admiral Pound</hi> said that he anticipated no difficulty
                    in Algiers, and that in the British opinion, 29,000 men and 3,500 vehicles could
                    be unloaded at Casablanca in the fortnight.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> asked Admiral Pound if the British
                    could undertake both Casablanca and Algiers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Pound</hi> replied in the affirmative.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> then expressed some concern about the
                    availability of shipping for the second convoy and undertook to confirm that
                    January 7 could be accepted, from the American point of view, as the date on
                    which planning began.</p>
                <p rend="center">2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Directive for the Supreme Commander of the
                            <gloss target="#t_ABDA1">ABDA</gloss> Area—Attitude of the Dutch</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Stark</hi> recalled that certain amendments to
                    Annex 2 of the draft directive for General Wavell had been proposed by the
                    British in order to meet certain points raised by the Dutch.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d99fn1">See the letter from Hollis to Hopkins. January 5. 1942. <hi
                            rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_304">p. 304</ref>.</note>
                    These had not yet been accepted by the Dutch, but had been approved by the
                    President and the Prime Minister. He confirmed that these proposed amendments
                    were acceptable to the United States Chiefs of Staff.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> said that the Dutch representative in
                    Washington had come into the War Department a good deal over the question of the
                    Dutch position. It appeared that the population of the Netherlands <pb
                        facs="0247" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/> East Indies were feeling rather hurt
                    at not having been consulted over the question of supreme command. They did not
                    consider that the Dutch Government in London was fully representative of them.
                    Some trouble had also been caused through the omission from General Wavell’s
                    directive of any instruction to set up his Headquarters in Java. In the original
                    communication to the Dutch Government, which proposed the setting up of a
                    Supreme Commander, a passage to this effect had been included.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d99fn2">The “original communication” to the Netherlands Government,
                        as well as to the Governments of Australia and New Zealand, was made by the
                        British Government on January 2, 1942; see the statement in ABC–4/CS3,
                            <gloss target="#t_WW1">WW</gloss>–9 (Revised), <hi rend="italic"
                            >post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_317">p. 317</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Every endeavor had been made by <hi rend="smallcaps">Brigadier General Gerow</hi>
                    to smooth down the feelings of the Dutch representative in Washington and to
                    induce him to fall in with the agreed views of the United States and British
                    Chiefs of Staff,<note n="3" xml:id="d99fn3">See the letter from Gerow to Loudon,
                        January 2, 1942, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_303">p.
                            303</ref>. See also Roosevelt’s memorandum of January 9 to Marshall, <hi
                            rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_313">p. 313</ref>.</note> but
                    in view of the fact that negotiations with the Dutch Government were being
                    conducted by the British, the position was somewhat embarrassing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Pound</hi> expressed the appreciation of the
                    British Chiefs of Staff for the way in which the United States Staffs were
                    dealing with this matter. A telegram had been sent to General Wavell instructing
                    him to set up his Headquarters in Java,<note n="4" xml:id="d99fn4">Not
                        printed.</note> and in fact, he was establishing himself at Batavia on
                    January 10.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Chiefs of Staff</hi> took cognizance of the prior
                    approval of ABC–4/5, <gloss target="#t_WW1">WW</gloss> 6, with Annex 2 amended,
                    and also of the fact that further amendments would possibly be made upon reply
                    from the Dutch and Australian Governments. (See Annex 1)<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d99fn5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_313">p. 313</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Procedure for the Assumption of Command by
                        General Wavell</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Conference</hi> had before it an amendment by the
                    British Chiefs of Staff on the procedure for the assumption of command of
                    General Wavell (US–ABC–4/CS–3, British <gloss target="#t_WW1"
                        >WW</gloss>–9).<note n="6" xml:id="d99fn6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_317">p. 317</ref>.</note>
                    Various minor amendments were agreed to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral King</hi> suggested that it would be advisable to
                    insert in the draft telegram to General Wavell a sentence to indicate that
                    instructions were being sent to Admiral Hart and General Brett telling them to
                    report to him for duty in their respective posts. The following addition to the
                    draft telegram at Annex B was accordingly agreed to:</p>
                <p>“General Brett and Admiral Hart are being ordered by the United States Government
                    to report to you as Deputy Supreme Commander <pb facs="0248" n="174"
                        xml:id="pg_174"/> and Commander of the Combined Naval Forces in the <gloss
                        target="#t_ABDA1">ABDA</gloss> area respectively.”<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d99fn7">The revised draft telegram is <hi rend="italic">post</hi>,
                            <ref target="#pg_318">p. 318</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It was agreed: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>That the draft telegram in Annex C to the Memorandum by the British
                            Chiefs of Staff should be dispatched forthwith. (See Annex 2)<note n="8"
                                xml:id="d99fn8">The annexed paper was ABC–4/CS3, <gloss
                                    target="#t_WW1">WW</gloss>–9 (Revised), <hi rend="italic"
                                    >post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_317">p. 317</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>That the procedure proposed in the Memorandum should be adopted and
                            the Memorandum, subject to the amendments agreed upon in discussion,
                            should be approved. (See Annex 2)<note n="8" xml:id="d99fn13">The
                                annexed paper was ABC–4/CS3, <gloss target="#t_WW1">WW</gloss>–9
                                (Revised), <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_317">p.
                                    317</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">4. <hi rend="smallcaps">Immediate Assistance to China</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Conference</hi> had before it a memorandum received
                    from the United States Chiefs of Staff on immediate assistance to China.
                    (ABC–4/9, <gloss target="#t_WW1">WW</gloss>(<gloss target="#t_JPC1"
                        >J.P.C.</gloss>)9).<note n="9" xml:id="d99fn9">The paper, as revised and
                        approved, was serialized as ABC–4/9, <gloss target="#t_WW1">WW</gloss>–10,
                        dated January 10, 1942, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_319"
                            >p. 319</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Pound</hi> said that the British Chiefs of Staff
                    recognized the importance of doing everything possible to facilitate assistance
                    to China, and were in general agreement with the proposals in the paper. They
                    wished to suggest certain amendments to it, which were designed to make it
                    conform to the idea of Unity of Command.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The British Chiefs of Staff</hi> proposed certain
                    amendments, which were discussed at some length.</p>
                <p>At the suggestion of <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> the word
                    “operate” in the fourth line of the first amendment was altered to “engage in
                    joint operation”. Similarly in the last line but one of the second amendment the
                    words “General Wavell” were altered to “the Supreme Commander in the <gloss
                        target="#t_ABDA1">ABDA</gloss> Area”.</p>
                <p>The following further amendment was agreed to.</p>
                <p>On page 3, paragraph 4, line 5, the words “General Drum” were amended to read,
                    “the United States Representative”.<note n="10" xml:id="d99fn10">For the initial
                        consideration of sending Drum to China, see Romanus and Sunderland, pp.
                        63–70.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshal Dill</hi> suggested that the United States
                    Representative in China might be informed of the existence and scope of the
                    organization which had been built up in China under General Dennys. He undertook
                    to forward a note on this point to General Marshall.<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d99fn11">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Conference</hi> approved the memorandum on immediate
                    assistance to China as amended in discussion. (See Annex 3)<note n="9"
                        xml:id="d99fn14">The paper, as revised and approved, was serialized as
                        ABC–4/9, <gloss target="#t_WW1">WW</gloss>–10, dated January 10, 1942, <hi
                            rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_319">p. 319</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">5. <hi rend="smallcaps">Post-<gloss target="#t_Arcadia1"
                            >Arcadia</gloss> Collaboration</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This paper was brought up by British Chiefs of Staff and discussed briefly. (See
                    Annex 4)<note n="12" xml:id="d99fn12">The paper under reference is <gloss
                            target="#t_WW1">WW</gloss>–8, dated January 8, 1942, <hi rend="italic"
                            >post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_217">p. 217</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0249" n="175" xml:id="pg_175"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Conference</hi> adjourned at 5:30 P.M., to meet at 4:00
                    P.M., January 11, 1942.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
