<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Denby to Mr. Olney..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1895p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1895-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1895-10-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-10-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="168"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d168">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Olney</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-10-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 4, 1895</hi>
                        </date>. (Received Nov. 19.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2385.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that upon
                    representation being made to me by the American missionaries residing at Taiku,
                    in the province of Shansi, that trouble was apprehended, I addressed the Yamên
                    on the subject and demanded that repressive and precautionary measures be
                    immediately taken.</p>
                <p>I inclose the Yamên’s reply, from which it appears that the local authorities
                    have been ordered “to examine into the matter and take precautions against
                    disturbances and to make earnest efforts to protect foreigners.”</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 2385.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Tsung-li Yamên</gloss> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Denby</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-10-03">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">October</hi> 3, 1895</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: We have had the honor to receive your
                        communication, wherein you state that at Taiku and vicinity, in the province
                        of Shansi, cartoons of the war are being offered for sale, and it is being
                        asserted that all the foreign powers were engaged in hostilities with China.
                        You state that reports of this character tend to excite the populace, and
                        that if measures are not taken to hold them in check trouble will arise. You
                        request us to instruct the local officials of that vicinity to issue
                        proclamations informing the people that the cartoons and their narratives
                        are mere fabrications, in order that the people and the missions may remain
                        in harmony, and that the foreigners residing there may be protected.</p>
                    <p>Upon receipt of your dispatch we at once perceived that reports of this
                        character might very easily cause trouble, and it therefore became our duty
                        to telegraph to the provincial authorities to examine into the matter and
                        take precautions against disturbances, and to make earnest efforts to
                        protect foreigners, and thus prevent the occurrence of mishaps. We also send
                        this note for your excellency’s information.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
