<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Thompson to Mr. Olney..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1895p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1895-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1895-08-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-08-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="56"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Thompson</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Olney</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Petropolis</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-08-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 7, 1895</hi>
                        </date>. (Received Aug. 30.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 393.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my No. 391, of July 30, 1895, in
                    regard to the occupation of the island of Trinidad by a British force and
                    inclosing a copy of the published correspondence on the subject between the
                    minister for foreign affairs and the British minister accredited to this
                    Government, I now have the honor to inclose a translation of that correspondence
                    which appeared in the Rio News of July 30.</p>
                <p>There are no further developments of importance, and, as stated in my former
                    dispatch, the matter awaits the consideration of the British Government.</p>
                <p>Meetings of protest and indignation continue to be held throughout the States,
                    and the entire country is aroused to the apparently unjust and untenable
                    pretensions of Great Britain.</p>
                <p>Our Government has come in for some criticism by the local press on account of
                    the supposed knowledge we had of the occupation at the time and the absurd
                    report that the British took it only in anticipation of an American occupation
                    which had been planned and was about to take place.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas L. Thompson</hi>
                    </signed>.</closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 393.—Extracts from Rio
                            News.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Document A</hi>.—Telegram.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">To the Brazilian Legation, London:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Financial News gives account of occupation of island of Trinidad in name of
                        English Government. Inform without delay.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister of Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Document B</hi>.—Telegram.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>, <hi rend="italic">21, 7, ʼ95</hi>.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister of Foreign Affairs, Rio:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Lord Salisbury absent. Learned from foreign office that island of Trinidad
                        has been occupied in name of Government since last January for Argentine
                        submarine cable; no publicity nor official notification. First English
                        occupation 1700, Dr. Halley. English colony established 1781; afterwards
                        abandoned our people, English immigrants, 1789. Since then regular visit
                        English war vessels, last being <hi rend="italic">Ruby</hi> 1889, which left
                        signs of visit without protest any nation. It is asserted there was no
                        vestige of other occupation.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Correa</hi>.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Document C.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On the 19th instant I had the honor of learning from Mr. Constantine Phipps,
                        envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of Her Britannic Majesty,
                        in regard to the account published by various journals of the occupation of
                        the island of Trinidad in the Atlantic Ocean between South America and the
                        west coast of Africa by subjects of Her Majesty, that the report did not,
                        seem to him to be unfounded. I immediately remarked that since this island
                        belonged to the Republic of the United States of Brazil, the occupation
                        would be illegitimate and inoperative (nao poderia prevalecer). I asserted
                        that such control was inadmissible, as I would prove at the <pb facs="0126"
                            n="66" xml:id="pg_66"/> proper time. I informed him that not only had I
                        telegraphed to the Brazilian legation at London for information on the
                        subject, but also that the public mind would be agitated at a time like this
                        in which other facts of an international character are moving and exciting
                        the natural and noble feeling of nationality.</p>
                    <p>The Paiz having on the following day announced the intention of the Federal
                        Government to send to that island a war vessel for the purpose of
                        ascertaining whether the occupation had been really effected, Mr. Phipps had
                        the courtesy to call on me at 3 o’clock p.m. to say that, more fully
                        informed, he was able to state that since last February the island had been
                        occupied in the name of the English Crown as abandoned territory on which
                        there were no signs of its possession by any other nation. I did not conceal
                        my surprise, not to say annoyance, on hearing this, and I renewed the
                        statements which I had made on the previous day, supported by historical
                        antecedents and the evidence of geographers.</p>
                    <p>All doubt as to the reality of the occupation being thus removed, Mr. Phipps
                        said that it would be well to suspend the order for sending the man-of-war,
                        since he would inform his Government of my remarks and within forty-eight
                        hours would probably receive instructions for his guidance in regard to this
                        incident, so disagreeable to the relations which are fortunately maintained
                        between the two countries, Brazil and England.</p>
                    <p>I now proceed to perform the duty of stating here, as I promised Mr. Phipps,
                        the reasons which led me to classify as illegitimate the recent occupation
                        of the island of Trinidad. Permit me, however, to say, in the first place,
                        that by telegram received yesterday the Brazilian legation in London
                        informed me that it had learned from the foreign office that the occupation
                        took place in last January in the name of the English Government for the
                        service of the Argentine submarine cable, without publicity or any
                        notification whatever.</p>
                    <p>The island of Trinidad, as Mr. Phipps is aware, is situated in 20° 31ʹ south
                        latitude and 13° 47ʹ 57" longitude east from Rio de Janeiro, and according
                        to the Practice of Navigation and Nautical Astronomy of H. Rapper
                        (lieutenant, Royal Navy, 7 London, 1862), is 651 geographical miles from the
                        point situated in the same latitude on the coast of the State of Espirito
                        Santo. It was discovered in 1501 by the Portuguese, and it was only on April
                        15, 1700, that the English captain, Edmund Halley, arrived there, J. Cook
                        touching there on his second voyage, on May 31, 1775.</p>
                    <p>In 1781 the Government of Great Britain, being then at war with that of
                        Spain, caused the island to be occupied for the purpose of harassing the
                        Spanish trade with the colonies of the Plate. This led to serious complaints
                        addressed by Spain to Portugal, which ordered the viceroy of Brazil to send
                        an expedition to cause it to be disoccupied. There was then formed, in the
                        year 1782, a Portuguese military establishment, and on the 16th of September
                        of that year the viceroy received orders to open regular communications with
                        the island.</p>
                    <p>In the voyage of La Perouse in 1785, a Portuguese flag was seen on a
                        mountain, and it was only on February 6, 1795, that the detachment and arms
                        were withdrawn, being conveyed by the frigate <hi rend="italic">Princeza da
                            Beira</hi>, which arrived at Rio de Janeiro on October 11 of the same
                        year.</p>
                    <p>With the independence of Brazil the island of Trinidad ceased to belong to
                        Portugal.</p>
                    <p>In 1825 the Brazilian corvette <hi rend="italic">Itaparica</hi>, commanded by
                        Capt. Diogo Jorge de Brito, visited the island in commission of the
                        Brazilian Government. In 1831 the regency in the name of the Emperor caused
                        surveys and investigations to be made with a view to making use of the
                        Islands. Moreover, in commission from the Government, the corvette <hi
                            rend="italic">D. Isabel</hi> visited it in 1856, the corvette <hi
                            rend="italic">Bahiana</hi> in 1871, the corvette <hi rend="italic"
                            >Nictheroy</hi> in the same year and in 1884, and recently the transport
                            <hi rend="italic">Penedo</hi>, in April, 1894, under the command of
                        first lieutenant of the navy, Joaquin Sarmanho.</p>
                    <p>Before sending the transport <hi rend="italic">Penedo</hi> on this commission
                        in 1894 the Government of the Republic had taken steps intended to make use
                        of the island for penitentiary service, as appears from dispatches from the
                        department of justice, dated July 11 and October 14, 1891.</p>
                    <p>Not to mention Pierre Larousse (Dict. Univ. T. XV), Malte-Brun and Elisee
                        Reclus (the latter as late as 1894) enumerate the island of Trinidad among
                        the possessions of Brazil.</p>
                    <p>I must also state to Mr. Phipps that under the regime of the Empire the
                        Brazilian Government, by Decree No. 9334, of November 29, 1884, granted
                        permission to Citizen Joao Alves Guerm to explore mines, extract natural
                        products, and establish salt pits on the island of Trinidad, considering it
                        a dependence of what was then the province of Espirito Santo. All this is
                        conclusive.</p>
                    <p>Occupation is a legitimate method of acquiring domination only with relation
                        to things that have no owner, res nullius, and such are those which are not
                        under the dominion of anyone else, either from never having belonged to
                        anyone or from having been abandoned by their former owner.</p>
                    <p>In conformity with the rule of nemo suum jactare proosumitur, abandonment is
                        something which is not to be presumed. It depends on the intention of
                        relinquishing, <pb facs="0127" n="67" xml:id="pg_67"/> or on the cessation
                        of physical power over the thing, and must not be confounded with simple
                        neglect or desertion. A proprietor may leave a thing deserted or neglected
                        and still retain his ownership. The fact of legal possession does not
                        consist in actually holding a thing, but in having it at one’s free
                        disposal. The absence of the proprietor, neglect, or desertion does not
                        exclude free disposal, and hence animo retinctur possessio.</p>
                    <p>Gaius (Inst. C. 4, sec. 154) teaches * * * “quoniam possidemus animo solo
                        quum volumus retinere possessionem.”</p>
                    <p>“Neque vero deseri locum aliquem satis est, ut pro derelicto habendus sit,
                        sed manifestis apparent indicus derelinquendi affectio,” adds Muhlenbruck.
                        (Doctrina pandect, secs. 241 and 251.</p>
                    <p>Abandonment can only result from the expressed manifestation of the will, for
                        the animus is the possibility of repeating the first will to acquire
                        possession, and, as Savigny teaches (sec. 32), there is no necessity of
                        having constantly the consciousness of possession. Abandonment requires a
                        new act of the will in a contrary direction to that of the first will,
                        animus, in contrarium actus. “Pro derelicto autem hebetus quod dominius ea
                        mente adjecerit ut id rerum suarurm est molit,” in the language of the
                        Institute.</p>
                    <p>When the thing whose abandonment is alleged in order to legitimize occupation
                        belongs to the dominion of a nation, still more rigorous becomes the
                        necessity of causing the act to rest on some positive and express
                        manifestation of the will of the owner, showing that he does not desire to
                        continue in possession, for in questions of territorial dominion abandonment
                        is not to be presumed. The presumption is not that the thing is a res
                        nullius, as in the case of the Institute. “Insula quae in mare nata est
                        (quod raro accidit) occupantis fit: nullius enim esse creditur.”</p>
                    <p>If the island of Trinidad was discovered by the Portuguese, whose military
                        occupation thereof continued until 1795; if the facts are historical (and
                        the memory of nations excludes the idea of their being unknown); if the
                        Government by public and positive acts has always shown its conviction that
                        the island of Trinidad is national territory, then the condition of res
                        nullius, which justifies occupation, does not exist.</p>
                    <p>Possession is lost corpore only when the ability to dispose of a thing is
                        rendered completely impossible, after the disappearance of the status which
                        permits the owner to dispose of the thing possessed.</p>
                    <p>If Brazil has not displayed by any express act the intention (vontade) of
                        abandoning the island, which had been adjudicated to the Brazilian continent
                        by the act of this country’s acquiring its political independence; if there
                        does not exist, as Mr. Phipps will agree, a status preventing it from
                        disposing or making use of the island when and as it pleases; if Brazil has
                        preserved intact, together with its dominion, its possession of that island,
                        which is not a res pro derelicto, then its occupation in the name of the
                        English Government is not a legitimate means of acquiring dominion.</p>
                    <p>Presenting these reflections to Mr. Phipps, I believe that he will not
                        decline to lay them before the Government of Her Majesty, the Queen of
                        England, as a protest against the occupation of the island of Trinidad,
                        which forms a part of Brazilian territory, and I am convinced that, after
                        the removal of the mistaken impression that the said island was abandoned
                        and consequently res nullius, that Government will issue orders for its
                        disoccupation, which will be due homage to the principles of justice and
                        will once more emphasize the mutual desire of the two countries, Brazil and
                        England, to maintain unaltered the relations between them.</p>
                    <p>However little may be the value of the island of Trinidad, the Federal
                        Government considers itself bound to act in this way, for in any case, if
                        there were conscious or intentional wrong national honor would not be less
                        affected.</p>
                    <p>I renew to Monsieur le Ministre the assurances of my high consideration.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Carlos de Carvalho</hi>.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Document D.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Petropolis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">July 20,
                        1895</hi>.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Monsieur le Ministre</hi>: I did not fail, subsequent
                        to my interview with your excellency on Friday and Saturday last, to
                        communicate to Her Majesty’s principal secretary of state for foreign
                        affairs your excellency’s observations relative to the assumption by Her
                        Majesty’s Government of the island of Trinidad.</p>
                    <p>I am instructed to inform your excellency that the possession of the island
                        in question was first taken by Great Britain in the year 1700. No evidence
                        was then found of Portuguese possession and no protest was made by Portugal.
                        In the opinion, therefore, of the Marqius of Salisbury there can not be any
                        Brazilian title to the island superior to that of Great Britain.</p>
                    <p>When Her Majesty’s Government resumed possession of that island and of Martin
                        Vaz in January last no trace of foreign occupation was found, and as
                        Trinidad is required as a telegraph cable station Her Majesty’s Government
                        can not consent to waive their rights to it. I have great pleasure in
                        informing Lord Salisbury that your excellency had, in the most friendly
                        manner, shared the view which I did myself the honor of expressing, that it
                        was inexpedient, pending my reference of the question <pb facs="0128" n="68"
                            xml:id="pg_68"/> to Her Majesty’s Government, that a Brazilian ship of
                        war should he sent to Trinidad, and I feel convinced that your excellency
                        will not fail to perceive that there can now be no question of sending a
                        ship to assert a right to sovereignty over an island in the possession of
                        Her Majesty’s Government.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself of the opportunity, Monsieur le Ministre, to renew to your
                        excellency the assurances of my very high consideration.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Con. Phipps</hi>.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Document E.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">[2d section, No. 22.]</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Rio de Janeiro, July 23, 1895</hi>.</p>
                    <p>At this moment, 25 minutes to 1 o’clock p.m., I have the honor of receiving
                        the note dated the 20th instant, in which Mr. Constantine Phipps, envoy
                        extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of Her Britannic Majesty,
                        communicates to me, by order of his Government, that possession of the
                        island of Trinidad Was first taken by Great Britain in the year 1700 without
                        protest from Portugal, and that, consequently, in the opinion of Lord
                        Salisbury, principal secretary of state for foreign affairs, there can not
                        be any Brazilian title to the island superior to that of Great Britain. Mr.
                        Phipps adds that the Government of Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain,
                        having occupied the island of Trinidad and that of Martin Vaz for the
                        purpose of maintaining there a telegraph station, can not consent to
                        relinquish its right thereto.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Phipps will permit me to say in the reply to be transmitted to Lord
                        Salisbury, that the best proof of the right of Brazil to the island of
                        Trinidad is the solemn, positive, and practical acknowledgment of that right
                        by the English Admiralty, which, on August 22, 1782, issued peremptory
                        orders to the English officer in charge of the island of Trinidad to
                        evacuate it forthwith and deliver it to the Portuguese Government as a part
                        of the possessions of the Kingdom of Portugal in South America subject to
                        the viceroyalty of Brazil.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Phipps will thus see that Lord Salisbury, in dating the English title
                        from the year 1700, in which Capt. Edmund Halley touched at the island of
                        Trinidad, discovered by the Portuguese in the beginning of the sixteenth
                        century, labors under a mistake which may be readily corrected by having
                        recourse to documents in the archives of the British Government.</p>
                    <p>I present to Mr. Phipps’s consideration a copy of the instructions given to
                        the captain commanding the ship <hi rend="italic">N. S. dos Prazeres</hi>,
                        on December 7, 1782, by the viceroy of Brazil, Luiz de Vasconcellos Souza,
                        for the military establishment on the island of Trinidad which was to
                        follow, as it actually did follow, the withdrawal of the English forces that
                        were intrusively occupying the island. All this the viceroy communicated to
                        his Government on December 20 of the same year.</p>
                    <p>By these instructions Mr. Phipps will see that Great Britain yielded to
                        justice and reason in disoccupying the island of Trinidad and proclaiming
                        the rights to which Brazil succeeded in virtue of its political independence
                        and in view of the island being under the jurisdiction of the government of
                        Rio de Janeiro.</p>
                    <p>The title of 1700, alleged by Lord Salisbury, can not resist the evidence of
                        anterior and posterior facts.</p>
                    <p>I also submit to Mr. Phipps’s appreciation the royal letter of February 22,
                        1724, in which D. John, King of Portugal, gave orders for taking steps to
                        prevent the English company of Guinea from using the island of Trinidad for
                        the slave trade. It was undoubtedly a solemn protest against the act of
                        Captain Halley in 1700.</p>
                    <p>I appeal, as behooves me, to the sentiments of justice of the Government of
                        the Queen of Great Britain to remove this cause of disturbance in the
                        friendly relations that it maintains with the Republic of the United States
                        of Brazil. I have no doubt that, after the verification of what I state, the
                        Government of Her Britannic Majesty will spontaneously order the evacuation
                        of the island, as it did in 1782.</p>
                    <p>And, since Mr. Phipps in the concluding part of his note alludes to the
                        suggestion, which he made to me, of suspending the order for sending a war
                        vessel for the purpose of investigating what is occurring there, and
                        declares that, in view of what is set forth in the name of his Government,
                        there is no longer any necessity for sending it to ascertain whether in
                        occupying the island Her Majesty’s Government is performing an act of
                        sovereignty, I earnestly protest against that assertion, reserving all and
                        any rights of the Republic of the United States of Brazil; and I beg
                        permission to say to Mr. Phipps, confirming what I verbally declared to him
                        to-day, at 11.30 a.m., that, strong in the consciousness of its right, the
                        Republic of the United States of Brazil will not abandon it, confiding, in
                        the first place (antes de tudo), in the sentiments of the Government of Her
                        Majesty the Queen of England.</p>
                    <p>I renew, Mr. Minister, the assurances of my high consideration.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Carlos de Carvalho</hi>.</p>
                    <pb facs="0129" n="69" xml:id="pg_69"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Document F.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Order issued by the Admiralty of Great Britain for
                            disoccupying the island of Trinidad.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">By the commissioners who hold the office of the Lord High
                        Admiral of Great Britain, Ireland, etc.</p>
                    <p>In obedience to the order of the King, which was communicated to us by Lord
                        Grantham, one of the principal secretaries of state of His Majesty, you are
                        ordered by the present Government to evacuate the island of Trinidad and
                        embark with His Majesty’s subjects and effects there existing on board the
                        vessel which shall deliver you this order, so that you and they may be
                        conveyed to Lisbon, or to England, as may be most expedient to the court of
                        Portugal.</p>
                    <p>Given under our signet on the 22d day of August, 1782.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Keppel</hi>.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ch. Brett</hi>.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">T. I. Pratt</hi>.</p>
                    <p>To Capt. Philip d’Auvergne, or to the officer commanding His Majesty’s
                        Britannic forces, left on the island of Trinidad by Commodore Johnstone.</p>
                    <p>By order of their lordships:</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ph. Stephens</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Three documents in addition to the foregoing accompany the second note of
                        Minister Carlos de Carvalho.</p>
                    <p>The first of these three documents is a copy of the instructions given by the
                        viceroy of Brazil on December 7, 1782, to the commander of the ship <hi
                            rend="italic">Nossa Senhora dos Prazeres</hi>, who is placed in charge
                        of an expedition composed of his own vessel and a frigate, together with
                        three transports, and is ordered to proceed to the island of Trinidad,
                        deliver to the English commander of that island the order of the Admiralty
                        for its evacuation, and take on board the British subjects occupying it,
                        using force if, for unknown reasons, they should fail to obey the order.</p>
                    <p>The next document is a dispatch from the viceroy of Brazil to the Portuguese
                        Government, dated December 20, 1782, giving an account of the preparations
                        for the expedition and of its departure on the 16th of that month.</p>
                    <p>The last of the documents offered by the Brazilian minister of foreign
                        affairs as a proof of Portuguese dominion in the island is a royal letter,
                        dated February 22, 1724, and addressed by the Portuguese Government to the
                        captain-general of Rio de Janeiro. This letter alludes to information
                        received by that Government of the landing of English on Trinidad for the
                        purpose of colonizing the island. The vessel which left these colonists
                        proceeded to Ilha Grande for the purpose of trading. This purpose it failed
                        to accomplish because it was twice driven away by Portuguese forces. It then
                        returned to the port of Ajuda and landed its merchandise. The English
                        afterwards loaded with slaves a vessel belonging to the Guinea company,
                        which was supposed to have proceeded to the coast of Brazil.</p>
                    <p>The Portuguese Government expresses the belief that the object of the English
                        in colonizing Trinidad is to land slaves there, on account of the facility
                        with which the latter may be conveyed from that point to Ilha Grande. It
                        accordingly issues orders for preventing the harm which this trade, in its
                        opinion, would cause to Portugal and Brazil.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
