<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-05-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="562" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d562">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Instructions to Sir Julian Pauncefote.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                        Office</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-05-17"><hi rend="italic">May 17,
                                1895</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 93.]</seg></opener>
                        <p rend="center">[Handed to Mr. Uhl by Sir Julian Pauncefote, May 27,
                            1895.]</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your excellency’s
                            dispatch, No. 29, of the 24th January, Inclosing a note from Mr.
                            Gresham, of the 23d January,<note n="1" xml:id="d562fn1">See <ref target="frus1894app1#pg_226">Foreign Relations 1894, Appendix 1,
                                    p. 226</ref>.</note> relative <pb facs="0679" n="619" xml:id="pg_619"/> to the operation of the regulations laid down by
                            the Paris Tribunal of Arbitration for the fur-seal fishery, and the view
                            entertained by the President of the United States that, the regulations
                            having failed in their object, further provisions are required to
                            preserve the herd from extermination.</p>
                        <p>In order to avert this result Mr. Gresham had been directed to
                            propose:</p>
                        <p>That a commission should be appointed by the Governments of Great
                            Britain, the United States, Russia, and Japan, consisting of one or more
                            men from each country, eminent for scientific knowledge and practical
                            acquaintance with the fur trade. This commission should visit the
                            Asiatic side of the North Pacific as well as the American, and also the
                            islands which the seals frequent, and report to their respective
                            Governments as to the effect of pelagic sealing on the herd and the
                            proper measures needed to regulate such sealing so as to protect the
                            herd from destruction and permit it to increase in such numbers as to
                            permanently furnish an annual supply of skins.</p>
                        <p>That during the deliberations of this commission the respective
                            Governments should agree upon a modus vivendi as follows:</p>
                        <p>“That the regulations now in force be extended along the line of the
                            thirty-fifth degree of north latitude, from the American to the Asiatic
                            shore, and be enforced during the coming season in the whole of the
                            Pacific Ocean and waters north of that line. Furthermore, that sealing
                            in Bering Sea be absolutely prohibited pending the report of such
                            commission.”</p>
                        <p>Her Majesty’s Government have given the facts set forth by Mr. Gresham in
                            support of these proposals their most serious consideration, but after
                            examining attentively the figures and information at their disposal they
                            have come to the conclusion that the condition of affairs is not of so
                            urgent a character as the President has been led to believe.</p>
                        <p>In the second paragraph of his note Mr. Gresham states: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>It would appear that there were landed in the United States and
                                    Victoria 121,143 skins, and that the total pelagic catch, as
                                    shown by the London trade sales and careful estimates of skins
                                    transshipped in Japanese and Russian ports, amounts to about
                                    142,000, a result unprecedented in pelagic sealing. It would
                                    further appear that the vessels engaged in Bering Sea, although
                                    only one-third of the total number employed in the North
                                    Pacific, in four or five weeks killed 31,585 seals—not only over
                                    8,000 more than were killed in Bering Sea in 1891 (the last year
                                    the sea was open), but even more than the total number killed
                                    during the four months on the American side of the North Pacific
                                    this season.</p></quote></p>
                        <p>He goes on to say— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>This startling increase in the pelagic slaughter of both the
                                    American and Asiatic herds has convinced the President, and, it
                                    is respectfully submitted, can not fail to convince Her
                                    Majesty’s Government, tha tthe regulations enacted by the Paris
                                    Tribunal have not operated to protect the seal herd from that
                                    destruction which they were designed to prevent, and that unless
                                    a speedy change in the regulations be brought about,
                                    extermination of the herd must follow. Such a deplorable result
                                    should, if possible, be averted.</p></quote></p>
                        <p>I must, in the first place, observe that arguments based on figures which
                            include the pelagic catch on the Asiatic or western side of the Pacific
                            are calculated to lead to erroneous conclusions as to the working of the
                            regulations, and as to their effect on the seals frequenting the
                            Pribilof Islands.</p>
                        <p>There can be no doubt that there has been a large increase in the number
                            of seals taken off the Japanese coast last year in comparison to any
                            previous year. The total number taken there in 1893 was only a <pb facs="0680" n="620" xml:id="pg_620"/> little over 29,000, while last
                            year it appears from the returns to have been not less than 51,000.</p>
                        <p>But no point has been more constantly insisted upon by those who have
                            examined and argued the question on behalf of the United States than
                            that the seals frequenting the eastern and western sides of the Pacific
                            form two absolutely distinct bodies or “herds,” and do not intermingle.
                            In the opinion of the experts and counsel employed on behalf of Great
                            Britain this doctrine was pushed too far. They held that a certain
                            amount of intermingling might and indeed did take place in Bering Sea.
                            But though our knowledge of seal life is still far from complete, it may
                            certainly be held as tolerably established that the two main bodies of
                            seals are distinct, and that increased pelagic catch on the Japanese
                            coast does not constitute a serious menace to the seals frequenting the
                            Pribilof Islands.</p>
                        <p>Whether that increased catch can be continued without serious diminution
                            of seal life on the Asiatic side is a question which has still to be
                            tested by experience.</p>
                        <p>For the present the regulations apply to the eastern side only, and their
                            success or failure must be judged solely by their effect on the herd
                            which they were intended to protect. I proceed, therefore, to examine
                            that effect as shown by the figures in the possession of Her Majesty’s
                            Government.</p>
                        <p>From the table printed at page 207 of the report of the British
                            commissioners, it appears that in the years 1889, 1890, and 1891 the
                            pelagic catch on the eastern side was as follows: <table cols="2" rows="3">
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1889</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">42,870</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1890</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">51,560</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1891</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">68,000</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table></p>
                        <p>These figures include the catch of both British and American vessels.</p>
                        <p>The figures of the American catch for later years are not available, but
                            the Canadian catch on the eastern side in 1891, 1892, 1893, and 1894 are
                            given in the official report as follows: <table cols="4" rows="2">
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1891</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">52,995</cell>
                                    <cell>1893</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">28,613</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1892</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">39,107</cell>
                                    <cell>1894</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">38,044</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table></p>
                        <p>The American catch for 1894 on the eastern side is given in the table
                            inclosed in Mr. Gresham’s other note, forwarded in your excellency’s
                            dispatch No. 29, as 17,558, so that the total catch on that side last
                            year was 55,602. This, as contrasted with the catch of 1891, shows a
                            diminution of about 12,500.</p>
                        <p>In that year, though the modus vivendi was partly in force, the Canadian
                            catch in Bering Sea was 29,146, whereas in 1894 it was only 26,425. This
                            shows a diminution of about 10 per cent in the catch.</p>
                        <p>Her Majesty’s Government have no returns of the American pelagic catch in
                            Bering Sea in the season of 1891, and are therefore unable to make a
                            comparison between the total catch there in that year and in 1894. They
                            are unable to understand on what grounds Mr. Gresham has stated the
                            total in 1891 to have been less than 23,585 when, according to their
                            information, the Canadian catch alone was 29,146.</p>
                        <p>Turning, now, to the number of vessels employed in the fishery, these do
                            not appear to have increased, but, on the contrary, to have
                            decreased.</p>
                        <p>There are no trustworthy figures available as to the United States
                            sealing vessels previous to those now furnished for 1894 by Mr. Gresham,
                            but there are full official returns with regard to the Canadian sealing
                                <pb facs="0681" n="621" xml:id="pg_621"/> fleet, and the following
                            table, showing the numbers and operations of the fleet during the last
                            four years, is interesting in this connection: <table cols="6" rend="bordered" rows="6">
                                <row>
                                    <cell rows="2">Year.</cell>
                                    <cell rows="2">Number.</cell>
                                    <cell rows="2">Tonnage.</cell>
                                    <cell cols="2">Number of hunters.</cell>
                                    <cell rows="2">Total catch on both sides of Pacific.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>White.</cell>
                                    <cell>Indian.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1891</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">51</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">3,378</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">716</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">336</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">50,495</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1892</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">66</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">4,456</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">961</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">511</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">46,362</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1893</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">55</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">3,743</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">847</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">432</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">68,231</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1894</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">59</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">3,866</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">888</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">518</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">90,485</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table></p>
                        <p>It will be seen from these figures that the number of Canadian vessels
                            and the number of hunters employed on them last season is below that of
                            1892, the great falling off in 1893 being due to wrecks and seizure of
                            vessels in the previous year.</p>
                        <p>As regards the total number of vessels, both British and American,
                            employed in the fishery, these are given at page 185 of the United
                            States case before the Tribunal of Arbitration as 115 in 1891 and 123 in
                            1892, while in 1894 they were only 92—a most material decrease.</p>
                        <p>The number of vessels and of men employed on them having thus decreased,
                            while the total catch on both sides of the Pacific has undoubtedly
                            increased, it is clear that there has been a general increase in the
                            average catch per man and per vessel. This is no doubt due in
                            considerable degree to increased efficiency, to the fact that under the
                            regulations the use of the spear has largely replaced that of firearms,
                            and that consequently fewer of the seals shot or speared were lost. Much
                            is probably the result of those accidental circumstances of weather and
                            climate which go to make a good fishing season. But the fact tends also
                            to show that more seals were met with than before, and from this point
                            of view the increased catch does not point to any imminent danger of
                            extinction of the species.</p>
                        <p>As regards the effect of the regulations on the number of seals
                            frequenting the Pribilof Islands, it seems premature to attempt to form
                            an opinion.</p>
                        <p>Her Majesty’s Government have noted the fact, which is not quoted by Mr.
                            Gresham, but has been stated on authority, that only 16,000 seals were
                            allowed by the United States Treasury agent to be killed on the Pribilof
                            Islands during the last season. It is a feature of the question which
                            deserves attention, but in the absence of information as to the standard
                            weight of skins and other conditions fixed by that officer it is not
                            possible to estimate the significance of this restriction. It does not,
                            however, necessarily point to any grounds of immediate apprehension, as
                            only 20,000 seals could be taken in 1890, though the standard in that
                            year was undoubtedly low.</p>
                        <p>In any case, as the number of seals taken outside Bering Sea, on the
                            American side was, owing to the regulations, much less than usual, and
                            pelagic sealing does not begin in that sea till the 1st of August, by
                            which time killing on the islands is over, it is evident that the small
                            take on the islands was not due to the results of the pelagic catch of
                            last year.</p>
                        <p>Taking all these circumstances into consideration, Her Majesty’s
                            Government can not agree that any sufficient evidence as yet exists to
                            show that the regulations have failed in their effect or that there is
                            such urgent danger of total extinction of the seals as to call for a
                            departure from the arbitral award by which the two nations have solemnly
                            bound themselves to abide.</p>
                        <pb facs="0682" n="622" xml:id="pg_622"/>
                        <p>The arbitrators had before them all the information both as to the
                            condition of the herd and the results of pelagic sealing which the
                            resources of both nations could supply, and after exhaustive
                            consideration they, in the judicial exercise of their discretion, fixed
                            five years as the period after which the regulations might be revised.
                            Only one year has elapsed, and beyond the fact that though the sealers
                            have scrupulously adhered to the regulations they have had a successful
                            season, there is no substantial ground to support the contention that
                            the period for revision of the regulations fixed by the arbitrators
                            ought to be so materially curtailed.</p>
                        <p>To set aside their authority upon so slight a ground would, in the
                            opinion of Her Majesty’s Government, be a most serious blow to the
                            authority of arbitral decisions, and to the general principle of
                            arbitration which both Governments have at heart to promote.</p>
                        <p>Her Majesty’s Government are, however, anxious to do all in their power
                            to contribute to a fair and thorough examination of the facts connected
                            with the seal fishery, and to the adoption in useful time of any
                            measures which may be necessary for the preservation of the species.
                            They have examined carefully the specific proposals contained in Mr.
                            Gresham’s note, in order to see how far any portion of them could be
                            accepted with this view, having due regard to the important British
                            interests involved.</p>
                        <p>As regards the proposed modus vivendi for this season, Her Majesty’s
                            Government regret that they find themselves unable to accept this
                            proposal.</p>
                        <p>Even if some adequate grounds had been furnished for its adoption in the
                            interest of the fishery, it is to be remembered that the sealers have
                            already almost all started and are now scattered over the whole breadth
                            of the North Pacific, where it is impossible to warn them.</p>
                        <p>They have made their preparations oh the assumption that the interference
                            and interruption to which their industry has been subject more or less
                            for the last ten years had at length come to an end, and that the
                            conditions under which it might be prosecuted had at last acquired some
                            permanence and stability. To spring upon them again in the midst of
                            their operations so stringent a proposal as that of the United States
                            would be an act of great injustice, and would involve Her Majesty’s
                            Government in the payment of heavy compensation.</p>
                        <p>The measure suggested would in fact put an end to pelagic sealing, as it
                            would have only the first four months of the year, when from various
                            causes comparatively few seals are caught, while the sealers would have
                            to lay their vessels up during the remaining two-thirds of the year. The
                            adoption of such a restriction under present circumstances, and upon the
                            only grounds which can be adduced to justify it, would be almost
                            tantamount to an announcement that whenever there has been a successful
                            pelagic fishing, steps will at once be taken to prevent the recurrence
                            of such an event.</p>
                        <p>Nor can Her Majesty’s Government believe that the appointment at present
                            of an international commission, such as is suggested by Mr. Gresham,
                            would lead to any useful result.</p>
                        <p>It will be remembered that the commissioners appointed by the United
                            States and Great Britain, who visited the islands in 1891 to examine
                            this same question, found themselves unable to agree, except as to a few
                            vague general statements, and presented reports in which they differed
                            widely, not only as to the remedial measures necessary, but even as to
                            many of the most important facts in seal life, and only the same result
                            can be expected from a second more numerous commission.</p>
                        <pb facs="0683" n="623" xml:id="pg_623"/>
                        <p>Such commissioners, it must be borne in mind, can only be on the islands
                            for a few weeks at most, while the period during which the seals
                            frequent the islands extends from May to October or November, and the
                            phases of seal life exhibited are constantly changing.</p>
                        <p>The question to be dealt with is the progress and the growth or decrease
                            of the herd, and the information required to enable it to be effectively
                            grappled with can only be gathered by continuous observations carried on
                            constantly during the greater part of the period that the islands are
                            resorted to by the seals, and extending over a series of years. The new
                            commission might, no doubt, be able to gather some new facts as to seal
                            life, but nothing but continuous and comparative study could qualify it
                            to form a judgment as to the effects which the pursuit of the seals at
                            sea and the slaughter on land is producing on the herd, and to suggest
                            any remedial measures with confidence and authority.</p>
                        <p>Instead of appointing such a commission, though possibly as a preparatory
                            step to its appointment, Her Majesty’s Government would propose the
                            appointment of agents to reside on the seal islands and to collect
                            authoritative information by observations, which should extend over such
                            a period as will be sufficient to enable a judgment to be formed of the
                            effect of the fishing upon the preservation of the herds.</p>
                        <p>If such agents appointed by the United States and Great Britain were to
                            conduct investigations jointly during the next four years, both
                            Governments would by that time have, With the particulars derived from
                            the sealers’ logs and other sources, a body of information which would
                            enable the two nations to approach the question of revising the
                            regulations in a thoroughly scientific manner, and to protect, as far as
                            possible, the numerous and varied interests involved in the seal
                            fishery.</p>
                        <p>Her Majesty’s Government do not wish, however, to be understood as
                            desiring to postpone all discussion until that date. The agents would
                            naturally make their reports at regular and not too distant intervals,
                            and if the facts disclosed in these reports, or information obtained
                            from other sources, should at any time show a state of things urgently
                            calling for remedial measures, Her Majesty’s Government would be willing
                            at once to examine with the Government of the United States the method
                            in which such measures could best be applied. Similarly they will be
                            ready to do what is in their power to obtain early returns of the
                            results of the fishery during the present year, in order that they may
                            be examined by the two Governments at the first practicable moment.</p>
                        <p>If these proposals recommend themselves to the Government of the United
                            States it might be desirable also to approach the Russian Government
                            with a view to the appointment of similar agents on the Commander
                            Islands. There is little independent information available in regard to
                            the conditions of seal life on these islands, and as the Russian
                            Government desire that the regulations made by the arbitrators for the
                            western side of the Pacific should be extended to the eastern side, it
                            seems reasonable that there should be inquiry how far such extension is
                            necessary and applicable.</p>
                        <p>Your excellency is authorized to read this dispatch to Mr. Gresham, and
                            if he should so desire, to hand him a copy of it.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>