<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="634" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d634">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Olney</persName> to Sir
                                    <persName type="to">Julian Pauncefote</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-02-07"><hi rend="italic">February 7,
                                1896</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 319.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: In the matter of the claim of
                            Purser Bain, I have the honor to inclose herewith copy of a letter just
                            received from the governor of Louisiana, with copy of the inclosure
                            therein referred to, to wit, a letter to me from the attorney-general of
                            the State of Louisiana.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Olney</hi></signed>.</closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 319.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Olney</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">State of Louisiana, Executive Department</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Baton Rouge, La.</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-02-03"><hi rend="italic">February 3, 1896</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your letter of the 25th ultimo, and
                                inclosures, came while I was confined to my bed with la grippe, and
                                was therefore referred to the attorney-general for
                                investigation.</p>
                            <p>I herewith inclose his answer, which I adopt and make my own.</p>
                            <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy J. Foster</hi>.</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cunningham</persName>
                                    to Mr. <persName type="to">Olney</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                            Orleans, La.</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-01-30"><hi rend="italic">January 30, 1896</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your letter of January 25, with
                                inclosures, was received by Governor Foster while in this city, and
                                as he is very unwell he requested me to look over the papers and
                                make such reply as I considered proper.</p>
                            <p>When I wrote to you on December 10, 1895, I presumed that all that
                                was expected of the State authorities was to bring the parties
                                charged with the shooting of Bain to trial. The inclosures
                                accompanying your letter would indicate that the British authorities
                                are seeking to obtain some compensation to Bain for injuries
                                received, although the claim is not specifically set out. There is
                                no appropriation under the control of the governor or any other
                                State officer out of which such a claim could be paid; I do not
                                think the legislature, under the constitution of this State, has the
                                power to make such an appropriation; and I do not think Bain has any
                                claim against the State. If he has any claim against anyone for
                                damages, it is against the city of New Orleans, and the courts are
                                open to him, as to any other man, to prosecute his claim.</p>
                            <p>As stated in my former letter, certain parties have been indicted for
                                the shooting of Bain, and the officer charged with the duty of
                                prosecuting such offenses, the district attorney, is ready and
                                anxious to try the case whenever practicable. It may be possible
                                that Bain cannot afford to spare the time necessary to attend this
                                trial; but every lawyer knows that a case cannot be tried without
                                the witnesses. I will notify the district attorney of Mr. Bain’s
                                expected arrival soon on the <hi rend="italic">Inventor;</hi> but no
                                examination of Bain by any local authority at this port, except as a
                                witness on the trial, could do any good. If the parties had not
                                already been indicted, he could be examined any day before the grand
                                Jury, but for the trial of the case before the jury a day has to be
                                fixed and time allowed for the summoning of witnesses. If <pb facs="0755" n="695" xml:id="pg_695"/> Mr. Bain will remain here
                                long enough, the case can he fixed for trial; hut even then no one
                                can foresee every contingency that might entitle the one party or
                                the other to a continuance.</p>
                            <p>With all due respect, the State authorities were guilty of no neglect
                                of duty, and no failure to protect the commerce of this city. As in
                                all labor troubles, there was more or less of indiscretion on both
                                sides of the controversy. Some thought the trouble due entirely to
                                the unreasonable attitude of the labor associations controlled by
                                the white screwmen and white longshoremen; but many thought that the
                                steamship agents were largely responsible for the trouble in giving
                                the preference to unorganized colored labor. Without regard to the
                                merits of this controversy, the governor called out the militia and
                                gave full and ample protection to the commerce of this city as soon
                                as practicable after his attention was called to the threatening
                                situation.</p>
                            <p>Whether Bain was struck by shots intended for other persons, or by
                                shots aimed at him in common with others, can only be determined by
                                the evidence developed on the trial of the indictment now pending,
                                or in a suit which he may institute if he wishes. But I never knew
                                until now that it was claimed by any one that Bain was intentionally
                                shot, and I have not the remotest idea that he was.</p>
                            <p>Ships are loaded in this port by screwmen and longshoremen, under
                                contracts with stevedores, who employ them for the purpose. The
                                steamship <hi rend="italic">Engineer</hi> was being loaded by
                                colored screwmen and longshoremen under contract with a stevedore,
                                and neither the purser nor any other officer of the ship had
                                anything to do with, nor any control over, these colored laborers;
                                so that, when an attack was made by whites upon the colored
                                laborers, there was no occasion for any hostility against Bain,
                                direct or indirect, and the injury to him must have been accidental.
                                This does not affect the criminality of the parties who fired the
                                shots, who, under our law, should be punished for this Unintentional
                                injury to the same extent as if the shots had reached the
                                destination intended; the intent with which an act is done gives
                                character to the act, whatever its result may be.</p>
                            <p>Regarding the statements in some of these communications inclosed,
                                that it was an open secret that a perfect arsenal was kept in a
                                certain building, I have but to say that every man of experience
                                knows that the idlest rumors sometimes assume the dignity of open
                                secrets. I think one of the steamship agents notified me, on the day
                                that the militia took control of the situation, of every place
                                suspected by them of having arms secreted therein. I reported all
                                these places to the officer in command nearest the locality
                                specified, and I think that such strict guard was kept over them,
                                and such investigation made, as would have exposed these arms if any
                                had been secreted. What may have been secreted before the outbreak,
                                and where, it was then impossible to ascertain. I did not go upon
                                the ground myself, but, in conjunction with the governor, was in
                                frequent communication with the military and police officers, and
                                they reported from time to time at the governor’s headquarters.</p>
                            <p>Whatever may be the complaints of parties affected by the unfortunate
                                labor troubles last spring, no one can honestly pretend that the
                                British ships were not fully protected after the real situation was
                                made known to the governor, or claim that the State authorities were
                                in any manner to blame for the unfortunate troubles which culminated
                                in that disturbance of the commerce of this port. Any statements to
                                the effect that appeals were made in vain to the State authorities
                                for protection were doubtless made under the influence of excited
                                passions at the time, and were in fact without any foundation in
                                truth. The governor did not call out the militia on receipt of the
                                first excited telegram from an unknown party, but he directed his
                                chief military officer in this city to report the true situation to
                                him, and came to this city on the next train. Unfortunately the
                                rioting occurred early in the morning before his arrival, but
                                neither he nor any other State authority was in any manner to blame
                                for it. No further disturbance occurred after he took command of the
                                situation.</p>
                            <p>No one deplores more than the governor the unfortunate labor troubles
                                of last spring; no one will do more to prevent their recurrence; and
                                no one need remind him of the injury to the commerce of this port
                                and of the embarrassment to the officials of the Government, local,
                                State, or national, caused by such troubles; but I respectfully
                                suggest that he had no power to foresee and prevent these troubles
                                any more than the authorities in any other State or country,
                                American or European, where such troubles are of so much more
                                frequent occurrence than they are here.</p>
                            <p>In common with the governor of this State, I regret exceedingly that
                                this matter should have become the subject of an international
                                correspondence, as the agents of the British steamer here, with the
                                assistance and cooperation of the district attorney and myself,
                                could so much more expeditiously and effectively have taken the
                                necessary steps for the protection of Bain, and the punishment of
                                those responsible for his injuries. Everyone here felt the deepest
                                sympathy for Bain, as an unfortunate victim of a trouble for which
                                he was not responsible, and have been ever willing to <pb facs="0756" n="696" xml:id="pg_696"/> extend to him such
                                protection and redress as any other man is entitled to; but we fail
                                to see that he is entitled to any greater rights than are enjoyed by
                                any other man.</p>
                            <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">M. J. Cunningham</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Attorney-General of Louisiana.</hi></signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>