<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-06-29T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-06-29T19:00:00-05:00" n="100" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">825.24/519: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-29T20:00:00-04:00">June 29,
                                    1942—8 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>744. Your 1007, June 19. The problem you present has arisen in other
                            countries where vital mines are operating. Recognizing the viewpoint you
                            express, the Office of Exports has not required and is not requiring
                            Certificates of Necessity for export applications for materials going to
                            mines enjoying mine serial preference ratings.</p>
                        <p>The Projects Division of the Board of Economic Warfare is attempting to
                            obtain and break down the requirements of the strategic mining companies
                            as apart from other industrial requirements for other allocated
                            commodities. Such a separation cannot be accomplished before the fourth
                            quarter at which time it is contemplated that the quarterly allocations
                            announced will be net allocations available to the industries in Chile
                            distinct from the requirements of the mining companies.</p>
                        <p>For the first, second and third quarters, however, all shipments of
                            allocated commodities to the mining companies are charged off to the
                            allocations which were announced for those quarters. This charge off
                            will obviously not be satisfactory to the Junta but the production
                            situation here makes it necessary. In explanation to the Junta please
                                <pb facs="0105" n="91" xml:id="pg_91"/> inform it that the agencies
                            are cognizant of the problem involved and that it is hoped a solution
                            will be worked out for the fourth and subsequent quarters.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>