<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Colombia ( (Lane))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-05-16T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-05-16T22:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-05-16T22:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-05-16T22:00:00-05:00" n="170"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/2610: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lane</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-05-16T23:00:00-04:00"
                            >May 16, 1942—11 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>575. Your 601, May 5, 9 p.m. Are we correct in assuming on the basis of the
                    Minister of War’s instructions to General López not to make any issue with
                    United States military authorities in the event <pb facs="0165" n="151"
                        xml:id="pg_151"/> of an emergency necessitating our forces entering
                    Colombian territory, that General Andrews may without prior and specific
                    permission from the Colombian Government dispatch United States Army task forces
                    to cope with any situation which might arise in Colombian waters or territories
                    through enemy action? If this understanding is correct, the War Department is
                    entirely satisfied and does not feel that it will be necessary to conclude an
                    agreement formalizing the right of United States armed forces to take whatever
                    action is indicated to cope with unforeseen emergencies. If, however, you feel
                    that a useful purpose would be served by concluding an agreement with the
                    Colombian Government providing that the two countries may undertake operations
                    on or over the lands and in or over the territorial waters of the other country
                    for the purpose of hemisphere defense, when such action is urgently necessary, a
                    draft of such an agreement will be sent you for your consideration.</p>
                <p>The Department is of the opinion that existing arrangements and understandings
                    with the Colombian Government are such that a formal agreement is not necessary
                    and perhaps would be undesirable.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
