<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Diplomatic Representatives in Certain
                    American Republics</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d199</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">199</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-03-28T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-03-28T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recPnftMNhM1QKAYO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Stockpile</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-28T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-28T20:00:00-05:00" n="199"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d199">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M)/5924a: Circular telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Representatives in Certain American
                            Republics</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="52" xml:id="d199fn52">Sent to representatives in Colombia, Bolivia,
                        Peru, Ecuador, Guatemala, Panama, Mexico, Venezuela, Costa Rica, and El
                        Salvador. With the exception of the prefatory paragraph, the same was sent
                        to Argentina and Brazil.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-28T21:00:00-04:00"
                            >March 28, 1942—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In order to give you background regarding the extreme urgency of the rubber
                    situation, which has led this government to request you to institute immediate
                    negotiations for the acquisition of the entire rubber production of the country
                    to which you are accredited, you are advised of the following factors: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>With the shutting off of far eastern sources of rubber (excepting only
                            the Island of Ceylon) the nations which are directly producing armaments
                            and implements of war,—namely, the United States, the United Kingdom and
                            Canada,—are dependent for new crude rubber supplies entirely on the
                            American republics and Africa—sources which have produced only a
                            fraction of our needs.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Existing stocks of crude rubber are wholly inadequate to meet military
                            requirements and synthetic rubber plants are being rushed. Nevertheless,
                            synthetic production will not be at full capacity before 1944, and in
                            any event it is not at all certain that the use of crude rubber in tires
                            and tubes can be entirely dispensed with.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>A realistic analysis of the situation requires the conclusion that
                            both the United States and the American countries united with us must
                            dispense with all non-military uses of rubber not absolutely essential
                            to the conduct of the war.</item>
                        <pb facs="0187" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Careful and expert consideration is being devoted continuously in this
                            country to methods of saving crude rubber in manufacture and of
                            developing substitutes, and the advantages of these improvements may be
                            fully realized only if the maximum amount of crude rubber is turned over
                            to this country.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>It is highly desirable that no one of the American Republics should
                            acquire or use an amount of rubber disproportionate to the respective
                            war or defense needs of that country and of the other American
                            Republics, including the United States; likewise that articles
                            manufactured from rubber should be allocated to the American republics
                            on the basis of the contribution to be realized thereby to the winning
                            of the war. Argentina, which we understand has on hand a stockpile
                            sufficient for 8 or 9 months’ normal production for civilian needs in
                            addition to supplies available for military needs, should not have the
                            opportunity of amassing further stocks at the expense of the war
                            effort.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The practical application of the foregoing means that it is absolutely necessary
                    for the United States to acquire from producing countries all available crude
                    rubber, including stocks on hand and rubber hereafter produced. It also means
                    that the producing countries must cooperate with us in limiting internal
                    consumption. Among measures which would achieve these ends, aside from the sale
                    of rubber to us, are the limitation of exports (both of crude and manufactured
                    rubber) to the United States, limitation of rubber manufacture within the
                    country, limitation of rubber products in the country to uses essential to the
                    conduct of the war, and the prevention of hoarding.</p>
                <p>These steps are a practical carrying out of Resolution II of the Rio
                        conference<note n="53" xml:id="d199fn53">For correspondence concerning the
                        Third Meeting of the Foreign Ministers of the American Republics, held at
                        Rio de Janeiro January 15–28, 1942, see <ref target="frus1942v05#pg_6">vol.
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 6</ref> ff.; for text of Resolution
                        II, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, February 7,
                        1942, p. 119.</note> calling for an economic mobilization of the American
                    republics and requiring positive action to that end. Any system under which the
                    United States is put in the position of competing as to price with other
                    American Republics for the acquisition of a commodity which should be allocated
                    on the basis of war or defense needs, aside from any question of cost in
                    dollars, will cause confusion in the negotiation of contracts and may result in
                    a failure to make available to the conduct of the war the maximum amount of
                    rubber and rubber products needed for that purpose. If the United States, in
                    order to acquire crude rubber in the American republics, is required to
                    negotiate from country to country at varying prices, none of the producing
                    countries will be satisfied. There is no hesitation on the part of the United
                    States in paying amounts necessary to procure the rubber under an orderly
                    method, and our government is prepared to take into consideration all local
                    features affecting price.</p>
                <pb facs="0188" n="174" xml:id="pg_174"/>
                <p>The United States has carried out, and is continuing to carry out, substantial
                    and important plans for the development of resources and for aiding in the
                    maintenance of internal economies in the American Republics. The allocations
                    agreed upon and the priority treatment now being accorded to the other American
                    Republics with respect to many tight products are relatively much less severe
                    than the treatment accorded to civilian users of the same products within the
                    United States. This Government expects that there will be a parallel development
                    in which the American republics will cooperate fully in all measures designed to
                    allocate to the various republics the maximum amount of rubber products on the
                    basis of respective war or defense needs. Arrangements through barter or
                    otherwise which obtain for a particular country a disproportionate amount of
                    rubber products will in the end only deter the common cause.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
