<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Chile ( (Bowers))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-03-18T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-03-18T21:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-18T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-18T21:00:00-05:00" n="22"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d22">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">825.24/395: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-18T22:00:00-04:00"
                            >March 18, 1942—10 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>306. Your 436, March 17, 9 p.m. The War Department has now sent Colonel Sackville
                    detailed instructions by both air mail and telegraph, emphasizing the political
                    considerations in this arrangement and the necessity for eliminating all sources
                    of friction. The War Department, of course, assumes that in view of the
                    instructional capacity of the United States forces, the Chilean authorities will
                    wish to provide them with such limited administrative authority as may be
                    necessary to supervise the setting up of the batteries and the instruction of
                    Chilean forces in their operation. Anything beyond this authority over
                    mechanical operations would be presumably in the realm of tactical jurisdiction.
                    The War Department’s instructions to Sackville have been summarized as follows
                    for your information: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Each battery will operate under the immediate administrative
                            jurisdiction and command of the senior U. S. Army officer present at
                            each locality. For tactical functioning, all four batteries, under the
                            command of Colonel Sackville, will be under the general supervision of
                            the Commander in Chief of the Chilean Army, or his duly authorized
                            representative at each locality. In case of any difficulty relative to
                            the tactical control or disposition of his unit, final decision will
                            rest with the Commander in Chief of the Chilean Army.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
