<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Costa Rica ( (Scotten) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d277</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">277</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-05-06T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-05-06T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rGICCioSV3my" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Financial crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-05-06T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-05-06T20:00:00-05:00" n="277"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d277">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">818.51/985: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Costa Rica</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Scotten</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">San José</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-05-06T19:00:00-06:00"
                            >May 6, 1942—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received May 7—2:03 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>224. Referring to Department’s 174, May 5, 9 p.m. The Costa Rican Minister is
                    apparently correct in his statement that the approval of Congress would be
                    necessary for the increase of the existing credit. Paragraph 16–A of article 73
                    of the Costa Rican Constitution assigns to Congress the right to authorize the
                    Executive to negotiate loans or make other contracts and to mortgage the
                    national revenues as security therefor.</p>
                <p>It is clear that the President desires to avoid congressional discussion of a
                    loan, fearing that it would bring to light at least incompetence and
                    mismanagement and possibly dishonesty on the part of the present administration.
                    This situation was reported in my personal letter of April 27 to Mr. Bonsal and
                    in the last paragraph of my despatch No. 135 of April 29.<note n="26"
                        xml:id="d277fn26">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The President would naturally prefer a secret loan with which he could tide over
                    the present financial crisis of his administration.</p>
                <p>I doubt the wisdom of granting such a credit however which might result in a
                    situation similar to that following the loan to the Tinoco Government by the
                    Royal Bank of Canada in 1917 or 1918 which was followed by arbitration by the
                    Chief Justice of the United States<note n="27" xml:id="d277fn27">See <ref
                            target="frus1921v01#pg_663">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1921, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 663</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1921v01#pg_668">668</ref>.</note> who I understand decided
                    that as the loan had not had the approval of the Costa Rican Congress it was not
                    an obligation of the Costa Rican Government.</p>
                <p>While a secret loan or even gift to a friendly government or a government which
                    the United States wished to keep on friendly terms during the war might in some
                    cases be advisable from the standpoint of expedience I do not consider such a
                    situation to exist here as even if the present Government should fall the entry
                    into power of any group unfriendly to the United States and consequently
                    dangerous to our war effort is most unlikely.</p>
                <p>Should no financial assistance be accepted by the President at present it is
                    possible that the political crisis might become so acute as to cause his
                    resignation. However, I believe it likely that should we offer no alternative to
                    some proposal involving congressional approval, such approval would be obtained.
                    No doubt the congressional debate would include some violent criticism of the
                    Government but its large majority would in all probability ensure the acceptance
                    of the loan.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotten</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
