<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Guatemala ( (Des Portes) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-03-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="459"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d459">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">814.24/196</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Guatemala</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Des Portes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2632</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-10">March 10,
                            1942</date>.<lb/>[Received March 12.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my despatch No. 2602
                    of March 4, 1942 (File No. 711/824.2),<note n="7" xml:id="d459fn7">Not
                        printed.</note> reporting the preliminary reaction of the Guatemalan
                    Government to the observations contained in the Department’s telegram No. 78 of
                    February 19, 9 p.m., 1942, the substance of which was conveyed to the Guatemalan
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs in a Note of February 20, 1942, regarding the
                    furnishing of military equipment to this Republic.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Office by a Note No. 3229 of March 6, 1942, a copy and translation of
                    which are enclosed, has now made formal reply setting forth its point of view
                    relative to the type of engagement which it deems appropriate for the
                    procurement of the arms and ammunition. It may be observed that the spirit and
                    sense of the formal reply closely approximates that of the preliminary response
                    as contained in the President’s oral statements and the Ministry’s
                        Memorandum<note n="7" xml:id="d459fn8">Not printed.</note> summarizing
                    negotiations in the matter.</p>
                <pb facs="0450" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/>
                <p>No material technical difficulty should be encountered in supplying the
                    Guatemalan Government with the equipment it desires for its own immediate
                    military needs and for which it proposes to pay cash. The matter of the larger
                    amount of equipment which Guatemala needs for cooperation with the United States
                    Government in hemisphere defense presents a much more difficult problem. It
                    occurs to me that this phase might possibly be solved by an arrangement whereby
                    Guatemala would secure the equipment under the normal terms of the Lend-Lease
                    Act, without any exceptions of principle in its favor which might be considered
                    as unfair departures by other American Republics, but at the same time the
                    contract to be so drawn as to afford in substance the end sought by Guatemala.
                    Concretely, it is suggested as a compromise that perhaps Guatemala might be
                    induced to make small installment payments over the usual period of years, with
                    the proviso that at the end of the war the Guatemalan Government would be
                    permitted, as it evidently desires, to return to the United States such
                    equipment as it has not expended and which is in good condition. The value of
                    the equipment so returned would be credited against the obligation contracted by
                    this Republic under the Lend-Lease Act. If the amount of equipment returned were
                    to exceed the monetary balance due by Guatemala subsequent to installments
                    effected, the sum of the excess would be refunded to the Guatemalan Treasury. If
                    the equipment returned were not sufficient to liquidate the monetary balance
                    due, the Guatemalan Government would be obligated to discharge the sum of the
                    deficit. Such a proposal of course presupposes, on the side of the United
                    States, that the arrangement is legally possible and within the policy adopted,
                    and, on the Guatemalan side, that the installment payments called for would be
                    so spaced and in such moderate amounts that the demands could be met by
                    Guatemala within its extraordinary budgetary resources and without resort to
                    public loans.</p>
                <p>I do not know whether such a plan would be agreeable to the Guatemalan
                    authorities. Doubtless the Department may evolve a more satisfactory
                    arrangement, the present suggestion being advanced by me merely as one solution
                    which might merit exploration and without any attempt to pass on the justice of
                    Guatemalan pretensions. The ostensible value of the plan, which the Legation
                    ventures to submit for examination, is that the United States would be assured
                    of payments in keeping with the provisions of the Lend-Lease Act and Guatemala
                    would obtain acceptance of its contention that it be not obliged to pay for arms
                    and ammunition over and above its immediate needs and which are not actually
                    expended by it.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fay Allen Des Portes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0451" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Guatemalan Ministry for Foreign
                                Affairs</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American Legation</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 3229</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Ministry for Foreign Affairs has the honor to refer to the memorandum
                        from the Legation of the United States dated February 20 last, relative to
                        the matter of furnishing arms in accordance with the lend-lease act.</p>
                    <p>The Ministry had delayed replying to the kind memorandum of the Legation in
                        order to make clear the status of pending negotiations. The questions which
                        arose having been elucidated, the Minister is today able to make a
                        clarifying and definitive reply with regard to the decision of the
                        Government of the Republic relative to the draft contract submitted for its
                        consideration.</p>
                    <p>The President of the Republic has taken up directly with His Excellency the
                        Minister of the United States the different phases of the pending
                        negotiations; and His Excellency the Minister is aware of the good will of
                        the Government of Guatemala to cooperate with that of the United States in
                        matters pertaining to continental defense. Apart from this consideration, on
                        which the Ministry for Foreign Affairs wishes to emphasize the resolve of
                        this Government, it believes that it will be advantageous and useful to
                        state as clearly as possible the attitude of the Government of the Republic
                        regarding the matter of arms.</p>
                    <p rend="center">I.</p>
                    <p>The Government of Guatemala is grateful for the benevolent offer of the
                        United States to furnish to it armament and munitions of war; and declares
                        that, as regards arms which it needs for its own defense and local use, it
                        has determined to pay in currency and for cash.</p>
                    <p>This Government considers that the payment, made at the moment of the
                        delivery of the material, ought not to bring to it greater burdens (<hi
                            rend="italic">no ha de reportarle may ores gravámenes</hi>), and,
                        moreover gives it the right to the usual discounts to those who pay
                        cash.</p>
                    <p>A simple and clear contract could be drawn up setting forth exactly the
                        reciprocal obligations of buyer and seller; and, as soon as that draft
                        contract is approved, this Government would proceed to sign it without
                        further delay.</p>
                    <p rend="center">II.</p>
                    <p>Having concluded drawing up the terms of the contract for the purchase of
                        arms for Guatemala’s own defense and local use as set forth in the preceding
                        paragraphs, it is pertinent to consider another <pb facs="0452" n="438"
                            xml:id="pg_438"/> aspect of the special situation of the Republic in
                        relation to the present international emergency: This aspect is as
                        follows:</p>
                    <p>As the Legation is aware, the Government of Guatemala has placed at the
                        disposition of the United States whatever it has and possesses in its
                        territory which could be used for cooperation in defense of the fundamental
                        interests of the hemisphere at the head of which the United States has
                        placed itself in the crusade for liberty and human rights. Notwithstanding
                        the danger of thereby attracting attacks of totalitarian forces, airports
                        and coasts of the Republic have been fortified or are being fortified for
                        the defense of the continent.</p>
                    <p>It is logical, as a consequence of the measures of military nature that, in
                        order to collaborate with the United States forces presently and in the
                        future on Guatemalan soil, the Guatemalan Army needs to import arms adequate
                        for the defense which is being organized: The Government of the Republic
                        deems that its conduct in this matter is to cooperate with the United States
                        in the collective defense; it does not consider it just that, under the
                        circumstances referred to in the preceding paragraph, the armament which may
                        have been ceded to it for mutual defense and which may be in good condition
                        and not needed after the cessation of hostilities, should be an expense to
                        the Guatemalan Government.</p>
                    <p>The Government of Guatemala has been referring to this type of armament, as
                        His Excellency the Minister of the United States will recall, with the
                        insistent request that such matériel be furnished as a loan under the United
                        States law of March 11, 1941, with the option of returning it after the war,
                        provided it is in good condition or unused.</p>
                    <p>The Government of Guatemala has not pretended that, under similar
                        circumstances, it be given advantageous concessions over the other American
                        Republics. Now, by reason of the explanations made, whether orally or in the
                        extract of the diplomatic correspondence which the Ministry for Foreign
                        Affairs had the honor to place in the hands of His Excellency the Minister
                        of the United States, it (the Ministry for Foreign Affairs) understands that
                        the matter is elucidated and crystallized in the aforementioned terms.</p>
                    <p>In summary, the Government of Guatemala is disposed: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>To buy arms which it needs for its own defense and local use,
                                paying cash;</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>To obtain under the terms of the lend-lease law, arms which are
                                needed to collaborate with the United States in the defense of the
                                American continent.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>As has been explained, the Government of Guatemala has hastened to place at
                        the service of collective defense all the national resources <pb facs="0453"
                            n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/> which are necessary to repel direct
                        aggressions of the Axis powers: In order to fight against those forces, the
                        Government of Guatemala will have to make great sacrifices over and above
                        the material damages which the aggressors may cause. This not being exactly
                        the case of the other American Republics which have already signed contracts
                        for arms with the United States, and, on the other hand, which probably will
                        not pay cash for those for local use only, the Government of Guatemala does
                        not see the reason why those Republics should find unfair the conditions
                        proposed by Guatemala. Moreover, if Guatemala gives as much as it has and
                        proposes the return after the war of the arms in good condition or unused,
                        it surely is not seeking a unilateral agreement for the exclusive benefit of
                        Guatemala.</p>
                    <p>The Ministry for Foreign Affairs takes this opportunity to reiterate to the
                        Legation of the United States the assurances of its highest and most
                        distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-06">March 6,
                                1942</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
