<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="47" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d47">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/25657</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                                State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-06">November 6, 1942</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Ambassador of Chile called to see me this afternoon at his request.
                            The Ambassador told me that he had just learned that General Espinosa,
                            Chilean representative on the Interamerican Defense Commission, had
                            received direct word from General Escudero, Chief of Staff of the
                            Chilean Army that the Government of Chile intended to break relations in
                            the near future and that General Espinosa was, consequently, to shape
                            his conduct in the United States with that in mind.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador had also received word that his Government had issued
                            directives to the Chilean newspapers to prepare the way editorially for
                            a rupture of relations with the Axis.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said that he wished to state very frankly that he now felt
                            that the action taken by this Government in bringing home publicly and
                            clearly to public opinion in his own country and to the members of the
                            Chilean Senate and House of Representatives the true facts in the
                            picture had been altogether desirable and that the results in all
                            probability would soon prove it. I told the Ambassador that the
                            statement he had just made was, of course, deeply gratifying to me
                            personally.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador further discussed at some length recent developments in
                            Chilean politics …</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps">elles</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>