<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Under Secretary of State ( (Welles) ) to the President of Haiti (
                    (Lescot))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d487</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">487</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-07-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-07-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-07-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-07-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="487"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d487">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">838.51/4492</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the President of Haiti</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lescot</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-14">July 14,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I refer to your letters of June
                    23 and July 1, the first of which I had the pleasure of receiving from the hands
                    of your distinguished Secretary of State for Finance, Mr. Abel Lacroix, through
                    whose kindness I am sending you this reply. It has been a privilege to discuss
                    with Mr. Lacroix the different problems brought up in your letters. The detailed
                    report which he will bring you will, I am confident, demonstrate to you again
                    the complete accord which prevails between our two Governments regarding the
                    measures which they can jointly take to meet the critical situation with which
                    they are confronted.</p>
                <p>The revised proposal of the Export-Import Bank for financial cooperation with the
                    Government of Haiti and with the National Bank is the result of a careful study
                    of all the information available regarding Haitian revenues and expenditures
                    both past and future. It is obviously impossible, under present circumstances to
                    forecast the exact future course of the imports upon which Haitian revenues so
                    largely depend. The situation is one calling for close and frequent consultation
                    between the officials directly concerned.</p>
                <p>These consultations together with the demonstrated correctness and sense of
                    responsibility of your Government in budgetary matters justify the conviction
                    that such problems as may arise in the future will be satisfactorily and
                    promptly solved.</p>
                <p>It is not possible at this time to give you any positive statement regarding the
                    shipping situation. It is most serious; we have all suffered grievous losses.
                    Yet our shipbuilding program is progressing by giant steps and our available
                    means of defense and offense <pb facs="0490" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/> against
                    the submarine menace are being strengthened and multiplied daily. Further
                    hardships and losses await us. Our certain victory depends upon our manner of
                    meeting and enduring them.</p>
                <p>The suggestions regarding convoys which you made in your letter of July 1 are
                    being given careful consideration by the appropriate authorities. This
                    Government is doing its utmost, consistent with the overall requirements of
                    general strategy, to relieve the shipping situation in the Caribbean area. Mr.
                    Lacroix has discussed this problem with the appropriate officials.</p>
                <p>I am happy to take advantage of this opportunity to tell you how greatly we
                    appreciate the energetic solicitude with which you have personally directed the
                    assistance given to survivors of vessels lost near the Haitian coasts. I can
                    only say that these acts are characteristic of your generosity and of your
                    unfailing interest in the welfare of my compatriots and of all those who are
                    dailing [<hi rend="italic">daily</hi>] risking their lives to win the battle of
                    supply.</p>
                <p>I was distressed to learn of the loss at sea of your personal effects, as a
                    result of enemy action, following your recent trip to Washington.</p>
                <p>The invitation to visit you in Haiti, which you and Madame Lescot have so kindly
                    renewed, is appreciated very much by Mrs. Welles and myself. Although it does
                    not appear possible for us to be absent from Washington for any period of time
                    in the foreseeable future, we are very grateful for the invitation, and Mrs.
                    Welles joins me in sending to you and to Madame Lescot our cordial
                    greetings.</p>
                <p>Believe me,</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
