<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-19T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-19T20:00:00-05:00" n="551" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d551">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711F.1914/432: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-19T21:00:00-04:00">March 19,
                                    1942—9 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>162. Your despatch 922, March 9, 1942. You are authorized to accept draft
                            of Article I as proposed by Panama in its note D.P. 3239 dated March 6,
                            1942, inserting in paragraph 1 “definitive” before “treaty” and changing
                            “state of emergency” to read “state of international insecurity”. The
                            Panamanian proposal for Article V should be modified accordingly. You
                            may likewise accept, <pb facs="0613" n="599" xml:id="pg_599"/> making
                            such changes in phraseology as you deem desirable, the suggested
                            modifications of all other articles, except the proposed addition to
                            Article VIII concerning wear and damage to roads and the proposals for
                            Article XII concerning annual rentals.</p>
                        <p>The Department feels it is unable at this time to determine the extent of
                            wear or damage to Panamanian roads which will be caused yearly by troop
                            movements, and therefore prefers to retain the phraseology submitted by
                            this Government. There would apparently be no more room for disagreement
                            regarding the estimate at a later date than there is at the present
                            time.</p>
                        <p>The Department reiterates its proposal of an annual rental of one balboa
                            for all the public lands. Further consideration will be given the
                            question of the rentals to be paid for the use of private lands when
                            figures on the breakdown between public and privately owned lands are
                            made available. Please urge the appropriate Panamanian authorities to
                            endeavor to obtain this information for Department at earliest possible
                            date. When agreement has been reached on all other provisions of the
                            draft agreement, please forward copy of phraseology agreed upon.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>