<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-17T16:10:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-17T16:10:00-05:00" n="708" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d708">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">831.6363/1346: Airgram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Venezuela</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Flack</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-17T16:40:00-04:30">November
                                    17, 1942—4:40 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received November 21—11 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>A–212. Following is translation of excerpt dealing with oil industry from
                            President Medina’s address at Maracaibo yesterday.</p>
                        <pb facs="0767" n="753" xml:id="pg_753"/>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“My speech is getting long, but I see in your faces a question which
                                I do not want to leave unanswered: The revision of our petroleum
                                policy as announced by me at the Palacio de Miraflores on that
                                memorable occasion. The National Government, in fulfillment of one
                                of its inevitable duties, firm in its purposes and sure of its
                                action, proposes to obtain a fairer State participation from the
                                exploitation of petroleum, and also that its industrial process be a
                                sure source of work for the Venezuelan laborer. I must observe that
                                this Government, obedient to the Law, endorser of the guarantees
                                which honor our Constitution, watchful of the righteousness of its
                                procedures and not in the least given to hastiness, respects the
                                rights legally acquired, does not consider as adversaries those
                                enterprises which have brought their capital to extend the
                                development of our natural wealth; but, animated by a spirit of
                                right and justice it believes that Venezuela should receive an
                                adequate participation in keeping with its position as owner of that
                                which constitutes the real source of that industry, and that its
                                industrial process should have its principal headquarters in
                                Venezuela in order that the opportunities for the employment of
                                Venezuelan labor may be intensified. The Government does not attack,
                                it tries to convince and is sure that in its purpose there is fair
                                satisfaction for the Nation and a steady and secure equilibrium for
                                industry because agreements are lasting only when they have a basis
                                of equity and justice. I have said that the Government is not given
                                to hastiness and when, from the Presidential Seat I announced the
                                revision of our petroleum policy, it was because I felt sure that we
                                would come to it by one way or the other, by means of conviction and
                                cooperation or by legal means; if, unfortunately, all of the
                                expected results can not be obtained by the first means, then,
                                leaving aside the reasons for equity, the Government, arming itself
                                with incontrovertible juridical and moral power shall proceed, in
                                the name of the Republic, to regain possession of that which
                                corresponds to it by right.</p>
                            <p>From the very same moment that I assumed the Presidency, I became
                                extremely interested in this matter of our petroleum policy, which I
                                consider of the utmost importance to our economic development, and
                                it is my conviction that the year 1942 will see the end of a cycle
                                in the history of our petroleum: the cycle of trial of ignorance and
                                empiricism; today we know what we have and it is a duty of my
                                Government to initiate the first stage of what we might call the era
                                of technical, economical and financial exploitation at the service
                                of the State in cooperation with the enterprises associated with us
                                to transform in effective wealth the potential richness of our
                                subsoil.”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Flack</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>