<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The French Ambassador ( (Jusserand) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d195</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">195</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="195"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.77/1656</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The French Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jusserand</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-02-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 5, 1918</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: The attention of the
                    Government of the Republic has been drawn to the advantage that could be taken
                    of existing circumstances in recasting the agreements that now bind the Allied
                    financial groups with regard to the Hukuang lines so as to eliminate the German
                    group.</p>
                <p>These agreements for which there is a historic explanation are irksome to all and
                    a never-ending source of conflicts. The French group represented by the Banque
                    de l’Indo-Chine thinks it would be beneficial to start them anew on entirely
                    different bases and that by heeding the lessons of past experience an agreement
                    may be arrived at that is likely to live and will be acceptable to the Chinese
                    besides securing the future of the lines.</p>
                <pb facs="0312" n="200" xml:id="pg_200"/>
                <p>The representative of the French group broached the question to his American
                    colleague who coincides in his views and drew up on the subject favorable
                    recommendations that are no doubt known to his Government. The English
                    representative likewise thinks it necessary to perfect a new agreement before
                    the end of the war, and has also made his opinion known in London. Under these
                    conditions it seems that the negotiations which were begun in 1914 on the
                    subject can be resumed at once and speedily carried to a successful
                    conclusion.</p>
                <p>But before taking active steps in these new negotiations the financial groups
                    would like to have the three Governments concerned agree on the principle. The
                    initiative of the French group meets with the full approval of the Government of
                    the Republic which wishes me to draw your excellency’s attention to the great
                    interest which attaches to taking away from our enemy the power to resume his
                    place in the former Hukuang agreement at the end of the hostilities.</p>
                <p>Mr. Pichon would be glad if your excellency could find it possible to concur in
                    this opinion and advise the American group that you would countenance
                    negotiations in that direction with the French and English groups.</p>
                <p>Be pleased [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Jusserand</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            French Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Jusserand</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 2069</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-02-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 15, 1918</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        receipt of your excellency’s note of the 5th instant communicating the views
                        of your Government in support of the proposals of the French and British
                        groups concerned that the Hukuang Railway agreements should be recast in
                        such a manner as to eliminate the German group from further interest
                        therein.</p>
                    <p>I shall be glad to have you say to your Government that its suggestions will
                        have my very careful consideration, and that as soon as a decision is
                        reached in regard to the matter I shall have pleasure in communicating it
                        through your excellency.</p>
                    <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
