<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-11-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 837.51/284</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of the Treasury</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McAdoo</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-11-20">
                                        <hi rend="italic">November 20, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: Under date of November
                                7, Assistant Secretary Leffingwell wrote you enclosing copy of a
                                letter, dated October 29, from the Cuban Minister, which for the
                                time being terminated negotiations relative to a loan by this
                                Government to the Cuban Government. Mr. Gonzales, our Minister to
                                Cuba, informs me that the Cuban Government has, at the suggestion of
                                the State Department, made commitments for advances to the Cuba
                                Railroad, in order to insure getting out the next Cuban crop, and
                                that, at the suggestion of the Navy Department, has made contracts
                                for the purchase of submarine chasers. Mr. Gonzales further informs
                                me that the Cuban Government has relied upon receiving a loan of
                                $15,000,000 from this Government with which to meet these
                                commitments. I should like to have from you, therefore, a statement
                                of your views in order to ascertain if there is any moral obligation
                                to give Cuba financial assistance. I was not only willing, but glad
                                to make a loan to Cuba, and I was sorry that the Cuban Government
                                encountered legal obstacles for negotiating a loan on the basis that
                                had been outlined. I desire to have the above information because it
                                may be possible, if found advisable, to work out some plan to give
                                at least temporary assistance to Cuba.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">W. G. McAdoo</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                            State</gloss> to the Secretary of the Treasury</hi>
                                        (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">McAdoo</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-12-01">
                                            <hi rend="italic">December 1,
                                        1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                                    the receipt of your communication of November-20, 1917,
                                    requesting an expression of opinion from this Department as to
                                    whether any moral obligation rests upon the Government of the
                                    United States to give Cuba financial assistance. In reply I
                                    desire to inform you that an examination of the correspondence
                                    passed between the Department and the Cuban Government would
                                    appear to show that a certain moral obligation does exist for
                                    the reason that the American Minister to Cuba, under
                                    instructions from the Department in preliminary conversations
                                    respecting the proposed loan, especially recommended to the
                                    Cuban Government that a certain portion of this loan, roughly in
                                    the neighborhood of $3,000,000, be set aside for the purpose of
                                    establishing a credit in favor of the Cuba Railroad, should this
                                    railroad guarantee <pb facs="0427" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> to
                                    expend these moneys in the necessary improvements in roadbed and
                                    additions to their rolling stock and in repairing the damages
                                    done to the road during the last revolution.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Whigham, President of the Cuba Railroad, informed the
                                    American Minister at Habana, that the Cuban Government has
                                    assured him of credits in the neighborhood of $3,000,000, upon
                                    the statement of which his railroad had undertaken large
                                    improvements.</p>
                                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>