<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Cuban Minister ( (De Céspedes) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-03-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-03-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="356"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d356">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 837.51/298</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Cuban Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Céspedes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 61</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-03-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 18, 1918</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: I have the honor to deliver to
                    your excellency, with a request that it be returned, the credentials which set
                    forth the new powers that have been conferred upon me by the Honorable the
                    President of the Republic, to conclude with the Government of the United States
                    the loan of 15,000,000 pesos to my Government, secured by the bonds of the
                    Treasury of Cuba, issued in accordance with the law of July 31, 1917.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d356fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_295">p. 295</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I beg your excellency to make my new credentials known to the Treasury
                    Department.</p>
                <p>I reiterate [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Carlos Manuel de Céspedes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mario G. Menocal</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">president of the republic of cuba</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">To All Who These Presents May See, Greeting</hi>:</p>
                    <p>Know ye, that reposing special certainty and confidence in the integrity,
                        tact, and ability of Señor Carlos Manuel de Céspedes y Quesada, Envoy
                        Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the Republic of Cuba to the
                        United States of America, I have vested him in the full power and authority,
                        of every description, to interview and confer, in the name and as
                        representative of the Republic, with any person or persons authorized in
                        good form by the Government of the United States of America who may appear
                        vested with equal power and representative character, and with the said
                        attorney or attorneys; in fact, to negotiate at will and conclude a loan
                        from the Government of the United States of America in an amount that may
                        not exceed 15,000,000 pesos, to receive at set periods the sums that may be
                        delivered chargeable to the said loan, executing the corresponding
                        obligations in the form that may be deemed expedient, and to pledge and be
                        able to give as security all or part of the 15,000,000 pesos of bonds of
                        Series A of the Treasury of Cuba authorized by the law of July 31, of the
                        year 1917 last.</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I issue the present full power signed with my hand,
                        authenticated with the seal of the Nation and countersigned by the Secretary
                        of State.</p>
                    <p>Given at the City of Habana, at the Palace of the Presidency, on this 15th
                        day of the month of March, one thousand and nine hundred and eighteen.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. G. Menocal</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Seal of the Republic of Cuba <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Pablo Desvernine</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
