<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Food Administration to the Chief of the Latin American
                    Division of the Department of State ( (Stabler))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d375</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">375</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="375"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d375">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 837.61351/43</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States Food
                            Administration</gloss> to the Chief of the Latin American Division of
                        the Department of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stabler</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-09-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 27, 1917</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: We are enclosing herewith copy of an article
                    which will be released to the press on September 30, stating the entire plan of
                    the Food Administration in regard to sugar.</p>
                <p>As this article embodies the views of the administration with regard to the
                    handling of the Cuban crop, we feel it will be of interest to you, in view of
                    the fact that you have been appealed to by the Cuban Minister.</p>
                <p>Yours very truly,</p>
                <closer>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">U. S. Food Administration</hi>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Per Geo. M. Ralph</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Article released to the press on September 30, 1917, by
                            the Public Information Division of the United States Food
                            Administration</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The United States Food Administration issues the following:</p>
                    <p>Sugar represents an entirely different problem for the Food Administration
                        from almost any other commodity it has to handle, in view of the fact that
                        about 50 per cent of the sugar we consume is imported from foreign
                        countries.</p>
                    <p>It might be interesting to know that the entire domestic production from
                        Louisiana, Hawaii, Porto Rico, and domestic beet follows the general trend
                        of prices as established in the New York market. The New York price is based
                        generally on the price of Cuban centrifugal, to which is added the duty of
                        one cent and the refiner’s differential. The Cuban sugar, therefore, becomes
                        the dominating factor, and the domestic products follow and meet this
                        competition. The domestic producers do not raise sufficient supplies for the
                        United States, causing the Cuban sugar to become the predominating feature
                        and actually control the price in the United States.</p>
                    <p>It is the intention of the Food Administration to enter into negotiations
                        with the Cuban Government and the Cuban planters to see if a voluntary
                        agreement cannot be reached fixing a price for Cuban sugars in New York that
                        will be satisfactory to the Cuban producers and at the same time insure a
                        fair price for the consuming public in the United States. The Administration
                        has every reason to believe that such a voluntary agreement can be
                        effected.</p>
                    <p>In order to handle the situation and arrange for the distribution of the
                        available sugar in the world, an international sugar committee of five
                        members has been formed. Two of the members of this committee were appointed
                        by the Allied Governments, and the men selected for this important work are
                        Sir Joseph White-Todd and John R. Drake, both of whom are familiar with the
                        sugar situation. The two American members of the committee appointed by the
                        Food Administration are Earl D. Babst, president of the American Sugar
                        Refining Co., and William A. Jamison of Arbuckle Bros., neither of whom is
                        interested in any way in the production of Cuban sugar. Mr. George M. Ralph,
                            <pb facs="0453" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/> head of the sugar division of
                        the Food Administration, will be the fifth member of the committee.</p>
                    <p>It will be the duty of this committee to arrange for the purchase and
                        distribution of all sugar, whether for the United States or the Allied
                        countries.</p>
                    <p>There will also be a committee of American refiners consisting of: Mr. C. A.
                        Spreckels, New York; Mr. Jas. H. Post. New York; Mr. C. M. Warner, New York;
                        Mr. Geo. H. Earle, jr., Philadelphia; Mr. Dwight P. Thomas, Boston, which
                        has been formed to cooperate with the international committee with the idea
                        of assisting in the distribution of that part of the imported sugar that
                        comes to the United States refineries.</p>
                    <p>The three American members of the international committee will serve as a
                        subcommittee to handle and decide purely domestic questions with which the
                        Allied members are not concerned.</p>
                    <p>Conferences held in Washington and New York between representatives of the
                        entire sugar refining industry of this country and the Food Administration
                        have resulted in a voluntary agreement for the duration of the war. Refiners
                        will undertake not only to obtain their supplies of raw sugar under the
                        direction of the International Sugar Committee, but they also have agreed to
                        work on a stipulated margin between the cost of raw sugar and the selling
                        price of refined, thus limiting profits and going a long way towards
                        stabilizing prices and eliminating speculation.</p>
                    <p>This cooperative buying between the refiners, and those purchasing raw
                        supplies for England, France, Italy, and Canada, with the resultant
                        elimination of competitive buying, is expected to save consumers many
                        millions of dollars, and to prevent the rapid fluctuations in prices that we
                        have seen since the outbreak of the European War in 1914. The natural
                        channels of trade were then suddenly disrupted, and a large part of the
                        world’s available supply of sugar was cut off, due to the fact that the
                        Central powers were no longer exporters. This was followed by a reduced
                        production of sugar in France, Belgium, and Russia, leaving the world with a
                        decreased sugar supply, but without any corresponding decrease in
                        consumption. Sugar producers were then in a position to exact high prices,
                        but now, through governing regulation, it is Intended that consumers’
                        interests shall be protected, in an effort to combat the old laws, based
                        only on supply and demand.</p>
                    <p>As a step in this process, refiners have agreed to refine sugar on a net
                        margin between the cost of their raw material and the selling price of their
                        refined product of approximately 1.30 cents per pound after trade discounts
                        have been deducted. The basis for this margin had its origin in the
                        five-year pre-war period. The figure was arrived at by taking the average
                        margin for five years previous to and including 1914, and adding the
                        increased cost of operation which refiners must now face. For example, in
                        refining sugar there is a loss in weight of about 7 pounds on every 100, and
                        as raw sugar is expected to cost in round figures about 2 cents per pound
                        more than in the five-year prewar period, this alone amounts to an increased
                        cost of 14 cents per 100 pounds. Bags, jute, and cotton have increased in
                        price equivalent to about 15 cents per 100, coal 5 cents, labor 8 cents,
                        bone black 2 cents. These increases, added to the old pre-war basis, bring
                        the figure up to 1.281 cents, so that in selling on a margin of 1.30 cents
                        net, only .019 cents per pound has been left to cover the increased cost of
                        lighterage and cartage, added interest on the larger amount of money
                        invested in the business, Increased insurance, due to explosion risks and
                        the higher valuation of sugar, as well as the higher cost of all materials
                        used in the refineries. Of course, this small fraction will not cover these
                        increased costs, so it will be seen that notwithstanding the fact that the
                        differential is higher than formerly, the actual net margin of profit left
                        to refiners is about the same as the pre-war basis. Their advantage must
                        come mainly through ability to run their plants at full capacity for nearly
                        the entre year, due to the large increase in export business which is now
                        obtainable.</p>
                    <p>The Food Administration is naturally much gratified in securing this
                        cooperation, as through it an important step had been taken to eliminate
                        speculation and place values on a stable basis, the effect of which will be
                        more apparent during the latter part of this year and in 1918 when new sugar
                        crops come on the market.</p>
                    <p>Within a short time conferences between representatives of the Cuban
                        Government, Cuban planters, and the Food Administration will be held, and
                        the price to be paid for Cuban sugar for the next crop, which begins in
                        December, will be considered.</p>
                    <pb facs="0454" n="342" xml:id="pg_342"/>
                    <p>The cost of producing sugar in Cuba has advanced greatly within the past
                        three years due to increasing cost of labor, increasing cost of all kinds of
                        supplies, increased freight rates, cost of bags, and increased taxes. These
                        conditions will naturally be taken into cons deration by the administration
                        in agreeing on a price with the Cuban planters, as it is essential that fair
                        profits be allowed to all producers in order that production be not
                        discouraged. Increasing the production of sugar to-day is just as important,
                        if not more so, than reducing the price to the consumer, as our allies
                        fighting in the trenches of Europe must be kept supplied with an adequate
                        amount of this most important food product.</p>
                    <p>The refiner sells his product to the wholesale grocery jobber through a
                        broker, and in turn the jobber sells to the retail trade. The margin of
                        profit for the jobber and the broker, like that of the refiner, will be
                        limited by the Food Administration to an amount that will represent a
                        reasonable charge for the services performed. By these regulations and
                        agreements the Food Administration hopes to eliminate speculation and to
                        deliver sugar into the hands of the retail trade at a fair cost based upon
                        the present cost of production, manufacturing, and distribution. There the
                        Food Administration’s control stops and it will be necessary for the
                        consuming public to see that they obtain their sugar at a proper price from
                        the retail trade. The administration will assist in every way through
                        publicity in keeping the country posted as to what the retailer should
                        charge in the various sections of the United States. It will be up to the
                        consumer to do the balance.</p>
                    <p>Inasmuch as the price of Cuban sugar on the New York market really controls
                        the entire domestic production, it was not the intention of the
                        administration to attempt in any way to regulate domestic producers.</p>
                    <p>A situation arose in June and July which made such action imperative. Bills
                        were introduced in Congress providing for the elimination of the drawback on
                        export sugar, and the application of a consumption tax. Foreign buyers, who
                        up to that time had been making their purchases through American refineries,
                        decided that as the bills were introduced as war measures, and would
                        therefore be enacted into law promptly, it would be to their advantage to
                        buy Cuban sugars direct at any price from the then Cuban market, not
                        exceeding an advance of 1½ cents which was the extent to which sugar would
                        have been affected if the bills had passed.</p>
                    <p>This started a violent speculation in Cuban sugars, with the result that the
                        price advanced from 5.77 in the last week in June to 7.77 the first week in
                        August. While there was very little sugar left in Cuba, it meant that if
                        such a condition was permitted to continue, the cost to the American public
                        would be something in excess of $30,000,000 between then and the beginning
                        of the new Cuban crop in December.</p>
                    <p>Refined sugar naturally followed raw, and quotations advanced to as high as
                        $9.15 per 100 pounds. To protect the public against these unnatural,
                        unnecessary, and speculative prices, the Food Administration immediately
                        changed its policy and made a direct appeal to the domestic beet-sugar
                        producers to come to the aid of the country with their product. In August
                        representatives of 85 per cent of the domestic beet-sugar industry met with
                        the Food Administration in Washington and pledged the interests which they
                        represented to maintain a price for their product of not to exceed 7.25 cane
                        basis seaboard refining points, from the beginning of the crop, starting in
                        October, until same had been distributed. Announcement of this fact had the
                        immediate effect of stopping the speculation in Cuban sugars and of reducing
                        the price generally throughout the country to more normal levels. The main
                        thing that it accomplished, however, was that it stopped further speculation
                        and prevented the price to the American consumer reaching much higher
                        levels. If the speculation in Cuban sugar had not been checked, it is not
                        unreasonable to believe that sugar would have been selling wholesale to-day
                        at prices ranging anywhere from 10 cents to 12 cents a pound. This alone
                        demonstrates conclusively the value of a domestic-grown product to the
                        United States. Too much emphasis can not be placed on this fact, and the
                        attention of the American public should be directed to this most important
                        industry.</p>
                    <p>Aside from Louisiana cane representing about one-third of the beet
                        production, and combined with the’ beet representing a total production of a
                        little over 1,000,000 tons, there is no sugar that would be available for
                        consumption in the United States if our coasts were blockaded by foreign
                        powers, as Germany’s now are. This 1,000,000 tons of domestic production
                        represents less than 25 per cent of the consumption of the country. It is
                        evident, therefore, <pb facs="0455" n="343" xml:id="pg_343"/> that every
                        encouragement should be given to this, one of our most important domestic
                        industries.</p>
                    <p>Immediately after the conferences with the beet producers in August a
                        conference was arranged at which representatives of 100 per cent of the
                        domestic industry were invited to attend, in order that action on part of
                        the industry might be made unanimous. Conferences between the Food
                        Administration and all the beet producers of the United States have been
                        held in Washington during the past few days, and it is gratifying to the
                        Government and the Food Administration to say that 100 per cent of the beet
                        producers of this country, representing many different states in the Union,
                        have voluntarily entered into an agreement with the Food Administration
                        whereby and under which the sale and distribution of the entire beet sugar
                        produced in the United States is placed in the hands of the Food
                        Administration, to be sold at a price not exceeding 7.25 cane basis seaboard
                        refining points.</p>
                    <p>The Food Administration has appointed the following committee to handle the
                        details of the distribution of the beet sugar to be known as the Food
                        Administration Sugar-Distributing Committee: H. A. Douglass, Detroit, Mich.;
                        E. C Howe, Denver, Colo.; W. H. Hannam, San Francisco, Calif.; S. H. Love,
                        Salt Lake City, Utah; W. S. Petriken, Denver, Colo.; S. W. Sinsheimer,
                        Huntington Beach, Calif.; W. P. Turner, Detroit, Mich.</p>
                    <p>The Western Sugar Refining Co. and the California-Hawaiian Sugar Refining
                        Co., both located at San Francisco, Calif., have notified the Food
                        Administrator that while it will result in tremendous losses to their
                        interests, they will join with the beet producers of the country and make
                        the price for cane sugar in the western half of the United States not to
                        exceed 7.25 cane basis seaboard refining points. This links up two of the
                        domestic sugar industries (domestic beet and Hawaiian cane) in meeting the
                        views of the Food Administration, and credit is due the western refiners in
                        complying with the views of the administration. The sugar that these
                        refineries have been receiving, and which they now have on hand, has been
                        purchased on the basis of the price of Cuban sugars in the New York market,
                        and in naming the 7.25 price they are virtually selling their refined
                        product on the basis of what the raws cost them.</p>
                    <p>As the Colorado-Utah and Michigan beet crops will not be in full swing until
                        the middle of October, and as the time of transportation from the producing
                        centers to the Atlantic seaboard is not less than twenty days, the situation
                        on the eastern seaboard presents a different problem from the West. It is
                        therefore probable that in order to save great loss the eastern refiners
                        will be compelled to maintain present prices for cane sugar until there is
                        sufficient beet available to control the eastern market.</p>
                    <p>A statement is now being prepared by the administration for the benefit of
                        the sugar trade, giving full information in regard to how the plans of the
                        administration are to be worked out.</p>
                    <p>As the domestic beet and Hawaiian cane productions are not sufficient to
                        supply the entire United States with sugar, there is bound to be some
                        confusion in certain eastern sections between October 1 and the arrival of
                        the new Cuban and Louisiana crops. Any differences between the price of cane
                        and beet sugars in the eastern markets will be eliminated on receipt of
                        these crops.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
