<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of the Navy ( (Daniels) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d399</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">399</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-08-11T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-08-13T22:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBIWbnPJBWQERtR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-08-13T22:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-08-11T23:00:00-05:00" n="399"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d399">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 439.00/36</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of the Navy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                            calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1918-08-13T23:59:59-04:00"
                            notBefore="1918-08-12T00:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">undated</hi>
                        </date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received August 13, 1918.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to previous correspondence with your
                    Department in connection with the liquidation of claims against the Dominican
                    Republic, I have the honor to forward herewith two copies of Executive Order No.
                    193, together with Spanish translations thereof, issued by the Military Governor
                    of Santo Domingo under date of August 2, 1918, in regard to the issue of bonds
                    for the purpose of paying the awards made by the Dominican Claims Commission of
                    1917.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Josephus Daniels</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Executive Order No. 193 of the Military Government of
                            Santo Domingo, dated August 2, 1918</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the Dominican Claims Commission of 1917,
                        created by Executive Order No. 60<note n="1" xml:id="d399fn1">
                            <ref target="frus1917#pg_721">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1917, p. 721</ref>.</note>
                        for the purpose of investigating and adjudicating claims against the
                        Dominican Republic, has rendered a preliminary report to the Military
                        Governor covering the claims presented and registered but not yet
                        adjudicated, showing that more than 8,800 claims have been presented
                        representing a face value of about $15,000,000, and</p>
                    <pb facs="0490" n="378" xml:id="pg_378"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, said Commission expresses the opinion
                        that many of the claims will not be sufficiently substantiated to warrant
                        payment of the full face value, as claimed, so that in all probability the
                        liquidation of the awards to be made thereof will require a sum much less
                        than the face value of the claims presented; and</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, due to the abnormal conditions at present
                        existing in all financial centers of the world, it is impracticable to
                        negotiate a foreign loan for the purpose of providing for the payment in
                        cash of said awards, and</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, under the terms of the American-Dominican
                        Convention of February 8, 1907, “until the Dominican Republic has paid the
                        whole amount of the bonds of the debt its public debt shall not be increased
                        except by previous agreement between the Dominican Government and the United
                        States,” and</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, this increase has now been authorized,
                        and the consent of the United States of America has been obtained for the
                        liquidation of the floating indebtedness of the Dominican Republic hitherto
                        unauthorized by the United States, when it shall have been adjudicated and
                        the corresponding awards made by the Dominican Claims Commission of
                        1917:</p>
                    <p>Now, therefore, by virtue of the powers vested in the Military Government of
                        Santo Domingo, and with the consent of the Government of the United States,
                        the payment of the awards to be made by the Dominican Claims Commission of
                        1917 is hereby authorized and ordered to be made as follows: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The said Commission shall transmit all awards to the Secretaría de
                                Estado de Hacienda y Comercio where they shall be registered and in
                                turn transmitted to the Contaduría General de Hacienda for
                                payment.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>All awards made by said Commission shall be paid in bonds of the
                                Dominican Republic, at par, with accrued interest, to be issued as
                                hereinafter authorized; <hi rend="italic">provided, however</hi>,
                                that all fractional amounts of such awards of less than fifty
                                dollars ($50.00) shall be paid in cash. The cash payments herein
                                provided for shall be made by checks drawn on the Designated
                                Depositary for the Dominican Republic, chargeable to a special
                                account to be opened for the purpose based on the appropriation
                                authorized in paragraph three (3) hereof.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>For the purpose of making the cash payments authorized in the
                                preceding paragraph, such amount as may be necessary is hereby
                                appropriated out of any moneys in the Treasury not otherwise
                                appropriated.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>For the purpose of paying in bonds the awards made by the
                                Dominican Claims Commission of 1917, as authorized in paragraph two
                                (2) hereof, the Contaduría General de Hacienda is hereby authorized,
                                empowered and directed to issue bonds of the Dominican Republic, in
                                the form and conditioned as hereinafter provided, to the amount that
                                shall be necessary to pay such awards, which necessary amount shall
                                not be exceeded. Said bonds shall be issued in settlement of the
                                award in each case in the following order: first, Series M; second,
                                Series D; third, Series C; and fourth, Series L; in the proportional
                                amounts required to make up the total of the award. Upon the request
                                of a holder of said bonds, the Contaduría General de Hacienda may
                                issue one or more bonds of the larger denomination in exchange for
                                bonds of the smaller denominations of equivalent value, but in no
                                case shall bonds of smaller denominations be issued in exchange for
                                a bond or bonds of larger denominations.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Said bonds shall be in coupon form, and may be in any or all of
                                the following series and denominations; Series L, fifty dollars
                                ($50.00); Series C, one hundred dollars ($100.00); Series D, five
                                hundred dollars ($500.00); Series M, one thousand dollars
                                ($1,000.00); and shall be numbered consecutively beginning with
                                number one of each series. They shall bear the facsimile signature
                                of the officer administering the affairs of the Secretaría de Estado
                                de Hacienda y Comercio and the signature of the Encargado de la
                                Contaduría General de Hacienda. They shall be dated January 1, 1918,
                                and shall bear interest at the rate of five per cent (5%) per annum,
                                which interest shall be payable semi-annually, on the first day of
                                each January and of each July. The bonds shall be payable at par on
                                or before January 1, 1938, in currency of value equivalent to gold
                                coin of the United States of America of the present standard of
                                weight and fineness, and said bonds shall become redeemable and
                                shall be payable at par in such amounts on each interest date as the
                                amount of the amortization fund, hereinafter provided for, available
                                on such interest dates will permit; <hi rend="italic">provided</hi>
                                that the bonds shall be so redeemed and paid by series as follows:
                                first, Series L; second, Series C; third, Series D; and fourth,
                                Series M. The numbers of the bonds of each series to be so <pb
                                    facs="0491" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> redeemed shall be
                                determined by lot at public drawing conducted by the Contaduría
                                General de Hacienda at Santo Domingo City within one week on either
                                side, of the first day of November, or May, as the case may be, and
                                notice of the series and numbers of such bonds to be so redeemed and
                                paid shall be given by the Contaduría General de Hacienda to the
                                Designated Depositary, hereinafter mentioned, thirty days in advance
                                of each redemption date, and such notice shall be published at least
                                once each week during the thirty days immediately preceding and
                                following each redemption date in the Official Gazette of the
                                Dominican Government and in one of the daily newspapers in the City
                                of Santo Domingo, and in one of the daily newspapers in the City of
                                New York. All interest upon the bonds so selected for redemption
                                shall cease from and after the designated date of redemption. Both
                                principal and interest shall be payable either in Santo Domingo
                                City, at the principal office of the Designated Depositary for the
                                Dominican Republic, or at any of its branch offices in the Dominican
                                Republic, or at its office in the City of New York.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The said bonds are hereby declared to be exempt from the payment
                                of taxes of any kind whatsoever of the Government of the Dominican
                                Republic or of any local authority therein.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>For the payment of the interest on said bonds, as it falls due,
                                and of the principal, the good faith of the Dominican Republic is
                                hereby irrevocably pledged, and said bonds and the obligations
                                created thereby, shall not be impaired by any law or decree which
                                the Government of the Dominican Republic or any authority thereof
                                may subsequently enact or issue, or by any interpretation thereof,
                                or by any interpretation of any law or decree heretofore enacted or
                                issued, but said bonds when duly issued shall constitute a legal and
                                binding obligation on the Government of the Dominican Republic until
                                properly redeemed and paid.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>There is hereby pledged, with the consent of the Government of the
                                United States, from the customs revenues of the Dominican Republic,
                                such amounts as may be required for the payment of the stated
                                interest of said bonds; and, to the amortization fund for the
                                redemption and payment of said bonds on the redemption dates
                                hereinbefore provided, the further sum per annum, to be deposited in
                                equal monthly installments, beginning January 1, 1918, of an amount
                                equal to one-twentieth of the total amount of the bond issue. The
                                sums pledged in this paragraph shall constitute an additional charge
                                upon all customs revenues of the Republic collected in accordance
                                with the convention of February 8, 1907, between the United States
                                of America and the Dominican Republic, after their application to
                                the first four objects designated in Article 1 of that convention,
                                and before any payment is made to the Dominican Government.
                                Additional payments for account of the amortization fund herein
                                provided may be made at any time by the Dominican Government in its
                                discretion.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>The General Receiver of Dominican Customs is hereby authorized to
                                make monthly deductions, commencing January 1, 1918, from the
                                customs receipts of the Dominican Republic, to cover the amounts
                                referred to in the preceding paragraph, and in accordance with the
                                official advice thereof furnished him by the Contaduría General de
                                Hacienda, and immediately to deposit said amounts with the
                                Designated Depositary for the Dominican Government in a special
                                account entitled “Dominican Republic 5 per cent Bond Issue 1918”;
                                and such monthly deductions and deposits shall be regularly
                                continued by the General Receiver of Dominican Customs until all of
                                the bonds herein provided for shall have been redeemed and
                                paid.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>The foregoing provisions in regard to the payment of interest on
                                said bonds, and of the principal, shall be deemed to be in the
                                nature of a continuous appropriation, and no further appropriation
                                for such purpose shall be required. The General Receiver of
                                Dominican Customs is authorized to make such deductions and
                                deposits; the Designated Depositary for the Dominican Republic is
                                authorized and directed to make such payments; and the Contaduría
                                General de Hacienda is authorized and directed to allow due credits
                                in accounts therefor.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>The Designated Depositary shall render accounts to the Contaduría
                                General de Hacienda covering the periods ending June 30th and
                                December 31st, of each year, of all receipts, accruals of interest,
                                and payments from the account “Dominican Republic 5 per cent Bond
                                Issue 1918,” and shall surrender with such statements of account all
                                coupons and bonds redeemed and paid. Upon verification of such
                                accounts the Contaduría General de Hacienda shall <pb facs="0492"
                                    n="380" xml:id="pg_380"/> make entry thereof, allow credit in
                                account therefor, and cancel and destroy the coupons and bonds so
                                received.</item>
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>Such funds as may be necessary to defray the expense of printing
                                the bonds, advertising notices relating thereto, and other expenses
                                incidental to the issuance, redemption, and cancellation thereof,
                                are hereby appropriated out of any moneys in the Treasury not
                                otherwise appropriated.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">H. S. Knapp</hi>
                        </signed>, <hi rend="italic">Rear Admiral, United States Navy</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Military Governor of Santo Domingo</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Issued at <placeName>Washington</placeName>, D.
                            C., U. S. A., <lb/> by authority of the Government of the United States, <lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-08-02">2 August 1918</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
