<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ecuadoran Minister ( (Elizalde) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d421</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">421</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-06-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-06-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-06-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-06-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="421"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d421">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 422.11G93/996</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ecuadoran Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Elizalde</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-06-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 5, 1918</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Minister of Ecuador respectfully salutes the Secretary of State and has the
                    honor to submit to him a rough draft of the conference he had with him at 11.15
                    a.m. on the 4th instant.</p>
                <p>The Minister wishes to have an authorized and accurate record of that conference
                    for transmission to the Government of Ecuador and takes the liberty of asking
                    the Secretary of State to be so good as to make corrections wherever needed in
                    the enclosed rough draft, a favor which will be duly appreciated.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum on a conference between the Secretary of State
                            and the Ecuadoran Minister</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Elizalde</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-06-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 4, 1918</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Señor Elizalde answered the call of the Secretary of State.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lansing said that he wishes to aid Ecuador and warned at the same time
                        that the interests due to the railway company must be paid in order to avoid
                        more serious restrictions being placed by the War Trade Board on the import
                        of cacao in the United States.</p>
                    <p>Señor Elizalde said that the moment did not appear to him to be well chosen
                        for taking such measures, inasmuch as the customshouse receipts, which are
                        practically the only source of revenue of the Government, had considerably
                        decreased and a large deficit in the estimates and deep uneasiness prevail
                        in the country on that account.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lansing said that the exports of Ecuador this year are larger than they
                        were last year.</p>
                    <p>Señor Elizalde replied that he had not yet received the returns, but was sure
                        that the imports were much less than they were last year.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lansing asked how there was money for the German contractors to build
                        railways in Ecuador and none with which to pay the interest due to the
                        Guayaquil &amp; Quito Railway Co.</p>
                    <p>Señor Elizalde answered that the Cuenca railway contract had been given to a
                        German firm, but that was before the war and that the work was started with
                        funds specially created for the purpose without detriment to the income
                        assigned for the service of interests on the railway bonds; he added that at
                        present work on the Cuenca railway is suspended.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lansing insisted that the interests must be paid in accordance with the
                        Ecuadoran estimates of 1917, which he showed to the Minister, and certain
                        parts of which were pointed out by Mr. Lansing.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lansing added that he thought that his opinion would have weight with the
                        War Trade Board and that he would be glad to have in the promise of
                        resumption of payment of those interests a good argument to bring against a
                        reduction of cacao imports.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lansing then said that the publication by the Government of Ecuador of
                        certain notes exchanged with the American Legation at Quito had created a
                        very bad impression and that it should not have been done.</p>
                    <p>Señor Elizalde declared that when it happened and when Mr. Hartman, American
                        Minister at Quito, protested, Señor Elizalde called upon Mr. Polk, Counselor
                        of the Department of State, and in expressing the regret which the protest
                        had caused to the Government of Ecuador, then explained to Mr. Polk that the
                        publication was made not with the object of stirring up of difficulties
                        between the two Governments, but rather of avoiding them.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lansing in bringing the interview to an end told Señor Elizalde that
                        hereafter he should talk this matter over with Mr. Stabler, Chief of the
                        Latin American Division, as Mr. Lansing is going to the country for a few
                        days.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
