<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-12-07T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-07T16:00:00-05:00" n="498" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d498">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 882.51/876a</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Chargé in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Laughlin</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d498fn1">The same (No. 6560), on the same date, to the
                                    Ambassador in France.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-12-07T16:00:00-05:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">December 7, 1918, 4 p.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3323. Following is substance of memoranda handed to representatives
                                of British and French Embassies November 19, 1918: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>In connection with credit $5,000,000 which has been
                                        established by United States Treasury Department for
                                        Republic of Liberia, it is planned by Government of United
                                        States to take following financial steps in converting
                                        Liberian loan of 1912 and administering affairs of Liberia: <list>
                                            <label>1.</label>
                                            <item>Readjust international obligations of Liberia
                                                financially through supplementary amendment to
                                                refunding loan agreement of 1912, reconstructing and
                                                converting loan and its administration into an
                                                all-American receivership. It will be unnecessary to
                                                pay off or refund international loan of 1912 and
                                                float new one, but bonds may remain where they are
                                                except as individuals may wish to dispose of their
                                                holdings. In individual cases bonds might be bought
                                                for sinking fund, but seems unlikely that any
                                                considerable number will be offered now if interest
                                                promptly met.</item>
                                            <label>2.</label>
                                            <item>Create an American Receivership of Customs and
                                                Internal Revenues, including departmental fees and
                                                port charges every nature, to be administered
                                                through American assistance to the general receiver
                                                of customs and Financial Adviser of Liberia.</item>
                                            <pb facs="0658" n="546" xml:id="pg_546"/>
                                            <label>3.</label>
                                            <item>All arrears interest on refunding loan of 1912 to
                                                be paid to date at once, and future payments
                                                interest to be promptly met from month to month.
                                                Until revenues Liberia sufficient to meet this
                                                charge, necessary funds will be advanced by United
                                                States from loan-credit of $5,000,000 recently
                                                granted Liberia.</item>
                                            <label>4.</label>
                                            <item>Payments to be made of unbonded arrears salary
                                                claims and bills against Liberia or receivership on
                                                joint approval Secretary of Treasury of Liberia and
                                                Financial Adviser. Practically all such arrears,
                                                claims, and bills were investigated, registered and
                                                bonded to and including July 1, 1918, by a domestic
                                                debt commission, consisting of Secretary of Treasury
                                                and Financial Adviser. Many claims and evidences of
                                                indebtedness were rejected. Domestic debt thus
                                                bonded amounts to about $200,000. This does not
                                                include claims enemy subjects.</item>
                                            <label>5.</label>
                                            <item>Payment to be made of contemplated sinking fund
                                                and interest on domestic bonds issued by Liberia as
                                                of July 1, 1918.</item>
                                            <label>6.</label>
                                            <item>Until revenues Liberia will permit it to assume
                                                such expenses, advances will be made from time to
                                                time on certificate of and through general receiver,
                                                of such sums as may be necessary for administrative
                                                expenses of Liberia or receivership; pay interest or
                                                sinking fund on domestic or international
                                                obligations; readjust indebtedness; provide improved
                                                transportation facilities by land and sea, as well
                                                as improved means for transmission mail and
                                                messages; provide harbor improvements, especially at
                                                Monrovia; assist organizing and maintaining modern
                                                public school system; provide scientific system
                                                intensive agriculture; provide sanitation and system
                                                potable water; establish and maintain just equitable
                                                administration of hinterland; maintain effective and
                                                efficient military police or constabulary as peace
                                                organization under American military officers, and
                                                develop potential resources and possibilities of
                                                Liberia.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>In handing these memoranda to British and French representatives,
                                they were informed that this Government contemplated proposed action
                                merely as means of assisting Liberia; that the international
                                arrangement by which responsibility was divided among four
                                Governments had not proved a working plan, but very expensive and
                                cumbersome; that this Government is deeply interested in welfare of
                                Liberian people and desires to give them in this way an opportunity
                                to prove whether they may not themselves improve their own
                                condition; that the new credit is to be used for betterment of
                                conditions generally and development of Liberia. Representatives
                                were also told that this Government hoped that their Governments
                                would receive the matter sympathetically.</p>
                            <p>For your information: This is a matter which is of importance and
                                Department desires to know at earliest possible moment attitude of
                                Government to which you are accredited.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Polk</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>