<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-07-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-07-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="590" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d590">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 711.12/132a</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Consular Officers in Mexico</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Circular]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-07-22">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July 22, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: The attached memorandum faithfully
                            interprets the wishes of the President and indicates the policy of the
                            Department of State towards Mexico. In order that this policy may be
                            given the largest possible measure of expression it is essential that
                            the Department be kept fully informed relative to actual conditions in
                            Mexico. You will therefore give the closest study to the conditions in
                            your consular district, with particular reference to anti-American
                            feeling, its origin and extent, and food shortage and industrial and
                            other requirements, and you will as soon as possible briefly telegraph
                            the Department such recommendations as you may feel will be helpful in
                            dealing with the general situation as well as with the conditions
                            peculiar to your consular district. You will follow up this cable with a
                            mail despatch in which you should give a complete and frank expression
                            of your views, together with your reasons for any recommendations you
                            may make.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilbur J. Carr</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>MEMORANDUM</head>
                            <p>The President, in addressing the Mexican editors whom he received at
                                the White House on June 7, took occasion to reiterate his sentiments
                                of friendship for the Mexican people.<note n="1" xml:id="d590fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_577">p.
                                    577</ref>.</note> To drive home to the Mexican people the
                                settled conviction that the President is determined to translate
                                into concrete and tangible form his expression of friendship for
                                Mexico has been the problem which has engaged the particular
                                attention of the Department for the past six weeks. The following is
                                a brief history of the Department’s efforts to meet and solve this
                                problem.</p>
                            <p>On April 6, 1918, the Mexican Secretary for Foreign Affairs presented
                                to Ambassador Fletcher a note to which was attached a list of
                                commodities needed by Mexico. This list was immediately forwarded by
                                the Department to the War Trade Board and to the Food Administration
                                and conferences were held with a view to the readjustment of our
                                conservation policy with reference to the needs of Mexico as set
                                forth in the list. At the conclusion of this conference the
                                Department under date of June 24, 1918, telegraphed to Ambassador
                                Fletcher asking his suggestions as to the most practicable way to
                                meet Mexico’s needs. The Department suggested to Mr. Fletcher the
                                advisability of seeking an interview with President Carranza in
                                order to express the desire of this Government to give tangible
                                expression to the friendship which it has always <pb facs="0743" n="631" xml:id="pg_631"/> entertained towards Mexico. The
                                Ambassador was authorized to assure President Carranza that this
                                Government earnestly desires the political integrity and the
                                commercial prosperity of Mexico and that it would gladly cooperate
                                in supplying Mexico with her needs in exchange for such portion of
                                that country’s products as she did not herself imperatively require.
                                He was also authorized to suggest the willingness of this Government
                                to send to Mexico City a commission to confer with Mexican officials
                                in order to adjust the questions now pending between the two
                                countries.</p>
                            <p>On June 28 Ambassador Fletcher informed the Department that he had
                                had a very cordial interview with President Carranza and had
                                informed him of President Wilson’s desire to translate into action
                                his friendly sentiments for Mexico and that President Carranza had
                                appeared greatly pleased and said that he thought intercourse both
                                personal and commercial between the two countries should be
                                normalized and the restraints now being put upon commerce and
                                communication removed so far as possible. President Carranza added
                                that if something were done along these lines he was of the opinion
                                that all difficulties and show of resentment would speedily
                                disappear. As to a loan, he stated that proposals of a tentative
                                character had been made by a few private American bankers and that
                                little had been accomplished because of the realization that without
                                the sanction of the United States Government the loan could not be
                                obtained. President Carranza felt that nothing could be gained by
                                negotiations with these private concerns and admitted that the
                                United States was the only place where Mexico could obtain the loan.
                                He declared that he was not in any way obligated to any banking firm
                                in this country. The Ambassador then assured President Carranza that
                                he saw no reason why this matter could not be arranged. He suggested
                                a conference, but President Carranza thought such a move unnecessary
                                as he had little faith in conferences and preferred to deal directly
                                with the Ambassador. He assured the Ambassador that he would be
                                pleased to receive him at any time with a view to putting into
                                effect the “new” policy of President Wilson.</p>
                            <p>On July 2, 1918, the Department telegraphed the Ambassador that as a
                                result of the conferences of the War Trade Board and the Food
                                Administration it had been learned that corn and pork products might
                                now be exported to Mexico in a much more liberal manner, and the
                                Ambassador was informed that he would shortly be instructed to make
                                a statement for publication in the Mexican press.</p>
                            <p>Following this, on July 6, 1918, the Department telegraphed the
                                Ambassador that the Department of State had arranged for a more
                                liberal policy governing the granting of export licenses for
                                shipments to Mexico, always, of course, subject to the restrictions
                                imposed by the United States Trading with the Enemy Act, and the
                                United States Enemy Trading List. The Ambassador was authorized to
                                make the appropriate announcement in the Mexican press, but was
                                instructed to make it plain that our Government had found it
                                necessary to conserve for itself and for the use of the Allied
                                Governments certain articles which would be permitted, ordinarily,
                                to go to Mexico; but that, on account of increased production, the
                                list of articles which have been prohibited is becoming shorter, and
                                the necessity for the strict application of the embargo likewise
                                decreasing; and that export licenses for the following products
                                would now be issued in the manner indicated: <list>
                                    <item>Between now and November, 1,500,000 bushels of
                                        corn.</item>
                                    <item>Pork products—licensed freely; also the following
                                        foodstuffs: butter, mutton oil, oleo oil, barreled beef,
                                        corn meal, corn flour, oats, peas (not seed), tea, cocoa,
                                        condensed milk, canned sardines, canned herring, dried
                                        fruit, and confectionery, including chocolate candy.</item>
                                    <item>Common soap—License to be granted for 2,000 tons.</item>
                                    <item>Mining machinery—Licenses will be liberally granted, where
                                        required for production of metals.</item>
                                    <item>Cyanide—since there is not sufficient to meet the demand,
                                        all countries have been rationed with respect to this
                                        commodity. However, Mexico is now being allowed sufficient
                                        cyanide for its gold products.</item>
                                    <item>Dynamite, caps and fuse—being licensed as required for
                                        mining purposes.</item>
                                    <item>Copper—While it is doubtful that this country can afford
                                        to give licenses for copper in manufactured form to an
                                        amount equal to 10 per cent of the total importation of
                                        copper from Mexico, licenses will be granted, in so far as
                                        possible.</item>
                                    <item>Zinc—Same rule applies as governs copper.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0744" n="632" xml:id="pg_632"/>
                                    <item>Ferromanganese—Licenses can be granted only to limited
                                        extent, because of great demand and shortage in this
                                        country.</item>
                                    <item>Agricultural machinery—Licenses will be granted liberally
                                        for its exportation.</item>
                                    <item>Coke—If drawn from districts which will be specified,
                                        licenses will be granted.</item>
                                    <item>Articles of steel and iron manufacture, which are
                                        mentioned in the request of April 6, of the Mexican Foreign
                                        Office—This is very indefinite. As a rule, licenses will be
                                        freely granted for all articles of iron and steel not used
                                        by this country for producing war material. On account of
                                        the necessity for conservation, this country restricts the
                                        exportation of these commodities to all countries.</item>
                                    <item>Railway machinery and materials, as shown in the enclosure
                                        to the note from the Mexican Secretary of Foreign Relations
                                        (No. 294, dated April 6, 1918.)<note n="1" xml:id="d590fn2">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_624">p.
                                                624</ref>.</note>—Licenses will be granted for
                                        everything except structural steel, bronzing sheets, sheet
                                        steel, ingots, boiler tubes, copper tubes, bars or pipes,
                                        plant for the manufacture of boiler tubes, unless it be a
                                        secondhand plant, which could be spared. Licenses would
                                        probably be granted for some new shop tools of varying
                                        classes, but unless some secondhand general shop machinery
                                        could be spared, exportation of this machinery would be
                                        difficult. We could spare only secondhand material for a
                                        car-wheel and locomotive foundry. We are making it possible
                                        for the Monterey Iron &amp; Steel Co. to turn out at least
                                        10,000 tons of 75-pound rails (which is one of the items in
                                        the list attached to the request of the Mexican Secretary of
                                        Foreign Relations), and with regard to the other item, which
                                        calls for 20 locomotives, 10 sleeping cars, and 5
                                        combination express and baggage cars, we cannot promise
                                        these now, on account of the shortage in this country.
                                        However, it may be possible for the Mexican Government to
                                        purchase a few of these which may not be needed in this
                                        country (for instance, second-hand ones), and, in such case,
                                        we would be pleased to consider granting a license.</item>
                                    <item>Ammonia—In regard to licenses for its exportation, Mexico
                                        will be given the same treatment applied to all other
                                        Central and South American countries; that is to say, no
                                        licenses granted for the purpose of beer-making, but granted
                                        when it is to be used for ice-making, refrigerating, and
                                        foodstuffs.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Ambassador was authorized to state that the foregoing list was
                                not meant to be exclusive; that it was possible that, from time to
                                time, this Government might find itself in a position to add
                                thereto, and that, should such a condition arise, it would be
                                pleased to give careful consideration to any request for additions
                                which might be made by the Mexican Government.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador was instructed to make it clear, in any announcement
                                which he might make, that, in giving this demonstration of its
                                friendliness, this Government relied on Mexico’s continuing to allow
                                the exportation to this country of such commodities as were not
                                imperatively needed by her; and that it also relied upon Mexico not
                                to permit the reexportation of such commodities as will, under this
                                plan, be granted export licenses from the United States to
                                Mexico.</p>
                            <p>On Wednesday afternoon, July 10, 1918, Ambassador Fletcher gave out a
                                statement for publication in the morning papers of July 11. This
                                statement embodied the matter set forth in the telegram last above
                                outlined.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>