<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-04-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-04-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="645" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d645">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.512/1935</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Fletcher</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 890</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-04-03">
                                        <hi rend="italic">April 3, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of my No. 815 of
                                March 1 last, and in compliance with the Department’s telegraphic
                                instructions Nos. 895, March 19, and 915, March 26,<note n="1" xml:id="d645fn1">Not printed.</note> I have the honor to enclose
                                a copy of my note No. 290 of April 2, 1918, embodying the views of
                                the Department and the formal protest of the Government of the
                                United States against the violation or infringement of legitimately
                                acquired American private property rights involved in the
                                enforcement of the petroleum decree of the 19th of February
                                last.</p>
                            <p>I called upon the Minister for Foreign Affairs on Monday morning, to
                                inform him, as directed by your telegraphic instruction 895, of the
                                instructions which I had received with regard to this decree, and I
                                reminded him that he had informed me in a previous interview that it
                                was possible that some modifications might be made in the said
                                decree. He answered that a circular had been or was being prepared,
                                which would clarify certain features of the decree, but would make
                                no modifications in substance, and that it was the Government’s
                                intention to put the decree into effect. Therefore, as reported in
                                my telegram 925 of April l,<note n="1" xml:id="d645fn2">Not
                                    printed.</note> and as instructed by the Department, I addressed
                                to him the formal protest enclosed.</p>
                            <p>In this connection, I enclose a copy and translation of the circular
                                issued by the Department of Industry, Commerce, and Labor, dated <pb facs="0825" n="713" xml:id="pg_713"/> March 11, 1918, clarifying
                                Article 14 of the decree of February 19 last, to which reference was
                                made in my telegram No. 890 of March 21, the Department’s 936, April
                                1, and my 925, April 1.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry P. Fletcher</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The American Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Fletcher</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Mexican Secretary of State for Foreign
                                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Aguilar</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 290</seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-04-02">
                                            <hi rend="italic">April 2, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: The decree of the 19th of
                                    February, 1918, which was published in the <hi rend="italic">Diario Oficial</hi> on the 27th of February last,
                                    establishing a tax on oil lands and on oil contracts executed
                                    prior to the first of May 1917, etc., has been brought to the
                                    attention of my Government, and I am under instructions to state
                                    to your excellency that my Government has given most careful
                                    consideration to the effect which this decree, if carried into
                                    operation, will have upon American interests and property rights
                                    in Mexico.</p>
                                <p>The said decree provides for the imposition of certain taxes on
                                    the surface of oil lands, as well as on the rents, royalties,
                                    and production derived from the exploitation thereof. It is
                                    noted also that among the provisions for the collection of such
                                    taxes is one requiring that payment in kind shall be delivered
                                    to the Mexican Government at the storage stations of the
                                    operators. Articles 4, 13, 14 of the said decree seem to
                                    indicate an intention to separate the ownership of the surface
                                    from that of the mineral deposits of the subsurface, and to
                                    allow the owners of the surface a mere preference in so far as
                                    concerns the right to work the subsoil deposits upon compliance
                                    with certain conditions which are specified. While the United
                                    States Government is not disposed to request for its citizens
                                    exemption from the payment of their ordinary and just share of
                                    the burdens of taxation so long as the tax is uniform and not
                                    discriminatory in its operation, and can fairly be considered a
                                    tax and not a confiscation or unfair imposition, and while the
                                    United States Government is not inclined to interpose in behalf
                                    of its citizens in case of expropriation of private property for
                                    sound reasons of public welfare, and upon just compensation and
                                    by legal proceedings before tribunals, allowing fair and equal
                                    opportunity to be heard and giving due consideration to American
                                    rights, nevertheless, the United States can not acquiesce in any
                                    procedure ostensibly or nominally in the form of taxation or the
                                    exercise of eminent domain, but really resulting in confiscation
                                    of private property and arbitrary deprivation of vested
                                    rights.</p>
                                <p>Your excellency will understand that this is not an assertion of
                                    any new principle of international law, but merely a reiteration
                                    of those recognized principles which my Government is convinced
                                    form the basis of international respect and good neighborhood.
                                    The seizure or spoliation of property at the mere will of the
                                    sovereign and without due legal process fairly and equitably
                                    administered, has always been regarded as a denial of justice
                                    and as affording internationally a basis of interposition.</p>
                                <p>My Government is not in a position to state definitely that the
                                    operation of the aforementioned decree will, in effect, amount
                                    to confiscation of American interests. Nevertheless, it is
                                    deemed important that the Government of the United States should
                                    state at this time the real apprehension which it entertains as
                                    to the possible effect of this decree upon the vested rights of
                                    American citizens in oil properties in Mexico. The amount of
                                    taxes to be levied by this decree are in themselves a very great
                                    burden on the oil industry, and if they are not confiscatory in
                                    effect—and as to this my Government reserves opinion—they at
                                    least indicate a trend in that direction. It is represented to
                                    the State Department that the taxation borne by the oil fields
                                    of Mexico very greatly exceeds that imposed on the industry
                                    anywhere else in the world. Moreover, it would be possible under
                                    the terms of the decree, in view of the fact that the Mexican
                                    Government has not storage facilities for the taxes or royalties
                                    required to be paid in kind, by storing the same in the tanks of
                                    the operators, to monopolize such storage facilities to the
                                    point of the practical confiscation thereof until emptied by
                                    order of the Mexican Government or by the forced sale of the
                                    stored petroleum to the operators at extravagant rates.</p>
                                <p>It is, however, to the principle involved in the apparent attempt
                                    at separation of surface and subsurface rights under this
                                    decree, that my Government desires to direct special attention.
                                    It would appear that the decree in question is an effort to put
                                    into effect, as to petroleum lands, paragraph 4 of Article 27 of
                                    the Constitution of May 1, 1917, by severing at one stroke the
                                    ownership of the <pb facs="0826" n="714" xml:id="pg_714"/>
                                    petroleum deposits from the ownership of the surface,
                                    notwithstanding that the Constitution provides that “private
                                    property shall not be expropriated except by reason of public
                                    utility and by means of indemnification.” So far as my
                                    Government is aware, no provision has been made by your
                                    excellency’s Government for just compensation for such arbitrary
                                    divestment of rights nor for the establishment of any tribunal
                                    invested with the functions of determining justly and fairly
                                    what indemnification is due to American interests. Moreover,
                                    there appears not the slightest indication that the separation
                                    of mineral rights from surface rights is a matter of public
                                    utility upon which the right of expropriation depends, according
                                    to the terms of the Constitution itself. In the absence of the
                                    establishment of any procedure looking to the prevention of
                                    spoliation of American citizens and in the absence of any
                                    assurance, were such procedure established, that it would not
                                    uphold in defiance of international law and justice the
                                    arbitrary confiscations of Mexican authorities, it becomes the
                                    function of the Government of the United States most earnestly
                                    and respectfully to call the attention of the Mexican Government
                                    to the necessity which may arise to impel it to protect the
                                    property of its citizens in Mexico divested or injuriously
                                    affected by the decree above cited.</p>
                                <p>The investments of American citizens in the oil properties in
                                    Mexico have been made in reliance upon good faith and justice of
                                    the Mexican Government and Mexican laws, and my Government can
                                    not believe that the enlightened Government of a neighboring
                                    Republic at peace and at a stage in its progress when the
                                    development of its resources so greatly depends on its
                                    maintaining good faith with investors and operators, whom it has
                                    virtually invited to spend their wealth and energy within its
                                    borders, will disregard its clear and just obligations toward
                                    them.</p>
                                <p>Acting under instructions, I have the honor to request your
                                    excellency to be good enough to lay before his excellency the
                                    President of Mexico, this formal and solemn protest of the
                                    Government of the United States, against the violation or
                                    infringement of legitimately acquired American private property
                                    rights involved in the enforcement of the said decree.</p>
                                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                                <closer>[File copy not signed]</closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2—Translation]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Circular No. 5 of March 11, 1918, relative to
                                        the taw on petroleum lands and petroleum,
                                        contracts</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d645fn3">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Diario Oficial</hi>, March 18,
                                        1918.</note>
                                </head>
                                <p>In order that parties interested may give due compliance to the
                                    provisions of Article 14 of the decree issued on the 19th ultimo
                                    by the Constitutional President of the United Mexican States,
                                    relative to the tax established on petroleum lands and on
                                    petroleum contracts having for their object the lease of lots
                                    for the exploitation of petroleum and other hydrocarbons which
                                    may exist in the subsoil, this Department makes known to the
                                    companies and persons interested in the petroleum industry that
                                    the declarations they are obliged to present within the period
                                    and under the conditions indicated in Article 14 of the said
                                    decree, shall be made in triplicate, on unstamped paper, and
                                    shall contain the following information:</p>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">general data</hi>
                                </p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Name of the company or person;</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Residence; city, street, and number;</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Present board of directors;</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Representative or person empowered to transact business
                                        with the Department of Industry, Commerce, and Labor.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">properties owned</hi>
                                </p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>Location, giving name, number of the lot, <hi rend="italic">hacienda</hi>, municipality, canton or
                                        district, and State;</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>Date of acquisition;</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>Area;</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>Seller;</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>Price of purchase;</item>
                                    <pb facs="0827" n="715" xml:id="pg_715"/>
                                    <label>10.</label>
                                    <item>Plan or description of boundaries, indicating the names of
                                        surrounding lands and of their owners.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">lands under lease</hi>
                                </p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>11.</label>
                                    <item>Location, giving name, number of lot, <hi rend="italic">hacienda</hi>, municipality, canton or district, and
                                        State;</item>
                                    <label>12.</label>
                                    <item>Area;</item>
                                    <label>13.</label>
                                    <item>Plans or description of boundaries, indicating the names
                                        of surrounding lands and of their owners;</item>
                                    <label>14.</label>
                                    <item>Owner, of land;</item>
                                    <label>15.</label>
                                    <item>Date on which the owner of the surface made the
                                        lease;</item>
                                    <label>16.</label>
                                    <item>Date on which the declarant made the contract;</item>
                                    <label>17.</label>
                                    <item>Length of contract;</item>
                                    <label>18.</label>
                                    <item>Rental, dominion, and other conditions.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p>The companies or persons, either the present exploiters or the
                                    last concessionaires of the right to exploit the subsoil of the
                                    leased lands, who should not present their declarations within
                                    the period indicated in Article 14 of the decree to which the
                                    circular refers, shall not be allowed to perform any work
                                    thereon, and shall be caused to suspend such work as they may
                                    have been doing on the lots covering which they may not submit
                                    declarations; this without prejudice to the imposition of the
                                    penalties stipulated by the said decree.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <dateline rendition="#left">Constitution and Reforms.
                                            <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-03-11">March 11,
                                            1918</date>.</dateline>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi>, <signed>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. J. Pani</hi>
                                    </signed> [<hi rend="smallcaps">rubric</hi>]</closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>