<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-02-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="81" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d81">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.00/2780</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Reinsch</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1905</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-02-12">
                                        <hi rend="italic">February 12, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report on the
                                general political situation in China as it has developed since the
                                first of the year.</p>
                            <p>The contrast between the conciliatory policy of Acting President Feng
                                and the desire for military gestures on the part of the Northern
                                tuchuns, reported on in my No. 1788 of December 7, 1917,<note n="1" xml:id="d81fn1">Not printed.</note> has become more marked as
                                time has passed. While unity of action is outwardly maintained,
                                there is known to be deep-seated hostility between the militarists
                                under General Tuan and the followers of the Acting President. It is
                                to be regretted that no way was found for taking General Tuan
                                Ch’i-jui out of politics by giving him a dignified national mission
                                abroad in connection with war action. As it is, General Tuan has
                                again been completely identified with the Northern militarists,
                                particularly the Anhui faction, and bitter feeling has been aroused
                                against him in the center and south of China.</p>
                            <p>Notwithstanding their professed ardent desire for military action
                                against the South, the Northern tuchuns have thus far been satisfied
                                with making continuous exorbitant demands for money on the Peking
                                Government, the funds supposedly to be expended for military
                                preparation. In Hunan, their forces have retired from Changsha to
                                Wuchang at the cost of about twelve million dollars and of a great
                                deal of suffering to the country through which these military
                                coolies passed.</p>
                            <p>The Acting President, while apparently desirous to have a
                                conciliation with the South and always to leave the door open for
                                peaceful <pb facs="0197" n="85" xml:id="pg_85"/> settlement, has
                                been weak in that he has not been able to formulate and carry out a
                                clear, definite policy. When the so-called National Council was
                                first convoked,<note n="1" xml:id="d81fn2">See <ref target="frus1917#pg_106">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1917, p.
                                    106</ref>.</note> it might easily have been possible to get the
                                country to agree to a new election law for Parliament, if a definite
                                time for such election had been fixed. Instead of that, General Feng
                                gave the impression that he was supporting the National Council, and
                                it was believed that he would not oppose an attempt to have it
                                displace Parliament, an action most distasteful to the South. The
                                Acting President’s traditional compromising tactics were not
                                adequate to the present situation.</p>
                            <p>The crisis seemed to be impending when the President, on January 25,
                                suddenly decided to leave Peking. It was formally given out that he
                                was undertaking an inspection trip, with a view to persuade the
                                “militant” tuchuns to take more active and concerted measures
                                against the South. This is perhaps the most convoluted inversion
                                that Chinese politics has yet produced; that the “militant” tuchuns,
                                supposedly champing at their bits, should need presidential
                                persuasion, and that it should be the pacifist President who started
                                on such an errand is at first sight reminiscent of <hi rend="italic">Alice in Wonderland</hi>, and yet this explanation of the
                                reasons for the President’s trip was solemnly given out to the
                                diplomats by the Minister of Foreign Affairs.</p>
                            <p>The fact was that neither the President nor the tuchuns really wanted
                                to fight. The tuchuns were making quantities of money without any
                                danger to themselves. Both, however, were in danger of losing face.
                                Chinese politics has become more and more theatrical, and as the
                                figures on the stage stamp about and try to make a deep impression
                                by terrifying gestures, so in the minds of both the President and
                                the tuchuns, a terrifying gesture against the South was needed, and
                                it was hoped that this might do the business. From the point of view
                                of the Acting President, who, after all, was supposedly at the head
                                of the whole country, the action of the South involved a certain
                                loss of face; the South, while willing to talk peace, was rather
                                uncompromising with respect to the conditions. So it is possible
                                that the President honestly believed that if a military show could
                                be made in Hunan, a compromise might be more readily reached. This
                                at any rate was the inner explanation which was given of his policy.
                                As for the tuchuns, they also desired a terrifying gesture against
                                the South, but they distrusted the President; before beginning to
                                gesture, they demanded that he should issue a mandate declaring
                                public hostilities in force against the South. After that they would
                                act. So it might be understood that the President took his journey
                                of inspection for the purpose of making the tuchuns agree to the
                                terrifying show of military action against the South without first
                                demanding the President to issue a mandate of absolute hostility,
                                which was against his underlying instinct of compromise.</p>
                            <p>The President started on his trip, got as far as Peng-pu, where he
                                met General Ni Ssu-ch’ung, the most notorious of the “militant”
                                tuchuns, and returned to Peking. It was given out that his trip had
                                been eminently successful, that he had persuaded the tuchuns to take
                                common action, and that even Li Shun had promised to send a brigade
                                against the Hunanese. Mandates have been issued, but <pb facs="0198" n="86" xml:id="pg_86"/> so far there has been no result except
                                further appropriations of public moneys to the “militants.”</p>
                            <p>The early return of the President is, however, not believed by any
                                one to be in accordance with his original program. It is believed
                                that his real objective was Nanking, where, in touch with Military
                                Governor Li Shun, he might hold the balance of power between the
                                North and the South. The Consul at Nanking and Mr. E. M. Lamb, the
                                representative of the naval attaché, report from the accounts of
                                eyewitnesses that Ni Ssu-ch’ung met the Acting President at Peng-pu,
                                accompanied by the larger part of his military forces. He is said to
                                have addressed the Acting President in the strongest language, and
                                to have laid before him cogent reasons for returning immediately to
                                Peking. The President had with him at the time only the military
                                guard he was carrying on his own train. He accepted the suggestion
                                of Ni Ssu-ch’ung.</p>
                            <p>At the present time the position of the Acting President in Peking is
                                weak and full of embarrassment. Rumors of all kinds abound,
                                including the perennial one of an impending restoration. From such
                                information as I have from influential Chinese in close touch with
                                the situation, it would appear that the faction which is grouped
                                about General Tuan Ch’i-jui and which uses his name and reputation
                                as their banner, is thinking seriously of ousting General Feng
                                Kuochang from his position, and by an act of the so-called National
                                Assembly, placing Hsti Shih-ch’ang in his place. Liang Shih-yi, Chow
                                Tze-chi, and Chu Ch’i-ch’ien, with their minor associates, have just
                                been pardoned. Liang Shih-yi is returning from a prolonged stay in
                                Japan. It is most likely that the Tuan faction is attempting to make
                                a combination with this so-called communications clique, counting on
                                the ability of these men and the support which they supposedly might
                                get from Japan, to strengthen the Tuan faction sufficiently to
                                enable it to hold its own against the South. Through Ts’ao Ju-lin
                                and General Tuan Chih-kwei, the Minister of War, Japanese support
                                had already previously been arranged in the matter of the
                                ten-million-yen loan and the furnishing of large quantities of arms.
                                The extent of the support given and to be given by the Japanese
                                Government to the Tuan fact [faction?] is, as will be known to you,
                                one of the burning issues in Japanese politics at present.</p>
                            <p>Considered from the point of view of government and authority, the
                                present Cabinet is the weakest which has existed during the last
                                five years, at least. The Cabinet is weak through having no policy
                                and through being divided on account of the deep-seated
                                incompatibility of its component parts. The orders of the Government
                                carry no authority beyond Peking. On the financial side, the
                                weakness is most pitiable, and is clue to the exhaustion of the
                                treasury through the demands of the “militant” tuchuns.
                                Notwithstanding the large proceeds of the remitted Boxer indemnity,
                                the Government banks are still in a state of approaching bankruptcy.
                                The Minister of Finance, Wang K’o-min, … has not only been unable to
                                carry on the finances of the country out of the abundant income of
                                the customs and the salt revenue, but he has borrowed large sums
                                from Japanese sources, in some cases with the mortgaging of specific
                                valuable property and rights, in all cases to the injury of Chinese
                                financial independence.</p>
                            <pb facs="0199" n="87" xml:id="pg_87"/>
                            <p>Turning now to the Southern provinces, aside from the military
                                successes of General T’an Hao-min in driving the Northern troops
                                from Changsha and Yochow to the north, the most important
                                development is an attempt to create a confederated council or
                                commission for the constitutionalist provinces. The men who are now
                                mentioned as likely to compose this council are the following:
                                military, T’ang Chi-yao, Cheng Pi-kwang, and Lu Yung-t’ing; foreign
                                affairs, Wu Ting-fang; finances, Tong Shao-yi; and peace
                                negotiations, Ts’en Ch’un-hsüan. In connection with this proposal, I
                                have the honor to enclose Canton’s despatch No. 62 of January 21,
                                    1918.<note n="1" xml:id="d81fn3">Not printed.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The project would involve the elimination of Sun Yat Sen from primary
                                influence. In the words of Mr. C. C. Wu, the object of the leaders
                                of this movement is not permanent separation of North and South, but
                                an effort to bring about more complete cooperation and unity in the
                                movement for constitutional government. The Southern leaders have
                                protested to Japan against loans to the Peking Government. They are
                                also planning to make representations with respect to the use of the
                                customs and salt revenues, demanding assurances that these funds
                                will not be used for factional militarist support. The chief
                                difficulty with the Southern movement thus far has been lack of
                                unity. The suspicion has been that while having the advantage of the
                                North in standing for an important principle of public
                                policy—constitutionalism and representative government—yet the
                                individual military leaders of the South were probably animated by
                                motives similar to those of the North, particularly the desire to
                                maintain and fortify their own personal positions. In fact, all of
                                China is in danger of disintegrating into feudalities under military
                                men who do not even have the merit that they can fight but who do
                                their work through crooked intrigue and corruption, hiring coolie
                                forces as a matter of face and gain to themselves. If this spirit
                                can be overcome in the South through encouragement for loyal
                                cooperation in a common cause, the movement will gain enormously in
                                strength. In fact any group of permanent leaders who would be bound
                                together by loyalty to each other and a truly public motive, would
                                be irresistible in China. As it is, each man stands alone, fights
                                for his life, wealth, and official existence.</p>
                            <p>The importance of Nanking as a pivotal point in Chinese politics has
                                become even greater than before. Military Governor Li Shun is the
                                youngest of the tuchuns. He has therefore been accessible to ideas
                                of national action which the older men are too [conservative] to
                                receive. He too has to fight for his authority over his troops and
                                provinces, because every possible means is brought to bear to
                                undermine it. He is stigmatized as too ambitious for his youth, as
                                inexperienced, and as desirous of playing his own game. But to all
                                observers who stand outside of the intrigues of Chinese politics, he
                                appears to be a man who has caught sight of the possibility of a
                                national policy which the others had not even conceived. He belongs
                                to the so-called Chihli group of the Northern military part, of
                                which General Feng Kuo-chang and General Ts’ao K’un, the tuchun of
                                Chihli Province, are also members. But he has of late tried more and
                                more to disengage himself from the intrigues of the Northern
                                military parties and to assume the position of a mediator between
                                the North and the South, trying to develop a national policy to <pb facs="0200" n="88" xml:id="pg_88"/> which they could all rally.
                                The dirtiest methods of intrigue have been used against him in an
                                effort to undermine him, particularly through buying his subordinate
                                commanders. The only action that a “militant” tuchun is formidable
                                in, is bribery; in this bloodless underground warfare they are
                                thoroughly at home.</p>
                            <p>Since the return of Acting President Feng to Peking, the break
                                between General Li Shun and the Northern tuchuns has become almost
                                open, although it was announced, as reported above, that Li Shun had
                                agreed to furnish a brigade for the expedition against the South.
                                From information from various reliable sources, I am convinced that
                                General Li Shun has now made up his mind that if there is to be any
                                fighting it is not to be against the South, but against individual
                                corrupt militarists who continue to disturb the peace of the country
                                for selfish motives. With this in view, General Li Shun recently
                                sent a circular telegram to all the military governors, a copy of
                                which is herewith enclosed.<note n="1" xml:id="d81fn4">Not
                                    printed.</note> The telegram puts the double inquiry as to
                                whether the recipient desires to fight, and, if so, for what cause
                                or principle: “If there is going to be civil war, that war should be
                                waged for a just cause and with a definite and clear objective. … In
                                the past both peace and war have been made without purpose, without
                                consideration for the country, and recklessly.” General Li Shun
                                through this telegram is attempting to arrive at a clear statement
                                of the issue, and to isolate those who desire to continue the
                                present confusion without public motives.</p>
                            <p>Another step which has been taken is an invitation on the part of the
                                Kiangsu provincial assembly to all other provincial assemblies to
                                send delegates to Nanking in order to discuss the possibility of
                                national peace and concord. All but the Provinces of Anhui, Chihli,
                                Honan and Sinkiang have already accepted this invitation. …</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul S. Reinsch</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>