<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>10. Telegram 250151 From the Department of State to All Diplomatic Posts,
                    December 26, 1973, 2137Z.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-12-26T16:37:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-12-26T16:37:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="rec0YIEoMSlyPKAGO" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="general-agreement-on-tariffs-and-trade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001009859"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">GATT</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="recQ2U5eNbEz7Znwk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006006835"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Donor</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090254"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Natural resources</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Science and technology</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recfab616ca717a635" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="decolonization" subject="colonialism">Colonialism</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recfBXf5mApMtKJKj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peacekeeping-forces" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002546" lcsh-match="exact">Peacekeeping</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-12-26T16:37:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-12-26T16:37:00-05:00" n="10"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                <head>10. Telegram 250151 From the Department of State to All Diplomatic Posts,
                    December 26, 1973, 2137Z.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d10fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy Files. Confidential.
                        Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SCW1">Schaller</persName> and other <gloss
                            target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> staff members; cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNL1">McNutt</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MGN1"
                            >Monsma</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SSD1">Schiff</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_WJW3">Walker</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_GD1">Goott</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BRJ3"
                            >Bettauer</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Morey</persName>, and
                        in <gloss target="#t_ACDA1">ACDA</gloss>; and approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_PDH1">Popper</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>’s September 24 address to the United Nations is
                        scheduled for publication in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                        1969–1976, volume XXXVIII, Foundations and Organization of Foreign Policy,
                        1973–1976.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d10fn2">The Department assessed how well the
                        United Sates achieved its goals during the 28th United Nations General
                        Assembly and outlined issues likely to arise at the 29th General Assembly.
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-12-26T21:37:00+00:00">December 26, 1973,
                        2137Z</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>TELEGRAM <lb/> Department of State <lb/> 250151</p>
                <p>R 262137Z DEC 73</p>
                <p>FM SECSTATE WASHDC <lb/> TO ALL DIPLOMATIC POSTS <lb/> AMEMBASSY BANJUL BY POUCH
                    <lb/> AMEMBASSY TAIPEI BY POUCH <lb/> XMT AMEMBASSY SUVA <lb/> AMEMBASSY
                    SAIGON</p>
                <p>STATE 250151</p>
                <p>E.O. 11652: GDS <lb/> TAGS: PFOR, <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                </p>
                <p>SUBJECT: ASSESSMENT OF 28TH UNGA <lb/> REF: (A) STATE 163147; (B) <gloss
                        target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 5723; (C) USUN 5727; (D) USUN 5732</p>
                <p>1. SUMMARY: ON THE WHOLE, OUTCOME FOR US OF 28TH <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                        >GA</gloss> WHICH RECESSED DECEMBER 18 WAS BETTER THAN WE HAD EXPECTED, WITH
                    SUPPORT OF OUR DIPLOMATIC MISSIONS CONTRIBUTING GREATLY TO SUCCESS IN SEVERAL
                    CRITICAL SITUATIONS. INITIATIVES IN SECRETARY’S GA ADDRESS HAD POSITIVE IMPACT.
                    WE WERE ABLE TO ATTAIN OBJECTIVES ON SEVERAL IMPORTANT POLITICAL ITEMS, WHILE
                    REMAINING IN SMALL MINORITY ON MOST AFRICAN AND ISRAELI RELATED ISSUES. IN
                    ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL AREAS US JOINED IN CONSENSUS WITH DEVELOPING COUNTRIES ON
                    NUMBER OF IMPORTANT RESOLUTIONS IN CONTRAST WITH RELATIVE ISOLATION IN 1972. WE
                    ALSO MADE MODEST GAINS IN HUMAN RIGHTS AREA AND IN URGING FISCAL RESPONSIBILITY.
                    HOWEVER, GROWING AFRO-ARAB COHESION AND MILITANCY IN PURSUING OBJECTIVES OFTEN
                    CONTRARY TO OUR INTERESTS WILL MAKE DEFENSE OF US POSITIONS AND ACHIEVEMENT OF
                    OUR GOALS IN <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> CONTEXT EVEN MORE DIFFICULT NEXT
                    YEAR. ACTION REQUESTED: REVIEW WITH HOST GOVERNMENT AS APPROPRIATE. ALSO,
                    EMBASSY COMMENTS APPRECIATED. END SUMMARY.</p>
                <p>2. GENERAL ASSESSMENT: WE ARE REASONABLY PLEASED WITH OVERALL GA RESULTS. THERE
                    WERE SOME SUCCESSES IN ALL FIELDS. WHERE SETBACKS OCCURRED, THEY WERE CONTAINED.
                    POLEMICS WERE KEPT WITHIN BOUNDS WITH FEW EXCEPTIONS, SUCH AS <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> ON MIDDLE EAST, AND <gloss target="#t_PRC1"
                        >PRC</gloss> ON CAMBODIA AND AGAINST USSR ON DISARMAMENT. OUR SATISFACTION,
                    HOWEVER, IS TEMPERED BY REALIZATION THAT PROSPECTS FOR NEXT YEAR’S GA LESS THAN
                    PROMISING.</p>
                <p>3. 28TH GA DEMONSTRATED INCREASING TENDENCY OF <gloss target="#t_LDC1"
                        >LDC</gloss>’S TO PREOCCUPY UN WITH THEIR PRIORITIES AND TO GAIN UN
                    ENDORSEMENT OF POLITICAL POSITIONS ESTABLISHED IN NON-ALIGNED AND <gloss
                        target="#t_OAU1">OAU</gloss> FORUMS. TO SOME EXTENT THIS STEMS FROM
                    FRUSTRATION THAT IMPORTANT WORLD PROBLEMS ARE LARGELY DEALT WITH OUTSIDE UN. IN
                    MAIN, HOWEVER, MILITANT GROUP OF “NONALIGNEDS” ARE SEEKING TO CAPITALIZE ON
                    THEIR PARLIAMENTARY VOTING POWER TO MAKE GA SERVE THEIR PURPOSES.</p>
                <p>4. US POSITION ON POLITICAL ISSUES WAS INCREASINGLY DEFENSIVE. WE SOUGHT BY
                    FINESSING CONFRONTATIONS AND REDUCING UN ROLE IN ISSUES OF IMPORTANCE TO REDUCE
                    OUR VULNERABILITY IN DEBATE, E.G., ON KOREA. OTHERWISE WE STROVE TO ANTICIPATE
                    AND MANEUVER TO LIMIT THE DAMAGE, E.G., ON KHMER CREDENTIALS, MIDDLE EAST, AND
                    DISARMAMENT. ON ECONOMIC AND DEVELOPMENT ISSUES, WE NEGOTIATED RESOLUTIONS THAT
                    LEAVE BASIC DECISIONS TO <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>, <gloss
                        target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> AND OTHER FORA WHERE ECONOMIC REALITIES RECEIVE
                    GREATER WEIGHT.</p>
                <p>5. OUR TASK WAS COMPLICATED BY GROWING AFRO-ARAB MILITANT DOMINATION OF
                    NON-ALIGNED MOVEMENT AND BY FREQUENT UNWILLINGNESS OR INABILITY OF MODERATES TO
                    RESIST PRESSURE FOR GROUP SOLIDARITY. VOTES OR POSITIONS WERE OFTEN JUSTIFIED BY
                    REFERENCES TO NON-ALIGNED CONFERENCE (<gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>)
                        <gloss target="#t_Reses1">RESES</gloss> EVEN WHEN SUBJECTS HAD NOT BEEN
                    FULLY DEBATED OR ENDORSED BY ALL PARTICIPANTS AND WERE FAR REMOVED FROM DIRECT
                    INTEREST OF COUNTRIES CONCERNED (E.G., NAC RESES ON KOREA, CAMBODIA, PUERTO
                    RICO).</p>
                <p>6. NONETHELESS OPPORTUNITIES REMAIN TO AVOID AUTOMATIC APPLICATION OF NON-ALIGNED
                    VOTING MAJORITY BY SPLITTING OFF MODERATE NON-ALIGNED FROM MILITANTS THROUGH
                    SUCH MEANS AS: (A) ADOPTING POSITION ON “MIDDLE GROUND” OR WHICH OTHERWISE
                    DEEMED EQUITABLE OR REASONABLE (E.G., DEFERMENT OF KHMER REPRESENTATION ITEM;
                        <gloss target="#t_UNEF1">UNEF</gloss> FINANCING FORMULA); (B) WORKING WITH
                    SELECTED AFRO-ASIAN REGIONALS (E.G., SE ASIAN EFFORTS IN KHMER CREDENTIALS) AND
                    OTHERWISE CONVINCING NON-ALIGNED THAT SPECIFIC PROPOSALS ARE IN THEIR OWN
                    INTEREST (SUCCESSFULLY IN CASE OF CONVENTION ON PROTECTION OF DIPLOMATS); AND
                    (C) ENCOURAGING RECOGNITION THAT SUCCESS OF DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM DEPENDS ON
                    CONTINUING COOPERATION OF DONOR COUNTRIES. AT SAME TIME, EXIGENCIES OF US
                    WORLD-WIDE INTERESTS AND COMMITMENTS USUALLY INHIBIT US FROM EFFECTIVE
                    LOG-ROLLING. MOREOVER OUR INCREASED IDENTIFICATION WITH ISRAEL AND PORTUGAL IN
                    CONNECTION MIDDLE EAST WAR AND USE OF AZORES FURTHER REDUCED OUR ALREADY SLIM
                    MARGIN OF MANEUVER WITH AFRICAN AND ARAB UN DELEGATIONS.</p>
                <p>7. WE MUST EXPECT THAT AT 29TH GA NON-ALIGNED MILITANTS, AWARE OF THEIR VOTING
                    COHESION AND STRENGTH, IN CONTROL OF ASSEMBLY PROCEDURES, AND PROBABLY WITH
                    ALGERIAN FOREIGN MINISTER <persName corresp="#p_BAA1">BOUTEFLIKA</persName> IN
                    THE PRESIDENCY, WILL PRESS EVEN MORE ENERGETICALLY ISSUES OF IMPORTANCE TO THEM
                    SUCH AS COLONIALISM, RACE DISCRIMINATION, SOVEREIGNTY OVER NATURAL RESOURCES,
                    AND PREFERENTIAL TRADE AND DEVELOPMENT MEASURES. EVEN WHEN WE ARE SYMPATHETIC TO
                    THEIR OBJECTIVES, WE MUST OPPOSE METHODS SUCH AS APPLICATION OF UNREALISTIC
                    SANCTIONS OR USE OF UN AND ITS RESOURCES TO AID INSURGENT GROUPS.</p>
                <p>8. THUS, OVERALL PROBLEM FOR US THROUGH NEXT YEAR WILL BE HOW TO COPE WITH OUR
                    NEAR-ISOLATION ON POLITICAL ISSUES OF OVERRIDING INTEREST TO A UNGA DOMINATED BY
                    MILITANT AFRO-ARABS SUPPORTED NOT ONLY BY PRC AND SOVIET GROUP BUT ALSO ENJOYING
                    SYMPATHY IN SOME CASES OF WEST EUROPEANS. AS THIS TREND CONTINUES, GA LIKELY TO
                    BECOME EVEN LESS HOSPITABLE TO SERIOUS AND DISPASSIONATE CONSIDERATION OF
                    POLITICAL POLICY.</p>
                <p>9. SITUATION REQUIRES US TO REVIEW AND IMPROVE OUR DAMAGE-LIMITING TECHNIQUES AND
                    RE-EXAMINE OUR STYLE, WHICH IS FREQUENTLY IMPORTANT IN INFLUENCING GA RESULTS.
                    FURTHER, WE MUST ACTIVELY FOLLOW THROUGH ON INITIATIVES SUCH AS THOSE ANNOUNCED
                    BY SECRETARY, NOTABLY ON PEACEKEEPING, FOOD SECURITY, DEVELOPMENT, AND SCIENCE
                    AND TECHNOLOGY. FINALLY, WE SHOULD SEEK TO DEVELOP ADDITIONAL INITIATIVES IN
                    SUCH FIELDS AS HUMAN RIGHTS AND DISARMAMENT, WHERE THERE ARE PROSPECTS FOR MOVES
                    WHICH WOULD BE BOTH SUBSTANTIVELY AND COSMETICALLY USEFUL.</p>
                <p>10. ACTION REQUESTED: POSTS MAY FIND IT USEFUL TO REVIEW WITH HOST GOVERNMENTS
                    VARIOUS ASPECTS OF ANALYSIS CONTAINED IN THIS TELEGRAM AND REFTELS. POSTS WILL
                    KNOW BEST HOW TO TAILOR DISCUSSION TO LOCAL SITUATIONS, BUT WE HOPE THEY WILL AS
                    APPROPRIATE DRAW HOST GOVERNMENT’S ATTENTION TO OUR SERIOUS CONCERN RE LONGER
                    TERM EFFECTS OF UNDUE POLITICIZATION OF ISSUES, BLOC VOTING PRACTICES, AND
                    DOCTRINAIRE MILITANCY OF NON-ALIGNED. IF NOT MODERATED, THESE TRENDS COULD IN
                    OUR VIEW FURTHER UNDERCUT UNGA EFFECTIVENESS ON WIDE RANGE OF POLICY PROBLEMS.
                    WE WOULD ALSO APPRECIATE HAVING ANY EMBASSY VIEWS ON POINTS COVERED IN THIS
                    MESSAGE AND REFTELS. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">KISSINGER</persName>
                    <lb/> NOTE BY OCT: POUCHED BANJUL AND TAIPEI.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
