<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-04-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="124" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                        <head>124. Memorandum From the Coordinator for Population Affairs (Green) to
                            Secretary of State Kissinger, Washington, April 13, 1976.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d124fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Foreign Policy Files, P760069–0390. Confidential. Sent for
                                action. Drafted on April 13 by <persName corresp="#p_GM3">Green</persName>. Sent through <persName corresp="#p_KMB1">Kratzer</persName>. A handwritten notation indicates that
                                Kissinger approved, on May 7, the draft cable attached at Tab 1. Tab
                                1, not printed, was sent as telegram 113982 to all diplomatic posts,
                                May 10, indicating Kissinger’s personal interest in promoting U.S.
                                population policy objectives. (Ibid., Central Foreign Policy Files)
                                The memorandum of Kissinger’s conversation with Green and other
                                Department officials on Saturday, April 10, is published as <ref target="#d123">Document 123</ref>. <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 314 is published as <ref target="#d122">Document
                                    122</ref>. Kissinger’s May 6 speech to the United Nations
                                Conference on Trade and Development in Nairobi is published in
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, May 31, 1976,
                                pp. 657–672.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d124fn2">Green submitted a list of
                                specific actions Kissinger could take to support U.S. international
                                population policy.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-04-13">April 13, 1976</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <pb facs="d124-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d124-1"/>
                        <pb facs="d124-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d124-2"/>
                        <p>DEPARTMENT OF STATE<lb/>ACTION MEMORANDUM</p>
                        <p>April 13, 1976</p>
                        <p>TO: The Secretary<lb/>Through: OES - <persName corresp="#p_KMB1">Myron
                                Kratzer</persName>
                            <lb/> FROM: <gloss target="#t_OESCP1">OES/CP</gloss> - <persName corresp="#p_GM3">Marshall Green</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>Actions Regarding World Population Growth</p>
                        <p>The Problem </p>
                        <p>You requested at our meeting last Saturday that I submit a list of
                            specific actions where you could be helpful in regard to our efforts to
                            curb world population growth. Specific actions are briefly summarized
                            below.</p>
                        <p>Background Analysis</p>
                        <p>-- Attached at Tab 1 is a message to the field which sets forth your
                            concern about world population growth and the attention you expect our
                            Ambassadors to give to the issue, notably in their conversations with
                            leaders.</p>
                        <p>-- Your <gloss target="#t_UNCTAD1">UNCTAD</gloss> Speech. I have just
                            submitted to the Deputy Secretary suggested language for inclusion in
                            your UNCTAD speech, which relates to primary health services, status of
                            women, and greater emphasis on food-for-work type projects to increase
                                <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss> agricultural production, raise
                            rural living standards, provide employment, and reduce urban
                            migration.</p>
                        <p>-- Trips and Visits. As specifically mentioned in <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 314, it will be most helpful if the
                            President and you, as appropriate, discuss population issues with
                            interested foreign leaders during their visits to Washington or during
                            your trips abroad. To this end, we will be preparing suggested talking
                            punts for your forthcoming African trip.</p>
                        <p>-- Meeting Non-Governmental Population Groups. Last year the State
                            Department sponsored a meeting on population issues attended by
                            representatives of some 150 non-governmental groups concerned with
                            population-related issues. It would give all these groups a real shot in
                            the arm if occasion could be found this Fall for you to address a
                            similar meeting which could be either under State Department auspices or
                            organized by the World Population Society which is a new organization
                            with high prestige.</p>
                        <p>-- Greater Emphasis on Food-for-Work Projects. This may be covered in
                            your UNCTAD speech and represents one of several moves I believe we can
                            and should take in the area of promoting rural agriculture, community
                            development, and village organization. Among other benefits, such
                            measures will create a better setting for family planning programs.</p>
                        <p>Recommendation </p>
                        <p>That you sign the attached cable.--[approve HAK]</p>
                        <p>Attachment Cable to All Diplomatic Posts </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>