<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-05-17T18:04:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-05-17T18:04:00-05:00" n="14" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                        <head>14. Telegram 104050 From the Department of State to All Diplomatic
                            Posts, May 17, 1974, 2304Z.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d14fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy Files.
                                Confidential. Repeated to Beijing. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WJ4">Washburn</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_VX1">Vunovic</persName>; cleared in D and by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SLT1">Stull</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MJWJ1">McDonald</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NAF1">Neidle</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SRC3">Searing</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MNL1">McNutt</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SSM2">Schwebel</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GD1">Goott</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MGN1">Monsma</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WJW3">Walker</persName>,
                                and <persName corresp="#p_BRO1">Blake</persName>; and approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BWB1">Buffum</persName>. Telegram 99106 is
                                published as <ref target="#d13">Document 13</ref>.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d14fn2">The Department alerted posts
                                to “steamroller tactics” employed by non-aligned countries at the
                                United Nations and indicated that démarches should be made to
                                governments indicating U.S. concerns.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-05-17T23:04:00+00:00">May 17,
                                1974, 2304Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>TELEGRAM <lb/> Department of State <lb/> 104050</p>
                        <p>R 172304Z MAY 74</p>
                        <p>FM SECSTATE WASHDC <lb/> TO ALL DIPLOMATIC POSTS <lb/> INFO USLO PEKING
                            <lb/> AMCONSUL <lb/> AMEMBASSY TAIPEI <lb/> AMEMBASSY SUVA BY POUCH</p>
                        <p>STATE 104050</p>
                        <p>E.O. 11652: GDS <lb/> TAGS PFOR, XA, XB, XR, YO, RO, MT, UN</p>
                        <p>SUBJECT: <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> SIXTH SPECIAL SESSION --
                            STEAMROLLER TACTICS</p>
                        <p>1. UNGA SIXTH SPECIAL SESSION RAISED VARIETY OF ISSUES WITH WHICH DEPT
                            AND <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> WILL BE CONCERNED OVER NEXT
                            SEVERAL MONTHS. MOST WILL BE DESCRIBED IN FORTHCOMING CIRCULAR AIRGRAM
                            GIVING EXTENSIVE ASSESSMENT OF SESSION. STATE 94134 HAS REPORTED
                            SESSION’S HANDLING OF US $4 BILLION AID PROPOSAL. DEPT IS ALSO
                            CONSULTING MANY POSTS ON STATUS OF RELATIONS AMONG <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>’S AND WITH DEVELOPING COUNTRIES
                            FOLLOWING SIXTH SPECIAL SESSION (STATE 099106). THIS MESSAGE OUTLINES
                            FOR YOUR INFORMATION AND ACTION WITH HOST GOVERNMENTS MORE LIMITED
                            QUESTION OF OUR CONCERN OVER EMPLOYMENT BY NON-ALIGNED CONFERENCE
                            GROUP/GROUP 77 AT SPECIAL SESSION OF “AUTOMATIC MAJORITY.”</p>
                        <p>2. AS POSTS AWARE, WE HAVE LONG BEEN TROUBLED AT TENDENCY OF MANY LDC’S
                            AND SOMETIMES OTHERS TO PUSH THROUGH RESOLUTIONS WITHOUT ADEQUATE
                            CONSIDERATION OR REGARD TO PRACTICAL PROBLEMS OF IMPLEMENTATION.
                            REPEATED PASSAGE OF SUCH RESOLUTIONS WITHOUT SERIOUS EFFORTS TO MEET
                            IMPORTANT VIEWS OF MEMBERS IN MINORITY WHOSE COOPERATION ESSENTIAL FOR
                            IMPLEMENTING THEM DEBASES IMPORTANCE OF <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> RESOLUTIONS, PARTICULARLY IN <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. AT SIXTH SPECIAL SESSION, THE <gloss target="#t_G771">G-77</gloss> AND <gloss target="#t_NACG1">NACG</gloss> COMPOUNDED
                            PAST PRACTICE BY USING STEAMROLLER MAJORITY TO (A) PREVENT FURTHER BRIEF
                            EXTENSION OF SPECIAL SESSION FOR CONSIDERATION OF VOLUMINOUS
                            PRE-PREPARED DOCUMENTS (DECLARATION OF PRINCIPLES AND PLAN OF ACTION),
                            FINAL TEXT OF WHICH THERE WAS NO OPPORTUNITY TO STUDY ADEQUATELY (E.G.
                            ONE IMPORTANT AMENDMENT WAS IN FACT NOT SHOWN TO US UNTIL ADOPTION.),
                            (B) SHARPLY LIMIT MEANINGFUL NEGOTIATION DESPITE IMPORTANCE AND
                            COMPLEXITY OF SUBJECT, (C) PREVENT ADEQUATE CONSIDERATION OF DIVERSITY
                            OF VIEWS INCLUDING RESOLUTIONS PRESENTED BY OTHER UN MEMBERS AND (D) USE
                            DISPOSITION FOR CONSENSUS TO DISSUADE DISSENTERS FROM REQUIRING A
                            VOTE.</p>
                        <p>3. FOR EXAMPLE, AT APRIL 29 MEETING OF AD HOC COMMITTEE (OF THE WHOLE),
                            FRANCE, JAPAN (WITH MALAYSIA CO-SPONSOR), NEW ZEALAND (WITH SRI LANKA
                            CO-SPONSOR), AND US INTRODUCED RESOLUTIONS INTENDED TO IMPLEMENT
                            PROPOSALS MADE IN THEIR PLENARY SPEECHES. THEREUPON, DAHOMEY’S MOVE TO
                            ADJOURN DEBATE WAS ADOPTED BY UNRECORDED VOTE OF 56-16 (US)-38. DAHOMEY
                            MOTION, FROM WHICH ALMOST HALF MEMBERS PRESENT DISASSOCIATED THEMSELVES
                            IN VOTE, HAD EFFECT OF DELIBERATELY PREVENTING FURTHER DISCUSSION, AND
                            INTRODUCTION IN PLENARY, OF RESOLUTIONS IN WHICH THERE SUBSTANTIAL AND
                            VARIED GROUP INTEREST.</p>
                        <p>4. STEAM ROLLER PSYCHOLOGY INTENSIFIED TO SUCH AN EXTENT AT END OF
                            SESSION THAT SPOKESMEN FOR GROUP OF 77 SEEMED DETERMINED TO FORCE THE
                            CREATION OF AN IMPRESSION OF UNANIMITY, EVEN THOUGH IT DID NOT EXIST,
                            AND TO AVOID VOTING BY SUCH MEANS AS THREATENING TO WITHDRAW NEGOTIATED
                            DOCUMENTS AND SUBMIT ORIGINAL G-77 WORKING PAPERS, AS WELL AS TELLING US
                            THAT ANY REQUEST FOR A VOTE WOULD BE CHALLENGED AND G-77/NACG MAJORITY
                            UTILIZED TO OPPOSE THE REQUEST. EFFORT TO CREATE FALSE IMPRESSION OF
                            UNANIMITY IS PARTICULARLY TROUBLESOME WITH RESPECT TO A DOCUMENT THAT
                            BEGINS “WE THE MEMBERS OF THE UNITED NATIONS...” AS DOES THE
                            DECLARATION. SUCH A DOCUMENT SHOULD IN FACT BE AGREEABLE TO ALL MEMBERS,
                            WHILE DECLARATION WAS NOT. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>: IN FINAL
                            ANALYSIS WHEN PLENARY TOOK UP TWO RESOLUTIONS FOR ADOPTION, WE DECIDED
                            NOT TO REQUEST VOTING, GIVEN OVERALL SITUATION. END FYI. WE DID MAKE
                            CLEAR THAT USG DID NOT BELIEVE CONSENSUS IN FACT EXISTED. ADDRESSEES IN
                            THEIR APPROACHES SHOULD CITE EXAMPLE CONTAINED THIS PARA AS ILLUSTRATION
                            OF HOW FAR STEAM ROLLER PSYCHOLOGY HAD TAKEN HOLD AND ONLY IF USE OF
                            EXAMPLE WILL ASSIST IN PRESENTATION OF OUR CONCERNS. WE PARTICULARLY
                            DESIRE WHEN THIS FACTOR IS DISCUSSED THAT NO IMPRESSION BE LEFT THAT WE
                            WOULD HAVE REGARDED IT AS PROPER OR LEGAL PROCEDURE TO DENY REQUEST OF
                            MEMBER FOR A VOTE. IN FACT, WE WOULD WISH DISCOURAGE ANY POSSIBLE BELIEF
                            BY OTHERS THAT IT WOULD BE PRACTICAL POSSIBILITY TO DENY RIGHT TO HAVE
                            VOTE ONCE IT IS REQUESTED. UN CHARTER, UNGA RULES OF PROCEDURE, AND
                            PRECEDENT OF ASSEMBLY’S OPERATIONS, REQUIRES A VOTE WHEN REQUESTED.</p>
                        <p>5. STEAMROLLER TACTICS, ESPECIALLY USE OF MAJORITY TO PREVENT
                            INTRODUCTION AND DISCUSSION OF RESOLUTIONS IN UN AS WELL AS TO DETER
                            FINAL VOTE ON ADOPTION OF RESOLUTIONS, CONTRADICT REASON FOR EXISTENCE
                            OF GA AND OTHER ASSEMBLIES IN UN SYSTEM AS DELIBERATIVE BODIES. THIS
                            SHOULD BE SEEN AS ACUTE DANGER ESPECIALLY BY THOSE COUNTRIES, MOSTLY
                            LDC’S, WHO REGARD UN AS MOST IMPORTANT OPPORTUNITY FOR INTERNATIONAL
                            ACTION ON ISSUES IMPORTANT TO THEM. THIS EXPANDED USE OF AUTOMATIC
                            MAJORITIES WILL, IF CONTINUED, SERIOUSLY JEOPARDIZE ROLE OF UN IN MOST
                            IMPORTANT INTERNATIONAL ISSUES. IT CAN ALSO HAVE SERIOUS CONSEQUENCES,
                            WERE IT TO RESULT IN ALIENATING US PUBLIC OPINION FROM SUPPORT FOR UN
                            AND AID TO DEVELOPING COUNTRIES.</p>
                        <p>6. ACTION REQUESTED: UNLESS ACTION POSTS PERCEIVE IMPORTANT OBJECTIONS,
                            THEY SHOULD EXPRESS OUR DEEP AND HIGH LEVEL CONCERNS NOTED ABOVE WITH
                            HOST GOVERNMENT AT APPROPRIATELY HIGH LEVEL. EMPHASIS SHOULD BE PLACED
                            ON WHAT WE SEE AS SERIOUS RISK TO FUTURE EFFECTIVE WORK OF UN
                            ORGANIZATION POSED BY TACTICS SUCH AS THOSE EMPLOYED AT SPECIAL SESSION.
                            POSTS SHOULD POINT OUT THAT US IN EARLY DAYS OF UN DID NOT SEEK TO
                            RESTRICT DEBATE ON ISSUES BEFORE UNGA, DESPITE STRONG MAJORITY IT COULD
                            USUALLY MUSTER IN SUPPORT ITS POSITIONS. WE BELIEVE EQUALLY RESPONSIBLE
                            BEHAVIOR SHOULD NOW BE EXPECTED FROM THOSE WHO ARE ABLE TO COMMAND
                            MAJORITY IN INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS IN INTERESTS OF ORGANIZATION AS
                            A WHOLE. POSTS MAY IN THEIR DISCRETION INDICATE WE WOULD WELCOME ANY
                            COMMENTS HOST GOVERNMENTS MIGHT WISH TO MAKE ON THIS PROBLEM. PARIS,
                            ROME, TOKYO, LONDON, BONN, STOCKHOLM, OTTAWA AND CANBERRA, IN
                            PARTICULAR, SHOULD SEEK VIEWS OF HOST GOVERNMENTS ON STEPS WE MIGHT TAKE
                            INDIVIDUALLY OR IN CONCERT TO HEAD OFF STEAMROLLER TACTICS AND TO
                            FACILITATE MORE CONSTRUCTIVE LDC APPROACH IN FUTURE UN MEETINGS. WE MAY
                            SUGGEST OTHER CAPITALS FOR APPROACHES LATER. <persName corresp="#p_RKW1">RUSH</persName>
                            <lb/> NOTE BY OC/T: POUCHED SUVA. </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>