<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>170. Telegram 383 From the Mission to the United Nations to the Department of
                    State, February 4, 1974, 1954Z.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-02-04T14:54:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-02-04T14:54:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recNoYYqIUVtkYdVM" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009005770"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Family planning</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-02-04T14:54:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-02-04T14:54:00-05:00" n="170"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                <head>170. Telegram 383 From the Mission to the United Nations to the Department of
                    State, February 4, 1974, 1954Z.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d170fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy Files. Limited
                        Official Use. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_HEW1">HEW</gloss> and <gloss
                            target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>. The Department of State was to pass the
                        telegram to the Department of Labor. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName>’s Presidential Proclamation 4262, January 30, 1974, is
                        published in <hi rend="italic">Weekly Compilation of Presidential
                            Documents</hi>, Vol. 10, No. 5, p. 112.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d170fn2">The telegram recounted the principal
                        occurrences at the 25th session of the U.N. Commission on the Status of
                        Women, which met in New York from January 14 to February 1.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-02-04T19:54:00+00:00">February 4, 1974,
                        1954Z</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>TELEGRAM <lb/> Department of State <lb/>
                    <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 383</p>
                <p>R 041954Z FEB 74</p>
                <p>FM USMISSION USUN NEW YORK <lb/> TO SECSTATE WASHDC 2588 <lb/> INFO <gloss
                        target="#t_HEW1">HEW</gloss> WASHDC <lb/>
                    <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> WASHDC</p>
                <p>USUN 383</p>
                <p>STATE ALSO PASS DEPT OF LABOR</p>
                <p>E.O. 11652: N/A <lb/> TAGS: SGEN</p>
                <p>SUBJ: <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF WOMEN 25TH
                    SESSION - ROUNDUP</p>
                <p>1. SUMMARY: SESSION CHARACTERIZED BY EMERGENCE OF THE US IN NEW HUMAN RIGHTS
                    LEADERSHIP ROLE ON ISSUE OF EQUAL RIGHTS FOR WOMEN. SOVIET OPPOSITION TO
                        US-<gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss> SPONSORED RESOLUTION ASKING UN TO
                    CALL WOMEN’S CONFERENCE DURING INTERNATIONAL WOMEN’S YEAR (<gloss
                        target="#t_IWY1">IWY</gloss>) REVEALED CLEAR SOVIET BIAS AGAINST EQUALITY
                    FOR WOMEN. TIMELY RELEASE OF PRESIDENTIAL IWY PROCLAMATION DURING SESSION
                    FURTHER UNDERLINED US DEDICATION TO EQUAL RIGHTS PRINCIPLES. CREATED ADDED
                    SUPPORT FOR US IWY RES AND EFFECTIVELY STALLED SOVIET DRIVE DESIGNED TO FOCUS
                    WORLD WIDE ATTENTION ON SINGLE COMMUNIST WOMEN’S YEAR CONFERENCE SCHEDULED FOR
                    MOSCOW IN 1975. US INITIATIVES IN INTEGRATION OF WOMEN IN UN PROGRAMS FOR
                    DEVELOPMENT, FAMILY PLANNING, OBSERVANCE OF IWY WIDELY SUPPORTED. END
                    SUMMARY.</p>
                <p>2. COMMISSION CONCLUDED HIGHLY PRODUCTIVE, FORWARD LOOKING PROGRAM FOR SESSION
                    THAT ENDED LATE FEBRUARY 1. WORK CHARACTERIZED BY ACTION PROGRAMS TO ACCELERATE
                    INTEGRATION OF WOMEN IN UN EMPLOYMENT AND DEVELOPMENT PROGRAMS IN ALL ELEMENTS
                    OF THE UN SYSTEM, AND OTHER AREAS THAT WILL ADVANCE THEIR STATUS.</p>
                <p>3. HIGHLIGHTS INCLUDED FAVORABLE IMPACT US INITIATIVES FOR OBSERVANCE OF IWY,
                    POPULATION AND DEVELOPMENT PROVIDING NEW US LEADERSHIP ROLE IN HUMAN RIGHTS AREA
                    AND DECISIVE PROPAGANDA ADVANTAGE OVER SOVIETS. CLEARLY ESTABLISHED US
                    LEADERSHIP IN EQUAL RIGHTS STRUGGLE OF WOMEN BY REVEALING STRONG SOVIET BIAS
                    THIS SUBJECT. RESULT WAS A REALIGNMENT OF OLD COMMISSION VOTING PATTERNS WITH
                    SUPPORT FROM LDCS AND <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> FOR THE US AGAINST
                    SOCIALISTS.</p>
                <p>4. LDCS SUPPORT ON QUESTION OF EQUAL RIGHTS CAME DURING SERIES OF HARD FOUGHT
                    BATTLES WITH SOVIETS OVER ISSUE OF CHANGING UN PRIORITIES TO PERMIT UN FUNDING
                    OF IWY CONFERENCE. SOVIET OPPOSITION AND INTERVENTIONS BY MALE MEMBERS OF
                    DELEGATION REVEALED STRONG BIAS AGAINST EQUALITY FOR WOMEN. NINE LDC’S FROM ALL
                    DEVELOPING REGIONS JOINED US IN CO-SPONSORING CONFERENCE RES THAT WON DECISIVELY
                    21(US, LDCS, PRC)-3(USSR, BYELORUSSIA <gloss target="#t_SSR1">SSR</gloss>,
                    HUNGARY)-6. SUBSTITUTION OF MALE MEMBER OF SOVIET DELEGATION IN CHAIR DURING A
                    FUTILE FILIBUSTER EFFORT CREATED WIDESPREAD ANTAGONISM AMONG DELEGATES. GENEROUS
                    AND WARM-HEARTED POSITION SUBSEQUENTLY ADOPTED BY USSR DELEGATE WHO HAD BEEN
                    TEMPORARILY REPLACED BY MALE COLLEAGUE REVERSED TREND SOMEWHAT BEFORE SESSION
                    ENDED BUT DID NOT MATERIALLY AFFECT WIDE PROPAGANDA ADVANTAGE GAINED BY THE US
                    MOVE AND THE SOVIET BLUNDER.</p>
                <p>5. THE READING OF PRESIDENT <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">NIXON</persName>’S IWY
                    PROCLAMATION, THE FIRST BY ANY CHIEF OF STATE, IN CONCLUDING DAYS OF SESSION AND
                    PRIOR TO VOTE, ADDED MOMENTUM TO FAVORABLE VOTE AND US LEADERSHIP AND SERVED AS
                    PUT-DOWN FOR SOVIET POSITION AGAINST EQUALITY. REQUESTS POURED IN FROM ALL
                    DELEGATIONS FOR COPIES OF PROCLAMATION FOR USE BY GOVERNMENTS IN PREPARATION OF
                    SIMILAR INSTRUMENTS FURTHER STRENGTHENING PROPAGANDA IMPACT OF US INITIATIVE. </p>
                <p>6. DESPITE SOVIET OPPOSITION TO RAPPORTEUR STUDY ON STATUS OF WOMEN AND FAMILY
                    PLANNING, RESOLUTION FOR ITEM ADOPTED 24(US)-0-8(USSR) CALLING FOR RIGHT OF
                    INDIVIDUALS TO DECIDE FREELY AND RESPONSIBLY ON THE NUMBER OF SPACING OF THEIR
                    CHILDREN, ESTABLISHMENT OF NATIONAL POPULATION COMMISSIONS, INTRODUCTION OF
                    POPULATION EDUCATION AND EQUAL REPRESENTATION OF MEN AND WOMEN ON DELEGATIONS TO
                    1974 WORLD POPULATION CONFERENCE.</p>
                <p>7. RESOLUTIONS ON DEVELOPMENT ASKED <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> TO
                    INCLUDE IN ALL SESSIONS OF COMMITTEES ON REVIEW AND APPRAISAL AND DEVELOPMENT
                    AND PLANNING, INFORMATION THAT WILL GIVE DUE ATTENTION TO THE INTEGRATION OF
                    WOMEN BOTH IN PROGRAM REVIEW AND IN SUBSEQUENT RECOMMENDATIONS OF THOSE BODIES.
                    AUTHORIZED CHAIRWOMAN OF THE COMMISSION TO REPRESENT COMMISSION ON THE STATUS OF
                    WOMEN IN THE PREPARATION OF REVIEW AND APPRAISAL RECOMMENDATIONS.</p>
                <p>8. EGYPTIAN-USSR EFFORTS TO MAINTAIN ITEM OF PROTECTION OF WOMEN AND CHILDREN IN
                    EMERGENCY AND ARMED CONFLICTS SUCCEEDED WITH ACCEPTANCE OF DRAFT RES CALLING FOR
                    PREPARATION OF FORMAL DECLARATION ON SUBJECT BASED ON <gloss target="#t_WIDF1"
                        >WIDF</gloss> (COMMUNIST <gloss target="#t_NGO1">NGO</gloss>) PROPOSAL.
                        US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> APPEAL THAT SUBJECT BEST TREATED BY
                    PROPER JURIDICAL BODY IN THE LIGHT OF FEBRUARY <gloss target="#t_ICRC1"
                        >ICRC</gloss> MEETINGS IN GENEVA INEFFECTIVE. </p>
                <p>9. WIDESPREAD INTEREST IN NEW AGENDA ITEM ON INFLUENCE OF MASS COMMUNICATIONS
                    MEDIA ON ROLE OF WOMEN AND US VIEWS THIS SUBJECT. RES URGED GOVERNMENTS AND MASS
                    MEDIA TO WORK TOWARDS ELIMINATION OF SEX ROLE STEREOTYPING, FURTHER STUDY AND
                    RESEARCH.</p>
                <p>10. US REP TO STATUS OF WOMEN COMMISSION SHOULD BE PRESENT AT NEXT ECOSOC TO
                    PRESERVE US INITIATIVES AND WORK FOR APPROVAL OF COMMISSION PROGRAM BY COUNCIL. <lb/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJA1">SCALI</persName>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
