<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-05-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="171" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d171">
                        <head>171. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of
                            State (Springsteen) to the President’s Counselor in the White House
                            Office for Women’s Programs (<persName corresp="#p_AA5">Armstrong</persName>), Washington, May 14, 1974.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d171fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Foreign Policy Files, P740087–2370. No classification
                                marking. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HR6">Heater</persName>;
                                cleared by <persName corresp="#p_MJWJ1">McDonald</persName> and
                                Allen and in <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_IOEX1">IO/EX</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_CU1">CU</gloss>. Armstrong’s April 18 request for a progress report
                                and information about the status of the Executive Order is ibid.,
                                P740087–2373. </note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d171fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGSJ1">Springsteen</persName> updated
                                Armstrong on U.S. government efforts to promote the U.N.
                                International Women’s Year.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-05-14">May 14, 1974</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <pb facs="d171-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d171-1"/>
                        <pb facs="d171-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d171-2"/>
                        <pb facs="d171-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d171-3"/>
                        <p>DEPARTMENT O STATE <lb/> WASHINGTON, D.C. 20520</p>
                        <p>May 14, 1974</p>
                        <p>MEMORANDUM FOR MS. ANNE ARMSTRONG <lb/> THE WHITE HOUSE</p>
                        <p>Subject: International Women’s Year (<gloss target="#t_IWY1">IWY</gloss>)</p>
                        <p>In response to your April 18th inquiry concerning progress on planning
                            for, and the status of the Executive Order dealing with IWY (1975), I
                            have the following to report.</p>
                        <p>The United Nations Economic Committee (<gloss target="#t_UNEC1">UNEC</gloss>), the U.S. inter-departmental committee chaired by
                            State, has considered this matter and reached a measure of agreement on
                            the wording of the Order that will establish a National Commission of 35
                            members for the Year and set goals and guidelines directed toward
                            stimulating interest in IWY across the country. The draft Order provides
                            for a Secretariat and office and conference facilities for the National
                            Commission, as has been the practice with previous “Years.” The Order
                            will also recognize the National Commission’s responsibility to review
                            and coordinate the work of all elements of the Federal Government, and
                            to establish a cooperative working relationship with the U.S. Center for
                            the Observance of IWY in its work with the private sector.</p>
                        <p>The draft Order establishes a budget of $500,000 for the National
                            Commission. The Department is attempting to identify $100,000 of this
                            amount in State’s <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 75 and 76 budgets.
                            $400,000 will have to be provided by other elements of the Executive
                            branch and the relevant line obligations identified before the Order can
                            move from State to the Office of Management and Budget. We anticipate
                            this will be done no later than July 1974. We have received informal
                            estimates of contributions that might become available from the
                            Department of Health, Education, and Welfare ($125,000) amounts of
                            $30,000 from the Departments of Interior and Agriculture. Other sources
                            for this budget would logically come from Labor, Defense, and the Civil
                            Service Commission. However, the extent of their financial contributions
                            has not been indicated. This would be an area in which your office could
                            be particularly helpful.</p>
                        <p>We have not arrived at a firm agreement on the specific area of the
                            Executive Branch in which the Secretariat should be located.</p>
                        <p>We are continuing to press within the United Nations for the passage of
                            the U.S. sponsored resolution to hold an international women’s
                            conference in 1975. The matter is before the Economic and Social Council
                                (<gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss>) together with a
                            resolution containing a program for the worldwide observance of IWY. The
                            Soviets have opposed both resolutions as they plan to hold an
                            international women’s conference in East Berlin in 1975. However, our
                            Representative to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Commission on
                            the Status of Women, Mrs. Patricia Nutar, is now in New York at ECOSOC,
                            and we believe she will be as successful in winning approval for both
                            items as she was at the recent meeting of the Commission.</p>
                        <p>Our representatives have worked closely with the UN Secretariat, which
                            plans to fund IWY with a budget of $300,000 from within existing UN
                            resources. Our Delegation is also encouraging nongovernmental
                            organizations accredited to the UN to hold a brief conference at the
                            same time as IWY. We believe it important that their views be reflected
                            in the final Conference recommendations.</p>
                        <p>On a Federal level, interest in planning for the Year has come from women
                            representing a broad base of federally employed women who are united in
                            the objective of upgrading the status of women. The Federal Women’s
                            Coordinators in each of the Federal Departments and the UNEC
                            representatives have also shared the active interest in planning. We are
                            working to broaden this interest and to develop a more extensive base of
                            active participation among other Federal agencies.</p>
                        <p>In October 1973 the Bureau of Cultural Affairs of the Department of state
                            granted $36,000 to Meridian House International, which created the U.S.
                            Center for the Observance of International Women’s Year. I believe that
                            Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BRE3">Ruth Bacon</persName>, the Director of
                            the Center, has been in touch with your office and provided a recent
                            briefing on the subject.</p>
                        <p>The U.S. Center is developing its program with the advice of an advisory
                            group drawn from 35 nongovernmental organizations, the majority with
                            national and international affiliations. It has recently activated a
                            financial committee and a speakers bureau; and, with the help of a newly
                            recruited media consultant, is focusing on fund raising and
                            publicity.</p>
                        <p>Your interest and offer of assistance are most appreciated. In this
                            regard, our major obstacle appears to be the funding of this program.
                            Your suggestions and support could be of inestimable help as we attempt
                            to cope with this problem.</p>
                        <p>[signed] <lb/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SGSJ1">George S. Springsteen </persName>
                            <lb/> Executive Secretary</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>