<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>174. Memorandum From the Deputy Secretary of State (Ingersoll) to President
                    Ford, Washington, December 18, 1974.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="174"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                <head>174. Memorandum From the Deputy Secretary of State (Ingersoll) to President
                    Ford, Washington, December 18, 1974.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d174fn1"
                        >Source: Ford Library, Lindh and Holm Files, Box 26, Executive Order (1). No
                        classification marking. For Executive Order 11832, signed and issued on
                        January 9, 1975, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                        March 10, 1975, pp. 305–306.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d174fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_IRS1">Ingersoll</persName> recommended that <persName
                            corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> sign an Executive Order establishing a
                        National Commission on the Observance of the International Women’s
                        Year.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-12-18"
                        >December 18, 1974</date>
                </dateline>
                <pb facs="d174-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d174-1"/>
                <pb facs="d174-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d174-2"/>
                <p>THE DEPUTY SECRETARY OF STATE <lb/> WASHINGTON</p>
                <p>December 18, 1974</p>
                <p>MEMORANDUM FOR: THE PRESIDENT <lb/> From: <persName corresp="#p_IRS1">Robert S.
                        Ingersoll</persName> [RSI initialed] <lb/> Subject: National Observance of
                    International Women’s Year</p>
                <p>I. PROBLEM </p>
                <p>There is a need, which is increasingly pressing, for the Administration to
                    establish some mechanism to coordinate and direct the 1975 national observance
                    of International Women’s Year in this country.</p>
                <p>BACKGROUND/ANALYSIS </p>
                <p>In 1972 the United Nations proclaimed 1975 as International Women’s Year (<gloss
                        target="#t_IWY1">IWY</gloss>) and called upon all member states to conduct
                    an appropriate program of national observance. An international conference under
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> auspices is scheduled to meet in Mexico
                    City next June. </p>
                <p>In January of this year, President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                    proclaimed 1975 as International Women’s Year in the United States and called
                    for full national observance of it, including both the private and public
                    sectors.</p>
                <p>Interest in IWY is widespread and intense among women’s groups across the
                    country. These groups are acutely aware of the extent to which the Federal
                    Government committed itself, for example, to World Population Year in 1974 and
                    are watching closely to see whether the Administration makes a similar
                    commitment to the observance of IWY. Indeed, there is beginning to be some
                    criticism of the absence of any overt preparations in this regard.</p>
                <p>I am establishing in the Department of State the position of Coordinator for
                    International Women’s Year with the primary responsibility of coordinating the
                    U.S. participation in the Mexico City conference, but also to maintain liaison
                    with the UN, other governments and domestic United States organizations. I
                    anticipate that this person would have a small staff, to which the Department of
                    State and <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> have already committed four
                    positions.</p>
                <p>I also believe that it would be desirable for you to establish a National
                    Commission on the Observance of International Women’s Year 1975 for the purposes
                    outlined in the attached draft Executive Order. There is considerable interest
                    among women’s organizations in the establishment of such a Commission,
                    particularly since it would be seen to parallel the organizational structure
                    established in connection with World Population Year.</p>
                <p>The Departments of State, <gloss target="#t_HEW1">HEW</gloss>, Justice, Interior,
                    Commerce and Transportation have committed $330,000 of an estimated total budget
                    of $500,000 for such a Commission. Other agencies have been requested to
                    contribute towards this tentative budget.</p>
                <p>Recommendation:</p>
                <p>I recommend that you sign the attached Executive Order establishing a National
                    Commission on the Observance of International Women’s Year 1975.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
