<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-12-21T10:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-12-21T10:30:00-05:00" n="18" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d18">
                        <head>18. Memorandum of Conversation, New York, December 21, 1974, 10:30
                                a.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d18fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy Files, P740058–0148. Secret.
                                The meeting was held in <persName corresp="#p_BAA1">Bouteflika</persName>’s office at U.N. headquarters. The
                                “Kaunda mission” refers to an October 1970 visit by <persName corresp="#p_KKD1">Kaunda</persName> and other African leaders to
                                the United Kingdom to discuss prospective British arms sales to the
                                South African government. The “Eigal-Allon visit” refers to Israeli
                                Foreign Minister Yigal Allon’s trip to Washington for talks with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, which was
                                postponed until January 15, 1975. “Handbro” refers to Edvard Hambro
                                of Norway, who served as President of the United Nations General
                                Assembly in 1970 and 1971 and as President of the United Nations
                                International Law Commission from 1972 until 1977.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d18fn2">Kissinger and Bouteflika
                                discussed positions taken during the 29th United Nations General
                                Assembly and issues to be addressed in future negotiations.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1974-12-21T10:30:00-05:00">December 21, 1974, 10:30 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <pb facs="d18-01" n="1" xml:id="pg_d18-1"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-02" n="2" xml:id="pg_d18-2"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-03" n="3" xml:id="pg_d18-3"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-04" n="4" xml:id="pg_d18-4"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-05" n="5" xml:id="pg_d18-5"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-06" n="6" xml:id="pg_d18-6"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-07" n="7" xml:id="pg_d18-7"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-08" n="8" xml:id="pg_d18-8"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-09" n="9" xml:id="pg_d18-9"/>
                        <pb facs="d18-10" n="10" xml:id="pg_d18-10"/>
                        <p>MEMORANDUM OF CONVERSATION <lb/> PARTICIPANTS: <lb/> State Department:
                            <lb/> Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                            <lb/> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BWB1">Buffum</persName>
                            <lb/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BPW3">Parker Borg</persName> (notetaker) <lb/> Mr.
                            Toumayan (interpreter)</p>
                        <p>Algeria: Minister of Foreign Affairs <persName corresp="#p_BAA1">Abdelaziz Bouteflika</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>TIME &amp; DATE: 10:30 a.m., December 21, 1974 <lb/> PLACE: Office of
                            Minister Bouteflika, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, New York</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: I believe the Foreign Minister speaks English now.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: I had fully intended to study English, but I was not
                            able to do so. I’m sure you realize that I was too busy and that I put
                            in many many hours attending to my duties.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: There were times we wished you would take some rest from
                            your duties. I spent a lot of time explaining to my colleagues that you
                            are a revolutionary by temperament not by official ideology like the
                            Communists.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: This is a good way to put it; it’s a good definition.
                            Perhaps age is also a factor. I have not yet reached the age of wisdom.
                            My rebel temperament also plays a part.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: As you know, I admire your President greatly. I missed you
                            very much when I was in Algiers. Being a man of principles, you’re not
                            always easy to deal with but you’re always interesting.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: I’m very happy to have a chance to see you before my
                            departure. I was in Algiers recently and I explained to the President
                            that you and I had agreed on the timing for this visit at the end of the
                            session. I want to thank you for drawing attention to the fact that
                            January 9 was the approximate date of the Eigal-Allon visit.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: We didn’t want any embarrassments.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: We appreciate very much your attitude. We also wish to
                            avoid as much speculation as possible.</p>
                        <p>The Minister (Bouteflika): People would have said this is another of Dr.
                            K’s tricks. So thank you for drawing our attention to this. When you
                            mentioned the schedule around Christmas or early next year, we knew that
                            you would not propose any visit during the holiday week and that it
                            would therefore be early next year. This is fine for me -- another
                            reason being that I would like our new ambassador to be in Washington
                            when I come.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: Will you then come to Washington in January or
                            February?</p>
                        <p>Mr. Bouteflika: Preferably February.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: We will then entertain you and it will not be in the
                            context of the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: In any event I made it quite clear that after December
                            18 I was completely free of the UNGA.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: I think mid-February is a good period.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: Let me now tell you sore of my views of the 29th UNGA.
                            First of all let me assure you that in South Africa I was not behaving
                            like a naive choirboy but that I was acting quite deliberately. I remain
                            convinced that any decolonization contest is unwise at the time when
                            Rhodesia is beginning to think about the problem and when the Security
                            Council is unanimously voting a resolution on Namibia. Then the time has
                            come for the U.S. and the European countries with interests in South
                            Africa to begin a dialogue with the South African leaders. You cannot
                            pursue any longer a policy which is in disharmony with the rest of the
                            world.</p>
                        <p>I feel that there can be no revolution if South Africa prepares public
                            opinion at home, and I feel that this can lead to three or four
                            different stages just as you have acted with respect to the Middle East.
                            There you had at first an all or nothing situation, but you opted for
                            the stage by stage approach; with South Africa we shall do the same.
                            Houphouet-Boigny began the dialogue between the African leaders and the
                            South African leaders and we do not encounter the same problem that we
                            encounter in setting up the dialogue with the Israelis. Israel faced the
                            problem of being considered a foreign body in the Middle East. </p>
                        <p>The expressions had been used of pushing Israel into the sea. But the
                            wise South Africans are full-fledged Africans.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: Except that they themselves don’t think so.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: They do not think of themselves as Europeans. They
                            identify with what happens. As evidenced by the wonderful reception
                            extended to the Algerian delegation to the independence ceremony of
                            Swaziland when they stopped through Johannesburg on their way. The time
                            has come to think seriously about this and put it fully in the
                            agenda.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: Let us plan to discuss this in great detail when you come
                            to Washington in February. In principle, I am interested, but this must
                            be discussed with great discretion.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: Yes, discretion is necessary. </p>
                        <p>The Secretary: It is essential.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: At this <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> we gave a
                            clear warning, and this may help <persName corresp="#p_SID1">Ian
                                Smith</persName> of Rhodesia to implement constitutional changes.
                            Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CLJ1">Callaghan</persName> was
                            interested in constitutional changes. I found him very honest when he
                            talked to me about this. And Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName> was also very honest about this. At the time of
                            the Kaunda Mission to the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> then PM
                                <persName corresp="#p_HERG1">Heath</persName> was very unreceptive
                            but Wilson was very open to the idea and remains very open minded and
                            receptive today. </p>
                        <p>The second question I want to discuss with you is the Palestinian issue.
                            I remain convinced that at the GA we have given you one more trump card
                            to help you tell the Israelis that you are with them all the way. </p>
                        <p>I scrutinized minutely the behavior of your delegation at the time of the
                            inscription of the Palestinian issue on the agenda. I told de <persName corresp="#p_DGL1">Guiringaud</persName> that the U.S. preferred to
                            see this question discussed in committee, not at the GA. But was it not
                            the best way to tame the Palestinians by letting this question be
                            discussed at the GA? In this connection I omitted to say yesterday in my
                            press conference that I intend to say this. The U.S. deserves a very
                            special tribute. I have never seen them move so selflessly and sincerely
                            round the clock as they did then. They’re a wonderful team and they knew
                            that the prestige of the U.S. was at stake.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: They were under very strict instructions.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: They were wonderful and I have asked the Palestinians to
                            write to them telling them how grateful they are. Now I am going to talk
                            to you about Cambodia and I’m asking you not to become impatient with
                            me.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: I can never become impatient with you because I consider
                            you my friend and I do want to talk to you about Cambodia and Cuba and I
                            also want to talk to you privately about the Palestinians, this is why I
                            did not want to spend too much time about South Africa.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: At the time of the vote on the Cambodia resolution this
                            was the first time that the press said that the President of the UNGA
                            had acted with full objectivity. I watched from the podium and I helped
                            your resolution pass. I sensed that the atmosphere was becoming heavy.
                            There is a tendency in the press to present as a defeat to the U.S.
                            something which is nothing of the kind. Was South Africa a defeat to the
                            U.S.? You speak about the Palestinians and the press distorts this as if
                            it were a defeat to the U.S.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: There are more Jewish journalists in New York than there
                            are Arab ones.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: I have met Jews and Zionist Jews in New York. Some of
                            them are very very lucid. They know the terms of the problem and there
                            cannot be a settlement without the Palestinians and they want to try to
                            work out a settlement with the Palestinians.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: I believe you and I agree.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: The resolution did not pass because Egypt, co-author of
                            the resolution, remained absent, even though its delegation numbers
                            fifty. The story I got was that the car bringing the delegate to the
                            vote broke down, the votes took about six hours but the car remained out
                            of service during that time. Morocco which recognized <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> voted for the other
                            resolution; Tunisia which recognizes Sihanouk abstained; the emirates
                            and Bahrain who also recognized Sihanouk abstained. <persName corresp="#p_BJM3">Baroody</persName>, who is very skillful offered
                            amendments to the two resolutions but no one takes him seriously. If
                            other groups had negotiated seriously with Baroody, the result of the
                            vote would have been different.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: You are right.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: Baroody’s getting old and as men grow older their
                            sensitivities increase. I first observed this when I met General
                            DeGaulle for the first time. Even an outstanding man like him is not
                            immune to that rile.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: It is a painful phenomenon to observe.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: The first time I met DeGaulle I observed how age had
                            eroded him. How susceptible he had become to flattery and to his
                            sensitivities. The Thai Ambassador who is young, skillful and
                            intelligent used a moment of inattention to introduce an amendment which
                            changed the substance of the resolution. Any delegation could have then
                            invoked the 24-hour rule because of the change in the substance of the
                            resolution but no one did. He acted very fast and I like him for it.
                            Then the Ambassador of Sri Lanka got the point but no one understood.
                            The bold move of the Thai ambassador appealed to me. He made his move
                            very fast and he won. No one realized what was going on. We voted 56-54
                            and the resolution passed which is what I wanted. I point to your
                            attention this 56-54 result. If it had been 55-55, the resolution would
                            have come to a vote a second time then it would have been rejected and
                            so you won your vote by one vote. This leads me to the conclusion that
                            you have until the beginning of the next GA to settle that question. The
                            resolution speaks of two parties Sihanouk and <persName corresp="#p_LN2">Lon Nol</persName> which it places on an equal footing. At the 27th
                            GA the Handbro legal opinion on South Africa said and I quote: “Any
                            delegation can be suspended when there are two parties recognized by the
                            GA.” At the next GA Sihanouk will send letters of accreditation and the
                            credentials committee will be in an untenable position. Believe me I
                            speak to you as a friend.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: Well we have spoken about this in the past. We are not
                            opposed to Sihanouk playing in Cambodia the kind of role that <persName corresp="#p_SP2">Souvanna Phouma</persName> has played in Laos. We
                            are looking for a way to talk to Sihanouk but haven’t yet found one. Of
                            course it would help if he would restrain his eloquence for a few weeks,
                            but this is a minor point.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: The fact that he does not restrain his eloquence is not
                            a disservice to you because it annoys some of his supporters.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: The fact is how can we have a serious exchange with
                            Sihanouk.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: Without appearing to work at cross purposes with you I
                            want to invite their Defense Minister to Algiers. He is the Deputy Prime
                            Minister and head of the Khmer Rouge.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: What’s his name? Could Ambassador Parker talk to him
                            quietly?</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: I do not recall his name but I always feel that those in
                            power are more reasonable than those who are not. And I want to talk to
                            him without Sihanouk to see what are the limits of the problem.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: But you can tell him the U.S. has no national interest in
                            Cambodia. We want to end the war in a way that our national dignity is
                            preserved. We do not seek a permanent position in Cambodia.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: I simply draw your attention to the fact that you have
                            eight months to try to solve the problem because at the next GA you will
                            have a very bad situation on your hands. Now on Korea, even at the
                            Security Council among the five permanent members there begins to be the
                            feeling that there is no reason for the UN flag to be there. The US can
                            have a defense pact with any nation and keep troops in South Korea if it
                            wished but as a US, not UN, proposition.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: This is possible.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: It would be better if the idea came from you than if it
                            came from the Security Council.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: We can do that.</p>
                        <p>Amb. Buffum: I think we can work out an arrangement with the parties and
                            notify the Security Council.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: Do you think North Korea will agree?</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: Even if it doesn’t it does not matter since you do not
                            have relations with them now. Let me now speak to the revolutionary
                            spirit in you. If you have an opportunity to meet Kim Il Song you should
                            do so. In my view in the Third world there were Cuba, Algeria, Vietnam
                            and Korea each trying to set up an independent national policy. Cuba
                            cannot do so until it has normalized its relations with the U.S.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: I fully agree with you.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: Cuba is like a patient with one lung, who cannot take a
                            deep breath until it has healed. Algeria has a long history with France
                            and Europe and progress will take time. The policy of independence is
                            costly. Something or other is always coming up. Vietnam has been forced
                            by war to choose a policy of balance between Moscow and Peking, leaning
                            to either Peking or Moscow as one or the other shows greater reluctance.
                            The only country with truly a policy of national independence is North
                            Korea. I asked Kim Il Song why he did not rejoin the nonaligned group,
                            pointing out to him that after all countries like Cuba and Yugoslavia
                            are in it. He told me he had never thought about it. I pointed out to
                            him that he has defense pacts with the Soviet Union and Peking. He said
                            if Seoul renounces its defense pacts with the U.S. and Japan within 24
                            hours he will renounce his with Moscow and Peking. You won’t be sorry to
                            talk to Kim Il Song. I told him that. I had read his works and I see
                            that he encourages the cult of personality, having himself described as
                            the beloved leader of forty million North Koreans. He pointed out the
                            need for the Korean people to have someone with whom they can identify
                            as a national figure because in neighboring China there is one God who
                            is Mao and he wanted the Koreans to feel they did not have to seek
                            outside their own borders for a national figure.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: This is very important.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: You will understand them better after talking to
                            them.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: We had thought we would wait until after the GA.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: I know Kim Il Song is the most open of all the North
                            Korean leaders. The one who will find compromise, the others are just
                            like students with a master. You must try to get his personal views. At
                            this GA we voted on the economic charter but you must not take that too
                            seriously. We voted also on the revision of the San Francisco charter
                            but this is a very long process. Ambassador Malik asked me how come the
                            name of Algeria appeared alongside the names of Colombia and the
                            Philippines and Brazil. I told him Algeria belongs to the non-aligned
                            world, that we are not Communists. Eleven years ago <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> had told me that I was dogmatic
                            with respect to the Charter. How can we accept today references to
                            Germany and Japan as enemy states when they are both active in the
                            organization. How can we accept provisions on trusteeship when
                            decolonization is a reality. No one challenges the right of veto.
                            Actually a correct analysis would demonstrate that only two countries
                            should have a veto power. I do not want to hurt anyone’s feelings, but
                            there are only two superpowers in the world today, and they in fact have
                            an actual veto power. The more dogmatic the Soviets show themselves the
                            more flexible you should be and observe the situation without
                            challenging the tide of the third world. You must understand that the
                            third world does not wish to be Communist; the Chinese have understood
                            this.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: I have understood that. The Third World is torn between
                            rhetoric and cooperation. On the one hand they argue politically with
                            the industrialized world, on the other they seek economic cooperation.
                            This dilemma won’t work. In the special session next September we have
                            an obligation to attempt to solve the problem. I agree with your
                            President 100 percent. We must be cooperative. In bilateral terms, this
                            makes no difference at all because the U.S. continues to be a strong
                            country. However, Europe and Japan are no longer that strong. The U.S.
                            cannot have the Third World demoralizing Japan and Europe. You
                            understand I am talking to you now as an old friend and also as a leader
                            of the Third World. If we can work together during this special session
                            it must become a symbol of the cooperation between us then we can do
                            much. If it becomes a session of confrontation, then that worries me
                            greatly.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: It would never be a confrontation. We have also ended on
                            a conciliatory note. When we voted on the rearrangement of the economic
                            order, we voted ideas freely. The UN can be a democratic forum where
                            small countries are not afraid to hurt the feelings of big nations. The
                            US is a house of freedom. What we seek is not the result of
                            confrontation hut of a dialogue and of consultation. Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_SJA1">Scali</persName> said you would not
                            become a member of the Council of Governors (of the special fund)
                            because you would not belong to it since you had chosen the path of
                            bilateral cooperation. This was a very honest statement. Your country
                            can do what it chooses bilaterally and incidentally I certainly hope
                            that Algeria will be one of the countries with which you pursue
                            bilateral assistance.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: Absolutely, you must have no doubt about that.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: President Boumedienne has said if you have ten billion
                            dollars or 20 billion dollars available, we shall need them for our own
                            development. But here with the special fund you can made a political
                            investment to assist the drought stricken countries or can give aid to
                            the newly independent nations. Nations remember those who aided them
                            first. I would advise you to make a token contribution to the special
                            fund because being away altogether is not good for you.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: This is something that I want to discuss with my
                            associates.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: A country with your power has in this instance given the
                            impression that it was annoyed, angry. You should not remain absent
                            completely. If you are present within the fund you can help give it a
                            certain direction, but if you are absent, you’re always in the wrong.
                            Besides, you can still retain your bilateral relations because you can
                            earmark up to one-half or possibly two-thirds of your contribution to
                            bilateral recipients.</p>
                        <p>Amb. Buffum: The argument was not so much earmarking a share of one’s
                            contribution for bilateral recipients as it was using existing
                            organizations rather than setting up new competing bodies, your
                            President had told <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> that
                            the World Bank would be acceptable as a channel. A lot of things remain
                            unclear.</p>
                        <p>Min. Bouteflika: Yes, a lot of points I never made clear in advance but
                            are subsequently cleared up in practice. I will get back by you, Mr.
                            Secretary, in due time on all these points.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary: You have given me much food for thought and reflection. I
                            plan a speech about the UN where I will combine being critical and being
                            constructive.</p>
                        <p>(The Secretary then spoke privately with the Algerian Foreign
                            Minister.)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>