<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>19. Briefing Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                    International Organization Affairs (Buffum) to Secretary of State Kissinger,
                    Washington, January 31, 1975.) to Secretary of State Kissinger, Washington,
                    January 31, 1975.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-01-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-01-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">International organizations</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recfBXf5mApMtKJKj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002546"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Peacekeeping forces</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recNoYYqIUVtkYdVM" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014367"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Population control</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="recaJO7QI91wi0HaS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Development assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="rec8PCbWGrkAaOOXZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001000124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developed countries</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-01-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-01-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="19"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                <head>19. Briefing Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                    International Organization Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BWB1"
                        >Buffum</persName>) to Secretary of State Kissinger, Washington, January 31,
                        1975.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d19fn1">Source: National Archives, RG
                        59, <gloss target="#t_IOUNP1">IO/UNP</gloss> Files: Lot 93 D 191, U.N.
                        Institutional Problems—1974–75. Confidential. Drafted by Buffum and
                            <persName corresp="#p_NAF1">Neidle</persName> on January 31. Sent
                        through <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>. <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s September 24 address to the
                        United Nations is published in Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bulletin</hi>, October 15, 1973, pp. 469–473. The Case Amendment to the
                        1974 Foreign Assistance Act cut off funding for <gloss target="#t_UNESCO1"
                            >UNESCO</gloss> until the President certified to Congress that UNESCO
                        had “adopted policies which are fully consistent with its educational,
                        scientific, and cultural objectives” and “taken concrete steps to correct
                        its recent actions of a primarily political character.” On December 30,
                        1976, <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> certified that UNESCO had
                        adopted the prescribed policies (see Documents 102 and 103).</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d19fn2">Buffum outlined measures being taken
                        to address problems occurring in international organizations within the U.N.
                        system.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-01-31"
                        >January 31, 1975</date>
                </dateline>
                <pb facs="d19-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d19-1"/>
                <pb facs="d19-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d19-2"/>
                <pb facs="d19-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d19-3"/>
                <pb facs="d19-4" n="4" xml:id="pg_d19-4"/>
                <pb facs="d19-5" n="5" xml:id="pg_d19-5"/>
                <pb facs="d19-6" n="6" xml:id="pg_d19-6"/>
                <pb facs="d19-7" n="7" xml:id="pg_d19-7"/>
                <pb facs="d19-8" n="8" xml:id="pg_d19-8"/>
                <p>DEPARTMENT OF STATE <lb/> BRIEFING MEMORANDUM <lb/>
                    <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>
                </p>
                <p>January 31, 1975</p>
                <p>To: The Secretary <lb/> Through: <gloss target="#t_P1">P</gloss> - Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>
                    <lb/> From: <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> - <persName corresp="#p_BWB1"
                        >William B. Buffum</persName> [WBB initialed]</p>
                <p>Actions we are Taking Regarding International Organizations in the United Nations
                    System</p>
                <p>We have begun to take a hard look at the entire <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    system in the light of our experiences in the last year. This memorandum
                    describes briefly the main elements of the overall problem, our principal
                    working objectives and the main actions we are taking during the coming year
                    which we hope will help to counter recent unfavorable trends and even permit us
                    to make some gains.</p>
                <p>I. The Problem</p>
                <p>Our overall problem has two broad and interrelated dimensions:</p>
                <p>First, we face the largely operational side which is that of identifying those
                    aspects of the UN system which provide significant and concrete benefits to us
                    and devising the most practical means of protecting and strengthening them.</p>
                <p>Second, we have the more conceptual and longer range part of the problem which is
                    that of further developing our ideas about how interdependence should work,
                    translating our concepts into practical initiatives, and generally trying to
                    gain greater real acceptance among governments and within international
                    organizations for doing business on the basis of genuine consensus.</p>
                <p>The problem is an extremely complex one, both because there are so many disparate
                    institutions carrying out such a wide variety of endeavors and also because of
                    the complex political relationships which operate between various countries and
                    groups of countries in and outside the UN. There is clearly no single
                    panacea.</p>
                <p>There are, of course, limitations on our ability to control events in
                    multilateral institutions. In the handling of multilateral issues at the UN,
                    there is an inherent distortion in comparison with the handling of issues
                    bilaterally. Outside the UN, countries know that the weight given their views
                    will to a considerable extent depend on the significance of their actual role in
                    the activities in question. However, in the General Assembly, as well as the
                    comparable bodies of the specialized agencies, the appearance of equality
                    through the rule of one-country-one-vote and the ability of countries with
                    little real influence in the world to combine their voting strength leads to a
                    certain unreality. We cannot realistically hope to change the basic situation
                    since the present <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>/non-aligned majority will
                    not voluntarily agree to basic changes in the rules which lessen its
                    parliamentary power.</p>
                <p>Finally, I should note that all of our efforts must be viewed with the
                    realization that we are working with essentially innovative concepts. The idea
                    of interdependence and its application to practical affairs is really quite a
                    recent development. As you pointed out in your interview with Bill Moyers, many
                    of the new countries we must work with formed their identity in opposition to
                    the industrial countries. For the LDCs, therefore, it will, at best, be a
                    gradual process for many of them to shift away from the habit of confrontation
                    toward greater practice of interdependence, and we will certainly have to expect
                    a great many ups and downs.</p>
                <p>II. Objectives </p>
                <p>The following appear to be the most important working objectives:</p>
                <p>(1) Protect and strengthen the effectiveness and responsibility of the Security
                    Council in dealing with crisis situations, including particularly maintaining or
                    organizing necessary peacekeeping forces.</p>
                <p>(2) Pursue projects reflecting our view of interdependence with respect to topics
                    of interest to us, like world food problems, promotion of effective nuclear
                    safeguards, population control.</p>
                <p>(3) Work to protect specialized agencies from political confrontation extraneous
                    to the technical, economic and social missions which these agencies were
                    designed to serve and, to the extent possible, work to increase the efficiency
                    of the agencies in doing their jobs.</p>
                <p>(4) Endeavor to increase the willingness of LDC and non-aligned countries to
                    consider UN issues on their individual merits and not to pursue pre-cooked bloc
                    positions. Our objective with the non-aligned/LDCs add up, I believe, to the
                    basic task of showing convincingly to a sufficient number of these countries
                    that concentration on activities where genuine consensus can be built offers the
                    greatest promise of tangible benefits. Conversely, we should continue to stress,
                    as you have been doing, that pursuit of confrontation politics within the UN
                    system will cause a basic weakening of the system, including a risk of gradual
                    disassociation from parts of it by the United States. In other words, we must
                    try to find ways of making others realize more clearly that they cannot harass
                    us in international institutions while getting cooperation from us on matters of
                    interest to them.</p>
                <p>(5) Work for practical improvements in the practices and rules of procedures
                    applicable in deliberative bodies like the General Assembly and in international
                    conferences held under UN auspices. While improvements in practices and
                    procedures will not eliminate the basic difficulties with which we are
                    confronted, they could lessen to some extent the distortion factors which
                    prejudice productive work in a multilateral setting.</p>
                <p>III. Actions we are taking </p>
                <p>(1) Peacekeeping guidelines. Since your initiative at the 1973 <gloss
                        target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> in favor of establishing general guidelines,
                    there have been fairly extensive and complex negotiations within the UN’s
                    Committee of 33 on peacekeeping. For example, documentation has been prepared
                    which sets forth two and in many cases three alternate versions of many
                    guidelines. We will conduct a systematic review of the various issues in order
                    to ascertain whether there are new ideas we can put forward which would
                    reinvigorate the negotiations. Of most importance, however, we need to take
                    stock of whether and how we can practically encourage movement on the Soviet
                    side.</p>
                <p>(2) Preparation for the Seventh Special Session. Since the Session is eight
                    months away, we have an opportunity for comprehensive, substantive preparations
                    which contrasts very favorably with the extremely rushed and difficult situation
                    that faced us prior to the Sixth Special Session. We have found generally that
                    when the US has a concrete and well thought-through program, as in the case of
                    the World Food Conference, not only is our influence greater, but the outcome is
                    more satisfactory from our standpoint.</p>
                <p>For us to be effective it is not essential to propose greater roles for UN
                    agencies or more expenditure of UN funds. What does seem essential is that we
                    have comprehensive and convincing positions on how we believe the serious and
                    growing economic problems of the world can best be managed. With economic
                    contraction likely to be the prevalent state of affairs next year for both
                    developed and developing countries, there ought, logically, to exist some
                    increment of sobriety in the attitudes many countries bring to these
                    discussions. Assuming we pursue a serious effort of preparation, we can properly
                    regard the Seventh Special Session as something of a test case as to whether the
                    General Assembly can carry out responsible work in the field of world economic
                    issues.</p>
                <p>IO will cooperate closely with other bureaus and representatives of other
                    agencies. The problems which will be discussed at the Seventh Special Session
                    touch upon pretty nearly the whole spectrum of international economic issues.
                    What we do at the UN must therefore fit within the framework of our broad
                    worldwide economic strategy. In this connection, we should focus principally on
                    three areas. First, possible initiatives which would advance our overall
                    worldwide economic interests. This could include proposed actions which could be
                    pursued inside or outside of the UN system and which could serve both to
                    reinforce our leadership and to supplant proposals we consider unsound. Second,
                    proposals to strengthen the UN’s effectiveness in its traditional role of
                    providing technical and development assistance. Third, new suggestions to meet
                    the critical needs of the countries hardest hit by the world economic
                    crisis.</p>
                <p>A related project, which I should like to report to you, is that IO and <gloss
                        target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> have agreed to conduct a joint study of what
                    would be the most advantageous mix, from the standpoint of U.S. interests,
                    between bilateral and multilateral assistance programs. No such review has been
                    carried out in the recent past, and it is possible that, as a result, we will be
                    presenting to you specific recommendations which would have a bearing on our
                    approach to the development role of the United Nations, one of the key issues
                    for the Seventh Special Session.</p>
                <p>(3) Protection and improvement of the specialized agencies. We have already begun
                    a comprehensive review of the problems confronting the different specialized
                    agencies and the possible tactics which might be most successful to arrest
                    deterioration and to increase chances of being able to handle new challenges
                    successfully.</p>
                <p>The basic factors relevant in the different agencies vary widely, including: the
                    assigned tasks; the strengths and weaknesses within the different agencies;
                    their vulnerabilities to political campaigns; and our own assets in dealing with
                    challenges. For example, in some agencies there are strong, technically oriented
                    secretariats which consult with and accept advice from American delegations. In
                    these situations, we can plan to make maximum use of friendly secretariats who
                    want to get on with their essential tasks. In other secretariats, there has been
                    a long record of stultifying inefficiency or non-aligned manipulation and
                    therefore our opportunities for management through this channel are extremely
                    limited. Unavoidably, we will not be able to count on any single tactic for
                    improving the basic work of each agency. Rather, we will need to develop a
                    repertoire of approaches which we can draw upon in differing situations.</p>
                <p>To begin discussions among friendly developed countries, to encourage greater
                    efforts on their part, and to exchange basic ideas, I am attending from February
                    4 to 6 the annual Geneva Group consultations consisting of leading Western
                    contributors to the UN system.</p>
                <p>(4) Evaluation within the UN system. A UN committee will begin to meet this
                    spring to consider proposals for strengthening the UN’s machinery for evaluating
                    the effectiveness and efficiency of UN programs. There are, in fact, many areas
                    in which the UN’s operations are wasteful, and we have already developed some
                    specific ideas for improving inspection and evaluation.</p>
                <p>The issues are not basically confrontational with the LDCs because, if programs
                    can be made significantly more efficient, the benefits should be more
                    substantial for LDCs who are the principal recipients of UN assistance. We
                    intend to coordinate our efforts with like-minded developed countries and then
                    to broaden consultations to include leading LDCs.</p>
                <p>(5) U.S. participation in the new UN committee on revision of the Charter and UN
                    procedures. At the 29th UNGA, a committee, on which we expect to serve, was
                    established to consider proposals for amending the UN Charter, as well as
                    possible improvements in the UN’s practices and procedures not involving Charter
                    amendments. We intend to discourage Charter revision. This is bound to be a
                    defensive operation for us because we know that some countries plan to agitate
                    for elimination of the veto power in the Security Council.</p>
                <p>It may be possible, however, to develop practical proposals for changes in the
                    UN’s practices and procedures which are not regarded by the non-aligned as an
                    attempt by us to emasculate their parliamentary strength and which would improve
                    the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>’s ability to deal with agenda items. The
                    new committee will not meet until July; however, we are beginning the study of
                    possible proposals now, together with other interested bureaus, so that we can
                    have adequate time to coordinate with our friends and to insure that we have
                    ideas of our own to put before the first session.</p>
                <p>(6) U.S. participation in international conferences. Many international
                    conferences, not related to a regular schedule of board or assembly meetings,
                    take place under the UN system for a variety of purposes throughout each year.
                    In parallel with the increasing politicization we have seen in specialized
                    agencies, there has also been a growing tendency by the non-aligned/LDCs to use
                    these special conferences for confrontation and to pursue extraneous political
                    purposes. It is desirable to begin more extensive advance planning on how we can
                    resist situations likely to be stacked against us. We have also found that the
                    location of conferences can significantly affect how fair the proceedings are.
                    For example, our embassy in Mexico City has reported a serious deterioration in
                    the impartiality of Mexican host country chairmen at many conferences, even to
                    the point where U.S. and other Western delegations are often prevented from
                    fully expressing their views.</p>
                <p>It may, therefore, be desirable for us to take much tougher stance early in the
                    process of deciding on conference arrangements, including the possibility of
                    saying that we will not at tend some conferences if they take place in certain
                    locations or unless and until there has been satisfactory prior agreement on
                    essential procedural questions. IO will begin a study of the detailed
                    possibilities.</p>
                <p>(7) Intensified diplomatic efforts with LDCs/non-aligned. During the last UNGA
                    significant defections from non-aligned ranks took place on some issues. A
                    monolithic, non-aligned bloc was not maintained regarding either the Cambodian
                    or the Korean issues. It is in our interest to follow up in capitals throughout
                    the year, not just during General Assembly sessions, and IO will prepare the
                    instructions for doing this. Our diplomatic efforts should comprehend
                    discussions not only of political issues but UN economic issues as well.</p>
                <p>(8) Selective withdrawal from UN activities. By disassociating ourselves from
                    activities or projects we did not support and which we do not think can have
                    sound and practical results, we may be able to show others over a period of time
                    that there is little practical future for activities which are not based on
                    genuine consensus. We have in the past often participated for damage limiting
                    purposes in bodies or groups we have not favored. However, if an enterprise is
                    fundamentally unsound in our judgment, we might in some cases be less concerned
                    with the results, assuming that we are prepared to disregard them.</p>
                <p>There is a broad spectrum of situations to which non-participation might apply,
                    e.g., non-participation in consideration of, or voting on, particular items
                    before the UNGA or its principal committees; non-participation in ad hoc UNGA
                    subcommittees (like the Committee of 24 on colonial issues); non-participation
                    in particular sessions of UN bodies (like a special session of the GA);
                    non-participation in principal UN organs (like <gloss target="#t_UNESCO1"
                        >UNESCO</gloss>). We have already engaged in some non-participation in the
                    case of a few UN sub-bodies.</p>
                <p>A form of non-participation we have not previously utilized is that of declining
                    to participate in the adoption of a measure, that is, even declining to cast an
                    abstention. This option might be useful particularly as a way of showing
                    disapproval with the manner in which an item was handled, e.g., without
                    sufficient consultations, with unjustified haste, or the like.</p>
                <p>It is our judgment that until such time as there is substantial improvement in
                    the overall functioning-of the UN system, there are likely to be situations in
                    which some form of non-participation would be helpful to our overall efforts and
                    that several instances of non-participation by us would gradually and
                    cumulatively stimulate others to a more realistic appreciation of the long-term
                    dangers of pursuing confrontation politics in international organizations.
                    Accordingly, we intend to look carefully throughout the year’s work at
                    developing situations to see whenever some form of non-participation might be
                    appropriate and we may present this option to you for consideration more
                    frequently than in the past.</p>
                <p>(9) Selective withholding of contributions to the UN or its specialized agencies.
                    There are three possible types of withholding. First, we could withhold for
                    expenditures which we think were illegally or improperly authorized. Second, we
                    could withhold from an entire organization if we believe its activities have
                    been grossly irresponsible. This type of withholding has taken place only as a
                    result of decisions by Congress, e.g., UNESCO and earlier with the <gloss
                        target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss>. Third, we could withhold contributions
                    relating to individual resolutions or decisions of which we strongly
                    disapprove.</p>
                <p>An advantage to selective withholding could be that it could provide even
                    stronger evidence than selective non-participation that the U.S. will not accept
                    serious abuses within the system. On the negative side, however, withholding
                    would obviously raise difficult policy issues and could involve legal questions
                    about treaty obligations to pay assessed contributions. Our withholdings could
                    be utilized to justify widespread withholdings by others, with a significant
                    decrease resulting in the overall effectiveness of the UN and its bodies,
                    including possibly in areas where we are deriving benefit. It would be
                    relatively easy for some of the newly rich countries to pick up the deficits
                    when they wished to, thus minimizing the practical impact of our withholding and
                    even perhaps setting the stage for more irresponsible activities than before. At
                    the present time we do not see situations which would warrant our taking the
                    initiative to withhold funds. However, we shall keep this option in mind as the
                    year’s work proceeds and will call to your attention any situations that might
                    warrant its consideration.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
