<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>30. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Management
                    (Eagleburger) and the Director of the Policy Planning Staff (Lord) to Secretary
                    of State Kissinger, Washington, September 24, 1975.) and the Director of the
                    Policy Planning Staff (Lord) to Secretary of State Kissinger, Washington,
                    September 24, 1975.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-09-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-09-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HPZNpQil9Rnjj" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-civil-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026387"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil Service</term>
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">International organizations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89001442"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Computer</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005651"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monitoring</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="rec9Q8znYJYvxT0pI" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Multilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="public-diplomacy" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomacy</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-09-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-09-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="30"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d30">
                <head>30. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Management
                        (<persName corresp="#p_ELS1">Eagleburger</persName>) and the Director of the
                    Policy Planning Staff (Lord) to Secretary of State Kissinger, Washington,
                    September 24, 1975.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d30fn1">Source: National
                        Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy Files, P830152–0329. Secret; Nodis.
                        Moynihan’s paper is in the Ford Library, <persName corresp="#p_CJE2"
                            >Connor</persName> Files, Box 3, <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>,
                        Daniel P. Moynihan (1). Kissinger did not initial his approval or
                        disapproval of any of the recommendations. The tabs are attached but not
                        published. Tab 1, undated, is a draft memorandum from Eagleburger and
                            <persName corresp="#p_LW2">Lord</persName> to the Assistant Secretaries
                        for International Organization Affairs and the regional bureaus requesting
                        statements about how to approach the issue of “multilateral” diplomacy. Tab
                        2, August 30, is a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_LSW1"
                            >Lewis</persName> to Eagleburger which outlined alternatives for
                        organizing the Department for “multilateral” diplomacy. Tab 3, undated,
                        lists candidates for “multilateral” consideration. Although Kissinger did
                        not indicate his position on any of the recommendations made in this
                        memorandum, Documents 32, 34, and 35 indicate that Kissinger approved the
                        general approach recommended by this memorandum. </note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d30fn2">Eagleburger and <persName
                            corresp="#p_LW2">Lord</persName> recommended altering the Department’s
                        organizational structure and operations to better promote U.S. interests in
                        international organizations.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-09-24"
                        >September 24, 1975</date>
                </dateline>
                <pb facs="d30-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d30-1"/>
                <pb facs="d30-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d30-2"/>
                <pb facs="d30-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d30-3"/>
                <pb facs="d30-4" n="4" xml:id="pg_d30-4"/>
                <pb facs="d30-5" n="5" xml:id="pg_d30-5"/>
                <pb facs="d30-6" n="6" xml:id="pg_d30-6"/>
                <pb facs="d30-7" n="7" xml:id="pg_d30-7"/>
                <p>Department of State<lb/>Action Memorandum</p>
                <p>September 24, 1975</p>
                <p>To: The Secretary</p>
                <p>From: <gloss target="#t_M1">M</gloss> - <persName corresp="#p_ELS1">Lawrence S.
                        Eagleburger</persName> [LSE initialed] <lb/>
                    <gloss target="#t_SP2">S/P</gloss> - <persName corresp="#p_LW2">Winston
                        Lord</persName> [WL initialed]</p>
                <p>Organizing for “Multilateral” Diplomacy</p>
                <p>Adopting a Multilateral Approach</p>
                <p>In his paper, “Bilateral Trends and Multilateral Realities,” Ambassador Moynihan
                    points out that we are taking a beating in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    and related international bodies as well as at important international
                    conferences. He observes that this situation is not only harming our interests
                    but sometimes makes nonsense of serious efforts to deal with important
                    international issues. It also risks undermining Congressional and public support
                    for the UN and international conferences on acute world problems. This situation
                    has resulted not only from the hostility of communist, nonaligned and less
                    developed states but also from a simple failure to exert our diplomatic
                    influence. Moynihan believes we can most effectively come to grips with this
                    problem by giving our “multilateral” interests--specifically voting patterns in
                    the UN and other international bodies--priority over our bilateral relations
                    with those countries with which we have no significant bilateral interests. He
                    has identified 64 such countries. Since these states provide the bulk of the
                    votes against us in international bodies, we should launch a powerful campaign
                    to change the way they are voting.</p>
                <p>Problems of This Approach</p>
                <p>While Moynihan’s ultimate objective will have no opposition in the Department,
                    strong disagreement will arise over our scope for exerting greater influence and
                    the means of implementing the new approach, both in terms of our overseas
                    diplomacy and of the institutional arrangements in the Department to carry it
                    out. There are a number of weaknesses to the approach that will immediately be
                    pointed out.</p>
                <p>Countries where the bilateral relationship is insignificant are precisely the
                    countries where we will have the least potential to carry out a policy of
                    rewards and punishments. With no economic, political or security ties, there is
                    little or nothing we can offer by way of inducement or threaten by way of
                    punishment for the actions of those countries in the UN. Even in the case of
                    countries were we have an <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> program, such a
                    policy lacks credibility. A country such as Mauritania, for instance, is
                    completely dependent on Libyan support and largely indifferent to our threats or
                    promises. In any case, an AID program can be cut off only once and, if stopped,
                    would probably make that country more hostile to us. Some AID programs, as that
                    with Mali, are for humanitarian purposes, such as to limit mass starvation, and
                    to withdraw them would probably be impossible for domestic political reasons.
                    Moreover, the US government is not usually institutionally able to initiate an
                    AID program (as a reward to a compliant country) rapidly.</p>
                <p>The countries at issue generally have little interest in international problems,
                    poor communications and an inadequate civil service; consequently their UN
                    ambassadors are largely on their own. Pressure in capitals could have little or
                    no impact.</p>
                <p>A list of “multilateral” states will eventually become known; such a
                    classification might be considered second-rate status and as a result reduce or
                    destroy our influence there.</p>
                <p>The major nonaligned states, and those with significant influence in
                    international organizations, are no “multilateral” ones. As a result of the new
                    approach we would find ourselves concentrating our pressure on the 64 weakest
                    and least influential states in the world. Many of these countries are,
                    moreover, apt to follow the lead of the major nonaligned states rather than
                    succumb to our pressure.</p>
                <p>Reasons to Go Ahead</p>
                <p>The points are generally valid as far as they go, and they ought to caution us
                    not to expect overnight miracles. But the arguments by no means diminish the
                    cardinal fact that the US is not without prestige and influence in any country
                    and that we have generally failed not only to bring pressure to bear but even to
                    make our position on international issues known. Small influence or large, we
                    must do what we can and there is a lot more we can do.</p>
                <p>The fact that we have no evident means of exerting pressure on a nonaligned
                    state, or may not wish to retaliate against unfriendly behavior, is no reason
                    not to inform the country that we deplore its voting practices and that we
                    intend to take this into account at any time that the country may seek our
                    support on any bilateral or multilateral issues. In this connection, this new
                    approach will force the Department to think through a precise catalog of
                    potential rewards and punishments which can be resorted to if such were ever
                    deemed useful.</p>
                <p>The situation the US faces, to reiterate, is a dangerous erosion of our
                    diplomatic position in the world. This is most acutely evident in international
                    forums, and we see Moynihan’s approach essentially as a take-off point for
                    launching a broad initiative to try to solve this broader problem. Our strategy
                    must be a comprehensive one and will have to include Allies, friends, neutrals
                    and nonaligned, both influential and not. The immediate aim of this approach,
                    however, should be to focus on those nonaligned states where our bilateral
                    interests are of minimal importance.</p>
                <p>There is a great deal the Department can do right away. Using our computer
                    capability, we should examine voting records (which we have already begun to do)
                    as a basis for our efforts. We should inform all our ambassadors that issues in
                    international forums are priority matters and that they and their staffs must be
                    prepared to give to these issues whatever time and attention are necessary. We
                    should then support our embassies with full and timely information and
                    instructions. We should also raise these issues in Allied capitals and perhaps
                    in multilateral forums such as NATO; we should also instruct embassies
                    throughout the world to work with other friendly, especially NATO, embassies in
                    our efforts.</p>
                <p>From here on the problem will be more difficult. Producing a list of countries
                    and giving appropriate ambassadors full and timely instructions will certainly
                    help, but these steps will probably not elicit the institutional and
                    psychological changes needed in the department if the new approach is to be
                    effectively implemented. We will face suspicion from the regional bureaus that
                    their authority will be undermined and we will encounter the long-standing lack
                    of authority of functional bureaus, in this case <gloss target="#t_IO1"
                        >IO</gloss>. There are various ways of restructuring the Department, from
                    the creation of a new bureau for “multilateral” affairs to reliance on
                    exhortation and periodic monitoring. (<gloss target="#t_SP2">S/P</gloss> has
                    already done a useful study of this issue; this paper is attached at Tab 2.)</p>
                <p>The Initial Step</p>
                <p>We think it is best to proceed with a join memorandum from us describing the
                    proposal in general terms. We attach a draft memorandum for your approval (Tab
                    1). With your authorization, we would raise with the Assistant Secretaries,
                    though only orally at this point, the proposed list of countries which is
                    attached for your information at Tab 3. We think it would be unwise, given the
                    danger of leaks, to include the list of countries with the memo.</p>
                <p>As soon as we have an agreed list, we will have to develop with the bureaus more
                    precise methods of implementing the concept—determining what scope we have for
                    greater diplomatic persuasion in each individual case, how we can improve our
                    “persuasion” of countries not on the list (a factor that might otherwise be
                    forgotten in the aftermath of our emphasis on “multilateral” countries), and how
                    we might work with friendly third countries (for example, Britain, France and
                    Germany) and organizations (such as the <gloss target="#t_EC1">EC</gloss>).</p>
                <p>At the same time, and perhaps of most importance, we will have to determine what
                    changes will have to be made in the organization of the Department. While we do
                    not yet see all of these clearly, it seems evident that IO will have to bear the
                    brunt of the responsibility. We are inclined at the moment to think a new office
                    under a strong director should be established there for “multilateral
                    relations.” It may even be advisable to establish a new Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary in IO to take charge of this work. It would be understood that IO
                    would also have a watching brief for other countries whose support in
                    international forums is needed. Disagreements between IO and the geographic
                    bureaus will have to be referred to the Under Secretary for Political Affairs.
                    We do not believe we should pull our “multilateral” countries out of the
                    regional bureaus, though we may later on consider, as S/P suggests in the
                    attached paper, the establishment of an office of “multilateral country” affairs
                    within <gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>,
                        <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_EA1"
                    >EA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>We ourselves cannot agree on one key issue: the degree of IO’s control of
                    “multilateral” countries. Eagleburger believes that IO should have complete
                    authority on issues relating to multilateral forums though clearing instructions
                    with regional bureaus, while regional bureaus would clear instructions on other
                    matters with IO. He believes that short of having such authority, IO would be
                    unable to assert the control necessary to achieve the objectives of the new
                    approach. He knows that you have doubts about developing a “superstructure” to
                    handle this approach. Perhaps they are justified, but he now feels strongly that
                    anything short of a substantial shift of the organizational center of gravity
                    will be doomed to failure. We have seen the building at work for too long. Lord
                    is less certain that such drastic surgery is necessary. This, too, is an issue
                    which will have to be thoroughly discussed with the bureaus and worked out as we
                    go along. In any case we would prefer to wait to give you our final
                    recommendations on all of these questions until after we have explored them
                    thoroughly with the Assistant Secretaries.</p>
                <p>Once the approach has been agreed on, we will have to work with the bureaus to
                    draft a telegram to all missions to inform them of the new approach, how we
                    intend to implement it and what the new additional responsibilities of
                    ambassadors will be in “multilateral” countries.</p>
                <p>Should this approach prove successful, it could serve as a pilot project for the
                    Department in handling those other functional issues that are going to be major
                    elements of foreign affairs in the coming decades.</p>
                <p>Recommendation</p>
                <p>That you approve the attached memorandum to IO and the regional bureaus</p>
                <p>Approved<lb/>Disapproved</p>
                <p>That you authorize us to develop a list of countries with IO and the regional
                    bureaus</p>
                <p>Approved <lb/> Disapproved</p>
                <p>Alternatively, that you meet with <persName corresp="#p_BWB1">Buffum</persName>,
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> and us to discuss this approach
                    prior to our sending a memo to the bureaus</p>
                <p>I should like to meet with you<lb/>No meeting is necessary</p>
                <p>Attachments: <lb/> Tab 1 - Proposed Memo From <gloss target="#t_M1">M</gloss>
                    &amp; S/P to Assistant Secretaries of IO and the Regional Bureaus<lb/>Tab 2 -
                    Memo from S/P to M re “Organizing the Department for Multilateral Diplomacy”
                    <lb/> Tab 3 - Proposed List of “Multilateral” Countries</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
