<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-12-30T17:58:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-12-30T17:58:00-05:00" n="52" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d52">
                        <head>52. Telegram 313877 From the Department of State to All Diplomatic
                            Posts, December 30, 1976, 2258Z.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d52fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy Files. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WJ4">Washburn</persName>; cleared in draft by <persName corresp="#p_LWH1">Luers</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MRJ5">Martens</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_PS4">Perry</persName>, and in <gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss> and
                                    <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_LSW1">Lewis</persName>. For <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s September 30 address to
                                the U.N. General Assembly, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October 25, 1976, pp. 497–510. Simeon Ake of
                                Cote d’Ivoire was <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss>
                                President in 1976.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d52fn2">The Department reviewed the
                                principal accomplishments of the 31st United Nations General
                                Assembly.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-12-30T22:58:00+00:00">December 30,
                                1976, 2258Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>TELEGRAM <lb/> Department of State <lb/> 313877</p>
                        <p>R 302258Z DEC 76</p>
                        <p>FM SECSTATE WASHDC <lb/> TO ALL DIPLOMATIC POSTS <lb/> AMEMBASSY BANGUI
                            BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY BANJUL BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY BEIRUT BY POUCH
                            <lb/> AMEMBASSY BISSAU BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY DAMASCUS BY POUCH <lb/>
                            AMEMBASSY GABORONE BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY KIGALI BY POUCH <lb/>
                            AMEMBASSY LOME BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY MBABANE BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY
                            MAPUTO BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY MASERU BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY LILONGWE
                            BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY OUAGADOUGOU BY POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY SUVA BY
                            POUCH <lb/> AMEMBASSY VIENTIANE BY POUCH <lb/> XMT AMEMBASSY BANGUI
                            <lb/> AMEMBASSY BANJUL <lb/> AMEMBASSY BISSAU <lb/> AMEMBASSY DAMASCUS
                            <lb/> AMEMBASSY GABORONE <lb/> AMEMBASSY KIGALI <lb/> AMEMBASSY LOME
                            <lb/> AMEMBASSY MBABANE <lb/> AMEMBASSY MAPUTO <lb/> AMEMBASSY MASERU
                            <lb/> AMEMBASSY LILONGWE <lb/> AMEMBASSY OUAGADOUGOU <lb/> AMEMBASSY
                            SUVA <lb/> AMEMBASSY VIENTIANE</p>
                        <p>STATE 313877</p>
                        <p>E.O. 11652: GDS <lb/> TAGS: PFOR, <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p>SUBJECT: MULTILATERAL AFFAIRS: ASSESSMENT OF 31ST UNGA</p>
                        <p>REF: STATE 220772</p>
                        <p>1. BEGIN SUMMARY:</p>
                        <p>THIS CABLE IS THE FIRST OF SEVERAL ON MULTILATERAL AFFAIRS IN 1976 AND
                            1977. IT DESCRIBES SESSION’S ATMOSPHERE, REVIEWS PRINCIPAL DEVELOPMENTS
                            AND ASSESSES THEIR SIGNIFICANCE FOR <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>
                            AS BACKGROUND INFORMATION FOR AMBASSADOR AND EMBASSY OFFICERS. TALKING
                            POINTS FOR USE WITH HOST GOVERNMENTS WILL FOLLOW SHORTLY. END
                            SUMMARY.</p>
                        <p>2. BACKGROUND. A. 31ST UNGA CULMINATED A YEAR OF INTENSE MULTILATERAL
                            ACTIVITY ACROSS VIRTUALLY FULL RANGE OF ISSUES UNGA NORMALLY CONSIDERS.
                                <gloss target="#t_UNCTAD1">UNCTAD</gloss> IV, <gloss target="#t_CIEC1">CIEC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss>, AND MANY OTHER INTERNATIONAL MEETINGS WITHIN AND
                            OUTSIDE <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> SYSTEM STRENUOUSLY ADDRESSED
                            AGENDA OF ECONOMIC ISSUES ESTABLISHED BY THE 1975 UNGA SEVENTH SPECIAL
                            SESSION. POSITIONS OF THE <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss> MAJORITY
                            IN THE UNGA ON THESE ISSUES WERE FURTHER DEFINED AT <gloss target="#t_G771">G-77</gloss> MANILA AND MEXICO CITY MEETINGS AND
                            NON-ALIGNED ALGIERS AND COLOMBO CONFERENCES.</p>
                        <p>B. POLITICAL ISSUES AT 31ST <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> HAD ALSO
                            BEEN EXTENSIVELY NEGOTIATED AT PRECEDING INTERNATIONAL MEETINGS. AT
                                <gloss target="#t_OAU1">OAU</gloss> SUMMIT AND ELSEWHERE, AFRICANS
                            DEMONSTRATED THAT THEY DEFINITELY WOULD NOT NOW SUPPORT ISRAEL’S
                            EXCLUSION FROM GA, AND WERE INCREASINGLY RELUCTANT TO REAFFIRM
                            ZIONISM/RACISM WHEN THIS WOULD REDUCE SUPPORT FOR ACTIONS ON APARTHEID.
                            SIMILARLY, CONSIDERABLE NUMBER OF LDCS, TO WHOM WE HAD MADE REGULAR
                            REPRESENTATIONS, RECOGNIZED IRRELEVANCE OF KOREA AND PUERTO RICO ISSUES
                            TO THEIR OWN INTERESTS IN THE GA. RESULT, ASSISTED BY INEPTITUDE AND
                            ARROGANCE OF CUBA AND NORTH KOREA AT COLOMBO, WAS THAT THESE TWO ISSUES
                            LOST MUCH SUPPORT AND BOTH COUNTRIES DECIDED NOT TO PUSH THEM AT THE
                            31ST UNGA.</p>
                        <p>3. DYNAMICS OF THE 31ST GA. A. RELATIVE ABSENCE OF POLITICAL STRIFE
                            PROVIDED UNUSUALLY CLEAR VIEW OF USES OR MISUSES OF GA BY ITS MEMBERS
                            AND THEIR PURPOSES IN IT. THUS, 31ST UNGA SHOWED THAT MOST OF THE UNGA’S
                            LDC MAJORITY REGARD IT SERIOUSLY AS A WAY TO BE HEARD EFFECTIVELY, AND
                            TO FURTHER IMPORTANT FOREIGN POLICY OBJECTIVES. HOWEVER, WE SEE TOO MUCH
                            LDC BEHAVIOR AS STILL NOT SERVING THESE SERIOUS PURPOSES. UNGA’S
                            LEGITIMATE FUNCTION AS A SAFETY-VALVE FOR EMOTION AND FRUSTRATION IS
                            GROSSLY OVERUSED TO DISPLAY FERVOR AND SOLIDARITY AND TO PUNISH WITH
                            WORDS.</p>
                        <p>B. AUTOMATIC ADOPTION OF PRE-DECIDED, (QUOTE) NON-NEGOTIABLE (UNQUOTE)
                            RESOLUTIONS BY BLOC VOTES, AS IN 29TH AND 30TH UNGAS, AND SIXTH SPECIAL
                            SESSION, DID NOT RECUR. ALTHOUGH LDCS ORGANIZED AS THE GROUP OF 77 OFTEN
                            BECAME IMPATIENT WITH PROTRACTED NEGOTIATIONS ON G-77-SPONSORED
                            RESOLUTIONS OPPOSED BY ONLY A SMALL MINORITY OF DEVELOPED COUNTRIES,
                            G-77 NORMALLY CONTINUED NEGOTIATIONS WHEN NECESSARY TO AVOID NUMEROUS
                            DEVELOPED COUNTRY ABSTENTIONS OR NEGATIVE VOTES. UN MEMBERS ALSO
                            INCREASINGLY RECOGNIZED THAT CERTAIN RESOLUTIONS (E.G., CONVENING A
                            SPECIAL SESSION ON DISARMAMENT) REQUIRE AS NEARLY UNIVERSAL SUPPORT AS
                            POSSIBLE. DESIRE TO ADOPT SUCH RESOLUTIONS BY CONSENSUS SUSTAINED
                            NEGOTIATIONS ON THEM.</p>
                        <p>C. DEVELOPED COUNTRIES WERE ACTIVE IN THIS GA, FINDING MORE SUCCESS ON
                            THEIR INITIATIVES THAN IN RECENT PAST. THESE TENDED TO AVOID MAIN
                            POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC AREAS OF CONTENTION. FOR EXAMPLE, THE <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> SUCCESSFULLY OBTAINED CONSENSUS
                            ADOPTION OF ITS RESOLUTION ON AN INTERNATIONAL CONVENTION AGAINST TAKING
                            OF HOSTAGES. BY CONTRAST, JAPAN HAD TO ABANDON ITS RESOLUTION ON
                            CONVENTIONAL ARMS FOR LACK OF SUPPORT. THESE AND OTHER EXPERIENCES
                            EMPHASIZED VALUE OF DEVELOPED COUNTRIES’ INITIATIVES IN THE UN ON
                            COMPLEX OR SENSITIVE SUBJECTS.</p>
                        <p>4. GROUPS AND CAUCUSES. </p>
                        <p>A. THESE WERE PARTICULARLY ACTIVE THIS YEAR. AMONG DEVELOPED COUNTRIES
                            THE WESTERN EUROPEAN AND OTHERS GROUP (<gloss target="#t_WEO1">WEO</gloss>) WAS USEFUL FOR EXCHANGING INFORMATION AND COMPARING
                            VIEWS. HOWEVER, SMALLER IMPROVISED GROUPS HANDLED COORDINATION AND
                            NEGOTIATION OF SPECIFIC POSITIONS. OF THESE, KOREA CORE GROUP
                            COORDINATED STRATEGY, AND REPRESENTATIONS IN NEW YORK AND CAPITALS,
                            BETWEEN 30TH AND 31ST UNGAS AND WOULD HAVE HANDLED THE KOREA ISSUE AT
                            THE 31ST GA HAD IT NOT BEEN WITHDRAWN.</p>
                        <p>B. <gloss target="#t_EC91">EC-9</gloss> SHOWED IMPRESSIVE DETERMINATION
                            TO ACHIEVE COORDINATED POSITIONS. THESE EFFORTS AT CO-ORDINATION WERE
                            OFTEN PROTRACTED, PRODUCING INFLEXIBLE AND MINIMAL COMMON POSITIONS. WE
                            THUS FREQUENTLY HAD DIFFICULTIES IN ACHIEVING EC-9 SUPPORT FOR OUR
                            USUALLY MORE DEMANDING POSITIONS, PARTICULARLY ON ECONOMIC ISSUES.
                            HOWEVER, WE BELIEVE WE NOW HAVE A SOLID BASE FOR INCREASING
                            CONSULTATIONS WITH EC-9 COUNTRIES IN NEW YORK, CAPITALS AND EC-9’S OWN
                            FORUMS ON A WIDE RANGE OF ISSUES.</p>
                        <p>C. AMONG LDCS, MOST IMPORTANT FORMAL CAUCUSES WERE REGIONAL GROUPS,
                                <gloss target="#t_NAM1">NAM</gloss>, AND G-77. AFRICAN GROUP WAS
                            PARTICULARLY IMPORTANT BECAUSE OF ITS NUMBERS AND ENERGY WHICH GAVE IT
                            CONTROL OVER ISSUES MOST IMPORTANT TO IT. THE NAM, ENERGIZED BY COLOMBO,
                            WAS EXTREMELY ACTIVE AND SPONSORED RESOLUTIONS WHICH WERE ADOPTED ON
                            WIDE RANGE OF ECONOMIC, POLITICAL AND DISARMAMENT ISSUES. MANY OF THESE
                            RESOLUTIONS WERE COLOMBO POSITIONS AND WERE MANAGED BY THE COORDINATING
                            COUNTRIES ASSIGNED TO THEM THERE. THE NON-ALIGNED COORDINATING COMMITTEE
                                (<gloss target="#t_NACC1">NACC</gloss>) MET REGULARLY TO CONSIDER
                            PROGRESS REPORTS AND PROVIDE GENERAL GUIDANCE.</p>
                        <p>D. THE G-77 HAD A SEMI-FORMAL COORDINATING STRUCTURE UNDER A COMMITTEE
                            CHAIRED BY PAKISTAN TO WHICH GROUPS COVERING EACH ISSUE AND GA COMMITTEE
                            REPORTED. THE SPECIFICS OF BASICALLY AGREED POSITIONS WERE OFTEN
                            INTENSIVELY NEGOTIATED WITHIN G-77. G-77’S BASIC PURPOSE WAS TO
                            DEMONSTRATE LDC DISSATISFACTION WITH INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC NEGOTIATIONS
                            ON KEY ISSUES (DEBT, COMMODITIES), AND TO FURTHER INTERNATIONAL
                            ACCEPTANCE OF THE <gloss target="#t_NIEO1">NIEO</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>E. <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> APPEARED TO BE TRYING THROUGH
                            DISARMAMENT INITIATIVES AND OTHERWISE TO GAIN MORE VISIBILITY IN THE
                            UNGA. THE GENERAL FEELING THAT GENEVA CONFERENCE ON THE MIDDLE EAST (OF
                            WHICH USSR IS A CO-CHAIRMAN) SHOULD NOW BE REVIVED HELPED THIS EFFORT.
                            HOWEVER, LDCS’ RECOGNITION OF SOVIET IRRELEVANCE TO MOST OF THEIR
                            ECONOMIC OBJECTIVES, AND ABSENCE OF A SOVIET ROLE IN POLITICAL ISSUES
                            SUCH AS CYPRUS, ONCE AGAIN KEPT USSR FROM FINDING A PLACE IN THE 31ST
                            UNGA PROPORTIONATE TO ITS SUPERPOWER STATUS. </p>
                        <p>5. SECURITY COUNCIL. SECURITY COUNCIL WAS IN ALMOST CONTINUOUS SESSION
                            DURING THE 31ST UNGA. NON-ALIGNED COUNTRIES, TO EXPRESS THEIR OPPOSITION
                            TO PERMANENT MEMBERS’ USE OF THE VETO, TRIED TO PRESSURE <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> MEMBERS (PARTICULARLY USG) THROUGH GA
                            RESOLUTIONS ON ISSUES LIKE ADMISSION OF VIET NAM. EGYPT ATTEMPTED TO USE
                            THE CONCURRENT SESSIONS OF THE SC AND THE GA TO KEEP ATTENTION FOCUSED
                            ON ITS (QUOTE) PEACE OFFENSIVE (UNQUOTE), IN PARTICULAR BY CONVERTING ME
                            ACTIONS OF THE SC, ESPECIALLY CONSENSUS STATEMENT ON OCCUPIED
                            TERRITORIES, INTO GA RESOLUTIONS. WE OBJECTED NOT ONLY TO GRATUITOUSNESS
                            OF THIS MANEUVER, BUT ALSO TO CONSEQUENT BLURRING OF THE GA’S AND SC’S
                            SEPARATE ROLES BY IMPLYING THAT SC ACTIONS ARE NOT DEFINITIVE THEMSELVES
                            WITHOUT FURTHER ACTION BY THE GA. IN CONTRAST, SC AND GA COLLABORATED
                            APPROPRIATELY AND SMOOTHLY ON CYPRUS/<gloss target="#t_UNFICYP1">UNFICYP</gloss> RENEWAL, WALDHEIM’S RE-ELECTION, <gloss target="#t_UNDOF1">UNDOF</gloss> RENEWAL/REFINANCING, AND ADMISSION
                            OF ANGOLA AND WESTERN SAMOA.</p>
                        <p>6. ECONOMIC QUESTIONS. </p>
                        <p>A. THE ABSENCE OF BITTERLY CONTESTED POLITICAL ISSUES THIS YEAR MADE
                            EVIDENT IMMENSE AMOUNT OF TIME AND EFFORT GA NORMALLY DEVOTES TO
                            ECONOMIC ISSUES. AS USUAL, SESSION CONSIDERED A WIDE VARIETY OF ECONOMIC
                            ISSUES, INCLUDING: INSTITUTIONAL OR ORGANIZATIONAL MATTERS (E.G., <gloss target="#t_UNIDO1">UNIDO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_IFAD1">IFAD</gloss>), PROGRAMS (E.G., <gloss target="#t_UNDP1">UNDP</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_WFP1">WFP</gloss>), AND APPEALS FOR
                            SPECIAL ECONOMIC ASSISTANCE TO INDIVIDUAL AND GROUPS OF COUNTRIES (E.G.,
                            LANDLOCKED AND ISLAND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES). SOME OF THESE WILL HAVE
                            DIRECT PRACTICAL RESULTS, OTHERS WERE LARGELY HORTATORY. MOST REACHED A
                            TRUE CONSENSUS. A FEW, BECAUSE OF MAJOR DIFFERENCES, WENT TO VOTE. MAJOR
                            NORTH/SOUTH ISSUES PRODUCED MOST DIFFICULT RESOLUTIONS. THE GA’S
                            RESPONSES TO THESE WERE MIXED. ALTHOUGH G-77 PRESSED SWEEPING DEMANDS
                            AND CRITICIZED ALLEGED LACK OF RESPONSE BY DEVELOPED COUNTRIES, TONE OF
                            THE SESSION EVEN ON THESE DIFFICULT QUESTIONS WAS RELATIVELY FREE OF
                            RANCOR. IN GENERAL, THERE WAS REASONABLE WEO SOLIDARITY ON THESE ISSUES,
                            BUT IN SEVERAL CASES IT WAS FIRMNESS OF US POSITION THAT HELD WEO
                            WAVERERS IN LINE.</p>
                        <p>IT IS TOO EARLY TO JUDGE THE NET RESULTS OF 31ST UNGA ON NORTH/SOUTH
                            ISSUES. OVERALL, IT PROBABLY DID NOT ADVANCE OR RETARD ONGOING DIALOGUE
                            ON THESE ISSUES, BUT IT DID UNDERSCORE DIFFICULTIES AHEAD. G-77 HAS
                            CLEARLY NOT RELENTED IN ITS DEMANDS, ALTHOUGH SOME MODERATE LEADERS
                            DISLIKED THE EXTREMISM OF OTHER LEADERS SUCH AS PAKISTAN. MOREOVER,
                            DESPITE CRITICISMS IN SOME OF THESE RESOLUTIONS, IMPORTANT G-77
                            COUNTRIES SEEMED WILLING TO WAIT UNTIL THE NEW US ADMINISTRATION CAN
                            INDICATE ITS POSITIONS. ALL OF FOLLOWING ISSUES WILL BE BEFORE VARIOUS
                            FORUMS IN 1977. AMONG THESE MAY WELL BE A RESUMED 31ST UNGA SESSION ON
                            ECONOMIC ISSUES IN LATE SPRING.</p>
                        <p>B. CIEC. THE SECRETARY’S UNGA ADDRESS CALLED FOR RENEWED IMPETUS FOR
                            PARIS CONFERENCE ON INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC COOPERATION (CIEC). G-77 CIEC
                            RESOLUTION BY PAKISTAN SAID MOST DEVELOPED COUNTRIES HAD YET TO
                            DEMONSTRATE IN CIEC POLITICAL WILL NECESSARY FOR CONCRETE RESULTS. IT
                            URGED THEM TO RESPOND POSITIVELY TO LDC PROPOSALS (THUS IGNORING
                            DEVELOPED COUNTRY PROPOSALS ACTUALLY MADE IN CIEC). AFTER INTENSIVE
                            NEGOTIATIONS FAILED, PAKISTAN’S ORIGINAL DRAFT WAS ADOPTED BY 99-0-30
                            (VIRTUALLY ALL WEO’S PLUS SOVIET BLOC EXCEPT ROMANIA). THE US EMPHASIZED
                            OUR COMMITMENT TO CONTINUING DIALOGUE AND ACTIVE PARTICIPATION IN CIEC,
                            BUT CALLED RESOLUTION ONE-SIDED AND PREJUDICIAL TO CIEC. EC-9, JAPAN,
                            CANADA, AUSTRALIA AND OTHER WEOS MADE SIMILAR STATEMENTS. SOVIET BLOC
                            MEMBERS SAID THEY ABSTAINED AS NON-PARTICIPANTS IN CIEC. THE RESOLUTION
                            AND ITS NEGOTIATION WERE UNFORTUNATE, BUT WE WERE GRATIFIED BY WEO
                            SOLIDARITY, EVEN INCLUDING SUCH SOFT-LINERS AS SWEDEN. MOREOVER, A
                            NUMBER OF MORE MODERATE MEMBERS OF THE G-77 WERE DISSATISFIED BY
                            PAKISTAN’S HARD LINE. SINCE CIEC’S MINISTERIAL SESSION WAS LATER
                            POSTPONED (PROBABLY TO NEXT SPRING), THE NEGATIVE EFFECT OF CIEC
                            RESOLUTION MAY BE MINIMAL.</p>
                        <p>C. NIEO. PAKISTAN’S (G-77) RESOLUTION ON IMPLEMENTING NEW INTERNATIONAL
                            ECONOMIC ORDER (NIEO) WAS COMPLETELY UNACCEPTABLE TO US. IT CLAIMED A
                            6TH SPECIAL SESSION COMMITMENT TO NIEO BY ALL COUNTRIES; CRITICIZED
                            DEVELOPED COUNTRIES’ LACK OF POLITICAL WILL, URGED THEM TO PROMOTE NIEO,
                            AND EXPRESSED DISAPPOINTMENT AT SLOW PROGRESS IN CIEC AND IN
                            IMPLEMENTING RESOLUTIONS OF 6TH AND 7TH SPECIAL SESSION AND UNCTAD IV.
                            IT CALLED FOR 32ND GA ASSESSMENT OF THESE RESOLUTIONS, INTERNATIONAL
                            DEVELOPMENT STRATEGY (<gloss target="#t_IDS1">IDS</gloss>--SUB-<gloss target="#t_Para1">PARA</gloss> G BELOW), NIEO, AND CHARTER OF
                            ECONOMIC RIGHTS AND DUTIES (<gloss target="#t_CERDS1">CERDS</gloss>).
                            THE US DID NOT PARTICIPATE IN NEGOTIATIONS. NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN OTHER
                            WEOS AND CO-SPONSORS PRODUCED ONLY LIMITED IMPROVEMENTS. THE RESOLUTION
                            WAS ADOPTED BY 128-1(US)-8(<gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss>
                            COUNTRIES). US STATEMENT WAS ESSENTIALLY SAME AS ON CIEC RESOLUTION. WE
                            CAN EXPECT THE NIEO TO BE FREQUENT STANDARD PROBLEM IN G-77 RESOLUTIONS
                            ON NORTH/SOUTH ISSUES.</p>
                        <p>D. DEBT. THE SECRETARY’S UNGA SPEECH NOTED US PROPOSALS FOR DEALING WITH
                            LDC DEBT. ETHIOPIA, PAKISTAN, PHILIPPINES, AND SUDAN CO-SPONSORED
                            RESOLUTION CONTAINING THE LDCS’ CIEC DEBT POSITION. DESPITE US, EC-9 AND
                            SWEDISH EFFORT TO SUBSTITUTE PROCEDURAL RESOLUTION NOT PREJUDICING WEOS’
                            DEBT POSITION IN CIEC, SUDANESE REVISION OF ORIGINAL RESOLUTION PASSED
                            BY 99-1(US)-31 (ALL WEO’S AND SOVIET BLOC, EXCEPT ROMANIA). US NOTED
                            RESOLUTION’S INAPPROPRIATENESS SINCE CIEC CONTINUING, AND REITERATED US
                            POSITIONS INCLUDING US CONCERN FOR FINANCIAL PROBLEMS OF OIL IMPORTING
                            LDCS. NETHERLANDS (FOR <gloss target="#t_EC1">EC</gloss>), SWEDEN, JAPAN
                            AND AUSTRALIA ALSO EXPRESSED CONCERN THAT THE RESOLUTION WOULD PREJUDICE
                            CIEC.</p>
                        <p>E. TRANSFER OF REAL RESOURCES. PHILIPPINE RESOLUTION URGING DEVELOPED
                            COUNTRIES TO MEET 0.7 PERCENT OF <gloss target="#t_GNP1">GNP</gloss>
                            TARGET FOR OFFICIAL DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE (<gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss>) AND RECOMMENDING SPECIFIC MEASURES FOR ATTAINING
                            TARGET, PASSED BY 117(WEOS)-1(US)-18(9 SOVIET BLOC; EC-9, MINUS
                            NETHERLANDS AND DENMARK WHO VOTED YES, JAPAN, SPAIN). US STATED ITS
                            COMMITMENT TO INCREASE ODA EFFECTIVELY WHILE RE-EMPHASIZING THAT US DOES
                            NOT ACCEPT 0.7 PERCENT TARGET. SOVIET BLOC EXPLAINED IT ABSTAINED AS NOT
                            RESPONSIBLE FOR LDCS’ ECONOMIC PLIGHT. THE ODA TARGET ON WHICH WEO UNITY
                            IS WEAK WILL CONTINUE TO BE AN IMPORTANT LDC POSITION IN CIEC AND IN
                            UNCTAD TRADE AND DEVELOPMENT BOARD (<gloss target="#t_TDB1">TDB</gloss>)
                            MINISTERIAL.</p>
                        <p>F. UNCTAD IV. US JOINED A CONSENSUS ON UNCTAD IV OMNIBUS RESOLUTION.
                            RESOLUTION WITH 23 OPERATIVE PARAS NOTED AND INTERPRETED UNCTAD IV’S
                            RESOLUTIONS. IN NEGOTIATIONS, MOST DIFFICULT ISSUES WERE DEBT AND
                            COMMODITIES. THE ORIGINAL DRAFT GAVE UNCTAD <gloss target="#t_TDB1">TDB</gloss> AN UNWARRANTED ROLE ON DEBT, PROMOTED G-77 INTEGRATED
                            PROGRAM FOR COMMODITIES AND COMMON FUND, AND EFFECTIVELY PREJUDGED
                            WHETHER THE CODE OF CONDUCT FOR TECHNOLOGY TRANSFER SHOULD BE VOLUNTARY
                            OR BINDING. EVENTUAL G-77 MODIFICATIONS ENABLED THE US, OTHER WEOS, AND
                            EES TO JOIN THE CONSENSUS. IN LENGTHY STATEMENT OF RESERVATIONS AND
                            INTERPRETATIONS, US RECALLED THAT UNCTAD PREVIOUSLY LIMITED TDB
                            MINISTERIAL IN 1977 TO REVIEWING ACTION ON THE UNCTAD IV DEBT
                            RESOLUTION, AND REJECTED ANY ADVANCE US COMMITMENT TO ANY PARTICULAR
                            OUTCOME TO THE INTEGRATED COMMODITY PROGRAM NEGOTIATIONS.</p>
                        <p>G. IDS. UNITED STATES AGREED TO CONSENSUS ON SEPARATE G-77 IDS
                            RESOLUTION. THIS AUTHORIZES COLLECTION OF DATA ON THIRD INTERNATIONAL
                            DEVELOPMENT DECADE. NUMBER OF NEGOTIATED IMPROVEMENTS IN RESOLUTION
                            INCLUDES ITS TAKING INTO ACCOUNT ONLY NIEO OBJECTIVES RATHER THAN
                            ORIGINAL LANGUAGE EXPLICITLY MAKING IDS AN INSTRUMENT TO ACHIEVE NIEO.
                            WE HOPE THAT 32ND GA WILL ACCORDINGLY BE ABLE TO ASSESS THIRD
                            DEVELOPMENT DECADE RELATIVELY OBJECTIVELY DESPITE THE INDIRECT
                            ENDORSEMENT OF NIEO AND INCLUSION OF IDS IN RESOLUTION SUB-PARA C.</p>
                        <p>H. <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>. THE SECRETARY’S UNGA SPEECH NOTED OUR ACTION ON
                            REPLENISHMENT FOR WORLD BANK. G-77 RESOLUTION CALLING FOR PROMPT
                            REPLENISHMENT OF IDA AND FOR INCREASE IN IBRD CAPITAL PASSED WITHOUT
                            VOTE FOLLOWING EXTENDED NEGOTIATIONS. PRIMARY POINT OF CONTENTION WAS
                            OPERATIVE PARAGRAPH WHICH URGES IBRD MEMBER COUNTRY SUPPORT FOR
                            SUBSTANTIAL INCREASE IN BANK CAPITAL. US SAID RESOLUTION CAN BE APPLIED
                            ONLY TO THE 8.3 BILLION DOLLAR SELECTIVE CAPITAL INCREASE CURRENTLY IN
                            PROCESS. FRG, FRANCE AND JAPAN MADE SAME POINT. HOWEVER, G-77 SEE
                            RESOLUTION AS CALLING FOR A LARGER GENERAL INCREASE. WE ANTICIPATE
                            FURTHER G-77 PRESSURE IN BANK AND ELSEWHERE TO THIS END.</p>
                        <p>I. RESOLUTION ON 1979 UN CONFERENCE ON SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY FOR
                            DEVELOPMENT. THE SECRETARY’S SPEECH OFFERED US AS CONFERENCE SITE. WE
                            CO-SPONSORED RESOLUTION ENDORSING 61ST ECOSOC’S RECOMMENDATIONS ON
                            CONFERENCE’S FRAMEWORK, OBJECTIVES, AGENDA AND PRELIMINARY ACTIVITIES.
                            RESOLUTION GIVES FINAL SITE DECISION TO 32ND GA. GA ALSO REQUESTED
                                <gloss target="#t_UNSYG1">UNSYG</gloss> TO APPOINT <gloss target="#t_ASAP1">ASAP</gloss> A CONFERENCE <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>, AND DECIDED THAT COMMITTEE ON SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY
                            FOR DEVELOPMENT (<gloss target="#t_CSTD1">CSTD</gloss>) SHOULD MEET AS
                            PREPCON OF CONFERENCE IN EARLY FEBRUARY 1977 TO APPROVE GUIDELINES FOR
                            NATIONAL ASSESSMENTS OF SOCIO-ECONOMIC PROBLEMS SOLVABLE BY SCIENCE AND
                            TECHNOLOGY. IN PREPCON, US DEL WILL EXPLAIN US HOSTSHIP OFFER AND SEEK
                            PARTICIPANTS’ SUPPORT.</p>
                        <p>J. UNIDO. UNGA ADOPTED RESOLUTION (104-1(US)-27) REQUESTING INDUSTRIAL
                            DEVELOPMENT BOARD TO CONSIDER, AND UN INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT
                            ORGANIZATION (UNIDO) SECRETARIAT TO STUDY, MEASURES TO INCREASE LDCS’
                            SHARE OF GLOBAL INDUSTRIAL PRODUCTION. WEOS AMENDED RESOLUTION TO
                            INCLUDE UNGA 7TH <gloss target="#t_SS2">SS</gloss> RESOLUTION
                            LIMITATIONS ON GOVERNMENTS’ COMMITMENTS TO INTERFERE IN PRIVATE SECTOR.
                            USG WILL BE ALERT TO MAINTAIN THESE LIMITATIONS IN TERMS OF REFERENCE OF
                            UNIDO CONSULTATIONS ON FERTILIZERS (JANUARY 17-21, 1977) AND IRON AND
                            STEEL (FEBRUARY 7-11, 1977). UNGA ALSO ADOPTED CONSENSUS RESOLUTION
                            RENEWING MANDATE OF COMMITTEE DRAFTING CONSTITUTION (WILL MEET VIENNA,
                            MARCH 7 - APRIL 2) AND CALLED FOR PLENIPOTENTIARY MEETING TO APPROVE
                            CONSTITUTION IN SECOND HALF OF 1977.</p>
                        <p>K. THE INTERNATIONAL FUND FOR AGRICULTURAL DEVELOPMENT (IFAD), PROPOSED
                            BY <gloss target="#t_OPEC1">OPEC</gloss> MEMBERS AT WORLD FOOD
                            CONFERENCE AND GIVEN MAJOR SUPPORT BY SECRETARY AT UNGA 7TH SS ATTAINED
                            DURING THIS SESSION ITS FULL 1 BILLION DOLLAR FUNDING(OECD MEMBERS-56
                            PERCENT, OPEC MEMBERS-43 PERCENT, LDCS-1 PERCENT). THE G-77 WERE DEEPLY
                            DIVIDED OVER NORWEGIAN/VENEZUELA PROPOSAL TO TRANSFER THEIR $19.89
                            MILLION CONTRIBUTIONS FROM THE FUND FOR MOST SERIOUSLY AFFECTED NATIONS
                            TO IFAD WHICH WAS ADOPTED BY 52(US)-11-57. </p>
                        <p>7. POLITICAL ISSUES. THE MOST DIFFICULT OF THESE WERE MIDDLE EAST AND
                            SOUTHERN AFRICA. DEVELOPING COUNTRIES GAVE GREAT IMPORTANCE TO THESE AND
                            MAINTAINED CLOSE SOLIDARITY ON THEM. ON OTHER POLITICAL ISSUES LDCS WERE
                            CONSIDERABLY MORE OPEN TO ARGUMENT AND IN CONFLICT WITH ONE ANOTHER.
                            THIS WAS ESPECIALLY TRUE OF DISARMAMENT AND OUTER SPACE ISSUES.</p>
                        <p>A. GUAM. A RESOLUTION CONDEMNING US BASES ON GUAM WAS ADOPTED 60-21-42
                            WITH 23 ABSENCES, MANY OF THEM DELIBERATE, RESULTING IN A MINORITY
                            RESOLUTION. VIGOROUS LOBBYING SIGNIFICANTLY REDUCED THE NUMBER OF
                            AFFIRMATIVE VOTES FROM LAST YEAR AND INCREASED THE NUMBER OF
                            ABSTENTIONS.</p>
                        <p>B. SOUTHERN AFRICAN ISSUES. 31ST UNGA REFLECTED LAST SIX MONTHS’ INTENSE
                            DIPLOMATIC ACTIVITY IN SOUTHERN AFRICA. TO EMPHASIZE INCREASED
                            INTERNATIONAL AWARENESS, AFRICAN GROUP REQUESTED THAT THE ITEM ON
                            APARTHEID BE CONSIDERED ONLY IN PLENARY. THE GA LATER PERMITTED
                            REPRESENTATIVES OF TWO SOUTH AFRICAN LIBERATION MOVEMENTS TO ADDRESS
                            PLENARY, A PRIVILEGE USUALLY RESERVED FOR MEMBER NATIONS.</p>
                        <p>-- SOUTH AFRICA: ELEVEN RESOLUTIONS WERE ADOPTED: US OPPOSED FIVE,
                            ABSTAINED ON FOUR, AND JOINED CONSENSUS ON TWO. THE MOST IMPORTANT
                            RESOLUTIONS CONDEMNED RELATIONS BETWEEN ISRAEL AND SOUTH AFRICA,
                            CONDEMNED CREATION OF TRANSKEI, AND ENDORSED ARMED STRUGGLE TO LIBERATE
                            SOUTH AFRICA. ONE OF THESE, OPPOSED BY THE US, CALLED ON SECURITY
                            COUNCIL TO IMPOSE ARMS EMBARGO AGAINST SOUTH AFRICA. WE NOW EXPECT THE
                            SC TO MEET EARLY NEXT YEAR TO CONSIDER BOTH A MANDATORY ARMS EMBARGO AND
                            THE PROHIBITION OF FURTHER INVESTMENT IN SOUTH AFRICA.</p>
                        <p>-- NAMIBIA: OF EIGHT RESOLUTIONS THE US OPPOSED ONE, ABSTAINED ON FIVE,
                            AND JOINED A CONSENSUS ON TWO. MOST OF THESE, AND THE DEBATE, ENDORSED
                                <gloss target="#t_SWAPO1">SWAPO</gloss> AS ONLY TRUE REPRESENTATIVE
                            OF NAMIBIA PEOPLE AND IMPLICITLY AS ONLY NAMIBIAN GROUP QUALIFIED TO
                            NEGOTIATE WITH SOUTH AFRICA. THE DEBATE REPEATEDLY CONDEMNED THE
                            TRUNHALLE CONSTITUTIONAL CONFERENCE. THE FOURTH COMMITTEE REFUSED TO
                            HEAR THE REPRESENTATIVE OF NAMIBIAN CHIEF KAPUUO.</p>
                        <p>-- RHODESIA: AFTER WAITING FOR DEVELOPMENTS IN THE GENEVA CONFERENCE, THE
                            UNGA FINALLY ADOPTED TWO RESOLUTIONS, ONE WHICH EXPRESSED HOPE GENEVA
                            CONFERENCE WOULD SUCCEED, AND A SANCTIONS RESOLUTION CONDEMNING THE US
                            FOR BYRD AMENDMENT IMPORTS. THE OMNIBUS RESOLUTION WAS ADOPTED BY
                            CONSENSUS DESPITE HARD RADICAL AFRICAN FIGHT TO REMOVE ANY POSITIVE
                            MENTION OF GENEVA CONFERENCE. THE SANCTIONS RESOLUTION WAS ADOPTED
                            121-0-7(US). IN EXPLANATION OF VOTE US OBJECTED TO BEING SINGLED OUT FOR
                            CRITICISM WHILE OTHERS WITH MORE EXTENSIVE RHODESIA TRADE WERE
                            IGNORED.</p>
                        <p>C. ARAB-ISRAEL ISSUES. THE CURRENT ARAB PEACE OFFENSIVE DOMINATED 31ST
                            UNGA’S MIDDLE EAST DELIBERATIONS, AND HEAVILY INFLUENCED CONCURRENT
                            SECURITY COUNCIL DEBATES. IN NOVEMBER, A COUNCIL CONSENSUS STATEMENT ON
                            THE OCCUPIED TERRITORIES, INTER ALIA, EXPRESSED CONCERN OVER ISRAEL’S
                            CONTINUED OCCUPATION, ASKED ISRAEL TO FACILITATE RETURN OF THE REFUGEES,
                            REAFFIRMED APPLICABILITY OF THE FOURTH GENEVA CONVENTION, AND DECLARED
                            INVALID ISRAELI CHANGES IN STATUS OF JERUSALEM. THE US SUPPORTED THE
                            CONSENSUS STATEMENT WHICH DID NOT GO BEYOND POSITIONS WE HAD TAKEN IN
                            THE PAST. THE GA ADOPTED IN DECEMBER A RESOLUTION CALLING FOR EARLY
                            RECONVENING OF THE GENEVA CONFERENCE AND FOR SYG TO REPORT ON THIS. THE
                            US (WITH ISRAEL) OPPOSED BECAUSE OF TIMETABLES RESOLUTION IMPOSED ON THE
                            NEW US ADMINISTRATION. IN BOTH CASES, THE ARABS ATTEMPTED TO FORCE THE
                            PACE OF NEGOTIATIONS ON TERMS FAVORABLE TO THEMSELVES, WHILE FURTHER
                            ISOLATING ISRAEL.</p>
                        <p>OUR OVERALL OBJECTIVES IN THE ARAB-ISRAEL CONFLICT DICTATED
                            DAMAGE-LIMITING STRATEGY IN 31ST UNGA. WE RECOGNIZED THAT THE UN HAS
                            ROLE BOTH IN MIDDLE EAST PEACEKEEPING, AND IN SECURITY COUNCIL
                            RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE FRAMEWORK OF NEGOTIATIONS. HOWEVER, WE BELIEVE
                            THAT ONE-SIDED UNGA EFFORTS TO PRESCRIBE NATURE AND TIME-TABLE OF A
                            SETTLEMENT MAINLY HARDEN PARTIES’ POSITIONS AND DEFLECT SERIOUS EFFORTS
                            TO NEGOTIATE SETTLEMENT. THUS 31ST UNGA’S CONSIDERATION OF MIDDLE EAST
                            WAS IN OUR VIEW NEGATIVE; HOWEVER, DAMAGE DONE WAS MUCH LESS THAN
                            RESULTED FROM THE <gloss target="#t_PLO1">PLO</gloss> SPECTACULARS AND
                            ZIONISM/RACISM BATTLES OF PAST ASSEMBLIES.</p>
                        <p>D. ZIONISM/RACISM. THE ZIONISM/RACISM ISSUE, WHICH CAUSED SUCH NOTORIETY
                            WHEN ADOPTED AS 30TH GA’S RESOLUTION 3379 IN CONNECTION WITH THE DECADE
                            TO COMBAT RACISM, WAS GENERALLY MUTED THIS YEAR. RESOLUTION 3379 STILL
                            STANDS. HOWEVER, BEGINNING AT THE SPRING SESSION OF ECOSOC, SOME
                            MODERATE AFRICANS LED BY ECOSOC PRESIDENT AKE OF IVORY COAST, SOUGHT
                            SUCCESSFULLY TO DEFUSE THE ISSUE IN ECOSOC AND THE GA BY AVOIDING
                            EXPLICIT CITATION OF RESOLUTION 3379 IN ACTIONS ON THE DECADE.</p>
                        <p>TWO RESOLUTIONS ON THE DECADE CONTAINING NO DIRECT REFERENCES TO
                            ZIONISM/RACISM WERE ADOPTED IN THE GA. A NUMBER OF WESTERN EUROPEAN
                            COUNTRIES, AND SOME OTHERS, ABSTAINED. THE US HAS A CONSISTENT POLICY OF
                            NOT PARTICIPATING IN VOTES ON DECADE RESOLUTIONS UNTIL THE LINK BETWEEN
                            THE DECADE AND RESOLUTION 3379 IS BROKEN BY A RESOLUTION WHICH
                            ESTABLISHES AS RELEVANT TO THE DECADE ONLY THOSE GA RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED
                            BY CONSENSUS. ACCORDINGLY US DID NOT VOTE ON THE TWO 31ST UNGA DECADE
                            RESOLUTIONS, BUT STATED ITS REGRET THAT THE DECADE’S ORIGINAL CONSENSUS
                            HAD BEEN BROKEN BY RESOLUTION 3379, AND ITS HOPE THAT DECADE’S ORIGINAL
                            OBJECTIVES COULD BE RESTORED.</p>
                        <p>E. CYPRUS. UNGA CONSIDERATION OF CYPRUS WAS GENERALLY AS IN PREVIOUS
                            SESSIONS. A NON-ALIGNED RESOLUTION WAS ADOPTED BY 94(GREECE,
                            CYPRUS)-1(TURKEY)-27(US). IT WAS SUBSTANTIVELY SIMILAR TO, AND CALLED
                            FOR IMPLEMENTATION OF, PREVIOUS GA AND SC CYPRUS RESOLUTIONS. TURKISH
                            CYPRIOT REPRESENTATIVES DID NOT PARTICIPATE IN PRELIMINARY SPECIAL
                            POLITICAL COMMITTEE (<gloss target="#t_SPC2">SPC</gloss>) DEBATE ON
                            CYPRUS AS A PROTEST OF GA’S REJECTION OF TURKEY’S REQUEST THAT ENTIRE
                            DEBATE BE HELD EITHER IN PLENARY OR SPC. TURKEY UNDERSCORED IMPORTANCE
                            IT GAVE TO EQUAL STATUS FOR TURK AND GREEK CYPRIOTS BY MOVING GENERAL
                            COMMITTEE RECONSIDER ALLOCATION OF CYPRUS DEBATE. MOTION LOST
                            23(US)-70-23.</p>
                        <p>GA TREATMENT OF CYPRUS GENERALLY SERVED US OBJECTIVE OF AVOIDING BOTH
                            HARDENING OF POSITIONS, AND ADDITIONAL OBSTACLES TO SUBSTANTIVE
                            NEGOTIATIONS.</p>
                        <p>F. DISARMAMENT. THE 31ST UNGA ADOPTED 21 DISARMAMENT RELATED RESOLUTIONS.
                            MOST REITERATED PREVIOUS UNGA ACTIONS. ELEVEN DEALT WITH NUCLEAR ISSUES
                            SUCH AS NUCLEAR TESTING, NUCLEAR-WEAPON-FREE ZONES, NON-PROLIFERATION,
                            AND NUCLEAR NON-USE ASSURANCES. OF THESE, US OPPOSED A RESOLUTION ON
                            SALT, AND ABSTAINED ON TWO COMPREHENSIVE TEST BAN RESOLUTIONS (SPONSORED
                            BY USSR AND NEW ZEALAND, RESPECTIVELY), USSR RESOLUTION ON WEAPONS OF
                            MASS DESTRUCTION, SRI LANKA’S INDIAN OCEAN PEACE ZONE RESOLUTION, AND
                            PAKISTANI RESOLUTIONS ON SOUTH ASIAN NUCLEAR-WEAPON-FREE ZONE AND
                            SECURITY ASSURANCES.</p>
                        <p>THE TWO MOST SIGNIFICANT DISARMAMENT RESOLUTIONS WERE US-SOVIET-FINNISH
                            RESOLUTION OPENING ENVIRONMENTAL MODIFICATION CONVENTION (<gloss target="#t_ENMOD1">ENMOD</gloss>) FOR SIGNATURE AND RATIFICATION,
                            AND YUGOSLAV RESOLUTION CALLING FOR UNGA SPECIAL SESSION ON DISARMAMENT
                                (<gloss target="#t_SSOD1">SSOD</gloss>) IN 1978. THERE WILL BE A
                            PREPARATORY CONFERENCE FOR SSOD DURING 1977. THE ENMOD RESOLUTION
                            REQUIRED CLOSE CO-ORDINATION BETWEEN US AND USSR COUNTRIES IN SUPPORT OF
                            EXTENSIVE LOBBYING OF OTHER DELEGATIONS. THIS COLLABORATION REVIVED
                            COMPLAINTS BY NON-ALIGNED AND OTHER LDCS THAT SUPERPOWERS DOMINATE AND
                            PREEMPT GA’S WORK ON MOST IMPORTANT DISARMAMENT ISSUES. THEY ACCORDINGLY
                            STRONGLY SUPPORTED SSOD IN WHICH THEY WILL BE IN EQUALITY WITH
                            SUPERPOWERS. OTHERWISE, DISARMAMENT DEBATE AT THE 1976 UNGA MET BASIC US
                            INTERESTS: DEBATE WAS RESTRAINED, SOVIET PROPAGANDA-ORIENTED EFFORTS
                            SUCH AS THE WORLD DISARMAMENT CONFERENCE WERE REJECTED, COORDINATION
                            WITH OUR ALLIES INCREASED, AND RESOLUTIONS IN WHICH WE HAD PARTICULAR
                            INTEREST, SUCH AS ENMOD, <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss>, CHEMICAL
                            WARFARE AND MILITARY EXPENDITURE LIMITATIONS, RECEIVED BROAD
                            SUPPORT.</p>
                        <p>8. ADMINISTRATIVE AND BUDGETARY ISSUES. A. IN LINE WITH US OBJECTIVES,
                            JOINT INSPECTION UNIT WAS CONTINUED WITH AUTHORIZATION FOR IT TO ASSIST
                            EXTERNAL EVALUATION OF UN SYSTEM ACTIVITIES. (THIS IS IMPORTANT ADVANCE
                            TOWARD ESTABLISHMENT OF EFFECTIVE, INDEPENDENT UN EXTERNAL EVALUATION IN
                            WHICH CONGRESS HAS CONSIDERABLE INTEREST.) ALSO IMPORTANT TO US
                            INTERESTS WAS RELATIVELY NONCONTROVERSIAL EXTENSION OF FUNDING FOR
                            MIDDLE EAST PEACEKEEPING FORCES. ASSEMBLY ENDORSEMENT OF RECOMMENDATIONS
                            OF INTERNATIONAL CIVIL SERVICE COMMISSION WAS GOOD START TOWARD
                            RATIONALIZING UN SYSTEM SALARY STRUCTURE, ALTHOUGH WE REMAIN CONCERNED
                            ABOUT HIGH SALARY LEVELS. ALSO POSITIVE WAS SOME PROGRESS TOWARD
                            ESTABLISHMENT OF VIENNA AS A THIRD UN CITY WHICH US SUPPORTS.</p>
                        <p>B. MAJOR ITEM ON NEGATIVE SIDE, WAS SIZEABLE ADDITION TO BUDGET LEVEL
                            SUPPOSEDLY ADOPTED LAST YEAR FOR FULL 1976-77 BIENNIUM. WE GENERALLY
                            FAILED TO COMPENSATE FOR NEW OR EXPANDED PROGRAMS BY REDUCING OR
                            ABOLISHING CURRENT LOWER PRIORITY PROGRAMS. DEVELOPING COUNTRIES PRESSED
                            GENERALLY TO MAXIMIZE UN FUNDING FOR EXCLUSIVELY LDC ACTIVITIES. ON
                            LATTER, WE DID PREVENT PROVISION ENCOURAGING UN REGULAR BUDGET FUNDING
                            OF UN CONFERENCES IN DEVELOPING COUNTRIES AWAY FROM UN SITES. HOWEVER,
                            WE FAILED PREVENT UNCTAD SECRETARIAT FROM ASSISTING MEETINGS SOLELY OPEN
                            AND OF INTEREST TO LDCS. TRAVEL AND SUBSISTENCE EXPENSES OF GOVERNMENT
                            REPRESENTATIVES ON ECOSOC’S COMMITTEE FOR PROGRAM AND CO-ORDINATION WERE
                            ALSO FUNDED OVER US OPPOSITION. THESE SETBACKS FORESHADOW FURTHER LDC
                            EFFORTS TO INCREASE FUTURE UN REGULAR BUDGET FUNDING OF ACTIVITIES
                            DESIGNED FOR LDCS EXCLUSIVELY.</p>
                        <p>C. GREAT CONTROVERSY RESULTED WHEN OPEC MEMBERS RESISTED INCREASES IN
                            THEIR CONTRIBUTIONS REQUIRED BY A PROPOSED NEW SCALE OF ASSESSMENT FOR
                            THE NEXT THREE YEARS (THERE WAS NO CHALLENGE TO 25 PERCENT CEILING WHICH
                            IS US ASSESSMENT RATE). ULTIMATELY, GA ADOPTED PROPOSED ASSESSMENT SCALE
                            FOR 1977 ONLY AND REMANDED THE DISPUTES OVER CRITERIA TO SPRING SESSION
                            OF ENLARGED COMMITTEE ON CONTRIBUTIONS. EXTENSION FOR ANOTHER YEAR OF AD
                            HOC COMMITTEE ON RESTRUCTURING OF UN ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL SECTORS
                            DELAYED, BUT LEFT OPEN, ACHIEVEMENT OF A US OBJECTIVE HIGHLIGHTED IN
                            SECRETARY’S 7TH SPECIAL SESSION ADDRESS.</p>
                        <p>9. HUMAN RIGHTS. A. EXTENSIVE DEBATE ON HUMAN RIGHTS WAS IN MANY RESPECTS
                            DISAPPOINTING. IT PROVIDED NO NEW PRACTICAL AND EVENHANDED STEPS FOR
                            PARTICULAR HUMAN RIGHTS SITUATIONS OR IMPROVING UN’S HUMAN RIGHTS
                            MACHINERY. GOVERNOR <persName corresp="#p_SWW2">SCRANTON</persName> MADE
                            A HARD-HITTING, DETAILED SPEECH DISCUSSING THESE FAILURES.</p>
                        <p>B. A RESOLUTION CRITICIZING HUMAN RIGHTS SITUATION IN CHILE WAS ADOPTED
                            BY A LARGE MAJORITY. THE US ABSTAINED BECAUSE RESOLUTION IGNORED, EXCEPT
                            FOR VERY OBSCURE PREAMBLE REFERENCE, RECENT RELEASE OF POLITICAL
                            PRISONERS THERE, AND BECAUSE IT THREATENED FUTURE ECONOMIC SANCTIONS. OF
                            NUMEROUS RESOLUTIONS ON SOUTHERN AFRICA, MANY INVOLVED HUMAN RIGHTS
                            QUESTIONS. THE ONLY FOLLOW-UP TO LAST YEAR’S DECLARATION CONDEMNING
                            TORTURE WAS PROCEDURAL RESOLUTION ENDORSING WORK UNDERWAY TO IMPLEMENT
                            IT. US SUPPORTED SWEDISH PROPOSAL TO SAFEGUARD HUMAN RIGHTS OF POLITICAL
                            PRISONERS WHICH WAS SIDETRACKED BY BYELORUSSIAN COUNTER PROPOSAL. BOTH
                            WERE DEFERRED TO 1977. </p>
                        <p>C. THE US CONSIDERED A NUMBER OF HUMAN RIGHTS INITIATIVES. SUCH AS
                            IMPROVEMENT IN PROCEDURES FOR HANDLING PRIVATE COMPLAINTS OF VIOLATIONS
                            AND A GA SPECIAL COMMITTEE TO STUDY NATURE AND EXTENT OF TORTURE. WE
                            CONSULTED CLOSELY WITH FRIENDLY COUNTRIES TO OBTAIN SUPPORT. THE
                            REACTION WAS UNENTHUSIASTIC AND WE CONCLUDE IT WOULD BE USELESS, OR
                            WORSE, TO PUSH SUCH PROPOSALS WITHOUT WIDE AND ENTHUSIASTIC BACKING. WE
                            MAY SEEK SUCH SUPPORT BEFORE 32ND UNGA.</p>
                        <p>10. INTERNATIONAL TERRORISM. THE GA PROGRESSED HERE IN ADOPTING BY
                            CONSENSUS AN FRG RESOLUTION ESTABLISHING A 35-NATION COMMITTEE TO DRAFT
                            AN INTERNATIONAL CONVENTION AGAINST THE TAKING OF HOSTAGES. THE
                            RESOLUTION IS LESS EXPLICIT IN CONDEMNING HOSTAGE-TAKING THAN WE, THE
                            FRG, AND CO-SPONSORS, WOULD LIKE. IN NEGOTIATIONS THE FRG DID
                            SUCCESSFULLY AVOID A DISTORTING AMENDMENT BY LIBYA LIMITING DRAFT
                            CONVENTION TO (QUOTE) INNOCENT (UNQUOTE) HOSTAGES. HOWEVER, SOME ARAB
                            AND OTHER STATES (E.G., CZECHOSLOVAKIA, KENYA, NIGERIA, TANZANIA) DID
                            NOT RESPECT EFFORTS IN DEBATE ON FRG RESOLUTION TO KEEP HOSTAGE ISSUE
                            SEPARATE FROM BROADER ISSUE OF INTERNATIONAL TERRORISM AND ITS
                            UNDERLYING POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC CAUSES.</p>
                        <p>11. ASSESSMENT. A. OVERALL, 31ST UNGA SHOWED UNUSUAL REALISM, PRAGMATISM,
                            AND CONSTRUCTIVE EFFORTS TO DEAL WITH ISSUES IN RESOLUTIONS. UNTIL
                            ANOTHER SESSION, HOWEVER, WE WILL NOT KNOW WHETHER THIS ONE WAS A
                            TURNING POINT OR A LULL. CYNICAL OR IMPATIENT MISUSE OF THE GA FOR
                            RHETORICAL POSTURING AND PROCLAIMING OF NON-NEGOTIABLE STATEMENTS OF
                            PRINCIPLE, RATHER THAN AS A FORUM CONSTRUCTIVELY ADDRESSING ISSUES THAT
                            REQUIRE SERIOUS ATTENTION, IS STILL FAR TOO PREVALENT. THIS MISUSE MAY
                            WELL AGAIN BECOME PREEMINENT IF KOREA AND OTHER DIVISIVE POLITICAL
                            ISSUES RETURN TO JOIN MIDDLE EAST QUESTION AND SOUTHERN AFRICAN ISSUES
                            IN THE GA, OR IF DISSATISFACTION WITH PROGRESS ON INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC
                            ISSUES CONTINUES TO MOUNT.</p>
                        <p>B. WE BALANCE THIS CONTINUING CONCERN WITH SOME MODEST HOPE. WALDHEIM’S
                            RE-ELECTION FOR A FULL FIVE YEARS PROVIDES CONTINUITY WITH A SYG WITH
                            WHOM WE KNOW WE CAN WORK, AND STRENGTHENS HIM IN HIS ROLE IN IMPORTANT
                            INTERNATIONAL NEGOTIATIONS (E.G., CYPRUS) AHEAD. THE RELATIONS OF OTHER
                            DELEGATIONS WITH OUR OWN TESTIFIED TO THE EFFECTIVE LEADERSHIP ROLE OF
                            THE US; INDEED, DEVELOPED COUNTRIES IN PARTICULAR CONTINUED TO PRESS US
                            TO EXERCISE THIS ROLE MORE FREELY. WE WERE IN A SMALL MINORITY IN
                            OPPOSITION ON A NUMBER OF ISSUES. NONETHELESS, THE GA, AS A FORUM FOR
                            THE COLLECTIVE OPINION OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, WAS CLEARLY
                            TELLING US AGAIN THAT IT EXPECTS US TO BE A LEADER WITHIN AND OUTSIDE
                            THE UN ON ECONOMIC ISSUES, ON SOUTHERN AFRICA, AND ON THE MIDDLE EAST.
                            FINALLY, THIS UNUSUALLY SOBER AND BUSINESSLIKE GA SESSION HAS UNDERLINED
                            FOR US THAT AS A LEADER AND INDISPENSABLE PARTICIPANT IN INTERNATIONAL
                            EVENTS, WE MUST CAREFULLY DISTINGUISH LEGITIMATE EFFORTS IN THE GA TO
                            PERSUADE AND PRESSURE US, HOWEVER UNPLEASANT, FROM DESTRUCTIVE REFUSALS
                            TO NEGOTIATE.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RCW2">ROBINSON</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>NOTE BY OC/T: POUCHED TO ADDRESSEES.</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>