<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>78. Telegram 177759 From the Department of State to the Mission to the United
                    Nations and Secretary of State Kissinger, July 29, 1975, 0033Z.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d78</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">78</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-07-28T19:33:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-07-28T19:33:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077241"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Linkage</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-07-28T19:33:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-07-28T19:33:00-05:00" n="78"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d78">
                <head>78. Telegram 177759 From the Department of State to the Mission to the United
                    Nations and Secretary of State Kissinger, July 29, 1975, 0033Z.<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d78fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central
                        Foreign Policy Files. Secret; Immediate. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BJAJ1">Baker</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MJM1"
                            >Montgomery</persName>; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_SRF3"
                            >Stowe</persName> and in <gloss target="#t_EURSOV1">EUR/SOV</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_LUNA1"
                            >L/UNA</gloss>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_BWB1"
                            >Buffum</persName>. Repeated Immediate to London, Paris, Seoul, Tokyo,
                        Rome, and Beijing. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        accompanied <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> on a European trip
                        which included stays in Warsaw (July 28–29), Helsinki (July 29–August 2),
                        Bucharest (August 2–3), and Belgrade (August 3–4). On August 11 the United
                        States vetoed the proposed admission to the United Nations of the North and
                        South Vietnamese governments. On September 19 the United Nations General
                        Assembly voted 123–0 (with 8 abstentions, including the United States)
                        requesting that the Security Council revisit the issue of admission of both
                        Vietnam governments. On September 30, the United States again vetoed in the
                        Security Council admission of the Hanoi and Saigon governments.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d78fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_IRS1">Ingersoll</persName> forwarded <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s rationale for opposing the
                        entry of the North and South Vietnamese governments into the United
                        Nations.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-07-29T00:33:00+00:00">July 29, 1975,
                        0033Z</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>TELEGRAM<lb/>Department of State<lb/>177759</p>
                <p>O 290033Z JUL 75</p>
                <p>FM SECSTATE WASHDC<lb/>TO <gloss target="#t_USDEL1">USDEL</gloss> SECRETARY
                    IMMEDIATE<lb/>USMISSION <lb/>
                    <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> NEW YORK IMMEDIATE 3628/3629<lb/>INFO
                    AMEMBASSY LONDON IMMEDIATE<lb/>AMEMBASSY PARIS IMMEDIATE<lb/>AMEMBASSY SEOUL
                    IMMEDIATE<lb/>AMEMBASSY TOKYO IMMEDIATE<lb/>AMEMBASSY ROME IMMEDIATE<lb/>USLO
                    PEKING IMMEDIATE</p>
                <p>STATE 177759<lb/>CORRECTED COPY (OMISSION LINE 3 <gloss target="#t_Para1"
                        >PARA</gloss> 14)</p>
                <p>E.O. 11652:GDS<lb/>TAGS: PFOR, <gloss target="#t_UNSC1">UNSC</gloss>, <gloss
                        target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>, VN, KS</p>
                <p>SUBJECT: VIETNAMESE APPLICATIONS FOR <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    MEMBERSHIP</p>
                <p>FOR AMBASSADOR <persName corresp="#p_MDP1">MOYNIHAN</persName> AND ASSISTANT
                    SECRETARY <persName corresp="#p_HAA4">HARTMAN</persName>
                </p>
                <p>1. SECRETARY HAS DECIDED THAT WE SHOULD BE PREPARED TO VETO THE VIETNAMS
                    ADMISSION, IF NECESSARY, ON GROUNDS WHICH WILL CLEARLY BE BASED ON LINKAGE TO A
                    RENEWED <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> APPLICATION BUT TO AVOID ARGUING THE
                    VIETNAMS’ QUALIFICATIONS AND USE THIS POSITION TO URGE THE VIETNAMS NOT TO PRESS
                    THEIR APPLICATIONS. MOST DESIRABLE OUTCOME, OF COURSE, WOULD BE ADMISSION TO UN
                    OF ROC (AND NORTH KOREA ALSO IF IT DECIDED TO APPLY) ALONG WITH VIETNAMS AND
                    THIS SHOULD BE KEPT IN MIND IN DECIDING TACTICS. IN VIEW STRONG LIKELIHOOD THAT
                    NORTH KOREA WILL NOT CHANGE ITS ATTITUDE SOON AND THAT <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> AND CHINA WILL DEFER TO NORTH KOREA AND OPPOSE ENTRY OF ROK,
                    AT MINIMUM WE WANT TO BRING ABOUT SITUATION IN WHICH VIETNAM APPLICATIONS ARE
                    NOT PRESSED TO VOTE.</p>
                <p>2. ASSISTANT SECRETARY <persName corresp="#p_BWB1">BUFFUM</persName> IS INFORMING
                    ROK AMBASSADOR JULY 28 OF ABOVE AND OF DESIRABILITY OF ROK RENEWING ITS
                    APPLICATION AT ONCE. WE DO NOT BELIEVE ROK SHOULD PRESS FOR <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> CONSIDERATION, HOWEVER, UNLESS SC WERE TO BE
                    CONVENED TO CONSIDER VIETNAMESE APPLICATIONS.</p>
                <p>3. WE ALSO INTEND TO CONVEY TO SOVIETS IN NEW YORK OUR VIEW THAT APPLICATION OF
                    TWO VIETNAMS SHOULD NOT BE CONSIDERED APART FROM THAT OF ROK AND THAT NOW IS
                    TIME TO FINALLY RESOLVE MATTER OF DIVIDED COUNTRIES BY ADMISSION OF VIETNAMS,
                    ROK AND, IF IT WISHES, THE <gloss target="#t_DPRK1">DPRK</gloss>. QUESTION OF
                    APPROACHES TO <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> WILL BE ADDRESSED SEPARATELY
                    AND WE DO NOT INTEND TO APPROACH EITHER OF THE VIETNAMS ON THIS ISSUE IN THE
                    NEAR TERM, LEAVING TO USSR COMMUNICATION OF OUR VIEWS TO VIETNAM.</p>
                <p>4. WE ALSO RECOGNIZE THAT IT NECESSARY NOT ONLY THAT USSR AND PRC NOT OPPOSE
                    KOREAN MEMBERSHIP IN SECURITY COUNCIL BUT THAT THEY AGREE NOT TO LOBBY TO BLOCK
                    ROK APPLICATION (OUR PRESENT READING IS THAT WE HAVE ONLY 7 CERTAIN VOTES ON
                    SECURITY COUNCIL AND WOULD HAVE TO ATTRACT TWO MORE EVEN WITHOUT SOVIET AND
                    CHINESE VETOES).</p>
                <p>5. WHEN AND IF SECRETARY APPROVES OF THIS COURSE, USUN SHOULD ARRANGE TO CONTACT
                        <gloss target="#t_SMUN1">SMUN</gloss> AT <gloss target="#t_DEP1">DEP</gloss>
                    PERM REP LEVEL AND CONVEY US VIEWS ON VIETNAMESE AND KOREAN APPLICATIONS AS
                    OUTLINED IN THE FOLLOWING PARAGRAPHS.</p>
                <p>6. SMUN DEP REP SHOULD BE REMINDED THAT EARLIER THIS YEAR SOVIET EMBASSY IN
                    WASHINGTON, AT THE REQUEST OF HANOI, ASKED IF THE <gloss target="#t_USG1"
                        >USG</gloss> WOULD SUPPORT THE ADMISSION OF NORTH AND SOUTH VIETNAM INTO THE
                    UN. WE ASKED THEN IF THE SOVIET GOVERNMENT WOULD BE WILLING TO FACILITATE SOUTH
                    KOREA’S APPLICATION, JUST AS WE WOULD CONCUR IN NORTH KOREA’S APPLICATION WERE
                    THEY TO APPLY. USG HAS GIVEN FURTHER CAREFUL STUDY SINCE THEN TO THE QUESTION OF
                    MEMBERSHIP IN THE UN FOR THE TWO VIETNAMS AND BELIEVES THAT AT THE PRESENT TIME
                    IT WOULD NOT BE IN THE INTERESTS OF THE ORGANIZATION TO CONSIDER THESE
                    APPLICATIONS UNTIL THE QUESTION OF UN MEMBERSHIP FOR ALL PRESENTLY DIVIDED
                    STATES CAN BE RESOLVED.</p>
                <p>7. FAILURE TO STRIVE FOR AND MAINTAIN FULL PARTICIPATION IN THE UN NOT HELPFUL TO
                    ACHIEVING THE REDUCTION OF TENSIONS IN WHICH BOTH US AND USSR ARE
                    INTERESTED.</p>
                <p>8. THE COMBINATION OF THE VIETNAMS’ RECENT APPLICATION AND SOUTH KOREA’S
                    LONG-STANDING APPLICATION GIVES THE UN THE OPPORTUNITY TO BRING A DEGREE OF
                    NORMALITY AND STABILITY TO BOTH OF THESE AREAS, THE SCENE OF MUCH DISRUPTIVE
                    INTERNATIONAL TENSION. WE BELIEVE THE ADMISSION OF ALL OF THESE APPLICANTS WOULD
                    CONTRIBUTE TO THE REDUCTION OF INTERNATIONAL TENSIONS AND, TOGETHER WITH THE
                    ANTICIPATED ADMISSION OF MOZAMBIQUE, ANGOLA, AND OTHERS, VIRTUALLY COMPLETE THE
                    PROCESS OF UNIVERSAL ASSOCIATION WITH THE UN. BOTH OUR COUNTRIES SHARE AN
                    INTEREST IN REDUCTIONS OF TENSION AND FULL PARTICIPATION OF STATES IN THE UN AND
                    WE HOPE THE SOVIET GOVERNMENT WOULD FACILITATE ALL OF THESE APPLICATIONS.</p>
                <p>9. YOU SHOULD ALSO POINT OUT THAT THE INCREASINGLY SKEPTICAL PUBLIC OPINION IN
                    THIS COUNTRY TOWARD THE UN COULD BE NEGATIVELY AFFECTED BY THE SPECTACLE OF THE
                    ADMISSION OF TWO VIETNAMS WHILE SOUTH KOREA IS EXCLUDED. FURTHERMORE, CRITICS OF
                    DETENTE WOULD FIND A FURTHER RATIONALE FOR ARGUING THAT IT WAS A ONE WAY STREET,
                    ESPECIALLY IF IT BECAME CLEAR THAT THE SOVIET POSITION WAS INSTRUMENTAL IN
                    CAUSING THE SECURITY COUNCIL TO FAIL TO CONSIDER AND ENDORSE SOUTH KOREAN
                    MEMBERSHIP. SOVIETS SHOULD UNDERSTAND PARTICULARLY WELL THE ADVERSE PUBLIC
                    REACTION WHICH WOULD BE GENERATED IN THE US BY SUCH DISCRIMINATION AGAINST SOUTH
                    KOREA.</p>
                <p>10. ADMISSION OF BOTH VIETNAMS IN THE FACE OF CONTINUED EXCLUSION OF THE REPUBLIC
                    OF KOREA WOULD IN FACT CREATE SUCH ADDED DIFFICULTIES FOR THE CONTINUED SUPPORT
                    OF THE UN IN THE US AND HAVE SUCH A NEGATIVE IMPACT ON THE PROSPECTS FOR FUTURE
                    STABILITY ON THE KOREAN PENINSULA THAT WE WOULD BE PREPARED TO USE OUR VETO TO
                    KEEP IT FROM HAPPENING. WE MUCH PREFER ENTRY OF ALL DIVIDED COUNTRIES, WITHOUT
                    PREJUDICE TO FUTURE UNIFICATION. WE BELIEVE NOW IS THE TIME TO ACT.</p>
                <p>11. WHILE THE SOUTH KOREANS ARE RENEWING THEIR APPLICATION FOR ADMISSION TO THE
                    UN, WE DO NOT BELIEVE THAT THEY WOULD PRESS SC CONSIDERATION UNLESS SC WERE TO
                    BE CONVENED TO CONSIDER VIETNAMESE APPLICATIONS. THEREFORE, IF THE SOVIETS ARE
                    UNWILLING AT THIS TIME TO SUPPORT SOUTH KOREA’S APPLICATION, WE BELIEVE THAT
                    BEST SOLUTION WOULD BE FOR TWO VIETNAMS TO LEAVE THEIR APPLICATIONS STANDING BUT
                    NOT PRESS FOR EARLY CONSIDERATION. MEANTIME, WE WOULD EXPECT TO CONTINUE
                    CONSULTATION WITH USSR AND OTHER PERMANENT SC MEMBERS WITH A VIEW TO REACHING
                    AGREEMENT ON SOLUTION WHICH WILL BRING ALL DIVIDED STATES WHO WISH MEMBERSHIP
                    INTO UN.</p>
                <p>12. SMUN WILL BE AWARE THAT WE HAVE ISSUED VISAS TO <gloss target="#t_PRGSV1"
                        >PRG</gloss> AND NVN OBSERVERS AND HAVE NOT POSED ANY OBJECTION TO THEIR
                    ENTRY OR PARTICIPATION AS OBSERVERS IN THE WORK OF THE UN. WE BELIEVE THAT FOR
                    THESE GOVERNMENTS, AS WAS THE CASE FOR THE TWO GERMAN STATES, THE PRESENCE IN
                    NEW YORK OF THEIR REPRESENTATIVES ON THE SAME BASIS AS THAT OF THE TWO KOREAN
                    STATES CAN BE A USEFUL PRELUDE TO THE INCLUSION OF ALL FOUR STATES.</p>
                <p>13. YOU SHOULD ADD THAT WE WOULD REQUEST THAT THE SOVIETS, SINCE THEY APPROACHED
                    US INITIALLY ON BEHALF OF THE VIETNAMESE, MAKE OUR CONSIDERED VIEWS KNOWN IN
                    FULL TO THE TWO VIETNAMESE GOVERNMENTS, ADDING THAT OUR POSITION IS ONE OF
                    SEEKING TO BRING ADMISSION OF DIVIDED STATES ABOUT IN A CONTEXT CONDUCIVE TO THE
                    MAINTENANCE OF INTERNATIONAL PEACE, ESPECIALLY IN EASTERN ASIA, AND HELPFUL TO
                    THE GOAL OF UNIVERSAL UN MEMBERSHIP. WE HOPE THAT WE WOULD THEREFORE NOT BE
                    PLACED IN CIRCUMSTANCES WHERE WE SHOULD HAVE TO VOTE NEGATIVELY.</p>
                <p>14. USUN, IN CONVEYING FOREGOING FULLY, SHOULD REPORT ANY REACTIONS OR COMMENTS.
                    IN THE UNLIKELY EVENT THAT THE SOVIETS SHOULD CITE THE 1948 <gloss
                        target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> ADVISORY OPINION. YOU MAY COMMENT THAT NEITHER
                    THE USSR NOR THE SECURITY COUNCIL HAVE EXPRESSED SUPPORT FOR THIS OPINION AND
                    THAT, RELUCTANT AS WE ARE TO DEVIATE FROM IT, WE REGARD THE CONSIDERATIONS
                    PRESENTED AS MORE COMPELLING AT THIS MOMENT.</p>
                <p>15. FOR SECRETARY. USUN WILL EXECUTE FOREGOING AS SOON AS YOA APPROVE. WE BELIEVE
                    IT DESIRABLE THAT FOREGOING MESSAGE GET TO VIETNAMESE BEFORE THEIR OBSERVERS
                    SEEK TO SET DATE OF SC MEETING ON THEIR APPLICATIONS SINCE WE WOULD HAVE LITTLE
                    SUPPORT IN SC FOR DELAYING MEETING. RECOMMEND THAT YOU TAKE OPPORTUNITY IN TALKS
                    WITH <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">GROMYKO</persName> TO REFER TO OUR APPROACH TO
                    SMUN SO THAT HE WILL BE AWARE OF IMPORTANCE YOU ATTACH TO MATTER. WE INTEND TO
                    BRIEF <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, FRENCH, JAPANESE AND ITALIAN MISSIONS
                    IN CONFIDENCE ON OUR TALK WITH SOVIETS AND ALSO RECOMMEND TELLING PRC UN MISSION
                    ALTHOUGH WE COULD WAIT UNTIL YOUR MEETING WITH THEM SHOULD YOU PREFER. <persName
                        corresp="#p_IRS1">INGERSOLL</persName>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
