<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-05-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="12" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d12">
                        <head>12. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_ECB1" type="from">Elbrick</persName>) to
                            Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_HCA1" type="to">Herter</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d12fn0">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 751.00/5–2758. Confidential.
                                Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_LMJ1">Looram</persName>, initialed
                                by <persName corresp="#p_ECB1">Elbrick</persName>, and concurred in
                                by the Offices of European Regional Affairs and Northern African
                                Affairs. A handwritten notation on the source text by <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>, dated May 27, reads: “I
                                feel that at present there are so many points in <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>’s thinking and purposes
                                about which we can only speculate with in some cases little of a
                                solid nature to base an opinion.”</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-05-27">May 27, 1958</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Policy Considerations toward a <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de
                                    Gaulle</persName> Government</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0054" n="18" xml:id="pg_18"/>
                        <p>Following up our memorandum to the Secretary, which is attached &amp;
                            copy of which was sent to you estimating the policies of a <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> Government,<note n="1" xml:id="d12fn1">A copy of this memorandum, dated May 19, which
                                summarized the policies of a possible <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> government, is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 751.00/5–1958.</note> I am submitting herewith some
                            suggested U.S. policy considerations with regard to such a
                            government.</p>
                        <p>U.S. relations with <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>
                            will be admittedly difficult; they need not, however, be necessarily
                            restricted to a “holding operation”. We should concentrate, at least in
                            the initial phase, on those objectives which are primary to U.S.
                            interest and/or on which we may have some prospect for success: (1)
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and (2) western solidarity in
                            our relations with the Soviet Union. On North Africa we should maintain
                            a discreet posture; on European integration we should leave exclusively
                            to the Europeans to save what can be saved. In fact, on many issues—even
                            those of direct interest to us—we may have to rely heavily on the
                            Europeans, including the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss>, to try to
                            exercise some salutary influence. <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">De
                                Gaulle</persName> will not last forever and may decide to withdraw
                            from the scene after a limited period of time. It is not impossible,
                            moreover, that he may succeed in resolving some of France’s basic
                            problems, notably Algeria and governmental instability.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">North Africa</hi>: There is some reason to hope that
                                <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> will wish to move
                            toward a liberal, albeit paternalistic, policy both with regard to
                            normalizing relations with Tunisia and Morocco and to resolving the
                            Algeria issue. Depending on the circumstances of his return to power,
                            even he may have to move cautiously on this front. Without appearing to
                            abandon the Tunisians and Moroccans to France, we should give <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> every chance to succeed. He
                            will be most suspicious of U.S. interference in this sphere. Any such
                            indication could well have the result of diverting him from a liberal
                            policy and strengthen those forces on the Right who will be attempting
                            to do just this. Moreover, nothing would serve more than this to
                            undercut our efforts to keep <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            together.</p>
                        <p>At the outset of <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>’s
                            taking over, we should make our position on North Africa quite clear to
                            him reiterating the line we have often taken with the French: we have no
                            basic differences on objectives; until now we have had differences only
                            on the means. We consider Africa to be the hinterland for Western Europe
                            and that close African relations with Europe are both natural and
                            desirable. We strongly believe in the necessity for maintaining but not
                            imposing Western, i.e. French, influence in North Africa. We do not
                            believe that this can be done by military means. Until now we have
                            accordingly felt that French policies were on the contrary leading to
                            the end of Western influence in the area. Any <pb facs="0055" n="19" xml:id="pg_19"/> French policies, we should tell <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>, that can achieve the above
                            objectives will be assured of our support.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>:</hi>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">De Gaulle</persName> will not willingly
                            break up <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. We and the rest of the
                            members must see to it that his rigid temperament and nationalistic
                            tendencies do not result in the gradual disintegration of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. We may have to give in this
                            connection greater deference to French views on <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> military and political policies, and this irrespective
                            of the fact that French policies and energies will be focused primarily
                            on Africa. This situation will probably require a review of our policies
                            on sharing atomic information with the French and warrant a resumption
                            of Big Three meetings. In the meantime U.S. military assistance to
                            France should be continued as heretofore. If the <gloss target="#t_LOC1">LOC</gloss> Agreement<note n="2" xml:id="d12fn2">Not further
                                identified.</note> is not concluded by the time of <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>’s coming to power, we should
                            seek to conclude it as soon as possible thereafter. The whole question
                            of the <gloss target="#t_IRBM1">IRBM</gloss>’s will have to be raised
                            with <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> personally.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">East-West Relations:</hi> This may prove from our point
                            of view the most difficult and dangerous area of <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>’s policies. While
                            endeavoring to maintain the French-German rapprochement, <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> may in time be tempted to
                            make an independent approach to the Soviet Union—both in the interests
                            of world peace and to indicate once again that France is not merely
                            following U.S. policies. The Soviet Union may in this connection be
                            disposed to giving <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>
                            assurances on non-interference in North Africa in return for closer
                            bilateral relations. There will undoubtedly be a tendency on <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>’s part to recognize
                            Communist China, given the favorable sentiment of French public opinion
                            in this regard.</p>
                        <p>We should have a frank exchange of views earliest with <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> on overall East-West
                            matters. Tactically, we would do well to appear to leave some of the
                            initiative to him on these matters. In any event our thinking should be
                            very closely coordinated with the French. The <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> may be able to be more effective than ourselves in
                            restraining any precipitate action by <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName> in regard to Moscow, but obviously not in a
                            position to dissuade him from recognizing Communist China.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">European Integration</hi> may have to be put into
                            suspense during the period of <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName>’s government. One way to save it might be to give
                            to <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> the initiative of
                            launching a new concept of an association of European states. In this
                            connection <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> may tend to
                            favor the Free Trade Area over the Common Market. He will probably
                            oppose <gloss target="#t_EURATOM1">EURATOM</gloss>. In any case, this is
                            up to the Europeans; any activity on our part in support of European
                            integration will only provoke a most adverse reaction in <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> and thus prove
                            counter-productive.</p>
                        <pb facs="0056" n="20" xml:id="pg_20"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">U.S.-French Relations:</hi> During this difficult and
                            trying period, we may have to rely heavily on personal diplomacy. The
                            President’s relationship with <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName> will be an asset. It would be helpful if <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> would agree to make an early
                            visit to this country and this possibility should be explored. I
                            suspect, however, that <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>
                            might not wish to come here, at least at the outset. Under the
                            circumstances, it might prove necessary for the Secretary—and possibly
                            even the President—to visit France. A much less satisfactory alternative
                            would be for the new French Foreign Minister to make an early trip over
                            here. A strong effort will in any event have to be made at an early
                            stage to disabuse <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>
                            personally of some of his misconceptions and suspicions with regard to
                            U.S. policies and to have a full and frank exchange of views on
                            East-West issues. As stated above we should continue to provide France
                            with military assistance as heretofore. Presumably <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> will initiate an austerity
                            program, endeavor to put France’s finances on a sound basis and do
                            everything possible to avoid having to ask us for financial assistance.
                            However, if he should eventually have to request such assistance, we
                            should be prepared to give it sympathetic consideration.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>