<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-12-20T10:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-12-20T10:30:00-05:00" n="152" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                        <head>152. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d152fn0">Source: Department of State, Secretary’s Memoranda
                                of Conversation: Lot 64 D 199. Secret; Limit Distribution.
                                Presumably drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>
                                and approved by the Office of the Secretary on December
                            22.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_USMC1">US/MC</gloss>/8</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Rambouillet</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-12-20T16:30:00+01:00">December 20, 1959, 4:30
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">MEETING OF HEADS OF GOVERNMENT</p>
                        <p rend="center">Paris, December 19–21, 1959</p>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>President <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Algeria, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, Nuclear Weapons,
                                    <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>As the President was departing with Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>, Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>, and their parties, General <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> asked me if I would mind
                            waiting behind to have a short talk with him deux. I spent about 15
                            minutes with him alone.</p>
                        <p>The General said that he was anxious to cover with me the same general
                            ground which had been gone over with the President the day before.<note n="1" xml:id="d152fn1">See <ref target="#d150">Document
                                150</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>On Algeria, General <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName>
                            said that he had appreciated the support for his position which had been
                            promptly accorded by both the President and the Secretary of State. He
                            regretted that we had abstained on the final vote on the resolution in
                            the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss>, but this had not affected the
                            final outcome and could be considered a relatively unimportant
                                incident.<note n="2" xml:id="d152fn2">See <ref target="#d150fn3">footnote 3, Document 150</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>Insofar as <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> was concerned, the
                            General said that things in the alliance should remain as they were.
                            France would neither add nor subtract from its present effort and
                            attitude. Once French troops were back in Europe from Algeria, then
                            there would be time enough to consider possible command rearrangements
                            but for the time being the situation should remain as it is.</p>
                        <p>I raised the question of unified air defense and told the General that
                            this was a matter on which we felt strongly. I pointed out that, with
                            troops from a number of Allies in Germany and no unified command, we
                            were faced with a hopelessly confused and militarily inadequate
                            situation if trouble were to break out. The General dismissed the
                            seriousness of the problem. He said that he had been talked to about the
                                <pb facs="0357" n="321" xml:id="pg_321"/> question of the radar
                            system and communications and that we could proceed with this on a
                            coordinated basis. I told him that the essential thing was a unified
                            command which, in the event of trouble, could move with the necessary
                            speed. The General repeated that matters were to be left as they
                            were.</p>
                        <p>The General then said that by mid-March they would have their atomic
                            explosion but that they would not have by then much capability in this
                            field. He intimated that he assumed following the explosion the United
                            States would be in a position to cooperate with France. I replied that
                            the United States Government operated in this general area under
                            stringent statutory limits. I said that France would not be
                            automatically entitled to intimate collaboration with the United States
                            on atomic matters following the explosion of their first bomb and that
                            in point of fact what we might be able to do with France in this general
                            area would be determined in the last analysis by the general impression
                            of our Congress concerning the extent to which France was playing a
                            cooperative role in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. I said that
                            recent actions by France had created an unfortunate impression on our
                            Congress. The General did not pursue this point.</p>
                        <p>I then brought up the question of the stockpile of nuclear weapons in
                            France. The General acted aggrieved and asked how this could be
                            considered if such weapons were not exclusively under French control if
                            they would be stored on French soil. In consequence of his attitude I
                            got nowhere with him on this point.</p>
                        <p>The General then returned to the British attitude concerning the European
                            Economic Community. He said that he considered them to be unnecessarily
                            concerned. They had had in the early days an opportunity to join the
                            Community but had attached impossible conditions, particularly in
                            connection with their economic relations with the other members of the
                            Commonwealth. In general he showed a lack of sympathy and even suspicion
                            as far as British motivations were concerned. When I mentioned the
                            communiqué which had been agreed to that afternoon dealing with future
                            economic discussions and expressed my belief that this was a very
                            helpful move in the right direction, the General just shrugged his
                            shoulders.</p>
                        <p>General <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> said there had
                            been agreement that morning that there should be continuing
                            consultations between France, Great Britain and United States on a very
                            discreet basis.<note n="3" xml:id="d152fn3">See <ref target="#d151">Document 151</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>Our talk then broke. Throughout it, the General’s attitude was entirely
                            friendly. There was, however, no indication of any prospective change in
                            his position on the matters at issue in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>