<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="277" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d277">
                        <head>277. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>Although holding a very slim parliamentary majority and relying on the
                            votes of neo-Fascist deputies for its survival, the government of Prime
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_TF1">Tambroni</persName> took a hard line
                            against the political protests of the left-wing parties. Police
                            suppression of a Communist political rally in Bologna in early June 1960
                            led to further public protests and to fist fights in the Chamber of
                            Deputies. <persName corresp="#p_TF1">Tambroni</persName>’s decision to
                            grant permission to the neo-Fascist <gloss target="#t_MSI1">MSI</gloss>
                            to hold a party congress in Genoa led to riots in that city and the
                            eventual cancellation of the meeting. Between June 30 and July 7,
                            violent outbreaks took place throughout Italy. Leaders of the ruling
                            Christian Democratic Party held meetings with the representatives of
                            other center parties which resulted in a decision to replace <persName corresp="#p_TF1">Tambroni</persName>.</p>
                        <p>The negotiations for a new government were managed by Aldo Moro,
                            Secretary of the Christian Democratic Party, and resulted in a July 16
                            agreement among the Christian Democrats, Liberals, Social Democrats, and
                            Republicans to form a new government. This agreement was ratified by the
                            directorate of the Christian Democratic government on July 18. <persName corresp="#p_TF1">Tambroni</persName> resigned the following day.</p>
                        <p>On July 26, <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Amintore Fanfani</persName> formed
                            his third government, a four-party coalition of Liberals, Republicans,
                            Social Democrats, and Christian Democrats. In the confidence vote that
                            followed, the Socialist Party abstained. This action was a victory for
                            PSI Secretary <persName corresp="#p_NP1">Pietro Nenni</persName> over
                            those Socialist Party elements favoring closer cooperation with the
                            Communist Party. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_ZJD1">Zellerbach</persName> commented: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“For the first time since 1958 Italy now has a government based
                                    on broad center parliamentary support which offers prospect of
                                    developing into effective governing instrument. Shock engendered
                                    by Communist riots, and by realization of how close <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gronchi</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TF1">Tambroni</persName> were to consolidating
                                    personal power with adventitious aid of certain extreme right
                                    political, economic and clerical elements, caused democratic
                                    parties to close ranks.” (Telegram 426 from Rome, July 27;
                                    Department of State, Central Files, 765.00/7–2760)</p>
                            </quote></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>