<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-01-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="353" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d353">
                        <head>353. Memorandum of Conversation Between Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> and the British Ambassador
                                (<persName corresp="#p_CHA1">Caccia</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d353fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> Papers, <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> Correspondence, 1958. Top Secret; Eyes Only;
                                Personal and Private. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-01-21">January
                                    21, 1959</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>I referred to the “eyes only” to the President and me memorandum from Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName><note n="1" xml:id="d353fn1">Not found in Department of State files. According
                                to a memorandum of a telephone conversation, January 20, Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> contacted the
                                President to inform him that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CHA1">Caccia</persName> had just delivered a letter which stated that
                                Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>
                                wished to visit Russia. The memorandum stated in part: “The <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss> wanted to put the thought in the
                                Pres’ mind and maybe after dinner they could speak of it. It is hard
                                to say no. The Pres does not give much of a —, does the <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>? The Pres’ shotgun reaction is let
                                him go if he is that good. The <gloss target="#t_Sec1">Sec</gloss>
                                would have preferred to see us work at the problem, and we may have
                                to do it in the end,” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., White House
                                Telephone Conversations) <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> talked along the same lines on January
                                21, immediately prior to <persName corresp="#p_CHA1">Caccia</persName>’s arrival.</note> regarding his possible trip
                            to Russia and then a stopover at Washington, as well as Bonn and Paris
                            on the way back. I said that naturally on a matter of this sort which
                            had domestic, as well as international significance, we would not
                            attempt to do other than merely put forward certain suggestions and
                            thoughts for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s
                            consideration. The President and I did feel that a trip to Moscow by the
                            Prime Minister would be apt to set in motion other direct approaches by
                            the French, the Germans and perhaps others. This would be particularly
                            dangerous at a point when there was as yet no firm agreed position as to
                            how to react in Berlin if the Soviets persisted.<note n="2" xml:id="d353fn2">In a note dated November 27, 1958, to the
                                Governments of the United Kingdom, France, and the United States,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> proposed that
                                the Western portion of Berlin be disarmed and established as a
                                separate free city within the German Democratic Republic. For text
                                of this note, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin,</hi> January 19, 1959, pp. 81–89.</note></p>
                        <p>I said that we ourselves had abstained very carefully from anything which
                            could possibly be deemed a negotiation about the Berlin situation in our
                            talks with <persName corresp="#p_MAI1">Mikoyan</persName>, although no
                            doubt <persName corresp="#p_MAI1">Mikoyan</persName> would have been
                            quite glad to be the medium for direct bilateral talks between the
                            Soviet Union and the United States.<note n="3" xml:id="d353fn3"><persName corresp="#p_MAI1">Anastas Mikoyan</persName> made an
                                unofficial visit to the United States January 4–20, 1959, during
                                which time he talked with <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> on January 5 and with President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> on January
                            17.</note></p>
                        <p>I said that we had the impression that one of the reasons for <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s proposed trip was that it
                            would provide an understandable basis for a visit to Washington. I said
                            that the President felt that this roundabout approach was unnecessary
                            and that if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> wanted
                            to come to Washington and talk with the President about the situation,
                            we saw no reason why he should not do so. We had invited, and there was
                            a standing invitation to, General <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName> so he could <pb facs="0861" n="825" xml:id="pg_825"/> hardly complain. I added that I myself had been
                            turning over in my mind the possibility of a short trip to Europe to
                            confer with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>, General
                                <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">de Gaulle</persName> and Chancellor
                                <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> with a view to
                            helping to align our policies.</p>
                        <p>Sir <persName corresp="#p_CHA1">Harold</persName> expressed himself as
                            very gratified with the statement that we saw no obstacle to Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> coming to
                            Washington. He asked whether, in our opinion, it could be done in the
                            early future. I said we saw no reason why it could not be done almost
                            any time subject, of course, to the President’s engagements, but that he
                            had no other official state visit coming up before March.</p>
                        <p>Sir <persName corresp="#p_CHA1">Harold</persName> said that he would
                            immediately communicate our views to the Prime Minister and thanked me
                            for both the promptness and the substance of my comments.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="strong">JFD</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>