<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-03-20T11:20:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-03-20T11:20:00-05:00" n="357" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d357">
                        <head>357. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d357fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_WAC1">Whitman</persName> File, Miscellaneous Material. Secret;
                                Personal and Private. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GJNJ1">Joseph N.
                                    Greene, Jr.</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>’ Special Assistant. The meeting was held in
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>’ room at Walter
                                Reed Hospital.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-03-20T11:20:00">March 20, 1959, 11:20 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName></item>
                            <item>Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Selwyn
                                    Lloyd</persName></item>
                            <item>President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName></item>
                            <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At the President’s invitation to me to comment on some of the subjects
                            that he would be discussing with the Prime Minister and Foreign
                            Secretary, I said that I would first like to speak of the broad aspects
                            of the situation now confronting us, as I saw them. I said that I
                            thought the free world allies should not give the people of the world
                            the impression that we are frightened of the Soviets or that the Soviets
                            are in the driver’s seat. In some parts of the world, notably in Asia,
                            Africa and parts of Latin America, people are watching closely to see
                            whether they think the Soviet Union or the Western Allies are the more
                            powerful. We cannot, of course, prevent <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> from strutting across the stage and making
                            his grandiloquent speeches. But we can avoid the impression <pb facs="0869" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/> that whenever he sounds
                            conciliatory we rejoice and whenever he sounds threatening we are
                            fearful as though he were the Lord of Creation.</p>
                        <p>As to Berlin, I said that I thought that we should make no concessions
                            nor agree to any changes in the present arrangements except as part of a
                            larger agreement out of which we would get something. I said that I
                            thought our position in Berlin legally and morally impeccable and our
                            sovereignty there sound; the Soviets cannot by their own act deprive us
                            of sovereignty in Berlin nor put the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                            in a position to control our exercise of it. I noted that in such
                            matters we can, as we did in the contractual agreements with the Federal
                            Republic, voluntarily renounce some or all of our sovereign rights when
                            it is expedient to do so; but I thought the assumption that, simply
                            because the Soviets challenge our rights and position, we have to seek a
                            compromise, is all wrong.</p>
                        <p>As to the possibility of an early Summit meeting, I said that I had not
                            found persuasive the agreements favoring such a meeting, and that I did
                            not think we should now agree to go to one unless we can exact a
                            reasonable price in Soviet “deeds not words”. I recalled that in 1955,
                            the Soviets had paid such a price by agreeing to the Austrian Treaty.
                            Also they accepted the composition we proposed. I said that I had seen
                            no evidence that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> now
                            seems prepared to pay a price, but rather to drive us to the Summit by
                            threats. Nor had I been able to think of any acceptable agreement that
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> might now be
                            willing dependably to make with us. I said that I was opposed to the
                            idea of a Summit meeting premised simply on the hope that it might
                            produce something positive, without having any evidence that there is a
                            real prospect of this. I said that at such a meeting there would be
                            almost irresistible pressure upon the leaders of the democracies to
                            reach an agreement. The Soviet leaders would be under no such pressure
                            and we would be at a distinct disadvantage. I asked the Prime Minister
                            whether in his visit to Moscow he had discovered any element in the
                            Soviet thinking which might give hopes of useful negotiation at the
                            Summit.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister did not indicate that he had any basis for believing
                            that a worthwhile, acceptable agreement could be reached with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>. He did, however, go on to
                            discuss generally the question of German reunification.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister said that he had the general impression that zeal for
                            German reunification has somewhat abated. He had discussed this with
                            Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>, and also had
                            tried to elicit the Chancellor’s views on dealing with the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>.<note n="1" xml:id="d357fn1">Apparently
                                a reference to discussions held during <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s trip to Bonn March 12–13, 1959.</note>
                            The Prime Minister said that <pb facs="0870" n="834" xml:id="pg_834"/>
                            somewhat to his surprise <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>
                            had indicated that he is prepared to accept the status quo. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said that he had
                            commented to the Chancellor that this seemed to be close to what
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> says he wants and
                                <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> had replied that the
                            ultimate goal of German reunification could not, of course, be
                            explicitly abandoned and indeed it should be held out as a light at the
                            end of what might be a very long tunnel. In the time that would elapse
                            before this light were reached, ways could, as Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> understood <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>’s view, be found to lighten
                            some of the human burdens borne by the people of East Germany.</p>
                        <p>I recalled that I had discussed with <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> the possibility of arranging for a long-term
                            negotiation by Foreign Ministers and their Deputies, similar to the
                            negotiations that had eventually led to the Austrian Treaty. I said that
                            I thought this a possibility which ought not to be wholly discarded in
                            the present situation and I cited too the talks that we have been having
                            with the Chinese Communists.<note n="2" xml:id="d357fn2">Reference is to
                                talks between U.S. Ambassador to Poland Jacob Beam and Wang
                                Ping-nan, Ambassador of the People’s Republic of China to Poland,
                                which began in September 1958 in Warsaw.</note> Such talks can
                            provide a context for avoiding hostilities, even if the substantive
                            content of the talks is relatively inconsequential.</p>
                        <p>I repeated that to agree now to go to a Summit meeting at a fixed date in
                            the future would be a grave error and would suggest to the world that we
                            had completely given in to the Soviets, in reversing the attitude we
                            have taken for the past two years, namely that there must be some
                            prospect of fruitful results at a Summit meeting before we could agree
                            to go to one. I thought that it would be most dangerous to ourselves to
                            give such an impression.</p>
                        <p>I said that if we shall have to face the issue of whether to make
                            prospect of a positive outcome a condition of going to the Summit, I
                            felt that we might as well face it now, while there is still time to
                            find out, free of public pressures. Through a meeting of Foreign
                            Ministers, or privately through diplomatic channels—or, I said, not
                            necessarily through private channels; after all Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> had talked directly with Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>—we could try to
                            ascertain whether <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is
                            prepared to make an acceptable deal. I said in this connection I agree
                            with the thought that there will probably not be agreement with the
                            Soviets except with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>;
                            and that in many respects the prospect of talking with Gromyko was a
                            bleak and barren one. But I did believe that ways existed for finding
                            out whether or not there was anything that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> wanted that we could give and get a quid pro
                            quo; and that the possibility of Deputy talks should not be
                            discouraged.</p>
                        <pb facs="0871" n="835" xml:id="pg_835"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said that as the
                            British people see the present situation, the Soviets, far from adopting
                            an aggressive posture of advancing on the West, have simply said that
                            all they want to do is go away from where they are. The Prime Minister
                            said that if the Soviets carry out their threat to hand over to the
                                <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> control of our access to Berlin,
                            we shall be faced with very difficult practical problems, not the least
                            of these avoiding appearing to blockade ourselves out of Berlin. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said that he saw
                            four possibilities:</p>
                        <p>1) That the Soviets give in; 2) that we give in; 3) that there be
                            negotiations leading to an agreed solution for Berlin and the broader
                            problems of central Europe, and 4) that there be war. The Prime Minister
                            said that his Government would be quite prepared to mobilize more armed
                            forces if necessary. [<hi rend="italic">3 lines of source text not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said his Government
                            would not have the necessary public support unless they had a publicly
                            comprehensible issue. He thought that negotiations would have to be
                            attempted and would have to fail, before the British public could be
                            convinced of the need for preparations of force.</p>
                        <p>The President, on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s
                            point that the Soviets are not “advancing” observed that they are in
                            fact trying to get us out of Berlin and he wondered whether that were
                            not a sufficiently aggressive issue to be persuasive. I said that I
                            quite disagreed with the Prime Minister’s theory that if we are
                            threatened, we must negotiate, lest the public not support our being
                            firm. I said that our present considerable strength is conceived as a
                            deterrent to Communist imperialist aggression. It is a deterrent, and
                            there is not going to be the war of which the Prime Minister spoke. In
                            being firm we have sometimes to take added risks, such as our sending
                            troops to Lebanon and Jordan and holding Quemoy. But in that instance, I
                            felt sure, our show of firmness and determination, coupled with our
                            deterrent power, had avoided war. On Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName>’s point that the issues now posed in Berlin
                            are so difficult that we should negotiate a new arrangement for the
                            city, I said that I could not agree that there is anything wrong in our
                            present position there. It is the Soviets who are trying to make it
                            wrong, but that does not mean that we have to negotiate with them about
                            it. I asked what is the use of our spending $40 billion a year or more
                            to create deterrent power if whenever the Soviets threaten us and want
                            to take something from our present positions we feel that we have to buy
                            peace by compromise. If that is going to be our attitude, we had better
                            save our money.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister argued that the premises of our position in Berlin,
                            and particularly the premise of our presence by right of conquest, are
                            fast fading away, and that with their control of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>, the Soviets <pb facs="0872" n="836" xml:id="pg_836"/> have the upper hand. Hence, he said, we should try
                            to salvage something by negotiation.</p>
                        <p>The President intervened to suggest that time was growing short and that
                            this discussion could be continued at Camp David. He asked whether I had
                            any thoughts to express on other matters.</p>
                        <p>I referred to the Geneva negotiations on nuclear test suspension and said
                            that it now seems evident that there would not emerge from that
                            conference an agreement including control provisions acceptable to us. I
                            said I saw no prospect that the Soviets will abandon their concept of
                            the veto, which has been borne out in the operations of the United
                            Nations Security Council: that is, unless the Great Powers act in
                            accord, they should not act at all.</p>
                        <p>I said that I thought that since atmospheric tests are increasingly shown
                            to be injurious to life, we should extend indefinitely our suspension of
                            them and hope that the Soviets would reciprocate. But, I said, I was
                            sure that opinion in the United States would have no confidence in the
                            possibility of a reliable control agreement being reached at Geneva. I
                            recalled that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> had
                            himself suggested to me during my last visit to London<note n="3" xml:id="d357fn3">Reference is to <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>’ visit to London February 3–4.</note> the
                            possibility that he and the President might address letters to <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> setting out the proposition
                            on atmospheric testing and the impossibility of an agreement to control
                            specifically underground and high altitude tests unless the Soviets
                            alter their position on the veto in the control system.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said he understood
                            the scientists had changed their view of the dependability of the
                            conclusions on a control system, reached in Geneva in 1958. The
                            President said that it is his understanding that the scientists now find
                            that the originally proposed 180 world-wide stations would be inadequate
                            to detect underground testing of moderate proportions. The President
                            thought, however, that there might be present now elements of an
                            agreement with the Soviets that there would be no atmospheric tests and
                            no underground tests exceeding, say, 100 kilotons. He understood that
                            underground tests larger than this could in any event be detectable. The
                            President emphasized that he would not be willing to enter into an
                            agreement with the Soviets suspending underground tests unless he could
                            be sure that we could detect violations.</p>
                        <p>I remarked that I did not believe that we could, under any circumstances,
                            get a veto-less control system with Russia.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MH1">Macmillan</persName> said that he attaches
                            great importance to reaching some kind of an agreement in the Geneva
                            talks.</p>
                        <pb facs="0873" n="837" xml:id="pg_837"/>
                        <p>I said that I thought it is perhaps now time to put Soviet intentions in
                            this matter to the stern test by reacting firmly to their extreme
                            position on the veto and showing some sense of outrage at the Soviet
                            proposals. I thought that unless we reacted vigorously against this now,
                            but went on to discuss other matters, we would have missed the
                            psychological moment. Unless our reaction evoked better evidence than we
                            now have of honorable intentions, we should not go on with the present
                            conference or set up a successor to it but could exchange views
                            diplomatically.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>