<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-10-31T20:52:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-10-31T20:52:00-05:00" n="67" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                        <head>67. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d67fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 740.5/10–3158. Secret; Limit Distribution. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MBRH1">McBride</persName>; cleared by the
                                Office of European Regional Affairs, the Executive Secretariat, and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>; and approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ECB1">Elbrick</persName>. Repeated to
                                London, Bonn, and Rome.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-10-31T20:52:00">October 31, 1958, 8:52
                                p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1594. Paris for Embassy and <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss>.
                            Following is summary Secretary’s talk with French Ambassador October 31
                            on <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">deGaulle</persName> letter based on
                            uncleared memo of conversation:<note n="1" xml:id="d67fn1">Not
                                found.</note></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said French idea was not
                            extend geographic responsibility of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. They rather wanted strategic military planning on <pb facs="0150" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> tripartite basis covering such
                            areas as Africa and Middle East as well as political planning. Other
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> parties would not be directly
                            involved. <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> added French
                            entirely clear tripartite decisions could not engage others. Principal
                            French thought was organize more effectively consultation among three
                            powers who shared extra-European responsibilities and who were (or were
                            about to be) atomic powers.</p>
                        <p>With regard to procedural aspects, French hoped <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">deGaulle</persName> memorandum would remain
                            unpublished but thought line developed in foregoing paragraph could
                            serve for public presentation if necessary. Regarding possibility
                            publicity re tripartite talks if such talks held, French thought there
                            was no reason publicize talks but neither should we seek to hide them.
                            There were ample precedents for tripartite talks in connection with
                            disarmament, German reunification, summit matters, etc. We would simply
                            say <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">deGaulle</persName> had addressed
                            message to US and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, and three nations
                            directly concerned were discussing it.</p>
                        <p>Secretary thought paper should be developed on public line re tripartite
                            talks. This should refer to <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">deGaulle</persName> initiative and fact matter had been discussed
                            with Germans, Italians and <persName corresp="#p_SPH1">Spaak</persName>.
                            He thought we should indicate talks here were part of series of
                            exchanges re problem of organizing free world more effectively.
                                <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> pointed out French
                            would not discuss matter in same terms with Germans and Italians as with
                                <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and US. He thought it would be
                            difficult to speak of tripartite talks as “part of a series”.</p>
                        <p>Secretary noted <persName corresp="#p_DEGC1">deGaulle</persName>
                            memorandum as now interpreted had nothing to do with <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and that tripartite framework was
                            justified by French on different grounds. <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> might
                            be involved but neither treaty area nor text would be altered. Main
                            stress was on secret tripartite arrangements covering area outside
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Tripartite decisions could be
                            reported to <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> if necessary. Secretary
                            concluded French were now presenting quite different approach which,
                            while eliminating certain problems, raises others, and he would wish
                            consider more fully. He noted French idea for tripartite war plans in
                            areas such as Africa and Middle East would raise serious problems.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> inquired if he could report
                            Secretary was not rejecting tripartite talks. Secretary replied he was
                            not rejecting tripartite talks but was considering problem of how to
                            explain them. He added another problem in this worldwide planning
                            operation was that in areas such as Far East only US able and willing
                            make real contribution. If new French approach implied they were willing
                            create power in FE and accept responsibility there, we would be most
                            interested. <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said one of
                            French points was that in present situation US could take decisions
                            alone in Far East for instance which might engage France. Secretary
                            noted that under this criterion, many other nations also affected, and
                            this seemed hardly appropriate yardstick. <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> repeated basic <pb facs="0151" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/> French thesis was that tripartitism justified as
                            including those countries with extra-Atlantic responsibilities and
                            nuclear potentiality. Secretary indicated view US would remain only Free
                            World power able carry financial burden having significant nuclear
                            capability. Furthermore there was question conventional capability in
                            which French contribution greatly reduced as result Algerian war.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DAW1"><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>