<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Czechoslovakia (Briggs) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v04p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d237</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">237</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-08-18T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-08-18T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-18T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-18T10:00:00-05:00" n="237"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d237">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 702</seg>
                </opener>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">249.1111–<persName corresp="#p_OW1">Oatis,
                        William</persName>/8–1851: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Czechoslovakia (<persName corresp="#p_BEO1"
                            type="from">Briggs</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Praha</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-18T16:00:00+01:00"
                            >August 18, 1951—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>132. In absence on vacation <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SV1">Siroky</persName>, I called this morning on acting
                        <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> Sekaninova pursuant instructions
                        <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 114 Aug 16.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d237fn1">Telegram 114 stated that the Department of State was
                        prepared to put into effect the course of action dealing with the <persName
                            corresp="#p_OW1">Oatis</persName> case approved by the President but
                        instructed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">Briggs</persName> first to
                        inform Foreign Minister Široký privately of the intended U.S. actions. Such
                        an approach would give Czechoslovakia an opportunity to settle the <persName
                            corresp="#p_OW1">Oatis</persName> case before publicity attending the
                        export embargo made further Czechoslovak action difficult. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BEO1">Briggs</persName> was to avoid mentioning the
                            <persName corresp="#p_OW1">Oatis</persName> case, was to refer to
                        existing obstacles to better relations between the two countries, could
                        point out the state of feeling in the United States as reflected in various
                        resolutions introduced in Congress, and was to indicate that failure by
                        Czechoslovakia to take any action would lead to cutting off of all U.S.
                        exports to Czechoslovakia. (249.1111–<persName corresp="#p_OW1">Oatis,
                            William</persName>/8–1451)</note>
                </p>
                <p>I recalled that when presenting credentials nearly two years ago I had sought
                    dedicate my service here to constructive possibilities my mission with which
                    objective President <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gottwald</persName> had indicated
                    his agreement.<note n="2" xml:id="d237fn2">Regarding <persName corresp="#p_BEO1"
                            >Briggs</persName>’ presentation of credentials as Ambassador on
                        November 8, 1949, see telegram 1671, November 8, 1949, <ref
                            target="frus1949v05#pg_412">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 412</ref>.</note> In subsequent
                    discussions <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>’s dementis and <persName
                        corresp="#p_SV1">Siroky</persName>, especially with latter April last year,
                    I had tried develop <pb facs="0436" n="1402" xml:id="pg_1402"/> same
                    possibilities. But as Mme. Sekaninova aware obstacle has now arisen to good
                    relations which unless removed can render them still more difficult. I then
                    proceeded as per last paragraph <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> in
                    ref, without specifically mentioning <persName corresp="#p_OW1">Oatis</persName>
                    case. Described purpose my visit was to reiterate way ought to be found without
                    further delay to remove obstacle and place relations on more favorable
                    basis.</p>
                <p>At conclusion my remarks Mme. Sekaninova after considerable pause asked whether
                    all these matters had not already been discussed between <gloss
                        target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> and me during recent meetings notably
                    last month, to which I replied that the situation had indeed been discussed but
                    that purpose my call was to contribute if possible to removal of obstacle rather
                    than to discuss how it had arisen.</p>
                <p>Mme. Sekaninova said my observations would be conveyed to <persName
                        corresp="#p_SV1">Siroky</persName> on his return “in about ten days or two
                    weeks”. Her failure to respond more constructively probably need not however, be
                    regarded as significant as she lacks independent authority and customarily
                    informs callers their views will be reported to appropriate official.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Briggs</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
