<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-12-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="274" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d274">
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">No. 739</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.5622/12–1451</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of
                                    State for European Affairs (</hi><persName corresp="#p_BJCH1" type="from">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Bonbright</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">)
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d274fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MRM1">McKisson</persName> and approved by
                                        <persName corresp="#p_CJC1">Campbell</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_HLR1">Higgs</persName> of <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName> had just returned to Washington from
                                    Europe where he had headed the U.S. Delegation at the opening of
                                    the Sixth Session of the U.N. General Assembly in Paris,
                                    November 6 and the U.S. Delegation at the Eighth Session of the
                                    North Atlantic Council, held in Rome, November 24–28.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-12-14">December 14,
                                        1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: US Air Force Plane and Crew Forced Down and
                                Interned in Hungary<note n="2" xml:id="d274fn2">The circumstances of
                                    this incident are described in the note quoted in telegram 235
                                    to Budapest, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>. Accounts of the
                                    developments in this incident were reported in despatches 365,
                                    December 12, and 405, January 4, 1952, both from Budapest.
                                    (711.5622/12–1251 and 711.5622/1–452)</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The following brief account of this incident is submitted for your
                                background information in connection with your appointment with <pb facs="0503" n="1469" xml:id="pg_1469"/> Mr. <persName>Christian
                                    M. Ravndal</persName>, the new US Minister to Hungary, who is
                                leaving tomorrow for Budapest.<note n="3" xml:id="d274fn3">
                                    <persName>Ravndal</persName>, whose nomination to become
                                    Minister to Hungary was approved by the Senate on October 3,
                                    arrived in Budapest on December 20 but did not present his
                                    credentials and assume charge until early January 1952.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>It was announced in a Tass communiqué and in a Hungarian note to the
                                American Legation in Budapest on December 3<note n="4" xml:id="d274fn4">Transmitted in telegram 361 and despatch 333
                                    from Budapest, both December 3. (711.5622/12–351)</note> that
                                the US Air Force plane, which had been missing since November 19,
                                had been forced down on that date near Papa, Hungary, by Soviet
                                fighter planes and turned over by the Soviet command to the
                                Hungarian authorities. Although Legation Budapest had previously
                                made repeated inquiries, these were the first disclosures of the
                                whereabouts of the US plane which disappeared enroute from Erding in
                                the US Zone of Germany to Belgrade, Yugoslavia.</p>
                            <p>The Hungarian note of December 3, as well as a subsequent note of
                                December 11,<note n="5" xml:id="d274fn5">Transmitted in telegram
                                    401, December 11, and despatch 363, December 12, both from
                                    Budapest. (711.5622/12–351)</note> alleged that the plane had
                                deliberately violated the Hungarian border and that the aircraft, as
                                shown by the equipment it carried, had flown over the border with
                                the premeditated intention of parachuting “spies and diversionists”
                                (Yugoslavs) into Hungarian territory.</p>
                            <p>Legation Budapest on instructions from the Department made firm oral
                                representations to the Hungarian Foreign Office on December 3<note n="6" xml:id="d274fn6">The oral representations mentioned here
                                    were reported upon in telegrams 360 and 361 from Budapest, both
                                    December 3. (711.5622/12–351)</note> and presented written notes
                                December 4 and 6<note n="7" xml:id="d274fn7">Regarding the notes
                                    under reference, see telegrams 368, December 4, 370, December 5,
                                    and 378, December 6, and despatches 339, December 5, and 337,
                                    December 7, all from Budapest, in Department of State file
                                    711.5622.</note> requesting the prompt release and return of the
                                crew and plane. However, the Hungarian Government has demanded in
                                its abovementioned notes that the US Government severely punish “the
                                persons responsible” for the violation of the Hungarian border and
                                the Under Secretary of the Hungarian Foreign Office has stated
                                orally that the Hungarian Government is prepared to discuss the US
                                request for the release of the plane and its crew when a
                                “satisfactory reply” is received from the US Government regarding
                                the demanded punishment of “responsible persons”.<note n="8" xml:id="d274fn8">American Charge <persName corresp="#p_AGM1">Abbott</persName> reported on his December 11 conversation
                                    with Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BA1">Berei</persName>
                                    in telegram 400 from Budapest, December 11.
                                    (711.5622/12–1151)</note> We are dispatching a further note to
                                the Hungarian Foreign Office couched in stronger language than that
                                of our previous notes reiterating that the plane’s overflight of
                                Hungarian territory was wholly accidental, reminding the Hungarian
                                Government of our prompt and <pb facs="0504" n="1470" xml:id="pg_1470"/> forthright expression of regret in the
                                matter, and rejecting their demand for punishment of “responsible
                                persons”, while at the same time indicating that it is in accord
                                with regular procedure for US authorities to investigate the
                                circumstances of such inadvertent flights upon the return of the
                                plane and its crew.<note n="9" xml:id="d274fn9">For the text of the
                                    note summarized here, see telegram 235 to Budapest, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>In the light of the Hungarian Government’s attitude to date and the
                                nature of its demands in the matter it appears probable that the
                                Hungarian Government has no intention, in the absence of US
                                submission to those demands, to permit the return of the plane and
                                crew at an early date. Available means of bringing pressure to bear
                                on the Hungarian Government in this matter such as publicity,
                                economic action, and diplomatic action hold little promise of being
                                effective in this case.</p>
                            <p>In the circumstances reviewed above, and having in mind also the
                                course of the <persName corresp="#p_OW1">Oatis</persName> case,<note n="10" xml:id="d274fn10">For documentation, see Documents 670
                                    ff.</note> there is a definite possibility that we shall be able
                                to effect the release of the US aircraft and its crew only if we are
                                prepared to resort to more drastic measures than we have hitherto
                                employed or considered in previous cases of this kind. It is quite
                                likely that the American public generally and the Congress and press
                                in particular will become increasingly aroused over this incident
                                and that heavy pressure will be exerted by these quarters for the US
                                Government to take strong retaliatory measures against the Hungarian
                                Government or forceful action to compel compliance by the Hungarian
                                Government with US demands for the return of the Air Force crew and
                                plane.</p>
                            <p>We are urgently studying all aspects of the foregoing situation
                                including attention to the entire range of possible steps for
                                obtaining satisfactory action by the Hungarian Government in this
                                matter.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>