<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="286" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d286">
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">No. 751</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Department of State Wireless Bulletin</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d286fn1">The Department of State Wireless Bulletin
                                    was a summary of significant news items and official texts,
                                    transmitted daily to overseas Foreign Service missions.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 194</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-10">August 10,
                                        1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Polish Government Orders</hi> U.S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Information Office Closed</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The activities of the United States Information Service in Poland
                                have been closed down at the request of the Polish Government,
                                according to the U.S. State Department. The closing became effective
                                Wednesday.</p>
                            <p>State Department Press Officer <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">McDermott</persName>, in making the announcement late Thursday,
                                said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The action of the Polish Government is of particular
                                        interest coming as it did so soon upon the recent visit of
                                        Soviet Deputy Premier <persName>Vyacheslav
                                            Molotov</persName> to Warsaw and within 48 hours after
                                        dispatch of the message from the President of the Presidium
                                        of the Supreme Soviet of the U.S.S.R. to the President of
                                        the United States<note n="2" xml:id="d286fn2">For text of
                                            the communication, sent on August 6, see Document
                                            798.</note> setting forth Soviet professions of peace
                                        and friendship between peoples. With respect to the latter
                                        it is noted that the present action of the Polish
                                        Government, a government so closely associated with the
                                        Soviet model, in all ways, is the example of a deed as
                                        distinguished from words.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Polish Office Ordered Closed in N. Y</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Meanwhile, the Department said the Polish Ambassador to the United
                                States, <persName>Jozef Winiewicz</persName>, had been told that the
                                Polish Research and Information Service in New York must be closed
                                within 24 hours.</p>
                            <p>The State Department issued the following statement on the situation:
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Polish Foreign Minister called on the American
                                        Ambassador, <persName corresp="#p_FJ1">Joseph
                                            Flack</persName>, on August 8 and asked that the
                                        activities of the United States Information Service,
                                        including distribution of the English-and Polish-language
                                        Wireless Bulletins, film showings and library functions,
                                        should be terminated as of that date. Since the Polish
                                        Government insisted that this was final there was no
                                        alternative but to comply with this request.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Regards Action As Unwarranted</hi>
                            </p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The United States Government regards this action of the Polish
                                    Government as an entirely unwarranted interference with the free
                                        <pb facs="0540" n="1506" xml:id="pg_1506"/> exchange of
                                    information between nations, an exchange which this Government
                                    is always ready to foster on a fair and reciprocal basis. It is
                                    recalled, moreover, how much the Polish people appreciated, ever
                                    since the United States Information Service was established at
                                    Warsaw, the services it performed. There is every reason to
                                    believe that these activities in the interest of a better
                                    understanding between peoples will be missed by the Polish
                                    nation.</p>
                                <p>“The Polish Ambassador in Washington has been summoned today and
                                    informed that the Polish Research and Information Service at New
                                    York must be closed within 24 hours.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>In response to questions, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">McDermott</persName> said the Polish Foreign Minister,
                                    <persName>Stanislaw Skrzeszewski</persName>, gave no reasons for
                                requesting the closing of the <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss>
                                office in Warsaw. The <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> in
                                Warsaw included a library, motion picture theater and offices. The
                                Polish Research and Information Service in New York was described as
                                a propaganda agency.</p>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>