<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-12T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-12T20:00:00-05:00" n="425" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d425">
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">No. 890</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">668.81/4–1251: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Greece</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d425fn1">Drafted by <persName>Norbert L.
                                        Anschuetz</persName> of the Office of Greek, Turkish, and
                                    Iranian Affairs, and by <persName corresp="#p_HLR1">Higgs</persName> and cleared with <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName>, Berry, <persName corresp="#p_MGC2">McGhee</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PGW1">Perkins</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BJCH1">Bonbright</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CTD1">Cabot</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_OJH1">Ohly</persName>, Emery, and <persName corresp="#p_HCECJ1">Colonel Hartshorn</persName> of Defense.
                                    Repeated to Belgrade.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-12T20:00:00-05:00">April
                                        12, 1951—8 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3746. Eyes only Ambassador. <gloss target="#t_EMBTEL1">Embtel</gloss>
                                3312 Apr 4 rptd Belgrade 78.<note n="2" xml:id="d425fn2">Telegram
                                    3312 reported that Greek Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_VS2">Venizelos</persName> told Ambassador
                                    Peurifoy that the Yugoslav Minister to Greece had just made a
                                    formal <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> inquiring as to what
                                    action Greece would take in case Yugoslavia was attacked. After
                                    he described the conversation, <persName corresp="#p_VS2">Venizelos</persName> “in effect asked what US wishes him to
                                    reply to Yugoslavs.” (768.5/4–451)</note> Suggest you inform
                                    <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> that, as he knows,
                                this Govt attaches highest importance to closer friendly and
                                cooperative relations between Yugo and Greece and that we have
                                extended such appropriate help to that end as we cld. We feel
                                accordingly it is highly desirable Yugo and Greece come to mutual
                                agreement earliest possible moment on actions which each wld take in
                                event attack on either. We therefore hope they will undertake
                                discussions to clarify and coordinate their actions in such
                                eventuality. You might also indicate that, of course, US wld not
                                consider such bilateral discussions as proper forum in which attempt
                                formulate new basic polit, terr settlement in Balkans (i.e. Alb)
                                except only so</p>
                            <pb facs="0814" n="1780" xml:id="pg_1780"/>
                            <p> far present Grk-Yugo terr involved. Naturally we wld hope be kept
                                currently and fully informed concerning course of discussions.</p>
                            <p>Grk response to Yugos cld be along fol lines: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Greece naturally expects <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                                        wld lend support to Yugo or Greece in event
                                        aggression.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Greece of course prepared honor her obligations as member
                                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in participating
                                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action in support Yugo
                                        and assumes Yugo would do likewise in support Greece.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Greece therefore considers it would be in mutual interests
                                        Greece and Yugo examine in detail possible mil polit
                                        measures which might be taken in event attack against either
                                        and is ready participate further exchange views with Yugo at
                                        convenience Yugo Govt.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> only we expect have in near
                                future more detailed views this gen subj and foregoing designed
                                largely encouragement to Greece and Yugo to initiate convers.
                                Although suspicious possibility one objective <persName corresp="#p_VS2">Venizelos</persName>’ request for advice may be
                                force disclosure US security plans for the areas, we wld hope,
                                through close relations existing between Grk Govt and US Mission in
                                Athens, provide guidance which wld produce Grk-Yugo arrangements in
                                harmony with US plans without unnecessary embarrassment to US. If
                                question integration Grk-Yugo plans with US Balkan and Med plans is
                                raised you shld indicate you feel certain Wash wld consider
                                discussion such plans premature but that it wld undoubtedly wish
                                review situation in light Grk-Yugo agreement.</p>
                            <p>Re Sulzberger report in Belgrade’s 1431 Apr 5 rpt Athens 102<note n="3" xml:id="d425fn3">Telegram 1431 informed the Department of
                                    State that Sulzberger asked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">Allen</persName> whether he had heard
                                    anything about a high-level Greek proposal to Yugoslavia
                                    concerning the possible division of Albania between Greece and
                                    Yugoslavia. (768.5/4–551)</note> we have no info here confirming
                                such understanding. However, we wld not favor any move partition Alb
                                between Greece and Yugo. Re proposal Belgrade’s 1431 include Turks
                                in conversations we consider inadvisable complicate situation to
                                this extent. Turkey has demonstrated reluctance engage bilateral or
                                regional security discussions except on basis direct US
                                participation. Shld Grks and Yugos establish area real
                                understanding, thereby providing basis extending scope discussions
                                and plans, question Turkish participation might be considered.<note n="4" xml:id="d425fn4">In telegram 3497 from Athens, April 18,
                                    Ambassador Peurifoy reported that he presented the views set
                                    forth in this telegram to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_VS2">Venizelos</persName> on April 17 and that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_VS2">Venizelos</persName> said he
                                    would give his reply to the Yugoslavs along these same lines
                                    emphasizing the U.N. framework but making it clear that the
                                    Greek Government will provide support to Yugoslavia in case of
                                    attack, just as the Greeks hoped the Yugoslav Government would
                                    extend aid to them if Greece were attacked. <persName corresp="#p_VS2">Venizelos</persName> told Peurifoy that he
                                    would inform the Yugoslavs of Greek willingness to carry on
                                    detailed military-political negotiations along these lines but
                                    that the initiative would be left to Yugoslavia in light of
                                    their well-known sensitivity about not provoking the <gloss target="#t_Cominform1">Cominform</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_VS2">Venizelos</persName> also denied
                                    categorically that any discussion had taken place with
                                    Yugoslavia concerning the division of Albania.
                                    (668.81/4–1851)</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>