<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of Eastern European
                    Affairs (Reinhardt)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v04p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d461</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">461</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-09-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-09-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="461"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d461">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 926</seg>
                </opener>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">768.5/9–551</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of
                        Eastern European Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RGF1"
                        >Reinhardt</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-09-05">September 5,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Proposed Bilateral Discussions Regarding Military
                    Support for Yugoslavia.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Deputy Under Secretary, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">H. Freeman
                                Matthews</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>General Omar <persName corresp="#p_BGAMN1">Bradley</persName>,
                            Chairman, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJCH1">Bonbright</persName>, <gloss
                                target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RGF1">Reinhardt</persName>, <gloss
                                target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_BGAMN1">Bradley</persName> came in to discuss the
                    confused situation that had developed with regard to the bilateral staff talks
                    which Admiral <persName corresp="#p_CARB1">Carney</persName> has been instructed
                    to carry on with the United Kingdom, France and Italy on the subject of military
                    support for Yugoslavia. This matter is the subject of <gloss target="#t_EE1"
                        >EE</gloss> memorandum of August 30<note n="1" xml:id="d461fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> and memorandum of conversation between Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BJCH1">Bonbright</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BBAB1"
                        >Burrows</persName> of the British Embassy of the same date.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d461fn2">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>After a discussion of the problem of the bilateral talks General <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGAMN1">Bradley</persName> indicated that the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> would probably proceed along the following
                    line: (1) not push the Yugoslav paper which had been submitted to the Standing
                    Group (<gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss>) and to which the British were
                    objecting; (2) resume as soon as possible the politico-military talks (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BGAMN1">Bradley</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_FSOS1"
                        >Franks</persName>); and (3) endeavor to have Admiral <persName
                        corresp="#p_CARB1">Carney</persName> proceed if possible with the bilateral
                    talks as planned, but on the original limited agenda, not the very broad agenda
                    which he had recently submitted to the British in London. In reply to his
                    question General <persName corresp="#p_BGAMN1">Bradley</persName> was told that
                    this procedure would be acceptable to the Department. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MFP1">Matthews</persName> handed General <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGAMN1">Bradley</persName> a letter which the Department was
                    addressing to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AF1">Frank</persName> Nash in this
                    matter, requesting the Defense Department’s views as to the best manner in which
                    to proceed.<note n="2" xml:id="d461fn3">The letter explained the problem
                        concerning the proposed bilateral talks with the British and asked for the
                        Department of Defense views as to the manner in which to proceed.
                        (768.5/8–2851) On October 9, Secretary of Defense <persName
                            corresp="#p_LRA1">Lovett</persName> sent a letter to the Department of
                        State which had an attachment from the Joint Chiefs of Staff concerning
                        these bilateral talks with the British. The <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                            >JCS</gloss> memorandum, dated September 19, recommended that the
                        Department of State explain to the British that plans developed on a
                        bilateral basis should be considered only as an interim emergency measure
                        since <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> would ultimately provide the
                        appropriate military support when its capabilities permitted that General
                            <persName corresp="#p_EGDD1">Eisenhower</persName> would direct the
                        development of emergency plans evolving from these bilateral talks, and that
                        General <persName corresp="#p_EGDD1">Eisenhower</persName> and Admiral
                            <persName corresp="#p_CARB1">Carney</persName> would act as military
                        representatives of the United States. The <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                            >JCS</gloss> repeated their desire that the bilateral talks proceed as
                        soon as possible. (768.5/10–951)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0880" n="1846" xml:id="pg_1846"/>
                <p>In connection with General West’s recent conversation with Marshal <persName
                        corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName>, General <persName corresp="#p_BGAMN1"
                        >Bradley</persName> stated that it was quite clear that this had been done
                    without General <persName corresp="#p_EGDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s knowledge,
                    but he was not sure whether or not General <persName corresp="#p_TIM1"
                        >Irwin</persName> had had any advance notice.<note n="3" xml:id="d461fn4">No
                        record of this conversation has been found in Department of State
                        files.</note> General <persName corresp="#p_GLAM1">Gruenther</persName> was
                    in communication with the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> on this
                    subject.</p>
                <p>With respect to the British desire to keep any quadripartite military planning
                    outside of <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss>, General <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGAMN1">Bradley</persName> asked whether it was our feeling this
                    could be done without incurring the displeasure of the other <gloss
                        target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> members. He was told that it was the
                    Department’s view for the time being at least that it would be possible.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_BGAMN1">Bradley</persName> said that any visit
                    which General <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName> might make to
                    Yugoslavia in response to <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName>’s
                    invitation would be outside the framework of these other talks and would have
                    essentially an information-gathering purpose.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
