<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Embassy in France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v04p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d71</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">71</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-03-12T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-03-12T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-12T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-12T20:00:00-05:00" n="71"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 536</seg>
                </opener>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">663.001/3–1251: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d71fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WFT1"
                            >Williamson</persName> and cleared with <persName corresp="#p_PGW1"
                            >Perkins</persName> and the Department of Defense Repeated to London,
                        Vienna, Moscow, and Frankfurt for <persName corresp="#p_RSJ1"
                            >Reber</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-12T20:00:00-05:00"
                            >March 12, 1951—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4751. For <persName corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName>. Fol is Dept’s position
                    for Aust Treaty to replace conclusions in RPTS D–3/le, Jan 23:<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d71fn2">Document 525. These revisions were recommended to the
                        Secretary of State in a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_PGW1"
                            >Perkins</persName> on March 10. The memorandum, drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_WFT1">Williamson</persName>, informed the Secretary that
                        these revisions were being made in light of suggestions by the Joint Chiefs
                        of Staff and the Austrian Government. (663.001/3–1051)</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">“<hi rend="italic">4. Recommendations on US policy
                    position</hi>.</p>
                <p>1. To discuss with Brit and Fr series of progressive steps which might be taken
                    to obtain conclusion Treaty, namely: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>to adopt Sov version Art 48 bis and West versions Arts 16, 27, 42, and
                            48;</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>to adopt Sov versions Arts 48 bis and 16 and West versions Arts 27,
                            42, and 48;</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>to adopt West versions Art 27 and para 9 Art 42, and Sov versions rest
                            of Art 42 and Arts 48 bis, 16 and 48; or</item>
                        <label>(d)</label>
                        <item>to accept Sov versions all five arts. This last proposal wld be
                            justified as last resort if it wld obtain immed and final agreement to
                            Treaty.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>These steps may have to be modified in light Brit and Fr positions either on
                    specific arts or concluding Treaty at this time.</p>
                <p>2. Any Sov effort reopen agreed arts, such as proposed amendment Art 9, shld be
                    rejected.</p>
                <p>3. Any Sov effort link settlement Aust Treaty with other questions, such as
                    Trieste or Ger, shld be rejected.</p>
                <p>4. No agreement shld be reached which does not take into acct necessity that Aust
                    security forces will, prior to withdrawal West occupation forces from Aust, be
                    reasonably adequate to maintain internal security.”</p>
                <p>You may wish to discuss with Brit and Fr method of negot in Ministerial mtgs. As
                    we see it negots by Mins may (1) be limited to securing agreement on directive
                    to <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Treaty Deputies to resume active negot of
                    unagreed arts with view to concluding Treaty; (2) embrace substantive agreement
                    on unagreed issues, including directive to Treaty Deputies to conclude Treaty on
                    agreed basis; or (3) include complete action by Mins on remaining unagreed
                    issues of Treaty.</p>
                <p>First course least desirable in as much as it wld provide no assurance negots wld
                    not again be stalemated in Deputies’ mtgs. Second <pb facs="0146" n="1112"
                        xml:id="pg_1112"/> course, which wld provide substantive agreement on
                    Ministerial level but leave details to be worked out by experts in Deputies’
                    negots, favored as matter of tactics. Third course wld unnecessarily consume
                    time of <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>s with respect to details which
                    cld best be handled by Treaty Deputies who are organized and equipped to
                    complete final drafting of Treaty. Any of foregoing courses of action shld be
                    accepted, however, if Sov attitude indicates likelihood that it will lead to
                    early conclusion of Treaty.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WJE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
