<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-09-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="174" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 659.119/70</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Danish Minister</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1917Supp02v01#p_BC2" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Brun</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">J. No. 40.A.XXIX</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-09-27">
                                        <hi rend="italic">September 27, 1917</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On July 24 the American Government
                                through the agency of Mr. <persName corresp="frus1917Supp02v01#p_HHC1">Hoover</persName> delivered
                                to the commercial department of the Danish Legation a
                                    memorandum<note n="1" xml:id="d174fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_908">p.
                                    908</ref>.</note> setting forth the necessity for regulating the
                                export of supplies to Denmark and, while expressing the greatest
                                concern in the well-being of the people of Denmark and declaring the
                                reduction in the export of supplies to the barest minimum
                                necessitated, declared this to be only an intermediate situation and
                                added the expectation that a mutual arrangement on a basis described
                                in some detail might be arrived at.</p>
                            <p>On September 5 I had the honor to transmit to you a reply from the
                                Danish Government in a memorandum,<note n="2" xml:id="d174fn2">Not
                                    printed.</note> which in the first place gave an expression to
                                our invariably cordial and friendly feelings towards the United
                                States, and in the second place, while explaining again the economic
                                policy of Denmark as followed in the present war and dictated by our
                                neutrality, pointed out the hardships and difficulties <pb facs="0292" n="1046" xml:id="pg_1046"/> in which the embargo of
                                the United States had placed Denmark and would create for Denmark in
                                the future, and the sacrifices already made by Denmark in the
                                interest of the Entente and the powers joined with the Entente, but
                                at the same time declared the readiness of the Danish Government to
                                at once receive a proposal from the American Government regarding an
                                arrangement on the subject under discussion.</p>
                            <p>The Danish Minister of Foreign Affairs now instructs me by cable to
                                submit to you the earnest request that a proposition as indicated
                                above may be made without delay and an arrangement concluded. The
                                Minister directs me in this connection to say that the American
                                embargo, which at the outset was declared to be intended as a
                                provisional measure only, has now assumed a rather permanent
                                character and that, if a change is not to be expected soon, the
                                effect of the embargo, in connection with the similar measures taken
                                by Great Britain, will undoubtedly be that Denmark will so to speak
                                be thrust into the arms of Germany, not only economically by the
                                fact that Denmark will to an ever increasing degree be dependent
                                upon importations from Germany and Germany in return, well aware of
                                this situation, will in the same proportion increase its demand of
                                compensation from Denmark in quality and value, but also
                                politically, because it can under such circumstances not be avoided
                                that the Danish people by and by becomes convinced that the fate of
                                Denmark is indifferent to the nations now warring against Germany,
                                and that many Danes, whose sympathy is now with the powers of the
                                Entente and those joined with the Entente, will feel themselves
                                drawn towards Germany in the same measure in which Denmark is
                                compelled to look to Germany for obtaining the necessaries for our
                                national life.</p>
                            <p>By a policy of maintaining summary embargoes with regard to Denmark,
                                which are not understood either by the leading men or the masses of
                                the people in Denmark, the Entente powers and the powers joined with
                                them would, therefore, only benefit Germany and increase the
                                influence of Germany in Denmark (and other neutral countries).</p>
                            <p>In representing these facts and arguments most earnestly to you, I
                                have the honor to ask that you will give your serious and favorable
                                consideration to the subject, and be good enough to use your
                                influence to the effect that an arrangement as described may be
                                concluded at the earliest possible moment, lending support to our
                                efforts to avoid economic ruin and a political situation that could
                                only be disastrous.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="frus1917Supp02v01#p_BC2">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">C. Brun</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>