<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-12-21T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-12-21T18:00:00-05:00" n="277" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d277">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 656.119/189</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1917Supp02v01#p_PWH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Page</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-12-21T23:00:00+00:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">December 21, 1917, 11 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                                <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received December 22, 3.58
                                a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>8039. Please deliver copy of following to War Trade Board:</p>
                        <p>My 7990, December 17. Please inform me as soon as possible what progress
                            has been made towards adoption of <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>
                            regarding Dutch shipping proposed in <persName corresp="frus1917Supp02v01#p_TAE1">Taylor</persName>’s 7923,
                            December 11, 4 p.m., and my 7990, December 17. Conference of Allies here
                            in London has just asked Dutch to furnish full information as to entire
                            Dutch merchant fleet. When this is obtained, when the exact ration
                            figures <pb facs="0404" n="1158" xml:id="pg_1158"/> are determined, and
                            when a calculation is made of the requirements of Dutch inter-colonial
                            trade, we will immediately calculate and cable a statement of the
                            remaining tonnage which is to be placed at the disposal of the Allies as
                            agreed between them. The British are very anxious to commence
                            immediately the discussion of the trades insisted upon. This surplus
                            Dutch tonnage will be used but as we have no authorized representatives
                            of the United States Shipping Board here it is very difficult for me to
                            conduct these discussions.</p>
                        <p>The British are also anxious to consider a second <hi rend="italic">modus
                                vivendi</hi> which might supplement my first or in case the first
                            fails replace it which would call into immediate operation additional
                            Dutch vessels principally those now in Dutch ports. As this proposed
                            British <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> involves allocating
                            considerable Dutch tonnage in various trades I am again considerably
                            handicapped by lack of instructions and by not having in London a
                            representative of the Shipping Board.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="frus1917Supp02v01#p_PWH1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Page</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>