<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-08-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-08-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="295" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 654.119/10</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The French Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="frus1917Supp02v01#p_JJJ2" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Jusserand</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d295fn1">A similar communication was received
                                from the Italian Ambassador Sept. 8 (File No. 654.119/15). A British
                                memorandum received Sept. 8 endorsed the position of the French
                                Government (File No. 654.119/14).</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-08-25">
                                    <hi rend="italic">August 25, 1917</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received August 29.</hi>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: My Government informs
                            me that upon the recommendation of the International Commission on
                            Quotas that has been approved by the Allied Governments represented
                            thereon, it has been decided to set the quota of machine tools for
                            Switzerland at zero. The measure is intended to prevent the Swiss
                            factories that are working for the enemy from receiving appliances which
                            they could put to that use.</p>
                        <p>On the other hand, it is important to have exceptions made in favor of
                            the factories that are working for the Allies. To accomplish this the
                            Government of the Republic suggests that the following principle be
                            adopted: No machine tools will be allowed to be exported to Switzerland
                            without a permit from the French and Italian Commissions on Exceptions;
                            these commissions furthermore would not allow the passage through the
                            territory of their respective countries except upon investigations by
                            and the recommendation of the technical departments of the Allied
                            Legations at Berne. The transit license issued by them in such cases
                            would constitute a certificate of legitimate destination which should be
                            taken into account in the exporting country. The Allied technical
                            departments at Berne would thus be relieved of any actual accountability
                            for the refusals met by some applications, which they themselves would
                            not be called upon to render.</p>
                        <p>Since nearly all machine tools come from the United States at present, I
                            am instructed to inquire of Your Excellency whether the <pb facs="0420" n="1174" xml:id="pg_1174"/> Federal Government would be inclined to
                            concur in this procedure and only allow machine tools to be exported to
                            Switzerland when a transit license shall have been issued by the French
                            or Italian Commission on Exceptions, that is to say when a friendly
                            destination shall have been proved.</p>
                        <p>In emergency cases the transit license would be delivered at the American
                            Embassies at Paris or at Rome to enable them to notify by cable the
                            American customs that they should allow the machinery to go.</p>
                        <p>In asking me to formulate this request, my Government directs me to make
                            it clear that no decision will be reached with respect to such shipments
                            without a previous understanding among the Allied departments at Berne
                            and that it is only intended to utilize existing services in obtaining
                            the common goal, which is to prevent by every available means our
                            adversaries from making, through neutrals, use of the resources at the
                            command of the Allies.</p>
                        <p>I should be very thankful to Your Excellency if you would let me know at
                            your earliest convenience whether the Federal Government is, as the
                            French Government fondly hopes it is, disposed to concur in its views
                            and adopt the above-stated procedure.</p>
                        <p>Be pleased to accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="frus1917Supp02v01#p_JJJ2">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Jusserand</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>