<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Winant
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1027</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1027</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-26T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-26T20:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-26T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-26T20:00:00-05:00" n="1027" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1027">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860h.00/10–2245</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-26T20:00:00-05:00">October 26, 1945—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>9488. Deptel 9209 Oct 17. Molotov has now replied to our approach concerning
                    Yugoslav situation in writing along following lines:<note n="68" xml:id="d1027fn68">The Soviet reply was sent to the Department in telegram
                        3629, October 22, 1945, from Moscow, not printed. The substance as given
                        here is a close paraphrase of that telegram.</note>
                </p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>Soviet Govt believes there are no grounds for US, UK and Soviet Govts to make
                        any proposals to Yugos Govt on question of collaboration between Tito and
                        Subasic; in addition there is no basis for interference of these three Govts
                        in question of date of Yugps elections; and Soviet Govt takes position that
                        Yugos Govt should be permitted to decide question whether it is proper to
                        postpone elections set for Nov 11 to a later date.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>In view of this unwillingness of Soviet Govt to participate in tripartite
                    representations, Dept now suggests that US and UK Govts consider addressing
                    parallel communications to Marshal Tito and Dr. Subasic setting forth the
                    attitude of the two Govts in the circumstances in the following sense: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The US Govt has been following developments in post-liberation
                            Yugoslavia with particular attention in the light of the responsibility
                            toward the people of Yugoslavia assumed by the US in conjunction with
                            her Brit and Soviet allies at Yalta. The three signatories to the Crimea
                            Declaration recommended in that Declaration that the agreement between
                            Marshal Tito on behalf of the National Committee of Liberation and Dr.
                            Subasic on behalf of the Royal Yugoslav Govt be put into effect
                            immediately. That agreement provided for the establishment of a unified
                            Govt containing adherents of both parties to exercise the executive
                            authority pending the decision by a freely elected Constituent Assembly
                            on the final constitutional organization of the state. The agreement
                            further called for specific guarantees of <pb facs="1287" n="1275" xml:id="pg_1275"/> personal freedom, freedom from fear, liberty of
                            conscience, freedom of speech, liberty of the press, and freedom of
                            assembly and association.</p>
                        <p>“Elections for a Constituent Assembly have been announced for Nov 11,
                            1945. However, owing to failure effectively to implement these
                            guarantees, conditions have now been created in Yugoslavia under which a
                            single list of candidates representative of only one section of the
                            electorate will be presented for endorsement on that occasion. In
                            addition, the elections will be conducted and the votes counted by local
                            Liberation Committees and judicial organs of which the controlling
                            membership has been appointed by and is consequently overwhelmingly
                            responsive to the leaders of one faction. Finally? in view of these
                            conditions, one of the contracting parties to the Tito–Subasic agreement
                            has felt called upon to resign from the unified Govt, together with his
                            supporting colleagues.</p>
                        <p>“The US Govt believes that the developments outlined above demonstrate
                            conclusively that a situation has arisen inimical to the exercise of
                            democratic processes and prejudicial to the validity, as a free and
                            untrammelled expression of the will of all democratic elements of the
                            people, of the elections now contemplated. Accordingly, it profoundly
                            hopes that Marshal Tito and Dr. Subasic together with the leaders of
                            other democratic groups in Yugoslavia will spare no effort to find, in
                            direct negotiations between themselves or, if they so desire, in concert
                            with the US, Soviet and Brit Govts or such of them as are willing to
                            assist therein, a means of agreement by which the basis for the
                            collaboration of all democratic elements in Yugoslavia in a united
                            interim Govt may be reestablished to the satisfaction of all parties and
                            with effective provision for the unequivocal execution of the guarantees
                            contained in their previous accord. Pending the achievement of this end,
                            the US Govt urges that the elections scheduled for Nov 11 be postponed
                            to a later date.</p>
                        <p>“It may be noted that before communicating the foregoing views, the US
                            Govt has consulted the other signatories to the Yalta Declaration. The
                            Brit Govt has indicated that it takes a similar attitude and will
                            transmit similar communications. However, the Soviet Govt has taken the
                            position that no grounds exist for the three Govts to make any proposals
                            in this matter, that in addition there is no basis for interference of
                            the three Govts in the question of the date of the Yugos elections and
                            that the Yugos Govt itself should be permitted to decide the question
                            whether it is proper to postpone the elections set for Nov 11, to a
                            later date.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Please ascertain views of FonOff on foregoing and add that we further suggest
                    that notes in the above sense be addressed to Marshal Tito and Dr. Subasic by
                    the US and Brit Ambs in Belgrade on Nov 1.</p>
                <p>For your information, Dept has indicated to Brit Emb our belief that it is
                    unadvisable (reurtel 11049 Oct 22) to ask for text of Subasic letter of
                    resignation.</p>
                <p>Sent to London; rptd to Moscow and to Belgrade.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
