<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="1048" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1048">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860h.00/12–645</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Yugoslavia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Patterson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 174</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Belgrade</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-06">December 6,
                                1945</date>.<lb/>[Received December 19.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose a
                                memorandum<note n="94" xml:id="d1048fn94">Not printed.</note>
                            concerning the Yugoslav elections to the Constituent Assembly on
                            November 11, 1945, <pb facs="1308" n="1296" xml:id="pg_1296"/> prepared
                            by Vice-Consul Peter Constan, containing evidence of the intimidation of
                            voters and commenting on the official election returns. The Embassy
                            believes that this and other evidence it has received justify Mr.
                            Constan’s conclusion that the elections of November 11 were the least
                            free ever held in Yugoslavia and that the results announced bear no
                            resemblance to the votes cast.</p>
                        <p>Embassy members visited some 20 polling places in Belgrade on election
                            day and saw practically no unfairness at these places. This apparent
                            decency was made much of in Yugoslav news releases, which freely quoted
                            statements of Left-Wing Members of Parliament and British journalists
                            brought here by the Yugoslav government to observe the elections. This
                            point, however, is unimportant in judging whether the elections gave the
                            people of Yugoslavia a free opportunity to express their will at the
                            polls. The decisive facts are that masses of people were frightened into
                            voting for the National Front ticket; that the election machinery was
                            entirely in the hands of the National Front; that there were no
                            opposition or neutral observers in a position to verify the results; and
                            that the unscrupulousness shown by the National Front in pre-election
                            activities supports the belief that its members showed equally low
                            ethical standards in submitting election returns.</p>
                        <p>The Embassy has received masses of detailed figures from unofficial
                            observers indicating that in all localities reported upon the official
                            returns were untrue. There is reason to believe that many, at least, of
                            these reports are true since they come from observers in villages where
                            the inhabitants are personally known to them.</p>
                        <p>Before the election several peasants came to the Embassy from
                            considerable distances to tell us of the situation in their home
                            villages. They generally told us that they came secretly and in fear of
                            Ozna to beg us not to recognize the results of the elections, since,
                            although nearly all the villagers were opposed to the regime, the
                            majority would probably vote for it out of fear of what might happen to
                            them or their families if they did not.</p>
                        <p>There is no good reason to doubt the evidence of intimidation reported by
                            Mr. Constan since even government leaders went so far as to publicly
                            state that it would be traitorous to vote against the Front. A threat of
                            this kind is quite sufficient to intimidate a voter when he is convinced
                            that his job, his clothing, food, shelter and freedom from prison for
                            himself and his family depend upon his being known as a supporter of the
                            National Front.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Constan’s memorandum contains much first hand information, including
                            examples of two Yugoslav soldiers of American birth whose registration
                            applications he had taken, and one of whom served twenty days in jail
                            for falling out of formation while his unit was being marched to the
                            polling booth to vote.</p>
                        <pb facs="1309" n="1297" xml:id="pg_1297"/>
                        <p>Mr. Constan offers the following comment on one Yugoslav propaganda item:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Tito is proclaiming that this was the freest and quietest
                                    election ever held in Yugoslavia. I submit that a deadly quiet
                                    election in the Balkans, and I have seen many of them during the
                                    last 25 years, is proof positive of the lack of freedom. When
                                    Balkanites cannot have a fight during an election it means that
                                    they are afraid to speak their minds. As a matter of fact, in
                                    what part of the world, where freedom reigns, do people walk
                                    along silently and solemnly and separately, without the
                                    slightest show of demonstration, on an election day?”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>There was, as the Yugoslav press announced, dancing in the streets far
                            into the evening of election day, but its lack of the usual spontaneity
                            indicated that numbers were dancing, as they had voted, under duress.
                            Teraziye Square, Belgrade, on election night was reminiscent of a Times
                            Square, New York, election night only because of the contrast.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Patterson,
                                    Jr</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>