<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of First Meeting Regarding the Polish Question
                    Meeting held at the Department of State, April
                        22, 1945, 9:50 p.m. to 11:40 p.m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d193</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">193</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-04-22T20:50:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-04-22T22:40:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="diplomatic-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomatic relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-22T22:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-22T20:50:00-05:00" n="193" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860C.01/4–2245</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of First Meeting Regarding the Polish Question</hi>
                    <note n="65" xml:id="d193fn65">Meeting held at the Department of State, April
                        22, 1945, 9:50 p.m. to 11:40 p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" from="1945-04-22T21:50:00-04:00" to="1945-04-22T23:40:00-04:00">April 22,
                        1945, 9:50 p.m. to 11:40 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Principal Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Stettinius</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Eden</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Molotov</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Dunn</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Harriman</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Sir Alexander Cadogan<note n="66" xml:id="d193fn66">British Permanent Under Secretary of State for
                                Foreign Affairs.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Sir Archibald Clark-Kerr</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>(The first part of the Polish discussion, in which Mr. Eden and Mr. Stettinius
                    emphasized the extreme displeasure of the British and American Governments at
                    the signing of the mutual aid pact with the Warsaw Poles etc., was not recorded
                    since the officer assigned to this task was called out on other urgent
                    business.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> stated that in the message the Prime Minister
                    and the President sent to Marshal Stalin on April 18, the text of which Mr.
                    Molotov has asked for, our position was made quite clear regarding the position
                    the Warsaw Government was to play in the new Provisional Government. He then
                    read the following passage from the message: “We have never denied that among
                    the three elements from which the new Provisional Government of National Unity
                    is to be formed the representatives of the present Warsaw Government will play,
                    unquestionably, a prominent part.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that the Crimea decision says more
                    than that. It stipulates that the present Provisional Government in Poland is to
                    be reorganized. The Crimea decision, on the other hand, does not refer to the
                    Polish Government-in-exile in London, instead it favors the Provisional
                    Government in Warsaw. The American and British Governments on the other hand
                    have assumed the attitude that the Warsaw Government is just one of the elements
                    which is to be used to make up the new Government of National Unity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> pointed out that at Crimea we tried to lay
                    the basis for the formation of a new government in Poland to be made up in part
                    from Poles inside and outside of Poland. He added that when Mr. Molotov has had
                    a chance to read the joint message from the Prime Minister and the President, he
                    will see that there are new proposals set forth therein which form a practical
                    basis to bring about a creation of a new Government of National Unity.</p>
                <pb facs="0250" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> stated that he would like to see the
                    message in order to study it more carefully.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Stettinius</hi> stated that in this connection he
                    desired to read the next to the last paragraph of the Crimea declaration on
                    Poland. The following paragraph was read to Mr. Molotov: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“When a Polish Provisional Government of National Unity has been properly
                            formed in conformity with the above, the government of the U.S.S.R.,
                            which now maintains diplomatic relations with the present provisional
                            government of Poland, and the government of the United Kingdom and the
                            government of the U.S.A. will establish diplomatic relations with the
                            new Polish Provisional Government of National Unity, and will exchange
                            ambassadors by whose reports the respective governments will be kept
                            informed about the situation in Poland.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">He pointed out that this paragraph is very clear and most
                    important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that he agreed that this paragraph
                    is very clear, but added that the declaration also points out how we can
                    establish a new Polish Government of National Unity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> brought out the fact that the new Treaty of
                    Mutual Assistance just signed between the Polish and Soviet Governments
                    indicates that the Soviet Government is satisfied with the present Warsaw
                    Government which was certainly not the idea expressed in the Yalta declaration
                    and is certainly not the idea of the British Government and he believed that it
                    was not the idea of the American Government, both of which made it quite clear
                    that they desired to see established a new government in Poland. He added that
                    the fact that the Soviet Government had signed this treaty with the present
                    Warsaw regime was most disquieting to his Government and he believed also to the
                    Government of the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Stettinius</hi> confirmed Mr. Eden’s statement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that it cannot be denied that the
                    Warsaw Government is the only one now functioning in Poland. He added that of
                    course it would be desirable to arrive at an agreement which would meet the
                    views of the three Governments, but stated that developments continue to take
                    place and that Germany has found herself in a more difficult position since
                    Crimea. Under these circumstances the wishes of the Polish and Soviet peoples to
                    satisfy their desires to assist each other is understandable. He stated that if
                    a new Polish Government of National Unity is formed, no one cold imagine that
                    such a new Polish government would refuse to accept the treaty which has just
                    been signed with the Soviet Union. He pointed out, in this connection, that
                    Poland does not border on the United States and it also does not represent a
                    gateway through which <pb facs="0251" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/> aggressors could
                    attack the United States and the same applies to Great Britain. He stated that
                    in the position in which the American and British Governments are they can put
                    off questions for future consideration but the Soviet Government is in a
                    different position. It is not able to postpone questions but must consolidate
                    and improve relations brought about by the common struggle against Germany. He
                    stated that the United States and Great Britain would act in the same way if
                    they were in the same position as the Soviet Government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Stettinius</hi> stated that Mr. Molotov desired to
                    study the joint message and he asked Mr. Eden if there were any other questions
                    he would like to discuss at this time and added that we all desire to settle
                    this question in an amicable way, as Mr. Molotov had pointed out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that he agreed but he desired to
                    study the message.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Stettinius</hi> pointed out that we must get a solution
                    of this problem before San Francisco.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> added that while it was realized that Mr.
                    Molotov must study the message, we must make progress in these negotiations as
                    Mr. Stettinius had indicated since we have built the San Francisco Conference on
                    a collaboration basis and unless we can show the world that this collaboration
                    is real, the San Francisco Conference will suffer.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that we must do that but it should
                    be taken into account that we must fulfill the Crimea decisions as agreed upon.
                    He added that so far what has happened is that Poland has been refused
                    permission to send a delegate to San Francisco which is a very bad start.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Stettinius</hi> emphasized that we must bear in mind
                    that this is the case since no new Polish Government of National Unity has been
                    established. In other words, no government has been organized in Poland which we
                    can recognize. He reiterated the fact that the United States Government does not
                    want or intend to go against the Crimea decision.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> pointed out that of course everyone
                    respected the Governments of Bolivia and Haiti, for instance, and was pleased
                    that representatives of these countries would be at San Francisco. On the other
                    hand, it is regrettable that Poland would not be represented.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Stettinius</hi> pointed out that we would of course be
                    pleased to receive representatives of the new Polish Government of National
                    Unity at San Francisco.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that it would be hard to create a
                    new Polish government in Washington without any Poles being present here.</p>
                <pb facs="0252" n="240" xml:id="pg_240"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> retorted that it was also hard to create a
                    new Polish government in Moscow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> agreed that it had proved difficult to do
                    this in Moscow even with Poles nearby.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Stettinius</hi> emphasized the great importance that
                    the United States Government attaches to the question of the settlement of the
                    Polish problem. If we can’t make some concrete progress before the San Francisco
                    Conference it will have a very adverse effect on American public opinion and we,
                    therefore, might find it difficult to obtain the consent of the American people
                    to join the world organization. He then asked whether Mr. Eden and Mr. Molotov
                    would desire to resume the discussion tomorrow as planned or whether it would be
                    best to invite Dr. Soong to come to the meeting in order to discuss procedural
                    problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> replied that the most urgent matter was to
                    obtain Mr. Molotov’s reactions to the joint message of the Prime Minister and
                    the President and that if it should be possible to agree on the problems set
                    forth therein it would then be possible to discuss other matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that he would like to do this but
                    asked whether Mr. Stalin’s message could serve as a basis for the
                    discussions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> pointed out that the joint message is a reply
                    to Stalin’s message and represents our position and goes as far as we can go to
                    meet Stalin’s problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that he felt that if we were to
                    study carefully Stalin’s message we could draw some useful conclusions since
                    this message set forth the position of the Soviet Government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> stated that the joint message set forth our
                    reply to the position of the Soviet Government as outlined in Stalin’s
                    message.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>, in stating that he did not remember the
                    exact wording of the joint reply, asked if there were any statement therein
                    indicating that Stalin’s message cannot be used as a basis. He added that
                    perhaps we can discuss this question tomorrow since it seemed to him that
                    Stalin’s message was a very suitable basis and pointed out he was referring to
                    the practical suggestions contained therein.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> stated that when Mr. Molotov reads the joint
                    message he will see how far we have gone to meet Stalin’s ideas and he will see
                    how helpful our suggestions are.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that Marshal Stalin had recently
                    given very careful study to the Polish question including the matter of the
                    conclusion of the Treaty of Mutual Assistance and he attaches great importance
                    to his ideas as set forth in his message.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Stettinius</hi> asked when it would be desirable to
                    hold the next <pb facs="0253" n="241" xml:id="pg_241"/> meeting and it was
                    finally agreed that they should get together at 10:30 the morning of April
                    23.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
