<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-03-13T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-03-13T16:00:00-05:00" n="373" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d373">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Rumania)/3–1445:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-03-14T00:00:00+03:00">March 14,
                                    1945—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received March 15—11:47
                                a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>756. In accordance with the Department’s 569, March 12, 8 p.m., I have
                            today addressed to Molotov concerning our attitude to the situation in
                            Rumania, a formal note embodying the request set forth in the
                            Department’s message. I am stating in this note that a similar proposal
                            is being made to the British Government.</p>
                        <p>I believe we should recognize that if we are successful in arranging for
                            such a consultation here that we will face a considered and
                            predetermined policy established not by Molotov alone but by the higher
                            Soviet Governmental and party authorities. This policy is probably in
                            line with their long-range plans established some time ago for the
                            Balkan and eastern European states. The most, therefore, that we can
                            expect, at least in the early stages of the discussions, is a chance to
                            repeat orally and in greater detail the views which have already been
                            set forth to Molotov in my letters and which Berry and General Schuyler
                            have outlined to Soviet officials in Rumania. I recognize that the
                            Rumanian situation is in many ways secondary in importance to Poland and
                            if we come to a point in our relations with the Soviet Government where
                            we feel we must make a major issue I believe that we would be on firmer
                            grounds to do so in connection with <pb facs="0524" n="512" xml:id="pg_512"/> Poland. Also, a serious and public issue over
                            Rumania might prejudice our chances of a reasonable settlement regarding
                            Poland. On the other hand, I heartily concur with the Department’s firm
                            position taken in regard to Rumania and agree that we should not give in
                            and not let the situation go by default, but should continue to keep it
                            open and press for a satisfactory solution along the lines the
                            Department has set forth.</p>
                        <p>Should these consultations materialize, would the Department consider
                            detailing Berry to proceed here to act as my adviser while they are in
                            progress? I think it would be valuable to have someone who has a
                            thorough knowledge of conditions on the spot and who can speak with
                            authority in questions of fact, since the Soviet policy will undoubtedly
                            be founded on the thesis that our information is incorrect.</p>
                        <p>Sent to Department as 756, repeated to Bucharest as 45 and to London as
                            118.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>