<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        American Representative in Rumania (
                        Berry
                    )Parallel instructions were sent to
                        Ambassador Harriman in telegram 826, April 9, 7 p.m. This telegram stated
                        that the British Embassy in Washington had informed the Department of State
                        that the British Ambassador in Moscow had been instructed to advise Molotov
                        that the British were ready to terminate the sanctuary given to General
                        Radescu if there were categorical assurances that the Allied Control
                        Commission would take all necessary steps to protect Radescu. Ambassador
                        Harriman was instructed to make no representations to the Soviet Government
                        in favor of the British approach, but was authorized to state the American
                        Government’s attitude as given in the Department’s instructions
                        (871.00/3–645).</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d389</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">389</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-04-09T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-04-09T18:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="civil-rights" subject="civil-rights" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371" lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-09T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-09T18:00:00-05:00" n="389" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d389">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">871.00/3–645: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        American Representative in Rumania</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Berry</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="53" xml:id="d389fn53">Parallel instructions were sent to
                        Ambassador Harriman in telegram 826, April 9, 7 p.m. This telegram stated
                        that the British Embassy in Washington had informed the Department of State
                        that the British Ambassador in Moscow had been instructed to advise Molotov
                        that the British were ready to terminate the sanctuary given to General
                        Radescu if there were categorical assurances that the Allied Control
                        Commission would take all necessary steps to protect Radescu. Ambassador
                        Harriman was instructed to make no representations to the Soviet Government
                        in favor of the British approach, but was authorized to state the American
                        Government’s attitude as given in the Department’s instructions
                        (871.00/3–645).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-09T19:00:00-04:00">April 9, 1945—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>180. ReDeptel 114, March 9. The British Embassy has informed the Department that
                    AVM Stevenson has been instructed by the British Government to request in ACC
                    that Soviet authorities agree to take necessary measures to ensure safety of
                    General Radescu in the event that he leaves the British Mission. The British
                    Government has requested the United States Government to send instructions to
                    General Schuyler to support Stevenson in this matter when it is brought before
                    the ACC.</p>
                <p>The Embassy is being advised that you and Schuyler are authorized, when the
                    question is raised, to inform the Rumanian and Soviet authorities, respectively,
                    that it is our view that the Rumanian Government should be required by the ACC
                    to give assurances that necessary measures will be taken to ensure that Rumanian
                    political leaders who are not demonstrably Quislings or collaborationists are
                    not subjected to physical violence, persecution or deprivation of civil rights.
                    We consider that these assurances would cover the case of Radescu in the event
                    that he should leave the British Legation.<note n="54" xml:id="d389fn54">Telegram 328, May 7, from Bucharest, reported that former Prime Minister
                        Radescu was scheduled to leave the British Mission the same day and return
                        to his home following “rather feeble assurances” from Rumanian and Soviet
                        authorities as to his safety; after consultation between the British and
                        American Missions, it was decided that it would be undesirable for any
                        American action to be taken on the matter (871.00/5–745).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Repeated to Moscow and Caserta.<note n="55" xml:id="d389fn55">Repeated to Moscow
                        as 827, and to Caserta as 313.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stetttnius</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
