<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Harriman) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d480</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">480</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-01-05T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-01-05T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-05T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-05T12:00:00-05:00" n="480"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d480">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">871.6363/1–545: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-05T20:00:00+03:00"
                            >January 5, 1945—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received January 6—11:40 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>55. ReEmb’s 4979, December 24, 6 p.m.<note n="52" xml:id="d480fn52">For text of
                        this telegram, which reported the delivery to the Soviet Foreign Affairs
                        Commissariat of a letter dated December 24, 1944, setting forth American
                        proposals regarding the question of the removal of Rumanian oil equipment to
                        the USSR, see <ref target="frus1944v04#pg_288">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 288</ref>.</note> I have received today
                    a letter from Vyshinski,<note n="53" xml:id="d480fn53">Andrey Yanuaryevich
                        Vyshinsky, First Deputy Peopled Commissar for Foreign Affairs of the Soviet
                        Union.</note> dated January 4, on the subject of the removal of Rumanian oil
                    equipment in answer to the letter which I addressed to him on December 24. The
                    reply states that since the Germans delivered pipe and other oil equipment to
                    Rumanian oil enterprises in order to supply their own military and para military
                    units with oil products thereby obtained, such property obviously falls within
                    the terms of paragraph 2 of the armistice agreement<note n="54"
                        xml:id="d480fn54">For text of the Allied armistice with Rumania, signed at
                        Moscow, 5 a.m., September 13 (as of September 12), 1944, see Department of
                        State Executive Agreement Series No. 490, or 59 Stat. (pt. 2) 1712; for
                        documentation regarding the negotiation of the armistice, see <ref
                            target="frus1944v04#pg_133">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 133</ref> ff.</note> and the Soviet
                    Government sees no grounds for changing its view on this point. The Soviet
                    Government has in mind, however, the interests and needs of the Rumanian oil
                    industry and is prepared to meet our wishes in this respect. Vinogradov<note
                        n="55" xml:id="d480fn55">Lt. Gen. Vladimir Petrovich Vinogradov, Deputy
                        Chairman (Soviet) of the Allied Control Commission for Rumania.</note> has
                    accordingly given orders to cease further removal of such equipment from Rumania
                    to the USSR.</p>
                <p>The information at the disposal of this Embassy with respect to what has actually
                    taken place in Rumania along these lines is so fragmentary and out of date that
                    I am unable to comment on this reply. The last information I have with respect
                    to loadings and removal of this equipment is to the effect that loading of
                    tubing and casing was resumed on November 26. I have no knowledge of what has
                    happened since that date.</p>
                <p>I am also hesitant in these circumstances to address any further communication to
                    Vyshinski with respect to our proposal for a tripartite commission, which he
                    ignores in his reply. I would be glad to be informed whether this proposal has
                    in the meantime been the subject of any further discussions in Rumania.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Amrep Bucharest<note n="56" xml:id="d480fn56">Burton Y. Berry,
                        American Representative in Rumania, stationed at Bucharest.</note> as 3,
                    January 5, 8 p.m.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
