<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Department of State to the
                            British Embassy</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d497</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">497</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="497" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d497">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">741.52/3–1345</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">British Embassy</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department has given careful consideration to the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of the British Embassy dated March 13, 1945,<note n="11" xml:id="d497fn11">Not printed.</note> setting forth the general lines of
                    British policy toward Spain.</p>
                <p>This Government is in substantial agreement with the British Government’s
                    statement of policy toward the present Spanish regime and the Falange Party. It
                    considers that while the present regime remains in power it will be difficult
                    for Spain to assume its proper role and responsibilities in the field of
                    international cooperation and understanding. While this Government and the
                    American people entertain the most friendly feelings toward the Spanish people
                    and desire a development of genuinely cordial relations between the United
                    States and Spain, public sentiment in this country is profoundly opposed to the
                    present Spanish Government, both because of its policies and acts, which until
                    recently have been distinctly unfriendly to the interests of the United States,
                    and because that Government and the Falange Party were founded on undemocratic
                    principles.</p>
                <p>This Government considers that the form of government in Spain and the policies
                    pursued by that Government are the concern of the Spanish people, and it is not
                    the policy of this Government in normal circumstances to interfere in the
                    internal affairs of other countries. It shares the hope of the British
                    Government however, that any successor regime in Spain will be based on
                    democratic principles, moderate in tendency, stable, and not indebted for its
                    existence to any outside influences.</p>
                <p>A tranquil Spain is desirable, from the standpoint of international cooperation,
                    and a recurrence of civil strife in Spain could only militate against the
                    general postwar objectives of reestablishing peace and order in Europe and of
                    rehabilitating devastated areas. In the general interest therefore, and in the
                    particular interest of the Spanish people any tendencies toward renewed disorder
                    in Spain would be regretted.</p>
                <p>This Government fully agrees that there should be a close coordination of policy
                    between it and the British Government respecting Spain. The policy of the United
                    States Government toward the Franco regime, described hi the foregoing
                    paragraphs, has been followed by this Government without deviation for a long
                    time. There have been no acts of this Government or public utterances of its
                    officials on the subject at variance with that policy. It is not thought
                    possible that General Franco or his Government can be under any <pb facs="0685" n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/> misapprehension respecting the views of this
                    Government or of the American people toward the Spanish Government and the
                    Falange Party. These views have been expressed to General Franco and to his
                    Foreign Ministers repeatedly and with clarity over a considerable period of
                    time.</p>
                <p>In the circumstances, the Department of State is at a loss co understand why the
                    United Kingdom Government would take seriously enough to include in its
                    memorandum the reported allegations of the Spanish Government that United States
                    feelings toward it are less hostile than those of the United Kingdom
                    Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-06">April 6,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
