<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Chief of the Division of Northern
                    European Affairs ( (Cumming))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d568</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">568</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-01-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recZobsyHhwdJPklD" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085246"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Occupied territory</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recfZWpZzigwQIfjx" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002653"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airline</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="568"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d568">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.79658/1–1745</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Chief of the Division of Northern European Affairs</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cumming</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, [<date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-27">January 27,
                            1945</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In accordance with travel orders already issued
                    to you, you are directed immediately to proceed to Stockholm to assist the
                    American Minister, the Honorable Herschel Johnson, in the negotiation of an
                    agreement with the Swedish Government for the establishment of Air Transport
                    Command services to, through, and away from Sweden. You will journey to
                    Stockholm by air, accompanied by representatives of the United States Army Air
                    Forces who will be appointed by the War Department to act as technical
                    advisers.</p>
                <p>The nature of the proposals which the War Department desires to have made to the
                    Swedish Government and which are approved by the Department are as follows:</p>
                <p>[Here follow the specific proposals which, with certain modifications and
                    additions, are contained in the note of March 12 from the <pb facs="0760"
                        n="748" xml:id="pg_748"/> American Minister in Sweden to the Swedish
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs, printed on <ref target="#pg_753">page
                    753</ref>.]</p>
                <p>You will arrange with Mr. Johnson to keep the Department and the War Department
                    fully informed regarding the progress of the negotiations. No final agreement
                    should be signed without specific approval of the Department and the War
                    Department.</p>
                <p>The War Department considers that the pseudo-civilian air service, known as the
                        AATS,<note n="57" xml:id="d568fn57">Army Air Transport Service.</note> which
                    the Air Transport Command now operates between the United Kingdom and Sweden, to
                    be unsatisfactory from an operational standpoint. The aircraft must have
                    civilian markings and be registered with the Civil Aereonautics Administration.
                    This destroys the flexibility of the fleet of aircraft operated by the Air
                    Transport Command since only planes having civilian markings may be flown on the
                    AATS route between the United Kingdom and Sweden. It also leads to a disruption
                    of the flying schedules, for an Air Transport Command aircraft with regular
                    United States Army Air Forces insignia cannot be substituted for an AATS plane
                    when it requires repairs. The AATS aircraft do not have type and prototype
                    certificates, thereby making it necessary for them to be based outside of the
                    United States and preventing them from returning to this country for extensive
                    repairs and overhauling. Although members of the United States Armed Forces, the
                    crews operating the AATS aircraft wear civilian clothes. They therefore run the
                    risk of being executed as spies by the Germans, should a plane be shot down over
                    enemy-occupied territory. Finally, it is obviously advantageous to the Air
                    Transport Command to operate its own meteorological stations rather than be
                    dependent upon the British and Swedish authorities for weather data as must be
                    done at the present time. The aforementioned handicaps to efficient flying
                    operation would not exist if the Swedish Government would agree to the
                    establishment of regular Air Transport Command services to, through, and away
                    from Sweden.</p>
                <p>Should the Swedish authorities inquire during the course of the negotiations as
                    to reasons why the Air Transport Command proposes to charge for certain
                    transportation services, thereby likening it to a commercial air transportation
                    entity, you should inform them that this Government does not consider that the
                    charging of rates for the services offered in any way makes the present AATS
                    operation or the proposed Air Transport Command services commercial in
                    character, and that it has no intention of engaging in the general business of
                    air transportation for hire. The Secretary of War<note n="58" xml:id="d568fn58"
                        >Henry L. Stimson.</note> has officially informed the Secretary of State
                    that the Executive Order authorizing <pb facs="0761" n="749" xml:id="pg_749"/>
                    the Air Transport Command to charge for the transportation of non-military
                    passengers and freight is of an emergency and temporary nature. He has
                    furthermore stated that the air transportation requirements of the Armed Forces
                    greatly exceed the capacity of the Air Transport Command and that the Executive
                    Order merely authorized it to use, for official and civilian travel on missions
                    of importance to the over-all war effort, in relief and rehabilitation
                    activities and in expediting a return to peace-time conditions, such small
                    amounts of space as may from time to time be available and when such use does
                    not interfere with the needs of the Armed Forces. You should furthermore impress
                    upon the Swedish authorities that neither the AAT service nor the proposed Air
                    Transport Command services should be considered as operating in competition with
                    the ABA<note n="59" xml:id="d568fn59">AB Aereotransport, Swedish air
                        line.</note> or any other commercial airline.</p>
                <p>The aforegoing instruction has been approved by the War Department.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Acting Secretary of State: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James C. Dunn</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
