<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Acheson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d610</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">610</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="610"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d610">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5431/11–3045</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Acheson</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-30">November 30,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Swiss Minister called at my request. I read to him the principal paragraphs
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> of November 30, and handed him the
                        paper.<note n="49" xml:id="d610fn49">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi>
                    </note> We then discussed the situation for some time. The Minister made the
                    following points.</p>
                <pb facs="0813" n="801" xml:id="pg_801"/>
                <p>1. The Minister stated that he had hoped that the situation could be worked out
                    by direct talks between the Swiss Watch Industry and the American Watch
                    Industry, but that he had been informed that any such discussions would be
                    regarded by the Department of Justice as in violation of the Anti-Trust
                        Act.<note n="50" xml:id="d610fn50">Enacted July 2, 1890; 26 Stat.
                        209.</note> I said that I was not informed about this, but that I could well
                    see that the Department of Justice might properly take this position.</p>
                <p>2. The Minister said that the Swiss Government had gotten the impression from
                    statements made by American representatives of the Watch Industry in Switzerland
                    that the request for a limitation of imports was connected with the request for
                    the release of certain Swiss watch-making machinery and that, if the release
                    were granted, the request for the limitation of imports would be dropped.</p>
                <p>I said that this was not the case and that, while the matters were quite
                    separate, we felt that the Swiss had not been cooperative in regard to the
                    machinery.</p>
                <p>3. The Minister claimed that, without any limitation of imports, the American
                    Industry could make and sell watches up to the full capacity of its plants.</p>
                <p>I told him that we did not share this view—for one reason, because I understood
                    that the capacity of the watch-case makers had been fully taken up by importers
                    of Swiss watch movements.</p>
                <p>I explained to the Minister that, in connection with the passage of the Trade
                    Agreements Act,<note n="51" xml:id="d610fn51">Enacted June 12, 1934; 48 Stat.
                        943.</note> the President had assured American industry that it was not his
                    intention that any industry or portion of an industry should suffer injury
                    through the administration of the Act. The American Watch Industry had been
                    diverted to war production during the war and was experiencing difficulty in
                    returning to its peace-time production by reason of the very great volume of
                    Swiss imports. It seemed to me that the long-run interests of both countries
                    would be furthered if a reasonable attitude were taken so that the American
                    industry might get back to producing the comparatively small portion of the
                    American consumption of which it was capable. Any other attitude would produce
                    bitterness and resentment and might well cause the Congress to take action which
                    would not be carefully adjusted to the situation.</p>
                <p>The Minister agreed to report to his Government and to discuss the matter
                    further.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
