<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Eastern European
                        Affairs (
                        Durbrow
                    ) to the Director of Naval Intelligence of the Navy
                        Department (
                        Thebaud
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d619</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">619</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="visas" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436" lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="619" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d619">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.3361/1–2045</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Eastern European
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Durbrow</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of Naval Intelligence of the Navy
                        Department</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Thebaud</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-07">February 7,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Telegram 132, January 15, from Moscow and telegram 194,
                    January 20, from Moscow to Secretary of State<note n="10" xml:id="d619fn10">Telegram 194 not printed.</note> (paraphrases of which have been handed to
                    Major Wylie).</p>
                <p>It will be noted that the Embassy in Moscow regards the backlog of visas
                    requested for United States naval and military personnel as having been cleared
                    up and asks authority to issue visas in all outstanding cases of Soviet naval
                    personnel. This authorization was given and there is now only one case
                    outstanding, that of Lieutenant Captain Lulakov whose case was referred to the
                    Navy January 26 (memorandum 38<note n="11" xml:id="d619fn11">Memorandum 38,
                        January 22, 1945, not printed.</note>).</p>
                <p>The Embassy feels that the action which has been taken to date has had
                    considerable effect and has resulted in the Soviets bringing up to date their
                    consideration of requests for visas for United States naval personnel. The
                    Embassy recommends, consequently, that no further action be taken on the
                    proposed visa agreement, stating that the British agreement along similar lines
                    has not proved in practice to be of any real value.</p>
                <p>The Department is inclined to agree with the Embassy’s recommendation and
                    suggests that no further action be taken in this connection unless new delays
                    occur in Soviet consideration of applications for naval personnel visas.<note n="12" xml:id="d619fn12">In a letter of March 19, 1945, the Acting Secretary
                        of the Navy, H. Struve Hensel, replied that the Navy Department concurred in
                        this recommendation but requested the Department of State to continue to
                        refer to the Navy Department individual applications for visas for Soviet
                        naval personnel in order that comment might be made on each case on the
                        basis of its merits. At the same time, the Navy Department withdrew its
                        objections to issuing a visa to Lieutenant Captain Lulakov.
                        (811.3361/3–1945)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Elbridge Durbrow</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
