<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Ambassador in the Soviet Union (
                    (Harriman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d628</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">628</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-04-13T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-04-13T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-13T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-13T12:00:00-05:00" n="628"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d628">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Moscow Embassy Files: 59A543, Part 6, Box 357,
                    Folder 39</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Ambassador in the Soviet
                        Union</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>)<note n="38" xml:id="d628fn38"
                        >Memorandum prepared by Edward Page, Second Secretary of Embassy.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-13T20:00:00+03:00"
                            >April 13, 1945—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Marshal Stalin</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">V. M. Molotov, People’s Commissar for Foreign
                            Affairs</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">[V. N.] Pavlov, Interpreter</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">W. A. Harriman, American Ambassador</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Edward Page</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>When I entered Marshal Stalin’s office I noticed that he was obviously deeply
                    distressed at the news of the death of President Roosevelt. He greeted me in
                    silence and stood holding my hand for about 30 seconds before asking me to sit
                    down.</p>
                <pb facs="0839" n="827" xml:id="pg_827"/>
                <p>He then asked me many questions about the President and the circumstances which
                    brought about his death. I explained that the President had heart trouble during
                    the last year; that Dr. MacIntyre had informed me that he might live for years
                    or die suddenly. From the information I had received it appeared that the
                    President had gone to Warm Springs for a rest. He was in excellent health and
                    intended to return to Washington forthwith. He had evidently had a stroke and
                    had passed away very suddenly. I commented that Marshal Stalin had probably
                    received the President’s last message,<note n="39" xml:id="d628fn39">See
                        telegram 229, April 12, from President Roosevelt to Marshal Stalin, <ref
                            target="frus1945v03#pg_756">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p.
                            756</ref>.</note> that is, the message that I had received last night at
                    12:30 and transmitted to Marshal Stalin. The President at that time was already
                    dead but when I had sent the message I was not aware of this fact.</p>
                <p>I stated that I had come to see Marshal Stalin with the thought that he might
                    wish to ask some questions as to the situation in the United States as a result
                    of the death of President Roosevelt. The Marshal stated that he did not believe
                    that there would be any change in policy. I said that I was convinced that this
                    would be true in so far as the war, foreign policy, and all those other policies
                    where the President had made his plans clear. I continued that I had explained
                    to Mr. Molotov last night why the President had selected Mr. Truman as Vice
                    President. Mr. Truman had always followed the President’s program and had
                    heartily supported all his views. Mr. Truman was a man Marshal Stalin would
                    like—he was a man of action and not of words. Mr. Molotov had noted that he had
                    not made many speeches. This was quite true—he was not an individual who sought
                    publicity. He had been in the United States Senate since 1936 and had gained the
                    highest respect from both political parties. The President knew that he would
                    need Senate approval of his peace plans, of Dumbarton Oaks,<note n="40"
                        xml:id="d628fn40">For the Dumbarton Oaks conversations, August 21–October 7,
                        1944, see <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_713">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 713</ref> ff.</note> and of other
                    important internal and foreign policies. This was one of the main reasons he had
                    chosen Senator Truman for his running mate. I said that I was satisfied that
                    President Truman would carry out President Roosevelt’s plans precisely as he
                    understood them. Marshal Stalin was pleased to hear this. I continued that
                    President Truman would not try to interject his own personality into future
                    policies but would have the courage to develop them. From the domestic
                    standpoint, he was a New Dealer—but perhaps in the center.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, I said that President Truman naturally could not have the
                    great prestige that President Roosevelt enjoyed at the time of his death. Until
                    he had become Vice President he was not especially well known in the United
                    States because he had never <pb facs="0840" n="828" xml:id="pg_828"/> sought
                    publicity. The same was true abroad. This, in my opinion, could not help but
                    cause a certain period of uncertainty, both internally and externally, not
                    necessarily about the conduct of the war but on all foreign and domestic policy
                    questions. The San Francisco Conference, for example, might well cause more
                    difficulties. The American people did not know whether President Truman could
                    carry through President Roosevelt’s program as the late President would have
                    done. However, it was my belief that President Truman would gain the complete
                    confidence of the American people.</p>
                <p>I said that I believed that Marshal Stalin could assist President Truman at this
                    time: this would facilitate in stabilizing the situation in the United States
                    and in solidifying him with the American people. The American people knew that
                    President Roosevelt and Marshal Stalin had close personal relations and that
                    this relationship had a great effect on United States-Soviet relations. Marshal
                    Stalin interjected, “President Roosevelt has died but his cause must live on. We
                    shall support President Truman with all our forces and all our will.” The
                    Marshall then requested me to inform President Truman accordingly.</p>
                <p>I stated that I was going to make a suggestion which might be impossible to
                    realize. I was thinking of what Marshal Stalin might do to help President
                    Truman, to stabilize the situation in America and to reduce the disturbances
                    which had been caused by the death of President Roosevelt. I said that I
                    believed that the most effective way to assure the American public and the world
                    at large of the desire of the Soviet Government to continue collaboration with
                    us and the other United Nations would be for Mr. Molotov to go to the United
                    States at this time. I suggested that he might stop in Washington to see the
                    President and then proceed to San Francisco even though he might remain there
                    only for a few days. I said that if it would assist, I felt sure that we would
                    be pleased to place a plane comparable to the plane in which President Roosevelt
                    had gone to the Crimea at the disposal of Mr. Molotov. The plane could, make the
                    trip to Washington in 36 hours. If Marshal Stalin so desired, I remarked
                    jokingly, we could paint a red star on the plane and man it with a mixed
                    Soviet-American crew. Marshal Stalin remarked that he would prefer a green star.
                    I continued that these planes could make the trip with great comfort and speed.
                    If Marshal Stalin desired, we would paint the entire aircraft green. During
                    these exchanges of remarks, Mr. Molotov kept muttering, “Time, time, time.”</p>
                <p>I continued that these were details connected with the trip. I could not find
                    words to express too strongly what it would mean to the American people and to
                    President Truman, what it would mean to our overall relations, especially at
                    this time in our great tragedy <pb facs="0841" n="829" xml:id="pg_829"/> if Mr.
                    Molotov could come to the United States. The entire world would regard his visit
                    as a great stabilizing influence.</p>
                <p>After a brief discussion between Mr. Molotov and Marshal Stalin as to the dates
                    of the San Francisco Conference and the convening of the Supreme Soviet, Marshal
                    Stalin inquired whether I was expressing my personal views. I made it clear that
                    I was but added that I felt completely confident that I was expressing the views
                    of the President and the Secretary of State and that I felt sure that they would
                    be ready to confirm what I had said. Marshal Stalin then stated categorically
                    that Mr. Molotov’s trip to the United States, although difficult at this time,
                    would be arranged. He made it clear, however, that this decision was based upon
                    my assurances that the President and the Secretary would renew the hope that it
                    would be possible for Mr. Molotov to come to Washington and San Francisco as
                    they considered his presence there at this time of real importance.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
