<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by Mr. Charles E.
                            Bohlen, Assistant to the Secretary of State for White House
                        Liaison, to the Secretary of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d631</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">631</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="631" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d631">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.61/4–1945</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Charles E.
                            Bohlen</persName>, Assistant to the Secretary of State for White House
                        Liaison, to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-19">April 19,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The following is a list of questions which Mr. Molotov may raise or which you
                    might wish to raise depending upon the course which the discussions take:<note n="44" xml:id="d631fn44">For discussions between President Truman and
                        Foreign Commissar Molotov on April 22 at 8:30 p.m., and on April 23 at 5:30
                        p.m., see the memoranda of conversations on these days by Charles E. Bohlen,
                            <ref target="#pg_235">pp. 235</ref> and <ref target="#pg_256">256</ref>,
                        respectively. For the President’s own account, see <hi rend="italic">Memoirs
                            by Harry S. Truman</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Year of Decisions</hi>, pp. 75–82.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Implementation of the Crimea Agreement on liberated areas in Rumania.<note n="45" xml:id="d631fn45">For the Declaration on Liberated Europe, see
                            the Communiqué issued at the end of the Crimea Conference, signed on
                            February 11, 1945, by Prime Minister Churchill, President Roosevelt, and
                            Marshal Stalin. <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_971">
                                <hi rend="italic">Conferences at Malta and Yalta</hi>, pp.
                                971</ref>–<ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_973">973</ref>. For
                            documentation on Rumania, see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_464">pp. 464</ref> ff.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Implementation of the Crimea Agreement on liberated areas in
                            Bulgaria.<note n="46" xml:id="d631fn46">For documentation on Bulgaria,
                            see <ref target="frus1945v04#pg_135">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>,
                                pp. 135</ref> ff.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Need for improvement of the American position on Allied Control
                        Commissions in satellite states.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Failure of the Soviet Government to provide facilities for the entry of
                        UNRRA and Red Cross personnel into Poland and the Balkans.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Failure of the Soviet Government to satisfy our requirements for full
                        advance information concerning transfers to third countries of supplies
                        furnished to the Soviet Union under Lend-Lease or supplies of Soviet origin
                        similar to Lend-Lease materials.<note n="47" xml:id="d631fn47">For
                            documentation, see <ref target="#pg_937">pp. 937</ref> ff.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The implementation of the Crimea Agreement regarding the exchange of
                        liberated prisoners of war and civilians.<note n="48" xml:id="d631fn48">For
                            text of this agreement, signed at Yalta on February 11, 1945, see <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_985">
                                <hi rend="italic">Conferences at Malta and Yalta</hi>, p. 985</ref>.
                            Concerning the carrying out of this agreement, see <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1067">pp. 1067</ref> ff.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The Kravchenko case.<note n="49" xml:id="d631fn49">For documentation, see
                                <ref target="#pg_1131">pp. 1131</ref> ff.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The Soviet request for a six billion dollar loan.<note n="50" xml:id="d631fn50">See telegram 29, January 4, 2 p.m., from Moscow, <ref target="#pg_942">p. 942</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Forthcoming meeting of the Separations Commission in Moscow.<note n="51" xml:id="d631fn51">For documentation, see <ref target="frus1945v03#pg_1169">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp.
                                1169</ref> ff. For the Protocol on Reparations signed at Yalta on
                            February 11, 1945, by Prime Minister Churchill, President Roosevelt, and
                            Marshal Stalin, see <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_982">
                                <hi rend="italic">Conferences at Malta and Yalta</hi>, 1945, p.
                                982</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Implementation of the Crimea Agreement on
                        Liberated Areas in Rumania</hi>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Basic Facts</hi>.</p>
                <p>At the end of February a political crisis developed in Rumania, largely as a
                    result of a campaign by the Left-wing parties under Communist leadership, aided
                    by measures taken by the Soviet military authorities <pb facs="0845" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/> and encouraged by Soviet radio and press propaganda. After
                    some disorders took place in Rumanian cities Vyshinski<note n="52" xml:id="d631fn52">Andrey Yanuaryevich Vyshinsky, Assistant People’s
                        Commissar for Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union.</note> arrived in
                    Bucharest and forced the King<note n="53" xml:id="d631fn53">Michael I.</note> to
                    dismiss Premier Radescu and to accept a government headed by Groza<note n="54" xml:id="d631fn54">Petru Groza, leader of the Plowman’s Front.</note> and
                    including only representatives of the left-wing parties together with a few
                    opportunist politicians formerly associated with the historic parties, which
                    were now excluded from the government. Vyshinsky’s direct intervention took
                    place without consultation with American and British representatives. The Groza
                    Government has been in office since March 6. Developments since that date have
                    not changed our view that it is an unrepresentative minority government and that
                    the political situation should be stabilized.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Exchange of Views Between the United States and Soviet
                        Governments.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>During the crisis we made known our views to the Soviet Government on several
                    occasions. Ambassador Harriman presented three notes referring to the
                    Declaration on Liberated Europe, requesting the Soviet views, and suggesting
                    consultation. In its replies the Soviet Government stated that the action taken
                    was made necessary by the Radescu Government’s failure to fulfil the armistice
                        terms<note n="55" xml:id="d631fn55">For armistice with Rumania signed at
                        Moscow, 5 a.m., September 13 (as of September 12), 1944, see Department of
                        State Executive Agreement Series No. 490, or 59 Stat. (pt. 2) 1712.</note>
                    and by the intolerable situation existing in the rear of the Red Army. On March
                    14 we formally proposed tripartite consultation under the provision of the Yalta
                    Declaration calling for concerted Allied policies to assure in the former Axis
                    satellites interim governments broadly representative of all democratic elements
                    in the population. The British Government agreed to the proposal. Mr. Molotov
                    rejected it, however, saying that no consultation was necessary since the Groza
                    Government represented the democratic forces in the country and had restored
                    order. His note also implied that no action in the former satellite states on
                    the part of the three Governments was required under the Yalta Declaration
                    because Allied Control Commissions were operating there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Present American Position.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department has made clear to the Soviet Government that we take seriously our
                    responsibilities under the Yalta Declaration, and that these responsibilities
                    call for genuinely tripartite consultation and action on broad political
                    matters, whereas the functions of the Control Commissions are limited to
                    enforcement of the respective armistice agreements. Our specific reply to Mr.
                    Molotov’s refusal of the proposal <pb facs="0846" n="834" xml:id="pg_834"/> for
                    consultation has not yet been communicated to the Soviet Government, since its
                    timing depends on the course of the discussions on Poland. We maintain the
                    position that the three Governments are obliged to concert their policies, and
                    we feel that the Soviet Government, having intervened unilaterally to install a
                    government which we do not consider representative of all democratic elements
                    and having refused to consult with us, is hardly fulfilling its obligations. We
                    are, however, more interested in getting Soviet agreement to apply in the future
                    the principles of the Yalta Declaration than in insisting on a review of the
                    Soviet action of last February or on a drastic reorganization of the Rumanian
                    Government. We shall continue to press for an agreed Allied policy on Rumania
                    and we may find it necessary to make public the fact that the Soviet Government
                    has rejected our proposals.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Implementation of the Crimea Agreement on
                        Liberated Areas in Bulgaria.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On March 29 our Embassy at Moscow was instructed<note n="57" xml:id="d631fn57">Telegram 735, March 29, 8 p.m., to Moscow, <ref target="frus1945v04#pg_179">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 179</ref>.</note> to inform the
                    Soviet Government that our information clearly indicated that Bulgarian
                    electoral plans would make it impossible for the Bulgarians to hold free
                    elections without assistance. We suggested that a tripartite Allied committee be
                    constituted in Bulgaria to insure that all democratic political groups in the
                    country would have full freedom to bring their separate platforms and lists of
                    candidates to the voters’ attention and that the rights of the electorate in the
                    pre-election period and in the polling would be protected. This message was
                    communicated to Molotov on April 5.</p>
                <p>On April 11 Molotov replied<note n="58" xml:id="d631fn58">See telegram 1182,
                        April 15, midnight, from Moscow, <ref target="frus1945v04#pg_186">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 186</ref>.</note> in brusque terms,
                    questioning our motives in making the proposal and stating that the Soviet
                    Government’s information indicated that there was no intention of holding
                    elections in Bulgaria in the near future. Molotov went on to say that, in view
                    of the Finnish precedent, the Soviet public would be “dumbfounded” if there were
                    foreign interference in Bulgarian elections and he stated that the Bulgarians
                    did not deserve our “mistrust.”</p>
                <p>We suggest that Mr. Molotov be informed that we are glad to learn that there is
                    no intention of holding elections in Bulgaria in the near future and are
                    gratified by the implication in his message that the Finnish precedent will be
                    followed in Bulgaria. Information has reached us nevertheless to the effect that
                    it is planned to have a single “Fatherland Front” electoral list, with no
                    opportunity for the several parties within the “Front” to have their separate
                    lists or present their separate platforms to the electorate. Should this be the
                    case, and we assume that the Soviet Government is keeping itself informed in the
                        <pb facs="0847" n="835" xml:id="pg_835"/> matter, we feel that we should
                    again press our request for consultation. Since such action is not only
                    permissible but becomes an obligation under the Yalta Declaration on Liberated
                    Europe, we are unable to comprehend why the invocation of the Declaration should
                    be cause for misunderstanding. The American people fully expect that the
                    Declaration will be given reality in the treatment of liberated and ex-enemy
                    peoples.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">American Representation on the Allied
                        Control Commissions in the Former Satellite States</hi>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Present Status of American Representatives</hi>. Allied
                    Control Commissions, on which the three principal Allied Governments are
                    represented, were established in Rumania, Bulgaria and Hungary to supervise the
                    execution of the armistice agreements. The executive authority is, of course, in
                    the hands of the Soviet High Command since these states are in the Soviet
                    theater of military operations. The role of the American and British
                    representatives has been more or less limited to “observation,” even though, in
                    the Bulgarian and Hungarian armistice agreements,<note n="59" xml:id="d631fn59">For text of armistice agreement with Bulgaria, signed at Moscow, October
                        28, 1944, see Department of State Executive Agreement Series No. 437, or 58
                        Stat. (pt. 2) 1498; with Hungary, signed at Moscow, January 20, 1945, see
                        Executive Agreement Series No. 456, or 59 Stat. (pt. 2) 1321.</note>
                    provision is made for their “participation.” The Department has not been
                    satisfied with the status of the American representatives, partly because of the
                    many minor difficulties created by the Soviet authorities with respect to travel
                    and other matters, but more fundamentally because the Soviet authorities have
                    issued directives in the name of the Commissions without informing our
                    representatives and often on the basis of interpretations of the armistice terms
                    with which this Government was not in agreement but with which we became
                    involuntarily associated by virtue of the presence of American representatives
                    on the Commissions. We have attempted to secure Soviet recognition of the right
                    of our representatives to be informed of directives prior to their issuance to
                    the local governments. In Rumania we have had informal agreements to this
                    effect, but they have not worked out in practice. In Bulgaria we have had no
                    satisfaction at all. Provision was made in the statutes of the Hungarian Control
                    Commission for such a procedure, but the Soviet authorities, after a good
                    beginning, are not now strictly adhering to it. The result has been that in all
                    three countries ultimate authority rests with the Soviet Government which is at
                    liberty to act either directly, as in the recent Rumanian crisis, or through the
                    Control Commissions. Neither the presence of American representatives on the
                    Commissions nor the Crimea agreement to concert Allied policies has provided any
                    check on dynamic Soviet policy in this area.</p>
                <pb facs="0848" n="836" xml:id="pg_836"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Future Status of American Representatives</hi>. In the
                    Bulgarian and Hungarian armistice agreements it is stated that until the end of
                    hostilities against Germany the Control Commissions shall operate under the
                    general direction of the Soviet High Command. The Department failed to secure
                    Soviet agreement to the inclusion of reference to the “second period” (from the
                    end of hostilities against Germany to the conclusion of peace), during which the
                    three Allied Governments would have equal participation in and responsibility
                    for the work of the Commissions, but reserved the right to re-open this question
                    later. It might now be appropriate to raise it with Mr. Molotov. With the
                    termination of hostilities the Soviet case for retaining its present dominating
                    position will lose much of its force; most of the clauses of the armistice
                    agreements will no longer be operative. We have a right to expect that the
                    Soviet Government will withdraw its armed forces from these countries, in
                    accordance with Article VI of the Moscow Declaration of October 30, 1943.<note n="60" xml:id="d631fn60">
                        <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_755">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 755</ref>.</note> If the Soviet
                    Government shows no inclination to agree to such a change in the character of
                    the Commissions, it would be desirable for the United States to work for an
                    early end to the armistice period and liquidation of the control machinery
                    through the conclusion of peace and normalization of relations with the
                    satellite states.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">The Failure of the Soviet Government to
                        Provide Facilities for the Entry of UNRRA and Red Cross Personnel into
                        Poland and the Balkans.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>UNRRA has been attempting for several months to arrange for the entry of UNRRA
                    personnel into Poland in connection with the carrying out of its functions
                    there. Despite the fact that the Provisional authorities in Poland indicated
                    their agreement, it has not been possible to obtain the necessary visas. Similar
                    difficulties have been encountered by the Red Cross in getting its
                    representatives into Poland. Late in February, however, two Red Cross
                    representatives did finally get into Poland and one is still there. It has been
                    impossible so far for them to carry out any effective work since the sixty tons
                    of medical supplies sent from Moscow in February had not arrived in Lublin by
                    April 16.</p>
                <p>Mr. Molotov may take the position that this is a matter for the Polish
                    Provisional Government. You may wish to point out that these areas are under
                    Soviet military control and that UNRRA is an international organization in which
                    the Soviet Union is a prominent member. We cannot believe that these
                    difficulties could not be overcome if the Soviet Government desired to do so.
                    You may also <pb facs="0849" n="837" xml:id="pg_837"/> wish to stress the
                    humanitarian aspects of this matter and to point out that our sole interest is
                    to help the people in these areas who have suffered so much from the effects of
                    the war.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">5. <hi rend="italic">Failure of the Soviet Government to Satisfy
                        Our Request for Full Advance Information Concerning Transfers to Third
                        Countries of Supplies Furnished to the Soviet Union under Lend-Lease or
                        Supplies of Soviet Origin Similar to Lend-Lease Materials</hi>.</p>
                <p>The Lend-Lease Act<note n="61" xml:id="d631fn61">Approved March 11, 1941; 55
                        Stat. 31. Amended March 11, 1943 (57 Stat. 20), May 17, 1944 (58 Stat. 222),
                        and April 16, 1945 (59 Stat. 52).</note> requires prior approval by this
                    Government of such transfers and in the case of other countries we have insisted
                    upon this advance notice. We have also insisted that we be informed in advance
                    of transfers of materials similar to Lend-Lease supplies.</p>
                <p>With respect to the transfer of actual Lend-Lease materials, you may wish to
                    state that this is a matter of law and that we have no discretion about the
                    requirement for the advance notification. We have no intention of prohibiting
                    reasonable transfers, but if the Soviet Government is not willing to consult us
                    in advance we will be obliged to consider such transfers as an indication that
                    these materials are no longer needed by the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">6. <hi rend="italic">The Implementation of the Crimea Agreement
                        Regarding the Exchange of Liberated Prisoners of War and Civilians.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>You are familiar with the fact that despite the intervention of the President the
                    Soviet Government would not allow our contact teams to proceed to Poland to
                    assist our liberated prisoners of war in accordance with the terms of the Crimea
                    Agreement on this matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. Molotov may raise the question of our refusal to return to Soviet control
                    Soviet nationals captured in German uniform who claim the protection of the
                    Geneva Convention<note n="62" xml:id="d631fn62">For text of convention signed at
                        Geneva, July 27, 1929, see <ref target="frus1929v01#pg_336">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1929, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 336</ref>.</note> as German prisoners of
                    war.</p>
                <p>You may wish to explain that we have been concerned that the Germans might
                    retaliate on American prisoners of war in their hands if we did not comply with
                    the provisions of the Geneva Convention on this matter. We have insisted with
                    the Germans that prisoners of war captured in American uniform be treated as
                    American prisoners of war regardless of their nationality. Moreover, German
                    measures of retaliation might not be confined to this particular question. You
                    might assure Mr. Molotov, however, that we have no intention of holding Soviet
                    citizens after the collapse of Germany regardless of whether they desire to
                    return to the Soviet Union or not.</p>
                <pb facs="0850" n="838" xml:id="pg_838"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">7. <hi rend="italic">The Kravchenko Case.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Should Mr. Molotov raise this matter you might explain that we have done all we
                    could to meet the desires of the Soviet Government but that under our law
                    Kravchenko entered this country as a civilian, and should we try to deport him
                    he would be allowed a trial and would undoubtedly be deported but with the right
                    to depart for any foreign destination provided he would do so within a certain
                    length of time.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">8. <hi rend="italic">The Soviet Request for a Six Billion Dollar
                        Loan.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>You may wish to state that the Soviet memorandum<note n="63" xml:id="d631fn63">See telegram 29, January 4, 2 p.m., from Moscow, <ref target="#pg_942">p.
                            942</ref>.</note> on this subject is receiving the careful consideration
                    of this Government, but compliance with the Soviet requestion [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] would require prior legislation by Congress.</p>
                <p>Depending on the general tenor of the conversations you may consider it advisable
                    to point out to Mr. Molotov that in considering this matter the Congress will
                    doubtless be influenced by the prospect for full collaboration between the
                    United States and the Soviet Union in the establishment and maintenance of peace
                    and stability.</p>
                <p>You might further desire to remind Mr. Molotov that Congress reflects public
                    opinion and that public opinion in this country has been greatly concerned over
                    developments in Eastern Europe since the Crimea Conference. You will doubtless
                    wish to assure Molotov, however, that this Government sincerely desires this
                    collaboration, and we are anxious to do all we can to assist the Soviet Union in
                    reconstruction and in the further development of its prosperity.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">9. <hi rend="italic">Forthcoming Meeting of the Reparations
                        Commission in Moscow</hi>.</p>
                <p>You will recall that in reply to our inquiry as to whether the Soviet Government
                    would agree to the participation of France in the Reparations Commission the
                    Soviet Government replied that it agreed but that it also felt that Poland and
                    Yugoslavia should be represented. We replied that we felt that original
                    membership should be limited to the countries represented on the European
                    Advisory Commission which is concerned with related matters, particularly as the
                    members of this Commission are those responsible for the occupation of Germany.
                    We feel that if any additional countries are invited, all countries concerned
                    should be invited. If the Soviet Government desires the Commission to be
                    enlarged to this extent, we would be prepared to agree, although such a large
                    body would probably be very unwieldy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
