<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Harriman) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d690</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">690</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-11-22T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-22T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-22T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-22T11:00:00-05:00" n="690"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d690">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.61/11–2245: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-22T19:00:00+03:00"
                            >November 22, 1945—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 22—2:36 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3930. At the theatre last night I had a most disquieting few sentence
                    conversation with Litvinov.<note n="7" xml:id="d690fn7">Maxim Maximovich
                        Litvinov had been an Assistant People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs of the
                        Soviet Union since 1943. Just before this he had been the Ambassador of the
                        Soviet Union to the United States from December 1941 until September
                        1943.</note> He told me that he was disturbed by the international
                    situation, that neither side knew how to behave towards the other and that this
                    was the underlying reason for the London Conference breakdown and subsequent
                    difficulties. I suggested that time might cool the strong feelings that had been
                    aroused. He replied that in the meantime however issues were developing. I again
                    suggested that if we came to an understanding about Japan, it might clear the
                    atmosphere. He replied that we would then be confronted with other issues.</p>
                <p>I asked him what we, for our part, could do about it. He replied “Nothing”. I
                    then asked “What can you do about it”. He interpreted this to mean himself
                    personally and replied, “Nothing. I believe I know what should be done but I am
                    powerless”. He made it clear that he was speaking about the situation within the
                    counsels of the Soviet Govt. I then said “You are extremely pessimistic” to
                    which he replied “Frankly, between us, yes”.</p>
                <p>In evaluating this conversation it must be realized that Litvinov has been
                    consistently during the past 2 years extremely disgruntled with his personal
                    position, has been obviously antagonistic to Molotov, and the Soviet Govt has
                    evidently been disregarding his advice.</p>
                <p>In this connection all the reports I have recently received of conversations of
                    Americans, including my own, with Soviet writers and other intellectuals, follow
                    the same pattern “Why has America become so aggressive; why is she interfering
                    with Soviet attempts to bring ‘democracy’ into the Balkans? She made no
                    objection to the previous Fascist regimes. Why is she refusing to admit the
                    Soviet Union into Japan? Why is she threatening the Soviet Union with the atomic
                    bomb, etc?”. From the Soviet press and the party line which has been promulgated
                    through the agitators, the Russian people are much disturbed by what they have
                    been led to believe is the United States policy of aggression against the Soviet
                    Union.</p>
                <p>Adding up the above, together with Stalin’s comment that the Soviet Union may
                    have to pursue an isolationist policy, it seems clear that since Molotov could
                    not get what he wanted at London Conference <pb facs="0934" n="922"
                        xml:id="pg_922"/> the Soviet Govt under leadership of his group has been
                    pursuing to the fullest extent possible a policy of unilateral action to achieve
                    their concept of security in depth. Vyshinski and other Soviets have attempted
                    to stiffen the lines in Bulgaria and Rumania. Tito has broken with Subasic.<note
                        n="8" xml:id="d690fn8">For documentation on this subject, see <ref
                            target="#pg_1208">pp. 1208</ref> ff. Dr. Ivan Subasich, former Yugoslav
                        Prime Minister, had been a member of the provisional government representing
                        the former Royal Government.</note> The Chinese National Govt has been
                    double-crossed and Manchuria has been turned over to the Chinese Communists and
                    revolt has been fostered under Red Army protection in Iranian Azerbaijan,
                    renewed pressure has been brought on Norway and Turkey for bases.</p>
                <p>On the other hand Molotov has still indicated that he wants to come to an
                    agreement over Japan if he feels he has got all the traffic will bear. Stalin
                    has indicated that the Foreign Ministers should meet again. Soviet reports on
                    UNO appear to be cooperating in establishment of this organization.</p>
                <p>It would appear that Molotov’s policy following the London breakdown has been to
                    seize the immediate situation to strengthen the Soviet position as much as
                    possible through unilateral action and then probably to agree to another meeting
                    of the Foreign Ministers. We would at that time be faced with a number of <hi
                        rend="italic">faits accomplis</hi> and also entrenched Soviet positions.</p>
                <p>I hope the above will be accepted only as our tentative interpretation of recent
                    developments as they look from Moscow.<note n="9" xml:id="d690fn9">In telegram
                        4040, December 3, 1945, 11 p.m., from Moscow, Ambassador Harriman reported
                        that Litvinov showed himself as feeling “almost jubilant” since the Foreign
                        Ministers were going to meet again at Moscow (711.61/12–345).</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
