<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-03T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-03T08:00:00-05:00" n="862" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d862">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.404/2–345: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kennan</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-03T16:00:00+03:00">February
                                    3, 1945—4 [<hi rend="italic">9</hi>] p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received February 4—12:17 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>320. Following interpretive comment may be of interest to Department in
                            connection with election of new Russian Patriarch, reported in my
                            immediately preceding telegram.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>It will be recalled that the institution of the Patriarchate was
                                revived just before the revolution, after a 200–year interruption,
                                during which time the church had been administered by a state
                                    synod.<note n="64" xml:id="d862fn64">Peter the Great had caused
                                    the office of Patriarch to remain vacant after the death of
                                    Adrian in 1700. He abolished the Patriarchate and issued an
                                    ordinance in 1721 by which the church was to be governed by a
                                    Holy Synod over which he placed a layman called the <hi rend="italic">Ober-Procuror</hi>, whose duty it was to see
                                    that the Synod did nothing which would displease the Tsar. This
                                    began the secularization of the church authority. Under the
                                    Provisional Government following the February/March 1917
                                    revolution, the office of the <hi rend="italic">Ober-Procuror</hi> was abolished, a church assembly (sobor)
                                    met in August to consider changes in the government of the
                                    church, and on November 21 decided to restore the
                                    Patriarchate.</note> The Patriarch elected at that time died in
                                    1925,<note n="65" xml:id="d862fn65">The Patriarch Tikhon had
                                    been elected at the end of November 1917. After many
                                    vicissitudes, and persecution by the Bolshevik regime, he died
                                    on April 7, 1925, in the Donskoy monastery in Moscow. Concerning
                                    an appeal to President Harding on behalf of Tikhon, on trial
                                    before a Soviet tribunal, see <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_835">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 835</ref>–<ref target="frus1922v02#pg_840">840</ref>.</note> and the
                                anti-religious <pb facs="1127" n="1115" xml:id="pg_1115"/> policy of
                                the regime made the election of a successor impossible until a year
                                ago when another election was permitted.<note n="66" xml:id="d862fn66">On the election of the Patriarch Sergey on
                                    September 8, 1943, see <ref target="frus1943v03#pg_850">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 850</ref>; and concerning
                                    his death on May 15, 1944. see <ref target="frus1944v04#pg_1212">
                                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 1212</ref>–<ref target="frus1944v04#pg_1213">1213</ref>.</note> This
                                election, about a year ago, took place quietly, without fanfares and
                                without prominent foreign visitors. The new Patriarch, Sergei, died
                                after only some 4 months in office; and the immediate purpose of the
                                present ceremonies is the election of a successor.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The revival of the Patriarchate is the result not of any
                                spontaneous movement on the part of the church but [of] a deliberate
                                policy on the part of the Soviet Regime. This policy, in the
                                Embassy’s views, has little or nothing to do with state of religion
                                in the Soviet Union. It is founded in the determination of the
                                regime to make available for its own use every possible channel of
                                influence in foreign affairs. The all-Slav policy alone would
                                dictate an effort to appeal to religious sentiments of the other
                                Slav populations. But the aims of Soviet church policy go beyond the
                                Slavic world alone. Through the apparatus of the church the Soviet
                                Government wishes to have (1) a direct channel of influence to all
                                believers of the Eastern Church wherever they may reside, (2) an
                                iron in the fire of Near Eastern politics through Russian Church
                                property and traditional privileges, and (3) a means of disarming
                                criticism and gaining sympathy in western religious circles. In
                                order to achieve these objectives it is necessary that the Russian
                                Church, however [<hi rend="italic">over</hi>] the foreign activities
                                of which the influence of the regime is complete, should make the
                                most of its possibilities as numerically the most powerful of the
                                branches of the Eastern Church. The revival of the Patriarchate,
                                which enables the Russian Church to deal [on] substantially equal
                                terms with the other Eastern Patriarchs, is the first and most
                                elementary step in this direction.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The circumstances of the present ceremonies reveal clearly the
                                extent to which they are beamed on the outside world. Except for one
                                or two brief and inconspicuous notices concerning the arrival of
                                high visiting dignitaries and a brief factual report in the
                                government <hi rend="italic">Izvestiya</hi> (not in the party <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi>) of the election of Alexis, together
                                with his photograph biography, no news of the event has been noted
                                in the Soviet press, and the Soviet public is no better informed on
                                the election of the Patriarch of Moscow and all the Russias than on
                                the Plenum of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of
                                Kazakhstan. The ceremonies, on the other hand, were exhaustively
                                photographed and it is noted that the horde of government newsreel
                                photographers were the same as those who usually prepare photographs
                                for distribution outside the Soviet Union. Access to the <pb facs="1128" n="1116" xml:id="pg_1116"/> various ceremonies,
                                while free to foreigners, appears to have been severely restricted
                                in the case of Russians. The church was filled and surrounded on all
                                occasions by numerous contingents of secret police. The assembled
                                spectators were subjected to careful scrutiny; and an old lady who
                                had the temerity to offer for sale an Icon “from Riga” was
                                unceremoniously hustled off to an unknown destination.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>An interesting factor was the North American angle. The only
                                non-Russian to participate in the election was the Metropolitan
                                [Benjamin “of North America and the Aleutians”. He is the only
                                foreign member of the Synod. In his rank of Metropolitan]<note n="67" xml:id="d862fn67">Corrected on basis of text in Moscow
                                    Embassy files.</note> he is also fourth ranking official in the
                                entire Russian Orthodox Hierarchy.<note n="68" xml:id="d862fn68">The
                                    Metropolitan Benjamin (Fedchenko) had come to the United States
                                    from the Soviet Union in 1983 (see footnote 45, <ref target="#pg_1111">p. 1111</ref>). He was not a member of the
                                    Holy Synod, but was in attendance at the Local Council held to
                                    elect the new Patriarch.</note> In casting his vote, Benjamin
                                stated that he had not had the opportunity to consult his
                                parishioners or his priests on his choice, as should have been done
                                in accordance with church law, but that he had decided to vote for
                                Alexei in the conviction that his choice would receive the unanimous
                                consent of the North American branch of the church. It is also
                                interesting to note that his speech received more attention not only
                                from the congregation but also from the cameramen than any other
                                made. As for Thepphilus, head of the Schismatic branch of the
                                Russian Orthodox Church in America, one of the priests in the church
                                told an officer of the Embassy that he had decided at the last
                                minute not to come. In order for him to be received formally back
                                into the church it will be necessary for him to come to Moscow in
                                order to admit the error of his ways, to enter a monastery, to be
                                stripped of his rank and to be returned to that rank through gradual
                                stages. The priest added, however, that he believed Theophilus would
                                be coming to Moscow before long in order to rehabilitate himself. It
                                is hardly necessary to say that this is a step greatly desired by
                                the Moscow Patriarchate since Theophilus controls most of the
                                Orthodox property and communicants in the United States.<note n="69" xml:id="d862fn69">The number of parishes which recognized the
                                    jurisdiction of Benjamin was 13, whereas 358 parishes recognized
                                    the jurisdiction of Theophilus.</note> Plainly, if Benjamin, by
                                virtue of a recantation on the part of Theophilus, were to come into
                                control of this property and these communicants, it would give him a
                                material prestige more commensurate with his hierarchical standing.
                                It should be remembered that as a dependancy of the Moscow Church
                                the North American Metropolitanate is subject to the administrative
                                jurisdiction of the Moscow Patriarchate. The North American
                                Metropolitanate is unique in this respect and represents the only
                                area outside of the Soviet Union in which the Moscow Patriarch has
                                direct administrative jurisdiction.</item>
                            <pb facs="1129" n="1117" xml:id="pg_1117"/>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The immediate effect which this ceremonious patriarchal election
                                may have on the Russian Church itself should not be exaggerated. It
                                is true that it has made possible the most imposing gathering of
                                churchmen since the revolution, and that one of them, at least, has
                                now acquired a prominence and international connections which will
                                give him a certain independent dignity even in the eyes of the
                                    regime.<note n="70" xml:id="d862fn70">At the session of the
                                    Local Council on January 31, the Statute on the Administration
                                    of the Russian Orthodox Church was adopted unanimously. By its
                                    provisions all the aspects of church life are determined. This
                                    Statute declared that in the Russian Orthodox Church supreme
                                    authority in matters: of doctrine, administration and church
                                    justice—legislative, administrative and judicial—belongs to the
                                    Local Council periodically convened and consisting of bishops,
                                    clerics and laity. The Patriarch presides over the Local
                                    Council.</note> It is also true that knowledge of the event will
                                spread throughout the entire Russian religious community and will
                                give encouragement and hope to many believers at a moment when the
                                calamities of war have done much to stir religious feeling. But the
                                realities surrounding the teaching and practice of religion in
                                Russia can be scarcely affected by these events. The situation
                                cannot be compared with that prevailing before the revolution, when
                                the Russian rulers officially shared the ideology of the church.
                                Today the church, in its relations with the state, is dealing with
                                what purports to be in effect a rival religion, no less Byzantine in
                                conception and no less Russian in method. There has been, and can
                                be, no accepted dogmatic relationship between the Holy Sepulcher and
                                Lenin’s tomb. In the Communist Party, dignitaries of the Russian
                                Church will encounter other churchmen no less astute, no less
                                experienced, and considerably more disciplined than themselves,
                                armed in addition with all the attributes of physical power. In this
                                case, there can be no question whose interests will be served first.
                                As long as no young person in Russia can hope for normal advantages
                                of recreation and association unless he belongs to the Pioneers, as
                                long as the Young Communist League<note n="71" xml:id="d862fn71">The
                                    Young Communist League (the Ail Union Leninist Communist League
                                    of Youth; the Komsomol) was founded in 1918, with membership of
                                    youths, between 15 and 28 years of age, and it also directed the
                                    activities of the Young Pioneers, founded in 1924 for children
                                    between 10 and 15 years of age.</note> and the party remain the
                                stepping stones to almost every respectable career, and as long as
                                no Pioneer, Young Communist or party member can admit to the holding
                                of religious beliefs, so long the Russian church must remain at the
                                bottom largely a withering church of old priests and old women [and]
                                at the top one of a number of fronts for the policies of the Kremlin
                                in the outside world.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Sent to Department, repeated to Rome as 8, to Ankara as 5, and to Cairo
                            as 14.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Kennan</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>