<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Norway (
                        Osborne
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d89</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">89</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-02T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="89" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d89">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">857.014/10–245</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Norway</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Osborne</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 301</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Oslo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-02">October 2,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received October 23.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report, with reference to my
                    telegram No. 204, July 5 and No. 277, July 23, that there is still no public
                    knowledge of the Soviet demands on Norway with reference to Bear Island and
                    Spitzbergen. I believe this is a notable fact and one not altogether easy to
                    explain. As reported in my telegram No. 204, July 5 the Foreign Minister
                    discussed the matter in a secret session of the Storting with its 150 members;
                    he also dealt with it in a secret conference with the press; the Norwegian
                    military and naval authorities certainly know about it. Yet no American or other
                    foreign newspaper correspondent has apparently got even a smell of it; and I and
                    the one or two members of the Embassy staff who know of it have not had any
                    indication that anyone outside official circles is aware of it.</p>
                <p>This might not be so surprising if the matter were one of slight intrinsic
                    interest to the average member of the Norwegian public. That is certainly not
                    the case. Most of the well-to-do Norwegians are extremely sensitive with regard
                    to Russia and tend to be alert in respect of anything which contains the least
                    suspicion of Soviet aggressiveness. There can be no question that knowledge of
                    the Soviet demands would affect these people greatly—and most painfully. There
                    would moreover be the liveliest general public interest in any proposal to
                    derogate complete Norwegian sovereignty over the territories in question. Yet
                    the Soviet demands remain a well kept secret. There has been absolutely no
                    public mention of them—no hint even; <pb facs="0111" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> if
                    there has been private discussion, outside a restricted official circle, the
                    Embassy is unaware of it. The only explanation I can offer is that the
                    Norwegians are naturally a reticent people and that, in this case, fear has made
                    the considerable number who are in the know preternaturally reticent—which with
                    Norwegians means absolutely mum.</p>
                <p>In the meantime Foreign Minister Lie continues to inform me that the Soviets have
                    not raised the question again or made any reply to the Norwegian
                    counter-proposal mentioned in my telegram No. 204, July 5.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lithgow Osborne</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
