<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-03-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="916" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d916">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">702.6111/3–1045</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Secretary of
                                State</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-03-10">March 10, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Soviet Ambassador called on me today at his request and said that his
                            Government wishes to establish “representations” in Portland, Oregon and
                            Seattle, Washington, of the Soviet Consulate in San Francisco. This does
                            not mean that the Soviet Government wishes to open consulates in those
                            places, but merely to establish offices which are very much needed in
                            view of the fact that great amounts of Soviet supplies pass through
                            those ports, and many questions arise with regard to these shipments.
                            The Ambassador said he thought that such a step would be helpful also to
                            us as he is constantly receiving letters from the Governors and Senators
                            in the States of Oregon and Washington asking for information of one
                            kind or another.</p>
                        <p>I said to the Ambassador that I knew of no procedure for establishing
                            what he referred to as a “representation” and I asked him whether, if
                            such offices were opened, they should not be in charge at least of
                            subordinate consular officers such as a vice consul. The Ambassador
                            replied in the affirmative and said that the purpose of his Government
                            was to establish branch offices of the main office in San Francisco, but
                            not to open new consulates as such.</p>
                        <p>I said I would look into this matter and let the Ambassador know as soon
                            as possible of our attitude towards his Government’s proposal.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>