<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-12T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-12T17:00:00-05:00" n="181" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">560.AL/3–1248: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gallman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   us urgent</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                            </gloss>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-12T22:00:00+00:00">March 12,
                                1948—10 p. m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1035. For Amb Douglas, Clayton, and Brown from Bliss; for Wilcox from Bliss,
                        Upon receipt Havana’s 9 March 11,<note n="1" xml:id="d181fn1">Telegram 308
                            from Habana, March 11, <ref target="#pg_888">p. 888</ref>.</note>
                        considered it desirable convey to <gloss target="#t_BOT1">BOT</gloss>
                        officials substance second and following paragraphs beginning “only
                        objection Holmes has raised” and ending “not even accept this”, with
                        comments on urgency. <gloss target="#t_BOT1">BOT</gloss> most grateful for
                        clarification and after conversation with Havana by telephone state: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Our information is that the Australian suggestion put forward by
                                    Phillips<note n="2" xml:id="d181fn2">J. G. Phillips,
                                    Representative of the Australian Treasury Department, employed
                                    by the Commonwealth Bank.</note> in the working party on Tuesday
                                March 9 was rejected by Bronz. We could accept it if US would.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Action taken here and this reaction forwarded as of possible assistance to
                        Havana negotiations on article 23.</p>
                    <p>Re section 9 during film negotiations<note n="3" xml:id="d181fn3">In order to
                            conserve dollars the British Government, on August 6, 1947, imposed a
                            300% <hi rend="italic">ad valorem</hi> duty on imported films. The
                            valuation method resulted in a 75% tax on net earnings which would have
                            otherwise been remitted abroad. American film makers were most
                            concerned. On March 11, 1948, representatives: of the United States
                            motion picture industry negotiated an agreement with the British
                            Government which provided that the former rates of duty were to be
                            restored; that $17 million of earnings per year for U.S. film showings
                            would be remitted for two years; and that sterling uses of revenues in
                            excess of remitted amounts would be permitted. The four year agreement
                            was to be reviewed after 2 years, at which time conditions were to be
                            set for the remaining two years.</note> I mentioned it in that
                        connection and Wilson who had just come from Cabinet meeting on Charter said
                        “don’t talk to me of section 9” from which infer that Cabinet gave him rough
                        time on that question. Nevertheless Wilson and <gloss target="#t_BOT1">BOT</gloss> have not mentioned it since Cripps’ proposal was turned
                        down and apparently British have accepted our refusal consider it.</p>
                    <pb facs="0402" n="892" xml:id="pg_892"/>
                    <p>Tonight <gloss target="#t_BOT1">BOT</gloss> unable assist further on timing
                        except for effort clear article 23 at Havana and must await Cabinet decision
                        Monday on Charter as whole. Ministers not available meantime. [Bliss.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gallman</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>