<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-04-20T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-04-20T01:00:00-05:00" n="195" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d195">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">560.AL/4–2048: Circular telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to Certain <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Missions</gloss>
                        </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d195fn1">Sent to Brussels, Canberra, Habana,
                            Luxembourg, London, Ottawa, Paris, Praha, and The Hague.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   us urgent</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-04-20T01:00:00-05:00">April 20,
                                1948—1 a. m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Adverse attitude most other <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>
                            contracting parties and fuller study legal position as well as result
                            soundings Congressional opinion seem compel change in US position
                            suggested <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> Mar 26. Present
                            prevailing view Dept is to proclaim rates for Czecho and apply <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> to that country. Recommendation to
                            this effect has been made to Secretary Marshall at Bogotá and his reply
                            is awaited. If he approves, will still be necessary obtain White House
                            approval before US can proceed to put <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> into effect for Czecho. US will therefore not be able
                            to apply agreement to Czecho by April 20 deadline but if Marshall and
                            White House approve, US will apply <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>
                            to Czecho soon as possible, probably about middle May.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>In view foregoing US does not now intend call meeting contracting
                            parties <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> as suggested para 5,
                                <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> Mar 26.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Foregoing for your info only. Should govts to which you are accredited
                            inquire whether US will apply <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> to
                            Czecho, you should reply that matter is still under consideration and
                            that decision is expected shortly.<note n="2" xml:id="d195fn2">On April
                                22, President Truman issued a proclamation placing <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> into effect with respect to
                                Czechoslovakia on April 21. U.S. missions were informed that April
                                21 was chosen because it corresponded to the 30 day expiration date
                                after the Czech signature on the Protocol of Provisional Application
                                to <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>. The missions were
                                instructed to convey this information to the governments to which
                                they were accredited. In the case of the Canadian Government, the
                                Embassy in Ottawa was instructed in telegram 56, not printed, to
                                “indicate that this govt greatly appreciates its support but felt
                                that in view adverse reaction most other contracting parties <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>, proper course was to apply
                                    <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> to Czecho.”
                                (560.AL/4–2248)</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>