<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-04T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-04T12:00:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">800.014 Antarctic/3–448: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-04T12:00:00-05:00">March 4,
                                1948—noon</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>747. Antarctic question was discussed with Brit <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss> their request yesterday. We said our thinking is along
                        lines of some form international control such as trusteeship under <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> or condominium. We would appreciate
                        sympathetic study of problem by Brit along this line and would welcome any
                        Brit proposals. We plan approach other interested Govts along similar line
                        this month believing this offers best means of forestalling embarrassing
                        discussion Antarctica at Bogotá.</p>
                    <p>Brit reaction showed no departure from previous position of establishing
                        national sovereignties in Antarctica by court decision and no disposition to
                        survey possibility our proposals. Suggest this be discussed with <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> stressing our belief that
                        international control offers best solution though we are well aware problems
                        which would <pb facs="0476" n="966" xml:id="pg_966"/> have to be worked out.
                        You may add that we share Brit anxiety to prevent awkward discussions at
                            Bogotá.<note n="1" xml:id="d226fn1">In telegram 937, March 9, from
                            London, not printed, Chargé Waldemar Gallman reported that he had
                            discussed the Antarctica question with the British Foreign Office which
                            was apparently willing to consider some sort of international control.
                            British Foreign Secretary Ernest Bevin had finished the formulation of
                            views on Antarctica within the Foreign Office. Once these views had been
                            cleared with other parts of the British Government and with the
                            governments of the Dominions, they would be transmitted to Washington
                            (800.014 Antarctica/3–948).</note>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>