<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Acting Director of the Policy Planning
                        Staff (
                        Butler
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v01p2</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d5</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">5</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-12T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council" subject="national-security-council">National Security Council</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="5" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Policy Planning Staff Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Director of the Policy Planning
                        Staff</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Butler</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-12">March 12,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: In response to your request, there are
                    set forth below the Policy Planning Staff’s views on the <gloss target="#t_UMT1">UMT</gloss> statement you are to make before the Senate Armed Services
                        Committee.<note n="1" xml:id="d5fn1">For extracts from Marshall’s statement
                        before the Senate Armed Services Committee, March 17, and information
                        regarding the foreign policy aspects of the question of procurement of
                        manpower for the armed forces, see editorial note, <ref target="#pg_538">p.
                            538</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Planning Staff is concerned about the effect that your statement as drafted
                    may have.<note n="2" xml:id="d5fn2">Neither the draft statement considered by
                        the Policy Planning Staff nor the revision prepared by the <gloss target="#t_PPS1">PPS</gloss> has been found in the files of the
                        Department of State.</note> The reasons for this concern are: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The best information available to the Planning Staff is that the
                            prospects are poor for enactment of the <gloss target="#t_UMT1">UMT</gloss> legislation this year, even with the weight of your
                            prestige behind it. This being the case, failure to enact the
                            legislation after your strong testimony in its favor would have a very
                            bad psychological effect abroad, both in discouraging our friends and
                            encouraging further aggressive moves by the USSR;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The accelerated march of events makes necessary an immediate
                            strengthening of our military effectiveness to back our foreign policy.
                            It is the informal opinion of members of the National Security Council
                            Staff that the best way to attain this immediate strengthening of our
                            military position is through measures such as Selective Service;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Your proposed statement might be interpreted to mean that you believe
                            universal military training is adequate to supply the immediate need for
                            a military force strong enough to support our foreign policy;</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>While your quoted views as Chief of Staff still are valid in support
                            of <gloss target="#t_UMT1">UMT</gloss>, the situation they were,
                            designed to meet is radically different from the situation that exists
                            today. It seems preferable to refer to or summarize those views and
                            place greater emphasis on other measures which you consider would
                            provide the necessary immediate military backing for our foreign
                            policy.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In light of the above expressed views the Policy Planning Staff submits a
                    suggested redraft of your statement.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Butler</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
