<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 144Memorandum of Discussion at the 153d Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Thursday, July 9, 1953</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d144</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">144</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-07-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rGICCioSV3my" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Financial crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recdTuobyjHNvXKhT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011601"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bankruptcy</term>
                    <term ref="recLVtmipNOLIF0A1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recsTmAcLGbo1pCoe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic stability</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="144"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d144">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_EGAD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_EGAD1">Eisenhower</persName> papers, <persName corresp="#p_WA2"
                        >Whitman</persName> file</note>
                <head>No. 144<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Discussion at the 153d Meeting of the National
                        Security Council, Thursday, July 9, 1953</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d144fn1">Drafted on July 10 by <persName corresp="#p_GSE1"
                            >S. Everett Gleason</persName>, Acting Executive Secretary of the
                        National Security Council.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret eyes only</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-07-09">July 9,
                            1953</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The following were present at the 153rd meeting of the Council: The President of
                    the United States, Presiding; the Vice President of the United States; the
                    Secretary of State; the Secretary of Defense; the Deputy Director for Mutual
                    Security; the Director, Office of Defense Mobilization. Also present were the
                    Secretary of the Treasury; the Chairman, Federal Communications Commission (for
                    Item 1); General <persName corresp="#p_CGJ1">Collins</persName> for the
                    Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff; the Director of Central Intelligence; <persName
                        corresp="#p_CR1">Robert Cutler</persName>, Special Assistant to the
                    President; <persName corresp="#p_JCD1">C.D. Jackson</persName>, Special
                    Assistant to the President; Colonel <persName corresp="#p_CBGPT1">Paul T.
                        Carroll</persName>, Acting White House Staff Secretary; Ralph Clark, Central
                    Intelligence Agency (for Item 1); Commander Perry Johnson, <gloss
                        target="#t_USN1">USN</gloss>, Central Intelligence Agency (for Item 1); J.
                    J. Hitchcock, Central Intelligence Agency (for Items 1 and 2); the Acting
                    Executive Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>; and Hugh D. Farley,
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Special Staff Member.</p>
                <p>There follows a summary of the discussion at the meeting and the main points
                    taken.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of the following agenda items: electromagnetic
                    communications, significant world developments affecting United States security,
                    and the situation in Korea.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">United States Objectives and Policies With
                        Respect to the Near East (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 155)</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d144fn2">Regarding <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 155,
                        see Cutler’s memorandum, <ref target="#d134">Document 134</ref>. For text of
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 155/1, July 14, see <ref
                            target="#d145">
                            <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In introducing the report, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName>
                    observed that it had been revised to reflect the views which the Secretary of
                    State and the Director for Mutual Security had brought back from their trip
                    through the Near East. The chief new points in the present report were as
                    follows: (1) <gloss target="#t_MEDO1">MEDO</gloss> was no longer played up as a
                    likely defense arrangement in the future; (2) Egypt was no longer considered to
                    be the nucleus of an area defense organization, and the so-called northern tier
                    of states had been substituted for it; (3) a new look had been taken at the Suez
                    base problem; and (4) the report <pb facs="0435" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/>
                    advocated greater independence and greater responsibility in the area by the
                    United States vis-à-vis Britain.</p>
                <p>After Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> had read the General
                    Objectives and the General Courses of Action in <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 155, he asked the Secretary of State to comment.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> replied that he really
                    had nothing to add to the comments he had made upon returning from his recent
                    trip. He merely wanted to take the occasion, therefore, to stress one or two
                    points which constituted changes from our previous policies toward the states of
                    this area.</p>
                <p>The first was the impracticality of the <gloss target="#t_MEDO1">MEDO</gloss>
                    concept. It was too complicated, too much like <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>, and it obviously would not work. Something less formal and
                    grandiose was needed as a substitute.</p>
                <p>Secondly, Egypt must be discounted as a strong point for the foreseeable future,
                    because it was so engrossed in its own problems that the free world could not
                    depend upon it as the cornerstone of a Near East structure. On the other hand,
                    the so-called northern tier of nations, stretching from Pakistan to Turkey, were
                    feeling the hot breath of the Soviet Union on their necks, and were accordingly
                    less preoccupied with strictly internal problems or with British and French
                    imperialism. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> also
                    expressed the hope that the missing link in this northern tier–namely,
                    Iran–would some day join to eliminate the gap in the northern tier.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, the Secretary summed up his view that separate bilateral
                    arrangements with the states of this area were much preferable at the moment to
                    arrangements modelled on <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Even so, it was
                    dangerous to exaggerate even this possibility, but every effort should be made
                    in view of the terrible repercussions on Europe of the loss of the Near East to
                    the Soviets and the great advantages which would accrue to the Soviets if they
                    secured this prize. In short, the present policy was more modest, more
                    realistic, and more apt to produce results.</p>
                <p>At the conclusion of Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName>’
                    remarks the President said he had one observation to make. Without desiring to
                    defend all the details in the concept of <gloss target="#t_MEDO1">MEDO</gloss>,
                    he pointed out that we should not minimize the very great advantages which we
                    derive from such multilateral defense arrangements in which the United States
                    participated. He said that we might well want bases in the Near East at some
                    future time, or that we might even wish to station troops in the area. The great
                    advantage of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> type of defense
                    arrangement was in providing for such contingencies. The President added, to
                    illustrate his point, that if some arrangement had existed whereby the Western
                    powers and the United States could have sent armed forces to the Suez base area,
                    say, in January 1951, we <pb facs="0436" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/> might have
                    been spared the terrible fight between Egypt and Great Britain. Whatever the
                    difficulties, such pacts as he had in mind, said the President, permitted us
                    greater flexibility, and we must not allow the <gloss target="#t_MEDO1"
                        >MEDO</gloss> concept to disappear entirely from our thinking. It should be
                    reconsidered if at some future time it appeared more practicable.</p>
                <p>In reply to the President, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2"
                        >Dulles</persName> said that the State Department was now engaged in trying
                    to devise a formula which would permit the stationing of United States and
                    British forces in the Suez Canal area in the event of the threat of an attack.
                    The general idea of the formula was that any of the Arab States which believed
                    itself threatened by external aggression would have the right to call for the
                    assistance of one or more of the Western powers. This formula was to be achieved
                    by bilateral negotiations, since these were more likely to succeed than
                    arrangements based on the Arab League or on <gloss target="#t_MEDO1"
                        >MEDO</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> also pointed out that he
                    would certainly discuss the Suez problem again with the Marquess of <persName
                        corresp="#p_SLR1">Salisbury</persName> when the latter reached Washington
                    for the Foreign Ministers conference. Time was of the essence, continued
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName>, because the Egyptians
                    had warned him when he was in Cairo that they could keep the lid on until after
                    we had talked about this problem again with the British, but that thereafter
                    trouble would begin if no settlement were reached. Unfortunately, continued
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName>, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> has been absolutely adamant on
                    holding the Suez base, and whether he can be induced to take a more flexible
                    position was a question. The British were convinced that the Egyptians would
                    ultimately give in if the British stood pat. We, on the other hand, believe that
                    if the British do stand pat, Egyptian guerrillas will attack the base.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> informed the Council that the
                    Defense Department had misgivings with regard to paragraph 16–f of the present
                    paper, which called for consideration and exchanging more formal commitments
                    with such Arab countries as gave convincing demonstration of a determination to
                    defend themselves and of willingness to cooperate with the United States.</p>
                <p>The President then suggested that the Defense Department explain its views.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGJ1">Collins</persName> replied that he was simply
                    unable to understand the nature of the more formal commitments herein proposed,
                    and stated that the Staff Study did little or nothing to indicate the nature of
                    these commitments. Noting, however, that paragraph 16–d contemplated bilateral
                    treaties with several states, General <persName corresp="#p_CGJ1"
                        >Collins</persName> supposed that paragraph 16–f at least contemplated
                    something more than that.</p>
                <pb facs="0437" n="397" xml:id="pg_397"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> pointed out that the earlier
                    sections of paragraph 16 referred to military assistance, whereas the
                    commitments in paragraph 16–f indicated the possibility of sending token U.S.
                    forces to certain of these countries or to the establishment of base rights for
                    U.S. forces in them.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> agreed with the views of
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> as to the meaning of the
                    paragraph, but said that the possibility of a situation arising in which it
                    would be possible for the United States to make more formal commitments for the
                    defense of the states of this area, now appeared to be so remote that he was
                    quite willing to strike the paragraph and to substitute for it a statement that
                    such commitments might be considered at some future time if conditions
                    warranted.</p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>After further discussion of the use proposed for these funds, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> warned the Council of the continued
                    deterioration of Israel’s fiscal and economic situation, which was caused by the
                    over-importation of goods. A serious financial crisis impended in Israel. We had
                    already been obliged to loan them $7 million to prevent default, and Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> anticipated that the Israelis
                    would be back presently with a request for $100 million to stave off impending
                    bankruptcy.</p>
                <p>The President inquired whether we were being as tough with the Israelis as with
                    any other nation.</p>
                <p>The Vice President added that this question was precisely what disturbed him. As
                    he saw the situation, the United States had been for some years under very heavy
                    political pressure to subsidize an Israeli economy which could never balance
                    itself. It began to look as though they would come back again and again for
                    handouts from the United States, with no prospect of permanent stabilization or
                    improvement.</p>
                <p>The President remarked that he had had Rabbi Silver in yesterday and had pointed
                    out to him quite frankly that under no circumstances would the United States
                    favor the Israelis above the Arabs or vice versa. The whole objective of our
                    policy, he had said to Rabbi Silver, was to try to induce these enemies to get
                    along with each other. The President added that Rabbi Silver said that such a
                    policy was fine with him.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> went on to say that
                    troublesome as was the present status of Israel, worse was in store thanks to
                    their program for bringing to Israel some two million more Jewish refugees in
                    the near future. Such a program, if carried out, thought the Secretary, would
                    finish off whatever faint hope there was for economic stability. If we bailed
                    them out of their present serious situation, we can only anticipate that they
                    will go ahead and bring in additional refugees. <pb facs="0438" n="398"
                        xml:id="pg_398"/> It was precisely this prospect, moreover, that so worried
                    and terrified the Arabs, who felt that if many more Jewish refugees were brought
                    within the confines of Israel, that small country would explode and that the
                    Arabs would be the chief victims of the explosion. If, said Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName>, we could somehow get the Israelis to
                    put an end to their ambitious immigration program, this would do more than
                    anything else to ease tension between Israel and the Arab States. As a matter of
                    fact, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> pointed out,
                    according to reports, Adlai Stevenson had taken a very tough stand on this
                    question in recent conversations with <persName corresp="#p_BGD1"
                        >Ben-Gurion</persName>.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HGM1">Humphrey</persName> said that he had
                    understood that the United States had told the Israelis that they would have to
                    finance their immigration program with their present resources and credit
                    arrangements.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">Dulles</persName> replied that indeed we
                    had said just this, but the question was, can we actually maintain this
                    stand?…</p>
                <p>There was general agreement with this position.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d144fn3">The following paragraphs were designated <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 843 a-c.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Adopted the statement of policy contained in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    155, subject to the following changes: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>Insert a new subparagraph 12–b to read as follows, and re-letter the
                            subsequent subparagraphs appropriately: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“12-b. Capitalize on such elements of strength as remain to the
                                    British in the area by such support of United Kingdom positions
                                    as may be consistent with U.S. principles and policy
                                    objectives.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Delete subparagraph 16–f and substitute the following: <quote
                                rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“If more formal commitments with respect to defense arrangements
                                    in the area should appear desirable, submit appropriate
                                    proposals for Council consideration.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>Appendix A, “Near East Financial Data”, should be revised to show only
                            total economic aid to the area, without reference to specific states, in
                            order that flexibility in the use of available funds on a regional basis
                            may be maintained, as set forth in paragraph 17–a.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> The statement of policy in <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 155, as amended, subsequently approved by the President and
                    circulated as <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 155/1.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of other agenda items, including the possibilities of
                    reducing the United States civilian population in sensitive areas abroad,
                    continental defense, the Volunteer Freedom Corps, and foreign reactions to
                    administration policies.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Everett Gleason</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
