<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 157The Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern, South Asian,
                    and African Affairs (Jernegan) to the Ambassador in Iran (Henderson)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d157</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">157</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-11-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-11-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-11-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-11-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="157"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d157">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Ankara Embassy files, lot 57 F 72, 400 MED,
                    1953–54</note>
                <head>No. 157<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern,
                        South Asian, and African Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_JJD1" type="from"
                            >Jernegan</persName>) to the Ambassador in Iran (<persName
                            corresp="#p_HLW1" type="to">Henderson</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d157fn1">Repeated to the Ambassadors in Turkey, Iraq, and
                        Pakistan.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">official-informal</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-11-09">November 9,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Loy</persName>
                    </hi>: In your despatch No. 196 of September 30, 1953,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d157fn2">Not printed; it contained comments about an alleged
                        proposal by the Shah of Iran for a regional military agreement among Iran,
                        Pakistan, Iraq, and Turkey. (787.5/9–3053)</note> you referred to Cairo’s
                    telegram No. 280 of September 3,<note n="3" xml:id="d157fn3">Not printed; it
                        reported a conversation between <persName corresp="#p_CJ1"
                            >Caffery</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_ASN1">Nuri
                        Said</persName>. (641.74/9–353)</note> reporting that <persName
                        corresp="#p_ASN1">Nuri Said</persName> had told Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName> that when the Shah was in Baghdad he had
                    proposed a regional military agreement among Iran, Pakistan, Iraq and Turkey.
                    You remarked that if the Shah actually made such a proposal he must have done so
                    in a “moment of ebullience” and you went on to say that the Shah had not given
                    any indication to you of a belief that the time may be at hand for Iran to enter
                    into any such agreement. You added, however: “there is a possibility that if the
                    Western Powers would undertake to modernize the Iranian Army, the Shah would
                    show more interest in the establishment of an alliance among Iran, Pakistan,
                    Iraq, and Turkey.”</p>
                <p>Your despatch happened to reach us at a moment when this subject had just been
                    recalled to our thoughts as a result of working-level consultations with the
                    staff of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. We had found very keen working-level
                    interest in the possibility of just such a regional arrangement as <persName
                        corresp="#p_ASN1">Nuri</persName> mentioned, comprised of the same four
                    countries. This grouping would be ideal for the implementation of the strategic
                    concept they favored.… You will recognize this as the classic British plan which
                    has never been embraced by our own Joint Chiefs. We are unable to guess whether
                        <pb facs="0465" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/> the enthusiasm of the staff
                    planners indicates that the Chiefs are finally veering around to this concept.
                    The thought expressed by the Pentagon planners was that initially we should
                    attempt to bring about a four-power planning organization along the lines of the
                    moribund Middle East Defense Organization concept but without the direct and
                    overt Western participation which that contemplated and without attempting to
                    bring in any of the Arab States except Iraq. The ultimate objective, of course,
                    would be a full defensive pact possibly with additional participation from
                    states both within and without the Near East, but our military contacts in
                    question thought that much could be accomplished toward the defense of the area
                    without going that far.</p>
                <p>Having convinced themselves that it could be utilized to implement the strategic
                    concept they favored, the Joint Staff working group thought we should
                    concentrate most, if not all, of our available military aid funds for the Near
                    East, in this and succeeding fiscal years, on strengthening Iraq, Iran, and
                    Pakistan. (Turkey, of course, would get substantial help in any case.) They
                    would propose to do this even if only three, or perhaps only two, of the four
                    countries in question were disposed to enter into the kind of arrangement
                    contemplated. In other words, they considered that joint planning even if
                    confined to Turkey and Pakistan, Turkey and Iran, Turkey and Iraq, or any other
                    possible combination of two or more would be a significant step toward an
                    eventual satisfactory arrangement for the war-time defense of the Middle East
                    and South Asia and one which we should support to the extent of our
                    abilities.</p>
                <p>I do not know how far this thinking has spread in the Department of Defense. We
                    may have further indications within the next week or two since the Joint Chiefs
                    of Staff are expected shortly to give us their views on the manner in which
                    military aid funds should be apportioned in the area. On the part of the staff
                    planners, it seems to have been compounded of a number of elements: (a) the
                    changed situation in Iran and reports they had read of the Shah’s interest in
                    building an effective defense force; (b) the insistently expressed desire of
                    Pakistan leaders for closer military ties with us; (c) continuing indications of
                    Iraqi concern with the menace of the North and consequent disposition to
                    co-operate with the British and ourselves; (d) the possibility which the
                    combination of these elements with the elimination of the old Arab–based <gloss
                        target="#t_MEDO1">MEDO</gloss> project seemed to afford of developing an
                    organization which could be keyed directly to what they considered a viable
                    strategic concept.</p>
                <p>I need hardly say that in the abstract, the idea of the four-power pact appeals
                    as much to the Department of State as to anyone in the Pentagon. It is directly
                    in line with the Secretary’s idea of concentrating <pb facs="0466" n="426"
                        xml:id="pg_426"/> on the “northern tier”, which he formulated on his return
                    from his Near Eastern trip last Spring. If the pact should be developed, and the
                    Defense Department endorses the strategic concept which it would appear to carry
                    with it, we would be provided with a solid basis for military programs to the
                    region which is now altogether lacking. The modest military assistance programs
                    which will be developed this year must be justified almost entirely on political
                    grounds, and in the absence of more solid military justification prospects for
                    future programs will not be too bright. The Chiefs have implied that they will
                    be prepared to start a real military build up once we had a regional defense
                    arrangement in being which would make possible joint planning of the Western
                    Powers with the Middle East states. The difficulties of Congressional persuasion
                    would also be considerably eased. Since we are now reaching a critical stage in
                    the development of national policies concerning foreign aid, whether or not in
                    the next six to twelve months there appears to be a political base on which to
                    build a Middle East defense structure may be decisive in determining whether we
                    ever attempt a military program of real significance in the Middle East. Putting
                    forward at this particular time, however, does raise some serious problems for
                    us: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>It omits all of the Arab States, except Iraq, and likewise Israel. We
                            have been counting substantially on military aid to the Arabs,
                            especially Syria and Egypt, as a lever to improve relations and solve
                            some of the pressing regional problems such as Jordan Valley Development
                            and the Suez Base. Saudi Arabia, too, is very restive and is demanding
                            military aid as a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> for the Dhahran
                            air base and other items we need. Egypt and Saudi Arabia can probably be
                            taken care of as exceptions on military grounds; that is, Defense will
                            probably agree to allocating aid funds to those two countries as the
                            price of getting specific military advantages for our side, but Syria,
                            Jordan, Lebanon and Israel present relatively little military
                            justification for assistance, and although we might succeed in securing
                            limited funds for them this year, they would almost certainly be
                            excluded from any future programs.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Pakistan (not to mention the others) would almost certainly be
                            unwilling to join the pact unless she were assured of substantial
                            American military aid, and this raises the spectre of strong Indian
                            reaction. We may decide to risk this in any case even without a pact,
                            but it is an important consideration.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>If we attempt to bring about a four-power pact, there is a danger that
                            this very fact will bring such heavy pressure from their own peoples and
                            from other Arab States on the Governments of Iraq and Iran as to force
                            them to pull back from their present very tentative overtures to the
                            West, whereas assistance to them on a strictly bilateral basis would be
                            accepted without trouble and even with pleasure.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0467" n="427" xml:id="pg_427"/>
                <p>Other difficulties can also be envisaged such as strong Afghan objection (query:
                    Should Afghanistan be included in the concept?) and the inevitable Russian
                    charges of “aggressive imperialist encirclement”.</p>
                <p>I am writing you this rather lengthy exposition and sending copies to Ambassadors
                        <persName corresp="#p_WAM1">Warren</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BBY1"
                        >Berry</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HHA1">Hildreth</persName>, in
                    order to get the informal views of the men on the spot. I realize that little or
                    nothing of what I have said is new to you, but I thought it might be helpful to
                    set it down on paper as a basis for an exchange of ideas.</p>
                <p>With regard to Iran, of course, the first question to be answered is whether the
                    Shah <hi rend="italic">and</hi> the Government would be willing and strong
                    enough now and in the foreseeable future to risk the domestic and foreign
                    repercussions of a public alignment with a Western-oriented group, even though
                    that group would not be directly and formally tied to the Western Powers. The
                    same question arises, though perhaps to a lesser degree, with regard to the
                    governments of Iraq and Pakistan. Since it has a direct bearing on the answer to
                    this question, I should make clear that in fiscal year 1954 the amount of aid
                    which could be furnished to Iraq, Iran and Pakistan would necessarily be
                    relatively small. As a guess, I would say that Iran might get a total of $20
                    million (including the amounts already earmarked). Iraq perhaps $10 million and
                    Pakistan $15 to $20 million. If all went well, we would assume that larger
                    amounts could be made available in succeeding years, the sums depending
                    primarily on the military value received in the form of strengthened indigenous
                    defense forces and increased military facilities for Western forces in time of
                    need.</p>
                <p>If it should be felt that political factors in the region made it feasible at
                    least to plan for a four-power pact, the next question would be that of the
                    timing and procedures to be adopted. When should the first overtures be made to
                    the respective Governments? Through what channels? Should we try to get the
                    Turks or the Pakistanis to take the lead …, while we lent discreet support in
                    the background? Or would it be better for the United States to make simultaneous
                    direct approaches to all four? How should Britain be brought into the picture?
                    (It would seem impossible to leave her out altogether in a matter affecting Iraq
                    and Pakistan.) Should France have any hand in the operation?</p>
                <p>Many more questions of this kind could be posed, among them the economic
                    capacities of the respective countries to support stronger military forces, but
                    I doubt that it is worthwhile to take up space with them at this juncture.</p>
                <pb facs="0468" n="428" xml:id="pg_428"/>
                <p>It would be a great help to us in <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> if we could
                    have your comments and those of the other Ambassadors concerned at an early
                    date.</p>
                <p>Please treat this letter as strictly informal and personal. It has not been
                    cleared by anyone outside of our Bureau and is intended merely as a preliminary
                    sounding and not a basis for action.</p>
                <p>With all best regards and congratulations on the splendid job you are doing.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John D. Jernegan</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
