<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-01-27T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-01-27T08:00:00-05:00" n="183" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">782.5/1–2754: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 183<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey (<persName corresp="#p_WAM1" type="from">Warren</persName>) to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d183fn1">Repeated to Karachi, London, Paris, and
                                    Berlin.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-01-27T15:00:00+02:00">January 27, 1954—3
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>770. Berlin for Secretary. Foreign Minister ill past few days.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BN1">Birgi</persName> hopes review
                                developments with him this afternoon or tomorrow morning to obtain
                                approval various draft texts including agreement with Pakistan,
                                Turk–Pakistani communiqué and Turk comments re proposed US
                                statements welcoming communiqué and announcing decision extend
                                military assistance Pakistan.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_BN1">Birgi</persName> appreciated problem re
                                press speculation (Department telegrams 812 and 818).<note n="2" xml:id="d183fn2">Neither printed, but see <ref target="#d180">Document 180</ref>.</note> He is seeing <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> correspondent Hangen today and will tell
                                him no agreement exists nor have there been negotiations with
                                Pakistan thereon, although as Hangen aware <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Ghulam Mohammed</persName> discussed
                                possibility Turk–Pakistani cooperation in broad terms when he was
                                here (re Embassy telegram 766, January 27).<note n="3" xml:id="d183fn3">Not printed. It reported the Ankara
                                    representative of the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> had
                                    called to ask the Ambassador’s comment on a flash he had had
                                    from his Washington bureau, saying that Turkey and Pakistan
                                    would be signing a defense agreement immediately.
                                    (782.5/1–2754)</note></p>
                            <p>Instructions to Turk Ambassador Pakistan with texts US–Turk exchange
                                of notes and full background information being forwarded <pb facs="0511" n="471" xml:id="pg_471"/> Karachi by our courier
                                    tomorrow.<note n="4" xml:id="d183fn4">Telegram 17 from Ankara to
                                    Karachi, repeated as 774 to the Department of State, Jan. 28,
                                    reported a courier from Istanbul was arriving the next day with
                                    top secret material from the Turkish Foreign Office for the
                                    Turkish Ambassador in Karachi, and asked the Embassy to arrange
                                    for its delivery. (782.5/1–2854)</note> Summary instructions by
                                cable. Following substance instructions: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Agreement almost reached with US on tactics and timing.
                                        Turks awaiting US reply their memo January 23 [<hi rend="italic">21</hi>].<note n="5" xml:id="d183fn5">Not
                                            printed, but see <ref target="#d175fn3">footnote 3,
                                                Document 175</ref>.</note> Meanwhile Ambassador to
                                        take no action pending further instructions.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>For reasons secrecy Ambassador to discuss only with
                                        Governor General and Prime Minister.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>British informed of developments in general by US and
                                        Turks. Instructions review Turk position on three negative
                                        points made by British here re India, Berlin Conference and
                                        participation Western powers in proposed agreement (Embassy
                                        telegram 759, January 25).<note n="6" xml:id="d183fn6"><ref target="#d177">Document 177</ref>.</note></item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item><p>Turk Government has now similarly informed French
                                            Embassy (Embassy telegram 768, January 27).<note n="7" xml:id="d183fn7"><p>Not printed. It advised the
                                                  Department of State that in view of increasing
                                                  press speculation and probable French concern
                                                  about failure to advise them, the Turkish Foreign
                                                  Office had given some general background
                                                  information on the Turkish–Pakistan developments
                                                  to an officer of the French Embassy. The Turkish
                                                  Foreign Office explained that since it was a new
                                                  Turkish–Pakistan initiative, unrelated to the
                                                  Middle East Defense Organization, there was no
                                                  Western participation in the proposed agreement.
                                                  (782.5/1–2754)</p>
                                                <p>Telegram 2675 to Paris, repeated to Ankara,
                                                  Karachi, and London, Jan. 28, advised the
                                                  Embassies the French Embassy in Washington had
                                                  been informed of the general line of U.S. thinking
                                                  on Middle East defense matters, including the
                                                  possibility of Turkish–Pakistan arrangements and
                                                  U.S. assistance to Pakistan, and the hope of the
                                                  U.S. Government for French support if Turkey
                                                  should make a statement in the North Atlantic
                                                  Council. (780.5/1–2854)</p></note></p></item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>In view press speculation Ambassador to limit any public
                                        statement to general observations re Turk–Pakistani
                                        friendship and co-operation avoiding reference any defense
                                        agreement or military planning. Instructed consult and
                                        coordinate with our Ambassador this regard.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>Draft of proposed agreement will be telegraphed in
                                        Turkish. To avoid errors in translation Ambassador
                                        instructed request English text from our Embassy (which will
                                        be transmitted soonest by us).</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WAM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Warren</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>