<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-31T17:34:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="256" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d256">
                        <head>No. 256<lb/><hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi></head>
                        <p>Despatch 639 from Beirut, May 28, transmitted to the Department of State
                            copies of the completed agreements negotiated by the Trans-Arabian
                            Pipeline Company (<gloss target="#t_Tapline1">Tapline</gloss>) with the
                            Governments of Lebanon and Syria. The agreements with Lebanon consisted
                            of three letters, each dated May 17, and signed by the Lebanese Prime
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_SSB1">Sami Bey Solh</persName> and C. A.
                                <persName corresp="#p_SCA1">Swigart</persName>, President of <gloss target="#t_Tapline1">Tapline</gloss>. The first letter covered the
                            disposition of crude oil entitlement and the right to import and export
                            currencies and foreign exchange at the free market rate. The second
                            covered an increase in the loading fee, and the third consisted of a
                            collection of small items. The agreement with Lebanon was to be
                            effective on the date of signature, May 17. The Syrian agreement
                            consisted of one document, signed on May 21 by <persName corresp="#p_SCA1">Swigart</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SCF1">Fawzi Selo</persName>, the Chief of State and President of the
                            Council of Ministers. It was similar to the Lebanese agreement but was
                            to come into force upon ratification by the Syrian Government.</p>
                        <p>Despatch 653 from Beirut, June 3, transmitted a copy of the Iraq
                            Petroleum Company Heads of Agreement, with Appendices, negotiated <pb facs="0636" n="596" xml:id="pg_596"/> between the company and the
                            Lebanese Government. It had been signed on May 15 by <persName corresp="#p_SSB1">Sami Solh</persName> and S. Belgrave, for the
                                <gloss target="#t_IPC1">IPC</gloss>. The agreement was to be
                            submitted to the Parliament for ratification within the next few weeks
                            but, since it had been approved by the President and Prime Minister,
                            little opposition was expected. Documentation on this topic is in
                            Department of State file 883A.2553.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>