<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-05-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="29" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d29">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 59 D 95, CF
                            156</note>
                        <head>No. 29<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Second
                                Secretary of Embassy in Lebanon (<persName corresp="#p_MAH1">Meyer</persName>)</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d29fn1">This
                                conversation took place at the American Embassy in
                            Lebanon.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                <lb/> ST D–5/5</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Beirut</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-05-17">May 17,
                                    1953</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Lebanon</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>Participants:</head>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_DJF2">John Foster
                                            Dulles</persName>, Secretary of State</item>
                                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Henry A.
                                            Byroade</persName>, Assistant Secretary of State</item>
                                    <item>The Honorable Douglas MacArthur II, State Department
                                        Counselor</item>
                                    <item>Lt. Colonel Stephen Meade, U.S. Army</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Lebanon</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Col. <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">William A.
                                            Eddy</persName>, Middle East Consultant for <gloss target="#t_Tapline1">TAPLINE</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">ARAMCO</gloss></item>
                                    <item>Dr. Park Johnson, Presbyterian Field Representative</item>
                                    <item>Dr. William Stoltzfus, President Beirut College for
                                        Women</item>
                                    <item>Dr. Alford Carleton, President Aleppo College</item>
                                    <item>Reporter: <persName corresp="#p_MAH1">Armin H.
                                            Meyer</persName>, Second Secretary of Embassy</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Deteriorating Situation in the Near East</hi>.
                                Dr. Carleton opened the discussion by remarking that he and his
                                three associates represented altogether over 100 years of
                                association with the Near East. They regretted to report that the
                                situation in this area is worse than it was several years ago, that
                                frustration is deeper, and that there exists fundamentally a keen
                                sense of insecurity. They feared that this disintegration is not
                                only detrimental to United States interests, but is tragic for the
                                area itself. At the root of the trouble, of course, was Israel,
                                against whom the Arabs are conducting a cold war of much greater
                                importance to them than the cold war against Russia. Dr. Carleton
                                reported Colonel Shishikli had told him recently that not one
                                significant case can be cited where the United States has said no to
                                Israel. Unless America does something, Dr. Carleton said, it is no
                                use to talk to the Arabs at all. Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName> later asserted that the
                                United States has lost its <pb facs="0122" n="82" xml:id="pg_82"/>
                                “bargaining power” and that the situation is reaching the bottom, as
                                in Iran, where the local inhabitants do not expect anything and
                                cannot be bargained with. He stated that at the forthcoming meeting
                                of Arab Finance Ministers, discussions would take place to use oil
                                as a weapon against the West. The alternative to remedial action by
                                the United States was “awful”, according to Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName>, who believes the Shishikli,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NGM1">Naguib</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CC2">Chamoun</persName> regimes may be America’s
                                last chance. Dr. Johnson said the Arabs have lost faith in
                                disinterested help from America. No Arab leader can stick his neck
                                out to collaborate with the West, he said.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi>. Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName> reported that he passed
                                through Jerusalem two days after the Secretary’s party and found
                                there utter sadness at the Secretary’s having contributed to the
                                violation of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> resolution
                                regarding Jerusalem by dining with Israeli officials in Jerusalem.
                                Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName> also recalled
                                that the U.S. Ambassador had acceded to Israeli wishes by attending
                                the inauguration ceremony in Jerusalem. If we are not able, Colonel
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName> said, to do
                                anything for the Holy City of Jerusalem, the Arabs can see no help
                                from us. When Dr. Carleton suggested the Israelis should be pushed
                                back, the Secretary asked who would do it. The Secretary also asked
                                what was Jordan’s attitude toward internationalization. Dr. Carleton
                                explained Jordan opposed simply because they have no faith in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and that if <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> took over Jerusalem’s administration, the entire
                                city would soon be an annex to Israel. Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName> was also sure that Israel
                                would score a <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi>. He agreed that
                                practically it would be most difficult to carry out
                                internationalization, but he insisted that the United States should
                                not meet the Israelis in Jerusalem. He reiterated that Israel was
                                clearly violating a specific <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                                Resolution. The Secretary pointed out that <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Resolutions are only recommendations, and that the
                                tendency is for each interested party to expect the other fellow to
                                live up to the resolution with which the interested party is
                                concerned. He noted that the Arabs were first to oppose the 1947
                                resolution and did so with violence. Now they want to return to that
                                resolution which they could have had five years ago.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Asylum in U.S. for Arab Refugees</hi>. When Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName> asked just what
                                the United States could or should do, one suggestion made by Dr.
                                Stoltzfus was that the United States might offer to take in a token
                                number of Arab refugees to show our good will. Such a gesture would
                                soften Arab attitudes. The Assistant Secretary replied that this
                                proposal has been given thorough consideration and the answer
                                usually was that such a move would be a sign to the Arabs that we do
                                not really understand their problem. Dr. Johnson suggested that it
                                not be a single isolated proposal but that <pb facs="0123" n="83" xml:id="pg_83"/> it be a part of a whole program. Compensation,
                                he said, is a psychological as well as a financial problem.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">United States Attitude</hi>. The Secretary
                                declared that there is not the slightest tendency for the present
                                administration to be pro-Jewish, since it is not under any
                                obligation whatsoever to Jewish interests. What the administration
                                must do, he said, is what is good for the United States. It is not
                                easy, the Secretary pointed out, to view favorably the steps of what
                                one might call a pro-Arab policy. It would require, for example, a
                                position against the United Kingdom in Egypt and that meant turning
                                over about the only strong point in the Near East to chaos. Not only
                                would that strength be wiped out but there would indeed be, as
                                General <persName corresp="#p_SCF1">Robertson</persName> had told
                                him, a state of war between Egypt and the United Kingdom. It would
                                be impossible, therefore, to have both a pro-UK and a pro-Arab
                                policy. The Secretary indicated that there is a present British
                                tendency to work out an alliance with Israel, basing their thinking
                                on hard-headed military realities concerning the Suez and the Near
                                East. The question arises shall the United States see these strong
                                points (Suez and Israel) wiped out in the Near East. In the ensuing
                                uproar, Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName> gained
                                the floor and said that as a former U.S. military observer he could
                                state that never would Israel serve usefully as a striking force for
                                us. All that would happen would be that the perimeter of hate would
                                be enlarged. Israel conceivably could move into Amman, Damascus and
                                Beirut, but staying there would be another question and United
                                States forces would be required to occupy every Arab village and
                                town in the event of global conflict. The Secretary stated he was
                                not advocating this course of action, but it appears to be current
                                Churchillian theory, and he posed the theory in order to get answers
                                from the visitors present. He added that the British even had an
                                occasional thought about occupying Cairo and Alexandria. Dr.
                                Carleton this time gained the floor and declared that any linking of
                                the Suez and Israel issues would be fatal. Israel, he said, must be
                                frozen in its tracks. The Secretary reiterated that he was merely
                                looking for answers. Past U.S. policies were bad, and he was asking
                                provocative questions to obtain useful ideas.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Secretary’s Thinking re Israel</hi>. The
                                Secretary then outlined his current thinking on the Israel question
                                and wondered whether this thinking was sufficiently drastic.
                                Specifically, he believed: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>The presence in the Arab world of the Secretary and his
                                        associates was in itself a noteworthy and helpful
                                        measure.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>Under legislation currently being sought from Congress,
                                        increasing aid is planned for the Arab States. This is a
                                        break with the past.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0124" n="84" xml:id="pg_84"/>
                                    <label>(c)</label>
                                    <item>The United States Government should consider some form of
                                        guarantee against Israeli expansion. Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName> insisted it be a U.S.
                                        not a <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> measure.</item>
                                    <label>(d)</label>
                                    <item>Something should be done to create a military balance
                                        between the Arabs and Israelis. Israel now is much the
                                        stronger, which in itself is an inducement to aggression. He
                                        realized also that by building up Arab military potential,
                                        we run the risk of stoking the fires for a second round
                                        against the Israelis.</item>
                                    <label>(e)</label>
                                    <item>Formal peace is not possible in the near future. It will
                                        have to come bit by bit, gradually.</item>
                                    <label>(f)</label>
                                    <item>Full internationalization of Jerusalem would require
                                        troops which we are not willing to commit. Therefore, some
                                        sort of international control other than outright
                                        internationalization appears most practical.</item>
                                    <label>(g)</label>
                                    <item>Joint border controls should be promoted. The Secretary
                                        mentioned progress in this direction during his visit to
                                        Israel and Jordan.</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Colonel <persName corresp="#p_ECWA1">Eddy</persName> thought that the
                            Arab boycott of Israel was the last phase of past developments in that
                            issue and that the elimination of the boycott should not be pushed until
                            Israelis expansion has been frozen. The Secretary replied that perhaps
                            the control of Israel’s subsidy could be used to stop Israeli expansion
                            and he noted that this tool has already had a salutary effect on Israeli
                            immigration. Decrease in subsidy, furthermore, has caused unemployment
                            to rise in Israel, which while not a happy thing, was in this case a
                            stabilizing factor.</p>
                        <p>All the above things, the Secretary said, might ease the tensions,
                            eventually permitting us to proceed with building strength in the area.
                            The time factor, however, is important, and better results would be
                            likely if the Egyptian stumbling block can be removed.</p>
                        <p>In closing, the Secretary thanked the four American “Near East hands”,
                            and said he appreciated the opportunity to put up the problems to them
                            in the general quest for solutions.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>