<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-02-06T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-02-06T03:00:00-05:00" n="329" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">886A.2553/2–654: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 329<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Saudi Arabia
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_WG1" type="from">Wadsworth</persName>) to
                                the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d329fn1">Repeated to Dhahran.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Jidda</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-02-06T11:00:00+03:00">February 6, 1954—11
                                a.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>333. 1. <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> and Pacific Western Oil
                            Company received on January 31 identical letters from Minister of
                            Finance <persName corresp="#p_SSA1">Abdullah Suleiman</persName> stating
                            agreement had been concluded between <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss>
                            and AS Onassis Company and quoting Article 4 thereof which in substance
                            provides all oil shipped from Saudi Arabia by a concession and oil
                            companies or their parent companies must be shipped (a) in tankers owned
                            by companies and employed in transport Saudi oil prior December 31, 1953
                            or (b) in tankers of “Saudi Arabian Maritime Company” (presumably joint
                                Onassis–<gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> Company controlling
                            Onassis-owned tankers). Letter instructed companies take necessary steps
                            to put provisions Article 4 of agreement into effect.</p>
                        <p>2. Preliminary reaction Owen <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss>
                            representative to <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> and according to
                            him other <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> officials is that
                                <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> cannot <pb facs="0827" n="787" xml:id="pg_787"/> accept shipping arrangements provided
                            Article 4 of agreement. Owen states Terry <persName corresp="#p_DJT1">Duce</persName> is briefed re <persName corresp="#p_SSA1">Shaikh
                                Abdullah</persName>’s letter and can inform Department fully why
                            arrangements set forth in letter are impracticable.</p>
                        <p>3. At Owen’s request, I touched on matter briefly at end my audience with
                            King at Tabuk February 3 (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 331,
                            February 4)<note n="2" xml:id="d329fn2">Not printed.</note> and
                            requested his permission obtain further information on agreement from
                                <persName corresp="#p_SSA1">Shaikh Abdullah</persName>; King agreed.
                            I also requested him permit companies discuss implications agreement and
                            its effect on Saudi Arabian interests with appropriate Saudi officials
                            and with King himself if companies considered desirable. After some
                            hesitation King said company should first discuss it with Finance
                            Minister after which he willing receive <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> officials if they believed agreement harmful
                            country’s interests.</p>
                        <p>4. According Owen, <persName corresp="#p_OFW1">Ohliger</persName>
                            <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> Vice President in charge
                            concession affairs has telegraphed King requesting audience but as of
                            last night had not received reply. Owen flew Dhahran yesterday for
                            company conference. I shall comply his request defer discussing matter
                            with <persName corresp="#p_SSA1">Shaikh Abdullah</persName>.</p>
                        <p>5. King outlined some benefits agreement would bring Saudi Arabia as
                            follows: Free transport oil for <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> use,
                            royalty payment to <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> of 1 1/2 shilling
                            per ton on all other oil transported by Onassis tankers; 50 Saudis would
                            be trained yearly therein; most important tankers would be subject Saudi
                            law and regulations and fly Saudi flag.</p>
                        <p>None of these provisions agreement were mentioned in letter to oil
                            companies but Owen has obtained substantial confirmation thereof from
                            unofficial sources. He is also told Onassis agreed to build drydock
                            Jidda.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WG1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Wadsworth</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>