<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-08-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-08-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="469" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d469">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">884A.10/8–1252</note>
                        <head>No. 469<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Israeli Ambassador (<persName corresp="#p_EAS1" type="from">Eban</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d469fn1">A covering letter (No. AE/310, not printed) was
                                dated Aug. 11.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">AE/315</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-08-12">August 12, 1952</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Ambassador of Israel presents his compliments to the Honorable the
                            Secretary of State and has the honor to refer to the Notes exchanged
                            between the two governments on April 30<note n="2" xml:id="d469fn2">Neither printed.</note> and May 1, 1952<note n="3" xml:id="d469fn3">For the agreement for emergency assistance effected by exchange of
                                notes at Washington dated May 1, which entered into force May 1, see
                                3 <gloss target="#t_UST1">UST</gloss> (pt. 3) 4266.</note>
                            concerning the utilisation by Israel of funds available under the United
                            States Mutual Security Act of 1951.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In paragraph 4 of his Note of April 30, 1952 the Secretary of
                                State announced his decision to despatch a representative to Israel
                                for the purpose of surveying the current financial and economic
                                problems of the country. In reply, the Ambassador of Israel conveyed
                                his Government’s willingness to receive such a representative and to
                                provide the fullest available information on its foreign exchange
                                income and expenditures, its internal budgets and fiscal procedures.
                                The Government of Israel further agreed to make such information
                                available for the duration of United States economic assistance to
                                Israel.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>During the month of July 1952, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MRF1">Mikesell</persName>, the representative of the United States
                                appointed pursuant to the Secretary of State’s Note of April 30,
                                1952, carried out a rapid survey in Israel of the country’s
                                short-term debt position on the basis of information made available
                                by the Government of Israel. The Government of Israel drew attention
                                to urgent obligations which would arise for payment from the first
                                week of August 1952 onward. It also conveyed its view that even
                                after fulfillment of these immediate obligations, periodic
                                emergencies would inevitably occur unless Israel was assisted to
                                refinance the major portion of its short-term dollar <pb facs="1020" n="980" xml:id="pg_980"/> indebtedness, amounting to
                                approximately $115,000,000 for the twelve months’ period beginning
                                July 1, 1952.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In the course of examining its financial problems in recent
                                months, both before and during Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MRF1">Mikesell</persName>’s mission, the Government of Israel became
                                aware of the need to institute substantial revisions in its economic
                                and fiscal policies, as well as in some of its administrative
                                procedures. Early in 1952, the Prime Minister announced a series of
                                economic reforms, calculated to combat inflation and to restore
                                financial equilibrium. This policy, which involved an
                                intensification of austerity programs and a stricter control of all
                                foreign currency expenditures, has borne marked results; yet it
                                cannot, in the nature of things, have yielded its full effect within
                                so brief a time. At this stage, the Government of Israel has decided
                                to adopt further detailed measures to promote financial recovery and
                                to avoid recurring threats to its financial structure. In accordance
                                with paragraph 8 of his Note of May 1, 1952, the Ambassador of
                                Israel, on instruction from his Government, herewith conveys to the
                                Government of the United States the following information on the new
                                steps which will be taken with this aim in view.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item><p>The Government of Israel is now in the course of preparing a
                                    foreign exchange budget for the twelve months’ period beginning
                                    July 1, 1952. Every effort will be made to have this budget
                                    ready by September 15, 1952. The foreign exchange budget will
                                    constitute a working basis for Israel’s foreign currency
                                    operations throughout the year, and will accordingly be drawn up
                                    along the following lines: <list>
                                        <label>(a)</label>
                                        <item>No part of Israel’s revenues either for current or
                                            development purposes during the twelve months beginning
                                            July 1952 shall be derived from a net increase in short-
                                            and intermediate indebtedness. On the contrary, it will
                                            be Government policy to attain the maximum net reduction
                                            of outstanding short-term debts by repaying such amount
                                            of short-term debts as may be feasible and refunding as
                                            much as possible into long-term obligations.</item>
                                        <label>(b)</label>
                                        <item>Non-transferable or tied income items will be matched
                                            against appropriate specific items of expenditure. Cash
                                            expenditures and debt service will be off-set only
                                            against cash income.</item>
                                        <label>(c)</label>
                                        <item>Due consideration will be given to all outstanding
                                            obligations.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>Within the twelve months’ period, the principles described in (a)
                                    and (b) will be modified only when there are seasonal
                                    fluctuations in income and expenditure. It will be the policy of
                                    the Government of Israel to regulate its expenditures within the
                                    limits of this foreign exchange budget.</p></item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Since the assistance extended by the United States under the
                                Mutual Security Act of 1951 and 1952 constitutes an important
                                element <pb facs="1021" n="981" xml:id="pg_981"/> in Israel’s
                                foreign exchange income, the Government of Israel intends to make
                                its detailed foreign exchange budget available to the
                                representatives of the United States Mission in Israel. In order to
                                facilitate effective co-operation in the use of such assistance
                                between the Government of Israel and the representatives of the
                                United States Mission in Israel, the Government of Israel intends to
                                follow the procedure of regular consultations with that mission
                                which would enable stock to be taken periodically of Israel’s
                                financial position.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>The Ministry of Finance will keep records showing all incomes,
                                expenditures, commitments, new credits or borrowings, imports and
                                services carried out or authorized, external and internal cash
                                positions and cash balances in all currencies. Figures for each
                                month will be analysed in relation to all sections of the Israel
                                budget, with special reference to the foreign exchange components
                                thereof.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>The Government of Israel intends to establish concurrently with
                                the preparation of the foreign exchange budget, a special
                                Governmental Organ endowed with full authority to make all
                                allocations of foreign currency, including the granting of
                                permission to make foreign exchange commitments against foreign
                                exchange income. The Government is resolved to take all measures to
                                ensure that all foreign exchange committments will be kept strictly
                                within the limits of its foreign exchange income. As soon as
                                possible, a system of accounting will be instituted under this Organ
                                which will reveal the current and prospective foreign exchange
                                position of the country weekly or monthly according to the nature of
                                the item.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>It is the intention of the Government of Israel to centralize all
                                import programming including the screening as to order of priority
                                of requirements submitted by various ministries.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>The Government of Israel adheres to the view presented by the
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Ambassador of Israel to the
                                Secretary of State on June 19, 1952, that any fundamental
                                stabilization of its financial position will be impossible, unless
                                longer periods of maturity can be obtained for its indebtedness, the
                                impact of which is especially heavy for the twelve months’ period
                                beginning July 1952. The Government of Israel, for its part, will
                                make every effort to negotiate arrangements with its creditors
                                whereby short-term debts might be extended and spread over a longer
                                period of years, provided that Israel’s credit standing with
                                pertinent creditors would not thereby be impaired to the extent of
                                making it impossible for the State to supply the population with the
                                most basic necessities. Meanwhile, the Government of Israel will not
                                divert current income to net debt retirement at a rate <pb facs="1022" n="982" xml:id="pg_982"/> which will make it
                                impossible for Israel to cover her essential import needs.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>The Government of Israel fully recognizes that the reforms
                                necessary to achieve a balanced foreign exchange budget will require
                                increased sacrifices on the part of its people and it is prepared to
                                make such sacrifices. The Government is confident that the new
                                measures which it has decided to adopt, and especially those
                                enumerated above, will help the country to advance, through arduous
                                efforts and heavy sacrifices, toward a balanced economy in a manner
                                worthy of the democratic principles and social ideals which Israel
                                strives to exemplify, and conducive to the continuation of internal
                                stability which it has so far been able to maintain, in a troubled
                                and unstable area. While the difficulties which these measures are
                                designed to overcome are admittedly acute, they do not constitute
                                the sole or main element of Israel’s economic situation. These
                                difficulties, in part, arise from a process of dynamic growth, at a
                                rate scarcely precedented in the history of nations. In sharing a
                                frank discussion of these difficulties with the Government of the
                                United States, Israel is moved by a sense of profound appreciation
                                of the assistance which the Government and people of the United
                                States are rendering to it in the critical and formative period of
                                its early development.<note n="4" xml:id="d469fn4">Acknowledged by
                                    the Department of State in a note of Aug. 28, not printed.
                                    (884A.10/8–1252)</note></item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>