<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-12-31T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-12-31T11:00:00-05:00" n="537" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d537">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">884A.00 TA/12–3152: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 537<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Israel (<persName corresp="#p_DMB1" type="from">Davis</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d537fn1">Repeated to Amman, Damascus, and
                            Beirut.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tel
                                        Aviv</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-12-31T18:00:00+02:00">December 31, 1952—6
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1064. <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 881.<note n="2" xml:id="d537fn2">In telegram 881 from Tel Aviv, Nov. 28, <persName corresp="#p_DMB1">Davis</persName> reported that <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Sharett</persName> had mentioned to him that
                                morning having seen press reports that Jordan and Syria had signed
                                an agreement on the Yarmuk project. <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Sharett</persName> referred to prior expressions of the Israeli
                                Government’s interest in the matter and its desire to be kept
                                informed, and suggested that a project involving Yarmuk water rights
                                should be the subject of international conversation. <persName corresp="#p_DMB1">Davis</persName> recommended to the Department
                                early action to bring Israel into discussions.
                                (884A.2614/11–2852)</note> Helpful attitude toward Yarmuk project
                            indicated by Israeli Government in August (when Foreign Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Sharett</persName> suggested to <persName corresp="#p_FER1">Fryer</persName> and me that US Point IV and
                            Israel engineers discuss matter so that Israeli Government would be
                            sufficiently informed to avoid actions that might hamper project—<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 281)<note n="3" xml:id="d537fn3">Telegram 281 from Tel Aviv, Aug. 18, reported that Ambassador
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DMB1">Davis</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FER1">Fryer</persName> had expressed the hope to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Sharett</persName> that the Israeli
                                Government would not put obstacles in the way of Jordan’s Yarmuk
                                project. <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Sharett</persName> suggested
                                that U.S. Point Four and Israeli engineers discuss the matter at a
                                technical level in order that Israel be sufficiently informed to
                                avoid actions that might hamper the project. A representative of the
                                Foreign Ministry had recently reexpressed the interest of the
                                Israeli Government in having such discussions take place. (884A.00
                                TA/8–1852)</note> has been replaced by one of suspicion and
                            resentment.</p>
                        <p>In line with apprehension revealed by Foreign Minister, (<gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>), chief US division Foreign
                            Ministry again raised Yarmuk question with Embassy officer, stating that
                            “rumor strongly persists that mutually beneficial agreement for the
                            construction of a dam as well as for a power and irrigation scheme has
                            been signed between Syria and Jordan”. Israel, he stated, “is not being
                            kept informed” and “fears it will be faced with <hi rend="italic">fait-accompli</hi>”. In reply to Embassy officers reminder that
                            Department had reaffirmed its assurances that it viewed favorably
                            discussions between Israel experts and the engineers concerned,
                            informant took position that meeting of engineers was now of “secondary
                            importance” and that basic principle was involved. He stressed fact that
                            Jordan’s complaint last summer to changing salinity of Jordan River was
                            taken up with Israel Government, while Israel not being kept informed of
                            Yarmuk project <pb facs="1128" n="1088" xml:id="pg_1088"/> vital to her
                            interests. Expressed opinion that “If Israel finds self faced with <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> it will have to draw obvious
                            conclusion that unilateral action by one side justifies unilateral
                            action by other”. During same conversation <persName corresp="#p_TJ1">Tekoah</persName> of Foreign Ministry legal division reinforced
                            above view with specific reference to interests of Kibbutzim on right
                            bank of Yarmuk and Palestine electric concessions, and stressed
                            “Israel’s right to be consulted before plans for project worked out”.
                            Water problems in area, he emphasized, could only be handled on
                            inter-state basis and Israel ready to discuss water problems directly
                            with Arab countries on any level.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DMB1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>