<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 699Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State to the President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d699</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">699</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="699"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d699">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_EGAD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_EGAD1">Eisenhower</persName> papers, <persName corresp="#p_WA2"
                        >Whitman</persName> file</note>
                <head>No. 699<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d699fn1">The memorandum was initialed by President <persName
                            corresp="#p_EGAD1">Eisenhower</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-10-21">October 21,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum for the President</hi>
                </p>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Attention</head>
                    <item>General <persName corresp="#p_CBGPT1">Paul T. Carroll</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Withholding Aid to Israel</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="1412" n="1372" xml:id="pg_1372"/>
                <p>Attached for your information is a telegram<note n="2" xml:id="d699fn2">
                        <p>The telegram, addressed to the President, was sent as telegram 643 from
                            the Embassy at New Delhi on Oct. 18 at 9 a.m. It reads as follows:</p>
                        <p>“Our recent on-the-spot investigation of the Arab-Israel situation leads
                            us to the unanimous conclusion that our government should immediately
                            cease all aid to Israel until said state takes appropriate action to
                            comply with United Nations directives and resolutions. We are convinced
                            that continued economic support of Israel in the face of the reported
                            acts of aggression and other flagrant violations of United Nations
                            directives and recommendations has led to serious deterioration of not
                            only Arab-American relations but also our relations with the entire
                            Moslem world. Signed <persName corresp="#p_AHC1">H. Cal
                                Andersen</persName>, chairman Ben F. Jensen, Oakley Hunter.”
                            (684A.86/10–1853)</p>
                    </note> from three members of the <persName corresp="#p_AHC1"
                        >Andersen</persName> subcommittee of the House Appropriations Committee
                    opposing aid to Israel until it complies with <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    directives.</p>
                <p>In this connection, you may be interested to know that no economic aid funds have
                    been made available to Israel so far during this fiscal year. The first
                    allocation of funds was just being made when word was received that the Israelis
                    were unilaterally diverting the Jordan River in the demilitarized zone at Banat
                    Yaacov. We informed the Israel Ambassador on September 18 that we would not
                    release any funds until the Banat Yaacov matter was clarified, as we did not
                    want our assistance to coincide with an Israeli action which might result in
                    hostilities.</p>
                <p>Later, the Chief of Staff of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Truce
                    Supervisory Organization requested the Israel Government to cease its work on
                    the diversion of Jordan River waters. Rather than comply, the Israel Government
                    speeded up construction on the diversion dam. We thereupon told the Israelis
                    that we would not feel justified in releasing aid until they had complied with
                    the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> decision, and that cessation of work after
                    completion of the dam would not, in our view, constitute compliance.</p>
                <p>The matter has been further complicated by the recent attack by Israeli forces on
                    Jordan frontier villages. In concert with the UK and France, we have taken the
                    question to the Security Council of the United Nations.</p>
                <p>We do not plan to authorize release of any economic aid funds to Israel until
                    these issues have been resolved to our satisfaction.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGW1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Walter B. Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
