<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 794The Secretary of State to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d794</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">794</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-04-12T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-04-12T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recbqzzF4Eebaylpi" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="border-administration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006007505"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Border control</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-04-12T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-04-12T19:00:00-05:00" n="794"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d794">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">684A.86/4–1354: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 794<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-04-13T01:00:00+01:00"
                            >April 13, 1954—1 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 4. For Acting Secretary from the
                    Secretary. In morning meeting April 12 with <persName corresp="#p_ESA1"
                        >Eden</persName> we discussed at length Israeli-Arab situation. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KSI1">Kirkpatrick</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ASR1">Roger
                        Allen</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SCAE1">Shuckburgh</persName>
                    present. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AWW1">Aldrich</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BWW1">Butterworth</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MLT1"
                        >Merchant</persName> with me.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> said King of Jordan angry at British
                    over his recent statement in Commons to which he had refused to add new
                    gloss.</p>
                <p>I said that I was deeply disturbed over situation in Middle East and that I
                    feared Israel may calculate that matters cannot improve until they become worse.
                    Conditions under the armistice are unsatisfactory with Israel treated as an
                    enemy, blockaded, etc. I said that inference could be drawn from Israeli acts
                    that they were prepared to reopen war in order to create situation from which
                    peace settlement rather than armistice would follow. The Arabs for their part, I
                    said, were fearful of a new attack. A new factor in situation was weight now
                    being thrown behind Arabs by Soviets as witnessed to by their recent vetoes. All
                    of this meant that the area with its immense oil reserves were in increasing
                    jeopardy. I concluded by saying that these events were not likely to happen in
                    near future. It was entirely possible that in year or two they would come to
                    pass and that it was difficult to know with certainty the proper course of
                    action for us to follow. I expressed doubt that by US following more balanced
                    policy in area, we could count on so increasing our influence with Arab states
                    as to promote stability and harmonious relations.</p>
                <pb facs="1554" n="1514" xml:id="pg_1514"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> said that he agreed entirely with
                    our analysis as well as my apprehensions and that he likewise was puzzled as to
                    policy to pursue. He said that UK had tried to get Jordan and Israel together on
                    border problems but that Jordan had refused. He believes that <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> now will veto any such talks within the
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, although <persName corresp="#p_ASR1"
                        >Allen</persName> expressed doubt on this score. <persName corresp="#p_ASR1"
                        >Allen</persName> noted that Prime Minister of Jordan had recently told UK
                    Ambassador that he would not personally object to meeting on frontier problems
                    with the Secretary General in small subcommittee of the Security Council.</p>
                <p>I said that it was my understanding Arabs would not agree to any agenda for such
                    a meeting and that all they were interested in was securing another resolution
                    of censure for Israel.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ASR1">Allen</persName> suggested (and <persName
                        corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> agreed) that only current course was to
                    nibble at edges of problem seeking first frontier control. He felt we should
                    continue to try to get them together under the aegis of <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss>. Failing that, we might attempt procedure now being used with
                    Trieste under which two of us presumably the French would talk first to one side
                    and then the other in effort to narrow area disagreement and find solution
                    acceptable to both parties.</p>
                <p>I pointed out physical as well as political difficulties of effective border
                    control and emphasized importance of restoration cooperation between both police
                    forces which I had urged on my trip last May.</p>
                <p>The matter was left that we agreed our estimates of the situation and its
                    seriousness were substantially identical but that I had not committed the US to
                    any particular proposal or course of action. <persName corresp="#p_ESA1"
                        >Eden</persName> said that UK would attempt to put their suggestions for
                    moving forward on frontier problem in concrete form and then instruct their
                    Embassy to discuss it with Department.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<persName corresp="#p_DJF2">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
