<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 811The Acting Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic and Consular
                    Offices</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v09p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d811</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">811</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-04-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-04-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-04-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-04-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="811"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d811">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">684A.86/4–2854: Circular airgram</note>
                <head>No. 811<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                            <gloss type="to">Certain Diplomatic and Consular Offices</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d811fn1">Sent to Amman, Baghdad, Beirut, Cairo, Damascus,
                        Jidda, London, Paris, Tel Aviv, and Jerusalem.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>–6175</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-04-28">April 28,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Discussions With UK on Arab-Israeli Border Situation</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Department initiated on April 26 discussions with representatives of the
                    British Embassy on means to bring about in the short term period improvements in
                    the present situation on the Israel-Jordan border. The British representatives
                    were given a copy of the attached paper which sets forth the rationale for the
                    talks and the possible measures which might be taken. It was made clear to the
                    British that the paper is a working level document and does not represent a firm
                    Department position. The points given under Section III(B) were taken from the
                    useful suggestions received from the <persName corresp="#p_SFM1"
                        >Field</persName> to which were added thoughts developed in the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>The British presented a paper containing suggestions from the Foreign Office
                    based in turn on comments from British posts. Although differing in wording and
                    emphasis, the British proposals correspond to points 2, 4, 6, 7, 10, 11 and 13
                    of Section III(B) of the enclosure. . . .</p>
                <p>The British informed the Department that their suggestions had been made
                    available to the French, who expressed no objection in principle except to the
                    provision for frontier rectification.</p>
                <p>The objective of the present discussions is to obtain agreement between the Three
                    Powers on measures which might be taken. Until the course of the discussions in
                    the Security Council becomes clearer, it is not feasible to determine definitely
                    how the proposals could be presented most effectively to the parties. Direct
                    diplomatic action by the Three Powers in Amman–Tel Aviv could complement and
                    support any work of the Security Council.</p>
                <p>The Department recognizes that implementation of the various measures may involve
                    a considerable financial outlay which, in turn, would affect the United Nations
                    budget. Therefore, it will be necessary to consider the budgetary situation in
                    determining which measures should be adopted and their order of priority.</p>
                <pb facs="1573" n="1533" xml:id="pg_1533"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Action required:</hi> The Missions in the Arab Capitals,
                    Jerusalem and Tel Aviv are requested to submit as soon as possible their
                    comments on the feasibility and usefulness of the different points listed under
                    Section III(B). Any additional suggestions also would be welcomed.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGW1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Enclosure</note>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>Subject:</head>
                        <item>Arab–Israel Border Situation</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>Problem:</head>
                        <item>To bring about in the short term period improvements in the present
                            dangerous situation on the Israel–Jordan border.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">I. Existing Situation</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>Israel apparently has embarked upon a policy of aggravating the border
                            situation in the belief that, at the risk of open warfare, she can force
                            the replacement of the Armistice by a peace settlement. The use of force
                            and retaliatory raids appear to be deliberate Government policy.
                            Although the problem caused for Israel by Arab infiltration should not
                            be minimized, the evidence indicates only individuals or small groups
                            are responsible. Jordan has made a determined effort within its
                            capabilities to stamp out this practice.</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>Israel has been campaigning for a high-level meeting over an extended
                            period. She wishes as broad a discussion as possible, including what
                            would amount to peace talks. However, according to <persName
                                corresp="#p_SR1">Shiloah</persName>, she is prepared to accept a
                            fixed agenda, limited to consideration of measures to improve the
                            operation of the Armistice Agreement. Israel has withdrawn from
                            participation in local commanders’ meetings in retaliation for alleged
                            Jordanian failure to curb infiltration.</item>
                        <label>C.</label>
                        <item>Jordan has refused to attend a high-level meeting or to honor her
                            obligations under Article XII. She apparently feels such talks would
                            lead to discussions of a permanent peace with Israel. In her refusal,
                            she has been supported by the Arab League.</item>
                        <label>D.</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and Arab obstructionism has
                            fettered efforts of the Security Council to take effective action on the
                            Palestine questions.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">II. Procedures</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The problem may be approached through three different mechanisms: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>Through a procedural Security Council resolution designating a <hi
                                    rend="italic">rapporteur</hi> and asking him to consider with
                                the parties and <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> representatives
                                concerned means to improve the border situation. The US and UK are
                                now supporting Security Council action, although <pb facs="1574"
                                    n="1534" xml:id="pg_1534"/> they have differences of opinion
                                over how discussions with the parties should be carried out. The
                                British have favored establishment of a subcommittee.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>If efforts in the Security Council prove fruitless, a meeting
                                between Jordan and Israel might be secured through direct diplomatic
                                action by the Western Powers in Amman and Tel Aviv, using the
                                Tripartite Declaration as a point of departure.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Endeavor to secure separately Israel’s and Jordan’s agreement to
                                concrete measures to improve the border situation. The Tripartite
                                Powers would “shuttle” between Amman and Tel Aviv for the purpose.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> intends to propose
                                this approach to the Secretary in Paris on April 24. We have
                                telegraphed the Secretary that we approve the proposal, but believe
                                the timing of the first approach should be decided after the course
                                of the Security Council discussion becomes clearer.</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>Considering Soviet obstructionism in the Security Council and
                                probable Jordanian refusal to attend a meeting, “C” appears to offer
                                the only prospects.</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item>In considering procedure, account should be taken of the
                                following: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The Armistice Agreement, which forms the legal basis for
                                        the existing situation, may be modified only by the parties.
                                        The same is true of the <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss>
                                        rules of procedure. Thus, agreement between the parties to
                                        any changes appears essential.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Under existing circumstances, the <gloss target="#t_MAC1"
                                            >MAC</gloss>s and <gloss target="#t_UNTSO1"
                                            >UNTSO</gloss> do not provide an adequate forum to cope
                                        with the situation.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and particularly the
                                            <gloss target="#t_UNTSO1">UNTSO</gloss> should be
                                        represented at any meeting in view of its importance in the
                                        Palestine problem and the danger to its prestige which would
                                        result from exclusion.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Jordanian fears of a meeting could be eased by spelling
                                        out the agenda in advance, making clear the discussions
                                        would be within the context of the armistice agreements and
                                        would not involve “peace talks.”</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>Because the Arabs become so intractable when in a group,
                                        Syrian, Egyptian and Lebanese participation along with
                                        Jordan at any meeting should be avoided if possible.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">III. Substance</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The parties themselves are responsible for enforcement of the Armistice and,
                        therefore, for preventing border incidents. The <gloss target="#t_UNTSO1"
                            >UNTSO</gloss> has no enforcement authority; its role is to observe and
                        report. Consequently, the essential ingredient is cooperation between the
                        parties and a desire by the parties that the frontier should remain quiet.
                        (The importance of this point is stressed by all comments from the <persName
                            corresp="#p_SFM1">Field</persName>.)</p>
                    <p>Two possibilities may be considered: <pb facs="1575" n="1535"
                            xml:id="pg_1535"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>Assumption by the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> or the Western
                                Powers of direct responsibility for border security, involving, in
                                effect, discarding as unworkable enforcement by the parties of the
                                Armistice Agreement. <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The course would involve a heavy commitment, including
                                        willingness to use force to prevent violation of the
                                        frontier. The force could take the form of troops provided
                                        by the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> or Western
                                        Powers.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The procedure would be warranted only if the conclusion is
                                        reached that cooperation between the parties cannot be
                                        induced and, therefore, that no amount of tinkering will
                                        render the Armistice Agreement workable.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The present situation does not appear to demand such
                                        drastic measures. They would be required at the end of any
                                        outbreak of open fighting.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>Revamping and strengthening the armistice agreements in letter and
                                in spirit. The essential prerequisite is cooperation by the parties
                                between themselves and with the <gloss target="#t_UNTSO1"
                                    >UNTSO</gloss>. Assuming this cooperation, the following
                                measures could be considered: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>Appointment of a new Chief of Staff, preferably a figure
                                            of world stature (for example, General <persName
                                                corresp="#p_BGO1">Bradley</persName> or General
                                                <persName corresp="#p_VFGJ1">Van Fleet</persName>),
                                            whom the parties would be forced to respect. The timing
                                            and manner of any change would be of the utmost
                                            importance to avoid damage to our relations with the
                                            Arabs, who regard General <persName corresp="#p_BMGV1"
                                                >Bennike</persName> as their friend. The approval of
                                            the Secretary General of the United Nations would be
                                            required, and General <persName corresp="#p_BMGV1"
                                                >Bennike</persName>’s retirement would have to be
                                            presented as voluntary.</p>
                                        <p>Appointment of higher-ranking officers of outstanding
                                            ability as chairmen of the <gloss target="#t_MAC1"
                                                >MAC</gloss>s.</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Increase number of observers, recruiting with special
                                        attention to quality and impartiality. The period of service
                                        of the observers, except for the Chief of Staff and <gloss
                                            target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss> chairmen, could be
                                        shortened since old timers appear to develop localitis. If
                                        the term of service is relatively short, the observers could
                                        be expected to live in frontier villages near the usual
                                        trouble spots. At present the tendency of the observers is
                                        to live on the Arab side of the lines. They should be
                                        required to divide their time between the two sides and
                                        should be provided an increased cost-of-living allowance to
                                        meet the higher costs on the Israel side.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Assignment on a consultation basis of experts from the
                                        United States-Mexican border service and of special police
                                        officers. Such officials might be expected to have
                                        worth-while suggestions for controlling infiltration and
                                        investigating crimes. The British military and colonial
                                        services might provide officers with similar
                                        experience.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Assignment of United Nations translators, and
                                        politico-legal advisers to each <gloss target="#t_MAC1"
                                            >MAC</gloss>.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>Recognition in practice by the parties that the observers
                                        have freedom of movement and investigation, including the
                                        unquestioned <pb facs="1576" n="1536" xml:id="pg_1536"/>
                                        right to cross the frontiers at any point the observers deem
                                        advisable.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>Adoption of new rules of procedure in the <gloss
                                            target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss>s. An objective would be to
                                        speed up the process of investigation and of handling of
                                        complaints in the <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss>.
                                        Specifically, the chairman should be permitted to introduce
                                        resolutions and to initiate investigation.</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>Prompt and continuing publicity by the United Nations of
                                            <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss> decisions and of
                                        conditions on the border and responsibility
                                        therefore.</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>Improved equipment for the observers. This might include
                                        assignment of helicopters, which might have special moral
                                        effect on would-be infiltrators and could patrol the lengthy
                                        frontier. Assignment of tracking dogs directly to the <gloss
                                            target="#t_UNTSO1">UNTSO</gloss>. Improved radio
                                        communication.</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>Acceptance by the parties of their obligation to attend
                                            <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss> and other meetings
                                        called by appropriate United Nations officials.</item>
                                    <label>10.</label>
                                    <item>Clear delineation of the demarcation line by United
                                        Nations surveyors, followed by the erection of physical
                                        barriers at points of greatest friction. Jordanian
                                        apprehensions that demarcation would imply acceptance of
                                        permanent frontiers for Israel could be minimized by a
                                        statement similar to that contained in the Armistice
                                        Agreement—the boundaries delineated are without prejudice to
                                        the rights, claims and positions of either party hereto in
                                        the ultimate peaceful settlement of the Palestine question
                                        (Article II).</item>
                                    <label>11.</label>
                                    <item>Notification to the <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss> by
                                        both parties of the punishment given persons accused and
                                        convicted of infiltration or other individual violations of
                                        the Armistice. Such sentences need not be published. The
                                        procedure could serve to reassure Israel, particularly, that
                                        Jordan is making sincere efforts to stop
                                        infiltration.</item>
                                    <label>12.</label>
                                    <item>Issuance of passes for the movement of Arabs from the Gaza
                                        Strip to Jordan under United Nations supervision. The
                                        movement could take place in convoys along specified routes.
                                        At the present, a relatively large-scale illegal movement
                                        takes place between these two points. Legalization of this
                                        traffic, which generally may be innocent in motive, should
                                        serve to reduce incidents.</item>
                                    <label>13.</label>
                                    <item>Reinstatement of the local commanders’ agreements. The
                                        persons concerned with armistice enforcement, including
                                        General <persName corresp="#p_RLG1">Riley</persName> and
                                        General <persName corresp="#p_BMGV1">Bennike</persName>,
                                        attach first importance to cooperation on the local level.
                                        Police officials should be used and a premium attached to
                                        maintaining the quietest sector. (Reports from the <persName
                                            corresp="#p_SFM1">Field</persName> attached first
                                        importance to the local commanders’ and similar
                                        agreements.)</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
