<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-08-12T16:32:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-08-12T16:32:00-05:00" n="860" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d860">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">684A.85/8–754: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 860<lb/><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                Egypt</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d860fn1">Sent also to Tel Aviv
                                and Amman.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-08-12T17:32:00-04:00">August 12, 1954—5:32
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>240. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 205 Cairo,<note n="2" xml:id="d860fn2">Printed as telegram 38 to Amman, <ref target="#d853">Document 853</ref>.</note> Cairo 179, Tel Aviv
                            147, Amman 45, to Dept.<note n="3" xml:id="d860fn3">Documents <ref target="#d855">855</ref>–<ref target="#d857">857</ref>.</note><persName corresp="#p_DBGM1">Dayan</persName>
                            apparently had meeting of military rather than police commanders in
                            mind. View <persName corresp="#p_GLCS1">Gohar</persName>’s expressed
                            willingness meet Israel counterpart and since arrangement in Gaza area
                            would require only one as opposed to perhaps three meetings along Jordan
                            frontier Dept. inclined suggest Embassies Cairo and Tel Aviv endeavor
                            arrange meeting between Israel and Egypt commanders for some time after
                            20th. Tel Aviv might explain to <persName corresp="#p_DBGM1">Dayan</persName> that although Department officers gathered from
                            Washington talk he would prefer first meeting take place between
                            Jerusalem commanders Department feels less complications involved if
                            start made in Gaza. Present concern in Jordan over impending changes
                                <gloss target="#t_UNTSO1">UNTSO</gloss> personnel would also appear
                            indicate advisability making first attempt in Gaza.</p>
                        <p>Both Embassies should stress to governments importance <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> attaches arrangements designed lessen
                            incidents along frontier and sincere US hope that out of this first
                            meeting a workable procedure for lessening tensions Gaza and elsewhere
                            might evolve. Topics for discussion might include improvement methods
                            for prevention infiltration and reduction instances nervous unauthorized
                            firing by forces across armistice lines. Will be recalled April
                            discussions broke down when Israelis attempted broaden agenda to point
                            where Egyptians feared “peace talks.” Governments should be urged limit
                            agenda to border problems which Emb Tel Aviv might emphasize must be
                            resolved to foster atmosphere conducive settlement other Israel-Arab
                            issues.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF2"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>