<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-04-30T12:55:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-04-30T12:55:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                        <head>143. Telegram From the Embassy in France to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d143fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 676, Country Files—Europe, France, Vol.
                                V. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-04-30T17:55:00+00:00">April 30, 1970,
                                1755Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>5481. Pass Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WAK_1">Watson</persName>.</p>
                        <p>1. I am concerned about the way the French, after a long period of
                            relative quiet about Viet-Nam, are beginning to disassociate themselves
                            publicly from US in that area. So far this has been more implicit than
                            explicit, but <persName corresp="#p_SM_1">Schumann</persName>’s remarks
                            in his widely circulated statement to the National Assembly April 28
                            (Paris 5426)<note n="2" xml:id="d143fn2">Not found.</note> revives and
                            strongly reaffirms the Gaullist line on Indochina which was so harmful
                            to us on previous occasions. <persName corresp="#p_SM_1">Schumann</persName>’s line on Cambodia, lauding as he did Sihanouk
                            just at a moment when we are offering badly needed help to Lon Nol, is
                            symptomatic and worrying. This more blatant anti-Lon Nol and
                            pro-Sihanouk <gloss target="#t_GOF_1">GOF</gloss> line is also reflected
                            on the French television which on occasions has presented the Cambodian
                            affair as largely a civil war between two Cambodian factions,
                            overlooking the presence of 40 thousand NVA/VC in Cambodia.</p>
                        <p>2. My fear is that this implicityly anti-U.S. line on Cambodia could soon
                            be expanded into an explicitly anti-U.S. line on the whole Indochinese
                            question, including Viet-Nam. This could do a lot of mischief.</p>
                        <p>3. Certainly efforts should be made to prevent such a development. I do
                            not think we could in the short run persuade the French to change their
                            policy, for they seem to be convinced that it is in their interest to
                            maintain a sort of pro-Communist neutrality throughout Indochina. I do
                            feel, however, that by high-level intervention we might get them to shut
                            up or perhaps even take a slightly more benevolent “wait and see” public
                            line towards coming events in Indochina.</p>
                        <p>4. Therefore, I suggest that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WAK_1">Watson</persName> might carry an oral message on the Cambodian
                            situation from President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>
                            to <persName corresp="#p_PG_1">Pompidou</persName> which he could
                            deliver during the private conversations after the presentation of
                            credentials ceremony on May 6.<note n="3" xml:id="d143fn3">No oral
                                message was prepared. In telegram 5748 from Paris, May 6, <persName corresp="#p_WAK_1">Watson</persName> reported that during the
                                presentation of credentials ceremony, “<persName corresp="#p_PG_1">Pompidou</persName> repeated small quotation of Sihanouk to him
                                that Sihanouk would like us to gradually leave but not all of them.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PG_1">Pompidou</persName> stated that he
                                is trying to keep as moderate a view as he can possibly do in the
                                current Cambodian situation, but he is very much against current
                                operation for he fears that the Far East can be as harmful to the US
                                as Algeria was to France, adding that an American undoing would
                                therefore be an undoing of France, Europe and the West.” (National
                                Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 676, Country Files—Europe, France, Vol.
                                V)</note> Before the <pb facs="0554" n="515" xml:id="pg_515"/>
                            President’s statement tonight about the Indochina situation, we do not
                            wish to suggest anything specific.<note n="4" xml:id="d143fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> gave a speech on
                                southeast Asia at 9 p.m. on April 30. (<hi rend="italic">Public
                                    Papers: <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>,
                                    1970,</hi> pp. 405–410)</note> However, as the aim of the
                            exercise would be to persuade the French to keep quiet, Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_WAK_1">Watson</persName> could well ask
                                <persName corresp="#p_PG_1">Pompidou</persName> to withhold judgment
                            on our policy and maintain a public posture which would not make our
                            efforts to manage the situation more difficult.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_BR_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Blake</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>