<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>213. Memorandum for the President’s File by the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v41</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d213</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">213</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="213"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d213">
                <head>213. Memorandum for the President’s File by the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d213fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, White House Special Files,
                        President’s Office Files, Memos for the President. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-10-11">October 11, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>’s Meeting with
                        Italian Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Aldo Moro</persName> on
                        October 11, 1971, from 11:30 a.m. to 12:20 p.m. in the Oval Office of the
                        White House</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <head>ALSO PRESENT</head>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_OE_1">Egidio Ortona</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. Neil Seidenman (Interpreter)</item>
                </list>
                <p>The President said he is always glad to see the Foreign Minister, and
                    particularly at this time, while he is in the US for the <gloss target="#t_UN_1"
                        >UN</gloss> General Assembly, and prior to his return to his country to face
                    some rather serious political problems.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Moro</persName> thanked the
                    President, adding that it was comforting to know that the President has followed
                    the situation in Italy with such close attention and understanding. Indeed,
                    there are problems in that quarter. The Foreign Minister stated that he
                    nevertheless had hope and confidence that even against a background of an
                    agitated situation in the area of social issues, there are other areas of solid
                    ground, in particular that of foreign policy. The President can be assured that
                    in this area, despite the various controversies that crop up among the coalition
                    parties, there is no conflict with regard to the United States and fidelity to
                    the Atlantic Alliance as the mainstay of Italian policy. Even the PSI, which has
                    a number of internal problems, is steadfast on this score. At the present time,
                    looking toward the Presidential elections, it is difficult to foresee what
                    difficulties may arise. Some parties may hold back and shift position according
                    to electoral needs. However, they can surely be counted upon to act with a sense
                    of responsibility, particularly in the light of requirements affecting social
                    issues, while having to work concurrently against the problems of recession.
                    Still, it is likely that they will proceed with greater responsibility in view
                    of decreasing public disorder over recent months. Hence it would seem one is
                    justified in hoping to overcome the critical social issues and to move in
                    harmony with the other members of the European family. It should also be noted
                    that with the political monopoly of the Soviet Union dissolving, repercussions
                    are being felt within the <gloss target="#t_PCI_1">PCI</gloss>. <pb facs="0753"
                        n="714" xml:id="pg_714"/> Because of this, there is a general trend toward
                    greater freedom of action in the political sphere and strengthened interest in
                    the problems of Europe, with all political forces at work enjoying increasing
                    freedom from pressures from the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>The President observed that as we look at the free world today, we see more than
                    one hundred nations of all sizes. But as we look at these, with their economic,
                    political, and military strength, in being or potential, we can look at the free
                    world as “one hand.” In Europe, the major nations are four: Italy, Germany,
                    France, Great Britain. With the US there are five, and looking at another part
                    of the world, Japan makes six. But what these countries do together, to the
                    extent they are able to develop similar policies in the economic field and other
                    areas, including actions in the area of their foreign policies, they will
                    greatly influence and affect the future of freedom in the world. That is why we
                    consider that we have a special relationship with Italy, France, Germany, Great
                    Britain, Japan. However, this does not mean that tiny nations are not important
                    to us, such as Chad. But we must be sure to maintain close consultation among
                    the major powers of the free world about how to face issues that confront
                    us.</p>
                <p>The President said he was aware that Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> had discussed the US approach to the
                    difficult vote coming up at the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>. He said he
                    wished to reaffirm our position on this matter as it was stated to him by
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>. The President said he
                    was aware that this represented a hard problem for Italy. However, with
                    reference to the US position, our view is that for the <gloss target="#t_UN_1"
                        >UN</gloss> not to consider the expulsion of a member country from that body
                    to be an Important Question would constitute a disastrous precedent. Were that
                    position to be approved, the President saw the possibility of future situations,
                    at times when emotions were high, for example, where if one or more nations did
                    something that was not to the liking of a simple majority of members, they would
                    be <hi rend="italic">out</hi>, and that could mean the collapse of the
                    Organization. This is why we deem it essential to have the issue of expulsion
                    considered as an Important Question. In the second place, support for the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> in Congress would be in jeopardy, if it were
                    felt in that body that the United States could not obtain enough support at the
                        <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> to have something of critical importance
                    in our view considered as an important question. The President added that he was
                    not making these statements in order to put pressure on the sovereign and
                    independent government of a good friend, but simply to explain why the US
                    considers this matter to be so essential.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Moro</persName> thanked the President for his
                    very articulate and tactful approach to the issue, especially with reference to
                    the first point he had made. Italy has every wish as an independent nation and
                    as a part of Europe to work with the United States. The emergence of “new
                    centers <pb facs="0754" n="715" xml:id="pg_715"/> of influence” means to Italy
                    precisely that the countries of Europe, Europe as a whole, and the United States
                    will seek common approaches to the greatest number of issues, certainly on all
                    the important problems. It is for this reason that there is confidence that
                    solidarity among friends will enable our countries to find solutions to economic
                    and monetary problems that have come to the fore. With reference to the second
                    subject raised by the President, Italy is very much aware of the weight and
                    seriousness that the US attaches to this question, which has been set forth with
                    great eloquence. For this very reason, the Italians find themselves in very
                    difficult circumstances. The United States, of course, thanks to the President’s
                    bold and forward-looking initiative, has taken an important step toward China.
                    Italy has moved further down the road of diplomatic relations with China, and
                    within this context is eminently aware of the weight and importance that China
                    attaches to a vote of recognition, which must be recognition as the only
                    legitimate government of the Chinese people. Then, as the President is
                    undoubtedly aware, the Italian government is at grips with the domestic
                    political considerations involved. Each year Italy has had to face this issue,
                    trying to balance all the pressures surrounding it, personified by Hon.
                        <persName corresp="#p_NP_1">Nenni</persName> who has long been one of the
                    staunchest advocates of recognition, as well as for solidarity with the US.
                        <persName corresp="#p_NP_1">Nenni</persName>, himself, will visit China
                    October 20. It is in the light of this background that it is useful to gather
                    the views of the US on this particular matter so that they might be fully and
                    accurately conveyed to the Government of Italy and help toward making a
                    responsible decision. The President may be certain that the very last thing the
                    Italians want is to do something that would dismay the US. Every effort is made
                    so that whatever is done will help, not harm the US. Therefore it is with this
                    spirit of friendship toward the US that Italy will take up this question in
                    great earnest, at the same time coupled with an acute awareness of the
                    international implications of the problem, and recognizing the possible domestic
                    repercussions concerned. The Foreign Minister reiterated his appreciation to the
                    President for the delicate manner in which he presented this issue, and again
                    gave assurances that all of the President’s comments would be taken very closely
                    into account by the Government of Italy in reaching a decision.</p>
                <p>The President suggested that the two governments remain in very close touch
                    regarding the matter. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    would be back from his trip to the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>,<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d213fn2">October 16–25.</note> before the vote takes
                    place.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Moro</persName> agreed, stating that Ambassadors
                        <persName corresp="#p_OE_1">Ortona</persName> and Vinci would be entirely
                    available for consultation.</p>
                <pb facs="0755" n="716" xml:id="pg_716"/>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> stated that he did not
                    foresee that anything would happen during his visit to Peking that would affect
                    the voting, therefore nothing of an embarrassing nature should be expected.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Moro</persName> asked the President what the
                    strategic outlook was, with regard to China, setting aside the tactical
                    approach, which he understood at this point. What are the prospects for a
                    solution to the problem of Formosa vis à vis China, given Formosa’s insistence
                    that its government should represent the Chinese people? Does the President
                    envision an ultimate solution to this problem, or does he think of this in terms
                    of a situation that will endure and which must be accepted by all parties
                    concerned?</p>
                <p>The President said that it might be interesting to hear from Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> in this connection when he returns
                    from his trip, barring those aspects of the discussions there that cannot be
                    readily divulged. But essentially it is an historical process.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> stated that in the first
                    place, we have been careful at the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> not to
                    take a position with regard to this. The analogy we draw of this is the case of
                    the two votes accruing to the Soviet Union, considering the vote of
                    Byelo-Russia. This would constitute a precedent for two votes by one country
                    within the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>. In the second place, it is a
                    question of taking a historic viewpoint, as pointed out by the President. The
                    fact that both governments involved agree that there is only one China may make
                    an eventual negotiated solution easier. There might be greater difficulty were
                    one of the governments to claim that there are two Chinas. Hence we would not
                    have to make a judgment as to legitimacy of governments involved.</p>
                <p>The President at this point said he wished only to stress that the issue must not
                    be settled by force. This is admittedly not a clear answer, but the situation
                    itself is not clear and is very complex. The President emphasized further that
                    he was aware of the domestic implications of this issue in Italy. But he said he
                    could not himself underestimate the problems the US would have regarding our
                    relationship with the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> if Taiwan is expelled
                    from the Organization.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Moro</persName> congratulated the President for
                    the work the US is carrying forward in seeking an end to the problem of the
                    Middle East. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>’ quiet,
                    patient mediations has been resourceful and admirable, and while they have yet
                    to produce concrete results, still they constitute the essential thread that
                    holds the parties to the search for an ultimate solution. While Israel and Egypt
                    continue to maintain their divergent positions, there would seem to be some hope
                    that a formula for opening the Canal as a partial solution might constitute a
                    necessary step toward the larger solution that is sought. In this regard, the
                    work <pb facs="0756" n="717" xml:id="pg_717"/> of Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> is essential and encouraging as a vital
                    contribution on the part of the US to world peace, and toward avoiding another
                    conflagration in that part of the world.</p>
                <p>The President thanked the Foreign Minister for his remarks, and expressed his
                    appreciation for the role of Italy in the Middle East problem, as the major
                    Mediterranean power involved, therefore having much at stake. The President
                    concluded by saying, “Without getting myself into Italian politics: Buona
                    fortuna!”</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Moro</persName> thanked the President, expressing
                    the hope that it would be within their power to continue to move toward progress
                    along lines for freedom, justice, and friendship toward the United States.</p>
                <p>The President observed that President <persName corresp="#p_SG_1"
                        >Saragat</persName> has been a strong president who has consistently acted
                    in support of these principles.</p>
                <p>At the end of their remarks, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA_2">Moro</persName>
                    approached the President to ask whether he envisioned early efforts to solve the
                    economic and financial problems at issue. The President reassured him on this
                    score, saying that the US is not going to become isolationist. He said that the
                        <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> meeting was set up so as to work toward
                    establishing a solid structure, and that Minister Ferrari Aggradi was
                    helpful.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
