<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-01-31T17:51:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-01-03T14:00:00-05:00" n="217" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d217">
                        <head>217. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>After a prolonged deadlock, Christian Democrat <persName corresp="#p_LG_1">Giovanni Leone</persName>, who had previously
                            served as Prime Minister in two short-lived all-DC minority governments
                            in 1963 and 1968, won election as President of the Italian Republic on
                            the 23rd ballot, December 24, 1971. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CE_1">Emilio Colombo</persName> resigned on January 15,
                            1972, after representatives of the Republican Party withdrew from his
                            government. An effort by <persName corresp="#p_AG_2">Giulio
                                Andreotti</persName> to obtain parliamentary confirmation of a
                            minority all-DC government failed on February 26. On February 28,
                                <persName corresp="#p_LG_1">Leone</persName> dissolved Parliament
                            before completion of its 5-year term for the first time in Republican
                            Italy’s history.</p>
                        <p>The May elections resulted in only minor changes in the parliamentary
                            representation of the three largest parties—Christian Democratic,
                            Communist, and Socialist. By now the Socialists and Social Democrats had
                            dissolved their merger; running separately, however, their share of the
                            vote closely followed their combined total in 1968. The Socialist Party
                            of Proletarian Unity (PSIUP), however, lost all 23 of its seats in the
                            Chamber of Deputies and in July formally merged with the Italian
                            Communist Party. Among the smaller parties, the Liberals lost heavily in
                            both chambers of Parliament while the Republican Party showed strong
                            gains. The neo-fascist Italian Social Movement doubled its seats in both
                            the Chamber of Deputies and the Senate.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>