<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-02-28T11:41:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-02-28T11:41:00-05:00" n="219" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d219">
                        <head>219. Backchannel Message From the Ambassador to Italy (<persName corresp="#p_MG_2">Martin</persName>) to the President’s Deputy
                            Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d219fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 424, Subject Files,
                                Backchannel Messages Europe 1972 [2 of 2]. Secret; Sensitive;
                                Immediate; Eyes Only.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Rome</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-02-28T16:41:00+00:00">February 28, 1972,
                                1641Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>495. Reference: WH 20959, 25 Feb 1971.<note n="2" xml:id="d219fn2">Not
                                found.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>1. Until the last moment, there was a bit of uncertainty whether the
                            generally agreed script, ending in an unprecedented dissolution and
                            early elections, would be followed to the end. <persName corresp="#p_LG_1">Leone</persName> signed the dissolution decree
                            this morning at 10:07 and we are now faced with elections on 7 May. I
                            am, therefore, now able to respond with more precision to your message
                            of 25 February.</p>
                        <p>2. The temper of the country definitely is swinging to the right.
                                <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Almirante</persName> will gain most from
                            this trend unless the Christian Democrats make an all-out effort which I
                            believe they are inclined to do. They will need help.</p>
                        <p>3. The Communist <gloss target="#t_PCI_1">PCI</gloss>, still smarting
                            from the severe psychological shock of the public humiliation of their
                            miscalculation in the Presidential elections, will go all out and will
                            receive considerable support from the Soviet Union. They are deeply
                            worried about the threat from their left and are desperately trying to
                            prevent the Manifesto Group<note n="3" xml:id="d219fn3">Reference to a
                                dissident group of Communists who had been expelled from the <gloss target="#t_PCI_1">PCI</gloss> in 1969 over issues of policy and
                                party discipline. The dissidents organized their efforts around a
                                small circulation newspaper, <hi rend="italic">Il Manifesto</hi>,
                                which was influential in intellectual circles.</note> from filing
                            separate electoral lists.</p>
                        <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_SG_1">Saragat</persName>, motivated primarily by
                            a burning desire to recapture control of the <gloss target="#t_PSDI_1">PSDI</gloss> from which he was on the verge of being practically
                            excluded, has succeeded in forcing an electoral line which, while still
                            anti-Communist, will be more to the left than the majority of the rank
                            and file of his party would have liked. Consequently, the <gloss target="#t_PSDI_1">PSDI</gloss> will lose several hundred thousand
                            votes they might otherwise have counted on. These votes will not all be
                            lost to the centrist forces, however, and the <gloss target="#t_PSDI_1">PSDI</gloss> may enter the new Parliament with about its present
                            strength. <persName corresp="#p_SG_1">Saragat</persName>’s present line
                            may attract some support which would have gone to the Socialists.</p>
                        <p>5. The Republicans are expected to make considerable gains, while the
                            outcome for the Liberals is uncertain. If they wage an aggressive <pb facs="0767" n="728" xml:id="pg_728"/> campaign, they may draw votes
                            away from the <gloss target="#t_MSI_1">MSI</gloss> on the basis that a
                            vote for the Liberals may contribute to a sound base for a centrist
                            government while a vote for the <gloss target="#t_MSI_1">MSI</gloss>
                            will be wasted.</p>
                        <p>6. [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>] He has arranged
                            channels to keep the two of us in quiet, unobtrusive but intimate
                            contact. He believes this election to be as important to Italy and to
                            overall American policy as were those in 1948. He has requested that we
                            help as much as we can. I have said that we would do what we could.</p>
                        <p>7. I have not yet seen [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                                declassified</hi>] but expect to do so in the coming week. I have
                            indicated in previous conversations that we would be inclined to be
                            helpful if the [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                            declassified</hi>] showed more cohesion and compactness than had been
                            evident in recent years. He believes that their success in the
                            Presidential election, and the subsequent cohesion that brings us now to
                            early elections, has met that pre-condition. I agree.</p>
                        <p>8. We have reviewed the situation this morning and have arrived at the
                            following priorities and general order of magnitude of [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] for a vastly
                            expanded political action program over the period between now and May
                            7:</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">3 paragraphs (7 lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>9. Under existing authority, I have today committed [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] to get the preliminary
                            organizational activities under way. This leaves us with only [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] left from the
                                [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]
                            authorized by the 1971 March 10 decision of the 40 Committee.<note n="4" xml:id="d219fn4">See <ref target="#d208">Document 208</ref>.</note>
                            I would prefer to keep this separate as a reserve rather than blanket it
                            into the new authorization I have requested in para 8 above. If more is
                            needed as targets of opportunity present themselves during the
                            elections, I shall not hesitate to ask.</p>
                        <p>10. I do not know whether you actually have to have a meeting of the 40
                            Committee before going ahead with the additional authorization, but
                            obviously time pressures will be very great. I anticipate no
                            difficulties except perhaps with my inflexible and continuing
                            pre-condition—that the authority for the mix and implementation be left
                            entirely under my authority. I just don’t intend to have another Chile
                            here.</p>
                        <p>11. Our friend mentioned in your last paragraph<note n="5" xml:id="d219fn5">[<hi rend="italic">name not
                                declassified</hi>]</note> is celebrating his birthday in
                            Switzerland. He is happy as a clam since we have helped him untangle
                            some of his personal problems here. He has accepted the fact that there
                            is only one representative of the President here.</p>
                        <pb facs="0768" n="729" xml:id="pg_729"/>
                        <p>He would be quite happy with the above program if he were to know about
                            it although he has never learned from me that such a program exists and
                            I do not intend to discuss any details with him. Now that elections are
                            upon us, he will be quite relaxed.<note n="6" xml:id="d219fn6">In <gloss target="#t_bckch_1">backchannel</gloss> message 500 from Rome,
                                March 2, <persName corresp="#p_MG_2">Martin</persName> reported [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>] to back the center
                                parties to the fullest extent. (National Archives, Nixon
                                Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                                Box 424, Subject Files, Backchannel Messages Europe 1972 [2 of 2])
                                In telegram WH21059, February 29, <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> thanked <persName corresp="#p_MG_2">Martin</persName> for his evaluation and promised speed action
                                on his request. He added that with the elections set “it will be
                                helpful for you to utilize the services of our friend to the fullest
                                extent feasible.” (Ibid., Backchannel Messages Europe 1972 [1 of
                                2])</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Warm regards.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>