<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-01-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="306" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d306">
                        <head>306. Letter From the Former Ambassador in Spain (<persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Hill</persName>) to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d306fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 706,
                                Country Files—Europe, Spain, Vol. IV. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-01-28">January 28, 1972</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <opener>
                            <salute>Dear Mr. President:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>On leaving my post in Spain,<note n="2" xml:id="d306fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Hill</persName> left post on January
                                12.</note> I would like to call your attention to a major problem
                            remaining in our relations with Spain and give you my thoughts as to how
                            it might be solved.</p>
                        <p>Our relations with Spain are excellent, but in recent months, the Spanish
                            Government has begun to take actions in the military field, which if
                            continued, would greatly diminish the value of the bases to us. [<hi rend="italic">10 lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>I am convinced that there is a relationship between the recent military
                            difficulties and the Spanish Government’s serious concern over our
                            posture regarding their agreement with the European Community, their
                            desire for beneficiary status under our generalized preferences scheme,
                            and their fear that we may impose restrictions on shoe imports from
                                Spain.<note n="3" xml:id="d306fn3">A memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_LM_1">Laird</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>, January 11, expressed
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LM_1">Laird</persName>’s concern that the
                                U.S. position on the Spanish-<gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>
                                preferential trade agreement might result in restrictions on the
                                freedom of U.S. military operations in Spain. A January 12
                                memorandum to William Eberle, Special Representative for Trade
                                Negotiations, provided information on the status and background of
                                the footwear issue in U.S. trade policy. Both memoranda are printed
                                in <ref target="frus1969-76v04#d266">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume IV,
                                    Foreign Assistance, International Development, Trade Policies,
                                    1969–1972, Documents 266</ref> and <ref target="frus1969-76v04#d267">267</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Spanish insist that if we establish a generalized preferences system
                            and exclude Spain because of the reverse preferences Spain grants to the
                                <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>, this would cause political as
                            well as economic problems for them. The Spanish would be satisfied if
                            they could benefit from the system at least until 1975, by which time
                            their integration into the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> will have
                            reached such a point that they could dispense with preferences from the
                            U.S. I urge you to take this course of action.</p>
                        <p>The Spanish understand the problems which shoe imports represent for us.
                            However, unilateral U.S. action to restrict imports of Spain’s leading
                            export product would cause serious difficulties for the Spanish
                            Government. On the other hand, it is virtually impossible politically
                            for the Spanish Government to impose controls on shoe exports unless it
                            can show some concession from the United States in return.</p>
                        <p>The issues of generalized preferences and shoes might be disposed of by
                            tying them together. We could seek agreement from the Spanish <pb facs="0980" n="941" xml:id="pg_941"/> that they would establish
                            voluntary controls on shoe exports, along specified lines, to go into
                            effect when the Congress has passed generalized preferences legislation
                            under which Spain could be a beneficiary, at least until 1975.</p>
                        <p>I propose that the problem of the Spain-<gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> agreement, which poses an even greater threat to our
                            relations, be solved as follows. We could inform the Spanish that we are
                            prepared to support Spain diplomatically in its forthcoming attempt to
                            obtain a commitment from the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> on
                            ultimate full integration. Assuming Spanish willingness, under our
                            bilateral agreement, to offer adjustments or compensation for any case
                            of <hi rend="italic">actual</hi> damage to U.S. exports, we would not
                            press our plan to invoke <gloss target="#t_GATT_1">GATT</gloss>
                            provisions against Spain. In return, we would expect Spain to implement
                            the military provisions of the Agreement of Friendship and Cooperation
                            in a fully cooperative spirit. We should start this course of action as
                            soon as possible, because it must be linked to the forthcoming
                            renegotiation of the Spain-<gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> agreement,
                            which is to take place in the near future.</p>
                        <p>I do not believe any of these problems can be solved in isolation. They
                            should all be dealt with in one negotiation, which, because of its
                            complexity, would have to be conducted through normal diplomatic
                            channels to stand any chance of success.</p>
                        <p>Mr. President, <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Nat Samuels</persName> is
                            well-liked and respected by the Spanish officials. He can do the job and
                            it should be done soonest.</p>
                        <p>With warm regard.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_HRC_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Robert C. Hill</persName><note n="4" xml:id="d306fn4">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Hill</persName> signed “Bob” above
                                    his typed signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>