<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>64. Paper Prepared by the National Security Council Staff</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v41</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d64</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">64</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ministerial meeting</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077241"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Linkage</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recJFd5tAUUdqBj9H" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">East-West relations</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recydYSQ1GmGAh8yu" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recH8UKNUTXoDXkax" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005651"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monitoring</term>
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="64"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d64">
                <head>64. Paper Prepared by the National Security Council Staff<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d64fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H-Files), Box H–182,
                        National Security Study Memoranda, <gloss target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss>
                        121. Secret. This paper is a summary of the 29-page <gloss
                            target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss> 121 Response. <gloss target="#t_NSSM_1"
                            >NSSM</gloss> 121 is <ref target="#d60">Document 60</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-05-14">May 14, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <gloss target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss> 121—Issues at the June, 1971 <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Ministerial Meeting</p>
                <p rend="center">ANALYTICAL SUMMARY</p>
                <p>The US will face three East-West political issues at the <gloss target="#t_NAC_1"
                        >NAC</gloss> Ministerial meeting at Lisbon:</p>
                <p>—the current allied attitudes to issues relating to Germany and Berlin;</p>
                <p>—allied conditions and preparations for a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>,
                    and the question of using a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> to establish
                    permanent East-West machinery; and</p>
                <p>—<gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> and its possible relation to <gloss
                        target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>.</p>
                <p>(Questions to be addressed by the Defense Planning Committee, especially <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> force improvements, are not thoroughly
                    treated in the study but will be handled through the <gloss target="#t_DPRC_1"
                        >DPRC</gloss>. They are discussed briefly at the end of this summary.)</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">I. Germany and Berlin</p>
                <p>Ministers can be expected to review progress and prospects in the Berlin
                    negotiations and other East-West talks relating to Germany. <hi rend="italic"
                        >However, given the current impasse on Berlin, and the linkage between a
                        Berlin agreement and the ratification of <gloss target="#t_FRG_1"
                            >FRG</gloss> bilateral accords with the USSR and Poland, there is no
                        real issue to be resolved at Lisbon</hi>. The study suggests that <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> communiqué formulations will likely be
                    limited to a reaffirmation of allied support for Four Power rights and <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> objectives. State plans to seek allied support
                    in reiterating that a “satisfactory conclusion” of the Berlin talks be obtained
                    before the allies move toward multilateral East-West explorations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">After Lisbon it could become more difficult to maintain allied
                        consensus on this subject</hi>:</p>
                <p>—If the Berlin talks should fail, or appear to drag on without noticeable
                    progress, some allies may wish to abandon the Berlin linkage, especially as
                    regards a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>.</p>
                <p>—Alternatively, a very modest accord on Berlin might not be accepted as
                    sufficient progress to justify forward movement toward a <gloss
                        target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> (especially if the <gloss target="#t_FRG_1"
                        >FRG</gloss> government did not use the agreement to <pb facs="0322" n="283"
                        xml:id="pg_283"/> submit the Moscow Treaty<note n="2" xml:id="d64fn2">The
                        Federal Republic of Germany and the Soviet Union signed the Treaty of Moscow
                        on August 12, 1970. The treaty included an exchange of notes between Germany
                        and the Western Allies on Quadripartite rights and a German letter to the
                        Soviet Government on reunification.</note> to the Bundestag for
                    ratification). The study suggests, however, that the majority of the allies will
                    consider <hi rend="italic">any</hi> Berlin agreement acceptable to the Three
                    Western Powers as adequate for proceeding with multilateral <gloss
                        target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> preparations. A complicating facor is that a
                    Berlin agreement might seem to warrant a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>,
                    but would not lead to ratification of the Eastern treaties.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">II. <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> Issues</p>
                <p>A. <hi rend="italic">Allied conditions for a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>The study points out that as yet no firm allied consensus exists on the specific
                    aims of a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>, its venue and its timing.
                    Nevertheless, many allies believe that a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> is
                    inevitable, and that it can serve Western interests even if it does not lead to
                    a new security system or “peace order” in Europe.</p>
                <p>—A <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>, it is felt, could increase East European
                    freedom of action vis-à-vis the West and perhaps ameliorate living conditions in
                    the East.</p>
                <p>—Some believe a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> might result in the
                    establishment of a mechanism for negotiating real security issues, such as
                        <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>.</p>
                <p>—A <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> would enhance (or at least appear to
                    enhance) the role of the Europeans in East-West relations.</p>
                <p>—Some allies contend that the mere atmospherics of a <gloss target="#t_CES_1"
                        >CES</gloss> would contribute to détente and a reduction of tensions.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, it is recognized by many allies that:</p>
                <p>—Key European security issues (e.g., Germany and Berlin, <gloss
                        target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>) will not be addressed at a <gloss
                        target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>.</p>
                <p>—Moscow could easily use a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> to promote Soviet
                    objectives (e.g., enhance the <gloss target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss>’s status,
                    sanction Soviet rule in Eastern Europe, divide the Western allies, inhibit West
                    European integration, encourage Western Europe to relax its military effort and
                    the US to reduce its military presence in Europe).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">At Lisbon, the study contends, the main issue will be whether
                        or not to go beyond the December, 1970, communiqué position which set two
                        preconditions for allied multilateral explorations</hi> regarding a
                    “conference, or a series of conferences, on security and cooperation in
                        Europe”:<note n="3" xml:id="d64fn3">See <ref target="#d55">Document 55</ref>
                        and <ref target="#d55fn2">footnote 2</ref> thereto.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1) Four-Power talks on Berlin must reach a “satisfactory conclusion;” and</p>
                <p>2) other on-going East-West talks must be “proceeding favorably.”</p>
                <pb facs="0323" n="284" xml:id="pg_284"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Most allies, it is asserted, would now prefer to drop the
                        second precondition of progress in “other on-going talks,</hi> retaining
                    only the Berlin precondition. Bonn believes this would focus greater attention
                    on the importance of a Berlin settlement. <hi rend="italic">The study recommends
                        that the US support restatement of the December, 1970, communiqué position
                        at Lisbon, but that we be prepared to join a consensus, should one develop,
                        in favor of eliminating the second precondition of progress in “other
                        on-going talks.”</hi> (No analysis is presented in support of this
                    recommendation from the standpoint of US interests.)</p>
                <p>B. <hi rend="italic">Preparations for a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>—the
                        Current Drift</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The appendix to the paper outlines three basic concepts of a <gloss
                        target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>:</p>
                <p>1) a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> with very limited objectives, in which
                    the Europeans take the lead and the US plays a less active role, with the aim of
                    convening an early one-time conference;</p>
                <p>2) a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> involving active US participation with
                    clearly defined, but still limited, objectives that might promote further
                    East-West contacts in the security and cooperation areas; and</p>
                <p>3) a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> as a serious policy objective, to be
                    used to establish permanent machinery for the resolution of outstanding
                    East-West issues in Europe.</p>
                <p>By our support for specific <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> agenda items in
                    previous <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> communiqués, and the role we
                    have recently played in the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> East-West
                    negotiations study, <hi rend="italic">the US is currently pursuing the second of
                        the above conceptual approaches to a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>.
                        This will lead to a primarily hortatory conference with limited tangible
                        results</hi>, as the study points out. According to this approach and
                    current studies, the agenda of a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> would
                    include the following:</p>
                <p>a. Principles governing relations between states, including the renunciation of
                    the use of force.</p>
                <p>—<gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> communiqués have already stated that
                    these principles should include “universal respect of the sovereign equality,
                    political independence and territorial integrity of each European state,
                    regardless of its political and social system.” The intent has been to oppose or
                    limit the <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> doctrine.</p>
                <p>b. Issues of cooperation in Europe, including enhanced technical, economic,
                    scientific and cultural exchanges and cooperation on the environment.</p>
                <p>—The Study also notes the idea, informally discussed by the US and some allies,
                    that these essentially non-military issues could be discussed at a Conference on
                    European Cooperation (<gloss target="#t_CEC_1">CEC</gloss>) as an alternative to
                    a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>, should there be no prospect that
                    concrete security issues such as <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> would be
                    addressed at a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>.</p>
                <p>c. Freer movement of people, ideas and information.</p>
                <pb facs="0324" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/>
                <p>—Already affirmed as an agenda item by <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    Ministers, the objective would be to elicit from communist governments actions
                    or commitments which would facilitate an expansion of East-West contacts.</p>
                <p>d. Other issues, including possible negotiations on <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1"
                        >MBFR</gloss> in an appropriate forum, and possibly consideration of
                    permanent machinery (although these issues have so far not been thoroughly
                    addressed and analyzed).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Procedural approaches:</hi> So far the US has expressed a
                    preference for “careful exploratory and preparatory phases,” aimed at reaching
                    maximum East-West consensus prior to a formal <gloss target="#t_CES_1"
                        >CES</gloss>. Believing that the Pact will not be prepared to reach a
                    preliminary consensus on issues prior to a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>,
                    the French have suggested an early conference of Ministers following
                    multilateral explorations, in order to discuss positions, refine them through
                    subcommittees, and later debate them further in later phases of the
                    conference.</p>
                <p>—The paper points out that the French approach would probably focus undue
                    attention on the initial Ministerial gathering, without any assurance that the
                    Soviets would deal meaningfully with issues proposed by <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> in subsequent phases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Assuming as it does the continuation of the present approach,
                        aimed at hortatory and limited tangible results, the study asserts that no
                        definitive new positions need be taken at Lisbon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—It is suggested that Ministers will note the work done to date and request
                    further studies. State recommends forceful language in rebuttal of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> doctrine (while asserting that we may
                    wish to weaken in a trade-off later), and an endorsement of early <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> attention to East-West environmental
                    cooperation if Italy proposes an initiative in this area. Suggesting that
                    Ministers will give only cursory attention to possible permanent machinery
                    beyond asking for further study, the paper offers no US position in this
                    area.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Comment: The study presents no solid discussion of US
                        interests or objectives in a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> or whether
                        we are adopting the approach which is in our best interest</hi>. However, if
                    we are interested in another approach it would necessarily have implications for
                    our posture at the Lisbon meeting. For example, if we were to decide to adopt
                    the third conceptual approach listed above [i.e., to give our full support to a
                        <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> provided that it address real security
                    issues, such as <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>, and establish permanent
                    East-West monitoring and enforcement machinery]<note n="4" xml:id="d64fn4"
                        >Brackets are in the original.</note> the US would presumably want at Lisbon
                    to emphasize steps toward permanent machinery as an essential element of a
                        <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>. Alternatively, if we see no US
                    interests served by a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>, we should retreat
                    from our recent active role in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> studies.)</p>
                <pb facs="0325" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">III. <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>
                </p>
                <p>Recalling positions of recent <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> communiqués
                    in favor of exploratory talks with interested Warsaw Pact states on <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>, and noting the recent statement of the US
                    position in the President’s Foreign Policy Report,<note n="5" xml:id="d64fn5"
                        >The President’s Second Annual Report to Congress on U.S. Foreign Policy,
                        February 25, 1971, is printed in <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName
                                corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>, 1971,</hi> pp. 219–345.</note>
                    the study points out that the allies have yet to reach an agreed position on
                    whether <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> is feasible or advantageous to
                    the Alliance, or how to approach <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>—The <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> maintains that <gloss target="#t_NATO_1"
                        >NATO</gloss>’s public position is ahead of its preparedness to actually
                    engage the East in <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> talks.</p>
                <p>—The <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> has recently proposed a phased process
                    of <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> negotiations, beginning first with
                    principles in the pattern of <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>, then
                    discussing constraints and possible freezes, before addressing the shape of
                    actual reductions. Though precluding multilateral <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1"
                        >MBFR</gloss> explorations before a satisfactory Berlin agreement, the
                    Germans argue that their new approach would enhance <gloss target="#t_NATO_1"
                        >NATO</gloss>’s détente image and militate against unilateral troop
                    cuts.</p>
                <p>—While remaining aloof from <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> deliberations
                    on <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>, the French are now giving the subject
                    more serious consideration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">At Lisbon</hi>, the study suggests, attention will focus on
                    whether the communiqué should signal greater interest in <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> and the program for further <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> studies. <hi rend="italic">There are two
                        specific issues:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1) <hi rend="italic">Our response to recent statements by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KA_1"
                            >Kosygin</persName> expressing Soviet interest in <gloss
                            target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—Several allies are expected to support a statement in the communiqué of allied
                    interest in the recent Soviet position. The paper proposes that the US agree to
                    noting the Soviet statements on the assumption that they contrast with previous
                    Soviet reticence on the subject and may reflect genuine Soviet interest.</p>
                <p>2) <hi rend="italic">Linkage of <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> and <gloss
                            target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>
                    </hi>.</p>
                <p>—The <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> supports some connection in the
                    communiqué between <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>, including a linkage in exploratory
                    discussions prior to a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>. The German
                    contention is that this would ensure that real military security issues be the
                    focus of any eventual <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>.</p>
                <p>—Some, but not all, other allies are expected to support the <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> approach.</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">State proposes to refer in the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1"
                            >NATO</gloss> communiqué to the relationship of <gloss
                            target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> to issues of European security and to
                        discussions related to a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>, but to keep
                        separate from a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> detailed explorations
                        and negotiations on <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>
                    </hi>. Under this formula, <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> negotiations
                    could go forward before, during or after a <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss>
                    in a separate forum. Multilateral <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> talks
                    would not be contingent on a Berlin settlement.</p>
                <pb facs="0326" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> The analysis in the study of the pros and cons
                    of <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>–CES linkage is skimpy and not
                    satisfactory. The linkage issue is not cast against a discussion of what kind of
                        <gloss target="#t_CES_1">CES</gloss> might best serve US interests.)</p>
                <p>Noting that further <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> studies will be needed after the Lisbon
                    meeting to seek an allied consensus on US substantive and procedural approaches,
                    the paper also suggests that <hi rend="italic">the issue of <gloss
                            target="#t_GDR_1">GDR</gloss> participation</hi> in <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>, as well as in <gloss target="#t_CES_1"
                        >CES</gloss>, will require further attention. <gloss target="#t_GDR_1"
                        >GDR</gloss> participation on the basis of full equality could have adverse
                    consequences for our position in the Berlin talks.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">IV. <hi rend="italic">Defense Issues</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The paper suggests in summary fashion that <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    force improvements will be reviewed at the meeting of the Defense Planning
                    Committee (<gloss target="#t_DPC_1">DPC</gloss>), especially:</p>
                <p>—progress in implementing the recommendations of the AD–70 study adopted last
                    December; and</p>
                <p>—progress of the European Defense Improvement Program (EDIP).</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Data on actual progress in these programs is not analyzed in
                        the study.</hi>)</p>
                <p>It is suggested that the <gloss target="#t_DPC_1">DPC</gloss> meeting will
                    provide an opportunity for the US to:</p>
                <p>—support the implementation of AD–70 and EDIP in close consultation among the
                    allies, with initial priority to West European aircraft shelter
                    construction;</p>
                <p>—urge that EDIP be considered only the first step toward even greater European
                    force improvement efforts;</p>
                <p>—reaffirm our intention to maintain and improve US forces in Europe, if the
                    Europeans do their share in improving their forces;</p>
                <p>—encourage improvements in Allied defenses in the Mediterranean.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
