<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.93/5–2550</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. <persName type="from">John Foster Dulles</persName>, Consultant to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-25">May 25, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                <cell>Mr. Hollington Tong<note n="1" xml:id="d179fn1">Member of the
                                        Central Advisory Committee of the Kuomintang and General
                                        Manager of the China Broadcasting Corporation.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>S—Mr. John Foster Dulles</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Mr. Tong said that he had left Formosa on April 26 and had come here via
                            Hong Kong, Paris and London. He expected to be going on to Tokyo and
                            back to Formosa the latter part of June. He asked what could be done to
                            improve relations between the Nationalist Government and the United
                            States and to insure more help in relation to the defense of Formosa. I
                            said to Mr. Tong that I did not think that this was a matter where there
                            was any possibility of any sort of a bargaining arrangement; that I had
                            in all frankness to say to him that there had been both in official
                            quarters and in American public opinion a very complete loss of
                            confidence in the will of the Nationalist forces to fight. The
                            impression prevailed that they had ample material strength to defend
                            Formosa if they would, but that there was grave doubt that they would.
                            Rumors were current that many of the leaders, including the
                            Generalissimo, were already making plans to get away from Formosa to
                            safety and past performance gave credibility to these rumors. I recalled
                            that when Mme. Chiang Kai-Shek was here during the war she had, in a
                            speech to Congress used the expression “God helps those who help
                            themselves”. I thought this was a very good time for the Nationalist
                            forces to take that to heart.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Tong asked whether I thought that if they should defend <pb facs="0358" n="344" xml:id="pg_344"/> Formosa for a certain period
                            of time that that would lead to a change of official and public opinion.
                            I said that I could not answer that question, but that I thought that
                            the spirit which prompted it was incorrect. The idea that by fighting
                            for a certain number of months they could then get a certain amount of
                            help was totally false. If they fought they would have to fight because
                            they had something that they really believed in and were willing to
                            sacrifice and die for. That was not something to be bargained about. I
                            referred to Churchill’s leadership in England in 1940 and to the
                            struggle of the revolutionists in Cuba. American public opinion had
                            become sympathetic because there was evidence of a cause of liberty in
                            which people believed and for which they were willing to die. If there
                            were evidence of that sort in relation to Formosa, it might or might not
                            affect the United States attitude. Certainly, however, the United
                            States’ attitude would not be altered if the only fighting that was done
                            was being done on a time basis for the purpose of winning U.S. support
                            and not because there was a cause of their own which attracted their
                            loyalty.</p>
                        <p>I said that it might very well be that there was no such cause; that
                            China had not developed the type of National and spiritual loyalties
                            such as prevailed in the Western countries. If that were the case, there
                            was nothing to be done about it.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Tong thanked me very much for the frankness with which I had
                            expressed myself.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>