<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="212" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d212">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.56/7–1850</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Special Assistant to the Secretary of Defense for
                                Foreign Military Affairs and Assistance</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Burns</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs</hi>
                                (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-18">July 18,
                                1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Rusk</hi>: Your letter of 21 June
                                1950<note n="1" xml:id="d212fn1">Not printed.</note> requests an
                            indication of the views of the Department of Defense regarding action to
                            be taken on the request of the Chinese Government to purchase 25 F–80(B)
                            jet fighters with its own funds and a further request to purchase F–51
                            aircraft understood to be surplus to United States requirements.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary of Defense has recommended to the Secretary of State that,
                            in order to increase the capacity and will of the Chinese Nationalist
                            Forces to fight, the Chinese Nationalist Government should be authorized
                            to make purchases, with its own funds, of any matériel under the control
                            of the United States, including tanks and jet aircraft, provided there
                            is no Service objection to these purchases. Delivery and shipment of
                            such purchases should be expedited by United States assistance.</p>
                        <p>If the Department of State concurs in the above recommendation, the
                            Department of Defense would have no objection, from an operational
                            standpoint, to the granting of an export license to the Chinese
                            Nationalist Government for the F–80(B) aircraft, or selling surplus U.S.
                            aircraft to them. However, production of the F–80(B) aircraft has been
                            discontinued, and it is expected that the entire productive capacity of
                            this plant will be occupied with orders for more modern types to meet
                            the requirements of the United States Air Force. The F–80(B)’s in the
                            current USAF inventory are similarly required.</p>
                        <p>A telephone conversation with Mr. McAfee of your office, on 14 July,
                            indicates that the Chinese requirement may be for F–84(<gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss>) aircraft instead of F–80(B). The situation
                            regarding F–84(<gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss>) or any other later model
                            would be the same as stated above.</p>
                        <p>The F–51 aircraft are no longer surplus to U.S. needs and, therefore, are
                            not available for sale to the Chinese Government at this time.</p>
                        <p>The overall requirements of the Chinese Nationalist Government for
                            military assistance are now under consideration within the Department of
                            Defense. In the event that this study reveals a priority need for jet
                            aircraft, the Department of Defense will consider the diversion of such
                            aircraft from our own stocks or from production.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>J. H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Burns</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>