<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in India ( (Henderson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d329</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">329</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-10-26T05:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-10-26T05:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-26T05:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-26T05:30:00-05:00" n="329"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793B.00/10–2650: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-26T16:00:00+05:30"
                            >October 26, 1950—4 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>996. <gloss target="#t_Totib1">Totib</gloss>. 1. ReDeptel 557, October 13,<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d329fn1">The text of this telegram read as follows: “Has Emb
                        any recent info re intended Tibetan approach to <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                            >GOI</gloss> for additional mil aid?” (793B.5/10–1350)</note> Calcutta
                    informed Embassy October 4 that Konchung Lobsang Tsewang and Rimshi L. T.
                    Surkhang of Tibet Trade Mission were arriving Delhi that afternoon and desired
                    advice from Embassy re military aid to Tibet. Consulate advised them contact
                    Embassy through Shakabpa.</p>
                <p>2. Members of trade delegation called upon me unannounced twelve days later
                    (October 16) and broached subject military aid. Since Embassy officer who has
                    handled matter throughout was absent an appointment was made for delegation call
                    again October 18, 11 a. m. At hour specified instead of delegation letter was
                    received cancelling appointment because “of urgent works” and expressing hope to
                    see me during their next visit here. Embassy had assumed from long delay in
                    opening discussion of military aid by Trade Mission that Tibetans were being
                    inhibited by course their discussions with Chinese or Government of India, or
                    being directly advised by them to refrain from contacting Embassy and we
                    therefore, considered it advisable to await developments rather than to take
                    initiative in matter. We also expected Shakabpa sooner or later would call and
                    bring us up to date or that favorable opportunity might open for sounding
                    Government of India officials. These expectations completely upset, however, by
                    yesterday’s departure (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 985, October
                    25) Shakabpa mission with nothing more than telephone advice from them.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d329fn2">
                        <p>The text of telegram 985 read as follows:</p>
                        <p>“Member Shakabpa mission telephoned Embassy yesterday to state mission
                            had received instructions from Lhasa to leave for Peiping immediately.
                            All members mission are flying Calcutta today and will spend few days
                            Calcutta and Kalimpong making preparations proceed Hong Kong by air.</p>
                        <p>“Press reports state no difficulties anticipated over Hong Kong entry
                            permits.” (693.93B/10–2550)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0555" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/>
                <p>3. Embassy officer therefore, called on Menon, Foreign Secretary, this morning
                    and in course of discussion latest developments Tibet raised subject military
                    aid and asked what had transpired while Tibetans were in New Delhi. Menon said
                    categorically Tibetan delegation had never raised question of additional
                    military aid with Government of India. Embassy officer doubted his word but was
                    in no position contradict. In any event Embassy impression from conversations
                    with Government of India and United Kingdom High Commission officials as well as
                    with Nepalese Ambassador is that Tibetans completely lost heart from attitude of
                    Government of India encountered in New Delhi and that this attitude was largely
                    responsible for fact that they failed pursue matter of military aid either with
                    Government of India or the United States. Nepalese Ambassador yesterday informed
                    us that Government of India seemed to be “washing its hands of Tibet” and said
                    that Shakabpa had informed him that position of Tibet was hopeless unless aid
                    could be obtained from Nepal or India. Nepalese Ambassador said that since India
                    was doing nothing Nepal was also helpless.</p>
                <p>4. Embassy can only assume in circumstances that question military aid for Tibet
                    is therefore dead, although Calcutta has been requested endeavor contact Tibetan
                    delegation there where they might feel freer talk about what happened in New
                    Delhi.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
