<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs
                    ( (Merchant) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d385</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">385</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-04-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-04-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-04-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-04-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="385"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d385">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">493.419/3–2450</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Far
                        Eastern Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Merchant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-04-20">April 20,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Policy Regarding Trade with Communist China</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>To determine the treatment to be accorded 1-B exports, particularly steel rails
                    and other transportation equipment, to Communist China under the terms of
                    existing <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> policy papers.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Background</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Attached for your signature is a draft letter (Tab A) to Secretary
                            Johnson<note n="1" xml:id="d385fn1">For the text of the letter as sent
                            by Mr. Acheson to Mr. Johnson on April 28 see <hi rend="italic"
                                >infra</hi>.</note> responsive to his letter to you of March 24,
                        1950 (Tab B).<note n="2" xml:id="d385fn2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_625">p. 625</ref>.</note>
                        Also attached for your signature is a letter to Secretary Sawyer (Tab
                            C)<note n="3" xml:id="d385fn3">See footnote 5 to the letter to Mr.
                            Johnson, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note> which would transmit for
                        his information your letter to Secretary Johnson.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The letter from Secretary Johnson recommends, in effect, that a previous
                        authorization for export of 15,000 tons of steel rails from western Germany
                        to Communist China be rescinded, that the, export from the United States to
                        Communist China of all railway transportation equipment be embargoed, that
                            <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> be informed of the United States
                        position in this regard and that strong pressure be brought to bear on
                        western European governments for parallel action in controlling exports of
                        ail strategic commodities to Communist areas of the Far East. These
                        recommendations reflect Defense views regarding policy towards China which
                        conflict, basically, with those of the Department and represent a challenge
                        to the principles contained in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 48/2
                        (“The Position of the United States with Respect to Asia”).</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 48/2. provides that “the United States
                        should permit exports to China of 1–B items within quantitative limits of
                        normal civilian use and under controls which can be applied restrictively if
                        it becomes necessary to do so in the national interest …” (Tab D).<note
                            n="4" xml:id="d385fn4">For the text of <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss> 48/2, see <ref target="frus1949v07p2#pg_1215">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, Part 2, p. 1215</ref>.</note> Despite
                        the President’s recent approval of this policy, the interpretation of this
                        sentence has become an important issue between State and Defense. Defense
                        has recently submitted to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff a
                        revision of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 41 (“United States Policy
                        regarding Trade with China”), on which the China trade aspects of <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 48/2 were based, designed to place an
                        embargo on the export to China of a considerable number of 1–B goods, and to
                        increase and subject to very tight restrictions those exports to China for
                        which licenses are required. These <pb facs="0643" n="629" xml:id="pg_629"/>
                        Defense proposals would in effect prevent the export to China of a large
                        number of goods that historically have moved in the China trade, and they
                        would appear to represent a policy towards China even more severe than is
                        now pursued towards the Soviet Union and its eastern European satellites.
                        Defense representatives maintain that their proposals are consistent with
                        the intent of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 48/2 by reference to the
                        “national interest” clause cited above.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item> The position taken by Defense representatives in the Interdepartmental
                        Advisory Committee structure responsible for actual export licensing
                        decisions has tended to subvert the intent of <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> 48/2. With a view to obtaining a flat embargo on the export
                        of steel rails and other transportation equipment to China, Acting Secretary
                        Early addressed a letter dated February 7, 1950 to Secretary Sawyer
                        recommending strongly that such goods be upgraded from the 1–B to the 1–A
                        list (Tab E).<note n="5" xml:id="d385fn5">Not printed.</note> Secretary
                        Sawyer replied on February 17 to this letter, indicating his willingness to
                        have the Advisory Committee structure review the strategic rating of
                        transportation items under control, but suggesting that the importance of
                        multilateral action to effective restriction probably would limit the extent
                        to which U.S. embargoes could be justified (Tab F).<note n="5"
                            xml:id="d385fn6">Not printed.</note> Secretary Sawyer’s response, while
                        entirely correct, does not dispose of the difficulties created by the basic
                        difference of view between State and Defense with respect to the China
                        problem.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>The general issue is most immediately related to the question of steel
                        rail exports from western Germany to China, our treatment of which thus far
                        has produced serious political repercussions in Germany. It is believed that
                        a clear decision on the question of steel rails, the principle of which
                        would apply to the treatment of transportation equipment generally as well
                        as other 1–B exports to China, would go far to correct misapprehensions
                        regarding the implementation of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> China
                        policy papers. The following analysis is therefore directed primarily to an
                        examination of the steel rail problem. </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The export of steel rails as a 1–B list item is governed by the provision
                        of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 48/2 which calls for licensing of
                        such exports to China in accordance with the normal civilian requirements of
                        that country. The Chinese economy has for decades made use of a few major
                        trunk railway lines for passenger and freight transportation. Inadequacy of
                        rail transport has been a major cause of China’s recurring famines. Military
                        campaigns in China, particularly those of the Chinese Communists, have not
                        been dependent primarily on rail transportation. It is unlikely, therefore,
                        that China’s imports of railway equipment to meet normal civilian
                        requirements would contribute appreciably to the Chinese Communist military
                        potential. China’s imports <pb facs="0644" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/> of
                        steel rails in the mid-thirties averaged approximately 80,000 tons, a
                        quantity sufficient to lay approximately 590 miles of track. In view of the
                        vast destruction of railways in China, annual exports to China of this
                        magnitude would not appear excessive.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>No effective multilateral agreement has as yet been obtained for
                        quantitative restrictions over exports of 1–B list items either to eastern
                        Europe or to China. Information is exchanged, however, with the U.K. and
                        certain other western European governments on 1–B exports to eastern Europe
                        and such an exchange is in prospect for 1–B exports to China. We intend in
                        the near future to renew our efforts for multilateral adoption of limitative
                        controls over 1–B exports (including steel rails) to eastern Europe and
                        would urge that such progress as is attained by these efforts be extended to
                        trade with China.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> has been advised by Defense and State
                        jointly of the principles deriving from <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        48/2 that should govern Japanese exports to Communist China and was
                        authorized to exercise his discretion in controlling 1–B list exports in
                        accordance with these principles. <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> was
                        informed that he would be expected to apply as a minimum such export
                        restrictions as were or might be adopted multilaterally. It was believed,
                        however, that <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> should not be expected
                        to place Japan at a competitive disadvantage by imposing restrictions on
                        exports for normal civilian use within Communist China more severe than are
                        applied by the U.K. and major western European governments.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese Communists have for several months been exploring in a number
                        of countries the possibility of placing an order for about 87,000 tons of
                        steel rails. We prevented Japan and Germany from accepting any such order
                        until <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 48/2 was approved by the President
                        on December 30, 1949. The general policy guidance referred to above (para 7)
                        was then sent to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>. With respect to
                        western Germany, we authorized acceptance of Chinese Communist orders for
                        steel rails but suggested that the quantity be limited to 15,000 tons for
                        the time being. Defense concurred in this action. However, the previous
                        denial and the current limitation of German steel rail exports, in the
                        absence of any parallel action by Germany’s competitors, has aroused
                        considerable resentment in Germany. High Commissioner McCloy has urged
                        strongly either that multilateral agreement on steel rail quotas for China
                        be obtained promptly or that western Germany be permitted to accept the
                        entire order if it can be placed there.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>We believe that an attempt to obtain multilateral restrictions on any 1–B
                        exports to China in advance of western European agreement to 1–A controls
                        for China would seriously prejudice the joint approach we are now making
                        with the British to this end. Moreover, it would clearly be unrealistic to
                        expect that European governments would control 1–B exports to China prior to
                        their institution of 1–B <pb facs="0645" n="631" xml:id="pg_631"/> controls
                        to eastern Europe. In the absence of multilateral quantitative limitations
                        on exports of steel rails to China, the continued imposition of quotas on
                        such exports from western Germany to China would not constitute an effective
                        restriction since the orders would undoubtedly be placed elsewhere. The net
                        effect of such action would be to add unnecessarily to the cost of U.S.
                        financial assistance to western Germany and to create increasingly adverse
                        political repercussions among the Germans. Unilaterally imposed quota
                        restrictions on German exports to China might lead to imposition of similar
                        restrictions on Japan for which the above observations would apply with
                        equal validity but with greater significance in view of the very great
                        importance to Japan of trade with China.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>It is believed that the Chinese Communists’ present extreme shortage of
                        foreign exchange constitutes an effective limitation on their import of high
                        cost capital goods. It is estimated, for example, that payment for the rail
                        order in question would require use of 10 to 15% of the present foreign
                        exchange resources of the Chinese Communists. Exchange of information by the
                        principal western suppliers on actual exports of steel rails and other 1–B
                        goods would reveal any movement of excessive quantities should it develop
                        and thus provide a clearer basis for vigorous efforts to obtain multilateral
                        restrictive action.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The export to China of all 1–B list goods, including steel rails and other
                        transportation equipment, should, in accordance with <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> 48/2 and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 41, be
                        permitted from the U.S., Japan and western Germany for normal civilian use
                        within China unless they are upgraded by the U.S. Government to the 1–A
                        list.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Continuing efforts should be made to obtain effective multilateral
                        agreement for limitative controls over the export of 1–B goods (including
                        steel rails) to eastern Europe, with the understanding that we would urge
                        that such agreement, if achieved, be extended to cover such 1–B exports to
                        China within the terms of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> China
                        policy.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>U.S. authorities in western Germany should be subject to the same policy
                        and procedural guidance regarding exports to China as is applied to <gloss
                            target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> for Japan. Thus, pending multilateral
                        agreement on 1-B controls for China, the U.S. High Commissioner for western
                        Germany should be permitted discretion in determining permissible exports of
                        steel rails and other 1–B goods for normal civilian use within China,
                        subject to such decisions by the U.S. Government as may be indicated in the
                        light of information exchanged among major western suppliers on actual
                        exports. The Department would, of course, provide such advice and
                        information as may be helpful to the High Commissioner, particularly in
                        determining China’s normal civilian requirements.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0646" n="632" xml:id="pg_632"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that, in accordance with your responsibility for coordination
                    of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 48/2 and <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 41, you sign the attached letter to Secretary Johnson, which
                    interprets these policies in the sense of the Conclusions above, and the
                    accompanying letter of transmittal to Secretary Sawyer.</p>
                <p>If the Department of Defense does not accept this interpretation, it would be
                    necessary, in accordance with <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> procedure, for
                    the issues to be considered by the Council and, if they cannot be resolved
                    there, for the matter to be submitted to the President for his decision.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Concurrences</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_RA1">RA</gloss>, <gloss
                        target="#t_GEA1">GEA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss>, <gloss
                        target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss> (Mr. Rusk), and
                        <gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss> (Mr. Webb) concur in this memorandum and the
                    draft letter to Secretary Johnson.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
