<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bruce) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d452</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">452</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-01-31T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-01-31T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-01-31T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-01-31T16:00:00-05:00" n="452"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d452">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.02/1–3150: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bruce</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-01-31T22:00:00+01:00"
                            >January 31, 1950—10 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>467. <gloss target="#t_mytel1">Mytel</gloss> 464.<note n="1" xml:id="d452fn1"
                        >Dated January 31, not printed.</note> Parodi<note n="2" xml:id="d452fn2"
                        >Alexandre Parodi, Secretary-General of the French Ministry of Foreign
                        Affairs.</note> has just handed British Ambassador<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d452fn3">Sir Oliver Harvey.</note> and me note to Soviet Government,
                    text of which follows in next telegram.<note n="4" xml:id="d452fn4">The Soviet
                        Union had recognized the Democratic Republic of Viet-Nam on January 30.
                        Telegram 468 from Paris, January 31, transmitting the French protest, is not
                        printed.</note> Parodi had requested that Soviet Ambassador visit him this
                    afternoon but met with answer that Bogomolov<note n="5" xml:id="d452fn5"
                        >Alexander Y. Bogomolov, Soviet Ambassador in France.</note> was not free.
                    Note accordingly has been sent to Soviet Embassy and will be released to press
                    tonight.</p>
                <p>Undoubtedly action of Soviet Government in recognizing Ho Chi minh and thereby
                    attacking integrity of French Union will induce violent reaction in France and
                    will make more definite and bitter the alignment of French non-Communist against
                    Communists.</p>
                <p>Recent debate in National Assembly upon ratification of March 8 accords in course
                    of which Communists even more blatantly than usual displayed their complete
                    subservience to Moscow and their avowed intention to betray French national
                    interests had considerable effect throughout country in demonstrating that they
                    constitute in effect an alien and seditious organism within this democracy. Also
                    their declared purpose to delay, frustrate and sabotage shipment not only of
                    arms to French soldiers in Indochina but of American military <pb facs="0719"
                        n="705" xml:id="pg_705"/> materials to France has met with vigorous response
                    from government which has pledged itself to allow no such interruptions or
                    incidents to occur.</p>
                <p>It was under conditions far less insulting than this that French tempers so
                    flared up in 1870 that Bismarck found it easy to provoke a war. No such reaction
                    is to be expected today, but this event will undoubtedly strengthen the will of
                    the people and their government here to resist and contain Communist
                    pressures.</p>
                <p>I think it important that our government should stigmatize in strongest terms
                    this act as breach of recognized principles of international relations, and as
                    conducive to creating conditions of disorder threatening to world peace that
                    Russians are always proclaiming with great thumping of breasts to be cardinal
                    objectives of their foreign policy.</p>
                <p>We may soon be faced with situation similar to that formerly prevailing in Greece
                    and even in Spain. The March 8 accords should be ratified by Council of Republic
                    on Friday of this week. Our recognition of Bao Dai and of Cambodia and Laos
                    should follow immediately thereafter. After that if any measure of military
                    and/or economic aid to Bao Dai is contemplated it would seem advisable that it
                    be announced at once and extended as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>It may well be that grave as are the worldwide implications of this Russian move,
                    one beneficial result may emerge, namely, a quickening of national pride in
                    France which will make a more cohensive and determined policy toward Russia and
                    Communism generally popular.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 467; repeated London 155. Department pass Moscow 28, Saigon
                    34.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bruce</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
