<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister at Saigon ( (Heath)) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d536</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">536</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-07-24T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-07-24T21:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-24T21:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-24T21:00:00-05:00" n="536"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d536">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851G.00R/7–2550: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister at Saigon</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d536fn1">Minister Donald R. Heath arrived at
                        Saigon on July 5.</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-25T10:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 25, 1950—10 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>100. 1. On occasions cited in <gloss target="#t_Legtel1">Legtel</gloss>s 52, July
                    15; 70, July 19; <gloss target="#t_Toeca1">Toeca</gloss> 140, July 21,<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d536fn2">None printed.</note> French have reminded us of
                    special role reserved for French under the March 8 and collateral agreements and
                    offered polite but unsolicited suggestions about course the mission should
                    pursue in contact with Viets.<note n="3" xml:id="d536fn3">Reference is to the
                        joint Mutual Defense Assistance Program survey mission to Southeast Asia
                        headed by John F. Melby, Special Assistant to Dean Rusk, Assistant Secretary
                        of State for Far Eastern Affairs, and Maj. Gen. Graves B. Erskine,
                        Commanding General of the First Marine Division. For the press release
                        announcing the dispatch of the mission, July 5, and other documentation on
                        its work and recommendations, see <ref target="#pg_1">pp. 1</ref> ff.</note>
                    They suggest changes in wording of my letters of credence to bring French Union
                    to fore (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 63, July 19);<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d536fn4">Not printed.</note> they urged on Blum inclusion of wording
                    in draft economic aid bilateral to stress Vietnam obligations as member of
                    French Union, and they have addressed to me the letter cited in <gloss
                        target="#t_Legtel1">Legtel</gloss> 70 which asks us to caution <gloss
                        target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> survey mission not to enter into any
                    commitments with Associated States’ representatives without consulting the
                    French interest. This letter was sent without prior discussion of the subject or
                    intimation to Legation that the High Commissariat considered such a caution
                    might be needed.</p>
                <p>2. I am confident that the French consider our attitude entirely correct. Our
                    relations continue to be, as they have always been, genuinely excellent and
                    marked by mutual respect. I report these matters merely for record and as
                    characteristic of a special French touchiness already familiar to the
                    Department. In view their delicate relations with Viets French are always afraid
                    that some uncoordinated activity of ours might upset the apple cart or prompt
                    the Viets to unrealistic plans and desertion of French-Vietnam understandings
                    (this fear was evident during the visit of the Griffin mission, the naval visit
                    and during the government crisis). Following Foreign Ministers’ conference
                    French attitude became less uneasy, the more so since no apple carts had been
                    upset by us in five months since our recognition of Bao Dai. I trust French
                    realize that this mission would lose much of its utility to US and to the
                    US-French entente if Viets were to consider it a tool of the High
                    Commissariat.</p>
                <pb facs="0852" n="838" xml:id="pg_838"/>
                <p>3. I believe that there are several reasons why French chose to dot the eyes for
                    us at this time: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>The Korean episode suggests necessity of tightening the ranks and
                            US-French cooperation.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Pignon is about to leave for extended stay in France and perhaps
                            thought it well to make position clear before his departure.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Similarly my arrival here as the first diplomatic envoy to Vietnam may
                            have seemed an opportunity to do the same thing.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Pignon recalls vividly the experience of the Griffin mission and the
                            intoxication produced among the Viets by their first negotiations with
                            outside powers. He has often said that if he had returned to Vietnam a
                            few days before the beginning of the meetings he could have averted Phan
                            Long’s defiance of the French on what was relatively an inconsequential
                            issue. He knows also that Viets and Bai Dai himself have tended recently
                            to call for revision of the provisions governing French and Vietnamese
                            relations in military matters. He may have feared they would make the
                            meeting with the military mission an occasion for pressing their
                            demands. He knew also that the meeting would be largely directed by Bao
                            Dai’s Minister for Armed Forces, Vinh, and that the Caodaists have
                            lately shown signs of disaffection toward Huu Government and with French
                            command.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>4. For these reasons Pignon took special pains to coordinate the meeting sent us
                    his letter and was in contact with Khac Ve, the acting president about agenda.
                    Whether as a result of his interest or not Viets asked little that French had
                    not already asked in their behalf (<gloss target="#t_Legtel1">Legtel</gloss> 84,
                    July 22),<note n="5" xml:id="d536fn5">Not printed.</note> stayed completely away
                    from controversial issues and never mentioned the “Bao Dai” or “Quat”
                        memoranda<note n="6" xml:id="d536fn6">The request for United States military
                        assistance submitted by Bao Dai is summarized in telegram 69 from Saigon,
                        January 31, <ref target="#pg_707">p. 707</ref>. The “Quat memorandum” refers
                        to a Vietnamese request for military aid presented to Colonel Duff, an
                        observer with the Griffin Mission. Chargé Gullion discussed the memorandum
                        with Vietnamese Defense Minister Phan Huy Quat on March 24. Quat indicated
                        that the list was largely based on the Bao Dai request with a few additions.
                        A summary of the list and the Legation’s comments on it were transmitted in
                        telegram 204 from Saigon, March 25, not printed. (751G.00/3–2550)</note>
                    which were the only official outline of arms needs which we had previously
                    received from them.</p>
                <p>5. In cordial conversation with Pignon recently I referred to his letter and
                    assured him that we were well aware of provisions of the March 8 and other
                    agreements which might affect distribution of US aid and that the military
                    mission was well briefed on these matters. My acknowledgement of his letter will
                    be limited to about that same statement. I believe Pignon appreciates our
                    position clearly.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 100; repeated information Paris 57.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
