<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="559" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d559">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/9–850</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Far
                                Eastern Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-09-08">September 8, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Foreign Ministers Meetings—Indochina, Summary
                            of Points Raised by Saigon and Paris concerning French Defense
                            Measures.</p>
                        <p>At the suggestion of Ambassador Jessup I am listing below a series of
                            specific points made in recent telegrams from Saigon, Hanoi and Paris in
                            the thought that you may wish to refer to them either separately with
                            Schuman or in one of the small closed meetings with both Bevin and
                            Schuman.</p>
                        <p>Both Paris and Saigon have emphasized the fact that there are two
                            questions of predominant importance now facing us concerning <pb facs="0891" n="877" xml:id="pg_877"/> Indochina. Without a decision
                            on them, a consideration of other lesser points is largely academic.
                            They are: (A) A decision as to whether the British and ourselves are
                            prepared to participate actively in the defense of Indochina in the
                            event of overt or covert Chinese invasion. If so, to what extent and
                            under what circumstances? (B) To what extent are we prepared to finance
                            the formation of National Armies in the Associated States? The
                            Vietnamese, French and we are agreed that this step comes closest within
                            present limits of practicability to meeting our objectives. Pleven has
                            mentioned a sum of 200 billion francs ($570 million odd) as the sum
                            required over a two-year period.</p>
                        <p>Other points are as follows: <list>
                                <label>1)</label>
                                <item>Advisability of replacing General Carpentier as Commanding
                                    General of French Union Forces in Indochina. Saigon and Hanoi
                                    both regard Carpentier as less qualified to carry out any plan
                                    for the formation of a Vietnamese National Army than General
                                    Alessandri, present CO., French Union Forces in North Vietnam.
                                        <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> Carpentier is generally opposed
                                    to the formation of a National Army and specifically opposed to
                                    arming a native militia on grounds that they cannot be trusted.
                                    Alessandri has a long Indochinese background and enjoys, with
                                    Pignon, the cooperation and respect of the Vietnamese to an
                                    extent not accorded to any other Frenchman.</item>
                                <label>2)</label>
                                <item>To apply all possible pressure on Bao Dai to return to
                                    Indochina immediately together with his family and thereafter to
                                    emerge from his oriental seclusion and assume a more active role
                                    as Chief of State. The maximum we might hope for from Bao Dai is
                                    that he be persuaded to take active field command of the
                                    Vietnamese National Army.</item>
                                <label>3)</label>
                                <item>Fully publicize the agreements concluded at the Pau
                                    Conference, primarily in Vietnam and the rest of Asia.<note n="1" xml:id="d559fn1">Regarding the conclusion of the Pau
                                        Conference, November 27, see footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_930">p. 930</ref>.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>4)</label>
                                <item>Urge the French to impress upon the Vietnamese Government the
                                    need for more effective tax collections. In this connection U.S.
                                    assistance through our present economic mission or otherwise is
                                    available.</item>
                                <label>5)</label>
                                <item>Urge that High Commissioner Pignon be authorized to release
                                    small arms in so far as available to the provincial governors
                                    for use in arming native militia and village chieftains in
                                    defense of the area recently liberated from the Viet Minh,
                                    particularly in the Red River Valley of Tonkin.</item>
                                <label>6)</label>
                                <item>Submit once more to the French the thought that the turning
                                    over of the High Commissioner’s palace at Saigon to Bao Dai
                                    might serve as a beneficial symbolic gesture.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The above points are supplemental to those emphasized in other documents
                            on Indochina prepared for the Foreign Ministers Meeting.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>