<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="634" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d634">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">756C.00/5–450</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Officer in
                                Charge of Indonesian and Pacific Island Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">O’Sullivan</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-04">May 4,
                                1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell>Mr. van Kleffens, Netherlands Ambassador</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>—Mr. Rusk</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>—Mr. Scott</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>UNP—Mr. Stein</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_PSA1">PSA</gloss>—Mr. O’Sullivan</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. van Kleffens called at his request this morning. He said it was with
                            great pleasure that he could deliver a note (Attachment A<note n="1" xml:id="d634fn1">No copy of the note was found attached to the
                                source text; however, a copy of note 2440, handed to Rusk on May 4
                                by the Ambassador, not printed, is certainly a copy of the note
                                under reference. It stated that for political, ethnic, cultural,
                                economic, and geographic reasons the Netherlands Cabinet believed
                                Western New Guinea should remain under Dutch authority.
                                (756C.00/5–450)</note>) setting forth, with regard to the future
                            status of Netherlands New Guinea, the position of his Government which
                            the Dutch Cabinet had decided upon and which he had received
                            instructions to draft and deliver. He then read the text of the note.
                            (Sent as telegram 403 to Djakarta, 92 to Canberra, 434 to The Hague,
                            2090 to London.<note n="2" xml:id="d634fn2">Not printed.</note>)</p>
                        <p>In reply to a question, Mr. van Kleffens stated that he often prepared an
                            answer to a letter before he received the inquiry. He then read what he
                            described as an informal memorandum (Attachment B<note n="3" xml:id="d634fn3">No copy of this memorandum was found attached to
                                the source text; however, a copy of a similar memorandum bearing the
                                handwritten notation “Handed Mr. Rusk by the Netherlands Ambassador
                                4 May 50,” not printed, stated that the disposition of Western New
                                Guinea was a matter for decision between the parties of the Round
                                Table Conference. (756C.00/5–450)</note>) setting forth the Dutch
                            reaction to the recent Australian note delivered to the Netherlands
                            Ambassador at Canberra on the future status of Netherlands New Guinea.
                            (Sent as telegram 91 to Canberra, 402 to Djakarta, 2091 to London, 433
                            to The Hague.<note n="2" xml:id="d634fn4">Not printed.</note>)</p>
                        <p>Mr. van Kleffens then requested that the <hi rend="italic">Aide-memoire</hi> be brought to the attention of the Secretary as
                            his Foreign Minister, Mr. Stikker, desired to discuss the future status
                            of Netherlands New Guinea with the Secretary at London.</p>
                        <p>In accepting the <hi rend="italic">Aide-mémoire</hi>, Mr. Rusk said that
                            he would be happy to see that it was brought to the attention of the
                            Secretary (the <hi rend="italic">Aide-mémoire</hi> was forwarded to the
                            Secretary under cover of a memorandum from Mr. Rusk to Mr. Battle).</p>
                        <p>In answer to a question, Mr. van Kleffens said that the Netherlands
                            Government did not envisage a continuation of its control in Netherlands
                            New Guinea in the form of a trusteeship. He said that his Government did
                            not like the manner in which the administering powers were treated in
                            the Trusteeship Council where, as he was sure <pb facs="1032" n="1018" xml:id="pg_1018"/> we knew, they are like “prisoners in the dock”.
                            Mr. van Kleffens admitted that the present Dutch position represents a
                            change from their position last Autumn. He said that at that time, the
                            Dutch Government had proposed a Netherlands Trusteeship for Netherlands
                            New Guinea in the hope that such an arrangement would be acceptable to
                            the Indonesians and would have liquidated the problem.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Rusk stated that there was some doubt in our minds regarding whether
                                <gloss target="#t_UNCIUNCFI1">UNCFI</gloss> is an appropriate organ
                            to act as “go between” in the question of the future status of
                            Netherlands New Guinea as the interests of some of its members were
                            involved. He emphasized that this was by no means a firm or final
                            departmental decision but is one of the factors that has entered into
                            our consideration of the problem.</p>
                        <p>In answer to a question, Mr. van Kleffens said that he did not know
                            whether the Australians had delivered a note setting forth their
                            position on the future status of Netherlands New Guinea to the
                            Indonesians. Mr. Rusk mentioned that while we were not sure, we thought
                            that the Australian note had in fact been delivered to <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss>. (Subsequently, Mr. Scott and Mr.
                            O’Sullivan phoned Mr. Helb, Counselor of the Netherlands Embassy, to
                            state that our information was to the effect that the note had been
                            delivered. Shortly after this conversation, Canberra’s telegram 139 of
                            May 4 was received,<note n="4" xml:id="d634fn5">Not printed.</note> and
                            Mr. Helb was then informed that our previous information was in error
                            and that the Australian note was not in Indonesian hands.)</p>
                        <p>Mr. van Kleffens dilated at some length during the conversation on the
                            fact that future status of Netherlands New Guinea was only one of many
                            factors affecting the relations between the Netherlands and Indonesia
                            and it was by no means the most important. He added that it was likewise
                            only one of many factors which would affect the stability of the regime
                            in Indonesia.</p>
                        <p>In reply to a question, Mr. van Kleffens said that while public opinion
                            in Netherlands New Guinea was not developed, the indications were,
                            particularly among the Christianized natives who, he said, formed an
                            appreciable portion of the population, that the inhabitants of
                            Netherlands New Guinea desired the continuation of Netherlands control.
                            He indicated that the Netherlands would not be adverse to a sounding of
                            public opinion on this matter, provided, of course, it would be run on
                            principles other than those used by the Indonesians to assess public
                            sentiment.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>