<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-18T05:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-18T05:30:00-05:00" n="637" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d637">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">856D.10/5–1850: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Indonesia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Cochran</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential   priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Djakarta</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-18T18:00:00+07:30">May 18,
                                    1950—6 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>662. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>s 375 and 446.<note n="1" xml:id="d637fn1">Neither printed.</note> Export Import Bank was
                            looked to for providing initial and important basic credit for
                            supporting <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss> in general economic
                            rehabilitation and currency stabilization. No international or other US
                            leading authority could be approached hopefully for this purpose first
                            few months new state. Granting 100 million dollar credit by ExIm upon
                            application Economy Minister Djuanda February came at most opportune
                            moment to strengthen confidence in country beset by military and
                            political troubles resulting importantly from Westerling affair. Same
                            credit created atmosphere of international support which permitted bold
                            monetary steps March 13 and 20. With US having taken lead, it became
                            practically obligatory Netherlands arrange credit 200 million florins to
                            Union partner following first conference Union ministers end Miarch.</p>
                        <p>President Sukarno and Prime Minister Hatta hoped for ExIm credit greater
                            than 100 million mentioning specifically 500. They have in mind
                            rehabilitation projects which they think warrant and necessitate
                            utilization foreign capital to this extent. Both realize however Export
                            Import Bank has responded generously and along sound business lines in
                            limiting initial credit to 100 million. They also appreciate necessity
                            providing ExIm with specific data in regard to contemplated projects for
                            which credit is to be utilized and have gone through difficult process
                            assembling data shortly after taking over unfamiliar offices from
                            Netherlands Government in circumstances of chaos and bankruptcy and
                            without ample indoctrination or even satisfactory cooperation. Best
                            experts available inexperienced government have gone Washington to seek
                            action on projects submitted. Geniunely hoped American capital goods may
                            shortly flow Indonesia under this credit. Critics US policy and of
                            friendship Hatta government for US endeavoring argue ExIm arrangement
                            was only on paper and that political and other difficulties that have
                            confronted <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss> have frightened off
                            Export Import Bank.</p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss> has now weathered worst months.
                            Monetary measures proving their merits. Exports beginning move in
                            gratifying measure with such commodities as rubber having benefit
                            exceptionally favorable prices. Imports not yet coming in normally since
                            prices many thereof trebled by monetary act and holders of imported
                            stocks refraining <pb facs="1038" n="1024" xml:id="pg_1024"/> from
                            buying more until liquidate present holdings at greatest profit
                            possible. Furthermore, still some speculation that further currency
                            changes possible and also worry over internal political conditions.
                            Believe next few weeks will witness clarification problems of unitary
                            state as well as <gloss target="#t_KNIL1">KNIL</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>At my insistence <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> credit for <gloss target="#t_NEI1">NEI</gloss> which was suspended second police
                            action December 1948 not revived until after successful termination
                                <gloss target="#t_RTC1">RTC</gloss> agreement. Consequently final
                            $40 million from <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> available to
                            provide textiles and rice during first few months new <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss> state. Otherwise great distress and
                            possibility financial ruin would have been experienced. Has now become
                            necessary place orders Japan for cheap cotton textiles to continue
                            inward flow as <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> imports end.</p>
                        <p>As Department knows textiles greatest single import for average
                            Indonesian consumer. Serves not only to satisfy essential needs but also
                            incentive to production commodities constituting most important exports.
                            With uncertain and troubled conditions existing first few months <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss> and with export returns disappointing
                            until just recently, it has been impossible government anticipate hard
                            currency receipts from exports and program imports accordingly. Most
                            reasonable calculations, however, showed needs from $22.5 to perhaps $60
                            million for cotton and cotton textiles that could hot likely be met from
                            exports.</p>
                        <p>I took initiative recommending US credit to relieve this situation and
                            still urgently request minimum 22.5 be provided soonest. I feel this is
                            bankable commodity credit that can be repaid after three or four years.
                            I have opposed special legislation or large new grants to <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss>. Should US fail give such help
                            shortly leftist element will allege US aid to <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss> illusory and attack Hatta government on ground
                            favoring US policies without receiving credits required to keep
                            workingman in necessities. This market prefers Japan and US textiles to
                            higher priced products from Netherlands, France and Belgium. Textile
                            credits from Europe have already been offered but Economy Ministry
                            desires keep trade lines with US and purchase more reasonably than now
                            possible in Europe. Believe Indonesia market fits well into US plans for
                            marketing it own cotton and for supporting Japanese economy.</p>
                        <p>Even if exports continue grow at rate anticipated by Economy Minister he
                            still sees need for textile credit of size above mentioned. He has
                            mentioned alternative selling <gloss target="#t_RUSI1">RUSI</gloss> gold
                            if US credit cannot be obtained. I strongly oppose this lest it wreck
                            degree stability now being achieved with such difficulty in Indonesian
                            currency. Both Hatta and Djuanda have abhorred idea drawing on ExIm 100
                            million credit for textiles. They prefer conserve this precious credit
                            for economic rehabilitation projects which they could not otherwise
                            finance <pb facs="1039" n="1025" xml:id="pg_1025"/> and which should
                            mean so much to relieving unemployment and achieving satisfactory
                            standard of life of a country that has suffered from ten years strife.
                            They feel if any part of ExIm credit used for textiles then pressure on
                            Government would be increased for utilizing other portions for other
                            consumer goods. Policy of Hatta government is to tighten belt and get
                            along on what would be to most countries spartan economy. To purchase
                            textiles is however absolutely essential and funds cannot be assured for
                            meeting requirements unless US credit is extended.</p>
                        <p>Djuanda insisted to me again this morning ExIm credit must be reserved
                            for capital projects if at all possible. Said exports first 15 days May
                            totalled 112 million florins against 111 million for month January. Said
                            these figures should not lead to false sense favorable position since
                            part recent exports have come from hoarded stocks and uncertain what
                            rate of exports will be when dependent upon current production. Will not
                            be able predict year’s imports safely until about July 1. Entirely
                            certain require minimum 22.5 million credit for cotton.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cochran</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>