<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-26T03:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-26T03:30:00-05:00" n="676" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d676">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">123 Cochran, H. Merle: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Indonesia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Cochran</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Djakarta</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-26T16:00:00+07:30">October
                                    26, 1950—4 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>574. Made farewell call on President Sukarno 10:30 October 26. Told him I
                            would be called upon to explain various matters upon visit to Department
                            including (1) Indonesian policy of neutrality, (2) failure to negotiate
                            with Melby mission in spite Indonesian need for equipment and military
                            training, (3) Ambon question, (4) prosecution of murderers of American
                            citizens.</p>
                        <pb facs="1105" n="1091" xml:id="pg_1091"/>
                        <p>With respect to (1) Sukarno used expression as he has on some previous
                            occasions that I should know Indonesian Government’s neutrality is one
                            of form while their sentiment is on our side.</p>
                        <p>President reiterated need for military aid but hoped we could provide
                            assistance and training behind a screen which would not provoke
                            Communist antagonism and allegations that Indonesia’s policy of
                            neutrality is sham.</p>
                        <p>Sukarno told me he planned visit President Quirino in Philippines during
                            December accompanied by Roem. He said he knew this would arouse much
                            criticism on part Mao Tse Tung and other Communists but he desired have
                            closer relations with Philippine Government and would do so in spite of
                            criticism.</p>
                        <p>With respect to Ambon, President thought <gloss target="#t_UNCIUNCFI1">UNCI</gloss> resolution had been mistake and that Lamping had been
                            unhelpful in his handling of situation. Said his government must be
                            strong enough to put down insurrectionists and achieve law and order. He
                            thought clean-cut victory in Parliament yesterday should give government
                            courage to carry out necessary measures for improvement situation.</p>
                        <p>President said Chinese Communists becoming quite aggressive in Indonesia.
                            Reports reached him that important sums of gold were being brought in
                            from China to finance widespread propaganda and related activities.
                            President said he hoped in <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> efforts
                            we would stress positively American institutions and way of life and not
                            resort to such publications as one his Minister of Information had
                            recently brought to his attention, “the Communists come to China”. He
                            said his government is itself taking steps to prohibit entrance Chinese
                            propaganda films and literature and prefers no international propaganda
                            struggle take place Indonesia. President said Indonesian intelligence
                            system weak. I agreed, mentioning need for improvement and pointed out
                            unpunished murderers of American citizens. See <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 573 re Doyle-Kennedy
                                murders.<note n="1" xml:id="d676fn1">Not printed; it reported that
                                Ambassador Cochran had received further evidence of the complicity
                                of <gloss target="#t_TNI1">TNI</gloss> officers in the murders of
                                Raymond Kennedy and Robert Doyle, American correspondents, on April
                                27 (256D.113 Kennedy, Raymond/10–2650).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>I expressed appreciation Sukarno’s message to UN on fifth anniversary. He
                            said anxious to work with UN and hoped Roem might be able attend General
                            Assembly, but did not want him to go US if disagreeable debate on Ambon
                            in progress in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. Further-more, stressed
                            importance having Roem in Djakarta these days to help with many
                            emergencies.</p>
                        <p>President stressed importance of solution <gloss target="#t_NNG1">NNG</gloss> question in favor Indonesia and have [<hi rend="italic">gave?</hi>] arguments with which Department is familiar.</p>
                        <pb facs="1106" n="1092" xml:id="pg_1092"/>
                        <p>President favored <gloss target="#t_STEM1">STEM</gloss> program being
                            carried out by small group technicians. Opposed <gloss target="#t_UNO1">UNO</gloss> idea of CCC for forestry work, but sought their aid in
                            transmigration projects.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cochran</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>