<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-01-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="687" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d687">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">694.001/1–1050</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Large</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Jessup</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">personal</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-01-10">January 10, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Dean</hi>: This is a brief personal note to
                            you to mention the most interesting point which has come up in the
                            course of the three conversations I have had with General MacArthur. I
                            have sent full memoranda of the conversations personally to Walt
                                Butterworth.<note n="1" xml:id="d687fn1">Mr. Jessup enclosed
                                memoranda of his conversations held with General MacArthur January
                                5, 8, and 10 with his letter of January 10 to Mr. Butterworth.
                                (694.001/1–1050) None printed, except the memorandum, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sebald and I spent about two hours with the General Sunday evening and
                            discussed on a purely informal and personal basis some of the general
                            problems of the Far East and particularly the question of the
                            negotiation of the Japanese Peace Treaty. We both prefaced and <pb facs="1129" n="1115" xml:id="pg_1115"/> added to our remarks by
                            Stressing the fact that on neither side were we speaking officially but
                            purely on the basis of a personal exchange of views. General MacArthur
                            is quite outraged by the views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff in regard to
                            the postponement of arrangements for negotiating the Japanese Peace
                            Treaty. He spoke very strongly on this subject and feels that the view
                            does not really reflect a military judgment but that General Bradley is
                            merely speaking for Secretary Johnson. Again with appropriate caveats
                            about his desire to avoid intruding or giving any implication of
                            attempting to dictate or influence policy decisions, he said that he
                            hoped that you would take the matter up with the President and have the
                            Joint Chiefs overruled. As you know, he feels very strongly that we
                            should go ahead with the negotiation of the Treaty. I fully agree with
                            him. In this connection, he stressed a point which the Consultants also
                            had in mind; namely, that the negotiation of the Peace Treaty would be
                            one of the dramatic steps by which we could recapture from the Russians
                            the initiative in terms of general Asiatic thinking. The General noted
                            in this connection that the Joint Chiefs had been overruled on Formosa
                            and he saw no reason why they should not be overruled on this question
                            of the Peace Treaty. Of course on the Formosan issue he agreed with the
                            Joint Chiefs.</p>
                        <p>On several different occasions, he stressed the excellent cooperation
                            which he had received from the State Department and indicated that his
                            difficulties had been due almost entirely to the Department of Defense.
                            I think I am quite aware of the problems existing along this line in
                            Washington, but I wonder whether on a matter so important as the
                            negotiation of the Japanese Peace Treaty it would not be possible for
                            the President to take the matter into his own hands and request General
                            MacArthur to report directly to him his views on this question. In terms
                            of American thinking, <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>’s support on
                            this would be of great importance and it would seem too bad if it were
                            necessary to have his views remain secret. Naturally, it is of prime
                            importance that what the General said to me in confidence should not
                            leak out, but I hope you will consider whether without disclosing the
                            General’s comments some way could be found to solicit an open expression
                            of his views. I would stress again that I would venture to suggest such
                            a procedure only in a matter of very great importance. I think the
                            negotiation of the Peace Treaty is such a matter.<note n="2" xml:id="d687fn2">
                                <p>In a memorandum of February 10 to William J. McWilliams, Director
                                    of the Executive Secretariat, Lucius D. Battle, Special
                                    Assistant to the Secretary, stated: “I have been holding the
                                    attached letter from Ambassador Jessup for some time. When the
                                    Secretary read it, he told me he saw no reason for circulating
                                    this to anyone. I assume that he felt it did not even require a
                                    reply.</p>
                                <p>“If you think it advisable, we might discuss the subject with one
                                    or two people who are working on the Japanese peace treaty. It
                                    would not even necessarily have to be phrased as a suggestion
                                    from Mr. Jessup. At any rate, the Secretary wanted this played
                                    very close.” (694.001/1–1050) No additional documentation
                                    regarding Mr. Jessup’s proposal has been found in State
                                    Department files.</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="1130" n="1116" xml:id="pg_1116"/>
                        <p>The trip so far is really very satisfactory, and I hope it will prove as
                            a whole to be worthwhile.</p>
                        <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Philip</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Jessup</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>