<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Northeast Asian Affairs (
                    (Allison) ) to the Consultant to the Secretary ( (Dulles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d709</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">709</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-04-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaty negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-04-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="709"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d709">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">694.001/4–2650</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Northeast Asian
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Allison</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Consultant to the Secretary</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dulles</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-04-26">April 26,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Background paper on Japan.</p>
                <p>There is attached the first of several background papers on various aspects of
                    United States policy toward Japan which this office has in preparation. It is
                    believed that this particular paper will be of special interest to you in
                    connection with your consideration of matters affecting a possible Japanese
                    peace treaty.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Japan’s Participation in International
                            Relationships</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> Policy</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>, in the Basic Post-Surrender Policy
                        for Japan, June 19, 1947, agreed: “To help the people of Japan in their own
                        interest as well as that of the world at large to find means whereby they
                        may develop within the framework of a democratic society an intercourse
                        among themselves and with other countries along economic and cultural lines
                        that will enable them to satisfy their reasonable individual and national
                        needs and bring them into permanently peaceful relationship with all
                        nations.” The Commission also agreed in this policy decision that one of the
                        ultimate objectives in relation to Japan, to which policies for the
                        post-surrender period for Japan should conform, was: “To bring about the
                        earliest possible establishment of a democratic and peaceful government
                        which will carry out its international responsibilities, respect the rights
                        of other states and support the objectives of the United Nations.”<note
                            n="1" xml:id="d709fn1">Full text, released to the press July 11, 1947,
                            is printed in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                            August 3, 1947, p. 216.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">U.S. Policy</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The U.S. Government has taken the position that <gloss target="#t_SCAP1"
                            >SCAP</gloss>, as the sole executive authority for the Allied Powers in
                        Japan and in accordance with the principles set forth in the Basic
                        Post-Surrender Policy for Japan, has legal authority, as well as the
                        obligation, to permit Japan to participate in international relationships.
                        On a broad policy basis <pb facs="1197" n="1183" xml:id="pg_1183"/> it was
                        believed when the position was developed in the spring of 1949, that the
                        situation in Japan required more than emphasis on internal reform and
                        economic stabilization; that through participation in international
                        relationships the Japanese would acquire direct experience and knowledge of
                        democratic institutions abroad; and that such participation would go far to
                        restore to the Japanese a measure of self-confidence and a renewed sense of
                        responsibility.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Development of This Policy</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>A number of the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> member governments
                        objected to this position and took the view that pending the signing of a
                        peace treaty with Japan, the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>, and not
                            <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, was the authority to regulate
                        Japan’s participation in international relationships. On April 21, 1949, the
                        U.S.—without prejudice to its basic position that <gloss target="#t_SCAP1"
                            >SCAP</gloss> already has the authority to permit Japan to participate
                        in international relationships, but with a view to obtaining the leadership
                        of the other member governments of the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>
                        in encouraging such participation by Japan—introduced a proposal to the
                            <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> which provided that “<gloss
                            target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, subject to his discretion and continued
                        control, should permit Japan to participate with other nations or groups of
                        nations in such international relations, conventions, meetings, consular
                        arrangements or other bilateral or multilateral accords as Japan may be
                        invited to enter into, accede to, attend or participate in and as <gloss
                            target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> shall consider to be in the interests of
                        the occupation.”<note n="2" xml:id="d709fn2">For remainder of text, see <ref
                                target="frus1949v07p2#pg_713">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, Part 2, p. 713</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In the course of the discussions on this subject in the <gloss
                            target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d709fn3">Summaries of <gloss target="#t_FEC1"
                                >FEC</gloss> meetings held during 1950 are in file 690.00 <gloss
                                target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>.</note> this proposal was broken down
                        into two parts. One provided that <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>,
                        subject to his discretion and continued control, should permit Japan to
                        participate with other nations or groups of nations in such international
                        agreements, conventions and conferences of a technical character as Japan
                        may be invited to enter into, accede to, or attend and as the Supreme
                        Commander shall consider to be in the interests of the occupation. The other
                        provided that the Japanese Government may, with the approval of <gloss
                            target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, appoint agents in any country willing to
                        receive them for the purpose of facilitating Japanese trade and/or handling
                        matters affecting the civil status or property rights of Japanese nationals.
                        The latter proposal was approved by a majority of the members of the <gloss
                            target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> on January 12, 1950, but was defeated by
                        virtue of Soviet non-concurrence. The Department, in accordance with its
                        basic position that <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> may authorize
                        Japan to participate in international relationships, then issued an
                            invitation<note n="4" xml:id="d709fn4">Not printed; a copy forms
                            enclosure 1 to despatch No. 263 from Tokyo, February 25, 1950.
                            (794.00/2–2550)</note> through <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> to
                        the Japanese Government to set up five overseas agencies in the U.S. and
                        Hawaii for performing trade promotion and certain consular-type activities.
                        The U.S. invitation was accepted by the Japanese <pb facs="1198" n="1184"
                            xml:id="pg_1184"/> Government on February 14. Except for Communist
                        protests, reactions in Japan and the U.S. to this development were uniformly
                        favorable. The Department and <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> are now
                        encouraging other countries (primarily Brazil, Argentina, India, Pakistan
                        and Thailand) to follow the example of the U.S. Government in inviting the
                        establishment of Japanese agencies in those countries.</p>
                    <p>The paper dealing with Japanese Participation in Technical Agreements and
                        Conferences had been forwarded from the Steering Committee to the Commission
                        by a majority vote. However, it soon became evident that due to the walkout
                        of the Soviet representative from the Commission on January 29, 1950, the
                        Commission would not be able to act favorably on the paper for some time
                        because of the position of several governments that the <gloss
                            target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> could not take action on substantive
                        matters in the absence of the Soviet representative. The U.S. therefore, in
                        accordance with the Terms of Reference of the <gloss target="#t_FEC1"
                            >FEC</gloss>, issued an interim directive to <gloss target="#t_SCAP1"
                            >SCAP</gloss>, dated February 21, 1950, on Japanese Participation in
                        Technical Agreements and Conferences<note n="5" xml:id="d709fn5">For the
                            Department’s press release of February 25, which includes full text of
                            the directive, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                            March 13, 1950, p. 414.</note> based on the substance of the paper
                        before the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>. In view of the fact that the
                        question of Japanese participation in technical agreements and conferences
                        is a constantly recurring one, the U.S. Government was also motivated by the
                        desire to establish some official sanction within the Terms of Reference of
                        the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> so that other governments might find
                        it easier to support such participation by Japan. The issuance of the
                        interim directive was approved by the French, Canadian, Pakistan and Burmese
                        representatives in the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss>. The British and
                        Australian representatives reserved the position of their governments on
                        this matter.</p>
                    <p>It is important to note that the majority of the <gloss target="#t_FEC1"
                            >FEC</gloss> support for both policy papers (technical conferences and
                        overseas agencies) was obtained as a result of considerable U.S. diplomatic
                        spadework.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">commentary</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Treaty negotiations, even if successful, may well involve many, many months.
                        Since Japan has faithfully complied with its surrender obligations, the
                        continuation of excessive restraints on Japan appears to have little
                        justification either morally or from the point of view of political wisdom.
                        One of the most effective ways to help offset already discernible Japanese
                        resentment against the protracted occupation—which necessarily must continue
                        for some time longer—would be along the lines of restoring to Japan greater
                        international personality: that is better facilities for international
                        trade, Japanese handling of consular-type affairs, Japanese adherence to
                        international conventions, and Japan’s participation in international
                        conferences and conventions. Aside from the obvious technical advantages of
                        such <pb facs="1199" n="1185" xml:id="pg_1185"/> arrangements, they would
                        permit the growing national awareness of the Japanese people to find
                        expression in the dignity and prestige that go with international
                        responsibilities rather than to engender hostility toward the U.S.
                        occupation and its objectives.</p>
                    <p>India, Pakistan and Burma have been generally sympathetic to the policy, but
                        other countries, including the United Kingdom and Australia, have tended to
                        interpret U.S. moves to bring occupied Japan back into the world community
                        as part of a substitution program for a peace treaty. These latter countries
                        have contended that a resumption by Japan of international functions and
                        responsibilities in advance of a general peace settlement could only be
                        justified if it could be clearly demonstrated that a peace settlement is
                        impracticable.</p>
                    <p>The further success of U.S. measures to bring occupied Japan back into the
                        world community, therefore, hinges largely on the treaty question. Either a
                        treaty will restore to Japan normal international relations or general
                        agreement among the powers that a treaty is impracticable will do so. The
                        present situation, in which no decision has been reached on either course,
                        is almost certain to block any further appreciable broadening of the scope
                        of Japan’s international relations.</p>
                    <p>It would be a grave error in judgment to suppose that because the occupation
                        in Japan is making apparent good headway and because the Japanese are
                        well-disposed toward the United States that this situation will necessarily
                        continue. Japanese willingness to cooperate with the occupation and the
                        friendly disposition of Japan toward the U.S. will continue only under
                        occupation policies which evolve with sufficient rapidity to accommodate
                        themselves to Japanese attitudes and circumstances. The participation of
                        Japan in international relations is an important way in which we can
                        maintain U.S. initiative in Japan, keeping one step ahead of the
                        developments there. But the further implementation of this policy is going
                        to be difficult, perhaps impossible, without an early definitive decision on
                        the peace treaty. As far as the participation of occupied Japan in
                        international relations is concerned, we appear to have reached the point of
                        diminishing returns.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
