<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Basis for Discussion by the Secretary of State With the Foreign Ministers of
                    the United Kingdom and Possibly France Concerning a Peace Treaty With
                    Japan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d712</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">712</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recdDEAik5EmT8luP" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-american-states"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007400"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Coast Guard</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="712"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d712">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Tab B]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Basis for Discussion by the Secretary of State With the
                        Foreign Ministers of the United Kingdom and Possibly France</hi>
                    <note n="*" xml:id="d712fn1">Defense representatives believe discussion of this
                        subject with the French should be limited to a minimum and the Department of
                        State staff concurs. [Footnote in source text.]</note>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Concerning a Peace Treaty With Japan</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-05">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">May</hi> 5, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Current basic policy on timing and procedure with respect to a peace treaty with
                    Japan is contained in paragraph 1 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 13/3:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“1. <hi rend="italic">Timing and Procedure</hi>. In view of the
                            differences which have developed among the interested countries
                            regarding the procedure and substance of a Japanese peace treaty and in
                            view of the serious international situation created by the Soviet
                            Union’s policy of aggressive Communist expansion, this Government should
                            not press for a treaty of peace at this time. It should remain prepared
                            to proceed with the negotiations, under some generally acceptable voting
                            procedure, if the Allied Powers can agree among themselves on such a
                            procedure. We should, before actually entering into a peace conference,
                            seek through the diplomatic channel the concurrence of a majority of the
                            participating countries in the principal points of content we desire to
                            have in such a treaty. Meanwhile, we should concentrate our attention on
                            the preparation of the Japanese for the eventual removal of the regime
                            of control.”<note n="†" xml:id="d712fn2">Defense representatives believe
                                this paragraph has been overtaken by events, but State Department
                                view is that it continues to be the policy approved by the
                                Praesident and has not been changed by him. [Footnote in source
                                text.]</note>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Pending a reassessment of U.S. policy toward Japan upon the return of the
                    Secretary of Defense from his visit to Tokyo in June, the United States should
                    not assent to the calling of a peace conference.</p>
                <p>An early<note n="‡" xml:id="d712fn3">Defense representatives would like to delete
                        the word “early”. [Footnote in Source text.]</note> peace treaty with Japan
                    is politically desirable but must not, because of its terms or because of the
                    circumstances under which it is concluded, endanger the security of the United
                    States, its friendly Allies, or Japan.</p>
                <p>A peace treaty, if one is to be concluded, should restore Japan to a sovereign
                    status with a minimum of restrictions and special disabilities in such matters
                    as trade, industry, and civil government. It should be of such a character as to
                    appeal to the Japanese and thus continue the process of drawing Japan into
                    friendly relations with the non-Communist nations.</p>
                <p>The treaty should not authorize, nor should it prohibit, the rearmament of Japan.
                    It should, however, permit the maintenance of adequately equipped and manned
                    police force and coast guard to maintain internal security in Japan.</p>
                <pb facs="1204" n="1190" xml:id="pg_1190"/>
                <p>No<note n="§" xml:id="d712fn4">Defense representatives suggest this read “a
                        minimum of post-treaty control machinery” etc. [Footnote in source
                        text.]</note> post-treaty control machinery should be established to
                    supervise the execution of the treaty.</p>
                <p>The United States and its friendly Allies must continue to be secured against the
                    possible resurgence of Japanese aggression and Japan must continue to be secured
                    against possible Soviet-Communist aggression.</p>
                <p>The United States and its friendly Allies might, provided that there is a
                    sufficient measure of agreement among them, have to proceed without the USSR and
                    Communist China.<note n="║" xml:id="d712fn5">Defense representatives propose in
                        lieu of this paragraph: “The United States and its friendly Allies should
                        not proceed with a peace treaty without the USSR and Communist China, but
                        this question should again be considered later this year.” The President
                        reviewed the history of the war against Japan and stated that the United
                        States position in Japan was a partnership affair with Britain and China
                        only, and that the United States, Britain and China could negotiate a peace
                        treaty with Japan whether the Soviet Union participated or not. You will
                        recall the President made this statement at an <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> meeting on Dec. 29, 1949. [Footnote in source text; see Mr.
                        Rusk’s memorandum of January 24, <ref target="#pg_1131">page
                        1131</ref>.]</note>
                </p>
                <p>There are two types of security arrangements which are receiving primary
                    consideration at the moment within the United States Government. This
                    Government, however, has not determined that either would provide an acceptable
                    settlement. Any final determination would depend in part on the willingness of
                    the Japanese to grant bases.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Alternative Security Arrangement I</hi>—Concurrently with the
                    conclusion of a treaty of peace, a collective security arrangement consistent
                    with the United Nations Charter would be concluded with Japan. The membership
                    might include, initially, in addition to Japan, those participating <gloss
                        target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> powers which would be interested in joining.
                    The parties other than Japan would undertake to come to the assistance of any
                    party which was the victim of an act of aggression committed by Japan. All the
                    parties would undertake to assist in defending Japan in the event that an act of
                    aggression were committed against Japan from any source. In connection with this
                    latter undertaking, Japan would make available to the United States such bases
                    in Japan as might be required for the purpose of securing Japan’s defense
                    against aggression.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Alternative Security Arrangement II</hi>—An agreement would be
                    entered into with Japan which would restore to Japan full sovereignty in matters
                    relating to its internal government and to the conduct of its political and
                    economic affairs with other nations. On the ground that they security objectives
                    of the Potsdam Proclamation have not yet been achieved, the treaty would leave
                    unchanged the existing legal authority furnished by Allied wartime agreements
                    and the Instrument of Surrender for the occupation regime of control (including
                        <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, <pb facs="1205" n="1191"
                        xml:id="pg_1191"/> the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> and occupation
                    forces in Japan), although this authority would be closely restricted to matters
                    of security and would not be exercised in the subject matters covered by the
                    treaty except in case of a grave emergency.<note n="¶" xml:id="d712fn6">Defense
                        representatives do not wish to restrict the exercise of this authority to
                        matters of security but wish to leave the way open to exercise it in all
                        matters covered by the treaty which assume a character of the utmost
                        importance and urgency. [Footnote in source text.]</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
