<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="730" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d730">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">694.001/7–1150</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Northeast
                                Asian Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Allison</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Consultant to
                                the Secretary</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Dulles</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d730fn1">Addressed
                                also to Messrs. Rusk, Hamilton, Howard, and Fearey.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-11">July 11, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The attached draft security clauses for a Japanese peace treaty are based
                            on a previous draft prepared by Mr. Howard and a discussion among
                            Messrs. Dulles, Howard and Allison this morning. The language <pb facs="1256" n="1242" xml:id="pg_1242"/> in Article V is a paraphrase
                            of language used by General MacArthur in his supplementary memorandum of
                            June 23.</p>
                        <p>The paper will be discussed at the 4:30 meeting in Mr. Dulles’ office
                            this afternoon.<note n="2" xml:id="d730fn2">No minute of this meeting
                                has been found in State Department files.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">ohn</hi>] M. A[<hi rend="smallcaps">llison</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Outline of Major Security Clauses</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-11">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">July</hi> 11, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Draft</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">article i</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Japan undertakes to apply for admission to the United Nations, which
                                application will be supported by the other Parties.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">article ii</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Pending admission to the United Nations Japan undertakes to act in
                                accordance with the principles of Article 2 of the Charter of the
                                United Nations for the maintenance of international peace and
                                security and the other parties undertake to assure to Japan the
                                corresponding benefits and protections of those principles.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">article iii</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In view of the possibility of a delay in Japan’s admission to the
                                United Nations and also in view of the fact that the Security
                                Council is not yet in a position to exercise its responsibilities
                                under Article 42 of the Charter, in order to carry out the
                                obligations of Article II above and in the interest of maintaining
                                international peace and security, Japan on its part will provide
                                such facilities and the United States will provide such forces on
                                behalf of the other treaty powers as may be determined by the United
                                States after consultation with the Japanese Government.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">article iv</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>At such time as the arrangements referred in Article 43 of the
                                Charter come into effect the arrangements in Article III above will
                                be merged with the arrangements under Article 43 of the Charter.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">article v</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Japan shall retain its national sovereignty over the facilities
                                furnished in accordance with Article III and the forces furnished by
                                the United States shall not have, except in time of hostilities or
                                imminently <pb facs="1257" n="1243" xml:id="pg_1243"/> threatened
                                hostilities, any responsibility or authority to intervene in the
                                internal affairs of Japan.<note n="3" xml:id="d730fn3">
                                    <p>In a draft of July 14 this language is rewritten as follows:
                                        “Japan shall retain its national sovereignity over the
                                        facilities furnished in accordance with Article III and the
                                        forces furnished by the United States shall not have any
                                        responsibility or authority to intervene in the internal
                                        affairs of Japan. In time of hostilities or imminently
                                        threatened hostilities, however, the United States forces
                                        shall have authority under the terms of an agreement to be
                                        concluded with Japan to enlist the cooperation and
                                        assistance of the Japanese Government and people for the
                                        defense of Japan.” (694.001/7–1450)</p>
                                    <p>In the course of a memorandum of July 17 to Mr. Allison, Mr.
                                        Fearey commented as follows on the language just quoted: “In
                                        order to avoid a conflict between the concept of ‘authority’
                                        and the concept of ‘cooperation’ in the second sentence as I
                                        previously suggested it, I would propose the following:</p>
                                    <p>“‘In time of hostilities or imminently threatened
                                        hostilities, however, the Japanese Government and people
                                        shall afford the United States forces cooperation and
                                        assistance in accordance with the terms of an agreement to
                                        be concluded between the Government of the United States and
                                        the Government of Japan.’”(794.5/7–1750)</p>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">article vi</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>During the period this agreement is in effect Japan will not grant
                                military facilities to another power except in accordance with
                                Article III.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">article vii</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Until another arrangement is made, the United States will bear all
                                expenses incurred in the maintenance of the armed forces referred to
                                in Article III and Japan will bear all expenses incurred in the
                                maintenance of the facilities referred to in Article III.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>