<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of Northeast Asian Affairs (
                    (Johnson) ) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (
                    (Rusk))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d777</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">777</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="777"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d777">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">794.5/10–3150</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of Northeast
                        Asian Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far
                        Eastern Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-31">October 31,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Financing of Increased Troop Strength in Japan</p>
                <p>There is quoted below the full text of an item appearing in Tokyo’s Weekly
                    Economic Notes of October 13<note n="1" xml:id="d777fn1">Not printed.</note> on
                    the above subject. If the opportunity arises, I recommend that we strongly
                    support, at least, <pb facs="1357" n="1343" xml:id="pg_1343"/> partial
                    “pay-as-you-go” for the support of our troops in Japan pending the conclusion of
                    a peace treaty.</p>
                <p rend="center">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Plan To Finance Augmented Troop Strength in
                        Japan as Occupation Cost</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At recent meetings of top military leaders in Tokyo it has been tentatively
                    agreed that, when the withdrawal of U.S. troops from Korea occurs, a sufficient
                    number should be stationed in Japan so as to provide the complement of troops
                    long called for but not made available; the number would exceed the former
                    totals in Japan by some fifty percent. The important question of local financing
                    for the additional logistic support required has also been discussed. It was
                    decided that to provide separately on a dollar pay-as-you-go basis for the
                    additional troops, supporting only about the original numbers through the
                    currently used Termination of War Account supported by the Japanese Government,
                    would be impracticable. It was accordingly determined that all troops should be
                    provided for through termination of war accounting, as a cost of the occupation.
                    It is reliably estimated that the annual cost to the Japanese Government for
                    support of occupation troops has averaged ¥80–90 billion annually and that the
                    augmentation of troops under the new plan would require an additional ¥30–40
                    billion annually, making support of occupation troops the largest expenditure in
                    the national budget. Some officials of Economic and Scientific Section (ESS),
                    General Headquarters (<gloss target="#t_GHQ1">GHQ</gloss>), <gloss
                        target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>, attending the meetings, have stated that
                    this added budget expenditure would not only be a strain on Japanese Government
                    finance, but, from a number of considerations, would at this time seem
                    politically most unwise. Assuming the augmentation of forces in Japan to be a
                    policy and military matter outside their proper jurisdiction, they have
                    suggested that a simpler financial scheme far more acceptable to certain
                    Occupation agencies and to the U.S. Government would include the elimination of
                        <gloss target="#t_GARIOA1">GARIOA</gloss> funds for Japan and, as an offset,
                    placement of all Occupation costs on a pay-as-you-go basis, thereby simplifying
                    accounting procedures and providing an approach far more palatable to the
                    Japanese. It is believed that the Japanese Government would welcome this type of
                    approach and, has, in fact, studied the problem of aid from the United States in
                    the post treaty period in relation to dollar gains to be made from residence of
                    U.S. troops in bases in Japan. Some Japanese officials tentatively estimate that
                    exchange receipts from U.S. Government military outlays in the post treaty
                    period may approximate 70 million dollars. The Mission considers the plan to
                    augment forces in Japan at this time a many-faceted problem deserving, extremely
                    careful scrutiny prior to implementation. It is possible that opposition to
                    these proposals will be expressed in some military quarters of <gloss
                        target="#t_GHQ1">GHQ</gloss> as they reluctantly accept the inevitability of
                    an early peace treaty with Japan.”<note n="2" xml:id="d777fn2">For further
                        pertinent documentation, see the paper cited in the editorial note under
                        date of October 15.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The foregoing information from Tokyo was transmitted for Department use only and
                    accordingly we must protect Tokyo in making any use thereof with other agencies
                    of the Government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
