<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Secretary of Defense ( (Marshall))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d790</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">790</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="790"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d790">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">694.001/12–1350</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Marshall</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-13">December 13,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: There is enclosed for your comment
                    a memorandum setting forth the ideas of the Department of State on steps which
                    should be taken with regard to Japan in view of the urgency of that
                    situation.</p>
                <p>In general the policies outlined in the attached memorandum are merely a further
                    implementation of the policy approved by the President and contained in the
                    joint memorandum of September 7, 1950, <pb facs="1378" n="1364" xml:id="pg_1364"
                    /> signed by former Secretary Johnson and myself. However, there are four
                    specific departures or additions upon which it is desired to receive the opinion
                    of the Department of Defense. From the military point of view, are there any
                    objections to: (1) seeking an early conclusion of a peace settlement with Japan
                    without awaiting a favorable outcome of the situation in Korea? (2) discussing
                    this peace settlement with assumption that the United States intends to commit
                    substantial armed force to the defense of the island chain of which Japan forms
                    part? (3) leaving the Ryukyu and Bonin Islands under Japanese sovereignty,
                    subject to the provisions of the contemplated military security agreement which
                    would presumably take special account of the position in Okinawa? (4)
                    exploration at this time of a possible Pacific Pact along the lines outlined in
                    paragraph 4 of the attached memorandum?</p>
                <p>Subject to receiving the views of the Department of Defense, the Department of
                    State contemplates recommending to the President that Mr. John Foster Dulles be
                    appointed to head a Presidential Mission to Japan which would be, expected to
                    depart in the very near future and to which mission we consider that a
                    representative of the Department of Defense should be attached.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d790fn1">In his letter of December 20 to General MacArthur, Mr.
                        Dulles, after mentioning his planned trip to Japan, reviewed the substance
                        of proposals (2) and (4) above, and stated his hope to have “… some fairly
                        definite understanding at the Presidential level …” regarding them before
                        his departure. In connection with the proposed Pacific Pact, he stated in
                        part: “This would provide a framework within which a Japanese force, if
                        developed, could have an international status rather than a purely national
                        status and this might ease reconciliation with the present Japanese
                        Constitution.” (694.001/12–2850)</note> The enclosed memorandum would form
                    the general terms of reference of the Mission. The Mission itself would have no
                    authority to make any commitments on behalf of the United States.</p>
                <p>Should you consider it helpful, Mr. Dulles is available to discuss the enclosed
                    memorandum with you, the Joint Chiefs of Staff, or anyone you may wish to
                    designate and he would welcome the opportunity to do so.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Japan</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-13">December 13,
                                1950</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Recent developments in Asia, and particularly in Korea, indicate that the
                        Soviet Union, the Chinese Communist regime and the North Korean regime are
                        moving to dominate Asia; that they are prepared in this respect to use force
                        and to risk general war, and that they have at least on the mainland,
                        capabilities which the United Nations cannot <pb facs="1379" n="1365"
                            xml:id="pg_1365"/> match. It is probable that a principal objective is
                        Japan, the industrial and human resources of which nation have for many
                        years been dominant in Asia, and which, if added to the resources now
                        possessed by the Soviet Union would greatly alter the balance of power in
                        the world to the disadvantage of the United States and its allies. Under
                        these circumstances, the task of preventing Japan from falling under
                        Communist influence is increasingly great, and it must be anticipated that
                        there will be a reluctance on the part of Japan to commit itself to be part
                        of the free world unless it can be assured that, from a military and
                        economic standpoint, Japan can, through her own efforts and in combination
                        with those of the United States, defend herself militarily and survive
                        economically. To meet this situation, the following program is recommended: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item> A basic strategic decision on the part of the United States to
                                commit substantial sea and air power to the defense of the island
                                chain of which Japan forms part. It will probably be necessary, at
                                some stage of the proceedings, to indicate to the Japanese with some
                                precision our military intentions in this respect.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>Subversive activities against the Communists on the mainland may
                                be an essential ingredient in any extended defense of the islands
                                against mainland attack. But this phase of the matter would not call
                                for discussion with, or participation by, the Japanese. </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>A basic economic decision on the part of the United States to
                                assure the economic survival of Japan without dependence upon
                                Communist mainland areas. This would require access by Japan to food
                                and raw materials and the foreign exchange Wherewith to pay for
                                them. To this end the United States should be prepared, if
                                necessary, to put our military garrisons in Japan on a
                                “pay-as-you-go” basis and, presumably, substantial orders for
                                military equipment would be placed in Japan under <gloss
                                    target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>. This again might have to be
                                developed with some precision in the course of negotiations.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Assuming that the foregoing decisions are in the affirmative, then
                                there should at once be sent to Japan a Presidential mission with
                                authority to explore and ascertain, in cooperation with General
                                MacArthur, the terms upon which Japan could be brought into the
                                orbit of the free world. The mission should have authority to
                                discuss and develop <hi rend="italic">ad referendum</hi>
                                arrangements with Japan which would include the following features: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>The quick restoration of peace to Japan either through a
                                        simplified peace treaty which would cover the points
                                        indicated in Annex A or a restoration of peace through joint
                                        action of the Congress and Diet, coupled with an exchange of
                                        notes and declarations of intention on the part of the
                                        Japanese which would cover most of the points dealt with in
                                        Annex A. Action taken in this respect should as far as
                                        possible be coordinated with similar action of friendly
                                        allies in the Japanese war.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>A bilateral agreement between the United States and
                                        Japanese Governments, dealing with the garrisoning of United
                                        States forces in and about Japan, including the Ryukyus and
                                            <pb facs="1380" n="1366" xml:id="pg_1366"/> Bonin
                                        Islands. The terms of this agreement would be along the
                                        lines of the draft agreement already discussed between the
                                        State and Defense Departments subject to such modifications
                                        acceptable to the United States Government as may be
                                        necessary to secure Japanese agreement. The possibility
                                        should be explored of making this agreement more acceptable
                                        to the Japanese and friendly Governments by bringing it
                                        within the purview of the United Nations Charter and of such
                                        United Nations machinery as envisioned in the Uniting for
                                        Peace Resolution.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item> A willingness on the part of the United States to make a mutual
                                assistance arrangement among the Pacific island nations (Australia,
                                New Zealand, the Philippines, Japan and the United States, and
                                perhaps Indonesia) which would have the dual purpose of assuring
                                combined action as between the members to resist aggression from
                                without and also to resist attack by one of the members, e.g. Japan,
                                if Japan should again become aggressive.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>In order to expedite progress toward agreement among the above
                                nations and to obtain the earliest and greatest psychological
                                advantage, such a mutual assistance arrangement might be
                                accomplished in two stages. The first would consist of a meeting of
                                the foreign ministers of the countries concerned, to take place as
                                soon as possible, at which a declaration of intent to make peace
                                with Japan and to consult regarding mutual security interests would
                                be issued. The second would consist of a more formal arrangement, to
                                be announced simultaneously with the conclusion of peace with Japan,
                                and to which Japan would be a party. The United States should agree
                                to the above courses of action only on the express acceptance by the
                                other nations concerned of the essential features of the Japanese
                                treaty as outlined in Annex A. </item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>If, and as soon as, the foregoing steps are approved, there should
                                be confidential discussions to inform the representatives in
                                Washington of friendly members of the <gloss target="#t_FEC1"
                                    >FEC</gloss> and similar discussions with members of the Foreign
                                Relations and Foreign Affairs Committees.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>From the standpoint of public relations, the departure of the
                                mission to Japan should not be considered as anything abnormal or
                                spectacular, but merely the normal development which was foreseen
                                following the President’s statement of September, 1950. It was then
                                taken for granted that following the exchange of views on Japanese
                                Peace Treaty which have taken place at the United Nations, the
                                negotiating representatives of our Government would go to Japan. Any
                                public announcement should stress that the principal purpose of the
                                mission would be to consult with General MacArthur and, through him,
                                informally with Japanese leaders, but that formal negotiations with
                                the Japanese Government are not contemplated. Therefore, a trip to
                                Japan at this time would not of itself be evidence of any new
                                decisions or any panicky mood.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Annex A</head>
                    <p>The United States proposes a treaty with Japan which would end the state of
                        war, restore Japanese sovereignty and bring back Japan <pb facs="1381"
                            n="1367" xml:id="pg_1367"/> as an equal in the society of free peoples.
                        As regards specific matters, the treaty would reflect the principles
                        indicated below: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Parties</hi>. Any or all nations at war with Japan
                                which are willing to make peace on the basis proposed and as may be
                                agreed.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">United Nations</hi>. Membership by Japan would be
                                contemplated.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Territory</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                                Independence of Korea would be recognized; (<hi rend="italic"
                                >b</hi>) the Ryukyus and Bonin Islands would be returned to Japan
                                provided that the provisions of any military security agreement
                                apply to these territories in the same manner as to Japan proper;
                                    (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>
                                status of Formosa would be recognized pending the development of
                                such conditions of peace and stability in the area as make possible
                                a <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> settlement.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Security</hi>. The Treaty would contemplate that,
                                pending satisfactory alternative security arrangements such as U.S.
                                assumption of effective responsibility, there would be continuing
                                cooperative responsibility between Japanese facilities and U.S. and
                                perhaps other forces for the maintenance of international peace and
                                security in the Japan area, and that Japan’s participation would be
                                exclusively of a character which would permit her to exercise the
                                inherent right of individual and collective self-defense (see U.N.
                                Charter, Art. 51). (This might be contained in a separate Treaty or
                                agreement not necessarily signed by all the Treaty Powers.)</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>[Here follow numbered paragraphs 5, 6, and 7, identical to those in the
                        seven-point memorandum of September 11.]</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
