<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum from the Secretary of State to the President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d802</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">802</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recDNr3fFoY74D9ro" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064651"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Import control</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="802"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d802">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">796.11/2–250</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum from the <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                            State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d802fn1">This memorandum, which was drafted by John F.
                        Melby, was transmitted to the Secretary of State on January 31 by Deputy
                        Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs Livingston T. Merchant
                        with the recommendation that it be signed by the Secretary of State and sent
                        to the President.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-02-02">February 2,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Topics which may be discussed by President Quirino
                    during his visit to the United States for medical attention.</p>
                <p>President Quirino comes to the United States at a time in his development when it
                    will be difficult to persuade him to that action which the United States
                    believes may reverse the current trend of economic and financial deterioration.
                    There is doubt that he yet understands fully the difficult dilemma in which his
                    country finds itself. He is also surrounded by advisers who, for the most part,
                    are little more understanding than he is. Furthermore, he has just won a
                    presidential election which, despite known corruption and instances of
                    dishonesty, has filled him with confidence that he has the internal Philippine
                    situation well under control. His not unnatural pride in his accomplishment of
                    having risen to the Presidency from humble origins sometimes obscures in his
                    mind the heavy responsibilities with which he is charged. Typical of his
                    political mistakes have been his ill-considered meeting last summer with Chiang
                        Kai-shek<note n="2" xml:id="d802fn2">For documentation on the meeting under
                        reference between Philippine President Quirino and Generalissimo Chiang
                        Kai-shek, President of the Republic of China, held at Baguio in the
                        Philippines in July 1949, see <ref target="frus1949v07p2#pg_1115">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, Part 2, pp. 1115</ref> ff.</note> largely
                    for internal political reasons, his manipulation of the Presidential election,
                    his excessive concern with his own political position, attempts to persuade the
                    Philippine electorate that the United States supported his election campaign,
                    and, more recently, his suggestion that the United States bribe him into not
                    appointing the Japanese collaborator Senator Madrigal, as ambassador to the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>To these discouraging factors must be added the quite natural Philippine
                    sensitivity over its recently acquired sovereignty. Typical of this reaction
                    which Ambassador Cowen has characterized as “morbid psychology” is the reaction
                    to my recent statement at the National Press Club in which I expressed the
                    regret of this Government that the Philippines had failed to make the best use
                    of its available resources.<note n="3" xml:id="d802fn3">Regarding the speech
                        under reference here and the Philippine reference thereto, see telegram 195,
                        January 17, from Manila, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> This statement
                    was interpreted in high quarters, including President Quirino himself, as a
                    charge of dishonesty and corruption which, of course, was the last thing which I
                    or anyone else in the Department intended.</p>
                <p>It is necessary to give due account to this natural sensitivity unless we are to
                    have a stubborn and resentful impasse with the Philippines <pb facs="1418"
                        n="1404" xml:id="pg_1404"/> in our attempts to persuade them to reform. On
                    the other hand, I am convinced that the time has come to explain to President
                    Quirino that Philippine performance must precede consideration of any additional
                    American aid if the current trend of deterioration is to be arrested and the
                    Philippines placed on a sound and self-supporting basis. This will mean, I
                    believe, that he must be talked to in simple, firm, and forth-right but tactful
                    terms. The specific problems outlined below and the recommendations thereon will
                    explain in more detail the foregoing generalities.</p>
                <p>In a recent telegram Ambassador Cowen has expressed his serious concern of the
                    consequences which might arise if President Quirino should receive any specific
                    assurances of American aid which he could take back with him.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d802fn4">See telegram 75, January 8, from Manila, <ref
                            target="#pg_1399">p. 1399</ref>.</note> Under instructions from the
                    Department the Ambassador has been using his influence to persuade the
                    Philippine Government to attempt those reform measures which must come first if
                    any further possible American aid is to be utilized effectively. These efforts
                    have so far been only moderately successful, but progress is being made. The
                    Ambassador fears if President Quirino finds he can come to Washington and secure
                    what he wants without fulfilling certain precedent conditions then the influence
                    of the Embassy in Manila will be to a large extent nullified. This is a
                    classical Philippine maneuver, playing off one part of the American Government
                    against another part, which President Quezon in particular used with marked
                    success. The Department fully agrees that President Quirino should not gain any
                    impression that he can bypass the Ambassador in Manila to suit his own purposes,
                    and it is recommended that if he makes any proposals which might be acceptable
                    to the United States Government he should be informed that he should first
                    discuss them with Ambassador Cowen.</p>
                <p>President Quirino will undoubtedly wish to discuss a number of military,
                    political and economic questions which are of concern to the Philippines and the
                    United States. These problems and the suggested replies are as follows:</p>
                <p rend="center">A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Military</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Defense of the Philippines</hi>. With the spread of
                    Communism in Asia, President Quirino has on several occasions expressed to
                    Ambassador Cowen his concern over the future security of the Philippines. In the
                    course of such conversations he has requested an expression of what the United
                    States might do in the event of an attack on his country.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that you reply with the substance of a letter of September 16,
                    1949 from the Secretary of National Defense to the <pb facs="1419" n="1405"
                        xml:id="pg_1405"/> Secretary of State, appropriate paragraphs of which are
                    attached as tab (1).<note n="5" xml:id="d802fn5">See <ref target="#pg_1410">p.
                            1410</ref>.</note> Reference might also be made to my recent statement
                    to the National Press Club that the United States would not countenance any
                    external attack on the Philippines.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Guerrilla Recognition</hi>. There is some evidence that
                    President Quirino may attempt to reopen the question of guerrilla recognition
                    for his own political purposes. You will recall that he discussed the question
                    during his visit to Washington last summer and that he was informed the question
                    was a closed one.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that you inform President Quirino the United States still
                    considers the issue a closed one and perceives nothing to be gained by
                    discussing it further.</p>
                <p rend="center">B. <hi rend="smallcaps">Political</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">A New Philippine Ambassador to the United States</hi>.
                    During recent weeks there has been speculation that President Quirino would
                    appoint Senator Vicente Madrigal as the next Ambassador to the United States.
                    Senator Madrigal has a record as a collaborator, not only with the Japanese
                    during the last war, but also with Germany during the first war. He has also
                    been deeply involved in financial corruption. Because of his record, his
                    appointment as Ambassador would be a source of embarrassment to the United
                    States Government, and in time, to the Philippine Government also. Ambassador
                    Cowen has discussed this question with President Quirino who at first gave an
                    appearance of irresoluteness and then asked the Ambassador not to report the
                    matter to his Government. President Quirino then brought up the question of the
                    very large claim Senator Madrigal has with the War Damage Commission<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d802fn6">The Philippine War Damage Commission was created by the
                        Philippine Rehabilitation Act of April 30, 1946, to make compensation for
                        physical loss or destruction of or damage to certain kinds of property,
                        public and private, in the Philippines occurring after December 7, 1941, and
                        before October 1, 1945, as a result of World War II.</note> which has been
                    held up pending investigation of the collaboration charges, and finally made the
                    offer that if the Ambassador would guarantee payment of this claim then he,
                    President Quirino, would not appoint Madrigal as Ambassador. Ambassador Cowen of
                    course, replied that this Government does not make this kind of deal.<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d802fn7">President Quirino’s conversation with Ambassador Cowen on
                        January 6 described here was reported upon in telegram 73, January 7, from
                        Manila, not printed (601.9611/1–750).</note> It is possible, however, that
                    President Quirino may attempt to secure your concurrence for this appointment in
                    order to discharge his political obligations to Madrigal.</p>
                <pb facs="1420" n="1406" xml:id="pg_1406"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that if President Quirino raises the question of Senator
                    Madrigal you point out to him the serious embarrassment which Senator Madrigal
                    would be to our two countries and if he persists in his request, that you inform
                    him the United States would regretfully be compelled to refuse an agreement.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Pacific Association</hi>. Last summer, as the result of an
                    ill-considered meeting with General Chiang Kai-shek, President Quirino, partly
                    for his own internal political purposes, proposed some kind of Pacific
                    association as a means of defense against the spread of Communism. Because of
                    the connection with Chiang Kai-shek and because of the diversity of interests
                    among the Southeast Asian nations, the response in Asia was only lukewarm.
                    Attempts to secure public American approval for the proposal have elicited from
                    this Government the statement that although the United States would look with
                    favor upon the principle of such an association, based on the independence,
                    integrity, and welfare of the peoples concerned, the United States will reserve
                    judgment on the specific development of the proposal until it has had an
                    opportunity to observe its specific application. President Quirino may attempt
                    to secure American assistance to get him out of the uncomfortable position in
                    which he finds himself in being publicly committed to a proposal which lacks
                    general enthusiastic appeal. There is attached as tab (2) a memorandum dealing
                    in greater detail with this subject.<note n="8" xml:id="d802fn8">“Tab 2” of the
                        source text, not included here, was a copy of Assistant Secretary of State
                        Butterworth’s memorandum of January 16 to the Secretary of State, <ref
                            target="#pg_1">p. 1</ref>. For additional documentation regarding the
                        attitude of the United States toward regional security arrangements in the
                        Southeast Asian area, also see <ref target="#pg_1">pp. 1</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>If President Quirino raises the question of a Pacific association it is
                    recommended that you say the United States looks with favor on the principle of
                    a Southeast Asian regional association but that to be effective it must be a
                    spontaneous movement dedicated to the independence, integrity, and welfare of
                    the participants, and that until there is evidence that these conditions have
                    been fulfilled the United States can express no opinion any specific
                    implementation of the principle.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Recognition of the Vietnam Government under Bao
                        Dai</hi>.<note n="9" xml:id="d802fn9">For documentation on the question of
                        the recognition of the Viet-Nam Government of Bao Dai, see <ref
                            target="#pg_690">pp. 690</ref> ff.</note> The Government of the United
                    States plans to extend recognition to the new states of Vietnam, Laos, and
                    Cambodia. The French Assembly <pb facs="1421" n="1407" xml:id="pg_1407"/> has
                    now ratified the Agreement already in effect between those states and France.
                    Similar acts of recognition by other Southeast Asian states would be most
                    helpful in assisting the new states to establish and maintain their independence
                    and stability. It is recognized that the degree of independence being
                    transferred to the Vietnam Government under Bao Dai is somewhat less than the
                    independence granted to the Philippines by the United States. This somewhat
                    lesser degree of independence has been granted because Vietnam for sometime will
                    require assistance from France, and because the peoples of Indochina are not as
                    advanced as the Philippine people and can only hope to approach the Philippine
                    level of absolute self-government after more experience. Furthermore, there is a
                    present Communist threat in Indochina which has been reenforced by the recent
                    debacle in China. As the most stable nation in Southeast Asia, Philippine
                    recognition of the three new states would be a concrete confirmation of the
                    anti-Communist stand already so effectively taken by the Philippine
                    Government.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that you seek an opportunity to discuss the foregoing with
                    President Quirino and urge on him the desirability that the Philippines
                    recognize Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia.</p>
                <p rend="center">C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Economic</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The principal problems confronting the Philippines today are economic and
                    financial. These problems arise largely from Philippine ineptitude and
                    wastefulness. Since its liberation in 1945, the Philippines has benefited by
                    U.S. Government aid and expenditures of over $1,500,000,000, including transfers
                    of civilian aid goods, military equipment and surplus property valued at over
                    $300 million, and cash expenditures of over $1,200,000,000, including war damage
                    payments, veterans pay and benefits, wage payments, credits and tax refunds.
                    Effectively utilized these resources could have made a significant contribution
                    to increasing the capital investment in the country and restoring the economy to
                    a more prosperous condition.</p>
                <p>The Joint Philippine-American Finance Commission report of 1947 blocked out a
                    broad program to achieve this purpose. Sound fiscal and financial policies,
                    however, have been ignored. Much of the Philippine financial resources have been
                    squandered on unnecessary luxury imports. Imports and transfers of capital out
                    of the Philippines have consistently exceeded exports and American aid by a
                    large margin, and insufficient progress has been made in increasing export crops
                    or in making the Philippines self-sufficient in its rice supply. As a result,
                        <pb facs="1422" n="1408" xml:id="pg_1408"/> dollar reserves during 1949
                    dropped by 40 percent from $400 million to $230 million. To stop the drain the
                    Philippines drastically reenforeed the inadequate import control regulations
                    which had been in effect since January 1948. Shortly thereafter exchange control
                    was imposed with your consent. Although it is premature to express an opinion on
                    the effectiveness of the regulations now in force, the previous record gives
                    little reason for encouragement that a further loss of foreign exchange can be
                    arrested by these measures.</p>
                <p>To make matters worse there is a serious budgetary deficit and every indication
                    that it will increase. The tax laws are inadequate, badly enforced, and revenues
                    are the object of a disturbing amount of graft and corruption of which President
                    Quirino must be aware. Perhaps the most serious aspect of this problem is the
                    seeming lack of understanding by responsible Philippine officials as to their
                    predicament and the unwillingness to take the necessary drastic measures to
                    remedy it. Back of this attitude is the firm Philippine conviction that they
                    need not worry because if worse come to worst they can always count on the
                    United States to bail them out when the borrowed time of American governmental
                    expenditures runs out. President Quirino must somehow be persuaded that this is
                    not necessarily so and that American aid can be effective only if it is preceded
                    by drastic reforms undertaken by the Philippines itself. It is probable that
                    President Quirino can be persuaded of this only by very firm and plain speaking,
                    and even then he may understand it only when the situation has become decidedly
                    worse than it is now. Having failed to secure what he wants through Ambassador
                    Cowen in Manila, he will undoubtedly attempt to secure some kind of commitment
                    from you, … For example, President Quirino has refused several requests of
                    Ambassador Cowen and our Commanding General in Manila for the repayment now past
                    due of some 70 million pesos left over from a fund set up to meet back pay
                    claims of Filipino troops, and has indicated that he wishes to discuss this
                    matter with you. He is also attempting to have this claim offset against certain
                    extraneous Philippine claims whose validity the United States cannot admit.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that when President Quirino raises the question of American
                    aid, the substance of the foregoing be conveyed to him in no uncertain terms,
                    and that emphasis be laid on the fact that no further American aid could be
                    considered unless and until there is tangible evidence that the Philippines has
                    taken steps to put its house in order and that it would then need and be in a
                    position effectively <pb facs="1423" n="1409" xml:id="pg_1409"/> to use
                    additional aid. It is further recommended, in discussing any requests for aid
                    that: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>A United States Economic Survey Mission composed of top level American
                            experts as outlined in the attached tab (3)<note n="10"
                                xml:id="d802fn10">“Tab 3” was a memorandum of January 26 from Deputy
                                Assistant Secretary of State Merchant to the Secretary of State, not
                                printed, it recommended that President Truman be advised of the
                                Department of State’s view that no further American grant assistance
                                to the Philippines was warranted until the Philippine Government
                                itself took steps to improve its domestic finances and foreign
                                exchange position and until a more definitive analysis could be made
                                of the means whereby American aid could be effectively utilized in
                                helping stabilize the Philippine economy. The memorandum recommended
                                that President Truman inform President Quirino that United States
                                consideration of the problem of further aid to the Philippines was
                                hampered by some doubt as to the exact requirements and the extent
                                to which proper corrective measures could and should be taken by the
                                Philippine Government. It was suggested in the memorandum that
                                President Truman might intimate that Quirino should consult with
                                Ambassador Cowen on the question and that, if the latter concurred,
                                the United States would send a topflight mission to survey the
                                Philippine economic situation. It was envisaged that the
                                recommendations of this mission would be for self-help measures
                                which the Philippine Government could undertake itself, but any
                                acceptable recommendations for American action would be given
                                careful consideration. Merchant’s memorandum concluded by expressing
                                the hope that such a mission would consider the possibility of
                                recommending the establishment of a continuing joint United
                                States-Philippine commission which might exercise final control over
                                any developmental funds which might later be placed at its disposal
                                (896.00/1–2650).</note> be discussed with him for the purpose of
                            obtaining a current appraisal of the problems which have been created by
                            the mismanagement of affairs since independence; that</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>If he raises any exchange or currency stabilization fund problems he
                            be advised to have his experts talk with Secretary Snyder<note n="11"
                                xml:id="d802fn11">John W. Snyder, Secretary of the Treasury.</note>
                            about them; and that</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>He be advised in no uncertain terms that this Government is disturbed
                            by the Philippine failure to repay the pesos advanced by the U.S. Army
                            which are excess to back pay claims and due to be returned.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Additional War Damage Appropriations</hi>. President Quirino
                    will probably ask specifically for an additional war damage appropriation to
                    bring payments up to the statutory limitation of 75% on approved claims. The War
                    Damage Commission also favored such an appropriation and estimates that
                    approximately $80,000,000 would do the job. The Department of State last summer
                    favored an additional proposal but the Bureau of the Budget opposed it. The
                    Department now inclines to change its position on the grounds that any such
                    appropriation would probably eliminate the possibility at some later date of
                    securing anything else from the Congress for the Philippines at a later date
                    which would be more economically productive. While the Department would not,
                    however, actively oppose any additional war damage <pb facs="1424" n="1410"
                        xml:id="pg_1410"/> legislation introduced into the Congress it would
                    consider its passage as unfortunate.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>If President Quirino raises the question of additional war damage payments it is
                    recommended that no commitments be made to him and that he be informed this is a
                    question for the Congress to decide.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]<note n="12" xml:id="d802fn12">In the
                                source text this enclosure is labeled “Tab 1”.</note>
                        </seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Extracts From Letter Dated 16 September 1949 From the
                            Secretary of Defense to the Secretary of State</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The United States has evidenced, by its very great expenditures in men and
                        materiel for liberation of the Philippines in World War II its deep concern
                        in the freedom and well-being of the Filipino people. This concern has in no
                        way been lessened by recent and current developments in the international
                        field nor is it anticipated that it can be altered by future
                        developments.</p>
                    <p>United States military interest in the Philippines, consequently, is strong
                        and durable. From the military viewpoint, the strategic importance of the
                        Philippines is not open to question. In the event of war, the United States
                        must insure that control of the Philippines not be taken by an enemy power
                        and present base rights in the Philippine Islands must therefore remain
                        available for military use in defense of the Philippines in war
                        emergency.</p>
                    <p>Our military interest in the Philippines has not been decreased by current
                        trends on the Asiatic mainland. Rather, such trends have served to focus the
                        attention of the Military Establishment of the United States on the
                        Philippines and have emphasized the strategic importance of the Philippine
                        Islands.</p>
                    <p>United States determination to support Philippine independence in the event
                        of war cannot be measured in terms of the numerical strength of United
                        States forces basing there now or later. Under essential peacetime
                        restrictions on military expenditures, it is impossible for the United
                        States to have available in all key areas those forces which would be needed
                        in an emergency. In fact, it is impossible to have forces of such strength
                        deployed in such areas anywhere in peacetime.</p>
                    <p>It is the intention of the United States, however, to retain some <pb
                            facs="1425" n="1411" xml:id="pg_1411"/> of its forces in the Philippine
                        Islands and to maintain United States base areas there in readiness for
                        emergency use.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
