<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-06-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="826" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d826">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">896.00/6–2050</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The President of the Republic of the Philippines</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Quirino</hi></persName>)
                                <hi rend="italic">to <gloss type="to">President Truman</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d826fn1">The text of a draft of this letter,
                                given to Ambassador Cowen by Foreign Secretary Romulo on June 10,
                                was transmitted in telegram 1697, June 11, from Manila, not printed
                                (896.00/6–1150). Telegram 1037, June 14, to Manila, not printed,
                                instructed that the proposed reply was wholly acceptable to the
                                United States (896.00/6–1150). Following slight drafting changes by
                                Philippine authorities, the final signed version of this letter was
                                reported upon in telegram 1761, June 19, from Manila, not printed
                                (896.00/6–1950) and was transmitted as an enclosure to despatch No.
                                796, June 20, from Manila, not printed (896.00/6–2050),</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Manila</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-06-08">June 8, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I was happy to read the
                            text of your letter, dated June 1, 1950,<note n="2" xml:id="d826fn2">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> which has been transmitted to
                            me by <pb facs="1474" n="1460" xml:id="pg_1460"/> Ambassador Myron M.
                            Cowen through Secretary of Foreign Affairs, Carlos P. Romulo, in advance
                            of the signed original.</p>
                        <p>A proper regard for the abiding interest which you, Mr. President, and
                            your government, have in the welfare of my country and my peoples moves
                            me to express my concurrence in your proposal to form an American
                            economic mission which will come to the Philippines to examine the
                            entire economic situation, make recommendations, and advise the
                            Philippine Government in working out a program which the United States
                            Government might consider in its efforts to assist the Philippines.</p>
                        <p>There is scarcely any need, at this juncture, to review the course of the
                            negotiations concerning this project of the United States Government.
                            Suffice it to say that the arrangement outlined in your letter is
                            accepted by the Philippine Government on a basis of cooperative
                            procedure indicated therein and out of a desire see this enterprise
                            carried out.</p>
                        <p>I appreciate your assurance that the US Government, and in particular,
                            the US Survey Mission, will seek the fullest cooperation of all
                            Filipinos who are concerned about the problems of the country. No other
                            group of Filipinos will be in a better position to render such
                            cooperation than the group of experts which I have designated, and to
                            which reference is made in your letter. I am gratified over your
                            statement that their advice will be availed of by the Survey Mission and
                            by the US Government at every opportunity, for, to quote your own words,
                            no American Mission, lacking such cooperation, “could be expected to
                            produce a program and suggestions which would be helpful to the
                            Philippines or susceptible of consideration by the US.”</p>
                        <p>The Philippine Government is prepared to receive the US Survey Mission at
                            any time, and to place all necessary facilities at the disposal of the
                            members to assist them in their work.</p>
                        <p>I am grateful to you for your kind inquiries about my health and most
                            specially for the spirit of helpfulness which inspires your esteemed
                            letter. I have never for a moment doubted the continued interest of the
                            US in the future and welfare of my country and people.</p>
                        <p>Your personal interest has made it more patent. I pray that Divine
                            Providence may give us continued strength and well-being to discharge
                            our grave responsibilities at this critical time.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Elpidio Quirino</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>