<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Douglas) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">85</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-11-14T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-11-14T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-11-14T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-11-14T11:00:00-05:00" n="85"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890.00/11–1450: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-11-14T16:00:00+00:00"
                            >November 14, 1950—4 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2813. Please pass <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> for Harlan Cleveland.
                    Department’s attention invited to fact that “Colombo Plan for cooperative
                    economic development in South and Southeast Asia” will be published both in
                    official and popular form November 21<note n="1" xml:id="d85fn1">Cmd. 8080, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Colombo Plan for Co-operative Economic Development in
                            South and South-East Asia, Report by the Commonwealth Consultative
                            Committee, London, September–October, 1950</hi>, was published on
                        November 28, 1950.</note> and that British Government planning give wide
                    publicity to it, thus raising in acute form question of US attitudes. We have
                    found among Asian representatives here great curiosity about and interest in US
                    position regarding plan and suggest that attitude of Asians toward US might
                    immediately be favorably affected if US should express itself as in favor of aid
                    to Asia and that conversely continued silence on our part might lead Asians to
                    believe US not interested aid to Asia.</p>
                <p>Embassy has been glad to learn from Joseph Jones<note n="2" xml:id="d85fn2"
                        >Joseph M. Jones, Special Adviser, Economic Analysis Staff, Far East Program
                        Division, Economic Cooperation Administration.</note> latest <gloss
                        target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> and Department thinking on aid to Asia.
                    Question arises whether Department may not wish to release to press statement
                    tied to Colombo report at an appropriate time or in any case to give Embassy
                    policy guidance for discussing matter with British Government and press which
                    continues to display lively interest in matter.</p>
                <p>Department may quite possibly not wish now give preview its development plan for
                    aid to Asia. On other hand Embassy suggests that publication of Colombo report
                    offers splendid opportunity for doing so and at same time for clarifying a few
                    main points as to desirable relation of US aid to Commonwealth plan. Such a
                    statement could include for example indication that Commonwealth conclusions as
                    to scope and kinds of program seem reasonable from what we, without detailed
                    investigation, have been able to judge. It could make it clear (if as Embassy
                    understands it is our position) that US aid to Asian countries would be
                    administered bilaterally in coordination with local plans and other aid accruing
                    in the individual country, and that we <pb facs="0174" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/>
                    believe there need be no conflict with US or UN assistance. It could specify
                    degree to which US feels it could participate in advisory and consultative group
                    in Colombo. It might with advantage emphasize in same statement that US is
                    already carrying on broad aid programs in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>
                    and that UN likewise has certain programs and plans for aid to Asia.</p>
                <p>Incidentally in informal discussions here British have suggested that bilateral
                    approach is only feasible approach for US aid to Asia. Also we gather impression
                    that British are overwhelmingly interested in application of plan to India and
                    have no design for re-establishing influence in <gloss target="#t_SEA1"
                        >SEA</gloss> through plan and seem willing to have US continue carry main
                    responsibility for this area.</p>
                <p>We feel that substantial political advantage could accrue from clearing up these
                    several points in an early public statement. We realize however that a large
                    strategy is involved and that any public statement on Colombo plan must fit into
                    it.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
