<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the United States Representative at the
                    United Nations ( (Austin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v01p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d138</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">138</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-04-08T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-04-08T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-04-08T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-04-08T18:00:00-05:00" n="138"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d138">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.AA/4–848: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the United States Representative at the United Nations</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-04-08T18:00:00-05:00"
                            >April 8, 1948—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>200. Suggested statement to be made at opening discussion Ital membership
                    application follows:</p>
                <p>McKeever should coordinate closely with Voice of America people N.Y. to insure
                    best possible coverage of statement Ital. Mission should also work closely with
                    Mascia this connection.</p>
                <p>“The United States has consistently given its full support to the application of
                    Italy for admission into the United Nations. Today, I have the honor to reaffirm
                    the support of the United States for Italy’s application.</p>
                <pb facs="0213" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/>
                <p>Even before the ratification of the Treaty of Peace with Italy, the United
                    (States maintained that as a co-belligerent with the Allies from 1943 to 1945,
                    and as a country which had made enormous strides forward under heavy handicaps
                    in her own postwar rehabilitation, Italy was entitled to special consideration
                    by this body of freedom-loving nations. Indeed, this special position of Italy
                    was recognized by my Govt and the Govts of the United Kingdom and Soviet Union
                    at Potsdam. A special para on Italy was included in the agreed-upon communique
                    issued at the end of that meeting, and it was agreed that the preparation of a
                    peace treaty for Italy should be the first task of the Council of Foreign
                    Ministers. After the ratification of the peace treaty, no shadow of an excuse
                    remained for the persistent exclusion of Italy from membership in the United
                    Nations.</p>
                <p>My Govt, together with the Govts of the U.K. and France, has requested this
                    renewed consideration of the Ital application. Speaking for my Govt, this action
                    is taken because we have the firm conviction that an injustice has been done to
                    Italy. This nation of 45 million people meets, by any conceivable standard, the
                    qualifications laid down in Art. 4 of the Charter concerning membership. This
                    has not been questioned. My Govt feels therefore that it should do everything
                    within its power to bring about a correction of this injustice. It believes this
                    opinion is shared not only by most of the members of this Council but by an
                    overwhelming majority of the total membership of the United Nations. This was
                    made abundantly clear in the resolution on Italy’s application which was passed
                    at the last meeting of the General Assembly. In the opinion of my Govt the
                    Security Council has not, thus far, given proper weight to that resolution.
                    True, it did meet briefly on the question while the Assembly was still in
                    session, but the members of this Council who were sitting on the Council at that
                    time will recall that the matter was not exhaustively considered after the
                    Soviet rep made known that his negative attitude towards the admission of Italy
                    had not changed.</p>
                <p>As the members of the Council will also recall, the Soviet Union has attempted in
                    the past to tie the Ital application with the applications recd from the other
                    ex-enemy states. This course of action, to our minds, is completely unjustified.
                    Each application must, in conformity with the Charter, be considered on its own
                    merits. The Soviet Union by attemping to place the Ital application in the same
                    category as the applications reed from states which this Council has determined
                    to be unqualified for membership does a grave injustice to the Ital people.
                    Surely, there is no justice in penalizing a people who have proved themselves to
                    be qualified for membership, by coupling them with states which by their own
                    actions have shown they are clearly disqualified.</p>
                <pb facs="0214" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/>
                <p>This attempt at bargaining is surely beneath the dignity of this Council.</p>
                <p>If on this renewed reconsideration of the Ital application the same tactics are
                    attempted, and if this Council should unfortunately fail to recommend Italy’s
                    admission, the world will have no doubt as to the reason for this injustice. The
                    world can interpret the act in no other way than as an expression by the Soviet
                    Union of a lack of friendship for the people of Italy.</p>
                <p>In conclusion may I stress again that Italy’s record clearly merits admission to
                    the United Nations. The Ital people have suffered greatly, they have worked
                    hard, and they have proven to the satisfaction of my Govt and, I believe, to
                    that of all democratic nations, that they have earned their right to a seat in
                    the world’s councils. My Govt has faith in the Ital people. It asks that they be
                    granted immediately their rightful position among the nations. It holds that
                    their contribution to the world community, based on generations of spiritual and
                    intellectual attainment, will add immeasurably to the betterment of that
                    community. It maintains that further to deny or condition in any way Italy’s
                    admission to the United Nations is to express a lack of faith in her people,
                    that it is without moral or juridical justification as I interpret the
                    principles of the Charter, that it is unfriendly to a free democratic nation,
                    and that it is unworthy of any nation or nations represented here.”<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d138fn1">The Security Council considered the membership items on its
                        agenda at two meetings on April 10; for the proceedings see United Nations,
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Records of the Security Council, Third Year,
                            No. 54</hi>, pp. 5 ff., and <hi rend="italic">ibid., No. 55</hi>. (It
                        may be observed parenthetically that as the first order of business at the
                        first of these two meetings that the Security Council unanimously approved
                        the application of the Union of Burma for membership in the United Nations,
                        and so recommended to the General Assembly. The General Assembly adopted the
                        Security Council’s recommendation and admitted Burma to the <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> on April 19.) <p>The vote on the Italian
                            application being a substantive matter, it did not carry as one of the
                            permanent members voted against the resolution. When the Security
                            Council assembled at the next meeting to take up the applications of the
                            remaining ten countries (Albania, Austria, Bulgaria, Finland, Hungary,
                            Ireland, the Mongolian Peoples Republic, Portugal, Romania and
                            Transjordan), it was decided simply to inform the General Assembly that
                            after reconsideration of the matter, the Security Council found that
                            none of its members had changed their position from that which already
                            stood on the record.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
