<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="191" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d191">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Disarmament Files</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Donald M. Leith of the Division of
                            International Security Affairs</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d191fn1">This
                            memorandum was directed to Dean Rusk, Director of the Office of United
                            Nations Affairs; Donald C. Blaisdell, Special Assistant to Mr. Rusk:
                            Howard C. Johnson, Associate Chief of the Division of International
                            Security Affairs; and John C. Elliott, Acting Assistant Chief of the
                            Division and Executive Secretary of the Executive Committee on
                            Regulation of Armaments.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-03">February 3, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The following notes include a brief statement of the highlights of my recent
                        trip to New York:<note n="2" xml:id="d191fn2">Leith visited the United
                            States Mission at the United Nations from January 20 to January
                            28.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Upon my arrival I went over with Mr. Osborn, in some detail, the
                                material so far prepared by <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> and
                                the Department dealing with the subject of conventional armaments.
                                Particular emphasis was given in our discussions to the proper
                                interpretation of <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> D–13/10e, the
                                basic statement of general principles,<note n="3" xml:id="d191fn3">For a statement of United States policy on this subject based
                                    on document <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> D–13/10e and
                                    submitted to the Commission for Conventional Armaments on
                                    September 17, 1947, see <ref target="frus1947v01#pg_660">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1947, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 660</ref>.</note> and <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> D–18/2e, dealing with the elements
                                of safeguards.<note n="4" xml:id="d191fn4">Not printed, but see
                                    previous draft, document <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss>
                                    D–18/2d, <ref target="frus1947v01#pg_703">
                                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 703</ref>.</note> I also
                                gave Mr. Osborn some background on the thinking which had led to the
                                development of <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> and Departmental
                                positions on the subject of regulation of armaments.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Mr. Osborn, Mr. Burton,<note n="5" xml:id="d191fn5">John R.
                                    Burton, Jr., Staff Member, United States Delegations to the
                                    United Nations Atomic Energy Commission and to the Commission
                                    for Conventional Armaments.</note> and I attended the 13th
                                Meeting of the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> Working Committee
                                on January 21. This was a particularly useful meeting at which to
                                have been present because Mr. Gromyko<note n="6" xml:id="d191fn6">Andrey Andreyevich Gromyko, Permanent Representative of the
                                    Soviet Union at the United Nations; Soviet Representative to the
                                    Commission for conventional Armaments.</note> made a general
                                statement criticizing the Australian Resolution,<note n="7" xml:id="d191fn7">The Australian resolution, relating to Item II
                                    of the Plan of Work (General Principles), is not printed.</note>
                                and during the course of this criticism revealed for the first time
                                the line he is generally expected to follow in attacking resolutions
                                having points in common with the Australian Resolution (as the
                                United States draft Resolution on Item II has). During this meeting
                                Mr. Osborn took the position that it was premature to appoint a
                                subcommittee to deal with resolutions on Item II, a position in
                                accord with Departmental thinking.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Although a sub-committee was not appointed, it was suggested that
                                the British and Australians should endeavor to merge their draft
                                resolutions into one.<note n="8" xml:id="d191fn8">The British
                                    resolution is not printed.</note> This suggestion was
                                accepted.</item>
                            <pb facs="0334" n="314" xml:id="pg_314"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The day following the meeting, we received a draft of the proposed
                                joint U.K.-Australian Resolution on Item II<note n="9" xml:id="d191fn9">Not printed.</note> for our suggestions. I was
                                given to understand that this was on the initiative of the U.K.
                                Delegation. The joint Resolution contained a few points to which we
                                had major objections. Mr. Osborn sent Mr. Burton and me to the
                                British to give them our views in an informal way. We emphasized
                                that such views as we expressed were in no sense official and that
                                we were not prepared, as yet, to commit ourselves to support any of
                                the resolutions so far submitted. The British appeared to be in
                                sympathy with our views and said they would discuss them with the
                                Australians. A revision subsequent to such discussion has been
                                forwarded to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> (<gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss>).</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The Chairmanship of the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>
                                changes Monday, February 2nd and Mr. Osborn takes over from Sir
                                Alexander Cadogan.<note n="10" xml:id="d191fn10">Permanent
                                    Representative of the United Kingdom at the United Nations;
                                    British Representative to the Commission for Conventional
                                    Armaments.</note> The date for the next meeting of the Working
                                Committee has not been set and none of the Delegations is, as yet,
                                pressing for an early convening of the Committee, Nevertheless, it
                                is likely that there will be at least one meeting before the middle
                                of February.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The tactics tentatively decided upon by <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> for the next few weeks are as follows:</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>When the joint U.K.-Australian Resolution is introduced to the
                                Committee, <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> proposes to offer,
                                as amendments, those important changes which have not been accepted.
                                It is even possible that we shall introduce a resolution of our own,
                                although the former method would be preferable since our resolution
                                would be similar in many respects to that of the other two
                                delegations. A vote on Item II will almost certainly be taken before
                                the end of the month. This means that the Commission will be faced
                                with the alternatives of either going on to Item III or not meeting
                                at all for an indefinite period. Mr. Osborn’s present instructions
                                call for proceeding with Item III.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>While Mr. Osborn agrees with those who feel that there may be-a
                                good deal of logic in stopping after the vote on a Resolution on
                                Item II, he feels that the general principles are so general, that
                                even a 9 to 2 vote on them would not make the strong record we
                                should like. He, therefore, believes it desirable to proceed far
                                enough into Item III to develop a majority supported statement
                                regarding elements of safeguards. By developing such an agreed
                                statement, Mr. Osborn feels that the majority and ourselves would be
                                in the strong position of having made constructive proposals both in
                                the atomic energy field and in that of conventional armaments which
                                the Soviets and their satellites alone had refused to accept.
                                Furthermore, he thinks that the Soviet <pb facs="0335" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> rejection of proposals on safeguards would
                                mean much more to the “man-in-the-street” than a difference merely
                                on principles—important as these principles may be.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>I asked Mr. Osborn whether he thought the discussion of safeguards
                                could be controlled in such a way as not to involve us too deeply in
                                the details of Item III, or so as not to invite a discussion on Item
                                IV, either one of which would at this time seriously embarrass us.
                                Mr. Osborn seemed confident that such discussion, could be avoided
                                in the light of his experience in the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> where a similar danger had existed. He said,
                                however, his final attitude on the matter would be strongly
                                influenced by the reaction of friendly delegations, notably the
                                Canadian, French, and United Kingdom Delegations. With their
                                cooperation he had no doubt that the discussion could be limited to
                                the desired scope.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>Mr. Osborn has already seen General McNaughton<note n="11" xml:id="d191fn11">General Andrew, G. L. McNaughton, Permanent
                                    Canadian Representative at the United Nations; Canadian
                                    Representative on the United Nations Atomic Energy Commission
                                    and Commission for Conventional Armaments; Chairman of the
                                    Canadian Atomic Energy Control Board.</note> of the Canadian
                                Delegation and Baron de la Tournelle<note n="12" xml:id="d191fn12">Baron Guy de la Tournelle, Alternate French Representative to
                                    the Commission for Conventional Armaments.</note> of the French
                                Delegation. Before meeting with these gentlemen, Mr. Osborn asked me
                                whether I thought the Department would feel it worthwhile for him to
                                see them, provided the conversation were kept on a highly personal
                                basis with a clear understanding that no decision has as yet been
                                reached by the State Department I told him I was sure the Department
                                would approve such action on the basis contemplated. Both men, when
                                consulted, seemed, favorable to Mr. Osborn’s suggestion.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>Mr. Osborn, therefore, believes it will be possible, with such
                                help as can be supplied from Washington, to undertake the
                                consideration of elements of safeguards in the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss> such as are outlined in. <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> D–18/2e, if the tactical situation
                                makes it appear wise to go ahead. However, he plans to discuss this
                                matter at the <gloss target="#t_RAC1">RAC</gloss> meeting on
                                Wednesday, February 4.</item>
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>Two Annexes are attached to this memorandum. Annex I is Mr.
                                Osborn’s memorandum of the conversation which he and I had with
                                General McNaughton, concerning the advisability of proceeding with a
                                consideration of safeguards. Annex II is a memorandum of
                                conversation I had with Mr. Osborn concerning his interview with
                                Baron de la Tournelle of the French Delegation.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0336" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>Annex 1</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-27">January 27, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Appointed Deputy
                                United States Representative to the Commission for Conventional
                                Armaments</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Osborn</hi>)</p>
                        <p>Mr. Leith and Mr. Osborn called on General McNaughton Tuesday afternoon,
                            January 27, 1948. George Ignatieff, General McNaughton’s top
                            assistant,-was present.</p>
                        <p>General McNaughton went over with them the situation in the Commission
                            for Conventional Armaments, with which he was relatively unacquainted.
                            He considered the plan of work and the draft of the British-Australian
                            resolution covering Item II—General Principles, immediately pointing out
                            the weakness of the Australian proposal for progress on disarmament by
                            stages.</p>
                        <p>General McNaughton then discussed the advisability of continuing through
                            Item III—Safeguards, attempting to get a majority report setting up the
                            general principles of safeguards, without, however, developing any
                            specific proposals. He rather indicated that he thought this could be
                            done in a four or five page document and that it would be worth doing
                            because if it got majority approval and the Soviets opposed it, as they
                            certainly would, it would again put the Soviets in the position of
                            refusing to come into a plan and a system of inspection which the
                            majority felt was essential to world security. General McNaughton did
                            not think there was any danger of our being drawn into a discussion of
                            actual reduction (Item IV). He suggested that we not make up our minds
                            at once on whether to proceed with Item III, but see how we made out on
                            Item II. In any event, he felt there could be no possibility of
                            considering Item IV; in other words, that the present work of the
                            Commission must be concluded either with Item II or with Item III.</p>
                        <p>Ignatieff was more diffuse in his statements and did not appear to
                            support the idea of a majority expression on principles covering
                            safeguards. (Mr. Osborn noted that on the Atomic Energy Commission
                            General McNaughton’s own views always prevailed, and always overruled
                            Ignatieff’s position, but this might not be the case in the Conventional
                            Armaments Commission:; with which General McNaughton was not as much
                            concerned.)</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0337" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>Annex 2</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-30">January 30, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by Mr. Donald M.
                                Leith of the Division of International Security Affairs</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Osborn called me Friday afternoon January 30, 1948, to report on his
                            conversation with Baron de la Tournelle of the French Delegation
                            regarding the subject of future activities in the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>. The Baron indicated that he was much
                            disappointed with the lack of progress so far made in the <gloss target="#t_CCA1">CCA</gloss>. He had expected that since the United
                            States had taken a position of leadership in the beginning, especially
                            respecting the Plan of Work and Item I, we would have had much more
                            concrete proposals to make respecting Items II and III and would have
                            been more eager to make them. He himself thought that it would be most
                            desirable at this point to develop a basic statement on safeguards which
                            could in turn become the basis for a vote on Item III. He felt very
                            definitely that the Russians would be in no position to agree to such a
                            statement in as much as it had already been made evident that a thorough
                            going system of inspection would be contrary to what they believed their
                            interests to be. He felt definitely that any discussions on Item III
                            could be controlled to such an extent that it would not be necessary to
                            deal with material that might be embarrassing to us at this time.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Osborn stated that in talking with Baron de la Tournelle the above
                            suggestions had been made on the initiative of the Baron.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>