<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="222" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Atomic Energy Files</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum for the Secretary of State</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d222fn1">Presumably drafted by R. Gordon Arneson, who in July
                            succeeded Edmund A. Gullion as Special Assistant to the Under Secretary
                            of State for atomic energy policy.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-20">August 20, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">problem</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Action to be taken on Dr. Niels Bohr’s<note n="2" xml:id="d222fn2">Danish
                            theoretical physicist and pioneer in the development of nuclear physics;
                            adviser, Manhattan Engineer District (United States atomic bomb
                            development program), 1943–1945.</note> proposal for “Openness.”</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">facts bearing on the problem</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>See Appendix A.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">discussion</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>See Appendix B.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">conclusions</hi><note n="3" xml:id="d222fn3">The
                            Secretary of State initialled his approval of conclusions 1–6.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Dr. Bohr’s proposal for openness should not be made by the United
                                States at this time.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In view of the domestic political situation and the danger of
                                “leaks”, the Department of State should not undertake an intensive
                                study of this proposal and its ramifications until elections are
                                over and any changes that may result therefrom have occurred.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>After the elections, the Department should sound out the
                                then-responsible political leaders on the extent of their support
                                for a thoro-going study of the proposal in terms of its feasibility,
                                repercussions on national security, chances and consequences of
                                Soviet acceptance, propaganda and moral value at home and abroad in
                                event of Soviet refusal, etc.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Further study of the proposal should be dependent upon the results
                                of such soundings.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Meanwhile, the United States should use those elements inherent in
                                the Bohr proposal which are also inherent in this Government’s
                                approach to world problems in developing a dominant theme in the
                                General Assembly. In doing so, the United States could expound on
                                    <pb facs="0409" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/> the kind of world in
                                which it would like to live, a world of openness in which (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) politically independent states could work
                                out their own destinies free of coercion; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                                problems before the United Nations and in other forums could be
                                worked put through the free interplay of ideas, and decisions could
                                be made and carried out on a cooperative basis; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) persons and ideas could be interchanged on the basis of
                                full reciprocity. In this connection: <list>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The United States should cite its record in foreign
                                        relations which demonstrates its efforts to achieve this
                                        kind of world, the most cogent example being negotiations
                                        for the international control of atomic energy.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>In citing the record, the United States should make clear,
                                        either directly or by implication, the role of the Soviet
                                        Union in preventing the development of such a world
                                        community.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The United States should call upon all nations to fulfill
                                        their responsibilities to, the world community to the extent
                                        necessary to attain effective solutions to common
                                        problems.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>No “offer” in the sense of the Bohr proposal should be
                                        made: stress should be put on the past and continuing
                                        efforts of the United States to achieve an open
                                        world.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Conclusion 5 (with reference to the Bohr proposal as such omitted)
                                and those sections of Appendix B “Discussion” pertinent thereto
                                should be referred to <gloss target="#t_UNA1">UNA</gloss> for
                                consideration in preparing the line to be taken by the United States
                                in the General Assembly.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Dr. Bohr should be informed of the action decided upon by the
                                    Department.<note n="4" xml:id="d222fn4">In a marginal comment
                                    opposite this conclusion, Marshall stated “I am not yet clear in
                                    my own mind on this.”</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>Appendix A</head>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">facts bearing on the problem</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>In the latter part of May, the Secretary of State received through
                                Mr. McCloy<note n="5" xml:id="d222fn5">John J. McCloy, President of
                                    the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development;
                                    Assistant Secretary of War, 1941–1945; Member, Secretary of
                                    State’s Committee on Atomic Energy, 1946.</note> a paper from
                                Dr. Niels Bohr which advocated that the United States should make a
                                broad offer to the Soviet Union to exchange all scientific and
                                technical information with the Soviet Union on a reciprocal basis.
                                In brief the argumentation was along these lines: (See Tab A, Bohr’s
                                “Comments”, dated May 17, 1948, Tab B, Bohr’s letter of June 10,
                                1948, to Secretary Marshall, and Tab C, Bohr’s “Annotations” dated.
                                June 19, 1948).<note n="6" xml:id="d222fn6">The accompanying tabs,
                                    A–M, are not printed.</note>
                                <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>Failure to overcome the impasse that now exists between
                                        the East and the West can only lead to the most terrible of
                                        wars in which no one can win.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0410" n="390" xml:id="pg_390"/>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>The way out of this impasse lies in the raising of “a
                                        great issue suited to invoke the highest aspirations of
                                        mankind.”</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>This great issue would be an offer by the United States of
                                        complete “openness” among the peoples of the world directed
                                        in the first instance to the Soviet Union.</item>
                                    <label>D.</label>
                                    <item>If such an offer were made, the United States would stand
                                        to gain whether the Soviet Union accepted the offer or not. <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>If the Soviet Union accepted the offer it would
                                                mean the end of the Iron Curtain and a change in the
                                                whole Soviet system of government with genuine
                                                participation on their part in the world community.
                                                The present impasse would be overcome and the world
                                                could proceed on the basis of a growing
                                                understanding to reconstruct the peace.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>If the Soviet Union refused—and it is most likely
                                                that they would—the United States would have rallied
                                                the forces of liberalism throughout the world to its
                                                standard. The Soviet Union might well find itself in
                                                such a position that all hopes of extending its
                                                influence further in the world would be lost.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>E.</label>
                                    <item>As to the security aspect of this proposal Dr. Bohr
                                        maintains that the security of the United States would be
                                        strengthened rather than weakened if the offer were carried
                                        through. Under present security phobias the United States is
                                        strangulating itself and is in danger of falling behind in
                                        many fields of science and technology. Moreover, giving the
                                        Soviet Union all information concerning atomic energy
                                        processes including the making of bombs (but not the bombs
                                        themselves) would probably so confuse and over-awe them that
                                        no net advantage would accrue to them. The United States on
                                        the other hand would gain much knowledge of the Soviet Union
                                        and would have breached the Iron Curtain which stands as the
                                        greatest threat to world peace and security.</item>
                                    <label>F.</label>
                                    <item>If it were to make this offer, Dr. Bohr emphasizes that
                                        the United States would have to be prepared to carry it
                                        through in all honesty. This requires the most meticulous
                                        study preparatory to any final decision on the idea.</item>
                                    <label>G.</label>
                                    <item>Dr. Bohr, aware that a vast educational program directed
                                        to public understanding of this problem would be required,
                                        and that the greatest popular fear which would have to be
                                        overcome concerns security, concludes that the one man who
                                        could carry conviction to the country on this matter is the
                                        present Secretary of State. This is so not only because of
                                        his unquestioned integrity, but also because he is
                                        identified in the public mind with the highest security
                                        interests of the country.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>On May 20 the Secretary had dinner with Dr. Bohr and Mr. McCloy at
                                which time the Secretary expressed concern about the security
                                aspects of the proposal and asked Dr. Bohr to elaborate his proposal
                                    <pb facs="0411" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/> in greater detail.
                                This was done in a letter of June 10, 1948. (See Tab B.) The
                                Secretary asked Mr. Baruch for his views which were received on June
                                2. Mr. Baruch commented that “a great issue was raised, suited to
                                invoke the highest aspirations of mankind” when the United States
                                made its atomic energy proposals of June 14, 1946. (See Tab
                                D.)</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The problem was referred for follow-up to the Special Assistant to
                                the Under Secretary. Mr. Gullion and Mr. Arneson undertook a series
                                of discussions with key people in Government service and others who
                                had previously been connected with atomic energy matters. These
                                included: <list>
                                    <item>Mr. Dean Acheson<note n="7" xml:id="d222fn7">Under
                                            Secretary of State, August 1945–June 1947.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Dr. Robert F. Bacher<note n="8" xml:id="d222fn8">Member,
                                            United States Atomic Energy Commission.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Mr. Benjamin Cohen<note n="9" xml:id="d222fn9">Counselor,
                                            Department of State, September 1945–July 1947.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Dr. Paul C. Fine<note n="10" xml:id="d222fn10">Adviser,
                                            United States Delegation to the United Nations Atomic
                                            Energy Commission.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Mr. John J. McCloy</item>
                                    <item>General K. D. Nichols<note n="11" xml:id="d222fn11">Maj.
                                            Gen. Kenneth D. Nichols, Director of the Armed Forces
                                            Special Weapons Project; Member, Military Liaison
                                            Committee to the United States Atomic Energy Commission;
                                            District Engineer, Manhattan Engineer District,
                                            1943–1945.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer<note n="12" xml:id="d222fn12">Director of the Institute for Advanced Study,
                                            Princeton, New Jersey; Chairman of the General Advisory
                                            Committee of the United States Atomic Energy Commission;
                                            Director of Los Alamos Laboratories of Manhattan
                                            Engineer District, 1943–1945.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Mr. Frederick H. Osborn</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label> </label>
                            <item>The resultant Memoranda of Conversation are attached as Tabs E
                                through M.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The consensus that developed from these conversations was as
                                follows: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>Dr. Bohr had hit upon the nub of the difficulty with the
                                        Soviet Union. Many people, however, have also perceived
                                        this.</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>Only a most meticulous study of all ramifications of the
                                        proposal could reveal whether it was feasible and
                                        desirable.</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>Such study could be effective only if the group doing it
                                        were given full access to all atomic energy and military
                                        weapons data and included highly competent personnel from
                                        the departments and agencies of government concerned,
                                        particularly the Atomic Energy Commission and the National
                                        Defense Establishment. (If the group were composed of
                                        individuals brought together under the auspices of some
                                        non-governmental organization, effective liaison with
                                        appropriate Governmental bodies would be imperative.)</item>
                                    <pb facs="0412" n="392" xml:id="pg_392"/>
                                    <label>D.</label>
                                    <item>Present public opinion as reflected in Congress and
                                        throughout the country generally would not support the Bohr
                                        proposal without an intensive campaign of public education.
                                        Any inkling at this time that the Government was giving
                                        serious study to the proposal would raise a frantic hue and
                                        cry from all quarters and the whole issue would be
                                        thrust—with chaotic results—into the political
                                        campaign.</item>
                                    <label>E.</label>
                                    <item>It would be difficult to initiate any thorough appraisal
                                        of the Bohr proposal intra- or extra-governmentally without
                                        having it become known.</item>
                                    <label>F.</label>
                                    <item>The forthcoming elections add additional complications.
                                        Whatever the outcome of the elections, common prudence would
                                        require that this matter be discussed with, and support
                                        obtained from, the leading Republican figures, including, at
                                        minimum, Governor Dewey, John Foster Dulles, Senator
                                        Vandenberg and Senator Hickenlooper before an intensive
                                        study is initiated.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>On June 14, 1946, the U.S. made a sweeping offer of “openness”,
                                supported by adequate safeguards in the field of atomic energy. As
                                elaborated over the past two years by the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss>, the plan for atomic energy control would produce
                                in this one field, and as a prototype for other fields, an
                                atmosphere of complete openness. The majority has committed itself
                                in the Second Report of the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss>
                                to a policy of no secrecy in this field, once a fully effective
                                system of control is established. The majority proposals place great
                                stress on adequate safeguards. Although the issue of “no veto”
                                received undue attention in the public press during the negotiations
                                and blurred the focus, the elements of safeguards required are
                                essential to the plan and would be equally required in the Bohr
                                proposal.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> in its Third Report,
                                dated May 17, 1948, has come to the conclusion, after more than two
                                years of intensive study, that the continued intransigence of the
                                Soviet Union and its satellites and their unwillingness to
                                participate in a cooperative world community, arises from a
                                situation beyond the competence of the Atomic Energy Commission.
                                Therefore the majority recommended that until such time as the
                                Soviet Union showed its willingness to participate in the world
                                community to the extent required by the majority proposals,
                                negotiations in <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> should be
                                suspended. The first two reports of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Atomic Energy Commission, which comprise the
                                majority proposals General Findings (Part II C) and Recommendations
                                (Part III) of the First Report, Specific Proposals (Part II) Second
                                Report, and the Report and Recommendations of the Third Report,
                                which contains the recommendation for suspension, have been referred
                                to the General Assembly and will be on its agenda this fall. Present
                                plans are for the members of the majority of the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> to sponsor jointly a resolution
                                in the General Assembly approving the majority proposals for
                                control, and the recommendation for suspension.</item>
                            <pb facs="0413" n="393" xml:id="pg_393"/>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>As far as the diagnosis of the disease is concerned the majority
                                of <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> and Dr. Bohr are in
                                agreement: The stumbling block is the attitude of the Soviet Union.
                                The difference lies in that Bohr proposes that we try again on a
                                much broader and more nebulous base. The majority considers that
                                those elements of cooperation essential not only to atomic energy
                                control but also to eventual control of other weapons of mass
                                destruction have been firmly established, and that it remains for
                                the Soviet Union to agree and that, in the absence of such
                                agreement, the peoples of the world should understand the nature of
                                the impasse that exists.</item>
                        </list>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>Appendix B</head>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">discussion</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">A. <hi rend="italic">Need for Thorough Study</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The Bohr proposal is admittedly made only in general terms. Bohr
                                feels that the details, while exceedingly important, are beyond his
                                competence and must be considered by those more familiar with the
                                political and military aspects involved. No one can quarrel with
                                what might ideally be achieved under his proposed offer. One must
                                raise sharply, however, queries concerning methods and tactics of
                                implementation. These queries can be answered only by most
                                thorough-going study, which would require imaginative people from
                                many areas of Government, notably the Department of State, the
                                National Defense Establishment and the Atomic Energy Commission.
                                What the net conclusions of such a study would be, no one can say at
                                this time.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The crucial ingredient in any complete examination of the proposal
                                is knowledge. This can come only from people in the various agencies
                                who would have full access to their particular phases of
                                information. This involves key people who could not take part in
                                such a study without making its existence known. It appears likely
                                that knowledge of the existence of such a project if initiated now
                                would be used in the election campaign with resulting jeopardy to
                                the study itself.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>On so important a matter as this, it is evident that it could
                                succeed only if—after having been determined to be feasible in a
                                technical sense—it secured not only the support of key figures in
                                both political parties but the overwhelming understanding support of
                                the U.S. public. While the bi-partisan approach in foreign affairs
                                has been eminently successful during the war and since, and might in
                                fact prove possible on this matter, the current build up of the
                                election campaign makes a coordination of viewpoint on this proposal
                                exceedingly complicated. At minimum, the Administration would need
                                the support of <pb facs="0414" n="394" xml:id="pg_394"/> Governor
                                Dewey, John Foster Dulles, Senator Vandenberg and Senator
                                Hickenlooper. It may well be that these gentlemen would not wish to
                                indicate any reaction to the idea in its present general terms in
                                the absence of a thorough study and in the expectation of a
                                Republican victory at the polls this fall. It is reasonable to
                                assume that they would prefer, if any study is to be undertaken,
                                that it be done under a new Administration.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">Probable Soviet Reaction to
                                Offer</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Apart from the specific technical aspects of the problem there are
                                certain points that can now be made in advance of a full examination
                                of all phases. These deal primarily with probable Soviet reactions.
                                Dr. Bohr has stated that the United States would stand to gain
                                whether the Soviet Union said “yes” or “no.” It seems evident that
                                real moral and psychological advantage would accrue to the United
                                States should the Soviet Union give a flat “no.” It may be presumed,
                                subject to further study, that the United States would stand to gain
                                if the Soviet Union accepted the offer. There is, however, a
                                twilight zone which appears to be the most likely contingency. It is
                                very much to be doubted that the Soviet Union would give either a
                                flat “yes” or “no” answer. In all probability the Soviet Union would
                                do something in between giving only the appearance of acceptance,
                                coupled with counter proposals and demands, similar to, if not
                                identical with, their actions in the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> negotiations. The Soviet Union would probably
                                mount a terrific counter-attack along the following lines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>The United States has sought continuously to gain control
                                        over the affairs of other nations through <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>, through atomic energy
                                        control, and many other actions since the end of the war.
                                        The United States seeks to dominate the world. Further
                                        evidence of this is their proposal for “openness”. Such a
                                        proposal is a crude attempt to interfere in the internal
                                        affairs of states. It is a gross assault on national
                                        sovereignty of nations. It is an attempt to obtain
                                        intelligence the United States has been unable to obtain by
                                        other means. One need only observe that while the United
                                        States is making what it calls a sweeping proposal of
                                        openness it continues to manufacture, stockpile, and
                                        intimidate the world with, the atomic bomb. If the United
                                        States is serious in its protestations for a peaceful world
                                        why then do they not give up the weapon, outlaw its use, and
                                        destroy the present stockpiles?</p>
                                </quote>
                            </item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The foregoing theme with infinite variations would, in all
                                probability, be played by the Soviet Union to the point where the
                                “great issue suited to invoke the highest aspirations of mankind”
                                would become a very sorry thing indeed. The issue would become so
                                confused that even those great numbers of people who would have been
                                greatly lifted up by the original offer would begin to have doubts
                                about the motives of the United States. The result predicted <pb facs="0415" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/> by Dr. Bohr that the
                                Soviet Union would alienate all liberal thought and put itself in a
                                hole, would not be realized.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>In corroboration of the foregoing one need only to recount the
                                history of the atomic energy negotiations in the United Nations. As
                                Mr. Baruch rightly points out in his letter to the Secretary, the
                                original United States proposals for atomic energy control
                                constituted “a great issue suited to invoke the highest aspirations
                                of mankind.” It did indeed lift the hopes of men when it was made.
                                There is perhaps in history no greater offer and it was generally
                                recognized as such by all thinking people. But what happened? It is
                                significant to note that the Soviet Union has never claimed that the
                                proposals evolved from the United States offer, namely, the present
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> majority proposals, were
                                unsuited to the task of controlling atomic energy for peaceful
                                purposes only. The Soviet Union has never laid stress on the merits
                                of the proposals themselves but have sought—and to a degree
                                succeeded—in confusing the issue by appeals to national sovereignty,
                                independence of states, charges of imperialism and monopoly against
                                the United States, and demands that atomic bombs be outlawed and
                                destroyed. As a result the challenge of the great issue has become
                                so blurred that the man on the street doubts whether the offer ever
                                should have been made and many do not realize that the United States
                                has offered to give up its atomic bombs when an adequate control
                                system is in effect.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">C. <hi rend="italic">The Problem of Stages</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Mr. Baruch in his reply to the Secretary of June 2 (Tab D) points
                                out that Dr. Bohr had stated “a number of truisms, but he does not
                                say how we can arrive at them.” Bohr’s proposal lacks any spelling
                                out of stages although he does suggest the following general
                                approach: a preliminary conference to determine whether the
                                proposition were acceptable “in principle”. [Here one must point out
                                that the Soviet Union has already accepted many propositions “in
                                principle”, including “strict international control of atomic
                                    energy”.]<note n="13" xml:id="d222fn13">Brackets appear in the
                                    source text.</note> This conference would be followed by a
                                balancing out of information and access that nations would be
                                willing to provide. Once a rough balance had been struck and found
                                to be mutually advantageous to all, a regime of openness would be
                                implemented immediately. In commenting upon time scale and the
                                problem of stages in connection with the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> plan of atomic energy control, Dr. Bohr considers
                                that failure to achieve agreement on that plan demonstrates the
                                necessity of “a line of policy, directly aimed at mutual openness on
                                a still broader and <hi rend="underline">more immediate basis</hi>
                                than contemplated in the, American proposal” (Tab B. <pb facs="0416" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/> Underscoring supplied). Moreover, he
                                stated in his brief “Annotations” of June 19, that: “Altogether, the
                                eventual acceptance of an offer of full mutual openness and the
                                actual admittance of observers may, in fact, be said to be an
                                irreversible step.” (Tab C).</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>The issue of stages is a crucial one. It cannot be assumed that
                                any country would be prepared to enter into a regime of openness at
                                one leap. In working out what would appear to most reasonable men to
                                be a fair and just sequence, one can be sure that the Soviet Union
                                would find much material for propaganda charges. They could haggle,
                                delay, and accuse <hi rend="italic">ad infinitum, ad nauseam</hi>,
                                in the working out and the implementation of stages. This might
                                indeed be the method they would employ in sabotaging the whole offer
                                even if they agreed initially to the general idea, in
                                principle.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>It is in working out this aspect of a great issue that the issue
                                itself tends to be lost sight of in the welter of grubby detail and
                                step-by-step caution.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">D. <hi rend="italic">The Basic Difficulty</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>The Bohr proposal strikes at the heart of the difficulty between
                                the East and the West only in a limited sense. The Iron Curtain is a
                                major symptom of the disease that infects the Soviet Union. That
                                disease would appear to be primarily mental. The Soviet state is
                                characterized by a fanatical materialist ideology. It has
                                effectively harnessed Czarist Russian imperialism, traditional
                                Russian xenophobia, modern propaganda techniques, Marxian ideology,
                                and a police state so that its ability to impose its will on its own
                                people and those of other nations is tremendous.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>All nations are guilty of a certain egocentrism. This is an easily
                                understood psychological and sociological phenomenon. Among nations,
                                however, with certain common traditions, culture patterns,
                                institutions, and ways of thought, this egocentrism need not give
                                rise to basic misunderstandings and conflict. Western nations may
                                quarrel with their friends but, in most instances at least, they
                                have a sufficient working knowledge of what their friends’ thought
                                processes, ambitions and needs are to give effective accommodation
                                to them. The Soviet Union, however, is not in this community of
                                nations. It has deliberately turned its back to it and suppressed
                                those elements and forces that would tend to foster Soviet
                                participation in the world community. It emphasizes its different
                                history and its long-standing isolation. Words, morals, and a code
                                of ethics do not mean the same to them as to us. Actions have
                                different meanings. Aspirations are of a different character. It is
                                as though the Western world considers that two and two make four,
                                while the Soviet Union considers that these two numbers add up to
                                different totals at different times. And this is <pb facs="0417" n="397" xml:id="pg_397"/> more than mere analogy. Soviet
                                philosophy in the fundamental sense rejects the Aristotelian
                                concepts of form and discreteness and is based on theories of
                                interaction and merging of identities along the lines of Bergsonian
                                creative evolution. One may indeed say that when the basic tools of
                                thought are different one can conclude that there can be no real
                                meeting of minds.</item>
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>Complete openness would not in itself change this hard core of
                                difference. It would have, to be sure, positive effects. If the West
                                were able to make its thought and action known directly to the
                                people of the Soviet Union, the comparisons that the Soviet people
                                might make would not be invidious to the West. A long period of full
                                intercourse might bring about gradual changes in the basic premises
                                of the philosophy of the Soviet State and its tenets of faith. Most
                                important, it would be in the long run permit the masses of the
                                people to exert their influence on large issues. Openness would also
                                wipe out many of the physical paraphernalia of the police state and
                                lay it open to the fresh breezes of common sense and appreciation of
                                the nature of the rest of the world.</item>
                            <label>13.</label>
                            <item>But because the police state paraphernalia is not the core of the
                                Soviet State itself but a manifestation of its different orientation
                                of thinking which is as real to the Soviet mind as Western thought
                                patterns are to Western peoples, it is inconceivable that the
                                Politburo could be induced to accept the offer in good faith. They
                                could not do so and continue to exist as they are. As has been
                                indicated above, such an offer would in all probability give rise to
                                a furious attack on the motives and objectives of those making
                                it.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">E. <hi rend="italic">The General Assembly: Soviet Peace
                                Offensive</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>14.</label>
                            <item>There has been much speculation, and our Embassies abroad have
                                been queried on this point, as to what line the Soviet Union may
                                take in the next General Assembly. Thus far the plurality, if not
                                the majority, opinion is that the Soviet Union will launch a peace
                                offensive. This might take many forms. The Soviet Union may offer
                                crumbs of concessions in Germany, in Korea; it may blandly suggest
                                that certain commercial air rights be granted in the Soviet Union,
                                that some increase in travel be permitted, that more consulates be
                                established. To accept such offers as moves toward openness would be
                                dangerous, for they would in all probability not indicate a change
                                in heart but a temporary tactical maneuver.</item>
                            <label>15.</label>
                            <item>It has been suggested that such a Soviet line makes it necessary
                                for the United States to appear more peaceful than the Soviet Union.
                                This would not be difficult to do, since the contrast is evident.
                                But peacefulness must not be equated with docility.</item>
                            <pb facs="0418" n="398" xml:id="pg_398"/>
                            <label>16.</label>
                            <item>The United States is a member of the majority which has
                                recommended that, the nature of the impasse being what it is,
                                negotiations in the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> should
                                be suspended. Fear of the Soviet peace offensive has caused some
                                doubts to be raised whether the United States should hold firm on
                                this recommendation.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">F. <hi rend="italic">United States Line in General
                                Assembly</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>17.</label>
                            <item>A possible Soviet peace offensive should be met with firmness.
                                Peaceful protestations on the part of the Soviet Union can readily
                                be tested. The record on many issues in the United Nations is clear.
                                Most of the members of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> have been
                                able to compose honest differences, to work out honorable
                                compromises, and to propose effective solutions to outstanding
                                problems. Throughout its history the United Nations has been faced
                                with “the everlasting no” of the Soviet Union. The most vital
                                example in this connection is the majority control plan for atomic
                                energy. If the Soviet Union intends to show a face of sweetness and
                                light in the next General Assembly, it should be asked politely but
                                firmly if this means it is ready to agree to the majority plan of
                                control. If its answer is “yes,” there is ground for restrained
                                optimism. If its answer is “no,” the peace offensive can be shown to
                                be lacking in substance.</item>
                            <label>18.</label>
                            <item>Throughout the history of the United Nations and the postwar
                                period, the record clearly shows that the United States has sought
                                to arrive at fair solutions to outstanding problems. In this
                                endeavor it has been joined by a preponderant majority of the
                                nations concerned. While not making an offer of openness along the
                                lines of the Bohr proposal, the United States can properly cite the
                                record over the past several years which demonstrates its efforts to
                                foster the development of the peaceful, cooperative world in which
                                we want to live. This is a world in which politically independent
                                states can work together to reach common solutions to common
                                problems. This is a world in which views can be freely exchanged and
                                information required for the solution of problems is made freely
                                available (it was the United States which gave to the <gloss target="#t_UNAEC1">UNAEC</gloss> a large bulk of technical and
                                scientific information—properly declassified—which was required for
                                a proper understanding of the nature of the problem of atomic energy
                                control and the soundness of the United States proposals). This is a
                                world where decisions can be made on the basis of the combined
                                thinking of the nations concerned.</item>
                            <label>19.</label>
                            <item>The record is clear that throughout these endeavors the Soviet
                                Union and its satellites have stood in the way of just and equitable
                                solutions. The record can be cited at great length. It is
                                appropriate that the blame for the impasse on many issues be placed
                                where it belongs.</item>
                            <pb facs="0419" n="399" xml:id="pg_399"/>
                            <label>20.</label>
                            <item>An opening speech in the General Assembly along the lines of the
                                foregoing would meet frontally any Soviet peace offensive. It would
                                be possible with this approach to ask the Soviet Union again and
                                again precisely what it means, to point out that words are of little
                                consequence unless they are substantiated by deeds, and that the way
                                to demonstrate good faith in the interests of peace is to cooperate
                                not only in the solution of common problems but also in the
                                implementation of the decisions reached. The bellwether of this
                                approach can very well be atomic energy control, for it is in this
                                field that the record of the United States is clearest, the issues
                                are sharpest, and the intransigence of the Soviet Union is most
                                evident.</item>
                            <label>21.</label>
                            <item>Whatever may be the ultimate decision on the Bohr proposal, a
                                General Assembly theme along the lines of the above would in no way
                                jeopardize either rejecting the Bohr proposals or accepting them in
                                full at a later date after they have been given the closest study.
                                Indeed Dr. Bohr himself in the closing paragraphs of his letter to
                                the Secretary (Tab B) has the following to say on this point. <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“If the international and domestic situation favored it, the
                                        most direct step would be a concrete proposal of universal
                                        openness, aimed at prompt realization. Yet, if such a
                                        procedure would not be deemed timely, it might be found
                                        suitable, after proper preparations, to use an early
                                        occasion, when re-stating the general lines of American
                                        policy, to stress the urgency of fullest mutual openness and
                                        express readiness to entertain proposals to this effect.</p>
                                    <p>“Even the preliminary approach, consisting of a declaration
                                        of aspiration and intent, might perhaps elicit an answer
                                        which could serve as a further stepping stone. But
                                        irrespective of such response, this initiative should
                                        contribute decisively to clarify the situation; it would
                                        greatly strengthen the moral position of all advocates of
                                        genuine international cooperation and bring adversaries
                                        everywhere in rapidly increasing difficulties.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>