<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="238" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d238">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">
                        <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: US(P)/A/C.1/42</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. <persName type="from">Howard C. Johnson</persName>, Adviser, United States Delegation to
                            the <gloss type="to">United Nations General Assembly</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-29">September 29, 1948</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Summary of Meeting Held in the Office of the Canadian
                            Delegation, September</hi> 29, 1948, 11 <hi rend="smallcaps">a. m.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Atomic Energy and Armaments</p>
                    <table cols="3" rows="15">
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                            <cell>[Mr. Osborn</cell>
                            <cell>—United States Delegation]</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. Johnson</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>General McNaughton</cell>
                            <cell>—Canadian Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. Holmes</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Sir Alexander Cadogan</cell>
                            <cell>—United Kingdom Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. Falla</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. Allen</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>M. de Rose</cell>
                            <cell>—French Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>M. van Langenhove<note n="1" xml:id="d238fn1">Fernand van
                                    Langenhove, Member of the Belgian Delegation; Permanent Belgian
                                    Representative at the United Nations.</note>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>—Belgium Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>L. Rolin<note n="2" xml:id="d238fn2">Henri Rolin, Member of the
                                    Belgian Delegation; President of the Belgian Senate.</note>
                            </cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="0457" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Dr. Urdaneta<note n="3" xml:id="d238fn3">Roberto Urdaneta,
                                    Arbeláez, Chairman of the Colombian Delegation; Permanent
                                    Colombian Representative at the United Nations.</note>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>—Colombian Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Dr. Wei<note n="4" xml:id="d238fn4">Hsioh-ren Wei, Adviser,
                                    Chinese Delegation.</note>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>—Chinese Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Dr. Arce<note n="5" xml:id="d238fn5">José Arce, Member of the
                                    Argentine Delegation; Permanent Argentine Representative at the
                                    United Nations.</note>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>—Argentine Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Dr. van Roijen<note n="6" xml:id="d238fn6">J. H. van Roijen,
                                    Member of the Netherlands Delegation; Netherlands Ambassador in
                                    Canada.</note>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>—Netherlands Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>(Reporter)</cell>
                            <cell>—Brazilian Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>General McNaughton explained the initiative taken by the Canadian Delegation
                        in this manner; that Canada moved the resolution in the Security Council
                        referring the question to the Assembly and hence had taken the initiative in
                        calling this meeting today. He indicated that the Canadian Delegation wished
                        to carry its knowledge and convictions on the subject of atomic energy to
                        the General Assembly. He indicated the belief that the Soviet Union
                        ultimately would have to accept the Atomic Energy Commission proposal and
                        that he did not wish to make it more difficult to bring the Soviet bloc in.
                        He hoped that all members of the Atomic Energy Commission could agree upon
                        joint sponsorship of a General Assembly resolution approving their work. He
                        also expressed the hope that all of the members of the Atomic Energy
                        Commission majority could help in carrying the plan to other members. Mr.
                        Osborn spoke of the endless efforts of the members of the majority and the
                        frustration in the Atomic Energy Commission as the result of the Soviet
                        tactics. He stated that the majority had worked informally together in a
                        spirit of closest cooperation. He stated that as long as 18 months ago the
                        Department of State had become convinced that the Soviet Union was not
                        serious about atomic energy control and was using the Atomic Energy
                        Commission as a propaganda forum only. But at that time other delegates
                        decided to carry the work further and we were glad to do so with them.
                        However, by this spring all the delegates of the major countries came to the
                        conclusion that there was a complete impasse and that it was necessary to
                        bring the matter to the General Assembly in the way now planned. The
                        remaining items involved questions of national interest and are largely
                        political; for instance, the United States position on stages, if written
                        under present conditions of Soviet preparation for war would necessarily be
                        very stiff, while if the Soviet had shown real evidences of world
                        cooperation they might be quite different. He said it was our feeling that
                        the General Assembly should approve the plan resulting from this earnest
                        work of the Atomic Energy Commission or repudiate it.</p>
                    <pb facs="0458" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/>
                    <p>Mr. de Rose indicated that he had no reluctance in taking part in the debate
                        but that we should have a carefully planned method of handling the debate.
                        He suggested that various delegations divide up the task of explaining the
                        proposals; one for instance might explain ownership; another the functions
                        of the Agency, etc. He suggested that further meetings of this group be held
                        in an effort to carefully plan the debate in Committee I.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Wei said that he would state his conviction on the plan in-presenting the
                        case to Committee I; that the main purpose was to obtain support of the
                        General Assembly for the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> proposals, and to
                        understand that there was no alternative, and that the Soviet propaganda was
                        wholly untrue.</p>
                    <p>Dr. van Roijen indicated that his country would support joint sponsorship. He
                        indicated great ignorance on the part of most countries and emphasized the
                        importance of explaining generally the extent to which this plan has been
                        worked out in detail. He agreed with de Rose’s views on procedure and stated
                        that it would be necessary to work out agreement on the actual wording of a
                        resolution.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Rolin who will represent Belgium in the debate, then spoke. (Mr. van
                        Langenhove had previously advised us that Dr. Rolin, President of the
                        Belgian Senate, had just come in and was not yet briefed on atomic energy.)
                        Dr. Rolin indicated that in his personal view the key to the world political
                        situation was disarmament—especially atomic energy control. He felt that
                        Soviet fear of atomic weapons may be the cause of the Soviet attitude. He
                        indicated that something must be done to bring to the public the fact that
                        the majority have agreed upon a real plan. He stated, however, that the
                        Atomic Energy Commission members should consider amendments, giving hope
                        that agreement will be possible and to prevent giving the impression that
                        the majority opposed any change. It is better, he said, to give the
                        impression that we are ready for open discussion rather than give an
                        ultimatum to the Soviet Union from the start. It was his feeling that the
                        Security Council resolution should not be the starting point for drafting a
                        General Assembly resolution which, in his view, must be meaningful in
                        itself. It was also his view that the Third Report was too negative in
                        speaking of the impasse; that the General Assembly must make possible a last
                        effort to reach agreement; He was convinced that nothing more could be done
                        but that we should not accept the recommendation of the Third Report.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Arce expressed the view that we should commence our discussions by
                        acceptance of the fact that the Soviet Union does not want agreement. He
                        stated that she is working on the bomb and does not want others to see what
                        she is doing. He felt that the United States should say that it must hold
                        the weapon to save the world against <pb facs="0459" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/> the time when the Soviet Union would get it. He felt it important to get
                        a great majority of the General Assembly to approve the Atomic Energy
                        Commission proposals. He felt that in Committee I the approach of Mr. de
                        Rose was sound but that in the General Assembly itself there should be a
                        reply to the speeches of the Soviet bloc. The plan must be explained in
                        simple terms in Committee I, and the discussion must terminate by the
                        approval of a resolution. In his opinion, the Latin American Delegations
                        will support the plan. (He later asked Mr. Osborn to have the United States
                        contact the Caribbean countries.) In his view, the Vyshinsky resolution<note n="7" xml:id="d238fn7">For text, see telegram <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 117, September 25, <ref target="#pg_431">p.
                            431</ref>.</note> was pure bluff, introduced for the purpose of
                        confusion, and had no relation to the Atomic Energy Commission proposal.
                        These should be kept completely separate. It was his suggestion that, in
                        Committee I, four or five delegations who best knew the proposals should
                        take the lead.</p>
                    <p>Sir Alexander Cadogan stated that it was important for the majority to
                        continue to stand together. He indicated that although the Security Council
                        resolution was negative, that the United Kingdom thought it its duty to show
                        what the situation was, and that continuing would be deluding the public. He
                        stated, however, that the resolution had a positive objective—that the
                        General Assembly might give some impulse to the question. It was his view
                        that Soviet interventions would make it difficult to carry out de Rose’s
                        plan for dividing up the presentation and expressed the view that several
                        governments would have to give a complete presentation at the beginning. He
                        felt that a certain amount of repetition was necessary.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Urdaneta agreed with the comments of Dr. Arce and Sir Alexander Cadogan.
                        He expressed the view that if three points were made clear the Latin
                        American countries would give their full support: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                        The Soviet position; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) if we can prevent confusing
                        the consideration of the Atomic Energy proposals by direct discussion of the
                        Soviet proposal and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) that the plan does not
                        constitute intervention in domestic affairs.</p>
                    <p>The Reporter from Brazil stated that Brazil would probably have no objection
                        to joint sponsorship.</p>
                    <p>General McNaughton expressed the view that the resolution must be more
                        understandable than the technical resolution of the Security Council and
                        stated he would frame such a resolution and circulate it privately.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Rolin expressed the view that the resolution should not be introduced at
                        the start but after a general discussion. He agreed with General McNaughton
                        that the discussion on atomic energy sfypuld be kept entirely separate from
                        the discussion of Vyshinsky’s resolution. General McNaughton then stated
                        that he assumed there was a consensus <pb facs="0460" n="440" xml:id="pg_440"/> that the debate on these questions should be kept
                        separate, and that we must insist that Committee I itself and not a
                        Subcommittee discuss the atomic energy matter.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Arce suggested that General McNaughton show the resolution, in the first
                        instance, to the United States, United Kingdom, France, China, Belgium and
                        Canada, and then to the other members of the Atomic Energy Commission
                        majority. This suggestion was approved.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Osborn stated that he would send 10 copies of the pamphlet prepared in
                        the United States, containing the Atomic Energy Commission proposals, to
                        each Delegation of the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> majority and that
                        the French were printing, in French, a somewhat similar pamphlet. He
                        suggested the advisability of dividing up the work of the educating of the
                        various member nations by the members of this group.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Wei stated that it was important that existing bombs be destroyed but
                        that it was more important to destroy the mechanism for making more
                        bombs.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">It was agreed:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That General McNaughton would prepare a draft resolution for
                                submission in the first instance to the United States, United
                                Kingdom, France, China, and Belgium, and then to other members of
                                the group.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That certain members of the Committee would divide up the task of
                                educating other United Nations members, and</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That another meeting would be held in the near future.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>H. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>