<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the Twelfth Meeting of the United States Delegation to the General
                    Assembly, Hotel d’léna, Paris, October 7, 1948</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v01p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d246</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">246</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-10-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="246"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d246">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: US(P)/A/M(Chr)/12</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Twelfth Meeting of the United States Delegation
                        to the General Assembly, Hotel d’léna, Paris, October 7, 1948</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1948-10-07">October 7, 1948</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follow a list of persons (33) present and discussion of various
                    matters.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Developments on Atomic Energy</hi> (Mr.
                    Osborn)</p>
                <p>Mr. Osborn explained that, after six days of debate in Committee 1, the Soviet
                    bloc had been able to keep the situation sufficiently confused so that the
                    majority of the delegates did not correctly understand the issues involved and
                    the various proposals which had been introduced. The debate had started with the
                    introduction by General McNaughton of a resolution approving the reports of the
                    Atomic Energy Commission and stating that its work should be suspended until the
                    USSR agreed to participate on the majority basis.<note n="1" xml:id="d246fn1"
                        >For information regarding the Canadian draft resolution, A/C.1/308, see
                        footnote 2, <ref target="#pg_441">p. 441</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Subsequently, a number of other resolutions had been submitted. Syria had
                    proposed an amendment calling for the conclusion of the convention even though
                    such a convention might not be agreed to by the USSR.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d246fn2">For text of the Syrian amendment to the Canadian
                        resolution, A/C.1/309, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (III/1), <hi
                            rend="italic">First Committee, Annexes</hi>, pp. 4–5.</note> An
                    Australian resolution followed this same general line.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d246fn3">For text of the Australian amendment to the Canadian
                        resolution, A/C.1/313, October 6, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                        (III/1), <hi rend="italic">First Committee, Annexes</hi>, pp. 5–6.</note>
                    Rolin of Belgium had proposed that an agreed resolution could best be worked out
                    in sub-committee, although Mr. Osborn noted that this proposal presupposed that
                    the USSR would agree with the majority, which it had failed to do for the last
                    two years in the Atomic Energy Commission.</p>
                <p>Mr. Vyshinsky had confused the debate further by the introduction of a resolution
                    which would have repudiated all the work that had been done by the Atomic Energy
                    Commission and which would require starting over on the basis of the action of
                    the General Assembly <pb facs="0472" n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/> in 1946, as this
                    action was interpreted by the USSR.<note n="4" xml:id="d246fn4">For text of the
                        Soviet resolution, A/C.1/310, see footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_445">p.
                            445</ref>.</note> Mr. Osborn noted that from the time Mr. Vyshinsky had
                    introduced his proposal, it had become apparent that a majority of the Assembly
                    delegations simply did not understand the problem.</p>
                <p>With one speaker inscribed on the list, the Chairman of the Committee had
                    announced that after this speaker, the debate would be closed and the Committee
                    would proceed to vote. Ambassador Austin, recognizing that the Committee was not
                    ready to vote, had discussed the situation with the Canadian representative, who
                    then asked for an adjournment on the grounds that he wished to modify his
                    original proposal. This was the situations of last night.</p>
                <p>During the evening, members of the Delegation, including Ambassador Austin and
                    Mr. Osborn, had met with the British, French, Belgians and Canadians. Mr. Osborn
                    said that Rolin, McNeil and Parodi had argued insistently that the temper of the
                    Assembly required the appointment of a sub-committee to go into the various
                    atomic energy proposals. Although Ambassador Austin had pointed out the
                    difficulties which such a procedure would raise (in particular, having to debate
                    the Vyshinsky resolution), the others had still insisted on a drafting
                    sub-committee, and he reluctantly agreed. Mr. Osborn pointed out that with this
                    adverse sentiment it was doubtful whether, if the United States had pushed for
                    an immediate vote, it could have obtained a significant majority in favor of its
                    position.</p>
                <p>After it was agreed to constitute a sub-committee, Mr. McNeil promised to arrange
                    for New Zealand to introduce the amendment previously discussed, asking the
                    sponsoring powers to consult and to report the results of their consultations to
                    the next meeting of the Assembly. After this resolution was introduced, the
                    Canadians would accept the idea of a drafting committee. Mr. Osborn thought that
                    it was very likely that the drafting committee would report on the Canadian
                    resolution, plus the amendment introduced by New Zealand, together with a
                    minority proposal by the USSR. Under these circumstances, he believed there
                    would be no question that the United States would obtain a substantial majority
                    for its position.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Austin emphasized that the present situation was one which, if not
                    handled carefully, could result in the acceptance of the Syrian amendment to
                    proceed to the drafting of a convention. This was true because the chairman of
                    the Committee had announced that he would put the amendments to the vote in the
                    order in which they had been submitted. In fact, Ambassador Austin believed that
                    unless the sub-committee were successful, the Committee would still approve the
                    Syrian amendment. He felt the Canadian resolution as amended <pb facs="0473"
                        n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/> would hold out great promise to the other
                    delegations since it contemplated unanimity, and, if the Assembly strongly
                    backed the idea of further consultations, there was a chance agreement might be
                    reached. In other words, the events of the last six days’ debate had brought the
                    United Nations to a parting of the ways, and if he had not gone along with the
                    views of the others last night, the United States position would have been
                    severely beaten on the vote.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Austin did not think a sub-committee was necessary, but hoped that its
                    work might make the other members of the United Nations understand the actual
                    situation among the five great powers. He hoped that the sub-committee would
                    serve as a sort of solvent in this increasingly difficult situation. The
                    Secretary asked for other comments and himself pointed out that this problem
                    must be considered in relation to the total present situation regarding the
                    maintenance of international peace.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of other subjects.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
