<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Draft Resolution Submitted by the United States to
                        Subcommittee 12 of the First Committee of the General Assembly
                    The United States introduced this proposal at the
                        5th Meeting of Subcommittee 12, October 21. It was withdrawn by the United
                        States Delegation at the 7th Meeting, October 25, 10:30 a. m., in favor of a
                        Belgian amendment (to French draft resolution A/C.1/325) A/C.1/SC.12/2; for texts of the operative portions of
                        the French and Belgian proposals, see footnote 1, p.
                            469. A/C.1/SC.12/2, subsequently
                        amended, was adopted by the Subcommittee at its 8th Meeting, October 25, 3
                        p. m., by a vote of 7 (Belgium, Brazil, China, France, Lebanon, United
                        Kingdom, United States) to 2 (Poland and the Soviet Union), with Australia
                        abstaining and El Salvador absent. The operative portion of the version
                        adopted varied only slightly from that of A/C.1/SC.12/2 except for the addition of a final paragraph which read
                        as follows: “[The General Assembly] Invites all nations in the Commission
                        for Conventional Armaments to co-operate to the utmost of their power in the
                        attainment of the above-mentioned objectives.” Also at the 8th Meeting,
                            the Subcommittee rejected a Soviet proposal consisting of document A/658
                            (for text, see telegram Delga 117,
                            September 25, p. 431) modified by Soviet
                            amendment A/C.1/SC.12/3, which revised
                            the final paragraph to read as follows: “The General Assembly recommends
                            for the purpose of the supervision of and control over the
                            implementation of the measures for the reduction of armaments and armed
                            forces and for the prohibition of atomic weapons the establishment
                            within the framework of the Security Council of an international control
                            body, to which full official data on the state of the armaments and
                            armed forces of the permanent Members of the Security Council—United
                            States of America, United Kingdom, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics,
                            France and China—must be submitted.” The vote on the Soviet proposal was
                            2 in favor (Poland and Soviet Union), 6 against (Belgium, Brazil, China,
                            France, United Kingdom, United States), Australia and Lebanon
                            abstaining, and El Salvador absent.
                        These results and the texts voted upon were recorded in the report of the
                            Subcommittee, A/C.1/356/Rev. 1, November 2; for text, see GA (III/1), First
                                Committee, Annexes, pp. 34–39.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v01p1</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d266</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">266</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="266" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d266">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: A/C.1/<gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.12/1</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Resolution Submitted by the United States to
                        Subcommittee 12 of the First Committee of the General Assembly</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d266fn1">The United States introduced this proposal at the
                        5th Meeting of Subcommittee 12, October 21. It was withdrawn by the United
                        States Delegation at the 7th Meeting, October 25, 10:30 a. m., in favor of a
                        Belgian amendment (to French draft resolution A/C.1/325) A/C.1/<gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.12/2; for texts of the operative portions of
                        the French and Belgian proposals, see footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_469">p.
                            469</ref>. A/C.1/<gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.12/2, subsequently
                        amended, was adopted by the Subcommittee at its 8th Meeting, October 25, 3
                        p. m., by a vote of 7 (Belgium, Brazil, China, France, Lebanon, United
                        Kingdom, United States) to 2 (Poland and the Soviet Union), with Australia
                        abstaining and El Salvador absent. The operative portion of the version
                        adopted varied only slightly from that of A/C.1/<gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.12/2 except for the addition of a final paragraph which read
                        as follows: “[The General Assembly] Invites all nations in the Commission
                        for Conventional Armaments to co-operate to the utmost of their power in the
                        attainment of the above-mentioned objectives.” <p>Also at the 8th Meeting,
                            the Subcommittee rejected a Soviet proposal consisting of document A/658
                            (for text, see telegram <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 117,
                            September 25, <ref target="#pg_431">p. 431</ref>) modified by Soviet
                            amendment A/C.1/<gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.12/3, which revised
                            the final paragraph to read as follows: “The General Assembly recommends
                            for the purpose of the supervision of and control over the
                            implementation of the measures for the reduction of armaments and armed
                            forces and for the prohibition of atomic weapons the establishment
                            within the framework of the Security Council of an international control
                            body, to which full official data on the state of the armaments and
                            armed forces of the permanent Members of the Security Council—United
                            States of America, United Kingdom, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics,
                            France and China—must be submitted.” The vote on the Soviet proposal was
                            2 in favor (Poland and Soviet Union), 6 against (Belgium, Brazil, China,
                            France, United Kingdom, United States), Australia and Lebanon
                            abstaining, and El Salvador absent.</p>
                        <p>These results and the texts voted upon were recorded in the report of the
                            Subcommittee, A/C.1/356/Rev. 1, November 2; for text, see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (III/1), <hi rend="italic">First
                                Committee, Annexes</hi>, pp. 34–39.</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-21">October 21,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Prohibition of the Atomic Weapon and the Reduction by One-third of the Armaments
                    and Armed Forces of the Permanent Members of the Security Council: Proposed
                    Amendments to French Draft Resolution (A/C.1/325)</p>
                <p>[Here follows a description of the modifications proposed by the United
                    States.]</p>
                <p>The French draft resolution so amended would read:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The General Assembly</hi>,</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Considering</hi> that the maintenance of peace and the
                    adoption of measures for the prevention of all recourse to force are the
                    essential aims that the peoples of the United Nations are resolved to
                    pursue;</p>
                <pb facs="0513" n="493" xml:id="pg_493"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Desiring</hi> to establish relations of confident
                    collaboration between the States within the framework of the Charter and to make
                    possible a general reduction of armaments in order that humanity may in future
                    be spared the horrors of war and that the peoples may not be overwhelmed by the
                    continually increasing burden of military expenditure;</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Recalling</hi> its resolution of 14 December 1946;<note n="2" xml:id="d266fn2">For text, see <ref target="frus1946v01#pg_1099">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 1099</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Declares</hi> that the regulation of armaments is a
                    fundamental aim of the United Nations;</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Affirms</hi> that this aim can only be attained in an
                    atmosphere of real and lasting improvement in international relations, which
                    improvement will permit the organization of peace in an atmosphere of renewed
                    confidence;</p>
                <p>Likwise <hi rend="italic">affirms</hi> that this aim cannot be achieved unless
                    States sincerely and honestly accept the stocktaking, publicity and control
                    measures calculated to lay the foundations for a general limitation of armaments
                    and to guarantee its strict implementation, and unless they, therefore, give the
                    indispensable undertakings;</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Believing</hi> that international confidence cannot be
                    restored without the co-operation of all States in a system of security,
                    including the international control of atomic energy;</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The General Assembly</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommends</hi> the Security Council: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>To promote the international regulation of conventional armaments and
                            armed forces with a view to the progressive reduction of the world total
                            of conventional armaments and armed forces as soon as conditions of
                            international security permit; and emphasizes the particular
                            responsibility of the five permanent members of the Security Council in
                            this matter.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>To develop through the Commission for Conventional Armaments, as a
                            stage in its system of safeguards, a plan for the receipt, verification
                            and publication by an international control agency of the information on
                            armaments necessary to determining the reductions to be required of each
                            nation.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>To request the Commission for Conventional Armaments to continue
                            without delay its work in accordance with the plan approved by the
                            Security Council at its 152nd session while seeking specially the means
                            for presenting an acceptable plan embodying the measures herein
                            proposed.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
