<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-12-09T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1947-12-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="40" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d40">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>An important area of agreement was reached between the United States and
                            the United Nations in March 1948 with the conclusion of the negotiation
                            providing for the financing of the building and furnishing of the
                            permanent United Nations headquarters facilities in New York City. The
                            essential provision was the granting of an interest-free loan of
                            $65,000,000 by the United States to the United Nations, to be repaid in
                            annual installments over a period of thirty years extending from 1951 to
                            1982.</p>
                        <p>Agreement as to broad principles and many details had been reached by
                            this Government and the United Nations by the end of 1947 (see <ref target="frus1947v01#pg_75">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1947, volume I, page
                                75</ref>; and final details were worked out early in 1948. On March
                            23, 1948 the agreement was signed by Ambassador Warren R. Austin, United
                            States Representative at the United Nations, and Mr. Trygve Lie,
                            Secretary-General of the United Nations, subject to the approval of the
                            United States Congress. For text, see 62 Stat. (pt. 3) 3725 and Treaties
                            and Other International Acts Series (<gloss target="#t_TIAS1">TIAS</gloss>) No. 1899.</p>
                        <p>On April 7, 1948 the Agreement was transmitted by President Truman to the
                            Congress, with a strong message asking for approval. Bills were
                            introduced separately in the two Houses, and the Senate took favorable
                            action on May 7 (S.J. 212). But action in the House of Representatives
                            became snarled in the omnibus bill (<gloss target="#t_HR1">H.R.</gloss>
                            6802). The <pb facs="0108" n="88" xml:id="pg_88"/> House finally on
                            August 5 accepted the Senate bill, S.J. 212, in the reconvened session
                            of the Congress which met on July 26. On approval by the President on
                            August 11 this legislation became Public Law 903; for text of the joint
                            resolution with provisions of the agreement, see 62 Stat. 1286.</p>
                        <p>The United States Administration had been most anxious that the loan
                            agreement receive approval before the Congress adjourned; and this was
                            one of three actions specifically requested by President Truman in his
                            message to the reconvened session on July 27; for text of the
                            President’s Message, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, August 8, 1948, page 185. On the occasion of his
                            approval on August 11, President Truman issued a statement expressing
                            his deep gratification that the Congress had completed action “on this
                            important measure”, declaring that “The loan demonstrates our faith in
                            the future of the United Nations . . . . it is another example of the
                            solidarity of the American people in behalf of our national policy of
                            strengthening the United Nations and the cause of world peace and
                            security for which it stands.” (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, August 22,
                            1948, page 235)</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>