<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Colonel Henry A. Byroade to
                        General Marshall</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d136</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">136</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="radio" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385" lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="136" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d136">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Henry A. Byroade</persName> to
                        General <persName type="to">Marshall</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-16">16 January 1945
                                [<hi rend="italic">1946</hi>]</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Re 53.<note n="86" xml:id="d136fn86">Not found in Department files.</note>
                    Conference as explained in my message January 14 was necessary as neither party
                    yet had representatives to send. Once people become available I will train them
                    to limit by taking decisive action without resorting to conference and
                    discussion.</p>
                <p>Up to now Communist Party is represented by General Yeh, his aide, and a few
                    radio mechanics. Central Government is in little better <pb facs="0372" n="360" xml:id="pg_360"/> shape, nominating late last night a Mrir Ho Bo TCIR
                    [garble] representative to Chihfeng.</p>
                <p>Yet, cannot afford to get off on wrong foot by sending Americans only to the
                    trouble spots. Have had my planes and personnel standing by all day to proceed
                    with team to Kalgan. General Yeh insisted that we not take off until he could
                    establish radio contact and clear our entrance. We decided to go anyway but
                    could not make it due to weather.</p>
                <p>Communists will have no qualified representatives here until we get into Kalgan
                    and bring their personnel out. His staff is scattered all over North China. I
                    began pressing him in Chungking for locations and members so I could set up
                    aircraft to bring them to Peiping. Have asked him every day since but still do
                    not have data.</p>
                <p>Do not feel above is Yeh’s fault. He has not succeeded in getting his radio
                    station here in operation as yet and is out of contact with his headquarters. He
                    informed me in Chungking that they could provide entire radio equipment for main
                    station here. I ordered complete set for him anyway after arrival here but this
                    equipment we desire had to get from Pacific and it has not yet arrived. He hopes
                    to get his radio in operation tonight.</p>
                <p>Reconnaissance plane reported yesterday as lost has been located on Chihfeng
                    airfield. We contacted this plane on ground and were informed that pilot and
                    crew were being prevented from take-off by Russian major in charge. This proves
                    Russians still in Chihfeng but incident not alarming as pilot was not armed with
                    proper identification and orders. Russian major requests we obtain clearances
                    for pilot to leave with Red Army headquarters in Chan Chun [<hi rend="italic">Changchun</hi>,] Manchuria. Do not believe this necessary as leaflets were
                    dropped there this morning and next plane will carry representatives of all
                    three parties. If they intern National Government and Communist representatives
                    then we will have story.</p>
                <p>General Yeh insists he does not have man to go to Chihfeng until we bring in some
                    of his personnel from Kalgan. This we will do soon as weather permits. Prospects
                    favorable for tomorrow and team will proceed Chihfeng next day via General Tu
                    li-ming’s headquarters in Chinchow.</p>
                <p>Being unable to put teams in field as yet we are sending Marine planes as well as
                    our own to 15 trouble areas in morning with locally prepared leaflets.</p>
                <p>Central Government here has only communications as yet to field commanders.
                    Consequently [comments?] are received all day long from them of Communists
                    violations of orders. Am aware that in Chungking both sides are complaining.
                    Most complaints have been <pb facs="0373" n="361" xml:id="pg_361"/> dated
                    January 14 or before. I am convinced that both sides have been jockeying for
                    final positions in last two days. Believe also that while main headquarters on
                    both sides, as well as commissioners here, may be sincere, that local commanders
                    may be making final pushes on their own authority. If this suspicion correct we
                    may expect decrease of incidents soon.</p>
                <p>Appreciate your concern. The Americans are ready. Teams will depart at earliest
                    moment Chinese can accompany. In meantime leaflet battle and orders to
                    commanders who are in radio contact with Central Government here are all that is
                    at our disposal. Know fully my duty to send out teams to critical areas.<note n="87" xml:id="d136fn87">The gist of this message was communicated on
                        January 16 by Colonel Caughey to General Chou En-lai.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
