<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Briefing of Committee of Three and Commissioners, Thursday,
                        February 28, 1946, 4 p.m.
                    At Peiping, the first stop of the Committee of
                        Three on its North China tour.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d211</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">211</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-02-28T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-02-28T03:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-28T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-28T03:00:00-05:00" n="211" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d211">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Briefing of Committee of Three and Commissioners, Thursday,
                        February 28, 1946, 4 p.m.</hi>
                    <note n="59" xml:id="d211fn59">At Peiping, the first stop of the Committee of
                        Three on its North China tour.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Peiping</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-02-28T16:00:00+08:00">February 28, 1946, 4 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>Mr. Robertson, United States Commissioner, opened the meeting with the following
                    statement:</p>
                <p>“My Chinese colleagues have asked that I act as spokesman in welcoming the
                    members of the Three-Man Committee to Executive Headquarters, which was born of
                    their agreements in Chungking. I take <pb facs="0466" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                    great pleasure in doing so. We are not only honored by your presence, but you
                    have come at a particularly opportune time.</p>
                <p>“We have endeavored to implement your agreements in the spirit in which they were
                    made. We have had some measure of success, but there are still trouble spots in
                    the field which are hindering and, if uncorrected, may even thwart the great
                    purposes for which you have labored so faithfully. We feel that your presence
                    here and in the field may lend the influence necessary to straighten out these
                    difficulties.</p>
                <p>“According to our information, the fault is not on one side. Apparently there are
                    officials on both sides who have not yet fully accepted the authority of the
                    Chungking agreements and therefore are not lending their full cooperation.
                    However, I am glad to report to you, General Chang, and to you, General Chou,
                    that we have observed no such spirit among your representatives here. There have
                    been differences of opinion, sometimes sharp differences of opinion, but we
                    Americans have been much impressed by the evident sincerity and earnestness of
                    your representatives in their desire to reach agreements which they consider to
                    be fair and equitable and within the scope of our terms of reference.</p>
                <p>“The courteous, friendly cooperation shown the Americans by General Cheng and
                    General Yeh has extended down throughout their organizations and has made our
                    work with them a very real pleasure.</p>
                <p>“I now present General Byroade, our very able Director of Operations, who, with
                    his chiefs, will brief you on the situation as it now exists. General
                    Byroade.”</p>
                <p>General Byroade said:</p>
                <p>“The Operations Division of this Headquarters has prepared a brief presentation
                    for your Committee. It is our purpose, in this presentation and in other
                    presentations to follow in the field, to be entirely frank in our statements of
                    the accomplishments, difficulties and problems of this Headquarters. In the
                    brief period of time allotted today it will of course only be possible to touch
                    the highlights of the situation in each team area. Full appreciation of the
                    exact situation in those areas can only be obtained after further discussion and
                    after your visits to the field.</p>
                <p>“The first presentation will be made by Colonel Ely, of the Plans and Operations
                    Section. Following Col. Ely, Col. Hill, of the newly organized Railway Control
                    Section, will present in brief the problems connected with railways. The last
                    speaker will be Col. Perrine, who will present briefly the repatriation
                    situation. Col. Ely.”</p>
                <p>Col. Ely said that he would present briefly the current situation as shown in
                    team reports, and proceeded to do so, as follows:</p>
                <pb facs="0467" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/>
                <p>“Team No. 1 arrived at Chining on the 16th of February. There it has stopped
                    fighting and has been engaged in investigating breaks in the railway and
                    establishing railway communications from Paotou to Fengchen. It is currently
                    engaged in investigating breaks reported west of Chotzushan.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 2 went to Chihfeng on the 17th of January. It has stopped fighting and
                    has made a number of trips in this general area to investigate troop movements.
                    It has found many minor troop movements, but no fighting of any consequence. It
                    has made an agreement on the railway; however this agreement has not been
                    completely implemented as yet. There are still barricades up and still
                    inspection of people moving back and forth along the roads; that condition is
                    improving but has not yet been solved.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 3 is now at Taiyuan, but originally went to Tatung on the 19th of
                    January. While it was at Tatung it made some agreements for opening up food
                    supply into Tatung and communications north and northeast of Tatung. It made
                    agreements for the reopening of the Tatung-Taiyuan railway. On the 3rd of
                    February it moved to Taiyuan and has been concerned primarily with the
                    disarmament census of Japanese and the investigation of certain reports of
                    attacks on the railway. On the 20th of February it was supposed to go to
                    Ch’inhsien, but was unable to get there because a bridge was out on the railway.
                    It returned to Taiyuan on the 25th of February and is now engaged in
                    investigating reports of breaks in this railway and National Government troop
                    concentrations in that area. It is also concerned in raising the reported siege
                    of Chungyang.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 4 went to Hsuchow on the 20th of January. Fighting there has stopped,
                    and the team has made certain basic arrangements for the reopening of the
                    Lunghai Railway and certain mines in this locality. It is currently engaged in
                    food relief for the garrison at Tsaochuang and in removing all blockhouses and
                    other fortifications on the railway south of Hsuchow.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 5 is at Kalgan, having arrived there on the 19th of January. It entered
                    into agreements to open up the Kalgan-Tatung communications and later the
                    Kalgan–Peiping communications. It is now engaged in implementing the
                    Kalgan–Tatung agreements and seems to have made great progress.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 6 has been used for special missions and has just returned from
                    Kueisui, where it was investigating alleged Communist concentrations near that
                    point. In the opinion of the team there were no concentrations of any
                    consequence. It has also assisted Team No. 1 in investigating breaks along the
                    railroad.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 7 went to Tsinan on the 20th of January. It has charge <pb facs="0468" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> also of Teams No. 15 and No. 16. Fighting was
                    stopped. Arrangements for opening up the Tsinan–Tsingtao railway are in progress
                    and for opening mines and railway near Poshan.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 8 has gone to Canton, arriving there on the 20th of January. It has
                    made attempts to get in contact with General Tseng Sen or his representative and
                    has made one field trip with that aim in view. It made this field trip on the
                    20th of February and returned to Canton on the 24th of February. It is
                    continuing to attempt to get in contact with the Communist representatives, but
                    does not believe it can make any progress until General Chang Fa Kuei is
                    authorized to recognize the Communists in that area.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 9 went to Hankow on the 20th of January and is currently engaged in
                    relieving starvation in the general area of Loshan and Kwangshan. Certain
                    special directives have been issued to stabilize the situation where nobody was
                    benefitting by troop movements, but many were very nervous about them.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 10 arrived in Hsinhsiang on the 28th of January. It stopped fighting
                    and succeeded in making certain arrangements to open up the Chiaotso–Hsinhsiang
                    branch of the railway. I believe they have the highway operating and have made
                    some arrangements on mines. The feeling in this area has been high, and there
                    has been considerable hard feeling in the Menghsien-Chiaotso-Hsinhsiang area.
                    Unfortunately the American member of that team was sick, and his replacement,
                    taken from Team No. 6, was unable to reach the area with the team today because
                    of weather. The team had been in Peiping for conference.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 11 went to Chengte on the 31st of January. It has been investigating
                    alleged disturbances in the area of P’ingch’uan, Ling-yuan and Lingnan. The
                    fighting in that area has been stopped, but they found a barricade on the
                    railway at P’ingch’uan. The team returned to Chengte three days ago to
                    investigate reports of further Outbreaks of fighting to the east. Steps are
                    being taken by this Headquarters to allow coal and food to come into Chengte and
                    possibly to open up the railway on the way to Peiping.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 12 went to Shihchiachuang on the 4th of February. It has been engaged
                    in opening up mines in that area. Its principal problem has been to stop local
                    fighting, which, while not on a large scale, is scattered over the whole
                    area.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 13 arrived in Tatung on the 2nd of February. It took over the work of
                    Team No. 3 and has done very good work in opening up communications in that
                    area. It is also attempting to get food into Tatung, but there has been a
                    harvest failure in that area and they are having difficulty in getting food
                    in.</p>
                <pb facs="0469" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                <p>“Team No. 14 arrived at Linfen on the 2nd of February. The fighting in that area
                    was in the vicinity of Houma, but the situation is now stabilized and there has
                    been no fighting since the arrival of the team. There was considerable
                    discussion on the withdrawal of troops and possession of towns and villages. At
                    present the situation is stabilized and there seems to be no chance of fighting
                    breaking out.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 15 went to Tehsien on the 2nd of February. It has been engaged in
                    relieving the siege of that city and in general making economic arrangements in
                    that area for feeding the troops. It has made valuable local agreements and is
                    now trying to work out some sort of money exchange rate to facilitate
                    commerce.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 16 went to Tsinan on the 10th of February and to Taian on the 14th of
                    February. It has been engaged in relieving the food situation in Taian and in
                    keeping the situation stabilized. Due to the shortage of railway teams, it has
                    taken over some railway work there also. It is currently engaged in food
                    distribution.</p>
                <p>“Team No. 17 was organized on the 19th of February. It was sent immediately to
                    Paoting, near the railway, and it investigated some threatened fighting and also
                    stopped the fighting further north on the railway. It was originally organized
                    to operate out of the Peiping area, but it appears it will have to go to some
                    other point. This other point would appear to be Ch’iahsien, although there have
                    been several other places where teams have been requested. The National
                    Government would like one at Yenchow (shown on the map as Tzuyang). The
                    Communist Party would like one at Huaiyin to investigate reported difficulties
                    in southern Kiangsu.</p>
                <p>“Now, Gentlemen, so far I have given you reports from entire teams that can be
                    justified and verified from reports signed by all three parties. Unfortunately
                    it is impossible to get a strong report signed by three persons. Very often the
                    team member—and this applies to both sides—will be a local man of the local unit
                    and he will not wish to sign anything which is contrary to the interests of his
                    own side. On other occasions he will operate under directives from this or other
                    headquarters—I mean, under directives from his own branch of this headquarters,
                    which are not always in accordance with directives from the Headquarters as a
                    whole. In Shantung Province—what I give you now is from American reports—there
                    is a series of cities down the railway which are in various stages of siege:
                    Tehsien, Tsinan, Yenchow and others. Some are under close siege, others much
                    less closely besieged. Various local agreements have been made in regard to
                    these cities and have not always been kept. The general difficulty is that the
                    Communists claim the troops inside the cities are not entitled to various
                    provisions of the Cease-Fire Order. This Headquarters, <pb facs="0470" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/> and, I am sure, the Communist Branch of this Headquarters
                    have attempted to correct that, but it does not always take effect in the
                    field.</p>
                <p>“I have another report which is so new that Captain Young has not seen it, so I
                    must give him a copy to familiarize him with it. It has not yet been presented
                    to the Commissioners because it came in so very recently. It has been typed in
                    English and translated and should be ready for transmission now. However, in
                    order to save time, I am going to cover it. This is a report from Colonel Holly,
                    American member of the team at Taiyuan. He went on a trip to Ch’inhsien, but
                    stopped about 90 li north of Ch’inhsien. Col. Holly writes a comparatively
                    complete report and makes some very serious charges. He states that Gen. Yen
                    Hsi-shan, the National Government Commander, has refused to establish contact
                    with Gen. Liu Po-cheng and has refused to receive Gen. Liu’s liaison officers.
                    He further states that Gen. Yen repeats the orders received from Executive
                    Headquarters to his Field Commanders, but does not issue directives of his own
                    to see that they are carried out. He states that Gen. Yen considers it the
                    team’s duty to make all decisions and issue all the orders for execution of the
                    Cease-Fire Order. He states that Gen. Han Tuan-pei, Army Commander, at the time
                    he interviewed him (which I believe was the 25th), had received no order since
                    Directive No. 2.”<note n="60" xml:id="d211fn60">Executive Headquarters General
                        Directive No. 2, January 20, not printed; see telegram No. 4, January 25,
                        from the Chargé in China, <ref target="#pg_378">p. 378</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In reply to General Marshall’s question, Col. Ely said that it was about a month
                    since Directive No. 2 was issued; January 20 was the official date, but it was
                    hard to say just when it was actually received in the field. Col. Ely then
                    continued:</p>
                <p>“Col. Holly further states that the places he visited were known ahead of time
                    and things were always dressed up so that he could neither see anything nor
                    could he get reliable information.</p>
                <p>“Col. Holly’s charges against the Communist Party are substantially as follows:
                        (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) that Gen. Lee Ta was to meet the team in the
                    Ch’inhsien area and would not come to the Funshuiling area where the team had
                    been set up; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) that the Communist Party is still
                    tearing up the railway tracks and tore them up while Col. Holly was there; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) that in his opinion the Communist Party representative
                    may be evading contact with the field team—this refers not to the regular team
                    representative, but to a special representative for the Ch’inhsien area.</p>
                <p>“Col. Holly sees no possibility of any satisfactory solution and no object in
                    sending a team to Ch’inhsien. He considers this worthwhile only if Executive
                    Headquarters—to use a colloquialism—“cracks down” on the field commanders and
                    makes them issue directives clear down to the lowest unit and see that those
                    directives are carried out. <pb facs="0471" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"/> He
                    believes also that the commanders should be forced to contact each other and
                    maintain liaison.”</p>
                <p>Col. Ely asked whether there were any questions on his part of the presentation;
                    there were none, and General Byroade introduced Col. Hill.</p>
                <p>Col. Hill made the following statement:</p>
                <p>“The Railway Control Section has assumed jurisdiction over all lines of
                    communication in North and Central China. Of these, of course, the railways are
                    the first and pressing consideration. There are a total of approximately 1,000
                    kilometers of railroad which require reconstruction or repair within the North
                    and Central China area. Given free rein it would be possible to have an
                    effective railway net within three months. However, a complete and thorough job
                    of reconstruction will require perhaps 18 months.</p>
                <p>“The Chiefs of the Railway Control Section have agreed to assign Priority 1 to
                    the Tientsin-Pukou road. On this road there are a total of 322 kilometers which
                    require repair, in four different sections. The sections marked in red on the
                    map are those which are non-operative, and those in blue are operative. Our
                    Field Team No. 18 was dispatched to Potou on the 18th of February. That team
                    reports a great deal of difficulty encountered in the past ten days. For one
                    thing, the National Government member of the team was almost lynched in a little
                    town just south of Potou. On the other hand, the Communist Party member has
                    resigned from the team and returned to Peiping, refusing to serve with the team.
                    In spite of these difficulties, the American member reports he has established
                    contact with the local commanders. They have agreed to permit extension of
                    telephone lines as far as Potou, and he believes he may have further success.
                    That last report was received from the team this morning. The Combined Chiefs of
                    Section agree that there should be set up immediately field teams for these
                    three points (Yucheng, Taian, Hsuchow). Departure of those teams has been
                    delayed due to the fact that we have been unable to secure United States members
                    for the teams.</p>
                <p>“Second priority has been assigned to the Tsinan–Tsingtao railway. On that road
                    there are a total of approximately 100 kilometers of breaks in three different,
                    short localities. Our field team No. 21 was dispatched to Kaomi, at the eastern
                    extremity of these breaks, on 22 February. Although there are men and materials
                    available for the repair, the field team has been unable to accomplish any
                    results yet, due to the fact that the Communist Party member of that team has
                    not reported. Immediate repair of that road is very important due to the
                    repatriation problem, which will be explained in a few moments.</p>
                <pb facs="0472" n="460" xml:id="pg_460"/>
                <p>“Third priority is assigned to both sides of the Lunghai Railway, particularly
                    from Hsuchow east, I have not shown the total amount of distance of breaks in
                    that road, because repairs are now going on just east of Hsuchow, and I don’t
                    know how far that repair has gone. The problem at that point has been handled up
                    to now by our Cease-Fire Field Team No. 4. This field team has reported
                    considerable difficulty due to disagreement between National Government and
                    Communist members, but those disagreements were handled by direct order from
                    this Headquarters day before yesterday. A report received this morning states
                    that work is now progressing satisfactorily on the road north of Hsuchow, or
                    first priority road, and east of Hsuchow on the Lunghai railway. No field team
                    from the Railway Control Section has been dispatched there for various reasons,
                    among which is the fact that the American member of Field Team No. 4 indicates
                    he believes he can handle the situation.</p>
                <p>“Fourth priority has been assigned to the Peiping–Suiyuan railway. On this
                    railway there is a small break of 23 kilometers between Peiping and Kalgan.
                    There are also breaks to the northeast and northwest of Tatung, which are now in
                    process of repair. Our Field Team No. 20 was sent to Nankou on the 25th of
                    February. The team reports they have been unable to arrive at any agreement for
                    the reconstruction of this break due to the fact that the Communist member of
                    the team has not reported. The Communist member of the party, however, left
                    Peiping this morning to join the team at Nankou.</p>
                <p>“Fifth priority has been assigned to the trunk line from Peiping to Hankow. On
                    this line there is one very serious break 190 kilometers long where the railway
                    has been almost completely destroyed. Materials and men are available at each
                    end of this break to effect repairs. Our Field Team No. 19 was sent to Anyang,
                    at the south end of the break, on February 20. I have not received a report from
                    this team for several days, and I am not sure what the situation is. The last
                    report, received about three days ago, states they were unable to begin repairs.
                    The north end of the break is being handled by Field Team No. 12. A report from
                    that team received this morning says that they are unable to effect repairs on
                    the north end because the Communist member of that team has not received
                    instructions from his higher headquarters.</p>
                <p>“Other railways on which a lower priority has been assigned are: Priority 6,
                    Tungpu Railway; Priority 7, Chengtai Railway; Priority 8, Pingch’en Railway.</p>
                <p>“The chief difficulties which the Railway Control Section has encountered so far
                    are: first, that the National Government personnel either fail or refuse to
                    destroy military works along the lines of communication; <pb facs="0473" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/> the second big problem is the fact that Communist Party
                    personnel frequently fail or refuse to obey orders issued by this
                    Headquarters.</p>
                <p>“Are there any questions?”</p>
                <p>General Marshall inquired how many more American officers were needed by the
                    Railway Control Section. Colonel Hill replied that he needed four immediately,
                    and should have five altogether—three for the field teams mentioned, one for
                    Headquarters, and one other for the proposed Team No. 25. General Marshall asked
                    whether these officers had to be engineers; Colonel Hill said it made no
                    difference whether they were or not, so long as they had sufficient rank—that
                    is, Lieutenant Colonel or higher.</p>
                <p>Gen. Byroade then introduced Col. Perrine.</p>
                <p>Col. Perrine presented a chart showing figures on Japanese to be repatriated, as
                    follows: <table cols="4" rows="6">
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="3">“Total Japanese in North and Central China</cell>
                            <cell role="num">388,400</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell cols="2">“To be shipped from following ports:</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 3em">Shanghai</cell>
                            <cell role="num">60,000</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 3em">Laoyao</cell>
                            <cell role="num">20,000</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 3em">Tsingtao</cell>
                            <cell role="num">72,800</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 3em">Tangku</cell>
                            <cell role="num">235,600</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">He then made the following statement:</p>
                <p>“An overall plan for repatriation of the Japanese was agreed upon by the Supreme
                    Commander Allied Powers, Japan, and United States Forces in China.
                    Responsibility for moving the Japanese through the areas of conflict in China
                    was assigned to the Executive Headquarters under the agreement for cessation of
                    hostilities as signed by the Committee of Three in Chungking. On February 14 in
                    Peiping, at the direction of the Commanding Officer, Executive Headquarters, a
                    meeting was held and it was decided that the responsibility for the moving of
                    Japanese repatriates to ports of embarkation would be the responsibility of
                    Executive Headquarters. At the ports of embarkation the Navy and the Marine
                    Corps would assume responsibility. The National Government and Communist Party
                    Commissioners in the Executive Headquarters have agreed that they will not
                    interfere in any way and will assist in the movements of Japanese repatriates to
                    meet the shipping schedules at the ports. A large number of Japanese in some
                    areas are creating food and coal problems in addition to those already existing
                    in those areas. In other areas they are causing disagreements between the local
                    troop commanders. Therefore it is of extreme importance that the Japanese
                    repatriates be moved at the earliest possible time.</p>
                <pb facs="0474" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/>
                <p>“The total Japanese in North and Central China to be repatriated are 388,400.
                    They will move through the following ports: Shanghai, Laoyao, Tsingtao, and
                    Tangku.</p>
                <p>“Those located in Honan Province and west of the railway break at Yunho will be
                    shipped through the port of Shanghai.</p>
                <p>“Those east of the break of the Lunghai railway will be shipped through
                    Laoyao.</p>
                <p>“The 72,800 located in the Tsinan-Tsingtao area will be shipped through the port
                    of Tsingtao. As explained by Col. Hill, there are several breaks in this
                    railway, and it requires the establishment of camps one day’s march apart in
                    this area. These camps are not completely established, but the repatriates are
                    moving over this line at the present time.</p>
                <p>“Repatriates located in the Peiping-Taiyuan-Tatung areas will be moved out
                    through the port of Tangku. To do this it is necessary to establish a camp at
                    Shihchiachuang, because this part of the railway is operating with a different
                    type of rolling stock from the rest of the line.</p>
                <p>“The last report for the ten day period ending 24 February showed that we have
                    shipped out through Tangku 11,710 Japanese during the ten day period. The same
                    report indicates that 10,075 have been shipped out through Tsingtao.</p>
                <p>“Are there any questions?”</p>
                <p>General Marshall asked what were the last reports on repatriation through
                    Shanghai. Col. Perrine replied that reports from Shanghai were not furnished
                    this Headquarters.</p>
                <p>General Marshall asked whether the figures referred to soldiers only. Col.
                    Perrine said they covered both civil and military.</p>
                <p>General Byroade then stated: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Gentlemen. That concludes the presentation. The combined staffs of this
                            Headquarters are now assembled in an auditorium a short walking distance
                            from here, just opposite the main gate of this compound. They are of
                            course most eager to have the pleasure of being presented to the members
                            of the Committee of Three. If it is agreeable to you, therefore, we will
                            now walk over to the auditorium. On the stage there are chairs for the
                            Committee of Three and the three Commissioners. The remainder of the
                            personnel in this room should take seats in the front rows of the
                            auditorium. I will there introduce you to the staff and request each of
                            the members of the Committee of Three to say a few words to the
                            personnel of the staff.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned to the auditorium.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
