<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Notes on Meeting of Conference of Three (Meeting No. 5)—General Marshall,
                        General Chang Chun, Central Government Representative, and General Chou
                        En-lai, Communist Party Representative—at General Marshall’s Residence,
                        Chungking, January 10, 1946, 8:15 a.m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d22</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">22</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-01-09T20:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-09T20:15:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-09T20:15:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-09T20:15:00-05:00" n="22" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d22">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Notes on Meeting of Conference of Three</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Meeting No. 5</hi>)—<hi rend="italic">General Marshall,
                        General Chang Chun, Central Government Representative, and General Chou
                        En-lai, Communist Party Representative—at General Marshall’s Residence,
                        Chungking, January 10, 1946, 8:15 a.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Chungking</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-10T08:15:00+07:00">January 10, 1946, 8:15 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>M[<hi rend="smallcaps">arshall</hi>]: If agreeable to you gentlemen the meeting
                    will come to order. Last night I had a talk with the Generalissimo and he
                    generously agreed to the issuance of the order for the cessation of hostilities
                    without reference to Chihfeng and Tolun.</p>
                <pb facs="0117" n="105" xml:id="pg_105"/>
                <p>G[<hi rend="smallcaps">eneral Chang</hi>]: After I had reported to the
                    Generalissimo he expressed the hope that we could continue our discussions,
                    conclude our discussions, so that the order for the cessation of hostilities
                    could be issued at the earliest possible time. Therefore, we would not at this
                    junction press for an immediate solution of the question of Chihfeng and Tolun
                    which would be a part of the problems relating to Jehol and Chahar. The
                    Generalissimo has full confidence in General Marshall and wishes to place these
                    problems into the hands of General Marshall for a just and equitable
                    solution.</p>
                <p>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">hou</hi>]: I feel very gratified to hear the statement
                    made by General Marshall and Governor Chang. I have full confidence that the
                    Generalissimo is eager to have this order published without delay due to
                    Chihfeng and Tolun.</p>
                <p>M: I appreciate very much the statement the Governor has made quoting the
                    Generalissimo regarding me personally and I appreciate very much General Chou’s
                    references to me personally. I assure you, gentlemen, that my purpose to the
                    best of my mental equipment is directed solely to an effort to help as much as
                    possible in solving a very complex problem. However, with your permission I will
                    not refer to the problem of Chihfeng and Tolun until after we complete the small
                    details that remain to be understood. Therefore, if that is agreeable, I would
                    like to go over finally the statement of exceptions and understandings. The
                    first paragraph reads: “It is understood and herewith reentered as a matter of
                    record to the minutes of these conferences that the cessation of hostilities as
                    now agreed upon was agreed upon with the understanding that the following should
                    be included within the formal minutes of the meeting.</p>
                <p>1. Paragraph <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, cessation of hostilities order does not
                    prejudice military movements south of the Yangtze River for the continued
                    execution of the plan of military reorganization of the National Government.” I
                    am assuming, gentlemen, if there is any difference you will interrupt and raise
                    the issue.</p>
                <p>“Paragraph 2. Paragraph <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, cessation of hostilities order
                    does not prejudice military movements of forces of the National Army into or
                    within Manchuria or toward ports in China for embarkation for Manchuria which
                    are for the purpose of restoring Chinese sovereignty.” That is the first time
                        that.…<note n="62" xml:id="d22fn62">Points appear in the original.</note>
                </p>
                <p>G: The Governor was referring to the opinion he expressed before that it seems
                    desirable to use the original wording of this paragraph without referring to the
                    method of transporting troops. He would like to know whether the word “ports”
                    includes all ports in China. Now at certain times of the year Hulutao may not
                    become navigable and other ports can not be made available for immediate use by
                    the <pb facs="0118" n="106" xml:id="pg_106"/> Chinese troops, it would seem
                    difficult for the Government to use certain ports that could be used, but does
                    the word “ports” refer to any port in China. For instance, Chinwangtao?</p>
                <p>M: My recollection of the previous discussion was that Chinwangtao was
                    specifically mentioned by me as an example of where a port would be available
                    for use even though within China in the event that ports in Manchuria were not
                    available due to being frozen. However, no reference was made by me to any other
                    port than Chinwangtao, as I understood that did not freeze up. If Chinwangtao
                    should freeze up, an issue would be raised regarding some other port, but I
                    should think that could be settled by agreement. General Chou?</p>
                <p>C: If Governor Chang thinks that the wording here is too rigid and entails
                    difficulties, General Chou suggests that this phrase, “toward ports in China for
                    embarkation to Manchuria”, be stricken out so that we will only have “into or
                    within Manchuria”. General Chou thinks that he can agree with that providing it
                    is stipulated in paragraph 5 that reports have to be sent daily to the executive
                    headquarters and under this condition if Government wishes to move troops to
                    Manchuria through Communist territories then they should first make a report to
                    executive headquarters and have it talked over there so there will be no
                    difficulty for their transit.</p>
                <p>M: Governor, would this be acceptable in its present form, or towards ports in
                    China for Manchuria if it was understood and agreed to by General Chou that
                    Chinwangtao would be available in the event that Hulutao was unavailable. Would
                    that be all right?</p>
                <p>G: The Governor accepts the suggestion made by General Chou that this phrase be
                    stricken out entirely.</p>
                <p>M: My understanding of that suggestion of General Chou that that phrase be
                    stricken out involves an interpretation of the proposed paragraph 4. That
                    proposed paragraph 4 provides for a daily report. As now written it does not
                    involve an agreement. Is that understood by General Chou.</p>
                <p>C: General Chou understood that in paragraph 4 only the question of reports is
                    involved, but if the National Army are to pass through Communist territories
                    like in Jehol then he understands that of course the Government would first
                    discuss with the Communist representative.</p>
                <p>M: I also understand. As I understand it the words, “or towards ports in China
                    for Manchuria” will be stricken out. Is that correct?</p>
                <p>G: Yes.</p>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: So ordered. The next exception now labelled paragraph 3 reads lines of
                    communications mentioned in paragraph <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, cease
                    hostilities, includes post communications. The fourth paragraph which <pb facs="0119" n="107" xml:id="pg_107"/> has not been approved reads as
                    follows: “It is further agreed that movements of forces of the National Army
                    under the foregoing stipulations should be reported daily to the executive
                    headquarters.” Is that acceptable, General Chou?</p>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: Is that acceptable, Governor Chang?</p>
                <p>G: The Generalissimo has just telephoned to us to say that there are certain
                    expressions or words in the translation of the cessation order which should be
                    improved and he is having a new draft being sent to us, rather a corrected
                    draft.</p>
                <p>M: We will have to wait until we [have] received that. The American is
                    acceptable.</p>
                <p>G: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: But the Chinese translation is in doubt.</p>
                <p>C: General Chou is waiting for the Chinese translation.</p>
                <p>M: I am now authorized as I understand it to include these special minutes as an
                    accepted document.</p>
                <p>G: Yes.</p>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: Agreed.</p>
                <p>M: With your permission then, Gentlemen, I will now turn to the actual order for
                    the cessation of hostilities. The first paragraph of the document is a
                    recommendation from this group to the Generalissimo and to Chairman Mao
                    Tse-tung. May I understand that the two representatives are authorized to state
                    for their chiefs that the body of the order as previously approved by them, the
                    representatives, is, acceptable?</p>
                <p>G: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: Is that correct, General Chou? (Discussion between General Chou and General
                    Chang.) Will you translate that, please?</p>
                <p>C: General Chou has asked Yenan for approval of this order, and he now gets word
                    from Yenan that Yenan has one more suggestion. First, that Yenan ratifies this
                    draft and, secondly, Yenan suggested that the words “Chinese Communist troops”
                    be changed to “Chinese Communist-led troops,” because there are certain units
                    which are not Communist troops but they are led by the Communists.</p>
                <p>M: Are there any objections to that?</p>
                <p>G: No objection.</p>
                <p>C: In all places “Communist troops” should be changed into “Communist-led
                    troops.”</p>
                <p>M: Is that acceptable?</p>
                <p>G: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: It is so ordered. Then it is agreed that this document, with <pb facs="0120" n="108" xml:id="pg_108"/> that alteration, is accepted by the Generalissimo
                    and by Mao Tse-tung. Is that correct?</p>
                <p>G: The Governor is not in a position to say definitely until we have received the
                    note from the Generalissimo which is on its way.</p>
                <p>M: Presumably that note refers to translations?</p>
                <p>G: We are not too sure about that.</p>
                <p>M: Then we will have to delay the formal acceptance of this document until the
                    Governor has heard from the Generalissimo. Meanwhile, it would seem—is the
                    Governor getting lost in papers?</p>
                <p>B: General Chou, we have “Communist Armies” in the papers. I believe you said
                    “Communist-led troops.” Would you rather substitute “troops” for “armies”?</p>
                <p>C: It is the same in Chinese. There is no question in Chinese.</p>
                <p>M: “Troops” and “Armies” are the same?</p>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: Then every company commander is an army commander? I will submit for your
                    consideration, pending the formal acceptance of the order, a draft of a proposed
                    press release. The document appears long, but most of it is a quotation. The
                    first paragraph reads: “We, General Chang Chun, Representative of the National
                    Government, and General Chou En-lai, Representative of the Chinese Communist
                    Party, have recommended to Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek and Chairman Mao
                    Tse-tung and have been authorized by them to announce that the following order
                    has been issued to all units, regular, militia, irregular and guerrilla, of the
                    National Armies of the Republic of China and of the Communist-led troops of the
                    Republic of China:” Then there follows a quotation of the order. Further it
                    states, on page two, at the bottom of page one, “As a matter of public interest
                    we are further authorized to announce that the following stipulations regarding
                    the above Cessation of Hostilities Order were agreed upon and made a matter of
                    record in the minutes of the conferences.” There then follows the exceptions. In
                    the middle of page two, another paragraph appears: “We are also authorized to
                    announce that the agreements, recommendations, and directives of the Executive
                    Headquarters will deal only with the immediate problems raised by the cessation
                    of hostilities and will not interfere with or impair the parties’ rights and
                    authority to negotiate in the future, political agreements, or make
                    recommendations covering the reorganization, integration, or deployment of
                    National Government forces or forces of the Chinese Communist Party.”</p>
                <p>G: General, we should like to pause for just one minute. This paragraph “or make
                    recommendations”—does this phrase follow “will not interfere or make
                    recommendations” or does it follow “the parties’ rights and authority to
                    negotiate”?</p>
                <pb facs="0121" n="109" xml:id="pg_109"/>
                <p>B: The parties’ rights.</p>
                <p>G: “The parties’ rights and authority” to make recommendations?</p>
                <p>M: Do you wish to change it?</p>
                <p>G: I want to be clear on this point.</p>
                <p>B: “The Executive Headquarters will not interfere or will not make
                    recommendations.”</p>
                <p>M: How do you want that in, “or will not make”?</p>
                <p>G: “Or” or “and”? “And.”</p>
                <p>M: “and will make.” All right. I might say that the point has been raised by some
                    of those involved in drafting this that the whole paragraph, commencing “We are
                    also authorized to announce,” well might terminate with, after the word
                    “hostilities” in the third line, the remainder of the paragraph they felt was a
                    matter of course.</p>
                <p>G: You intimate that the rest can be omitted?</p>
                <p>M: The thing is that the rest is implicit. It was put in so there would be no
                    technical misunderstanding, but it might well stop with after the word
                    “hostilities.”</p>
                <p>G: The Governor would propose to take out all the words after “hostilities.”</p>
                <p>M: Is that acceptable to General Chou?</p>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: All will be struck out after the word “hostilities.” A period will go in after
                    “hostilities.” The next paragraph reads: “American participation within the
                    Headquarters will be for the purpose of assisting the Chinese members in
                    implementing the Cessation of Hostilities order.” I would like to insert the
                    word “solely”—“American participation within the Headquarters will be solely.”
                    Is the paragraph as amended by me acceptable?</p>
                <p>C &amp; G: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: It is so ordered. The next paragraph reads, “The Executive Headquarters will
                    include an Operations Section, composed of the number of officers and men
                    required to supervise adequately in the field the various details.” Any
                    objection to that or is it acceptable?</p>
                <p>C &amp; G: Yes, sir.</p>
                <p>M: It is so ordered. Next paragraph reads, “It is agreed that separate and
                    independent signal communications systems may be established by the Operations
                    Section for each Commissioner in order to insure rapid and unhampered
                    communications.” I would suggest there that the words “by the Operations
                    Section” be struck out. Did you get my amendment?</p>
                <p>G: Drop the words “by the Operations Section”? Yes.</p>
                <p>M: Is that acceptable?</p>
                <p>G: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: Is that acceptable?</p>
                <pb facs="0122" n="110" xml:id="pg_110"/>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: So ordered. “The Headquarters will be located initially at Peiping.” Is that
                    acceptable?</p>
                <p>C &amp; G: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: “The names of the Commissioners in the Executive Headquarters follows:”</p>
                <p>G: I don’t know who will be the Commissioner, they haven’t been named yet. Nobody
                    knows. They haven’t been appointed.</p>
                <p>M: All right, then we will have to strike out this last paragraph.</p>
                <p>G: All right, take out the last paragraph.</p>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: Now, I wish to read to you the first paragraph. Is that acceptable as
                    written?</p>
                <p>C: With the exception of the last line it should be “Communist-led troops.”</p>
                <p>G: General, the suggestions made by the Generalissimo only concern the Chinese
                    text. They don’t involve any changes.</p>
                <p>M: Then we can finish with this now so that we can get it typed. Is that first
                    paragraph acceptable?</p>
                <p>C &amp; G: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: I propose that the blank spaces below in the next paragraph, which is a
                    quotation from the Cessation of Hostilities Order, be filled in as follows: “As
                    of 10 o’clock on the 10th of January of the year 1946 of the Republic.” Or what
                    is it?</p>
                <p>C: 35th.</p>
                <p>M: “35th year of the Republic.” Is this the 10th of January?</p>
                <p>C &amp; G: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: That should be “1000 hours”. That makes it a.m. It will not be necessary to
                    have any signature because this is a press release. Now may I Make
                    this—(discussion between General Chang and General Chou). I am trying to time
                    this with that meeting.</p>
                <p>G: But, according to this order everything will take effect on this date.</p>
                <p>M: Yes. It won’t get to the troops. The minute you receive it you stop. We can
                    only do the best we can.</p>
                <p>G: It will take a couple of days at least.</p>
                <p>M: Yes, but nobody can specify the exact number of days. While you get it, the
                    man over there may be fighting yet, but we can only do the best we can. There is
                    no other way you can do it, because there is a varied time schedule all over
                    China.</p>
                <p>G: The Governor says that before we leave this room the order will have supposed
                    to have taken effect.</p>
                <p>M: Whenever you do it it will mean that. We could say 1:00 o’clock today, but we
                    wouldn’t gain anything one way or the other. <pb facs="0123" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/> I participated in one Armistice where they took four
                    hours. I was Chief of Operations of an Army, but the fighting went on for six or
                    seven hours, but we still had the Armistice. That was Germany. We had prisoners,
                    casualties, very heavy fighting.</p>
                <p>G: Your conditions are different.</p>
                <p>M: It is a matter of communications.</p>
                <p>G: Yes, it is a matter of communications.</p>
                <p>M: They were not sufficient there; they are not sufficient here. What’s the
                    difference? If you should select an hour when you are certain that everybody
                    will have it, you are having fighting going on in a number of places for three
                    or four days. Is that tolerable?</p>
                <p>G: General Chang is afraid that it will take probably four or five days for the
                    order to reach all the important cities, not to speak of far-flung places, and
                    if we should say that this order will take effect today at 10:00 o’clock, then
                    during a period of four of [<hi rend="italic">or</hi>] five days either side may
                    be accused of violating the terms of the order because fighting is still going
                    on during that period. He would inquire if it could be so arranged, as he
                    discussed this question with General Chou before and General Chou also expressed
                    the opinion that it would probably take four or five days, for the order to take
                    effect. He now inquires if it would be in order if the order would be issued at
                    10:00 o’clock today and in the order will be fixed the date and time for it to
                    take effect?</p>
                <p>M: The present form of the Cessation of Hostilities Order involves that
                    particular character of statement which you have just referred to.</p>
                <p>G: “To carry out the following directive as from today at 10:00 o’clock. [”]</p>
                <p>M: No, the form agreed upon for Cessation of Hostilities Order included a
                    provision of that character which the Governor has just referred to. Will you
                    translate that please?</p>
                <p>C: General Chou favors the original form because he thinks this only stipulates
                    that the order has been issued at this time and all the troops on receiving this
                    order should immediately carry it into effect and if they cannot carry it into
                    effect at the time stipulated, then it is only because they haven’t received it,
                    but immediately after receiving it they should stop firing.</p>
                <p>M: I think what he is saying is the same thing I am thinking. If we should
                    provide a time here for the cessation of hostilities, based on how long it would
                    require to transmit this order to all the troops, you will have a period of very
                    serious possible consequences with troops on both sides maneuvering for best
                    advantage. That, I think, would be most regrettable. We are trying to cease
                    hostilities and we should avoid difficulties.</p>
                <p>C: Yes, General Chou entirely agrees.</p>
                <pb facs="0124" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/>
                <p>G: There will be a period, however, during which conflict will occur in certain
                    regions where the order has not been received and these conflicts are
                    unavoidable.</p>
                <p>M: But I think you get into much more serious ones if you leave it open. After
                    the words, the following directive, all units, regular, etc. are ordered to
                    carry out the following directive and then put a period right there.</p>
                <p>G: Cut out the date and the hour.</p>
                <p>M: Cut out the time.</p>
                <p>G: All hostilities will cease immediately.</p>
                <p>M: That means when you receive the order you stop. There is no way you can time
                    this without having a longer interval in there with everybody playing for
                    position and that is what I think should be avoided.</p>
                <p>C: General Chou advises that the original should be retained but if it is more
                    acceptable to leave it out then he thinks there should be an understanding
                    between himself and Governor Chang that it would take three or four days to get
                    a fixed time so that all orders will have reached the Armies in the front. Both
                    sides should assure that [on] a certain date all orders must have reached the
                    Armies in the front.</p>
                <p>M: That would be one way to do that right here in the minutes and not publicize
                    this complication to the troops. If the Governor and General Chou agree that the
                    orders will be issued in such a manner as to reach the troops within certain
                    number of days. Therefore, it would not be necessary to include in this any
                    wording after the word directive.</p>
                <p>G: Is it taken for granted that this order would be issued today.</p>
                <p>M: Yes. That would be my understanding.</p>
                <p>B: I think that ought to be in the minutes.</p>
                <p>M: I have the proposal that we record here in the minutes, not to be a published
                    exception that it is agreed that the order will be issued at noon today. If that
                    is acceptable? That the words after the word directive be omitted, as of 10
                    hours on the 10th of January, that that be struck out. Do you wish to put in at
                        noon?<note n="63" xml:id="d22fn63">Notation on the original: “Meaning the
                        time of publishing.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>G: The Governor suggested to say in the forenoon.</p>
                <p>M: That is agreeable.</p>
                <p>C: Agreed.</p>
                <p>M: The records of the minutes will show that General Chang and General Chou
                    agreed that the order will be issued before noon, this morning, January 10. That
                    is a matter of record. Next is it agreeable that that portion of the draft of
                    cessation of hostilities order in the first paragraph, third line, the word
                    directive be omitted, which <pb facs="0125" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/> reads as
                    follows: “on . . . . . hours on . . . . . day, on . . . . . . . month on . . . .
                    . year of the Republic.” Is that agreeable?</p>
                <p>G: Yes.</p>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: It is so ordered. Now I will ask you to return to the press release. Do you
                    want to await the Generalissimo’s comments.</p>
                <p>G: No.</p>
                <p>M: The words in that same paragraph, “as of . . . . . hours of . . . . . . day of
                    . . . . . . . month” on message will be struck out. Now I wish to inquire what
                    hour should be placed on this press release? May I suggest 10:30?</p>
                <p>G: The Governor would like to have a little time in which we could make a final
                    report to the Generalissimo before this is released, just to show the order and
                    everything in its final form to the Generalissimo. That won’t take too long.</p>
                <p>M: May I make this inquiry. Is there a probability of reopening the question of
                    the wording of the order.</p>
                <p>G: I would presume that he won’t make any changes.</p>
                <p>M: I would merely suggest to the Governor that he communicate to the
                    Generalissimo my own concern if there is any delay between whatever statement
                    the Generalissimo makes at ten o’clock and the release of these details. What
                    will happen in the U. S., I know, will be a very confused statement because
                    there will be a news flash immediately and unless they know what is stated in
                    this paper they are going to guess and then we are in for all kinds of trouble.
                    So that if this does not follow closely on the Generalissimo’s announcement you
                    are going to have all kinds of confusion and you will be forever straightening
                    it out.</p>
                <p>G: There won’t be any delay.</p>
                <p>M: The complication is that if we get nothing here and the Generalissimo
                    announces it they will flash his announcement with a lot of guess work.</p>
                <p>G: Is there anything else regarding the release.</p>
                <p>M: I understand the Governor does not wish that release be accomplished until he
                    has the approval of the Generalissimo. Now is my understanding correct that we
                    will await instructions from the Generalissimo until that release has been
                    looked over.</p>
                <p>G: Colonel Pee is going to deliver that and he will call here.</p>
                <p>M: That completes our business of the moment; before we go would it be agreeable
                    to you gentlemen to meet at 5 o’clock. When will it meet their pleasure to sign
                    the order. The English text will be the record text. You have enough basis now
                    for issuance of the order. Then the actual signing of the English text will be a
                    mere matter of form. Is that correct.</p>
                <pb facs="0126" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/>
                <p>G: You mean to sign the agreement.</p>
                <p>M: The proposal is drafted for our three signatures.</p>
                <p>G: The Governor suggests that he and General Chou sign the press release now,
                    immediately after we have heard from the Generalissimo.</p>
                <p>M: Is it agreeable to meet at 5 o’clock?</p>
                <p>G: Three o’clock. Governor Chang inquires when the Executive Headquarters will be
                    brought into being.</p>
                <p>M: That is what I wanted to do at three o’clock or this morning if we had time. I
                    have got that all here.</p>
                <p>C: General Chou has a technical request to make. That is regarding to signal
                    communications here, because up to now we are not able to send a man to operate
                    the radio station of the Military Council. Now since we have a separate system
                    in the executive headquarters, I hope that the government has no objection that
                    we have our own station here at the office and he hopes the original station can
                    be established. If I had communications with Yenan this afternoon I could
                    arrange these things to Yenan real quick.</p>
                <p>M: That would be my recommendation.</p>
                <p>G: General Chang likes to take this opportunity to say [to?] both that it is most
                    unfortunate that hostilities should have occurred. Now that hostilities will
                    cease it is a thing worthy of congratulations and he hopes that our efforts
                    towards the reestablishment of peaceful relations will produce still greater
                    results because the cessation of hostilities is not an end in itself. He wishes
                    that the committee of three which has already been appointed will proceed with
                    its work and that we urgently recommend to this committee that they immediately
                    proceed with the duties assigned to them so that our efforts will produce better
                    results and at the same time he wants to express my thanks to you, General
                    Marshall, for all you have done to bring us together and bring about the
                    cessation of hostilities and we also hope that you will contribute your further
                    efforts towards this discussion.</p>
                <p>M: Thank you, Governor, I appreciate very much your generous expressions of
                    whatever I may have done. I, too, regard this as a most favorable development
                    that we have reach[ed] a basis for terminating hostilities and I hope that it
                    will prove historic. I agree completely with the Governor regarding the
                    importance of proceeding with the negotiations for the reorganization of the
                    Armies of China. I understand a committee has been agreed upon to consider this
                    very complicated matter and I would think that it was imperative that a solution
                    be reached at the earliest possible moment because that is a fundamental to all
                    the difficulties. What we are doing is giving a pause for deliberation. Now,
                    certainly something very definite should be done to find a solution for the
                    difficult problem of reorganization of the Armies of China. Whatever the timing
                    of the execution of such a <pb facs="0127" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/> plan, it
                    seems to me it is essential to immediately develop a plan because at best it is
                    going to be a very difficult matter of compromises. It is my hope that the good
                    faith that will be built up under the terms of this cessation of hostilities
                    order as it is being carried out by this practical headquarters in the field
                    will result in a development of confidence in the good faith of all parties so
                    that it will not be as difficult as it would now appear to reach a solution. Now
                    as I understood the Governor, he proposed that this particular group submit an
                    urgent recommendation that this committee to which he referred be convened
                    immediately to proceed with the development of an acceptable plan for the
                    reorganization of the Armies of China. As I have said, I think that is both a
                    fundamental and imperative requirement and while I feel a reticence, or rather a
                    hesitation in injecting myself into that measure, with which I have not been
                    previously associated, I would be very happy to participate with this group in
                    submitting that urgent recommendation.</p>
                <p>G: Did you say that this committee or you would write a letter.</p>
                <p>M: I said while I hesitated, felt reticent, about injecting myself into a matter
                    with which I had not been previously associated or invited, I would be happy to
                    participate with this group in such an urgent recommendation.</p>
                <p>C: Since the time is short, I will only say a few words. First of all, I want to
                    thank General Marshall for his participation in the order of the cessation of
                    hostilities you have published. Governor Chang has also done his best. I myself
                    suggest sincerely that the reorganization of all Chinese troops can be
                    proceeded, which includes the Chinese Communist-led troops so that they will be
                    an equal part in the National Armies and I hope that this will also enjoy
                    General Marshall’s support.</p>
                <p>M: Then it is agreed we meet at three o’clock. I would like to make certain that
                    you get the correct interpretation of what I said that was misunderstood by
                    Governor Chang.</p>
                <p>G: The Generalissimo is going to speak at the meeting today at 10 o’clock and he
                    is going to make an announcement in regard to this and he thinks that it will
                    take at most 15 minutes or so and this will be released at about 11 o’clock.</p>
                <p>M: 11:15?</p>
                <p>G: 11:30.</p>
                <p>C: Yes.</p>
                <p>M: If agreeable to the Governor and if agreeable to General Chou I will have
                    these press men come into the hall and in the presence of the Governor and in
                    the presence of General Chou receive this 11:30 release.</p>
                <p>G &amp; C: Yes.</p>
                <pb facs="0128" n="116" xml:id="pg_116"/>
                <p>M: We don’t have to say anything but just give them this.</p>
                <p>(Press men invited in and told that the transmission time was 11:30<note n="64" xml:id="d22fn64">For text of press release, see <hi rend="italic">United
                            States Relations With China</hi>, p. 609.</note>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
