<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Draft Prepared by General Chou En-lai
                    Forwarded by General Chou to Lieutenant General
                        Gillem.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d245</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">245</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="245" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d245">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Prepared by General Chou En-lai</hi>
                    <note n="20" xml:id="d245fn20">Forwarded by General Chou to Lieutenant General
                        Gillem.</note>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Instructions for Executive Headquarters Regarding the Entry
                        of Field Teams Into Manchuria</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">Draft</hi>)</p>
                <p>Field teams, with carefully selected personnel, will be sent into Manchuria
                    immediately under the following instructions.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The teams will carry out their mission in accordance with the instructions
                        of the Executive Headquarters.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The teams should be established within the areas of the Government troops
                        as well as the Communist troops, keeping clear of places still under Russian
                        occupation.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Teams should proceed to points of conflict or close contact between the
                        Government and Communist troops to bring about a cessation of fighting and
                        to make the necessary readjustments.</item>
                    <pb facs="0577" n="565" xml:id="pg_565"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>While reestablishing Chinese sovereignty in Manchuria the Government is
                        authorized to move troops into the localities now<note n="21" xml:id="d245fn21">General Chang objected also to this draft because of
                            the word “now”.</note> being evacuated by the Soviet troops, viz: the
                        railway line between Mukden and Changchun, with a strip of 30 li on both
                        sides of that railway section.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>If it becomes necessary for the Government troops to occupy those
                        localities now held by Communist troops, it should be effected through
                        discussion among the field teams and if an agreement cannot be reached it
                        will be settled by higher authority.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The future disposition in Manchuria of all armies will be fixed according
                        to the reorganization plan.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The Government assures that it will immediately discuss the political
                        matters pertaining to Manchuria with the Chinese Communist Party in line
                        with the decisions of the Political Consultative Council. As an interim
                        measure the Government will maintain the present status of the
                        popularly-elected local governments without any obstruction or interference,
                        pending a settlement of the political matters.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date ana="#date_editorial-correction" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-16">March 17 [<hi rend="italic">16</hi>],
                        1946</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
