<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lieutenant General Alvan C. Gillem, Jr., to General Marshall</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d373</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">373</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="373"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d373">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant General <persName type="from">Alvan C. Gillem,
                            Jr.</persName>, to General <persName type="to">Marshall</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-06">6 April
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>453. Organization of the Committee of Three again in state of flux. General Chang
                    Chih Chung was ordered to Sinkiang by the Generalissimo over my protest on 29
                    March. Several days ensued, in spite of my insistence to the contrary, before
                    Generalissimo appointed General Chen Cheng.</p>
                <p>General Chen Cheng is a sick man and although I met with him individually on
                    three occasions and conference on two occasions he has now been removed from the
                    Committee by the Generalissimo on account of his health. General Yu Ta Wei was
                    pinchhitting for and assisting General Chen Cheng, but he now tells me he does
                    not desire to serve on the committee and so recommended to the Generalissimo
                    because he is “A military man with no ability towards political
                    negotiation.”</p>
                <p>This afternoon I met Chen Cheng who graciously volunteered to carry on until new
                    man is appointed. He is seeing Chou in the morning to attempt to lay ground work
                    for Manchuria solution. In meantime I have asked Generalissimo for prompt
                    replacement.</p>
                <p>Communists interpret Chen’s removal as a stall in furtherance of a “wait and see”
                    policy with respect to the Manchurian situation. Chou is also concerned over
                    three recent incidents: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Four-hour detention of 40 Communist team members upon arrival Mukden
                            Airfield on pretext of lacking proper credentials. Byroade resolved
                            matter locally and Robertson is fixing up credentials.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Arrest and detention in Peiping of several staff and newspaper
                            Communist personnel. Have not gotten report from Robertson as yet but am
                            informed by Communists that all personnel are now released.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Eight CAF fighters buzzed Yenan for half hour 3 days ago.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
