<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="388" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d388">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Draft of Additional Instructions for Field Teams
                                Entering Manchuria</hi><note n="4" xml:id="d388fn4">Prepared by Lt.
                                Gen. Alvan C. Gillem, Jr., as a fourth draft on this subject for
                                conference with Gen. Chou En-lai.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-09">April 9, 1946</date>.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>We, General Chen Cheng, Representative of the National Government of
                            China, and General Chou En-Lai, Representative of the Communist Party,
                            have recommended to Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek and Chairman Mao
                            Tze-tung and have been authorized by them to announce that the following
                            provisions are applicable to the situation in Manchuria: <list>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Further movement of Communist-led troops in Manchuria will
                                    cease.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Communist-led troops presently occupying positions on or near
                                    railroads referred to in the Sino-Soviet treaty of 14 August,
                                    1945, will withdraw from these positions so that the nearest
                                    element is at least one day’s march to either flank in order to
                                    permit free passage and use of those railroads by National
                                    Government forces.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Communist-led troops will evacuate all towns and cities
                                    astride <pb facs="0764" n="752" xml:id="pg_752"/> of or along
                                    railroads referred to in the Sino-Soviet Treaty so that the
                                    nearest element is at least one day’s march therefrom.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                <item>National troops will not pursue or harass withdrawing
                                    Communist troops or Communist troops which, complying with terms
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> above, are in the vicinity of railroads
                                    and towns and cities referred to within those terms.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The aforesaid measures are offered as an interim solution. Problems and
                            questions not covered will continue under discussion of the Committee of
                            Three.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>