<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by General Marshall to General Chou
                            En-lai</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d427</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">427</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-02T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="427" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d427">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by General <persName type="from">Marshall</persName> to General <persName type="to">Chou
                            En-lai</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">OSE 2</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-02">May 2,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear General Chou</hi>: I have been informed by Mr.
                    Robertson that Colonel Humphrey of Team number 26 proceed[ed] to the town of Pei
                    Piao (in eastern Jehol) on 1 May for the purpose of investigating a reported
                    massing of Communist troops. Colonel Humphrey, accompanied by one interpreter
                    and 2 Communist civilian guides attempted to contact the local Communist
                    commanders. During this trip the party was fired upon by Communist party snipers
                    and one civilian was killed. Colonel Humphrey received a slight wound. I have
                    been further informed that this is not the first instance of U. S. team members
                    being fired upon by Communist troops. Mr. Robertson protested this matter to
                    Commissioner Yeh who expressed his deep regret, promised immediate investigation
                    and promised to send messages to all Communist commanders to prevent recurrence
                    of such incidents.</p>
                <p>This situation has been complicated, if not caused, by the refusal of the
                    Communist member of Team 26 to accompany it from Chengtu in defiance of the
                    order of Executive Headquarters.</p>
                <p>The American officers whose lives or security have been placed in jeopardy by
                    these incidents are engaged solely in an effort to avert war and they are doing
                    so under orders for which I alone am responsible.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>G. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
