<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Counselor of Embassy in China (
                        Smyth
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d45</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">45</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-03-02T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-03-02T01:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-02T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-02T01:00:00-05:00" n="45" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d45">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/3–246: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Smyth</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-02T13:00:00+07:00">March 2, 1946—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received March 6—6:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>415. Organic general rules governing the Supreme National Defense Council enacted
                    by Kuomintang Central Executive Committee on January 29, 1939, are being
                    forwarded to Dept by airmail<note n="16" xml:id="d45fn16">Not found in
                        Department files.</note> in Chinese text and English translation. As far as
                    Embassy is aware these rules have never been made public. They were obtained
                    originally from Chinese source by staff member and their authenticity has now
                    been confirmed orally by Foreign Office.</p>
                <p>Article 1 of rules is as follows: “Central Executive Committee during the period
                    of the war hereby establishes the Supreme National Defense Council for the
                    purpose of coordinating the control of the party, the Government and the
                    military and exercising the power of the Central Political Council. The
                    subordinate departments and committees of the Central Executive Committee, and
                    the five Yuans of the Central Government, the National Military Council and its
                    subordinate departments and committees shall take instructions from the Supreme
                    National Defense Council”</p>
                <p>Article 8 as follows: “The President of the Supreme National Defense Council may,
                    without applying the ordinary procedure, summarily deal with all party.
                    Government, and military affairs by issuing orders.”</p>
                <p>Embassy considers these rules to be of considerable interest as specifically
                    setting forth supreme authority of Generalissimo which has hitherto been assured
                        [<hi rend="italic">assumed?</hi>]. They are especially interesting at this
                    time when Generalissimo’s authority may be subject to attack from Rightest
                    Kuomintang elements who are disgruntled at prospect of full implementation PCC
                    resolutions (Embtel 304, February 15, 3 p.m.) and drastic military
                    reorganization.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Smyth</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
