<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>General Marshall to Colonel
                            Marshall S. Carter</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d528</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">528</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="528" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d528">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Marshall</persName> to Colonel
                            <persName type="to">Marshall S. Carter</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-10">10 June
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>865. I think you should know the reasons behind recent heavy Communist propaganda
                    attack against U. S. and me personally. Extended absence of Generalissimo in
                    Mukden and Peiping while his armies hasten their advances in Manchuria, this
                    occurring just as I had brought the two sides to the verge of an agreement,
                    enraged Communists and what was much more serious aroused a deep suspicion in
                    their minds that I was favoring the Government side and was a party to the delay
                    caused by the Generalissimo’s prolonged absence while his armies capitalized
                    their success to the south of Changchun. Incidentally, use of my plane added to
                    Communist belief but he used plane on my urging for safety reason and because
                    Madame Chiang was ill, yet he insisted on her accompanying him.</p>
                <p>To add fat to the fire Generalissimo then made demand for agreement that the
                    Americans on teams, at Executive Headquarters and finally for me on Committee of
                    Three have authority to make final decision in case of all disagreement. To
                    offset approval this proposition might gain from American public the Communist
                    concentrated propaganda attack resulted, but it was hatched before the 15-day
                    proposition has been broached. The Communist are now inclined to accept me on
                    old terms of confidence but much harm has been done. Incidentally I would have
                    to be very careful of Soviet reactions against U. S. Government if I were given
                    power of decision on highest level which though military would necessarily
                    involve the final word regarding some of the most delicate questions concerning
                    the reorganization of local and provincial government in Manchuria.</p>
                <p>I would not risk this information through normal radio or office channels but I
                    pass it to you for limited use as seems best in your judgment. It might be well
                    to tip Shepley<note n="41" xml:id="d528fn41">James R. Shepley, former member of
                        General Marshall’s staff in China.</note> off, though this is questionable.
                    However, you are on the ground and you know the reactions: State Department,
                    press and radio, and maybe political part. <pb facs="1033" n="1021" xml:id="pg_1021"/> Chou is back from Yenan and negotiations are proceeding
                    initially in favorable manner.</p>
                <p>Another subject: Convey my congratulation to the Chief Justice.<note n="42" xml:id="d528fn42">Fred Vinson, formerly Secretary of the Treasury.</note>
                    Tell him I will miss his influence in NAC. Notify Baruch<note n="43" xml:id="d528fn43">Bernard Baruch, “elder statesman” and financier.</note>
                    that I am writing him a letter regarding Atomic questions he asked. Take
                    occasion to remark to Dean Acheson<note n="44" xml:id="d528fn44">Under Secretary
                        of State.</note> and Vincent that I am deeply sensible to the complete
                    backing they are giving me in every way, small embassy or consulate business,
                    funds, etc., etc. This is a hell of a problem but we will lick it yet,
                    pessimists to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
