<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-20T19:20:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-20T19:20:00-05:00" n="579" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d579">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minutes of Conference Between General Marshall and
                                Dr. Lo Lung-chi and Dr. Carsun Chang, at General Marshall’s House,
                                June 21, 1946, 8:20 a.m.</hi></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-21T08:20:00+08:00">June 21, 1946,
                                8:20 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <table rend="width: 50%" rendition="#center-block">
                            <row>
                                <cell>Also present:</cell>
                                <cell>Captain Soong</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Dr. Lo stated that he and Dr. Chang had suggested to Gen. Chou that he
                            consider giving the American team member final authority to conduct
                            local investigations. Regarding this Gen. Chou had wired Yenan and the
                            reply came back last evening which approved the American team member to
                            have the power to decide where and when the team was to go. He further
                            stated that members of minority parties met the Government delegates
                            yesterday and asked the Government to extend the 15 day truce. Dr. Chang
                            said that Gen. Chou told them that the Communist Party was willing to
                            give the final authority to American team members in ordering cease
                            fire. General Marshall said that he could not quite understand what Gen.
                            Chou meant by Americans’ final decision in ordering cease fire. For
                            instance, when fire was ceased, what should be done to prevent further
                            fighting? Dr. Chang stated General Chou’s implied meaning would be that
                            the American team members would have power to decide what distance each
                            side would have to withdraw. Gen. Marshall then said that it was not
                            sufficient to merely imply because the lower ranks among the Communist
                            Party would not adhere to this implication. Gen. Marshall said that Gen.
                            Chou had been reluctant in this matter because the lower ranks among the
                            Communist Party could not analyze the situation as to why Government
                            troops were using American equipment—guns, bombs, etc., and that they
                            all looked upon Americans with disfavor.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Lo said that Gen. Marshall’s arbitration power on the Committee of
                            Three level was another deadlock issue. Gen. Marshall said he saw no
                            particular reason why such an arrangement would not be appropriate in
                            Executive Headquarters and in the Field teams but that on the Committee
                            of Three level unanimous vote proceedings would have to continue with
                            the possible exception of rulings on interpretations of directives and
                            agreements. He could not accept the arbitration power as proposed by the
                            Government because it would impose too much responsibility upon the U.
                            S. Government. The Government insisted on it since they wanted to insure
                            that agreements would be carried out and since the existing procedure
                            was wholly ineffective.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Lo then said that they would be glad to go to see Gen. Chou this
                            morning regarding what Gen. Marshall had just said. However, <pb facs="1127" n="1115" xml:id="pg_1115"/> Gen. Marshall replied that
                            Gen. Chou was coming to see him 1100 hours this morning and he suggested
                            that they wait.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>