<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="601" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d601">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/6–2646</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Marshall</persName> to
                                President <persName type="to">Truman</persName></hi><note n="86" xml:id="d601fn86">Copy transmitted by the War Department to the
                                Department of State on June 26.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-26">June 26, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>[995.] <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: The negotiations
                            have reached a point where the detailed instructions to govern a
                            cessation of hostilities have been agreed to, also, the instructions for
                            the reopening of communications. Further, an important agreement has
                            been completed granting certain authorities to the American officer on
                            teams and at Executive Headquarters which should greatly facilitate the
                            control of situations by Executive Headquarters in the future. We are
                            now engaged in the far more difficult matter of the redisposition and
                            reduction of troops in Manchuria and North and Central China. The
                            Manchurian phase seems to be the least difficult of the three to
                            compose. The Communists submitted their detailed proposals<note n="87" xml:id="d601fn87">See <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> this
                            morning and I am at this moment engaged with General Chou in a
                                discussion<note n="88" xml:id="d601fn88">See <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note> of the proposals. I write while he is making
                            his statements in Chinese or listening to the translation of mine.</p>
                        <p>The Communist proposals are far apart from the government demands and
                            there remain but a few days in which to achieve a compromise solution.
                            The situation is further complicated by the freely expressed desire of
                            some to settle the issue by force, by mass meetings in Shanghai
                            carefully organized to stir up anti-American feeling related to current
                            Congressional consideration of Lend-Lease matters in particular.</p>
                        <pb facs="1214" n="1202" xml:id="pg_1202"/>
                        <p>I realize the circumstances which have caused the initiation of new
                            measures in Congress for aid to China at this time, but these moves,
                            coming at the most critical stage of my negotiations, are causing
                            difficulty and embarrassment. The Communists profess to regard recent
                            measures and official statements in Washington as proving their
                            contention that American economic and military support to the Kuomintang
                            Government will continue to be given irrespective of whether the
                            government offers the Communists a fair and reasonable basis for
                            settlement of military and political differences. The Communists
                            maintain new legislation intended to aid China is reinforcing the
                            government’s tendency to deal with the Communists by force and thus is
                            contributing to all out civil war. They relate the proposed
                            Congressional action to active support of the government military power
                            in the immediate future and not many months hence as would be the
                            case.</p>
                        <p>I think it is a fact that some die-hard Kuomintang elements in other
                            government councils are utilizing recent American measures as a basis
                            for pressing the Generalissimo to push forward with a campaign of
                            determination against the Communists. At the same time, these and other
                            Kuomintang extremists appear to be joining in anti-American agitation on
                            the grounds that American economic pressure is causing American imports
                            to displace Chinese products, bankrupt Chinese industrialists and
                            prevent Chinese recovery. These Kuomintang groups also are antagonistic
                            to the restraint exercised by myself and other Americans on the
                            government with regard to an anti-Communist military campaign, and are
                            even using the Communist line against American intervention in pursuance
                            of their aim to free the government from any American impediment to
                            drastic anti-Communist, action.</p>
                        <p>The agitation and propaganda resulting from the activity of the different
                            factions is being manifested in mass demonstrations, press campaigns and
                            mob actions, such as, the incident at the Nanking Railway Station on the
                            night of June 24 [<hi rend="italic">23</hi>]. It would be helpful if
                            government spokesmen in Washington seized favourable occasion to explain
                            the aims and development American measures for aid to China.<note n="89" xml:id="d601fn89">With the approval of President Truman, Acting
                                Secretary of State Acheson on June 28 issued a statement to the
                                press along lines suggested by General Marshall; for text, see
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, July 7, 1946,
                                p. 34.</note> The recent moves are but steps in the complete
                            implementation of a long agreed program for helping the Chinese nation
                            as a whole to rid itself of the Japanese. These moves include steps to
                            implement the agreement reached in Chungking, February 25 last, for
                            reorganization and unification of the armed forces of China. They are
                            intended to cement rather than destroy unity, and were planned <pb facs="1215" n="1203" xml:id="pg_1203"/> for a single National Army
                            made up of both Communist and Central Government troops. All of the
                            steps concerned involve a lengthy procedure of negotiation, agreements,
                            legislative action and, lastly, decisions by yourself in accordance with
                            the existing situation; these steps consume many months, more than a
                            year in this case, and if interrupted could not be quickly, if ever,
                            resumed.</p>
                        <p>It could be pointed out that measures to provide economic aid to China in
                            the form of supplies and credits are an impartial American effort to
                            contribute to a solution of the acute economic crisis in the country and
                            prevent a complete economic breakdown. It could be stressed that it is
                            the American hope that economic assistance be carried out in China
                            through the medium of a government of all factions, including the
                            Communists, and that the American Government feels that a few measures
                            of economic assistance could not be held in abeyance despite the
                            failure, so far, of Chinese groups to come together in a unified
                            government, without danger of an economic collapse which would spell a
                            great tragedy for the common people of China.</p>
                        <closer><signed>G. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>