<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-28T22:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-28T22:30:00-05:00" n="615" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d615">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Notes on Meeting Between General Marshall and
                                Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek, June 29, 1946, 11:30 a.m.</hi></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-29T11:30:00+08:00">June 29, 1946,
                                11:30 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>The discussion related to the efforts to reach a compromise solution on a
                            special document<note n="9" xml:id="d615fn9"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> which had been prepared to make possible an
                            agreement before the termination of the so-called truce at noon of the
                            following day.</p>
                        <p>The Generalissimo declined to modify the conditions demanded of the
                            Communists for the redistribution of troops. Specifically, he insisted
                            upon the evacuation of Cheng-te, of all of Kiangsu Province <pb facs="1261" n="1249" xml:id="pg_1249"/> (rather than all of the
                            section south of Huai-an), and the removal of existing local governments
                            in the regions to be evacuated by the Communists. There were many other
                            points at issue which were discussed. The foregoing were the most
                            important, except possibly his requirement for the complete evacuation
                            of Antung Province in Manchuria.</p>
                        <p>It was pointed out by me that I was left with no basis for further
                            negotiations because throughout the Government had confined itself to
                            demands in North China and had made no compromise other than some small
                            modifications of those demands. The Generalissimo took the line that he
                            could not accept any basis for the conclusion of negotiations that did
                            not guarantee in his opinion the future avoidance of difficulty with the
                            Communists. Temporary measures were not acceptable and his past
                            experience had made it evident that the demands he had insisted upon
                            were necessary.</p>
                        <p>I pointed out that the same logic could be carried to the extreme of
                            justifying the complete elimination of the Communist Party and army as
                            being the only measures satisfactory for the maintenance of future peace
                            in China. Further, I stated that my negotiations had been made
                            particularly difficult and trying, by reason of the freely expressed
                            opinions of high Government officials, particularly those in commanding
                            positions in Manchuria, that even if an agreement was reached it would
                            have no importance and they were determined to pursue a policy of force.
                            Political leaders of position in the Kuomintang Party had been similarly
                            free in their expression of opposition to negotiations and determination
                            to see the matter through by fighting. I expressed the opinion that
                            whatever might be thought to be the evidence of the past, that the
                            Government of China would be judged by the world, and certainly by
                            American public opinion, as having unnecessarily plunged the country
                            into chaos by implacable demands and the evident desire to pursue a
                            policy of military settlement.</p>
                        <p>The Generalissimo, after expressing his regrets that the negotiations had
                            resulted in failure and with assurances of appreciation of my efforts,
                            then produced a draft of a statement referring to me which evidently was
                            to be released to the press. It expressed regrets over the failure of
                            the negotiations. It said that, even so, the Government hoped I would
                            continue my efforts at mediation. I expressed thanks for the
                            complimentary references but stated that I much preferred no such
                            reference to me be made and that I would decline to be an umpire on a
                            battlefield.</p>
                        <p>The conference terminated with my statement that I would see General Chou
                            En-lai immediately, but there seemed to be no probability of reaching
                            any satisfactory agreement.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>