<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-07-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="689" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d689">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Walter S.
                                    Robertson</persName> to General <persName type="to">Marshall</persName></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-07-18">18 July 1946</date>.<note n="47" xml:id="d689fn47">Telegram as sent July 18 apparently garbled in
                                    transmission; repeated July 19.</note></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>5605. American officer has investigated following National Govt, claims
                            of Communist activities at Chefoo: <list>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>That Chefoo has been used as supply base and port of entry and
                                    departure for Communist troops moving between Shantung and
                                    Kwantung Peninsula.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>That fortifications were being constructed in Chefoo
                                    and</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>That Russian reconnaissance personnel has been operating on
                                    the Chefoo area.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Although the American observer selected the witnesses and conducted the
                            questioning of each witness, local Communist authorities insisted that
                            all such questioning be done in the presence of both military and
                            civilian authorities. The observer was permitted to move with relative
                            freedom within Chefoo proper but was not permitted to investigate Natl.
                            Govt. claims, in other areas of northern <pb facs="1397" n="1385" xml:id="pg_1385"/> Shantung. Local Communist officials insisted that
                            the observer be accompanied by military bodyguards whenever he left his
                            billets.</p>
                        <p>Since the presence of Communist Party officials during the entire
                            investigations may have intimidated the witnesses, it is felt that the
                            results, though negative, are inconclusive as regards claims <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> above. The
                            testimony did support the claim that fortifications at Chefoo have been
                            strengthened.</p>
                        <p>The observer cannot state definitely whether troops and munitions have
                            previously entered or left Chefoo. However, the observer believes such
                            movements were not accomplished during his stay in the area particularly
                            in view of the fact that the National Govt. naval blockade on Shantung
                            Peninsula has virtually halted all shipping into or out of Chefoo.</p>
                        <p>Communist instructions to the observer prior to departure from Lini were: <list>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>He would investigate claims concerning Chefoo only.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>The investigation was to be accomplished in a period of
                                    several days.</item>
                                <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Upon completion of the investigation the observer would return
                                    to Lini.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Prior to the observers departure from Chefoo, we directed that he remain
                            there pending the results of our request to the Communist Party Branch
                            to remove all restrictions from the conduct of the investigation. Local
                            authorities refused the observer permission to remain in Chefoo and
                            ordered his departure for Lini as originally scheduled.</p>
                        <p>Upon arrival there, Lini Hqs informed the observer that orders from
                            Commissioner Yeh Chien-ying were required to reopen the investigation.
                            Our request to General Yeh to lift the restrictions on the investigation
                            was without results. The observer has now returned to Peiping.</p>
                        <p>Due to the restrictive conditions imposed by the Communist Party on the
                            conduct of the investigation we consider that the testimony taken re
                            previous troop and supply movements is invalidated and that portion of
                            the investigation inconclusive. In view of the foregoing it is not
                            contemplated that the investigation will be reopened.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>