<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="80" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d80">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Lieutenant General <persName type="from">Albert C.
                                    Wedemeyer</persName> to General <persName type="to">Marshall</persName></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-02-05">5 February 1946</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>22232. Reply to 135<note n="85" xml:id="d80fn85">Telegram of February 1,
                                not printed.</note> follows:</p>
                        <p>With reference to the Army Program, it is my conviction that China cannot
                            properly support 60 active divisions. If the Generalissimo insists upon
                            such above program he is ill-advised concerning his economy. The Chinese
                            would be again dissipating their equipment and budgetary allowances over
                            such a large number of divisions, both National Government and
                            Communist, that a really effective force could not be created or
                            maintained. Further, the economy of the country would be jeopardized. We
                            had successfully convinced the Minister of War of this. After
                            considerable study my staff evolved an army program that I deem sound.
                            The Minister of War and the Vice Minister of War appear enthusiastic. As
                            you know it envisaged the creation of a new army with an ultimate
                            strength of 10 active U. S. type divisions, 40 inactive U. S. type
                            divisions and the necessary army, corps and supporting troops. The plan
                            also provides a national constabulary of 160 battalions for the
                            preservation of law and order and for the projection of lines of
                            communication in China.</p>
                        <pb facs="0220" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/>
                        <p>It has always been recognized that the present large Chinese army must be
                            demobilized gradually. Analysis of your plan to reduce the army by the
                            end of the first 12 months after agreement is reached, to approximately
                            90 National Government divisions and 15 to 20 Communist divisions,
                            appears sound. Continued demobilization to a total of 60 divisions
                            including 12 Communist divisions with the goal of reaching the total of
                            60 divisions in approximately 2 years after agreement also provides a
                            program of reduction that I feel could be agreed to. Thereafter, these
                            60 remaining divisions of the old army should be demobilized
                            progressively as divisions of the new army complete their training until
                            ultimately all 60 old divisions have been demobilized.</p>
                        <p>In connection with the equipment from the U. S. the plan for the new army
                            envisages complete U. S. equipment for the 10 active divisions, while
                            the Chinese would manufacture the bulk of the equipment for the inactive
                            divisions. The U. S. might provide that which the Chinese cannot
                            produce. In this connection, however, I have felt that it would be
                            inadvisable for the Chinese to stockpile for future use huge stocks of
                            equipment which may be obsolete before the need arises for its use. This
                            would be a wasteful expenditure which the Chinese cannot afford. Any
                            future emergency which will require the immediate use of more than the
                            10 active divisions would be foreseen in sufficient time to produce or
                            procure the latest equipment at a rate commensurate with the
                            mobilization program.</p>
                        <p>Concerning the equipment for the present interim army, I believe
                            equipment should be made available to the Chinese either under
                            lend-lease or by sales of surplus stocks now in the Pacific through the
                            Foreign Liquidation Commission. In this way certain stocks of U. S.
                            arms, ammunition, and equipment could be made available by minimum cost
                            to them. This will serve U. S. national interest, by putting U. S. arms
                            and equipment in the hands of Chinese forces friendly to us, and at the
                            same time liquidate the large stocks of surplus equipment now lying idle
                            in the Pacific. It should be recognized that this is distinct from
                                CAP,<note n="86" xml:id="d80fn86">Thirty-nine Chinese divisions,
                                known as Alpha units, sponsored by the United States.</note> and is
                            in addition to it.</p>
                        <p>The Generalissimo has indicated repeatedly that he desires to use U. S.
                            equipment throughout his armed forces. China’s economy cannot support an
                            immediate rearmament program of such magnitude. However, the program
                            should be approved, and its implementation tied to China’s economic
                            rehabilitation. There have been indications from U. S. high level
                            sources that Japanese equipment should be scrapped. I agree that the
                            Japanese equipment should be scrapped, both for the peace of the world,
                            and for simplified supply of the modernized <pb facs="0221" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/> Chinese army. However, the Chinese may not agree
                            to destroy Japanese equipment.</p>
                        <p>I do not feel that we should differentiate one iota in allocating
                            equipment to Chinese divisions, that is the Chinese Communists should be
                            given the same equipment that the Chinese National Government divisions
                            are given.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>