<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-11-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="185" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                        <head>No. 898.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">de
                                    Weckherlin</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the Netherlands</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-11-16"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 16,
                                    1887</date>. (Received November 18.)</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of State</hi>: The governor of the
                            Province of North Holland informs my Government that for some time past
                            a number of subjects of the Netherlands, belonging to the army of that
                            country, but being at home on indefinite leave of absence, have avoided
                            the fulfillment of their military obligations by shipping in ports of
                            the Netherlands, on board of foreign vessels, without having previously
                            obtained from the ministry of war the permission required for such an
                            engagement by article 129 of the law of the Netherlands of August 19,
                            1861, No. 72.</p>
                        <p>At the same time the aforesaid governor states that it is probable that
                            the consul of the United States of America at Amsterdam, when he
                            inscribes natives of the Netherlands upon the crew-list of American
                            merchant-vessels, does not require those who are of the age required by
                            law for serving in the army to show a document furnishing evidence of
                            their status in this respect, which document may be procured by parties
                            interested at the city hall.</p>
                        <p>I am instructed, Mr. Secretary of State, to communicate to you the
                            foregoing, and to express the hope that you will have the kindness to
                            call the attention of the consular officers of the United States of
                            America in the Netherlands to the provisions of article 129, which I
                            have just mentioned.</p>
                        <p>Be pleased, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">G. de
                            Weckherlin.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>