<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 953.Mr. Lothrop to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d240</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">240</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="south-and-central-asia">Central Asia</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recez5uVgqvmr6Nwm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006268"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Irrigation</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="240"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d240">
                <head>No. 953.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lothrop</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-05-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 31, 1888</date>. (Received June
                        15.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 176.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 27th instant, being the anniversary of the
                    coronation of the Emperor Alexander III, the Transcaspian Railway was opened
                    formally to Samarcand with great ceremony—an event of no common importance to
                    Russia, and even to the world. And it may well stir the dullest imagination when
                    we read that the crowning ceremonies were at the tomb of Tamerlane.</p>
                <p>This road is 1,350 versts in length—about 900 miles. It crosses the Amou-Daria
                    (the classic Oxus) by a bridge of great length, the construction of which has
                    delayed the completion of the road for some months.</p>
                <p>This work is principally a military road. It has been built and is controlled and
                    operated by the minister of war. At present it is little more than a skeleton
                    road. It is deficient in stations and rolling stock. But the great fact is
                    accomplished. It opens the door into the great field of Central Asia. All things
                    requisite to its efficiency will in time be added to it. Though a military road,
                    its political, economical, and commercial uses and results will not be
                    inconsiderable.</p>
                <p>It brings Russia near to its coveted cotton fields, from which so much is hoped.
                    It has already set in active motion measures for the restoration of the old
                    magnificent system of irrigation, which has fallen into dilapidation and disuse.
                    One of the old irrigating canals is said to have been 100 miles in length. All
                    successful cultivation of this region is dependent on irrigation, and a great
                    increase in the production of cotton <pb facs="0447" n="1407" xml:id="pg_1407"/>
                    seems to be confidently expected. This is really a matter of great
                    importance.</p>
                <p>The importation of cotton into Russia in 1887 is said to have been 10,000,000
                    pouds (the poud being 36 pounds), costing 96,000,000 rubles, and constituting 30
                    per cent. of the entire imports of the Empire. And it is mentioned with great
                    pleasure by the public prints that the production of cotton in Turkestan rose
                    last year to 500,000 pouds, being double of that of any previous year.</p>
                <p>It must not be supposed that the Transcaspian Railway is likely to rest at
                    Samarcand. Beyond lie Taschkend, Ferghana, and Semiretch, which the Russian
                    journals describe as “the richest provinces of Central Asia, abounding in water
                    and inviting colonization and culture.”</p>
                <p>As these lie in the direct path of the interest and the ambition of Russia, the
                    early extension of the railway may be confidently anticipated.</p>
                <p>At the same time the project of the construction of the great continental railway
                    across Siberia to the Pacific is agitated with increased interest.</p>
                <p>It is said that explorations of the line will be begun this year.</p>
                <p>It hardly seems probable that the available resources of the Empire will permit
                    the rapid prosecution of this gigantic undertaking, but it is a work which is
                    necessary to the security and welfare t)f the Pacific possessions of Russia.</p>
                <p>Its construction is therefore only a question of time.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Geo. V. N. Lothrop.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
