<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 67.Mr. Bayard to Mr. Herbert..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d522</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">522</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-12-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-12-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-12-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-12-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="522"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d522">
                <head>No. 67.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Herbert</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-12-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 10, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your note of the 5th instant, in which you call attention to the note of Lord
                    Sackville of <pb facs="0861" n="1819" xml:id="pg_1819"/> the 12th of October
                    last, in relation to the re-appraisement of three of the four British schooners
                    seized and condemned for illicitly taking seals in Behring Sea in 1887.</p>
                <p>The note referred to was at once communicated to the Department of Justice, with
                    a request for an opinion upon the question of re-appraisement. Some time
                    previously, upon the request of the Marquis of Salisbury, the sale of the
                    schooners had been stayed by this Government, in order that full opportunity
                    might be given to their owners to make some arrangement whereby they might
                    become repossessed of the vessels. On the 11th of October, the day preceding the
                    date of the note of Lord Sackville, above referred to, the Attorney-General
                    wrote to this Department a letter, copy of which is inclosed, in which he
                    intimated an opinion that the interests of both the United States and of the
                    claimants would be best subserved by a speedy sale of the vessels. By this
                    letter it appears that, although the schooners had long since been condemned, no
                    claims had been filed by their owners, and no bonds given for costs.
                    Nevertheless, the Department again consulted the Department of Justice in regard
                    to the proposition contained in the note under date of the 12th of October.
                    Under date of the 20th of October last a reply from the Attorney-General was
                    received, copy of which is inclosed. To this I made answer on the 27th of
                    October, expressing my concurrence in the view of the Attorney-General that
                    under the circumstances the wiser course for all concerned was to let the sale
                    of the vessels take place at once, as delay seemed impracticable, and could only
                    be productive of loss.</p>
                <p>On the 14th of last month the Attorney-General informed me that he had that day
                    directed the United States marshal in charge of the vessels at Port Townsend,
                    Wash., to take the necessary steps to effect a sale of the four vessels as
                    speedily as possible. Since that time no correspondence on the subject has taken
                    place with the Department of Justice, except a request from this Department on
                    the 17th ultimo that it might be informed of the proceedings of the marshal
                    under the order above stated. When a response to this request shall have been
                    received you will be duly advised of its contents.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">T. F. Bayard.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
