<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 68.Mr. Stevens to Mr. Rives..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1888p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d523</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">523</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1888-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1888-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278" lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871" lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1888-12-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1888-12-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="523" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d523">
                <head>No. 68.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Stevens</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Rives</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of the United States of America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Victoria, British Columbia</hi>
                        </placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-12-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 31, 1888</date>.<lb/>(Received January 12,
                                1889.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 388.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Information casually received this morning
                            leads me to believe that this dispatch, with inclosures, may prove of
                            interest.</p>
                <p>I am the more induced to make the report inasmuch as my No. 374, of
                            October 8 last, upon the same subject, the seizure off Copper Island on
                            July 1 last of the British sealing schooner <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi> gives but a brief account thereof, obtained from the
                            owners of the <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi>, and from the public press,
                            before the arrival here of the master of the vessel, and was
                            consequently ambiguous in some minor particulars.</p>
                <p>I am now enabled to give a more circumstantial account of the seizure, as
                            Captain Sieward, late master of the <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi>, has
                            recently given <pb facs="0862" n="1820" xml:id="pg_1820"/> me full
                            particulars of the seizure of the vessel and his subsequent proceedings,
                            and has left with me for perusal all papers in his possession concerning
                            the case, being letters—one from the Marquis of Salisbury—copies of
                            telegrams, diagram showing the position of the <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi> with reference to Copper Island, at the moment of
                            seizure, copy of treaty of March 30, 1867, between the United States and
                            Russia, and copy of the captain’s statement to Her Britannic Majesty’s
                            ambassador at St. Petersburg, signed by the captain and part of crew,
                            and sworn to before Her British Majesty’s consul at Nagasaki; of which I
                            send only copies of those most pertinent, especially the last-named
                            paper.</p>
                <p>Captain Sieward informs me that the agents of the British Government
                            provided fully for the expenses—save those paid by the Russian
                            Government at Petropolovski—and transportation of himself and the crew
                            of the seized vessel to this point, except a very small personal
                            outlay.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert J.
                            Stevens.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                    388.—Extract.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">R. B. D.
                                        Morier</persName> to Messrs. <persName type="to">Hall and
                                        Goepel</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">St.
                                            Petersburg</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-11-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 30,
                                        1888</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: Having received the final
                                communication which you had announced from the master of the <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi>, I have submitted the whole case to a
                                careful examination with a view of laying it before the Russian
                                Government.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>Much is made by Mr. Sieward of the statement of Groburtzky that he
                                would have seized the <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi> had she been
                                fitted out with apparatus for seal-catching anywhere within 100
                                miles south of Commander Islands. Had he assigned this as his true
                                motive for capturing the ship the case would be a very grave one,
                                but as he has given his motives for capturing the ship in a written
                                declaration, we are bound to go by that, and are not at liberty to
                                go outside this declaration and supersede a document signed and
                                sealed by anything he may have said <hi rend="italic">viva
                                    voce.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>It appears to me that it is of extreme importance to note the exact
                                words of this certificate, which does not state that he confiscated
                                the schooner for <hi rend="italic">being</hi> within customs limit,
                                but for seal-hunting<note n="*" xml:id="d523fn1">The meaning of this
                                    is that the seal-hunting being done from canoes, they were
                                    within the limit.</note> within the customs limit of Meday
                                (Medway) Island.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>The conversation between Sieward and Captain Gronberg, of which an
                                affidavit is given in Mr. Sieward’s letter of October 18, throws no
                                light upon the subject, because all that Captain Gronberg vouchsafes
                                to say is that the schooner was “about east by south and a half
                                south distant 3 miles from the southeast point of the island,” which
                                might leave her just inside or just outside the limit. It is
                                therefore perfectly clear that the ground they will take up will be
                                that the canoes and not the schooner were within the limits.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">R. B. D.
                                Morier.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                388.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Captain <persName type="from">Sieward</persName>
                                    to Mr. <persName type="to">Behring</persName>, Her British
                                    Majesty’s Chargé d’ Affaires, St. Petersburg</hi>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: Regarding the seizure of the
                                British sealing schooner <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi>, of
                                Victoria, British Columbia, by M. Groburtzky, on the Russian
                                merchantman <hi rend="italic">Alexander II</hi>, for alleged
                                violation of the fishing and hunting laws of the Imperial Russian
                                Government, of which I informed you in my dispatch of August 9,
                                1888, from Vladivostock, I now respectfully submit the following
                                facts: On July 1, 1888, at 6.30 a.m., during a heavy fog and calm, I
                                calculated the schooner’s position to be 16 miles south by west <pb facs="0863" n="1821" xml:id="pg_1821"/> of the southern extreme
                                of Copper or Med way Island. Judging myself in the open waters of
                                the North Pacific Ocean, I ordered the canoes out for hunting. At
                                about 7.30 a.m. the fog lifted, when the schooner was found to be
                                east by south about 6 to 8 miles distant from the southern extreme
                                of island, with the canoes out to the south and west of schooner.
                                When in this position a steamer was sighted, which bore at once down
                                upon us, proving to be the Alaska Commercial Company’s steamer <hi rend="italic">Alexander II</hi>, flying at peak the Russian
                                merchant ensign and at maintop a green flag with white cross. When
                                near, the schooner was hailed, and I, the master, was asked to come
                                aboard steamer, which I did; when on steamer’s deck I was informed
                                by Mr. Groburtzky that he would confiscate the schooner for being
                                within the limit. This I denied, but was answered that the boundary
                                ran from Cape Lapatka to the Island of Atton, and that I could
                                protest against the seizure to the authorities at Vladivostock,
                                where the case would be forwarded. As the officer produced no
                                documentary evidence of his authority, I asked upon what authority
                                the seizure was made, in answer to which the officer pointed to the
                                flag at maintop saying, “There is my authority.” The officers and
                                crew of schooner were then made prisoners and transferred aboard
                                steamer <hi rend="italic">Alexander</hi>. The schooner was towed to
                                the settlement Glinka, on Copper Island, where the skins, 133, were
                                landed at company’s warehouse. Here I had to deliver the schooner’s
                                papers to officer Groburtzky. Before doing so, I demanded a paper
                                stating the reason of confiscation, which I forward herewith, and a
                                copy of which I was asked to sign after it having been translated to
                                me by Mr. J. Mallewansky. It read in substance that this day the
                                schooner <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi> had been confiscated for
                                hunting within the limits of the Russian possessions. I here
                                notitled Mr. Groburtzky, in presence of Mr. J. Mallewansky, of my
                                protest against this seizure, which protest I would make before
                                nearest representative of Her British Majesty’s Government, and in
                                accordance with advice in your T. G. of August 15, 1888, have to
                                admiral and governor of Valdivostock, the certified copy of which
                                send herewith. The schooner was then brought to Petropolovsky by a
                                crew of steamer <hi rend="italic">Alemnder</hi>, where upon arrival
                                of schooner the salt stores, provisions, and also part of personal
                                property of ere w, were sold by Mr. Groburtzky without the
                                confiscation having been declared legal by any authority than his
                                own. I must add that we had no intention whatever to violate the
                                laws of the Imperial Royal Government, but intended to follow the
                                hunting in the open waters of the North Pacific Ocean, neither had
                                we any means to do otherwise, as the hunting outfit of schooner
                                consisted of six Indian canoes manned by two Vancouver Indians each,
                                had no fire-arms aboard, save three old muzzle-loading shotguns,
                                being the property of some of the Indians, also one shotgun and one
                                rifle, being the personal property of some of the members of the
                                crew.</p>
                    <p>From the foregoing it will be seen that the schooner was set by an
                                unknown current, not marked upon chart, during the fog to the north
                                and east of her course, and the canoes having left the schooner
                                during the fog, when there was no land in sight nor any visible sign
                                to prove the calculated position erroneous, will explain the
                                position of canoes at time of seizure; also that the schooner was
                                not less than the estimated 6 miles from land is clearly proven by
                                the <hi rend="italic">Alexander</hi> steaming two hours and forty
                                minutes at a rate of 6 knots per hour (see steamer engineer’s log)
                                from point of seizure to Glinka, which is 7 miles from south point
                                of island. This can be demonstrated on chart or diagram herewith,
                                showing that it was impossible for schooner to have been, as
                                alleged, within 3-mile limit or gunshot limit. As to the 133 seal
                                skins found aboard, I refer to schooner’s fishing log, now in the
                                hands of Imperial Russian Government. I also beg to call attention
                                to the fact that the steamer <hi rend="italic">Alexander II</hi> is
                                owned by the Alaska Commercial Company, who are also the lessees of
                                Copper and Behring Islands.</p>
                    <p>As to the reliability of the statement of Mr. Groburtzky as to the
                                true position of schooner at time of seizure I will say that Mr.
                                Groburtzky is no mariner, and consequently no competent judge to
                                personally determine the exact position of schooner. Furthermore, I
                                learned while prisoner aboard of <hi rend="italic">Alexander</hi>
                                that neither the first nor second officer of steamer had been called
                                upon by Captain Greenburg, of steamer, to witness or verify the
                                bearing and distance of schooner, so that the judgment of the
                                schooner’s actual position at time of seizure is but the guess-work
                                of the captain, Greenburg, of steamer <hi rend="italic">Alexander
                                    II</hi>, and of him alone, as a consultation on this serious
                                point with his officers might have resulted in proving the schooner
                                beyond the limits. In submitting the above facts to your careful
                                consideration I beg that you will use every means in your power to
                                effect a restitution of the unjustly and illegally confiscated
                                property and payment of damages incurred thereby.</p>
                    <p>The above sworn to before Her Britannic Majesty’s consul at Nagasaki
                                by myself; H. P. Bonde, mate; W. Standish, steward; G. Braum; P.
                                Doering; the 27th day of August, 1888, and forwarded together with
                                all documents by consul, Mr. Ensby, to St. Petersburg.</p>
                    <p>Very, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>H. F. S.,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Master.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0864" n="1822" xml:id="pg_1822"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                                388.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Copies of telegrams</hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Vladivostock</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1888-08-09">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 9, 1888</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">[Captain Sieward to the British embassy at St.
                                Petersburg.]</p>
                    <p>Sealing schooner <hi rend="italic">Araunah</hi>, of Victoria, was set
                                during heavy fog and calm by current within 6 miles of southern
                                extreme of Copper Island when seized by Russian Merchantman
                                Alexander. Left here with crew, among them twelve Vancouver Indians,
                                unprovided. Please advise.</p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sieward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Master.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">[From British embassy, St. Petersburg, August 13, 1888,
                                to Sieward, Vladivostock.]</p>
                    <p>Your telegram received. Steps will be taken with least delay
                                possible.</p>
                    <p rend="center">[From Sieward to British embassy, August 15, 1888.]</p>
                    <p>Will forward protest, sworn to before consul at Nagasaki. Also, all
                                documents pertaining to seizure. Please advise, if necessary to
                                protest here; also, if other steps required here. Owners names Hall
                                &amp; Gœpel, Victoria.</p>
                    <p rend="center">[Reply, August 17, 1888.]</p>
                    <p>Your case has been brought to the notice of Russian Government, who
                                have telegraphed to inquire into it. You might protest locally.
                                Forward all documents here.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dehring</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">British Chargé d’ Affaires.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
