<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-12-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="626" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d626">
                                <head>No. 64.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hubbard</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi></head>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokio</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-12-28"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 28, 1887</date>. (Received January
                                        21, 1888.)</dateline>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 417.]</seg></opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Respectfully referring to my
                                    dispatch No. 383, in which I had the honor to inclose a copy of
                                    a note from the Japanese minister for foreign affairs in reply
                                    to my note to him transmitting a copy of your circular
                                    instruction of July 9, and accompanying inclosures, with an
                                    invitation to His Imperial Japanese Majesty’s Government to
                                    enter into an arrangement with the United States Government for
                                    a mutual abolition or reduction of tonnage dues, etc., on
                                    vessels plying between the ports of our respective countries, I
                                    now have the honor to submit to the Department of State a copy
                                    of a note just received from Count Ito on the same subject.</p>
                                <pb facs="0981" n="1939" xml:id="pg_1939"/>
                                <p>The accompanying note is in reply to a communication from me in
                                    which I inclosed a copy of your instruction No. 164, expressing
                                    regret at the action of the Japanese Government in declining to
                                    enter into said arrangement or convention as desired by the
                                    United States Government. The reply of Count Ito explains
                                    itself, and I only have the honor to respectfully invite your
                                    attention to his communication and especially to the closing
                                    paragraph of his note.</p>
                                <p>I have merely acknowledged the receipt of this reply, informing
                                    the Japanese Government that I would refer the same and the
                                    accompanying inquiry to my Government for its early
                                    consideration. I have also assured the minister for foreign
                                    affairs that a response thereto would be made, and might be
                                    anticipated, in accordance with that spirit of justice and good
                                    neighborhood which has always been manifested by our laws as
                                    well as by our treaties with all friendly powers.</p>
                                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Richard B.
                                        Hubbard.</hi></signed></closer>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No.
                                            417–Translation.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Count <persName type="from">Ito</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Hubbard</persName>.</hi></head>
                                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Department for Foreign
                                                  Affairs</hi>,<lb/><placeName><hi rend="italic">Tokio</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="japanese-nengō" when="1887-12-24"><hi rend="italic">the 24th day, the 12th month, the
                                                  20th year of
                                        Meiji</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to
                                        acknowledge the receipt of your excellency’s note elated the
                                        9th instant, transmitting a copy of a communication from the
                                        honorable the Secretary of State, in which he expresses
                                        regret at the nonacceptance by His Imperial Japanese
                                        Majesty’s Governmentof the invitation of the United States
                                        to enter into a convention for the abolition of tonnage or
                                        other equivalent charges on merchant vessels plying between
                                        Japan and the United States.</p>
                                    <p>The nature of Mr. Bayard’s reply leads me to believe that he
                                        has slightly misapprehended the exact meaning of my former
                                        note on this subject.</p>
                                    <p>You will recollect that Mr. Bayard, in his instruction of the
                                        9th July last, a copy of which you forwarded to Count
                                        Inouye, intimated that the shipping acts under which his
                                        invitation was extended were sufficiently comprehensive to
                                        cover either a reduction or a complete abolition of tonnage
                                        and equivalent charges, and in the same connection ho added,
                                        “It is open to any foreign country in all or any of whose
                                        ports a less charge is made than that now imposed in the
                                        ports of the United States to obtain forthwith a reduction
                                        in the United States on vessels from such port or ports to
                                        an equality with that levied in the port or ports
                                        designated.”</p>
                                    <p>In replying to the invitation of the Government of the United
                                        States, I pointed out the reasons which prevented His
                                        Imperial Japanese Majesty’s Government from entering into an
                                        arrangement having for its object the complete extinction of
                                        all customs charges in respect of merchant shipping. In
                                        order, however, that vessels proceeding from Japan to the
                                        United States might, to a limited extent at least, take
                                        advantage of the acts in question, I took occasion to assure
                                        you that no tonnage dues were levied in the ports of Japan
                                        on vessels of the United States, and that such vessels were,
                                        in the matter of fees, placed upon a national as well as the
                                        most favored nation footing.</p>
                                    <p>The exemption of vessels of the United States from tonnage
                                        dues is already a matter of conventional understanding
                                        between our respective Governments, as will be seen by
                                        reference to article 6 of the trade regulations attached to
                                        the treaty of 1858. It was consequently more particularly in
                                        the direction of equivalent or other shipping charges that
                                        His Imperial Japanese Majesty’s Government were unable to
                                        accept the proposal of the United States.</p>
                                    <p>Having in view the fact, however, that those charges are
                                        considerably less than the tonnage dues ordinarily imposed
                                        in the United States, I beg to inquire what the future
                                        status of Japanese and other vessels proceeding thither will
                                        be in respect of navigation charges.</p>
                                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Count Hirobumi
                                            Ito</hi>.</signed></closer>
                                </frus:attachment>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>