<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of European Regional Affairs
                    ( (Parsons) ) to the Director of International Security Affairs ( (Cabot) ) and
                    to the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs (
                    (Bonbright))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recxoy5ut8BiKquym" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006004857"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Littoral</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="132"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/8–951</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of European
                        Regional Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PJG1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Parsons</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of International Security
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CTD1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">and to the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State
                        for European Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BJCH1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bonbright</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-09">August 9,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Need for Action to Demonstrate U.S. Interest in North
                    Atlantic Concept</p>
                <p>Evidence is piling up that our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> partners are
                    worried at our seeming preoccupation with the military aspects of <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and fear that we are losing sight of the
                    wider objectives of defending and improving democratic institutions and economic
                    progress of western civilization, including progressively closer long-range
                    association in North Atlantic and European communities in non-military as well
                    as military fields (<gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 161, August 4).<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d132fn1">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In mid-September we hope and expect to obtain the admission of Greece and Turkey;
                    the justification for pressing on with this is again primarily military and
                    strategic, specifically the armed strength of Turkey. At this same time we are
                    dispatching a military survey team to Spain and there are negotiations in
                    progress or pending for bases, surveys or other military requirements in Norway,
                    Portugal, France, the North African littoral, etc. Last, but not least, we will
                    have discussed Germany in tripartite meetings just before the Ottawa meeting and
                    here again our goal is to bring German military potential into being. These
                    operations, if not balanced by evidence of our interest in non-military
                    objectives of the Atlantic Treaty, are bound to disturb our <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> partners still further and their concern will
                    be reflected at the September Council meetings. Unless we are prepared to deal
                    with the situation promptly, it is conceivable that it could develop almost
                    critical proportions.</p>
                <p>(Evidence of the worries of our allies is most strikingly set forth in <pb
                        facs="0279" n="241" xml:id="pg_241"/> the last paragraph of <gloss
                        target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 157, August 2,<note n="2" xml:id="d132fn2"
                        >Not printed.</note> in which Mike <persName corresp="#p_PLB1"
                        >Pearson</persName> is quoted as telling <persName corresp="#p_ATC1"
                        >Achilles</persName> that he had frequently been asked in the course of his
                    European trip if the U.S. had decided that its objective was not to prevent a
                    war, but rather to win one. Further evidence of concern at the psychological
                    malaise in Europe and some thoughtful exploration of how to counteract it may be
                    seen in <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 1045, June I,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d132fn3">Not printed.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KM1"
                        >Katz</persName>’ telegram No. <gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss> 3411,
                    July 16, from Paris,<note n="3" xml:id="d132fn4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_219">p. 219</ref>.</note> and
                        <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 161, August 4,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d132fn5">Not printed.</note> paras 7 to 9 inclusive.)</p>
                <p>It appears inevitable that there will be a real effort at Ottawa: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>To seek reassurance from the U.S. as to where we are really trying to
                            go, and</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>To take some action to reaffirm the “North Atlantic concept”.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Under these circumstances, instead of waiting for the preoccupations of our
                    allies to deepen and to find expression at Ottawa, it would be to our advantage
                    to take the initiative (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) before the September meeting
                    of the Council and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) at the meeting. Our objectives
                    would include the following: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>An effort to overcome impressions that we value <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> only for such military security as we
                            can develop through it.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Further reassurance that the United States is interested in preventing
                            a war and that our strength, when developed, will never be used for
                            aggressive purposes.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>An attempt to counteract impressions that We seek to dominate partners
                            in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> by imposing upon them our
                            settled policies and to demonstrate our desire to take account of their
                            views in formative stages of policy making.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Development of a more positive attitude on the part of European
                            members towards <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, which is after
                            all so fundamentally a program of mutual self-help and self-preservation
                            requiring European leadership and drive as well as American.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Reaffirmation of our awareness that the defense build-up and
                            increasing economic strength are not only mutually consistent but
                            mutually necessary (<gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss> 3411), and
                            indication that the present intensive phase of build-up is the
                            investment stage which, once made, will permit a resumption of build-up
                            of civilian well-being.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Some expression of our simultaneous interest in <hi rend="italic"
                                >a</hi>) European integration, and <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                            long-range development of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> (so as
                            to forestall British and Northern European fears of an eventual
                            Berlin–Paris–Rome Axis unbalanced by a broader grouping).</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Possibilities for specific action thus far apparent would appear to be: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>Telegram to inform <persName>Stikker</persName> that his interest and
                            initiative (<gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss> 3411 and <gloss
                                target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 1045) is appreciated and we would
                            be interested in hearing any ideas which he had developed. (Such a
                            telegram to The Hague, repeated to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            capitals is in preparation.)</item>
                        <pb facs="0280" n="242" xml:id="pg_242"/>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>Instruction to <persName corresp="#p_SCM1">Spofford</persName> and to
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> capitals to use thinking
                            herein as background in talks with <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            government officials.</item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>Consideration here in Washington as to whether Secretary would
                            incorporate some of these thoughts in his general statement to the
                            Council in Ottawa or whether some development of them should be used by
                            him in a special statement introducing this subject as a separate agenda
                            item.</item>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>Issuance of a Council press release or declaration at end of meeting
                            reaffirming long-range and wider (especially non-military) objectives of
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_Depto1"
                                >Depto</gloss> 171, August 8,<note n="4" xml:id="d132fn6">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> develops this thought further
                            as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Declaration of intention. What we have in mind is declaration by
                                    Council that, without prejudice to developments in wider
                                    frameworks such as UN or <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss>,
                                    or smaller frameworks such as <gloss target="#t_EUR1"
                                        >EUR</gloss>, parties to <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                                        >NAT</gloss> expect to work towards progressively closer
                                    long-term association ‘between any or all of them’ in all fields
                                    by limited and practical steps to extent that experience
                                    demonstrates necessity for such action to advance their common
                                    interests. Ref to ‘any or all’ would be included in view both of
                                    Eur def force and of attitude of some toward Gr Turk
                                    membership.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </item>
                        <label>5)</label>
                        <item>Possibility of creation by the President of a public commission to
                            study the subject of Atlantic cooperation and the progressive
                            development of closer association among nations of the Atlantic
                            Community. (See Appendix.<note n="5" xml:id="d132fn7">Not
                                printed.</note>)</item>
                        <label>6)</label>
                        <item>Rapid development of our various ideas as to means of strengthening
                            the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> organization so that they
                            might be used in September either formally in the Council or informally
                            in private talks where they would at least help to demonstrate the
                            vitality of our interest in and thinking about <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                                >NATO</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>7)</label>
                        <item>Some exploration of the possibility of expanding foreign policy
                            coordination among the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> nations.
                            The example of the British Commonwealth where coordination is promoted
                            in part by an extensive, continuous interchange of information among the
                            partners, who nevertheless maintain their freedom to differ and to
                            negotiate on their differences, is worthy of study as a possible avenue
                            to greater policy coordination in the Atlantic Community. <gloss
                                target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 171 cites already existing interest
                            in this general approach on the part of <persName corresp="#p_LHM1"
                                >Lange</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TVSS1"
                                >Starkenborgh</persName> who has said that, in his opinion, it would
                            be the most practicable and useful step which could be taken in the near
                            future in the direction of closer Atlantic association.</item>
                        <label>8)</label>
                        <item>Initiation of program based on the undertaking of the <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> nations in Article 2, to strengthen
                            their free institutions and develop better understanding of (democratic)
                            principles. <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 171 suggests Council
                            action looking toward establishment of a high-level <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> advisory committee, the members of
                            which would head national advisory committees. Aided by the <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> Information Service staff as well as
                            by a working group of persons competent in the field of intellectual and
                            psychological mobilization, projects could be worked out for the <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> advisory and also the national
                            committees to promote. <pb facs="0281" n="243" xml:id="pg_243"/> Success
                            would be dependent upon the selection of outstanding personalities and
                            the goal of this idea (which is developed more fully in <gloss
                                target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 171) would be to obtain action in
                            the informational and cultural field to promote in growing association
                            with each other a more “dynamic counter-attraction to Communism” in the
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries and beyond.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Action Recommended</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1) That a telegram be sent to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SCM1"
                        >Spofford</persName> not later than Monday, August 13 embodying reactions to
                    this memo and to <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 171.</p>
                <p>2) That study be given to the list of objectives herein (which we by no means
                    consider inclusive) and to the list of possible action measures with a view to
                    developing a concrete program as rapidly as possible. Responsibility for working
                    up this study and coordinating with other offices should be centered in <gloss
                        target="#t_RA1">RA</gloss>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
