<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Delegation on the Temporary Council Committee to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-12T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-12T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-12T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-12T10:00:00-05:00" n="172"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/10–1251: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States Delegation on the
                            Temporary Council Committee</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d172fn1">Repeated to all <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss> capitals.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-12T16:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 12, 1951—4 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Repsec1">Repsec</gloss> 30. From <gloss target="#t_USDel1"
                        >USDel</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_TCC1">TCC</gloss>. Re <gloss target="#t_Repsec1"
                        >Repsec</gloss> 29, rptd London <gloss target="#t_Repna1">Repna</gloss> 88
                    and <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> missions.<note n="2" xml:id="d172fn2"
                        >Dated October 11, <ref target="#pg_308">p. 308</ref>.</note> Fol is final
                    text terms of ref Executive Bureau: <list>
                        <item>“1. In accordance with Council resolution on C7–D/19, 1951, there
                            shall be an executive bureau of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                                >NATO</gloss> temporary Council Comite. This bureau is composed of
                            the chairman and the two vice chairmen of the comite. The comite may
                            subsequently appoint any other members of the comite to the Executive
                            Bureau if necessary according to circumstances, with a view to
                            expediting the work of the comite.</item>
                        <item>“2. The Executive Bureau will in all phases of its work be under the
                            general guidance and direction of the comite.</item>
                        <item>“3. The Executive Bureau is empowered in the name of the comite to
                            call upon member govts and mil and civilian <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                                >NATO</gloss> agencies for info, advice and assistance in accordance
                            with paras 3 and 4 of the Council resolution. It will be the task of the
                            Executive Bureau and the secretariat to keep the members of the comite
                            informed as fully as possible of the requests for info being made to the
                            various agencies of their govts.</item>
                        <item>“4. The Executive Bureau shall prepare for the consideration of the
                            comite a proposed general course of action. It shall be responsible for
                            all necessary preparatory work to permit final appraisal by the comite:
                                (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of the ‘requirements of external
                            security, in particular of fufilling a mil acceptable <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> plan for the defense of Western Eur’,
                            and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of the ‘realistic politico-economic
                            capabilities of member countries’.</item>
                        <item>“5. To this end, in the consideration of the capabilities or programs
                            of any member country not represented in the Executive Bureau, <pb
                                facs="0353" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> that country’s member of the
                            comite shall for this purpose be a member of the Executive Bureau. In
                            the consideration of the capabilities or programs of each of the
                            countries represented in the Executive Bureau, there shall be appointed
                            as a member of the Executive Bureau for this purpose one other member of
                            the comite.</item>
                        <item>“6. The Executive Bureau shall be responsible for preparing for the
                            consideration of the comite, draft findings, and the basis therefor,
                            including courses of action.</item>
                        <item>“7. The Executive Bureau shall meet with the full comite to report
                            progress on its work whenever the comite shall determine or at the call
                            of the chairman.</item>
                        <item>“8. The Executive Bureau will arrange to keep other member govts fully
                            informed of the progress of the work.” (<hi rend="italic">End
                            Text</hi>)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Fol is text communiqué mentioned <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> temporary Council Comite, created
                        at the recent Ottawa conference, completed this afternoon its first series
                        of meetings. The comite has started immediately on the task set for it by
                        the North Atlantic Council, which is to analyse the problem of reconciling
                        the requirements of fulfilling a mil acceptable <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss> defense plan with the realistic politico-economic
                        capabilities of member countries. After meeting yesterday with Gen <persName
                            corresp="#p_E1">Eisenhower</persName> at <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1"
                            >SHAPE</gloss> for a general review of the mil aspects of the problem,
                        the comite met today to complete its organization and to lay out a general
                        plan of work.</p>
                    <p>“At its first meeting on Tuesday the comite elected as its chairman Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Averell Harriman</persName>, of the US, and
                        as its vice-chairmen, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GH1">Hugh
                            Gaitskell</persName>, of the United Kingdom, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_MJ2">M. Jean Monnet</persName> of Fr. The comite designated
                        as its secretary Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NSS1">Sigurd Nielsen</persName>
                        of Norway, a member of the international secretariat of <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> previously assigned to the Council
                        deputies.</p>
                    <p>“As envisaged by the North Atlantic Council at Ottawa, the comite has formed
                        an Executive Bureau composed of its chairman its two vice-chairmen. Acting
                        under the guidance and direction of the comite, the Executive Bureau will
                        organize the necessary preparatory work to permit the comite to make its
                        appraisals of defense requirements and economic capabilities and to develop
                        its recommendations. During the consideration of each country’s program, the
                        rep of that country on the comite will also serve as a member of the
                        Executive Bureau. In addition, the comite will add other members to the
                        bureau as needed, in particular when the bureau is considering the programs
                        of the United States, the United Kingdom and Fr.</p>
                    <p>“Arrangements are being made to keep all members of the comite fully informed
                        at all times of the bureau’s work. The comite will be assisted in its work
                        by all the permanent <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> agencies.</p>
                    <p>“The comite was in unanimous agreement that these arrangements wld provide an
                        efficient working method to carry out in the limited time available the
                        heavy responsibilities laid upon it. The spirit of close solidarity and of
                        complete participation on the part of all the member countries on a footing
                        of equality in the common task of the comite agreed by all to be the basis
                        on which the comite wld carry on its work.”</p>
                </quote>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
