<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Supreme Allied Commander, Europe ( (Eisenhower) ) to the Chairman of the
                    Temporary Council Committee ( (Harriman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d205</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">205</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-12-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-12-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="205"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d205">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/12–1451</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Supreme Allied Commander, Europe</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_E1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Eisenhower</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Chairman of the Temporary Council
                        Committee</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HWA1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d205fn1">The text of <persName corresp="#p_E1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName>’s letter was transmitted to the Department of
                        State in telegram <gloss target="#t_Repna1">Repna</gloss> circular 13 from
                        Paris, December 14; it was repeated to Heidelberg, Luxembourg, London, and
                        Ottawa.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-12-14">December 14 (?),
                            1951</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I am happy to know that your entire comite is now mtg to put its work into final
                    form. Responding to your request for my personal <pb facs="0416" n="378"
                        xml:id="pg_378"/> comment on the comite’s draft “plan of action”, I can
                    offer only broad comments since we here at <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1"
                        >SHAPE</gloss> have had no opportunity for exhaustive study.</p>
                <p>My first comment is that the results of the work of the Temporary Council Comite
                    and of its Screening and Costing Staff represent a truly monumental piece of
                    work. The participants in that task will certainly deserve a real tribute from
                    the whole <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> community if they are able to
                    complete their difficult work as effectively as they have advanced it thus far.
                    I am impressed not only by the spirit of cooperation that must have animated the
                    members of the comite in achieving the kind of agreement that is represented but
                    also by the objective manner in which they have tackled this most difficult
                    problem.</p>
                <p>I have the feeling that we are really seeing for the first time the dimensions,
                    in terms of an integrated mil, econ, and fin effort, of our build-up task. It
                    will be a real milestone in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> development to
                    have carried out with this degree of success the difficult task of reconciling
                    rapid build-up of security forces with practical limitations in the econ field
                    and to have one [<hi rend="italic">won?</hi>] this through joint and cooperative
                    action.</p>
                <p>The gen approach indicated in the plan of building a balanced combat-effective
                    force at the maximum rate which the availability of resources will permit is
                    clearly one which affords strong support to the fulfillment of the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> mission entrusted to me and, accordingly, I
                    heartily welcome it. I think your comite has reached something both practical
                    and effective in your handling of the programs proposed for each of the next
                    three years. I assume this same method of operation wld be continued until the
                    full requirements, necessary for the planned strategy, were provided for. In my
                    opinion, the forces envisaged are such as to provide a sound basis for actions
                    utilizing the resources which will become available during the coming year. I am
                    ready to assist in every way I can in the attainment in the greatest possibly
                    measure of the “maximum practicable” goals you have shown.</p>
                <p>The standards for maiming, training, equipping, and providing cadres are directly
                    related to this build-up of def forces. Those proposed as interim standards for
                    1952 seem well designed as gen guides which will contribute during the coming
                    year to the maximum practicable build-up of effective forces. In this field also
                        <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss> will be in a position to advise and
                    assist in making the best practicable application of this guidance to the
                    particular forces and particular circumstances of each country.</p>
                <p>From my own standpoint, and in the interest of saving time, I wld welcome the
                    immediate and urgent initiation by the countries of the actions recommended in
                    1952 for the achievement of the build-up program. It is understood, of course,
                    that Parliaments will have to determine <pb facs="0417" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"
                    /> the eventual levels, but the temporary council comite has already achieved a
                    great deal by cooperative action in preparing a program for the consideration of
                    the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> nations. If our joint effort follows
                    the broad lines that <gloss target="#t_TCC1">TCC</gloss> is suggesting, and if
                    it reaches the levels recommended, it is clear to me that there shld be full
                    value recd in return, in terms of a more rapid development of defensive
                    capability and creation of a real deterrent to aggression in West Eur.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<persName corresp="#p_E1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Eisenhower</hi>
                        </persName>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
