<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-02-20T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-02-20T12:00:00-05:00" n="256" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d256">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/2–2051: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy Representative on the
                                    North Atlantic Council</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SCM1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Spofford</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-02-20T17:00:00+00:00">February 20, 1951—5 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 534. 1. Reference
                                appointment Supreme Allied Commander Atlantic. <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 531<note n="1" xml:id="d256fn1">Not printed.</note> reported UK concurrence still outstanding.
                                Private inquiry indicates British desire some limitation of powers
                                of naval commanders. Precise nature not stated. Foreign Office hopes
                                prevail Defense Ministry concur appointment under terms proposed
                                resolution since latter joined in approving <gloss target="#t_DC1">DC</gloss>–24/2<note n="1" xml:id="d256fn2">Not printed.</note>
                                at fourth meeting <gloss target="#t_DC1">DC</gloss> and thresh out
                                terms of reference later. Meantime final actions deputies held up
                                which hope will not be for long.</p>
                            <p>2. To meet views expressed yesterday’s meeting <gloss target="#t_Dep1">Dep</gloss>s as well as your telephone message
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ATC1">Achilles</persName> transmit below
                                revised draft press communiqué for reconsideration at tomorrow’s
                                meeting deputies. Revised draft also being transmitted <persName corresp="#p_DGCE1">De Greef</persName>:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“<hi rend="italic">Verbatim text:</hi> Admiral <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">William M. Fechteler</persName> of the
                                    United States Navy has been named Supreme Allied Commander
                                    Atlantic, the North Atlantic Council Deputies announced
                                    today.</p>
                                <p>The North Atlantic Council, acting on recommendations adopted by
                                    the Defense Committee at its October meeting in Washington and
                                    its meeting in Brussels last December, requested the United
                                    States to designate an officer to fill the post of Supreme
                                    Allied Commander Atlantic. The President of the United States
                                    subsequently designated Admiral <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName>, whose nomination has now been
                                    unanimously approved by the North Atlantic Treaty Defense
                                    Ministers and the North Atlantic Council Deputies.</p>
                                <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName> will be
                                    supported by an integrated international staff drawn from the
                                    countries contributing forces to the North Atlantic <pb facs="0513" n="475" xml:id="pg_475"/> Ocean Command. This
                                    command and General <persName corresp="#p_E1">Eisenhower</persName>’s Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers
                                    Europe are mutually supporting commands which will coordinate
                                    their activities under the guidance of the standing group.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>If you desire further changes above, request notification prior
                                tomorrow’s meeting.</p>
                            <p>3. Re <gloss target="#t_Todep1">Todep</gloss> 259<note n="2" xml:id="d256fn3">Not printed.</note> timing release impossible
                                pending final action deputies. Plan is Chairman Council Deputies
                                will notify release time to all concerned thereafter.</p>
                            <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName> appointment
                                carried briefly most London morning papers attributed to official
                                announcement Copenhagen of Danish Government approval. No
                                interpretative or speculative comment except in <hi rend="italic">Mail</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Telegraph</hi> which played
                                front page with guarded speculation on scope of command. Do not
                                believe this should change plans for simultaneous release
                                Washington, London, Brussels.<note n="3" xml:id="d256fn4">In
                                    telegram <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 543 from London
                                    dated February 21, <persName corresp="#p_SCM1">Spofford</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_KRB1">Knight</persName> that the British were ready to concur in
                                    the appointment of Admiral <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName> but only if the last sentence of the
                                    American resolution pertaining to <gloss target="#t_SACLANT1">SACLANT</gloss>’s powers and functions was deleted. “In
                                    these circumstances,” <persName corresp="#p_SCM1">Spofford</persName> added, “I propose withhold US agreement
                                    pending resolution of difficulty in accordance with your
                                    telephone instruction.” (740.5/2–2151) In telegram <gloss target="#t_Depto1">Depto</gloss> 545 of the same day,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SCM1">Spofford</persName> informed the
                                    Secretary of State that action on the <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName> appointment had been
                                    deferred at the 12th meeting of the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> Deputies pending concurrence of the United
                                    Kingdom. He added that the Netherlands stated approval of the
                                    appointment subject to the stipulation that the Atlantic Command
                                    would not infringe upon the North Sea area currently under
                                    British Home Fleet Command. (740.5/2–2151) In Telegram <gloss target="#t_Todep1">Todep</gloss> 268 of the following day,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName> informed
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SCM1">Spofford</persName> that he was
                                    to use his own judgment “as to whether or not action shld be
                                    pressed at tomorrow’s mtg deputies. While we wld welcome early
                                    settlement, we wish to avoid deadlock or open split in <gloss target="#t_Dep1">Dep</gloss>s. Therefore may be advisable
                                    let dust settle to ascertain effect of debate” currently going
                                    on in the British Parliament concerning the British position on
                                    an Atlantic Command “before proceeding further. If appropriate
                                    you might remind British that UK has accepted <gloss target="#t_DC1">DC</gloss> 24/3 at Council level and 24/2 at
                                    Defense Comite level which clearly set forth pattern and
                                    principles for current action re appointment <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName>.”
                                    (740.5/2–2251)</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SCM1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Spofford</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>