<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Draft Anglo-United States Agreement Prepared by the United Kingdom
                    Representative on the Standing Group ( (Elliot))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-07-13T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-07-14T22:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receiqhGHZGpcOok4" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">SACEUR</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-07-14T22:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-07-13T23:00:00-05:00" n="295"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/7–1451</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Anglo-United States Agreement Prepared by the United
                        Kingdom Representative on the Standing Group</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_EAMWC1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Elliot</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d295fn1">A covering memorandum by Admiral
                            <persName>Sherman</persName> dated July 14 stated that the source text
                        was handed to him by Air Marshal <persName corresp="#p_EAMWC1"
                            >Elliot</persName>, and that <persName>Sherman</persName> had examined
                        the source text, considered it “satisfactory from a military point of view.”
                        Admiral <persName>Sherman</persName> added, however, that it was doubtful if
                        Egypt would agree to subparagraph (5). <persName>Sherman</persName>
                        recommended that the U.S. Representative on the Standing Group, Admiral
                            <persName corresp="#p_WVAJ1">Wright</persName>, be instructed to agree
                        to Standing Group action along the lines of the British draft “insofar as
                        its military features are concerned.” Political features of the draft would
                        have to be resolved on the political level. (740.5/7–1451) The source text
                        and Admiral <persName>Sherman</persName>’s memorandum were sent to Deputy
                        Under Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName>,
                        Admiral <persName corresp="#p_WVAJ1">Wright</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_RA1">RA</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_SISA1">S/ISA</gloss>.
                        An undated covering memorandum conveying these documents from <gloss
                            target="#t_RA1">RA</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_SISA1">S/ISA</gloss>
                        reads: “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CTD1">Cabot</persName>, I understand this
                        to be the latest paper submitted by UK to Standing Group, <persName
                            corresp="#p_MEM1">Ed Martin</persName>.” Italicized portions printed
                        here are in the source text.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                            calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1951-07-14T23:59:59-04:00"
                            notBefore="1951-07-14T00:00:00-04:00" when="1951-07">July
                        1951</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Command in the Mediterranean and the Middle East</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The U.S. Joint Chiefs of Staff, together with representatives of the Department
                    of State and representatives of the British Embassy and British Joint Services
                    Mission, suggest that the following tentative <pb facs="0598" n="560"
                        xml:id="pg_560"/> proposals be put to Governments regarding Command in the
                    Mediterranean, South East Europe and the Middle East:—</p>
                <p>(1) Greece and Turkey should be admitted as full members of <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    <hi rend="italic">subject in the case of the latter to Turkish agreement to play
                        a full part in the defense of the Middle East under an Allied Middle East
                        Command</hi>.</p>
                <p>(See below.)</p>
                <p>(2) There should be an Allied Middle East Command on the Headquarters of which
                    will be included, U.S., U.K., Commonwealth, French and Turkish officers. This
                    Headquarters would command such forces as members of <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> and their associates made available for the defence of the
                    Middle East area, it being understood that <hi rend="italic">at this time no
                        U.S. forces would be so available</hi>.</p>
                <p>(3) The Middle East Command will be <hi rend="italic">closely associated with
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> by means of a special system of
                        control, the form of which will require elaboration in further detail. This
                        should be effected by the action of the four <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss> members of the Middle East command, namely France, Turkey,
                        U.K., and U.S.A., whose representatives might meet in Washington</hi>.</p>
                <p>(4) There should be a Supreme Allied Commander, Middle East, who should be a
                    British officer. The U.S. will use their good offices to make this proposal
                    acceptable to the Turks. Consideration should be given to offering the Turks <hi
                        rend="italic">some high appointment in the Command Organisation</hi>.</p>
                <p>(5) The Headquarters of the Supreme Allied Commander, Middle East, should <hi
                        rend="italic">if possible be located in Egypt. Egypt should be offered
                        participation in the Command Organisation in return for placing the
                        necessary facilities at the disposal of <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss> forces</hi>.</p>
                <p>(6) Greece will form part of <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss>’s Command
                    but be represented at the Allied Headquarters, Middle East, by a liaison
                    mission.</p>
                <p>(7) Turkey will form part of <gloss target="#t_SACME1">SACME</gloss>’s Command
                    but will be represented at Headquarters, Allied Forces, Southern Europe, by a
                    liaison mission.</p>
                <p>(8) In the Mediterranean, the C-in-C, Allied Forces, Southern Europe (who is also
                    C-in-C, U.S. Naval Forces, Mediterranean), and the C-in-C, British Mediterranean
                    Fleet will each control his own forces and bases and will be responsible for the
                    security of his own sea communications, subject to such joint allocations of
                    area responsibilities as may be mutually agreed upon from time to time. Each
                    would maintain liaison at the other’s Headquarters.</p>
                <p>(9) In order to obtain the voluntary co-operation of Middle Eastern countries in
                    the defence of the Middle East, there should be established a Middle East
                    Defence Board, <hi rend="italic">consisting of political and military
                        representatives of</hi> the U.S., U.K., France, and Turkey. <hi
                        rend="italic">These four countries would invite countries able and willing
                        to contribute substantially to the defence of the area to be associated with
                        them on the board. Consideration should be given to the manner in which the
                        Commonwealth countries should be associated with the Middle East Defence
                        Board. There should be individual liaison arrangements between the Board and
                        the Middle East states not represented thereon</hi>. The Board would be
                    responsible to the countries participating in its <pb facs="0599" n="561"
                        xml:id="pg_561"/> membership. The Board would act in an advisory and
                    consultative capacity to national agencies and also to <gloss target="#t_SACME1"
                        >SACME</gloss>.</p>
                <p>(10) Any action towards the establishment of the Middle East Defence Board must
                    await the admission of Turkey to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
