<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States High Commissioner for Germany ( (McCloy) ) to the Secretary
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d428</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">428</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-03-17T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-03-17T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-17T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-17T08:00:00-05:00" n="428"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d428">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762A.5/3–1751: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="#p_MJJ1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d428fn1">This telegram was repeated to Paris and
                        London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfurt</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-17T14:00:00+01:00"
                            >March 17, 1951—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Ger defense contingent.</p>
                <p>7841. <persName corresp="#p_BA1">Bérard</persName> yesterday informally advised
                    me that predicated on his own recent visit to Paris and subsequent discussion
                    with <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Theodor Blank</persName>
                    <pb facs="0818" n="780" xml:id="pg_780"/> he has distinct impression mutually
                    satis solution will be evolved for present divergent Ger-Fr views re Ger defense
                    contingent and particularly differences concerning unit size and command. Stated
                        <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName> had indicated his hopeful view
                    was based on report which <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> and he
                    had recd from <persName corresp="#p_M1">De Maiziere</persName> that definite
                    progress is being made at Paris mtgs. <persName corresp="#p_BA1"
                        >Bérard</persName> stressed importance which Fr and <persName
                        corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BT1"
                        >Blank</persName> attach to creation true Eur army as real step toward
                    Fr-Ger <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi>. Further indicated Fr prepared and
                    believes Ger similarly ready make concessions in view political importance
                    achieving Eur army concept rather than adhering to rigid proposals their
                    respective mil experts. Also indicated chief Fr concern is not so primarily with
                    regard to actual unit size or other technical factors but rather to safeguard
                    against any possible recreation of a Ger army. Fear of latter possibility is
                    apparently chief Fr objection to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> concept.
                    Particularly emphasized that as time is important requisite for obtaining Fr-Ger
                    agreement on major broad aspects of matter US shld refrain from urging haste or
                    exerting pressure either here or in Paris or via <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>. Stressed that Fr consider Eur army is most far-reaching
                    factor for genuine Eur integration and development better Fr-Ger relationship
                    far surpassing <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan toward
                    achieving this all important end. Further urged that since creation Eur army
                    realistically depends on Fr and Gers it shld so far as feasible be left to these
                    two elements to work out satis solution. <persName corresp="#p_BA1"
                        >Bérard</persName> conceded US cld probably force a solution on Fr but was
                    certain Fr people wld ultimately recognize and resent such pressure thereby long
                    range purpose of better Fr-Ger relationship wld be defeated.</p>
                <p>Expressed hope I wld therefore counsel against haste or pressure on US part in
                    this matter and in favor of giving Fr further opportunity play major role in
                    working out satis solution with Gers. <persName corresp="#p_BA1"
                        >Bérard</persName> thought this wld be facilitated through discussion being
                    handled primarily by non-mil reps with political considerations playing
                    important role rather than sole emphasis on technical mil aspects. Have not
                    checked with <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName> correctness of
                        <persName corresp="#p_BA1">Bérard</persName>’s report of <persName
                        corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_BT1"
                        >Blank</persName> attitude.<note n="2" xml:id="d428fn2">Telegram 640, March
                        20, from Bonn, not printed, reported that <persName corresp="#p_BT1"
                            >Blank</persName> had told American representatives in Bonn that he was
                        most pessimistic about the European army talks in Paris and did not expect
                        any concrete results to emerge. <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName>
                        said that the French had made it obvious that they would not accept German
                        units large enough to play an autonomous military role for fear that the
                        Germans would use them to involve the French in a war of liberation of the
                        east German territories and that, despite French agreement to discuss mixed
                        corps in the Military Committee of the conference, they had privately told
                        the Germans that French public opinion would never agree to such an
                        arrangement. (762A.5/3–2051)</note> I stated that US position had
                    consistently been to permit full opportunity for Paris negots to produce results
                    and provided negots are not too protracted and results are militarily
                    practicable this wld presumably continue to be our attitude. I naturally made no
                    commitment <pb facs="0819" n="781" xml:id="pg_781"/> which wld preclude our
                    resuming active role any time we consider Fr-Ger efforts not producing desired
                    results and in meantime to do nothing which cld appear to be putting pressure on
                    Fr, particularly in regard to units which issue can be better settled in Paris.
                    I feel this is practicable as a number of issues remain which can be explored
                    here without any deliberate dragging of feet.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
