<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bruce) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d527</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">527</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-12-13T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-12-13T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Taxation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-12-13T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-13T11:00:00-05:00" n="527"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d527">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/12–1351: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BDKE1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bruce</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d527fn1">This telegram was repeated for information to
                        London, Bonn, Rome, Brussels, The Hague, and Luxembourg.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-12-13T17:00:00+01:00"
                            >December 13, 1951—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3533. Attn <persName corresp="#p_KRB1">Ridgway Knight</persName>. Subj is Eur Def
                    Force. Re <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 3412, Dec. 8.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d527fn2">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. Fol is a summary of Mins discussions at Strasbourg on <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                        >EDC</gloss> based on preliminary conversations with <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> and conf Secretariat who returned to
                    Paris late yesterday. Other heads of delegations returning <pb facs="1002"
                        n="964" xml:id="pg_964"/> Paris only today for steering comit meeting this
                    afternoon. We hope to obtain a clearer picture after we have had a chance to
                    canvass various delegates.</p>
                <p>2. Discussion ranged over most of outstanding questions during all-day session
                    which lasted until 1:30 Wednesday morning. Few definite decisions were taken,
                    altho conf Secretariat tells us that points of view of Mins on several important
                    questions were brought considerably closer together. Next meeting will open Dec
                    27 (earliest date on which all Mins cld be present); Mins then plan to continue
                    meeting until questions requiring their decision have been cleared up. Present
                    schedule calls for four days.</p>
                <p>3. Despite sharp exchanges, notably between <persName corresp="#p_AK1"
                        >Adenauer</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_ZPV1">Van Zeeland</persName>
                    on Belgians desire to maintain natl forces, atmosphere of this meeting appears
                    to have been much better than at previous mtgs at Paris and Rome. Mins
                    apparently showed real desire to solve issues and reach conclusion by end of
                    year. <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> was particularly impressed
                    with conduct of <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>, which he
                    described as “wise and calm”. Benelux Mins appeared somewhat more conciliatory
                    than at past mtgs, altho they made few of necessary concessions on common
                    financing and common procurement.</p>
                <p>Conf Secretariat claims to be encouraged by results and particularly by general
                    atmosphere of this mtg. They say <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman shares their
                        view. Schuman</persName> was very moved by announcement of remarkable vote
                    of French Assembly on <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan late
                    Tuesday and by ovation he recd from other Mins who realized full favorable
                    implication of this vote. <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_LIM1">Lombardo</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> are, however, discouraged because results did not
                    include clear instructions on particular points at issue before <gloss
                        target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> conf.</p>
                <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> thought that <persName
                        corresp="#p_SPH1">Spaak</persName> resignation from Presidency of Council of
                        Eur<note n="3" xml:id="d527fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SPH1">Paul-Henri Spaak</persName> resigned as
                        President of the Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe on December
                        10.</note> might be significant and useful move. He was also very pleased
                    with <persName corresp="#p_SPH1">Spaak</persName>’s article in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Paris-Presse</hi> yesterday (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>
                        3527).<note n="4" xml:id="d527fn4">The telegram under reference is not
                        printed.</note> He interpreted these actions as <persName corresp="#p_SPH1"
                        >Spaak</persName> taking issue with attitude of <persName corresp="#p_ZPV1"
                        >Van Zeeland</persName>.</p>
                <p>5. No definite conclusions were reached on common budget. <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> claims there was no change in <persName
                        corresp="#p_ZPV1">Van Zeeland</persName>’s insistence on natl armies
                    financed by natl budgets and equipped by natl programs. Conf Secretariat,
                    however, states <persName corresp="#p_ZPV1">Van Zeeland</persName> gave
                    indications he wld abandon his objections to common budget in definitive period.
                    Stikker continued to object to any modification of medium-term defense program
                    already approved by Parliaments of member states. Dutch Finance Min also is
                    apparently reluctant to agree to community control over admins of external aid.
                        <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>, supported by <persName
                        corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>, was very <pb facs="1003" n="965"
                        xml:id="pg_965"/> firm on present French-German position for common
                    financing in initial period and common budget in permanent period. This question
                    will be taken up again on Dec 27, possibly with participation of Finance
                    Mins.</p>
                <p>6. Main problem on composition of forces was <persName corresp="#p_ZPV1">Van
                        Zeeland</persName>’s insistence on maintenance as natl forces of two
                    regiments of Belgium regular army in addition to <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gendarmerie</hi> and Royal Guard. Apparently <persName corresp="#p_BT1"
                        >Blank</persName> in Paris had said he might agree to this. Accordingly
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZPV1">Van Zeeland</persName> was surprised and
                    hard-pressed for explanation when <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>
                    bluntly asked him why this was necessary. <persName corresp="#p_ZPV1">Van
                        Zeeland</persName> made vague argument that Belg was in exception because of
                    “two communities” in Belg state and that these bilingual regiments were symbolic
                    of Flemish-Walloon unity. <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> refused
                    categorically to accept this proposal and said he could not defend <gloss
                        target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> his own Parliament if all other members except
                    Germans were to find reasons to maintain natl forces.</p>
                <p>7. At insistence of <persName corresp="#p_DGA1">De Gasperi</persName>, Mins
                    agreed that during transitional period Assembly shld study: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Means of constituting directly-elected Assembly for <gloss
                                target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>,</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Powers to be given such an Assembly and,</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Any modifications necessary in other institutions to bring system in
                            line. They also agreed that final organization of <gloss
                                target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> shld have “federal or confederal
                            structure” characterized by “bicameral assembly and executive powers.”
                            Stikker was very irritated with <persName corresp="#p_DGA1">De
                                Gasperi</persName> for insisting on this commitment but finally gave
                            in after both <persName corresp="#p_ZPV1">Van Zeeland</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_BJ2">Bech</persName> had agreed.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>8. Mins agreed that recruiting shld remain a natl function but shld be carried
                    out under common rules set out in protocol annexed to treaty. Common rules wld
                    include uniform length of service for recruits in each branch of service from
                    all member states.</p>
                <p>9. <hi rend="italic">Ad referendum</hi> agreement was reached on French
                    compromise formula on designation of officers. It provides that officers of
                    German, French and Italian origin wld be designated by Commissioner but officers
                    of Belg, Luxembourg and Dutch origin could maintain monarchical tradition by
                    having respective sovereigns make appointments on binding recommendations of
                    commissioner. Apparently both natl auths and commissioner have a right of veto.
                    Corps commanders and higher generals wld be appointed by commissioner with
                    unanimous concurrence of Council.</p>
                <p>(Texts of papers approved by Mins on role of Assembly, recruiting, and
                    designation of officers are being cabled separately.<note n="5" xml:id="d527fn5"
                        >Reference here is to telegram 3551, December 13, from Paris, not printed
                        (740.5/12–1351).</note>)</p>
                <p>10. In absence of instructions from Mins, we have pressed <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> to have conf draft treaty on basis of
                    broad French-German-Ital agreement <pb facs="1004" n="966" xml:id="pg_966"/>
                    permitting Benelux countries to make reservations or to submit counter-draft
                    articles as they wish, draft treaty with reservations wld then be ready for
                    decisions at Mins level on Dec 27. <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>
                    agreed and is seeking agreement of <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName>
                    and <persName corresp="#p_LIM1">Lombardo</persName> before this afternoon’s
                    steering comite session. It may be desirable for this approach to be pressed in
                    Rome and in Bonn. Only major obstacle to broad agreement between French, Germans
                    and Itals may be Ital position on French-German proposal for common financing in
                    transitional period. However, Ital objection has been largely based on fact that
                    adequate commitment did not exist for common Assembly to have power of taxation
                    in permanent period. Ital delegation here has always supported French-German
                    proposal even without this commitment. <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> hopes that concession obtained by <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGA1">De Gasperi</persName> in para 7 above will enable
                        <persName corresp="#p_LIM1">Lombardo</persName> to obtain agreement from his
                    govt to go ahead on transitional arrangements.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bruce</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
