<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-10T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-10T03:00:00-05:00" n="545" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d545">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5/1–1051: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy High Commissioner for
                                    Germany</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HMGGP1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hays</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d545fn1">Repeated to Frankfurt and
                                    Heidelberg eyes only for <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HGTT1">Handy</persName>.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bonn</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-10T09:00:00+01:00">January 10, 1951—9 a. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>449. First meeting took place today between representatives of <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> on German military contribution to defense of
                                    Europe.<note n="2" xml:id="d545fn2">The meeting took place
                                    January 9 at Petersberg in the Allied High Commission
                                    building.</note> Present <persName corresp="#p_WJG1">Ward</persName> (chairman), General <persName corresp="#p_WJMGL1">Wansbrough-Jones</persName>, UK; <persName corresp="#p_BA1">Bérard</persName>, General <persName corresp="#p_CJL1">Ganeval</persName>, France; <persName corresp="#p_HMGGP1">Hays</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BBJ1">Buttenwieser</persName>, US; <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName>, Generals <persName corresp="#p_SH2">Speidel</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Heusinger</persName>, Germany. Meeting was informal with no
                                secretariat, record or minutes, and confined to verbal discussion
                                with no written documents exchanged. Brief opening statement by
                                chairman contained the general principle that any military
                                contribution of Germany must be within the framework of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. This was accepted by <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName> as the only method by which
                                Germany would be willing to contribute. Chairman then passed ball to
                                Germans asking their proposals.</p>
                            <pb facs="1029" n="991" xml:id="pg_991"/>
                            <p>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName> asked first the general
                                extent of the military contribution to be expected of Germany; said
                                Chancellor would have to be able to inform the Bundestag of the
                                defense forces provided by other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries for European defense in support of
                                German contribution.</p>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> deputies stated size and
                                composition of contingents to be provided by each country was in
                                planning stage and would be firmed up only after <persName corresp="#p_E1">Eisenhower</persName> had made his defense plan
                                and secured firm commitments from each country concerned. Moreover,
                                necessity for secrecy would prevent disclosures except of very
                                general nature. <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName>
                                acquiesced that only general nature of contribution could be made
                                known but stated that some idea of the numerical extent of German
                                military contribution must be made known to the Bundestag. <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> deputies stated that view of
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> was that maximum German
                                land contribution should be 20 percent of total land forces under
                                command <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss>. Note: British state
                                they interpreted paragraph 24–<hi rend="italic">f</hi> of C
                                    6–D/1<note n="3" xml:id="d545fn3">For text of Document C6–D/1
                                    December 13, 1950, see <ref target="frus1950v03#pg_531">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 531</ref>–<ref target="frus1950v03#pg_547">547</ref>; in particular
                                    footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_538">p. 538</ref>.</note> to mean
                                that German land forces could be one-fifth of other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> forces which would result in
                                German land forces comprising maximum of one-sixth of the total land
                                forces available to <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss>, this
                                interpretation was not commented on by French or US.</p>
                            <p>In order to give the Germans some idea of extent of military
                                contribution which might be expected by them by end of 1951, <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> deputies agreed to seek advice
                                from their governments of a numerical total to include sum of combat
                                and service personnel to be given Germans for planning purposes.
                                (Request advice.)</p>
                            <p>German representatives agreed to formulate their proposals for
                                administrative machinery for recruitment and training and assistance
                                they contemplated should be furnished by Allies in equipment and
                                military instructors for presentation at next meeting.</p>
                            <p>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName> stated <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> did not wish to produce
                                armament as they wanted to convince the world that Germany will not
                                again become a threat to peace of the world. He states, however,
                                there were many items needed by soldiers other than armament which
                                Germany could produce. Chairman pointed out <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> view was that to considerable extent Germany
                                should produce armament for her own needs as capacities of armament
                                industries of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries needed
                                by them selves. <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Blank</persName> agreed
                                to explore this subject further.</p>
                            <p>Meeting held in cordial atmosphere. German representatives seemed
                                sincere and displayed no evasiveness. Date of next meeting agreed
                                10:30 a. m., Tuesday January 16.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>[<persName corresp="#p_HMGGP1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Hays</hi></persName>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>