<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the Four-Power Exploratory Talks (
                    (Jessup) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v03p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d599</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">599</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-03-24T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-03-24T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-24T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-24T10:00:00-05:00" n="599"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d599">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1–PA/3–2451: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the Four-Power Exploratory
                        Talks</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_JPC1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jessup</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d599fn1">Repeated to Moscow, London, Vienna, and
                        Frankfurt.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-24T16:00:00+01:00"
                            >March 24, 1951—4: p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5685. From <persName corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName>. Seventeenth session
                    quadripartite talks devoted discussion Austrian agenda item.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d599fn2">For the text of the Austrian agenda item proposed by the
                        three Western Delegations, see footnote 2, <ref target="#pg_1088">p.
                            1088</ref>.</note> Sov del maintained previous position that: (1) Aust
                    Trieste questions inseparably linked and (2) Sov del desired inclusion Trieste
                    question as separate item on agenda.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Parodi</persName> led off with statement that
                    although divergent Sov and tripartite positions had been developed in previous
                    mtgs deps might <pb facs="1145" n="1107" xml:id="pg_1107"/> turn to question of
                    agreed wording for agenda item relating to Austria. <persName corresp="#p_DEAJ1"
                        >Davies</persName> fol then with query as to whether Sov del cld accept
                    tripartite formulation. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> replied
                    he cld see no reason why deps shld discuss wording this item since question of
                    principle still not agreed. He countered with question as to whether Sov
                    formulation Trieste item acceptable to West. <persName corresp="#p_JPC1"
                        >Jessup</persName> sought clarification <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName>’s remarks since he had not understood that Sov del had
                    ever questioned that <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>s wld discuss Aust
                    question. Again asked whether Sov del willing accept tripartite formulation Aust
                    item. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> replied that problem not
                    one of wording but one of differing opinions. Said tripartite wording presented
                    no real difficulties but Sov del first desired know whether three powers accept
                    Soviet wording re Trieste.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Jessup</persName> recounted previous discussions in
                    which three powers pointed out: (1) no connection between Austria and Ital peace
                    treaty; (2) record of Sov obstruction re conclusion Austrian treaty culminating
                    in introduction extraneous Trieste question at late date; (3) three powers not
                    accept idea any connection between Trieste and fulfillment Moscow agreement
                        1943.<note n="3" xml:id="d599fn3">For the text of the Moscow Declaration on
                        Austria, see <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_761">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 761</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName> inquired whether, if Sov del feels
                        <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>s shld discuss Sov allegations re
                    Ital treaty, it shld be discussed under fulfillments treaty obligations, which
                    occurs in both Sov and tripartite proposals, or whether Sov del thinks agenda
                    shld specify every treaty or agreement concerning which any <gloss
                        target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> might raise questions. Pointed out if
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> taking position <gloss
                        target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>s cannot discuss fulfillment obligations
                    without specific mention of treaty or agreement on agenda, necessary for deps
                    make complete catalogue. <persName corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName> felt this
                    wld load agenda with unnecessary detail.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DEAJ1">Davies</persName> reviewed briefly Sov obstructions
                    re conclusion Aust treaty, making fol points: (1) <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName>’s remarks raised doubts re seriousness Sov intent
                    conclude Aust treaty and Trieste gambit merely pretext for further delay; (2)
                    public opinion clear on fact Sovs attempting escape obligation, assumed under
                    Moscow declaration; (3) no foundation for Sov allegation re Western use of
                    Trieste or Austria as military bases; and (4) if Sovs desire discuss Trieste in
                        <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> mtg, they free do so but this
                    desire no excuse for separate treatment Trieste question in agenda.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> developed familiar argument that
                    Western powers responsible for violating agreements re Austria and for
                    obstructing conclusion Aust treaty by their attitude in London deps mtg, citing
                    Western attitude on specific articles draft Aust treaty as examples. After
                    rejecting <persName corresp="#p_DEAJ1">Davies</persName>’ statement re
                    non-fulfillment Moscow declaration by Sovs, <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> claimed that three powers object each time Sov del puts
                    forth proposals aimed at heart of Potsdam and Moscow declaration.</p>
                <pb facs="1146" n="1108" xml:id="pg_1108"/>
                <p>Sov del stated flatly that Trieste shld be included in agenda as separate item
                    and it was “not sufficient” to consider this question under fulfillment treaty
                    obligations. Re <persName corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName>’s query on listing
                    of other treaties, <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said he had
                    never made such a proposal and could not see why deps shld go to extremes of not
                    listing any treaties or of listing them all.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said no grounds for doubt re
                    seriousness Sov Govt intention conclude Aust treaty and that Sov Govt has more
                    grounds for doubt this connection than West. In countering arguments re late
                    introduction Trieste issue in Aust negotiations by Sovs, <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> traced UN consideration question
                    Trieste contending that West responsible for frustration UN efforts.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> developed familiar argument that
                    US–UK had turned Trieste into military base in violation Ital peace treaty and
                    that Western assurances of no aggressive intent do not change actual state of
                    affairs. After stressing necessity fulfillment treaty obligations, <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> claimed that policy of three powers re
                    Trieste [not?] in keeping with consolidation of peace. Drew parallel between
                    action three powers in Trieste and in West Germany.</p>
                <p>After developing thesis that Western powers not judges their assurances re lack
                    of aggressive intent, <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> applied
                    this reasoning to tripartite proposals re existing levels of armaments. Stated
                    that Western allusions to strength Sov armed forces incorrect and Sov answer
                    given in its note to UK in connection with Anglo-Soviet agreement. Stressed
                    again Sov view that acceptance tripartite proposals would untie hands Western
                    powers re arms race and German demilitarization [<hi rend="italic"
                        >remilitarization?</hi>], citing as evidence recent US announcement that 2.9
                    million men under arms and US armed forces will continue increase.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Dep1">Dep</gloss>s agreed reconvene 4 p. m. Tuesday.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<persName corresp="#p_JPC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jessup</hi>
                        </persName>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
