<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="609" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d609">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">762A00/4–1851</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Director of the Office of German Political
                                    Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_LP1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Laukhuff</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                    the Director of the Bureau of German Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BHA1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Byroade</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">personal</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-18">April 18,
                                    1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName>Hank</persName></hi>: I do not
                                know whether my letters have been of any usefulness to you or not.
                                However, in any event there would seem to be very little reason left
                                for my writing any more letters, except if some special point
                                arises, since the Department has made its decision to give way on
                                the last remaining point concerning Germany. I regret this decision
                                to give way at the last if necessary on the question of putting
                                German demilitarization first. I think it will cause us no end of
                                trouble on the propaganda front as well as put us in a
                                disadvantageous position at a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                                itself. All this in addition to the bad effect of our already having
                                accepted the item in any form. I confess I am almost sorry I ever
                                thought of adding the words “and effects”, which enabled us to get
                                this demilitarization point into item 1. (Delete “almost”!)</p>
                            <p>Incidentally, I understood the Department’s position to be that we
                                would give way on this point only <hi rend="italic">after</hi> all
                                other points are settled satisfactorily. I detect signs here of a
                                disposition to offer this lamb on the altar in an attempt to buy
                                Soviet acceptance of our point of view on other items. I doubt that
                                this would ever work, since the Russians would just gobble it up and
                                move on to wear us out on the other points.</p>
                            <p>Besides, the only real justification which could be advanced for
                                giving way on German demilitarization is that it would meet the
                                British and keep the tripartite front intact. But it is all too
                                clear that this will not placate the British any more than it will
                                the Russians. The British will just grunt, and move on to attack us
                                next for being too rigid on the armaments point, on Trieste, or
                                indeed on <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. For it seems clear
                                that the British will stop at no concession whatever to “meet the
                                Russians” in order to ensure a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>.
                                And it must be a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> with an agreed
                                agenda. They are more adamant in opposing the desire of the French
                                and ourselves to try the “split agenda” (the so-called <persName corresp="#p_PA1">Parodi</persName> formula) than they are in
                                opposing the Soviets.</p>
                            <p>The British attitude here can leave one with only the following
                                conclusions: that they regard the Brussels decisions on Germany as
                                an agreement in principle only, not to be carried forward seriously
                                before a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>; and that they will not
                                even put their hearts into their own rearmament or try to convince
                                their allegedly unwilling public that it is absolutely necessary to
                                re-arm, until they have had a <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                                discussion. These are not their words, but this is increasingly the
                                sense of what they are saying in our tripartite meetings. This is
                                frightening, and it <pb facs="1167" n="1129" xml:id="pg_1129"/>
                                would blow our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> program
                                sky-high if any intimation of such an attitude got out.</p>
                            <p>It does seem to me that we ought to confront the British now, without
                                any further delay, with a completely firm end position and with a
                                frank warning that their position seems to us to add up to what I
                                said in the paragraph above. The more so since the French are now
                                increasingly on our side. In other words I should think the time has
                                come for a show-down, though I sense a cautious disposition here to
                                avoid facing that.<note n="1" xml:id="d609fn1">
                                    <p>At this point in the source text, <persName corresp="#p_LP1">Laukhuff</persName> had inserted an asterisk, and had
                                        written below “April 19.—*There have been two new
                                        developments. First, the <persName corresp="#p_DEAJ1">Davies</persName> letter which we’ve telegraphed and
                                        which just confirms my diagnosis. Second, a tripartite
                                        meeting this morning at which the atmosphere got a little
                                        strained when <persName>Phil</persName> clearly
                                        characterized the British position as one of ‘capitulation’,
                                        without a stopping point.” A copy of <persName corresp="#p_DEAJ1">Davies</persName>’ letter was
                                        transmitted in telegram 6328 from Paris, not printed, while
                                        the U.S. Delegation reported on the tripartite meeting in
                                        telegram 6337 from Paris, April 19 (396.1–PA/4–1951 and
                                        4–1951).</p>
                                    <p>Above these remarks <persName corresp="#p_LP1">Laukhuff</persName> had also written “Am I getting too
                                        steamed up? It’s hard to keep perspective when one runs
                                        around the same squirrel cage day after day.”</p>
                                </note> We haven’t much time to fiddle-faddle around at this point
                                if we want to keep the public with us, and the only alternative to a
                                showdown is a slow but steady surrender to the British and then to
                                the Russians, point by point. That would make me <hi rend="italic">really</hi> sorry I ever had to get connected with this
                                enterprise.</p>
                            <p>I hope you don’t mind my unburdening myself like this. Some of this
                                is not my particular business and I don’t expect you to do anything
                                about it. I am sending a copy of this to Arch and to no one
                                else.</p>
                            <p>I hope the load is not too heavy on you these days. I’m sure neither
                                of us anticipated that I would be away so long. If I ever get back I
                                may have to take a week’s leave right off the bat to recover! My
                                best to everyone.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LP1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Perry</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>