<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>194. Memorandum for the Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d194</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">194</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-07T11:05:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-07T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recbbfe5a445f57e45" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Cuban missile crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-07T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-07T11:05:00-05:00" n="194"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d194">
                <head>194. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d194fn1"
                        >Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> Library, National
                        Security File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings File, Vol. 4.
                        Secret. Dated January 7, 1969. The meeting took place in the Cabinet Room.
                        The time and place of the meeting are from the President’s Daily Diary.
                        (Ibid.) A list of those present is ibid., National Security File, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meetings File, Vol. 4. A handwritten
                        memorandum, June 7, that Rostow apparently gave to the President during the
                        meeting, conveys a message from Moyers that <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                            >Eban</persName> had told <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Feinberg</persName>
                        he was going to take the position of no withdrawal without a definitive
                        peace, and he would be seeing Goldbe<gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> to ask
                        for U.S. support. <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Feinberg</persName> thought
                        this was the way for the President to retrieve his position after the
                            <persName corresp="#p_MCRJ1">McCloskey</persName> statement. (Ibid.,
                        Appointment File, June 1967, Middle East Crisis) Rostow evidently received
                        this message in a telephone call from Moyers at 12:28 p.m.; he left the
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting to return Moyers’ call.
                        (Ibid., President’s Daily Diary</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1967-06-07T12:05:00-04:00" to="1967-06-07T13:00:00-04:00">June 7,
                            1967, 12:05–1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>National Security Council Meeting, Wednesday, June 7, 1967</item>
                </list>
                <p>The following is a record from my notes made during the meeting, but, because of
                    the fast moving events in the Middle East, not transcribed until today.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> opened the discussion of the
                    situation in the Middle East by reporting that <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> had suffered a “stunning loss.” He had miscalculated the
                    military situation and Soviet support. There was widespread disillusionment with
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> in the Middle East.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d194fn2">At 9 a.m. that morning, Rostow sent the President reports
                        from the London press that <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s
                        position was threatened by the developments in the war, with a brief
                        covering memorandum that commented, “If <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName> goes, we indeed do have a new ball game.” (Ibid.,
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Histories, Middle East
                        Crisis)</note> The Soviets seemed to have been guilty of encouraging him.
                    The Arabs in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> felt that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> had let them down. Israel was riding high and
                    its demands will be substantial. Israel will probably demand a peace treaty with
                    the Arabs with the following objectives: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>Clear resolution of the state of belligerence.</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Getting rid of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> truce supervisory
                            machinery. Israel will accept no arrangements that derogate its
                            sovereignty.</item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>At the beginning it seemed that Israel was not seeking territorial
                            acquisition, but Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BW1"
                                >Barbour</persName> feels they will want Sharm el-Sheikh and
                            straightened out borders.<note n="3" xml:id="d194fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName> estimated in telegram
                                3988 from Tel Aviv, June 7, that the Israelis would insist on final
                                peace treaties with their neighbors with firm, accepted frontiers
                                and would not accept any international supervisory organizations. He
                                thought they would not want to absorb the West Bank but would want
                                to hold on to the areas of the Sinai, including Sharm el-Sheikh,
                                from which they withdrew under pressure in 1957, and that they would
                                expect other adjustments to widen the narrow belt between Jordan and
                                the sea and to improve their strategic position toward Syria.
                                (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                                    target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss
                                    target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 ARAB–ISR)</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0379" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/>
                <p>Looking ahead, the Secretary spoke of the importance to us of removing
                    belligerent rights, resuming international guarantees, and regional economic and
                    social developments to absorb intra-Arab and Arab-Israeli quarrels. If we do not
                    make ourselves “attorneys for Israel,” we cannot recoup our losses. We do have
                    something to bargain with in that Israel must be grateful to the US and Israel
                    requires continuing US support.</p>
                <p>The Secretary reviewed the question of “who did what?” He said we had a primary
                    obligation to ourselves to maintain peace. What we would have done had we been
                    in Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Eshkol</persName>’s shoes is
                    another question. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName> had laid bare
                    Israeli thinking and we understood it. In any case, the situation on June 8
                    appeared “more manageable than five days or three days ago.” The air battle had
                    been significant.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> said that the Russians had badly
                    miscalculated, even more so than in the Cuban missile crisis.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> said that arrangements for
                    evacuation of Americans were in progress everywhere except in Jordan. We still
                    were holding off in Kuwait and Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Gaud</persName> reported that we had had aid programs in six of the
                    fourteen Arab countries (plus Israel)-Sudan, Jordan, Tunisia, the <gloss
                        target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, Morocco, Israel—and a pipeline of one sort or
                    another to twelve. He had stopped obligations to all of these countries. He had
                    frozen everything for those countries who have broken diplomatic relations. In
                    addition there are US contributions to the world food program, <gloss
                        target="#t_UNRWA1">UNRWA</gloss> and voluntary agencies which we had not
                    stopped. The pipeline of unliquidated obligations added up to about $130
                    million. The President asked Mr. <persName>Rostow</persName> to pull all of this
                    information together and to see how it sorted itself out.</p>
                <p>With regard to our aid through international or private agencies, Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> said it would be serious to pull
                    out of the <gloss target="#t_FAO1">FAO</gloss>. On the other hand, with American
                    personnel coming out of countries like the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>,
                    voluntary agency programs might have to give for the time being.</p>
                <p>The discussion turned to the question of military equipment. The Vice President
                    said the Congress was watching the flow of arms shipments very carefully. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_REV1">E.V. Rostow</persName> noted Soviet shipments to
                    the Arabs.</p>
                <p>The President said “he was not sure we were out of our troubles.” He could not
                    visualize the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> saying it had miscalculated,
                    and then walking away. Our objective should be to “develop as few heroes and as
                    few heels as we can.” It is important for everybody to know we are not for
                    aggression. We are sorry this has taken place. We are in as good a position as
                    we could be given the complexities of the situation. We <pb facs="0380" n="348"
                        xml:id="pg_348"/> thought we had a commitment from those governments, but it
                    went up in smoke very quickly. The President said that by the time we get
                    through with all the festering problems we are going to wish the war had not
                    happened.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> said he could figure
                    out no explanation for the Soviet misjudgment. The Russians should have known
                    the Arabs’ capability. He felt the end of belligerence should be relatively easy
                    to handle with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Barring a direct
                    threat to Cairo, he felt the Soviets would probably stay out of war.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> felt that, in Moscow, those
                    advising caution may be strengthened.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> reported briefly on the
                    air war, noting that the Israelis had caught a large portion of the <gloss
                        target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> air force on the ground. He also pointed out
                    that the striking nature of the Israeli success reflected great superiority in
                    maintenance, leadership, training and discipline rather than numerical
                    superiority.</p>
                <p>The President then went on to read a statement later released to the press
                        (attached),<note n="4" xml:id="d194fn4">For text, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States: <persName
                                corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B. Johnson</persName>, 1967,</hi> Book I,
                        p. 599. The President stated that the members of the Special Committee, in
                        addition to <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName>, would be Fowler, <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1"
                            >Wheeler</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>. He stated that he would meet
                        with the Committee as necessary, as would Vice President <persName
                            corresp="#p_HHH1">Humphrey</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GAJ1"
                            >Goldberg</persName>.</note> establishing a Special Committee of the
                    National Security Council to deal with the Middle East crisis, with <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName> to serve as Executive Secretary
                    and as a special consultant to the President and with Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> as chairman.</p>
                <p>Secretary Fowler discussed briefly the effect of hostilities on the money markets
                    of the world. In sum, he felt there was nothing to indicate any massive movement
                    of funds. He said we were not interfering.</p>
                <p>At the President’s request for comment, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1"
                        >Bundy</persName> said the following about his new assignment. He would be
                    in familiar company and would do his best. He needed the help of people who had
                    been working in the crisis and would require the support of a small staff. He
                    knew his job was primarily to take the best possible advantage of work already
                    going on.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> concluded by suggesting that
                    there be a meeting of the new committee at 6:30 p.m.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>H.H.S.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
