<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>284. Intelligence Memorandum Prepared in the Central Intelligence
                    Agency</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rechaRqhHZqAlDnM2" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133293"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recRywIrZWsI9yUJ7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recco4TvraiYB3Tfh" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007556"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radar</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="284"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d284">
                <head>284. Intelligence Memorandum Prepared in the Central Intelligence Agency<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d284fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                            >Johnson</persName> Library, National Security File, Country File,
                        Middle East Crisis, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> Intelligence
                        Memoranda. Top Secret; Trine; No Foreign Dissem. Prepared in the Central
                        Intelligence Agency’s Directorate of Intelligence. A covering memorandum
                        from <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> to the President states
                        that it was the “special study” he had requested the previous evening.
                            <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>’ notes of the June 12
                        meeting of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Special Committee
                        indicate that the President requested a “special study on strafing &amp;
                        torpedoing of <gloss target="#t_USS1">USS</gloss>
                        <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi>—pilot conversations, etc.—everything we can
                            get—<gloss target="#t_NSA1">NSA</gloss>, etc.” (Central Intelligence
                        Agency Files, <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss> Files: Job 80–B01285A, Box
                        11, Folder 12, <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss> (<persName
                            corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>) Miscellaneous Notes of Meetings, 1
                        Jan 1966–31 Dec 1968) Rostow sent a preliminary version of this report to
                        the President at 12:45 p.m. on June 13 with a covering memorandum calling it
                            “<gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>’s first cut at the problem” and
                        noting, “They do not find evidence of U.S. identification before the
                        attack.” (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">SC No. 01415/67</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-06-13">June 13, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">THE ISRAELI ATTACK ON THE USS <hi rend="italic">LIBERTY</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The US Naval technical research ship <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> was attacked
                    by Israeli aircraft and torpedo boats off the Sinai Peninsula on 8 June. The
                    following account of the circumstances of the attack has been compiled from all
                    available sources.</p>
                <p>1. The <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> reported at 9:50 a.m. (2:50 a.m. Washington
                    time) on 8 June that it had been orbited by two delta-wing jet fighters,
                    presumably Israeli Mirages. At 3:05 p.m. (8:05 a.m.) the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Liberty</hi> was strafed by unidentified jet aircraft. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Liberty</hi> apparently was not able to establish
                    communications with other units of the US Sixth Fleet during the air attack, and
                    the first information available to the US commanders was after the subsequent
                    attack by unidentified torpedo boats, which occurred at 3:25 p.m.</p>
                <p>2. At 4:11 p.m. (9:11 a.m.) the US Commander in Chief, Europe, notified the
                    National Military Command Center in Washington that the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Liberty</hi> was under attack and was listing to starboard after being
                    struck by a torpedo. The Commander of the US Sixth Fleet declared the attacking
                    units hostile and sent attack aircraft from the carriers <hi rend="italic"
                        >America</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Saratoga</hi> to protect the <hi
                        rend="italic">Liberty</hi>. A good part of the ship’s communications
                    equipment was destroyed by the crew during the attack but emergency
                    communications were soon established with the <hi rend="italic">Saratoga</hi>
                    and with the naval communications station in Greece. Because of the tenseness of
                    the situation and the communications delays, the initial reports from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Liberty</hi> were sketchy and somewhat confusing.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Specifics of the Attack</hi>
                </p>
                <p>3. According to these reports, however, the sequence of events took place as
                    follows. The ship was attacked at 3:05 p.m. (8:05 a.m.) by <pb facs="0502"
                        n="470" xml:id="pg_470"/> unidentified jet fighters, believed to be Israeli,
                    at position 31–35N, 33–29E. Six strafing runs were made by the jets. Twenty
                    minutes later three torpedo boats closed at high speed and two of them launched
                    torpedoes after first circling the <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi>. One torpedo
                    passed astern, and the other struck the starboard side of the ship in the spaces
                    occupied by the SIGINT collectors. One of the boats was later identified as
                    Israeli and the hull number of one unit was noted as 206–T. Some 50 minutes
                    later two Israeli helicopters arrived on the scene.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Israeli Identification of the Ship</hi>
                </p>
                <p>4. None of the communications of the attacking aircraft and torpedo boats is
                    available, but the intercepted conversations between the helicopter pilots and
                    the control tower at Hatzor (near Tel Aviv) leave little doubt that the Israelis
                    failed to identify the <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> as a US ship before or
                    during the attack. Control told (helicopter) 815 at 3:31 p.m. (8:31 a.m.) that
                    “there is a warship there which we attacked. The men jumped into the water from
                    it. You will try to rescue them.” Although there were other references to a
                    search for the men in the water and although US units later searched the area,
                    no survivors were recovered from the sea, nor were there any indications that
                    any of the 22 missing personnel from the <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> had been
                    lost overboard.</p>
                <p>5. A subsequent message from the control tower to the helicopter identified the
                    ship as Egyptian and told the pilot to return home. Although the <hi
                        rend="italic">Liberty</hi> is some 200 feet longer than the Egyptian
                    transport <hi rend="italic">El Quesir</hi>, it could easily be mistaken for the
                    latter vessel by an overzealous pilot. Both ships have similar hulls and
                    arrangements of masts and stack.</p>
                <p>6. The weather was clear in the area of attack, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Liberty</hi>’s hull number (GTR 5) was prominently displayed, and an
                    American flag was flying. The helicopter pilot was then urgently requested to
                    identify the survivors as Egyptian or English speaking (this being the first
                    indication that the Israelis suspected they may have attacked a neutral ship).
                    The helicopter pilot reported seeing an American flag on the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Liberty</hi>. In another intercept between an unidentified Israeli
                    controller and the helicopter number 815, the pilot reported that number GTR 5
                    was written on the ship’s side. The controller told the pilot the number had no
                    significance.</p>
                <p>7. Thus it was not until 4:12 p.m. (9:12 a.m.) that the Israelis became convinced
                    that the <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> was American. This was about 44 minutes
                    after the last attack on the ship and the attack had apparently been called off,
                    not because the ship had been identified, but because it seemed to be sinking.
                    (The US Defense Attaché in Tel Aviv reports that Israeli helicopters and the
                    three torpedo boats searched the area until 6:04 p.m. (11:04 a.m.).) The Israeli
                    offer of assistance was declined <pb facs="0503" n="471" xml:id="pg_471"/>
                    because of the sensitive mission of the ship. According to US Navy reports, the
                    ship was saved only through the efforts of her crew.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Damage and Personnel Losses</hi>
                </p>
                <p>8. The ship suffered heavy material and personnel casualties. A hole estimated to
                    be 39 feet wide at the bottom and 24 feet wide at the top near the waterline was
                    opened by a torpedo. The ship is flooded below the second deck between frames 52
                    and 78 (36-inch frame spacing). The crew carried out emergency destruction of
                    classified communications and radar equipment, but the ship’s engineering plant
                    is intact. Several flash fires and cannon holes throughout the superstructure
                    caused some minor damage and the ship’s motor whale boat and virtually all of
                    its life rafts were lost. Personnel casualties include 10 killed, 90 wounded,
                    and 22 missing, most of whom were probably trapped in the flooded compartments.
                    The wounded and the dead have been removed from the ship and some additional
                    crew members put aboard. The ship is expected to arrive in Malta on 14 June for
                    dry docking and hull repairs. Security precautions are being taken to protect
                    the classified intercept equipment in the flooded spaces. The US Navy has
                    convened a board of inquiry to look into the incident.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ship and Its Orders</hi>
                </p>
                <p>9. The <gloss target="#t_USS1">USS</gloss>
                    <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> is a converted Victory class merchant ship
                    utilized as a SIGINT collector. The unit had moved from its normal station off
                    West Africa to provide additional SIGINT coverage of the Middle East crisis.
                    Official US statements, however, have described the Liberty as an electronics
                    research ship which had been diverted to the crisis area to act as a radio relay
                    station for US embassies.</p>
                <p>10. The Liberty sailed from Rota, Spain, on 2 June under orders to patrol no
                    closer than 12.5 miles of the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> coast and 6.5
                    miles of the Israeli coast. A modification of orders issued by the Commander of
                    the US Sixth Fleet at 12:17 p.m. (5:17 a.m.) on 8 June had not been received
                    aboard the Liberty, according to the ship’s commanding officer, before the
                    Israeli attack. This change, together with messages from other commands which
                    ordered the Liberty to approach no closer than 100 miles of the coasts of the
                        <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and Israel and 25 miles of the coast of
                    Cyprus, was delayed in transmission in part because of a misunderstanding of
                    responsibilities for delivery.</p>
                <p>11. At annex is a listing of events in chronological order.</p>
                <pb facs="0504" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Annex</head>
                    <p rend="center">CHRONOLOGY OF EVENTS</p>
                    <p rend="center">(Stated times are local; Washington times in parentheses)</p>
                    <table cols="2" rows="26">
                        <row>
                            <cell>2 June 1967</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> departed Rota, Spain en route to
                                position 32–00N, 33–00E, to remain 12.5 miles from Egyptian coast
                                and 6.5 miles from Israeli coast.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 2:50 a.m. (7 June 7:50 p.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <gloss target="#t_CINCUSNAVEUR1">CINCUSNAVEUR</gloss> Duty Officer
                                received phone instructions from Joint Reconnaissance Center
                                directing Liberty to comply with COMSIXTHFLEET 100-mile operating
                                area restriction.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 9:50 a.m. (2:50 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> was orbited by two unidentified delta
                                wing single engine jet fighters, presumably Israeli Mirages.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 12:17 p.m. (5:17 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>COMSIXTHFLEET orders <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> at least 100
                                miles away from coast of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and
                                Israel and 25 miles from Cyprus. This message apparently not
                                received by <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> prior to Israeli
                                attack.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:05 p.m. (8:05 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> attacked by unidentified jet fighters
                                which made six strafing runs. Ship at position 31–35.5N 33–29.0E (25
                                miles northeast of nearest land).</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:25 p.m. (8:25 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Three torpedo boats, one identified as Israeli, approach ship. One
                                boat bore number 206–T.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:27 p.m. (8:27 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> fires at torpedo boat at range of
                                2,000 yards.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:28 p.m. (8:28 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Ship hit by torpedo. Torpedo boats cleared to east about five
                                miles.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:30 p.m. (8: 30 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>COMSIXTHFLEET reports <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> hit by
                                torpedo at position 31–23N, 33–25E. Three unidentified gunboats
                                approaching.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:31 p.m. (8:31 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Hatzor air control (near Tel Aviv) told helicopters (two) to try
                                to rescue men who had jumped into the water from “warship which we
                                attacked.”</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:34 p.m. (8:34 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Israeli helicopter identified ship as “definitely Egyptian.”
                                Helicopters ordered back to base.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:39 p.m. (8:39 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Hatzor control told helicopter to rescue men.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="0505" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 8 June 3:50 p.m. (8:50 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>COMSIXTHFLEET orders carriers to provide air cover for <hi
                                    rend="italic">Liberty</hi>.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:52 p.m. (8:52 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> reported under attack to
                                COMSIXTH-FLEET.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:55 p.m. (8:55 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> reported hit by torpedo starboard
                                side (National Security Agency (<gloss target="#t_NSA1">NSA</gloss>)
                                follow-up to Critic, probably a delayed report).</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:55 p.m. (8:55 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Two Israeli helicopters orbited ship at range of 500 yards.
                                Israeli torpedo boats offered assistance which was refused.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:59 p.m. (8:59 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> still under air attack (<gloss
                                    target="#t_NSA1">NSA</gloss> follow-up to Critic).</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 3:59 p.m. (8:59 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Hatzor control told helicopter to clarify the nationality of the
                                first man he brings up.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 4:02 p.m. (9:02 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Helicopter reports (to Haztor) a big ship and three small ships
                                about a mile from the helicopter. (This places the torpedo boats
                                about eight miles from <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi>.)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 4:07 p.m. (9:07 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Hatzor told helicopters if men were Egyptians to take them to El
                                Arish; if they spoke English and were not Egyptians, to take them to
                                Lydda.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 4:10 p.m. (9:10 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Haztor told helicopter again to clarify nationality. (It appears
                                from the obvious importance of this question that the Israelis
                                suspected they may have hit an American or British and not an
                                Egyptian ship.)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 4:10 p.m. (9:10 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Hull number of <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi> seen by Israeli
                                helicopter pilot who did not recognize significance.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 4:12 p.m. (9:12 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Hatzor asked helicopter, “Did it clearly signal an American flag?”
                                and later requested helicopter to make another pass and check again
                                whether it was really an American flag.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 4:16 p.m. (9:16 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Hatzor orders helicopters to return to El Arish.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8 June 5:14 p.m. (10:14 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>Tel Aviv reports Israeli aircraft and patrol boats attacked ship
                                at 3:00 p.m. (8:00 a.m.) at position 31–25N, 33–33E. Suspecting a
                                U.S. ship, Israel rendering assistance and expresses deep
                                regret.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="0506" n="474" xml:id="pg_474"/>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 8 June 6:04 p.m. (11:04 a.m.)</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <p>The US Defense Attaché in Tel Aviv reports that Israeli
                                    helicopters and the three torpedo boats searched the area until
                                    6:04 p.m. (11:04 a.m.). The Israeli offer of assistance was
                                    declined because of the sensitive mission of the ship.</p>
                                <lb/>
                                <p>COMSIXTHFLEET then recalled the aircraft launched from the
                                    carriers <hi rend="italic">America</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Saratoga</hi> and sent two destroyers to assist <hi
                                        rend="italic">Liberty. Liberty</hi> proceeding north-west at
                                    eight knots.</p>
                                <p>There was no further contact between <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Liberty</hi> and Israeli forces. Two Soviet ships have
                                    trailed the <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi>, which proceeds under
                                    escort to Malta.</p>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
