<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>315. Telegram From the Mission to the United Nations to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-21T23:55:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-21T23:55:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-21T23:55:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-21T23:55:00-05:00" n="315"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d315">
                <head>315. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission to the United
                        Nations</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d315fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 ARAB–ISR/<gloss target="#t_UN1"
                            >UN</gloss>. Secret; Immediate; Nodis. Received at 2:18 a.m. A typed and
                        slightly paraphrased version was sent to the President by Arthur McCafferty
                        at 7:15 a.m. 5841/Secto 9. Eyes Only for President and Acting
                        Secretary.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-06-22T04:55:00+00:00">June 22, 1967, 0455Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Before we sat down to dinner tonight <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> and I drew aside for a few minutes of private talk about
                    the Middle East. I asked him what the Central Committee meant by accusing the US
                    of being in a plot with Israel. He said they found it very hard to believe the
                    US did not have advance information about the beginning of hostilities and we
                    could have made more of an effort to stop them. I told him categorically that
                    this was not the truth, that we had what we considered to be commitments from
                    both sides that hostilities would not begin, that we had no advance information
                    about the fighting and that our first message to the Chairman expressing our
                    astonishment and dismay represented the exact truth.<note n="2" xml:id="d315fn2">
                        <ref target="#d157">Document 157</ref>.</note> I told him that Israel was
                    not a satellite of the United States and that I assumed that Egypt was not a
                    satellite of Moscow; otherwise Moscow would bear a heavy responsibility for such
                    acts of folly as the closing of the Strait of Tiran and the whipping up of a
                    holy war psychology against Israel.</p>
                <p>We then turned to the immediate problem before the Assembly and it is clear that
                    the central issue will be the relation between the withdrawal of troops and
                    other elements in a general settlement. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> reaffirmed the commitment of the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to the existence of Israel as a state and
                    recalled that both they and we had voted for the creation of Israel twenty years
                    ago. He seemed to show flexibility on international maritime rights although he
                    commented perhaps these matters should be dealt with in special arrangements
                    similar to the Montreux Convention on the Bosporus. For lack of time we did not
                    get into other elements of a permanent solution, but it is quite clear that they
                    will press for the priority of withdrawal over against the settlement of other
                    issues. I drew the distinction between procedure and substance and said that I
                    thought if there could be broad agreement on substance, modalities could be
                    found to deal with questions of procedure. I also told him I did not think that
                    Israel had any particular interest in trying to retain Egyptian or Syrian
                    territory. (This was based on an earlier conversation I had had with <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eban</persName>.)</p>
                <pb facs="0568" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/>
                <p>I talked to him briefly about non-proliferation which we continued at dinner and
                    got the impression that they were reasonably satisfied with the draft text
                    worked out in Geneva which omits article three. He emphasized the importance of
                    controls and said there should be an international system which did not
                    discriminate in favor of members of a particular <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> family. I told him this was not an issue of principle between
                    the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and the US but that the obstacle was
                    his friend General <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>. I asked him
                    if <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> had discussed <gloss
                        target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                        Gaulle</persName> and was told the subject had not come up. He seemed to be
                    more optimistic about the Indian attitude than we.</p>
                <p>In a later private exchange <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    indicated he would probably stay on for about a week following the departure of
                        <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>. This probably means that he
                    will stay around to do his best to get their kind of resolution from the General
                    Assembly. I definitely got the impression that they were prepared to drop the
                    condemnation feature if a simple unadorned demand for withdrawal could get the
                    necessary number of votes.</p>
                <p>Remainder of conversation being reported septel.<note n="3" xml:id="d315fn3"
                        >Telegram 5848 from <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, June 22, reported
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s dinner conversation with
                            <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>. (National Archives and
                        Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                        1967–69, O<gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 7 <gloss target="#t_S1"
                            >S</gloss>)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAJ1">Goldberg</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
