<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>358. Telegram From the Mission to the United Nations to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d358</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">358</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-07-13T20:31:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-07-13T20:31:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-07-13T20:31:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-07-13T20:31:00-05:00" n="358"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d358">
                <head>358. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission to the United
                        Nations</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d358fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 ARAB–ISR/<gloss target="#t_UN1"
                            >UN</gloss>. Secret; Priority; Limdis. Received on July 13 at 10:34
                        p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-07-14T01:31:00+00:00">July 14, 1967, 0131Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>203. Mid-East Crisis.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Riad</persName> (<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>) met with
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> again today as follow-up to
                    confidential discussions of yesterday. <persName>Riad</persName> said he had
                    some comments to make regarding <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName>’s
                    queries of yesterday as to whether <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> in
                    position now to renounce belligerency, and that if gap on substantive res
                    unbridgeable whether <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> would believe time
                    propitious for <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> to decide upon some high level
                    rep to make contact with parties.</p>
                <pb facs="0677" n="645" xml:id="pg_645"/>
                <p>
                    <persName>Riad</persName>’s response to belligerency point consisted of a
                    reversion to three points which <persName>Fawzi</persName> made to Secy in his
                    last conversation.<note n="2" xml:id="d358fn2">See <ref target="#d327">Document
                            327</ref>.</note>
                    <persName>Riad</persName> recalled that <persName>Fawzi</persName> had informed
                    Secy that <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> is prepared to acquiesce tacitly
                    to freedom of passage of all ships through strait and that this information had
                    been conveyed to <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> and France as well. Secondly, <persName>Riad</persName>
                    recalled that <persName>Fawzi</persName> had stressed that <gloss
                        target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> is “determined to return to state of quiet”.
                        <persName>Riad</persName> said he would not wish to relate this terminology
                    to other terminology being discussed in corridors but <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                        >UAR</gloss> seriously meant return to state of quiet. Third,
                        <persName>Riad</persName> recalled that <persName>Fawzi</persName> and Secy
                    had talked about possibilities of placement of <gloss target="#t_UNEF1"
                        >UNEF</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> presence and that he
                    wished to make clear on behalf of <persName>Fawzi</persName> that Egypt would
                    definitely accept <gloss target="#t_UNEF1">UNEF</gloss> presence provided it was
                    on both sides of line.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Riad</persName> said they unable to mention belligerency in res
                    because of its implications with respect to Suez Canal.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Riad</persName> said that before he gave any specific answer to
                    willingness accept third party they wished to see how present discussions on
                    possible substantive compromise works out. He indicated that <gloss
                        target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> had informed non-aligneds of its willingness to
                    go along with draft presented by Malacela last night to Latinos. (This is draft
                    contained in Annex B of <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 198<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d358fn3">Telegram 198 from <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>,
                        July 13; not printed. (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 ARAB–ISR/<gloss target="#t_UN1"
                            >UN</gloss>)</note> and which we informed LAs this morning was clearly
                    unacceptable to US.)</p>
                <p>During course of day there appeared shift in <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                    position. About 4 p.m. this afternoon <persName>Riad</persName> sought out
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> to inform him that it might be
                    possible for <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> to accept word “belligerency”
                    in res provided it is appropriately modified. In saying this
                        <persName>Riad</persName> was referring to fol Indian formulation which we
                    have already informed Indians is not acceptable to US.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Further affirms that the political sovereignty and territorial integrity of
                        member states in the Middle East allow them a rightful freedom from threats
                        or acts of belligerency and consequently urges all states in the Middle East
                        to refrain and desist from threats or acts of war.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> focused principally on advantages
                    to everybody concerned in closing down <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                    promptly so that principal parties could begin to address themselves
                    realistically to serious questions and arrangements that must be sorted out if
                    durable peace is to be achieved in <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> said as long as public debate continues
                    it will be difficult for parties to begin discussions, indirect or otherwise,
                    and that in our judgment since gap between two substantive positions has been
                    found unbridgeable it <pb facs="0678" n="646" xml:id="pg_646"/> would be well to
                    get matter back to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> for further consideration
                    at some appropriate stage. <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> stressed
                    too advantages of getting some third party involved so that there can be
                    realistic focus on fundamental elements of settlement. <persName>Riad</persName>
                    did not disagree with this view but dwelt at some length on some need for
                    “something to come out of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>” and in particular
                    expression by Assembly in favor of withdrawal of Israeli forces.</p>
                <p>Conversation then turned to internal situation in <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                        >UAR</gloss>. <persName>Riad</persName> said situation very difficult
                    indeed, particularly from economic view. However he felt progress was being made
                    in “reshaping military” and that he personally felt it was very important for
                    influence of US to return to area at earliest possible moment. He said somewhat
                    emotionally that this was in everybody’s interests, including US. Implication of
                    what <persName>Riad</persName> said was concern over possible expansion of Sov
                    influence in area.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Riad</persName> concluded by saying <persName>Fawzi</persName> felt it
                    important that we keep in touch on regular basis. <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1"
                        >Sisco</persName> agreed and said he readily available at any time.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAJ1">Goldberg</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
