<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>500. Telegram [text not declassified] to the ] to the White House</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d500</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">500</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-11-03T10:16:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-11-03T10:16:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="rec6U5wOCAq8Rv0YT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136255"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Tourism</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recTdbwPhSPuOaeNu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recd7021a58b486ded" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="suez-canal" subject="suez-canal">Suez Canal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-11-03T10:16:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-11-03T10:16:00-05:00" n="500"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d500">
                <head>500. Telegram [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] to the <gloss
                        type="to">White House</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d500fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                            >Johnson</persName> Library, National Security File, Country File,
                        Middle East Crisis, Sandstorm/Whirlwind. Secret. Also sent to the Department
                        of State. Rostow sent the telegram to the President at 2:30 p.m. with a
                        covering memorandum, in which he commented that the <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_ARB1"
                            >Anderson</persName> conversation was important and interesting. Citing
                        paragraph 25, he noted that <persName corresp="#p_ARB1">Anderson</persName>
                        was “wholly correct” in his conversation and in dealing with the press, and
                        he added that he had “talked firmly” to the Chief of the United Press
                        International Washington Bureau, “who promised to try to kill the story.”
                        The handwritten note “PS, 11/3/67” on the memorandum indicates the President
                        saw it.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-11-03T15:16:00+00:00">November 3, 1967,
                        1516Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">document number not declassified</hi>]. Eyes Only to Secretary
                    of State and White House for the President:</p>
                <pb facs="1006" n="974" xml:id="pg_974"/>
                <p>Following is text message dictated (but not read) by <persName corresp="#p_ARB1"
                        >Anderson</persName> in presence [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of
                        source text not declassified</hi>], and edited and in parts reorganized by
                    latter at specific <persName corresp="#p_ARB1">Anderson</persName> request,
                    early evening 2 November. For the Secretary of State attention of the President
                    from <persName corresp="#p_ARB1">Anderson</persName>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>This will be a somewhat difficult message because of the circumstances
                        under which it is being dictated at the Beirut airport en route between
                        Cairo and Baghdad.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I met today with President <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> at
                        1230. He advised me that he was leaving later today for a vacation in the
                        desert near Al Almayn, and that this would be the first real vacation he had
                        taken in fifteen years. He was looking forward to swimming, sitting in the
                        sun and having time to think and relax. He opened the conversation by
                        saying, “above all else, try to make clear to your government and your
                        people that we are eager for a political settlement, for a political peace.”
                        He stated that this had not been true in the very beginning, after the
                        cessation of hostilities on 9 June, because “we were in a state of
                        confusion, uncertainty and doubt. We did not know, but we feared what the
                        Israelis were going to do.” Now, he said, “we know that our interest lies
                        not in war, but in peace.”</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>He then said, “Please try to convince your people and your government that
                        any question of direct negotiation, or even of negotiations with a third
                        party mediator present, would be an act of suicide. It would be so for me,
                        and it would be so for any other Arab leader.” He further said that even if
                        he attempted this or agreed to it, it would be suicide on the part of any
                        other Arab leader not immediately to denounce it and to demand to resume
                        hostilities against the Israelis. <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName> said, “under these circumstances, let us try to be
                        practical and, if we all want peace, and we do, then let us find a way to
                        settle our differences and live in peace.” He said we did not believe that
                        the details of an agreement could be worked out in public, or that anything
                        could be effectively begun by negotiations by a committee or any mediator
                        appointed by the U.N. until some formal action had been taken by the U.N.
                        “as a first step.” He then suggested that a resolution be offered to the
                        Security Council which would involve as its basis the five points that
                        President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> had made, and which
                        he described as follows: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>The right of Israel and of all other nations in the area to
                                live;</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>Free movement of “innocent” shipping in the waterways of the Gulf
                                of Aqaba and the Suez;</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Full withdrawal by the Israelis from the territories which they
                                had occupied at the time of the hostilities;</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>A declaration of non-belligerence between Arab states and Israel;
                                and</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item>Finally, settlement of the problem of the refugees.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="1007" n="975" xml:id="pg_975"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> stated that after the adoption
                        of this type of resolution, which he thought we should accept because it was
                        based on the principles announced by our President, the resolution should
                        direct the Secretary General to appoint one or more persons to consult with
                        the Arab nations involved and with Israelis and, from these negotiations, to
                        draw up “a declaration for detailed implementation, which would then be
                        submitted again for adoption or ratification by the Security Council.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>At this point, I told him that as I understood it, the Israelis professed
                        they would not be satisfied with any declaration made by third persons, even
                        including the Security Council, and that they wanted some contractual
                        undertaking between them and the Arab countries which would ensure
                        non-belligerence and the other ideas he had referred to. <persName
                            corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said that he could not speak for all
                        the other Arab countries, but as for himself, he would be willing to sign
                        such a (Security Council) declaration “after it had been agreed to,” or, as
                        an alternative, write a letter or other document to the Secretary General or
                        to the Security Council undertaking to carry out the details and
                        implications contained in the declaration. He felt that the other Arab
                        countries would be willing to do the same thing, but reiterated that “he
                        could not speak for them.” It is quite clear that he is willing to undertake
                        contractual obligations, just so long as they are not incorporated into a
                        simple treaty jointly made and signed between the <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                            >UAR</gloss> and Israel. This point he made from time to time, referring
                        always to the fact that even such an agreement would be suicide.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> then said that the most
                        difficult problems were going to be the Suez Canal and Jerusalem. I said
                        that obviously I could not speak on any of these topics, but could only
                        explore his own thinking. In this connection, I asked if he could agree to
                        let any ship, including the Israelis, transit the Suez Canal if such ships
                        carried not the flag of the country involved, but the U.N. flag. <persName
                            corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said, “I do not rule this out but
                        there is still the question of logs, manifests and trouble with the people.
                        On the other hand, if you will settle the refugee problem then I can allow
                        Israeli ships to transit,” he said. I told him I was skeptical that the
                        Israelis would ever negotiate for a resettlement in Palestine. At this
                        point, <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said, “All right, then,
                        let us settle with them by agreeing to pay them compensation.” In order to
                        clarify this point, I stated again that I wanted to be quite sure that he
                        would agree to a mutual settlement of the refugee problem without giving the
                        refugees the alternative choice of resettlement (comment: in Palestine) or
                        of taking money instead, and he again said that if resettlement is not
                        possible, we can agree on a mutual compensation. He continually links the
                        free passage of Israeli ships through the Suez Canal with the settlement of
                        the refugee problem.</item>
                    <pb facs="1008" n="976" xml:id="pg_976"/>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>He then brought up the question of territory. Here, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said that the key point is that Israel
                        cannot be allowed to expand, that for every Muslim nation, regardless of
                        whether or not it borders on Israel, the consuming fear is that Israel plans
                        territorial expansion. He said this is one of the basic problems in trying
                        to unite the New and the Old City of Jerusalem. It is regarded by everyone
                        of the Muslim faith as a violation of their religious rights and as Israeli
                        expansion.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>He then stated this, that again he would speculate that certain territory
                        surrounding the state of Israel might be regarded as essential to their own
                        security. <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said that if this is
                        so, let us demilitarize it. Again he said, “I cannot speak for all others,
                        but as for me, I will withdraw permanently all forces 10 miles, 15 miles, or
                        any agreed number of miles from the borders.” I asked him what he would
                        think about the complete demilitarization of the Sinai Peninsula. He said,
                        (“This I cannot do, because it is too big and extensive a land for me to say
                        that no military personnel can ever be placed there. I can agree that no
                        military personnel will ever be placed in Sharm al Shaykh, or within 10 or
                        15 miles of the Israeli borders, if they or their state will agree not to
                        place troops within the same distance.” He said again, “I cannot speak for
                        Jordan or Syria, but I believe that the same principles would be agreed to
                        by them.”</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said that except for territory,
                        most of the Arab nations are leaving other details of the Arab settlement to
                        him. He said, “It is a task I do not want, but one which others have asked
                        that I undertake. It, however, must be expected that each will decide with
                        reference to his own territory, and each of the neighboring states must
                        agree on the final settlement.” I told <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName> that obviously I was going fully to communicate his
                        views to my government, and he said, “This is exactly why I am telling you,
                        and I hope we will be getting a response that is favorable from your
                        government. You are going to Iraq. If you get any kind of response, please
                        advise my Ambassador in Iraq, and I will be glad to receive you at any time
                        you want to return.” <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> stated,
                        “Please try to explain to your government that however desperately we want
                        peace, we cannot have it at the price of destroying ourselves or any other
                        Arab leader, when you can be absolutely sure that anybody who succeeds me or
                        any of the other Arab leaders will be much more radical against the Israelis
                        than we are.”</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said that some of the Arab
                        states, notably Syria and Algeria, had been very vehement with him in
                        stating, “You cannot agree to a resolution or a declaration which includes
                        the right to live for Israel.” <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>
                        said, “I merely pointed out to them that we are no longer talking about
                        Israel’s right to live. We are talking about our own right to live.” He
                        repeated this two or three times. He also said he believed <pb facs="1009"
                            n="977" xml:id="pg_977"/> the Israelis had in mind his economic
                        destruction, because at present he had no revenue from the Suez Canal or
                        from tourism, and now they had destroyed his refineries. He said,
                        “Therefore, my task is now to build a strong economy within my own country.
                        This is the best way I can retaliate.”</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>I asked <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> if he would give me
                        his own version of the sinking of the Israeli ship <hi rend="italic"
                            >Eilath</hi>. He said he would be glad to. He said this ship had been
                        patrolling in and out of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> waters for a
                        number of weeks, “just on the border.” On or about 11 July, this same ship
                        had attacked and sunk two Egyptian torpedo boats and killed their crews.
                        This, he said, attracted no world attention. “Also, they sank them in our
                        own waters.” He said then General <persName corresp="#p_RLGY1"
                            >Rabin</persName> issued a statement saying that the Israelis were
                        looking for the Egyptian navy, but the navy was hiding. He said that in
                        addition to this, an Israeli plane sank another Egyptian torpedo boat in the
                        Suez. As far as the actual sinking of the <hi rend="italic">Eilath</hi> was
                        concerned, <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said, “It was all
                        finished and done with before I even heard about it. I was first informed
                        about 6:30 in the evening. At that time, I was not dealing with what should
                        or should not be done. I was dealing with a fact that had already happened.
                        I am sure that military commanders in other parts of the world do not ring
                        up their presidents and ask them what to do every time there is an invasion
                        of their territory.” <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> ended the
                        conversation by saying, “I want nothing but peace. I want to go as far as
                        humanly possible to achieve it. But I must not be asked to do the
                        impossible. I must not be asked to do something that would be condemned by
                        every other leader and by my own people. I am willing to go as far as the
                        facts of life will allow me, and I hope you will make this clear to and get
                        a favorable response from your government. Surely, they can support the
                        principles of your President, and surely we can find ways to work out the
                        details of implementation. Surely, peace must not depend both on
                        circumstances and procedures, upon the demands of the Israelis, some of
                        which they themselves know are impossible for us.” <persName
                            corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> again asked me to stay in touch with
                        his Ambassador in Iraq and be prepared to return if a response for his
                        government was forthcoming.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>I asked <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> whether all of the
                        difficulties concerning Yemen had been finally settled and if his agreement
                        with the Saudis was going to be carried out. <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName> replied, “Our relationships in Yemen have been settled
                        for good. We are going to carry out our agreements. The same goes for all of
                        the other states in the Southern Arabian Peninsula. My concentration is
                        going to be on the development of the <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                        >UAR</gloss>.”</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>Note that in my talk on the first day I arrived, I told Nasir we were
                        still puzzled as to why he had massed troops in the Sinai and we believed
                        this was why the whole issue had come about. <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName> did not <pb facs="1010" n="978" xml:id="pg_978"/>
                        refer to the Gulf of Aqaba, but said, “Whether you believe it or not, we
                        were in fear of an attack from Israel. We had been informed that the
                        Israelis were massing troops on the Syrian border with the idea of first
                        attacking Syria, there they did not expect to meet great resistance, and
                        then commence their attack on the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>.” I
                        said to him that it was unfortunate the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                        had believed such reports, which were simply not in accordance with the
                        facts. <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> said that the information
                        had not come to him from sources he would suspect. He added that among other
                        signs “your own State Department called in my Ambassador to the U.S. in
                        April or May and warned him that there were rumors that there might be a
                        conflict between Israel and the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>.” I told
                        him that so far as I knew, I had never heard this report before.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> observed that the U.S. must
                        remember that Jerusalem presents a special problem for all three faiths. He
                        commented that “In this country, we are Muslims, but we are not Islamic.” I
                        asked Nasir if he would consider permitting both the Old and New City of
                        Jerusalem to come under a single Israeli administration with respect to such
                        things as public utilities, etc., but with each faith to have custody and
                        supervision of its Holy Places. <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>
                        replied that even if he agreed to this any such solution would leave Israel
                        ultimately confronted with war or resistance so far as anybody could see
                        into the future. He said that nothing he or any other ruler in the world
                        could do would prevent that people will do things in the name of religion
                        that they would not consider doing in the name of politics. On the other
                        hand, he thinks Jerusalem could be zoned so that each faith would have the
                        administration of its own sector. “My country is Muslim, Christian and
                        Jewish, and I expect it always to be so. Each has his own particular
                        interest in how we settle the issue of Jerusalem.” We had no further
                        discussion on this subject, because <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName> said this was obviously a matter of such importance
                        that it would have to be the subject of negotiations, and one or more
                        persons should be appointed by the Secretary General pursuant to the
                        Security Council resolution discussed earlier above to manage such
                        negotiations.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>Concerning the shelling of the Suez refineries, <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName> commented that he recognized it as retaliation for the
                        sinking of the <hi rend="italic">Eilath</hi>, and that he thought the
                        Israelis had done this because it would hurt the <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                            >UAR</gloss> economically. He said, “We could have attacked their
                        refineries, but we decided that this had gone far enough, and we should have
                        peace and not escalation.”</item>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>’s willingness to sign an agreed
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> declaration or writing a letter to the
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> agreeing to the terms of such a
                        declaration is, of course, conditioned on Israel’s willingness to do the
                        same.</item>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>On conclusion of our meeting, <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>
                        thanked me for coming and expressed the hope that he would receive a
                        favorable response to the suggestions incorporated in the foregoing.</item>
                    <pb facs="1011" n="979" xml:id="pg_979"/>
                    <label>18.</label>
                    <item>After leaving <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>, I proceeded to
                        see Zakariyah Muhyi Al Din at his home. Zakariyah began by asking me to
                        brief him on what had taken place between <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName> and me, and I did so. Zakariyah asked whether we had
                        gotten into discussions of details concerning the territories involved,
                        especially the Gaza Strip. I told him <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName> had said other nations must be consulted insofar as
                        their territories were concerned, but that the Gaza Strip had not been
                        mentioned today. Zakariyah said that relinquishing the Gaza Strip could not
                        be decided on by the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> or the Israelis.
                        The <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> had never annexed Gaza formally
                        because it is territory belonging to the Palestinians, as is some of the
                        territory on the West Bank of the Jordan. I asked that if this is true, who
                        speaks for the Palestinians. Zakariyah smiled and said he did not know. I
                        asked whether it would be Ahmad Shukayri, and Zakariyah again smiled and
                        commented that Shukayri was an appointed, not an elected official, and that
                        there might well be some other political voice who could speak for the
                        Palestinians. He seemed disappointed that the issue had not been discussed
                        by <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>. I take it as Zakariyah’s
                        implication, and only that, that he does not believe the fate of the Gaza
                        Strip should be a determining factor. He is, however, concerned about the
                        people in the Gaza Strip, as to whether or not they could be incorporated
                        into the State of Israel, and perhaps more importantly, as to whether the
                        Israelis would allow them to stay. He said, “The real problem is not the
                        land but the people, and whether after we make peace the natives would be
                        ejected as undesirable.” I told him that these were the sorts of things I
                        had gathered from <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>, and that they
                        would be the subject of discussions by one or more persons who might be
                        appointed by the Secretary General pursuant to the resolution cited
                        above.</item>
                    <label>19.</label>
                    <item>Zakariyah said that he thought so far as he knew I had clearly outlined
                            <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>’s views. He said, “We want
                        to go as far as we can, because we know that war can only destroy us both,
                        and that peace can allow us to fulfill our obligations as a nation. But
                        please do not ask us to do the impossible, and please try to tell your
                        people that regardless of what others might say, direct negotiations or
                        negotiations with a mediator could not be possible, and even the Israelis
                        know this as well as we. I asked Zakariyah if it were not possible to change
                        public opinion on this subject, and he said, “No. Neither in this country
                        nor in other Arab countries. We might change their opinion on other topics,
                        but not on this.”</item>
                    <label>20.</label>
                    <item>I asked Zakariyah if there were anything he would like to add to the
                        review of <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>’s views. He said,
                        “Yes. First of all, we would like to have a new start in relationships
                        between our two countries. We have been through a period of confusion. We
                        know beyond all doubt that it is not in our interest to have any
                        misunderstandings with the U.S. We <pb facs="1012" n="980" xml:id="pg_980"/>
                        hope that your country feels the same way. We are fearful that your
                        government just does not understand us and that your people do not
                        understand us. We are fearful that they do not know what is possible and
                        what is impossible. Please explain that above everything else, we are
                        nationalists. We are Egyptians and we are not trying to rule the Arab world.
                        You may not believe that Nasir from time to time has felt that he has been
                        put into a corner. He feels he has been personally disliked at high levels
                        of your government.” I said that this was not so. Zakariyah went on, “He has
                        great respect for your President and for your people. He knows he has made
                        mistakes, but he thoroughly wants, as we all do, the friendship of the
                        United States and their help in making peace—but within the framework of
                        what is humanly possible. We do not think we can accomplish this. We do not
                        think our public relations are good, and we would like to be able to depend
                        on someone to get our point of view across. I hope that you get a favorable
                        response from your government along the lines of your talks with President
                            <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> and that we can move to
                        peace. We will be anxiously awaiting the response that is made as the result
                        of our conversations.”</item>
                    <label>21.</label>
                    <item>Zakariyah made the point that prior to the Khartoum meeting, the feeling
                        for continuation of some form of hostilities against Israel was very strong.
                        He said in fact that only on this aspect has there ever been Arab unity. But
                        at Khartoum, <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> took the initiative
                        in seeing that the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> must have political
                        peace, correct its own errors and settle its own problems with Yemen and the
                        other states in the Arabian Peninsula.</item>
                    <label>22.</label>
                    <item>Regarding Jerusalem, Zakariyah made essentially the same points as had
                            <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>. He noted that this problem
                        was of concern not only to the Arab countries, but also to a great many of
                        the African and other countries where there were high concentrations of the
                        Muslim faith.</item>
                    <label>23.</label>
                    <item>I was advised that if the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Secretary
                        General were to appoint an individual or group to draft a resolution along
                        the lines noted above, Zakariyah might well be sent to join Foreign Minister
                        Riyad in the discussions in New York. Like <persName corresp="#p_NS1"
                            >Nasir</persName>, Zakariyah thanked me for coming to Cairo and
                        expressed his hopes for a favorable response.</item>
                    <label>24.</label>
                    <item>I suspect the only way for me to be advised of the response to the
                        foregoing is to return to Beirut. When I return will depend on how far we
                        get in contractual discussions with the Government of Iraq. I can and will,
                        however, interrupt those discussions and come to Beirut to communicate with
                        you [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                        declassified</hi>]. We have devised a method so that he can discreetly
                        request me to return here. I assume there is no great hurry about getting
                        back to <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>, since he told me he was
                        going on vacation. I gather this is to be a short vacation, but <persName
                            corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> did not specify the number of days. I
                        also suppose he <pb facs="1013" n="981" xml:id="pg_981"/> would want to be
                        in touch if you consider the response a matter of urgency. I will do nothing
                        until I hear further from you. If it is decided for any reason that I should
                        not communicate a response to <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName>, I
                        will return to Beirut after conclusion of the conversations in Iraq and from
                        Beirut proceed home.</item>
                    <label>25.</label>
                    <item>I was asked by Pace of <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> and
                        Carruthers of the Los Angeles <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> whether I would
                        visit with them. I only spoke to Pace on the telephone and told him that I
                        was discussing commercial fertilizer and land reclamation as I have been
                        doing for some years. I would not give him the names of anybody with whom I
                        had had conversations. I did say that I was acting entirely on my own,
                        discussing commercial matters of long standing and was not in the <gloss
                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> with any official status.</item>
                    <label>26.</label>
                    <item>I have dictated this [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text
                            not declassified</hi>] in Beirut and will not have time to have it
                        transcribed for reading before I depart for Baghdad. I shall read it and
                        make such corrections as may be necessary on my return to Beirut.</item>
                    <label>27.</label>
                    <item>One final point from discussion with Zakariyah: While he spoke of making a
                        new start in our relationships, he said that of course at some point, we
                        must renew formal, diplomatic ties. I said only if this were the wish of
                        President <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Nasir</persName> and that they should
                        then instruct their Foreign Minister to be in touch with our Secretary of
                        State. I noted it was they who broke relations, and they who would have to
                        take the necessary steps to discuss their resumption.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
