<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Chile ( (Norweb) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign currency</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="oil" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="120"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d120">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">825.5151/120</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Norweb</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1560</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-10-25">October 25,
                            1933</date>.<lb/>[Received November 2.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that since my despatch
                    No. 1535 of September 6, 1933, various American interests, seizing upon a
                    favorable moment in the Chilean financial situation, have taken the frozen
                    credit problem into their own hands and by means of private deals with the
                    Government have liquidated within the short space of a few weeks at least
                    $2,000,000 of their blocked funds.</p>
                <p>The details of the negotiations that resulted in the repatriation of these funds
                    are quickly told. In the last three months Chilean currency has appreciated 100%
                    and dollars can now be bought for about 25 pesos instead of at the former rate
                    of 50 pesos. At this relatively reasonable level, foreign interests began to
                    seek means for obtaining <pb facs="0224" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/> foreign
                    exchange in order to move their funds and the idea was conceived of offering a
                    hard-pressed government a premium of 15 to 20% on all money transferred out of
                    the country. The bait proved irresistible and it was not difficult to obtain the
                    cooperation of the Finance Minister and through him, that of the Exchange
                    Control Commission. For all the Government’s assistance, however, the plan would
                    not have been possible if American business, in its eagerness to move funds from
                    Chile, had not been willing to pay for the privilege at a rate 2¼ times the
                    prevailing rates for commercial credits under compensation agreements, and if
                    the recent improvement in export trade conditions had not, for the first time in
                    two years, provided foreign exchange substantially in excess of current
                    requirements.</p>
                <p>All transactions under this arrangement are secret as they are in a sense
                    extra-legal. This aspect has caused several American firms to hesitate to avail
                    themselves of the opportunity, but the only danger of future repercussions would
                    seem to be in the remote possibility of a Congressional investigation and even
                    in that event the attack would probably center on the disclosure of Government
                    connivance. The principal companies involved are the General Motors, National
                    City Bank of New York, All America Cables, the International Telephone and
                    Telegraph Company, the local subsidiary of the Standard Oil Company of New
                    Jersey, and, among British firms, the Shell-Mex, Chile, Limited; but smaller
                    enterprises and private individuals with blocked funds also have been obtaining
                    exchange on similar terms.</p>
                <p>In its more diplomatic aspects the action of the Government indicates a
                    disposition to be more reasonable. Recently the Finance Minister spoke to an
                    American bank representative of his desire to avoid the threat of compensation
                    agreements with the United States and Great Britain. Beyond a doubt, this
                    attitude has influenced him to some extent in agreeing to these private deals
                    with the principal holders of blocked funds. Moreover, to my knowledge, American
                    and British nitrate producers have urged upon the Minister the importance of
                    doing something to remove the danger that nitrate shipments to the United States
                    and the United Kingdom may be blocked to take care of the frozen credit
                    situation. My British colleague also informs me that to his formal demand for
                    equality in the matter of foreign exchange, referred to in my despatch No. 1535
                    of September 6, 1933, the Government has recently replied that it is actively
                    studying the matter and hopes, within the near future, to make a definite
                    proposal to the British Government with a view to affording relief to frozen
                    commercial credits and providing adequate exchange for trading purposes.</p>
                <p>While these signs are encouraging, nevertheless, promises and extralegal
                    expedients cannot be counted upon to afford a permanent basis <pb facs="0225"
                        n="137" xml:id="pg_137"/> for the settlement of this vexatious problem. The
                    exodus of the funds in question, by relieving some of the pressure for a
                    compensation agreement to repatriate frozen credits, has served to improve the
                    tactical situation and if the process is continued our task with the Government
                    will be made considerably easier. However, we cannot tell if the trend of
                    exchange will remain sufficiently favorable to permit this procedure to
                    continue, and our satisfaction at the cooperation between the Government and
                    American business interests in the question of the transfer of frozen credits
                    must not cause us to lose sight of the importance of a more liberal attitude on
                    Chile’s part in supplying the exchange necessary for the needs of our current
                    commerce. Neither must we overlook the problem of obtaining the transfer of the
                    retirement funds of those individuals, who by force of circumstances, are not in
                    a position to bargain with the Government for the return of the foreign currency
                    due them.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">R. Henry Norweb</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
