<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-07-01T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-07-01T13:00:00-05:00" n="274" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d274">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/3567: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-07-01T13:00:00-05:00">July 1, 1933—1
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 2:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>103. My telegram No. 101, June 30, 4 p.m. I formally declared
                                mediation proceedings commenced this morning. I received in the
                                Embassy the delegates of the Government at 10 a.m. and the delegates
                                of the opposition at 11 a.m. I read the President’s message to both
                                groups. It was received with the most enthusiastic approval. The
                                declaration of the President is of peculiar value in that it makes
                                definitively clear the President’s personal interest in the success
                                of these negotiations.</p>
                            <p>I subsequently read a statement emphasizing the fact that my tender
                                of good offices would not have been made if I had not previously
                                clearly understood that my services were desired by both sides in
                                the controversy. A copy in full of my statement will be sent by
                                mail.</p>
                            <p>On Monday I shall hold a meeting of the delegates of the opposition
                                to determine the agenda and to exchange preliminary views. I have
                                arranged for a meeting of the governmental delegates on Tuesday for
                                the same general purpose. I am happy to state that there is very
                                evident on both sides not only a conciliatory disposition but an
                                apparent feeling of expectancy that these negotiations will have a
                                successful outcome.</p>
                            <p>The opposition factions are already splitting into two groups, one
                                extremely radical; and the other, the larger group, decidedly
                                conservative. In the former category is of course the A B C which is
                                composed very largely of radicals. Fortunately however the
                                representatives of that organization are both intelligent and
                                well-disposed and I am hopeful that for some weeks at least the
                                organization can be kept in line.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>