<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-08-22T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-08-22T15:00:00-05:00" n="329" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/3694: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-08-22T15:00:00-05:00">August 22, 1933—3
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 8:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>180. With the arrival this morning of Colonels Mendieta and Mendez
                                Peñate all of the old-time political leaders of the opposition have
                                returned to Cuba with the exception of Miguel Mariano Gómez who is
                                due to arrive by the end of the month.</p>
                            <p>A determined effort is being made now by certain of these leaders,
                                notably Menocal, in conjunction with the extreme radicals to
                                transform the present Government of Cuba into a purely revolutionary
                                    <pb facs="0458" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/>
                                <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> government. It is their announced
                                intention to abolish the Congress and the existing judiciary and to
                                remove all local provincial and municipal officials throughout the
                                Republic in order to replace them with their own henchmen. During
                                the past 3 days I have repeatedly emphasized in all of my
                                conversations with these leaders and with the leaders of the groups
                                and parties represented in the present Government that only through
                                the maintenance of a constitutional form of government in Cuba until
                                the next national elections would it be possible for the Government
                                to make effective the urgent measures required to improve economic
                                conditions here as well as the financial situation of the Government
                                itself and in addition thereto to take steps to ensure the
                                satisfactory result of the next elections through the enactment of a
                                new electoral code and through the passage of constitutional reforms
                                to be submitted to a constituent assembly. Furthermore, I have made
                                it clear that a <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> government governing
                                solely by decree would not in my judgment be able to retain the
                                support and the confidence of the people for any protracted period
                                owing to the unstable conditions which obtain in Cuba and that
                                insistence upon a revolutionary <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> form
                                of government would in all likelihood result in general chaos.</p>
                            <p>In an interview which I had yesterday with General Menocal I stressed
                                my own belief, as above-indicated, and further made clear that we
                                had continued official relations with the present Government of Cuba
                                in view of our belief that whatever the cause of the change in the
                                Government the result had been merely a change in the persons
                                entrusted with the executive power of the Government through methods
                                provided in the existing constitution. I told him that I felt it
                                essential, as I knew my Government did, that in this moment of
                                crisis all important leaders, of whatever faction they might
                                represent, get together in support of the present Government and
                                assist it in making effective, at the earliest possible moment, the
                                program of reform, both political and economic, which it had already
                                elaborated in principle.…</p>
                            <p>A portion of the press is coming rather timorously to the support of
                                the necessity of maintaining a constitutional form of government in
                                Cuba. None of the real leaders of public opinion have, however, as
                                yet had courage enough to come out openly against the popular
                                agitation for revolutionary government and a resultant clean sweep
                                of all of the former officeholders no matter whether they were
                                legitimately entitled to the offices they were holding or not. Until
                                I can persuade some of these leaders to come out positively against
                                any such policy, I am afraid to urge the Government to take the
                                stand because of the fact that the opportunity might then be used by
                                certain self-seekers to attack the Government on that ground to
                                their own advantage. <pb facs="0459" n="371" xml:id="pg_371"/> I
                                shall confer today and tomorrow with all of the outstanding leaders,
                                including those recently arrived, and I shall hope to be able to
                                persuade them of the necessity for prompt action along the lines
                                suggested in benefit of Cuba.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>