<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-09-09T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-09-09T17:00:00-05:00" n="371" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d371">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/3804: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-09-09T16:00:00-06:00">September 9, 1933—4
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 7:45 (?) p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>182. With reference to our telephone conversation of this
                                    morning<note n="45" xml:id="d371fn45">See <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> I delivered your message regarding his
                                action looking toward producing peace in Cuba to Dr. Puig, who
                                highly appreciated it. He said that he has not heard directly from
                                any countries except Chile. He said that both Chile and Argentina
                                are in harmony but Chile thinks opportunity should be given to all
                                countries to unite in concerted action, otherwise some who were not
                                given this opportunity might feel slighted. According to a telegram
                                from Mexican Chargé d’Affaires in Washington, sent after conferring
                                with Latin American colleagues there, Argentina, without discussing
                                the validity of the Piatt Amendment, would not approve of United
                                States intervention even in case of civil war. Dr. Puig will let me
                                know as soon as he hears further and I will telegraph. He is doing
                                everything possible to aid in securing order in Cuba. He says the
                                feeling against intervention by the United States is deep-seated and
                                unanimous.</p>
                            <pb facs="0502" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/>
                            <p>He showed me a telegram from Mexican Chargé d’Affaires in Washington
                                to the effect that some of the Latin American diplomats in
                                Washington hesitate to sign a round robin to Cuba because such
                                action might indicate they were trying to intervene in Cuban
                                affairs.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Daniels</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>