<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="378" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d378">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/4221</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of
                                    State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-09-11">September 11,
                                        1933</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The Brazilian Ambassador called on me this afternoon to say that he
                                had received a telegram from his Government stating that the
                                President’s action in calling in the Brazilian diplomatic
                                representative here and explaining our point of view in regard to
                                the Cuban situation had been highly appreciated at Rio.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador then asked me if we approved of what the Mexican
                                Ministry of Foreign Affairs was attempting to do in regard to the
                                suggestion to be made by the ABCM powers at Habana that it was
                                important for the Cubans to form a stable government capable of
                                maintaining order in the country. I told the Ambassador that we
                                approved of the attitude of the Mexican Government in the
                                instance.</p>
                            <p>The Ambassador added that his Government desired him to say that in
                                no case would Brazil take part in any action which might present
                                possibilities of degenerating into a movement directed against the
                                United States on the question of intervention. I said to Mr. Lima e
                                Silva <pb facs="0509" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/> that we did not
                                apprehend that the Mexicans had anything of that sort in mind; we
                                believed they were sincerely desirous of giving good advice to the
                                Cubans. Mr. Lima e Silva said that it was his understanding that as
                                the Mexican proposal now stood the idea was that the diplomatic
                                representatives of the four interested powers here in Washington
                                should agree on a declaration to be made at Habana. However, he
                                apprehended that the Argentine representative here would be unable
                                to take part in a move of this kind, it being clear from the
                                Argentine note published a few days ago that the Argentine Minister
                                for Foreign Affairs was opposed to the Mexican suggestions.</p>
                            <p>I thanked the Brazilian Ambassador for his information.</p>
                            <closer><signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">efferson</hi>] C[<hi rend="smallcaps">affery</hi>]</signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>