<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-09-11T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-09-11T18:00:00-05:00" n="382" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d382">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/3830: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-09-11T18:00:00-05:00">September 11, 1933—6
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 8:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>233. My 231, September 11, noon. In addition to the statements of
                                hostility and determined opposition to the present regime announced
                                this morning by the A.B.C. and the party headed by General Menocal
                                and the similar statement which is to be published this afternoon by
                                the Unión Nacionalista, the fourth largest political organization,
                                the O. C. R. R., likewise will issue this afternoon a similar
                                statement. As the result of these public declarations of opposition
                                the political situation <pb facs="0511" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/> is
                                crystallizing noticeably. The attitude thus taken makes it evident
                                to the public that the organized political strength of the Republic
                                which itself represents the large majority of the Cuban people is
                                opposed to a continuation of the present regime. Under these
                                conditions I desire once more to emphasize that in my judgment it
                                would be highly prejudicial to our interests to intimate in any
                                manner that recognition of the existing regime was being considered
                                by us. Every effort is being made and has already been made, through
                                fictitious reports inserted in the local press, to create the
                                impression that the Government of the United States is on the verge
                                of recognizing the group headed by Grau San Martín as the
                                provisional government of Cuba. Headlines appeared in the morning
                                newspapers that President Roosevelt intended to afford immediate
                                financial assistance to Grau San Martín and that recognition by the
                                United States would be obtained within a few hours or days. In view
                                of the campaign of misrepresentation and distortion of the truth
                                which is being conducted by the group now in power and which is
                                causing both consternation and resentment on the part of the
                                powerful parties opposed to the existing regime, I feel it would be
                                to be issued by you making unmistakably plain the attitude of the
                                Government of the United States in view of the conditions which now
                                exist in Cuba.</p>
                            <p>In accordance with my telephone conversation with you 2 days ago I
                                venture to suggest a statement along the following lines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The chief concern of the Government of the United States is,
                                        as it has been, that the Cuban people solve their own
                                        political problems in accordance with the desires of a
                                        majority of the Cubans. The Government of the United States
                                        believes that only through a provisional government which
                                        responds to the will of the majority of the Cuban people can
                                        stability be obtained and assurance be given that national
                                        elections can be held under the jurisdiction of such
                                        government with such full and ample guarantees of
                                        impartiality, the fairness as to make possible the
                                        successful inauguration of a new permanent and
                                        constitutional government of Cuba. It would seem unnecessary
                                        to repeat that the Government of the United States has no
                                        interest in behalf of or prejudice against any political
                                        group or independent organization which is today active in
                                        the political life of Cuba. In view of its deep and abiding
                                        interest in the welfare of the Cuban people and the security
                                        of the Republic of Cuba it cannot and will not accord
                                        recognition to any government in Cuba other than a
                                        legitimate and constitutional government unless conclusive
                                        evidence is presented that such government effectively
                                        represents the will of a majority of the people of the
                                        Republic, that it is capable of maintaining order and of
                                        guaranteeing the protection of ‘life, property and
                                        individual liberty’ and finally that such government is
                                        competent to carry out the functions and obligations which
                                        are incumbent upon any stable government.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <pb facs="0512" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/>
                            <p>The impression is very general today that the Grau San Martín regime
                                is evanescent. Of the four Cabinet members appointed yesterday
                                Chibas and Finlay have refused to serve and I am likewise advised
                                that Barquin will not take office. A complete Cabinet was to have
                                been announced this morning and such announcement has now been
                                postponed until 10 o’clock tonight. There seems to be very little
                                probability that any Cubans of standing or reputation will accept
                                office. I wish to emphasize again that conclusive evidence has now
                                been presented to my satisfaction that the existing regime
                                represents only the student, a few radical agitators and a small
                                number of insignificant radical groups which have no political
                                importance or following whatever.</p>
                            <p>The longer the present regime continues in power the more dangerous
                                the situation becomes. For over a week no government department has
                                been able to function and all semblance of order and discipline in
                                the Army is vanishing rapidly.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>