<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Cuba ( (Welles) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d402</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">402</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-09-17T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-09-17T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recb140a4efc2e771d" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Warships</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-09-17T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-09-17T14:00:00-05:00" n="402"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d402">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/3908: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-09-17T14:00:00-05:00"
                            >September 17, 1933—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 6:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>271. I have just finished a secret conversation of 2 hours’ length with Grau San
                    Martín at a friend’s house.</p>
                <p>I told him that I had requested Berle to see him last night in order that he
                    might realize how desperately serious the situation had become and how rapidly
                    dangers of every kind were increasing both in number and in extent. I said that
                    in my judgment confidence in his Government was daily diminishing and the
                    attitude now assumed by financial, commercial and agricultural elements in
                    refusing to pay taxes, in closing down or in canceling orders wherever possible
                    to dp so, and in protesting publicly their opposition to a continuation of the
                    present regime must certainly convince him, as it had me, that the Government
                    was not supported by exceedingly important elements in the country. I said that
                    in my opinion lack of confidence was not directed in any sense against him
                    personally nor most of the men with whom he had surrounded himself but in the
                    basic fact that his Government had been installed as the result of a mutiny in
                    the Army which in itself shattered all confidence in authority and in the second
                    place that it was responsive solely to one numerically small group in the
                    country, namely, the student group. I called his attention to the fact that I
                    was constantly receiving accurate information from all over the Republic and
                    that no matter how often his Government might announce that order was being
                    maintained, I knew, and I had no doubt that he knew, that disorders were
                    increasing every moment and that neither the lives nor the property of Cuban
                    citizens at the present time were safe and I was by no means certain that the
                    lives and properties of American citizens or other foreigners were safe except
                    in those ports where American warships were stationed. He admitted this fact
                    quite frankly. I then referred to the official declaration regarding recognition
                    issued by my Government in Washington 4 days ago.<note n="58" xml:id="d402fn58"
                        >See telegram No. 96, September 11, midnight, to the Ambassador in Cuba,
                            <ref target="#pg_424">p. 424</ref>.</note> I told him that in my <pb
                        facs="0532" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/> judgment none of the requisites which
                    he [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] had mentioned in that declaration existed in his
                    government; that the government did not have the support of the Cuban people
                    other than that of a relatively small group; that public order was most
                    decidedly not being maintained; that the government certainly was not stable and
                    that no government could be considered as carrying out the functions of
                    government when, as I had no doubt he knew, a great number of the provincial and
                    municipal internal revenue offices were now filled by soldiers who were
                    pocketing such few receipts as might come in and when furthermore it was plainly
                    apparent that at the same time that the government did not collect revenues it
                    likewise did not have sufficient funds in reserve to meet the ordinary daily
                    charges upon it for more than an extremely brief period.</p>
                <p>At this point he argued with me regarding popular support leaving the other
                    features of my statement uncontroverted. He said that every one in the country
                    would support the government if the United States would accord recognition. I
                    reminded him that our recognition could not in the first place be employed by
                    him as a means of obtaining popular support but was a matter which rested
                    entirely within our own sovereign discretion and that we did not, in justice to
                    the Cuban people, intend to exert that power as a means of attempting to keep a
                    minority group in control of the Cuban government.</p>
                <p>I told him that my conversations with the leaders of the really important
                    political groups opposed to his regime had convinced me that they were
                    unanimously in accordance with the main features of the program which he had
                    announced as the ideal of his government and of the student group and that on
                    that point consequently there was no question at issue. I told him, however,
                    that they all felt that the present government had been selected by the students
                    and that the members of his Cabinet were subservient to every whim of the
                    students; and that they felt that no government of this kind could either last
                    or even attempt to carry out the program which it had set for itself. I asked
                    him in the true interest of the Republic in this moment of gravest emergency
                    what possible objection the student group or he himself could have to a
                    government of concentration composed of men who were not active politicians and
                    who were individuals of high standing and reputation who might be indicated by
                    the various opposition groups because of the fact that they had confidence in
                    them which confidence they did not have in most of the members of the present
                    Cabinet.</p>
                <p>In his reply Grau San Martín adopted an extremely conciliatory attitude. He said
                    that he believed such a solution was necessary and that he himself favored it.
                    He said he recognized that practical considerations must be taken into account
                    and that at a meeting with <pb facs="0533" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/> the
                    political leaders this afternoon he would maintain that attitude since he did
                    not consider that individuals were of any importance in comparison with the
                    necessity of saving the country. The attitude so expressed to me is, of course,
                    exactly the reverse of what he has previously repeatedly said to the political
                    leaders in past conferences. It was very apparent throughout the conversation
                    that Grau San Martín was extremely apprehensive. When I touched upon the subject
                    of the Army and the conditions in the Army and the imminent danger which I
                    foresaw from the fact that the sergeants and soldiers now felt, quite correctly,
                    that the real control of the country is in their hands and that they can
                    exercise such control whenever they see fit, it was apparent that that question
                    was the cause of his apprehension. He told me that Batista wanted to be
                    President but that he thought that Batista would try to gain popular support for
                    the coming elections among the laboring classes and would not now attempt a
                    further <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> in order to install himself in the
                    Palace. He admitted that Batista “had to be handled” and that no orders could be
                    given to him with any expectation of their being carried out. He said there was
                    no alternative whatever to leaving Batista in his present post as Chief of Staff
                    and that if any attempt were made to remove him the Army would at once become
                    unmanageable. I reminded him that in my previous conversations with him he had
                    expressed the opinion that the sergeants and soldiers who had joined in the
                    mutiny were so pure in mind and were so devoted to the ideals of the students
                    that they had no ulterior ambitions. He told me that he was willing to admit
                    that he had been gravely mistaken on this point.</p>
                <p>The Department will easily gather from this summary of my conversation how
                    utterly impractical and visionary Grau San Martín is and how little hope of
                    success there can be from a government controlled by him and by the students.
                    The effects of his present apprehension, however, will make a compromise this
                    afternoon more likely. The meeting referred to will be held at 3 o’clock and
                    upon receipt of information as to the result of such meeting I shall telegraph
                    the Department.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
