<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-06-14T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-06-14T15:00:00-05:00" n="567" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d567">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.51/1576: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-06-14T15:00:00-05:00">June 14, 1933—3
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>83. My 54 and 62 and Department’s 37. The Secretary of the Treasury
                            advised me Saturday that the Government would be unable to make any
                            payments this month towards arrears in salaries of civilian employees of
                            the Government. The profits resulting from the six million dollars
                            silver transaction will be utilized in great part in meeting payments
                            due bankers and the balance remaining of about $1,400,000 will be used
                            to meet salaries of the judiciary, the Congress, and the Army. The Cuban
                            Government desired to obtain a tax advance from the petroleum companies
                            amounting to approximately $1,000,000 in accordance with the precedent
                            established December 1932, intending to devote this advance to salary
                            arrears. The Chase Bank thereupon interposed and insisted that any
                            advance so collected must be considered as public works revenues and
                            consequently solely applicable to interest and sinking fund charges upon
                            the bankers’ obligations.</p>
                        <p>The suggestion was consequently made that any tax advance received from
                            the petroleum interests be devoted to meeting the June payments due to
                            the bankers thus releasing an equivalent amount from the silver
                            seigniorage profits (which are not pledged) for payment on civilian
                            employees’ salary arrears. Both the Cuban Government and the local
                            representative of the Chase Bank see no reason why there should be any
                            objection to this proposal, but have requested that I support the
                            proposal and that the Department so advise the bankers. Doctor Averhoff
                            advises me that a strike will be declared by the governmental employees
                            if nothing is done for them this month.</p>
                        <p>Since there is no legal obstacle to the procedure above indicated, I can
                            see no reason why the Cuban Government should not take the action
                            outlined or why the American bankers should interpose any objection.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>