<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>11. Memorandum From the Deputy Director for Plans, Central Intelligence
                    Agency (Dulles) to Director of Central Intelligence ) to Director of Central
                    Intelligence Smith</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951-54IranEd2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recPnftMNhM1QKAYO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Stockpile</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recb6XG1ZU9Ik84CR" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Broadcasting</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="international-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150" lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" subject="ozone-layer" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271" lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127" lcsh-match="exact">Stockpile</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="international-military-education-and-training" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="11"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d11">
                <head>11. Memorandum From the Deputy Director for Plans, Central Intelligence Agency
                        (<persName corresp="#p_DAW_1">Dulles</persName>) to Director of Central
                    Intelligence <persName corresp="#p_SWB_1">Smith</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d11fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency,
                            <gloss target="#t_DDO_1">DDO</gloss> Files, Job 79–01228A, Box 11,
                        Folder 14, Iran 1951–1953. Top Secret. The undated attachment was apparently
                        drafted in the Directorate of Plans.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline rendition="#right">
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-28"
                        >March 28, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>’s Role in Iran</item>
                </list>
                <p>1. I have reviewed the attached memorandum<note n="2" xml:id="d11fn2">A list at
                        the end of <persName corresp="#p_DAW_1">Dulles</persName>’ cover memorandum
                        refers to two enclosures, TS 55559, attached and printed, and TS 55558,
                        which was not found.</note> respecting <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                    >CIA</gloss>’s role in Iran and pass it on with concurrence. I wish to stress,
                    however, that the steps which <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> alone can
                    take in this situation will probably not substantially change the present
                    downward trend and to be really effective should be combined with an over-all
                    program in the economic, financial, and military fields. This would imply
                    coordinated planning.</p>
                <pb facs="0084" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/>
                <p>2. With the present trend I feel that Iran may be lost to the West in the coming
                    12 months and believe that it is urgent to plan and carry out the steps which
                    might change the trend and protect this vital position in the Middle East.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_DAW_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAW_1">Allen W. Dulles</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>’S ROLE IN IRAN</p>
                    <p rend="center">Summary</p>
                    <p>1. Currently <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> operations are severely
                        restricted in Iran owing primarily to the hampering effect of increased
                        distrust of the West, including the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>. The
                        Iranians, alleging that <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> aid has been
                        wholly inadequate, remain unconvinced of the genuineness of <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> interest in Iran.</p>
                    <p>2. Under existing circumstances, and in the absence of a series of major
                        overt <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> efforts in the political, economic,
                        and military fields, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> can do little more
                        than intensify its psychological-political warfare with the object of trying
                        to prevent a bad situation from growing worse. To this end, <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> is:</p>
                    <p>a. Providing increased subsidization for selected Iranian newspapers.</p>
                    <p>b. Extending guidance and money to Iranian elements opposed to
                        ultra-nationalism and terrorism.</p>
                    <p>c. Investigating the feasibility of establishing new, pro-Western political
                        parties.</p>
                    <p>d. Taking steps to discredit and if possible disrupt forces hostile to <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> security interests.</p>
                    <p>e. Exploring the possibility of establishing [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                            line not declassified</hi>] a radio station for clandestine broadcasts
                        which would reach at least certain parts of Iran.</p>
                    <p>f. Gearing its collection machinery to provide intelligence needed for these
                        activities.</p>
                    <p>3. Obviously in the present situation these efforts alone cannot be relied
                        upon to prevent the possible collapse of the regime. Accordingly <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> is endeavoring to organize indigenous
                        resistance groups against the possibility that a hostile government may be
                        installed in Tehran.</p>
                    <p>4. If the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> should establish a policy of
                        all-out aid to Iran, which would produce a more friendly and cooperative
                        atmosphere, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> operations could be
                        expanded to include:</p>
                    <pb facs="0085" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/>
                    <p>a. A general overhauling of the Iranian intelligence and security
                        services.</p>
                    <p>b. Greater influence upon the Iranian press.</p>
                    <p>c. The possible establishment of a clandestine radio station in Iran.</p>
                    <p>d. Greatly intensified political warfare.</p>
                    <p>e. Accelerated organization, with better prospects of success, of resistance
                        groups and escape and evasion nets for operations in the event of Soviet
                        occupation.</p>
                    <p>This expanded scale of <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> operations would
                        not be possible of accomplishment covertly without the pretext and cover
                        which only a greatly increased overt program would provide.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>’S ROLE IN IRAN</p>
                    <p>1. In view of the seriousness of the Iranian situation, <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> is striving to do what it can to help
                        reduce the possibility of the country’s falling into Soviet hands and to
                        foster the establishment of an enduring pro-Western alignment. Existing
                        conditions are such, however, as to make all <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                            >CIA</gloss> operations exceptionally difficult and uncertain of
                        outcome. Of the various circumscribing factors, the most serious is a
                        mounting distrust of the West, including the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >US</gloss>, which makes it almost impossible to send additional covert
                        agents into the country, restricts the movements and effectiveness of those
                        already there, severely limits the number of Iranians willing to cooperate
                        with the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> in clandestine operations, and
                        makes the people in general unreceptive, if not downright hostile, to <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> overtures. <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >US</gloss> policy has not succeeded in demonstrating to the Iranians
                        that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> is genuinely interested in their
                        country or in convincing them that their salvation lies in firm alignment
                        with the West, and not in rapprochement with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                            >USSR</gloss> nor in an untenable course of neutrality.</p>
                    <p>2. It is believed that the conditions noted above will obtain so long as
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> assistance to Iran is maintained at
                        the present rate or at a rate which is not substantially more vigorous than
                        at present. It is questionable whether the program provided for in <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 107<note n="3" xml:id="d11fn3">
                            <ref target="#d6">Document 6</ref>.</note> even if fully and speedily
                        executed would suffice to reverse the unfavorable trend. Under these
                        circumstances, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> can do little more than
                        intensify its psychological-political warfare campaign in an effort to
                        prevent or retard further deterioration of the Iranian situation.
                        Specifically, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> is currently augmenting
                        the following existing programs in Iran:</p>
                    <p>a. Providing for increased subsidization of newspapers, for the preclusive
                        buying of newsprint or printing facilities, and (if circumstances warrant)
                        for the establishment of new newspapers. These meas<pb facs="0086" n="49"
                            xml:id="pg_49"/>ures are designed to combat the tendency of influential
                        sections of the Iranian press to encourage and support the chauvinism and
                        religious fanaticism which have a paralyzing effect on the Iranian
                        Government.</p>
                    <p>b. Extending guidance and financial support to individuals, groups, and
                        parties hostile to the ultra-nationalists, fanatical terrorists, and
                        pro-Soviet groups.</p>
                    <p>c. Investigating the feasibility of establishing new political parties, which
                        might include a progressive religious party, a moderate “socialist” party to
                        draw liberals away from the Tudeh Party, and a party with vigorous,
                        pro-Western representation in the Parliament.</p>
                    <p>d. Taking positive steps to discredit and if possible disrupt forces inimical
                        to <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> security interests by subversion and
                        by directing black propaganda against the leading chauvinists, fanatics, and
                        Communists.</p>
                    <p>e. Exploring the possibility of establishing [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                            line not declassified</hi>] a radio station for clandestine broadcasts
                        in Azerbaijani. These broadcasts (countering those of the Soviet “Free
                        Azerbaijan” station) could be beamed to certain parts of Iran but not so
                        effectively as if the station were located in Iran, which is hardly possible
                        under present conditions.</p>
                    <p>f. Gearing its collection machinery to provide increased intelligence needed
                        in connection with these various activities. “Soft” targets relatively easy
                        to penetrate for information purposes include [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines
                            not declassified</hi>] (especially the following of Mulla <persName
                            corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>), [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines
                            not declassified</hi>]. “Hard” targets requiring long-range operations
                        to penetrate include the Tudeh Party, [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines not
                            declassified</hi>].</p>
                    <p>g. [<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (3½ lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                    <p>3. For the reasons outlined in Paragraph 2 above, these efforts obviously
                        cannot be relied upon to prevent the possible collapse of the present
                        regime. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> has accordingly begun to
                        identify and establish contact with the tribal, military, and civil leaders
                        who would effectively support a resistance program in the event that a
                        hostile government is installed in Iran. Once agreements are reached with
                        these leaders, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> will determine the
                        material aid which they would require and will commence to acquire and
                        stockpile material at appropriate points.</p>
                    <p>4. If the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> should decide to follow a policy
                        of all-out aid to Iran, both overt and covert, the prospect of preserving
                        Iran during the cold war period could be immeasurably improved. Greater
                        cover would be available, and the atmosphere might be cleared for augmenting
                        and expanding <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> operations, which could
                        be more effective in support of a program directed positively toward
                        promoting stability and active cooperation with the West instead of toward
                        the negative objective of trying to prevent a bad situation from growing
                        worse. Emphasis would be placed on rehabilitating Iran and building up
                        immunity to Soviet <pb facs="0087" n="50" xml:id="pg_50"/> and
                        Soviet-inspired subversion, and plans could be more effectively laid for
                        operations to be carried out if Soviet troops should invade and occupy
                        Iran.</p>
                    <p>5. Under a <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> program of all-out aid, <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> operations could include the
                        following:</p>
                    <p>a. A general overhauling of the Iranian intelligence and security services.
                        The program would include material aid; training of key officers in modern
                        techniques; and insistence (at least to some degree) that <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> guidance in such matters be followed. The
                        objective would be to create an efficient organization with which <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> could work and which would be extremely
                        useful in helping to prevent hostile penetration of key government offices
                        and in running operations against the Tudeh Party, Soviet installations, and
                        the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> itself.</p>
                    <p>b. Greater influence upon the Iranian press. Subsidization would be increased
                        as needed; hostile publications could be forced out of business; and the
                        direction of certain influential papers would, in effect, be completely
                        taken over.</p>
                    <p>c. If possible, the establishment of a clandestine broadcasting station in
                        Iran. The station, purporting to be inside the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                            >USSR</gloss>, would transmit black propaganda designed to discredit the
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and Soviet Communism and aimed
                        particularly at the Azerbaijani and other waverers. This station could be a
                        powerful instrument in strengthening Iran against hostile penetration from
                        without and within.</p>
                    <p>d. Greatly intensified covert political activity in support of desirable and
                        against undesirable individuals and groups. If need be, the government
                        itself or key officials therein could be subsidized to promote <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> security interests. The subsidization of
                        politicians and political parties has long been a common practice in Iran,
                        and effective steps would be taken to encourage defection in the Tudeh Party
                        and to create vigorous new groups which would actively support <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> interests.</p>
                    <p>e. Increased efforts, with better prospects of success, to organize
                        resistance groups to function in the event of Soviet invasion and
                        occupation. This program would include more substantial efforts to prepare
                        tribal groups and segments of the army to carry out guerrilla activities
                        against Soviet units and installations. It might even prove feasible to
                        bolster the Shah’s avowed intention of withdrawing to the mountains and
                        setting up a government there.</p>
                    <p>f. [<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (6 lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
