<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>19. Intelligence Memorandum Prepared in the Office of Current Intelligence,
                    Directorate of Intelligence, Central Intelligence Agency</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951-54IranEd2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recebl4V1INuqlVGh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="rec2ojF1nU3Lvcn3X" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Kurds</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recLolgZHy7viyqKU" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068390"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="19"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                <head>19. Intelligence Memorandum Prepared in the Office of Current Intelligence,
                    Directorate of Intelligence, Central Intelligence Agency<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d19fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, <gloss
                            target="#t_OCI_1">OCI</gloss> Files, Job 91T01172R, Box 3, Folder 29.
                        Top Secret; ACORN.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline rendition="#right">
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-30"
                        >April 30, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The Soviet Attitude toward the Situation in Iran since the Assassination
                        of <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>1. The situation in Iran since the assassination of Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName> on 7 March has presented the Soviet
                    Union with favorable opportunities to increase its influence and gain ultimate
                    control over the country. The ostensible show of non-intervention in the
                    situation on the part of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> calls for a
                    comprehensive review of recent Soviet diplomatic moves, current propaganda,
                    activity along the Soviet-Iranian border, and the tactics of the outlawed
                    pro-Soviet Tudeh Party. The possibility of future Soviet intervention under the
                    terms of the 1921 treaty should also be considered.</p>
                <p>2. Diplomatically, the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> has continued its
                    policy, inaugurated in the latter half of 1950, of displaying friendship for the
                    Iranian Government and not interfering in the government’s problems connected
                    with oil nationalization, internal unrest, and relations with the British. There
                    is no evidence that the Soviet Ambassador in Iran has put any pressure on the
                    Iranian Government. In corroboration of this, Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH_2">Ala</persName> told the French Ambassador in late March
                    that there had been no Soviet pressure on him. The Soviet Union seems aware that
                    for the time being any ill-timed Soviet diplomatic pressure or demands for oil
                    rights might cause these advantages to be forfeited.</p>
                <pb facs="0108" n="71" xml:id="pg_71"/>
                <p>3. Soviet propaganda since 7 March, in its daily reporting on Iran, reveals the
                    Kremlin’s close interest in developments there, particularly with reference to
                    the oil situation, the recent strikes, and public demonstrations. Consistent
                    with its diplomatic effort to disassociate the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> from events in Iran, Moscow has refrained from commenting
                    editorially on actions taken by the Iranian Government or speculating on future
                    developments. Soviet press and propaganda have avoided any hint of
                    unfriendliness towards the government or comment on its instability. Since
                        <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName>’s assassination this
                    propaganda has concentrated on <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>–<gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> rivalry for Iranian oil and <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> exploitation
                    of Iran. The Communists’ “clandestine” “Free Azerbaijan” radio in Baku, on the
                    other hand, has adhered to its previous policy of attacking the Shah, Premier
                        <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Ala</persName>, and the Majlis as pawns of
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    imperialism and betrayers of the Iranian people.</p>
                <p>4. While the Soviet Union is believed capable of invading Iran successfully
                    without prior warning, there has been no indication that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is preparing to take such a step at this
                    time. Iranian military intelligence, although fragmentary, constitutes the best
                    source of information on Soviet border activities. This source reports Soviet
                    troop movements on the Azerbaijan frontier and some additional military
                    activities since late February. These are probably connected with the annual
                    Soviet maneuvers in this area, which began earlier than usual this year. Reports
                    that dissident elements (exiled Azerbaijani Democrats and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Barzani</persName> Kurds) are on the frontier ready to
                    invade Iran have appeared, as is common during periods of tribal migrations and
                    regular maneuvers. No reports of any Soviet activity on the Khorassan sector of
                    the border east of the Caspian Sea have been received. Soviet military maneuvers
                    on this section of the frontier generally begin later than those on the
                    Azerbaijan border.</p>
                <p>5. Communist policy in Iran since <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1"
                    >Razmara</persName>’s assassination has been aimed at inciting further agitation
                    on the oil issue while keeping Communist connections with the disturbances on a
                    covert level. Although there is no firm evidence of pro-Soviet Tudeh Party
                    involvement in the current disturbances, press reports and Iranian officials
                    commonly blame the Tudeh Party. The Tudeh is said to be behind the “Organization
                    for the Expropriation of the Anglo Iranian Oil Company” (<gloss
                        target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss>), which, with the National Front (the
                    ultra-nationalist faction in Parliament), has spearheaded the movement to
                    nationalize Iran’s oil. The Tudeh, according to Iranian intelligence reports, is
                    also behind the organization of the “Hayat-i-Islam,” which has been agitating on
                    the oil issue in the North. Tudeh agitators have also been reported in the
                    southern oil fields during the recent <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss>
                    strike. Tudeh agitation, as reported by Iranian military intelligence, showed a
                    noticeable increase in February in all parts of the country, but declined
                    markedly in March.</p>
                <pb facs="0109" n="72" xml:id="pg_72"/>
                <p>6. Moscow has followed a noncommittal policy concerning Soviet intervention in
                    Iran under the terms of the 1921 Iranian-Soviet treaty, and neither the press
                    nor the radio has referred to the treaty since <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1"
                        >Razmara</persName>’s assassination. Soviet Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_SIV_1">Sadchikov</persName>, conferring with Satellite officials
                    in Tehran on 16 April, reportedly stated that it was hardly likely that the
                    Soviets would intervene in Iran if British troops landed to maintain law and
                    order in the south. He added that any Soviet action would depend on the duration
                    of the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> action and that furthermore the
                    treaty’s terms would require an appeal to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> from the Tehran government. His delineation of Soviet
                    intentions may have been an effort to encourage a more forceful British policy
                    towards Iran. While the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> undoubtedly
                    realizes that British military forces are unlikely to occupy the oil area, any
                    Communist-inspired agitation in the oil fields during the strike was presumably
                    aimed at provoking the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>. Should
                    Communist-Nationalist agitation tactics bring on new disturbances in the oil
                    area, British intervention would intensify unrest and hatred of the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>’s
                    advantage. On 26 April, a Moscow commentary alleged British concentration of
                    armed forces in the vicinity of southern Iran and for the first time charged the
                    British with the intention of “interfering actively in internal affairs should
                    occasion arise.” Repeated emphasis on the possibility of <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> intervention could be viewed as an unspoken threat of Soviet
                    intervention under the terms of the 1921 treaty.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
