<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>28. Special Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951-54IranEd2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-05-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-05-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recB0YJZQjtJRQYKK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85094315"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Oil field</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recMLiy7lv6MyHtOh" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recLolgZHy7viyqKU" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068390"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recu8CRwmmn30dF6G" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081635"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Martial law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-05-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-05-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="28"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <head>28. Special Estimate<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d28fn1">Source: Central
                        Intelligence Agency, <gloss target="#t_NIC_1">NIC</gloss> Files, Job
                        79S01011A, Box 3, Folder 6, SE–6 Current Developments in Iran. Top Secret.
                        According to the note on the covering sheet, the estimate was submitted by
                        the Director of Central Intelligence on May 18. The Central Intelligence
                        Agency and the intelligence organizations of the Departments of State, the
                        Army, the Navy, the Air Force, and the Joint Chiefs of Staff participated in
                        the preparation of this estimate. All members of the Intelligence Advisory
                        Committee concurred in this estimate, except as noted by the Director of
                        Intelligence, <gloss target="#t_USAF_1">USAF</gloss>, with regard to
                        paragraph 4.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <idno type="document-identifier">SE–6</idno>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <dateline rendition="#right">
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-05-22"
                        >May 22, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                <p rend="center">CURRENT DEVELOPMENT IN IRAN</p>
                <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                <p>1. The clash of interests between Iran and the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    over Iran’s oil resources has reached a critical stage with the elevation of
                    Mohammad <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>, the leader of the
                    ultra-nationalist National Front group, to the premiership. Although a real
                    effort will undoubtedly be made to reach a compromise settlement, a solution
                    will be achieved only with great difficulty. In any event, there is little
                    indication that <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> and the
                    Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (<gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss>) will modify
                    their respective stands in sufficient time to permit an early settlement of the
                    issue.</p>
                <p>2. Although there are important elements opposed to <persName corresp="#p_MM_1"
                        >Mossadeq</persName>, it is unlikely that he can be removed from power so
                    long as the oil question remains a burning issue, except by violence or by the
                    establishment of a semi-dictatorial regime under the aegis of the Shah. In the
                    present highly inflammatory state of Iranian public opinion, an attempt to set
                    up a non-parliamentary regime would involve grave risks which the Shah has thus
                    far shown no willingness to take.</p>
                <p>3. As a result of the present impasse, the following critical developments may
                    occur before a settlement is reached:</p>
                <pb facs="0129" n="92" xml:id="pg_92"/>
                <p>a. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> might take physical possession
                    of the oil installations now operated by the <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1"
                        >AIOC</gloss>. He may also require the British employees of <gloss
                        target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss> to leave the country.</p>
                <p>b. The <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> has indicated that it will not employ
                    force in Iran without prior consultation with the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>. It is unlikely that the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    would attempt by force to forestall or counter physical occupation of the oil
                    installations by the Iranian Government, but the <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> could and might land troops in Iran for the actual or alleged
                    purpose of safeguarding British lives in the event of further violence or
                    sabotage.</p>
                <p>c. There is a serious possibility that the landing of British troops in southern
                    Iran, for whatever reason, would be taken by the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> as a pretext for sending its troops into northern Iran.</p>
                <p>d. In the event of further demonstrations and violence, which may well occur at
                    any time, the Tudeh Party might be able to seriously undermine internal
                    security. This danger would be increased if, as is possible, <persName
                        corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> legalizes the status of the Tudeh
                    Party or is unwilling to use Iranian armed forces to maintain order.</p>
                <p>e. The flow of Iranian oil to Western markets, which was recently curtailed for
                    about two weeks, might be again interrupted by a recurrence of strikes in the
                    oil field area or by a, b, c, or d above.</p>
                <p>4. Any intensification of the current crisis would give the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> added opportunities for exploiting the local
                    unrest and might eventually enable the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> to
                    deny a large part or the whole of the Iranian oil supply to the Western
                        Powers.<note n="2" xml:id="d28fn2">It is the view of the Director of
                        Intelligence, <gloss target="#t_USAF_1">USAF</gloss>, that this paragraph
                        should read as follows: “4. A continuation of the current crisis would
                        greatly enhance the capability of the Soviet Union to deny more and possibly
                        all the Iranian oil to the West through exploitation of the activities of
                        non-Soviet elements. Whether or not the British attempt to resolve the
                        current issue by the use of armed force, possible realization of an
                        important Soviet objective—acquisition of more oil—will have been greatly
                        facilitated.” [Footnote is in the original.]</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">Discussion</p>
                <p>1. Mohammad <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>, Iran’s new Prime
                    Minister, is an extreme nationalist. He will attempt to curtail severely foreign
                    influence in Iran and to adopt a neutralist policy toward the East-West
                    struggle. As he is also an impractical visionary and a poor administrator, it is
                    unlikely that he will do very much to solve the country’s critical economic and
                    social problems. Nevertheless, because he is an astute politician and has strong
                    popular support on the oil issue at least, he will probably not be easily
                    displaced while that issue is still unsettled. In internal affairs <persName
                        corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> has criticized former Iranian
                    governments for their failure to achieve social benefits for the people and has
                    opposed measures designed to restrict freedom of speech, assembly, and the
                    press. Politi<pb facs="0130" n="93" xml:id="pg_93"/>cally, he has urged that the
                    Shah be stripped of power and that the Majlis become the dominant factor in the
                    government. However, he does not believe that the present members of the Majlis
                    truly represent the interests of the Iranian people and advocates electoral
                    reform.</p>
                <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> is at present in a strong
                    political position, despite the facts that he has few personal followers in the
                    Majlis or in the traditional ruling class as a whole and that he is disliked and
                    distrusted by the Shah. Unlike his predecessors, he is not dependent on the
                    Shah’s favor or on factional politics in the Majlis. He has come to power as the
                    leader of a national movement which has aroused intense popular support. This
                    circumstance has caused the Majlis to nominate him to the Shah and compelled the
                    Shah to appoint him to office. Fundamentally his strength derives from, and is
                    in direct proportion to, the intensity of feeling against the British over the
                    oil issue. Although other critical problems will plague his administration, they
                    are not likely to cause his downfall so long as the oil crisis remains a burning
                    issue. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>’s campaign against the
                        <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss> has had the support not only of his
                    National Front group but also of the Fedayan Islam (the small terrorist group of
                    religious fanatics who were responsible for <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1"
                        >Razmara</persName>’s assassination), the illegal Tudeh (Communist) Party,
                    and probably the great majority of Iran’s laborers, trades-men, and students,
                    who can significantly affect political developments in Iran through strikes,
                    demonstrations, and violence. Both the Fedayan Islam and the Tudeh Party,
                    however, are constantly attempting to coerce <persName corresp="#p_MM_1"
                        >Mossadeq</persName> into adopting more extreme measures against Western
                    interests. Fedayan Islam has apparently unseated its more moderate leader and
                    has threatened <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>’s life.
                    Meanwhile, the Tudeh Party has gone beyond nationalization of the oil industry
                    to demand ousting of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> military mission,
                    refusal of <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> arms assistance, and closer
                    relations with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                <p>3. Because of the wide support for <persName corresp="#p_MM_1"
                        >Mossadeq</persName>’s chauvinistic crusade, few Iranian leaders dared
                    oppose him publicly. His influence in the Majlis was largely responsible for
                        <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName>’s failure to obtain a
                    revised <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss> agreement and loans from the
                    Export-Import Bank and the <gloss target="#t_IBRD_1">IBRD</gloss>. He condoned
                    the assassination of <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName> on the
                    grounds that the latter was traitorously lenient in his negotiations with the
                        <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss>. Finally, he pushed the oil
                    nationalization bills through the Majlis against the wishes of the Shah and
                    Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Ala</persName>. Many of the Majlis
                    deputies probably voted for the measures against their better judgment,
                    succumbing to the emotionalism of <persName corresp="#p_MM_1"
                        >Mossadeq</persName>’s appeal or fearing the consequences (possibly
                    including assassination) of opposing the measure.</p>
                <p>4. When <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Hussein Ala</persName> was Prime Minister,
                        <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> was chairman of the Majlis
                    Oil Commission appointed to draw up recommendations for taking over the <gloss
                        target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss> installations. The Shah, Prime <pb
                        facs="0131" n="94" xml:id="pg_94"/> Minister <persName corresp="#p_AH_2"
                        >Ala</persName>, and moderate members of the Majlis probably hoped that some
                    agreement could be patched up with the <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss>
                    before <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> could complete his work.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>, however, reported to the
                    Majlis more than a month ahead of schedule. Increased bitterness toward the
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>, reinforced by the intervening strikes
                    and violence in the oil field area, kept emotions high throughout the country
                    and simplified <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>’s job in
                    obtaining prompt Majlis approval for his recommendations. The new law sets up a
                    government committee to act as trustee for the oil properties until an Iranian
                    Company can be established and provides for setting aside 25 percent of oil
                    revenues to meet future claims of the “former company.” <persName
                        corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>’s precipitate move to force action on
                    the oil issue resulted in the immediate resignation of <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH_2">Ala</persName>.</p>
                <p>5. Although the responsibilities of office may to some extent act as a sobering
                    influence on <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>, he will almost
                    certainly attempt to implement the nationalization law and gain effective
                    control of the oil installations in southern Iran. He might be willing to
                    conclude a management contract with <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss>,
                    under which the latter would operate the oil installations under the direction
                    of an Iranian company. However, he would probably prefer to obtain the technical
                    assistance Iran needs by means of separate contracts with individual
                    specialists. If, in fact, <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> is
                    able to reach a settlement with the <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss> which
                    will substantially increase Iran’s oil revenues and provide for Iranian
                    supervision of the oil installations, he will have achieved his purpose.
                    Although his prestige would be high, his position would probably be rapidly
                    weakened by any considerable decline of anti-British feeling or by his inability
                    to cope with Iran’s fundamental economic and social problems. There is some
                    danger that he might attempt to maintain himself in power by turning his
                    chauvinistic crusade against the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>. He might
                    even refuse to accept further <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> military aid
                    and request the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> military missions to leave
                    the country.</p>
                <p>6. In view of the fact that both Iran and the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    have a very great interest in the uninterrupted production of Iranian oil, a
                    real effort will undoubtedly be made to reach a compromise settlement. However,
                    in view of the attitude of both governments, a settlement can probably be
                    reached only with great difficulty. The 11-man Oil Committee has already
                    threatened to revoke the residence permits of <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1"
                        >AIOC</gloss>’s foreign staff unless the <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1"
                        >AIOC</gloss> turns over its oil installations to the Iranian Government.
                    The <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> has taken the position that Iran has no
                    right unilaterally to abrogate its contract with <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1"
                        >AIOC</gloss> and, therefore, no right to expropriate the oil installations
                    under the guise of nationalization. The <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> has
                    proposed the establishment of a new British company to run operations in Iran,
                    which would include Iranians on the board of directors; equal sharing of
                    profits; and a progressive increase in the number of Iranians employed by the
                    company. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> will un<pb facs="0132"
                        n="95" xml:id="pg_95"/>doubtedly turn down this offer, for it manifestly
                    fails to meet the requirements of the oil nationalization law. The proposal
                    certainly does not represent the final British position. However, a serious
                    danger exists that critical developments will occur before the parties,
                    particularly the British, have sufficiently modified their respective positions
                    to permit initiation of genuine negotiations.</p>
                <p>7. The present impasse in the oil situation may lead to any one or more of the
                    following critical situations:</p>
                <p>a. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> is committed to a policy of
                    expropriation. On the basis of his past actions, it is extremely unlikely that
                    he will accept anything less than effective Iranian control of the oil industry.
                    Consequently, if there is no early relaxation of the British position, he will
                    probably attempt to take physical possession of the oil installations even at
                    the risk of closing down the whole industry.</p>
                <p>b. The <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> has indicated that it will not employ
                    force in Iran without prior consultation with the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>. It is unlikely that the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    would send its troops into the oil field area to forestall or counter occupation
                    of the oil installations by the Iranian Government, but the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> could and might land troops in Iran for the
                    actual or alleged purpose of safeguarding British lives and property in the
                    event of further violence or sabotage. The British Government is under public
                    pressure to adopt a strong policy against Iran, and British officials have
                    indicated that they will have to consider very seriously resorting to military
                    force if Iran unilaterally seizes the oil installations. If British troops
                    landed in southern Iran and Iranian forces were already in the area or were
                    subsequently sent into the area, for whatever reason, there might be clashes
                    between British and Iranian troops with inevitable serious consequences,
                    probably including an interruption in the flow of oil. Moreover, the landing of
                    British troops in southern Iran might be taken by the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> as a pretext for sending troops into northern Iran.</p>
                <p>c. Anti-British feeling will remain strong, and the danger of demonstrations and
                    violence will continue. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> has
                    consistently opposed martial law and restrictions on the freedom of speech,
                    assembly, and the press. One of his first acts in office was to remove a ban on
                    May Day demonstrations in Tehran, and martial law may soon be lifted in the
                    Abadan area. Furthermore, although the Tudeh Party has begun to attack <persName
                        corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>, he may yield to its demand for legal
                    status. There is a danger that the Tudeh Party may attempt to take advantage of
                        <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>’s leniency to foment
                    disturbances throughout the country and that <persName corresp="#p_MM_1"
                        >Mossadeq</persName> will be unwilling to use Iranian armed forces to
                    maintain order. In view of the tension and general unrest in the country, Tudeh
                    activity might seriously undermine internal security.</p>
                <p>d. If <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> takes physical possession
                    of the oil installations, he will undoubtedly seek foreign assistance in
                    operating the oil industry. <pb facs="0133" n="96" xml:id="pg_96"/> A number of
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> oil companies have already shown some
                    interest in the situation, and <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>
                    might well be able to persuade some company to operate in Iran on his terms.
                    Such a development would create widespread British antagonism against the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>. There is also a possibility that <persName
                        corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> might attempt to obtain Soviet
                    specialists to run the oil installations.</p>
                <p>8. There is little doubt that sooner or later efforts will be made by the
                    British, the Shah, and deputies in the Majlis to undermine <persName
                        corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>’s position. However, in view of
                        <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>’s popular backing, it is
                    unlikely that the Shah and the Majlis would dare oppose him while tension over
                    the oil issue remains high. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> is
                    more likely to force the oil issue by extreme action than permit himself to be
                    undermined by the Shah and the Majlis on other internal issues. It is therefore
                    unlikely that <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> can be overthrown
                    during this critical period except by violence or by the establishment of a
                    semi-dictatorial regime under the aegis of the Shah. Such a course of action
                    would involve risks which the Shah has thus far shown no willingness to
                    take.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
