<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="43" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                        <head>43. Despatch From the Embassy in Iran to the Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d43fn1">Source: National Archives,
                                    <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 84, Tehran Embassy Files,
                                1950–1952, classified general records, Box 24. Secret. Drafted by
                                Andrew Cuomo. The despatch was originally prepared as a memorandum,
                                dated August 17, and then sent as a despatch on August 20.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <idno type="document-identifier">No. 224</idno>
                            </seg>
                        </opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-20">August 20, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                        <p rend="center">RECENT INCREASE IN POLITICAL PRESTIGE OF <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">AYATOLLAH KASHANI</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Summary:</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Ayatollah Seyid Abol Qasem
                                Kashani</persName>, the fanatical, nationalist Iranian mullah, has
                            recently become increasingly prominent in Iranian political affairs. His
                            long career is one of constant opposition to British intervention in the
                            domestic affairs of Iran. The oil nationalization issue, of an
                            anti-British and highly nationalistic nature, has brought about an
                            atmosphere in this country which easily lends itself to exploitation by
                            such a man. He has more recently been assisted in elevating himself to a
                            position of prominence by publicity accorded him in the foreign press
                            and by the prestige given him through the fact that he alone among
                            religious leaders received calls from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">W. Averell Harriman</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRR_1">Richard Stokes</persName>.</p>
                        <p>His delusions of grandeur have been accentuated by events which have put
                            him in the limelight of a local political affair having international
                            implications. Although under present tense conditions, he has attained a
                            position of influence, that position is founded upon transitory
                            circumstances. It is doubtful that he could command sustained support
                            from any large segment of the population. He has neither the support nor
                            the confidence of his religious colleagues and his pretensions under a
                            determined attack would prove far superior to his capabilities.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Introduction:</p>
                        <p>Recently, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Ayatollah Seyid Abol Qasem
                                Kashani</persName> has become increasingly prominent in Iranian
                            public affairs. Ambitious, opportunistic, fanatical, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>’s influence depends
                            primarily on the support of the poorer and more ignorant classes of the
                            Iranian people, and the more fanatical elements of the bazaar. From
                            among this following <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>
                            can recruit those who would commit acts of violence for real or imagined
                            offenses against the Moslem faith. He has been implicated in several
                            assassinations and murders.</p>
                        <pb facs="0164" n="127" xml:id="pg_127"/>
                        <p>His power springs from these elements and he is careful to maintain his
                            influence over them. With such support, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> has been able to frighten into cautious silence
                            many who would otherwise oppose those causes which for whatever reason
                            he has chosen to espouse. At the moment, the popular issue—which he
                            helped make popular and which he is now exploiting to his advantage—is
                            that of oil nationalization. The issue and the popular, hysterical
                            attitude toward it on the part of the great masses of the Iranian
                            people, is perfectly suited to bring out the “talents” possessed by
                                <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Ayatollah Kashani</persName> by
                            virtue of training, experience, and inclination.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Background:</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> was raised in a highly
                            religious Moslem family. His father was a religious leader in the Shiah
                            Holy City of Najef in Iraq where the principal activity, particularly
                            during the days of <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>’s
                            youth and even today, revolved around the Shiah pilgrims who came to pay
                            homage at the tomb of Imam Ali, son-in-law of the Prophet. Educated by
                            mullahs, he became one himself at an early age. His father opposed the
                            British in Iraq during World War I and the still-young <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> found himself in a Holy War
                            declared by his father and other religious leaders against all
                            Christians. His father was killed in a battle following the British
                            landings on the Persian Gulf. Since then he freely threatens “Holy War”
                            at the least provocation and his hatred of the British, accentuated by
                            later events, verges on the psychopathic.</p>
                        <p>He continued to oppose British interference in Iranian affairs for some
                            years after World War I, but he must have appraised <persName corresp="#p_PRS_1">Reza Shah</persName> as one stronger than himself
                            for he cautiously kept out of that monarch’s way in spite of the
                            anti-clerical policies which were carried out during his reign and the
                            continuation of Iranian oil exploitation by the British.</p>
                        <p>Following the advent of World War II and the abdication of <persName corresp="#p_PRS_1">Reza Shah</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> again took up the task of
                            opposing British activities. When the Allies occupied Iran, the British
                            promptly imprisoned him in spite of objections raised by the then U.S.
                            Minister, <persName corresp="#p_DLG_1">Dreyfus</persName>. His relative
                            partiality to the U.S. dates from that time.</p>
                        <p>During the next twenty-eight months of forced inactivity, he never lost
                            touch with his followers and upon being released he quickly returned to
                            his plottings. This time his activities were directed against Prime
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName>, who exiled him
                            to the provinces. In early 1949, after the attempted assassination of
                            the Shah, as a precautionary measure Prime Minister Mohammed Sa’ed,
                            aided and advised by Army Chief of Staff <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Ali Razmara</persName>, sent <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> out of the country again.</p>
                        <p>The influence he wields was demonstrated when he was elected to the
                            Majlis while still in exile. He was elected as a National Front deputy
                                <pb facs="0165" n="128" xml:id="pg_128"/> in 1950 along with his
                            friend. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mosadeq</persName>. Both
                            attribute all of Iran’s shortcomings and misfortunes to British
                            interference in Iran. When <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName> became Prime Minister, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> did not find it difficult to
                            support National Front policies, particularly in attacking the man whom
                            both he and <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mosadeq</persName> believed to
                            be subservient to British influence and who had been instrumental in
                            bringing about his most recent exile.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recent Events:</p>
                        <p>In the meantime the British oil concession dispute flared up into a
                            popular movement into which were released all the aggressive energies of
                            the Iranian people generated by decades of frustration. The British,
                            through the Oil Company, were identified as the sole cause for all the
                            difficulties in which collectively and individually the Iranians found
                            themselves. The nation-wide hysteria over oil nationalization created an
                            atmosphere tailor-made for a reactionary religious leader with a flare
                            for political intrigue. He has tried to take full advantage of it. It
                            should be pointed out, however, that contrary to anything he may say at
                            the present time, at least until June of last year he had not opposed
                            the supplementary oil agreement offered by the <gloss target="#t_AIOC_1">AIOC</gloss> and under discussion at that time.<note n="2" xml:id="d43fn2">Embassy Despatch No. 382 of June 22, 1950. [Footnote
                                is in the original. Despatch 382 from Tehran is ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1950–1954,
                                788.00/6–2250.]</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Nevertheless, events moved on and he moved with them. With the unwitting
                            aid of the foreign press in combination with the aroused and unrequited
                            passions of the Iranian people, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> was elevated, and cleverly helped elevate
                            himself, to an influential position in Iranian political affairs. Dr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mosadeq</persName> was careful to call
                            on him as soon as he became Prime Minister, and has kept in regular
                            contact with him ever since. <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> in turn has supported the Prime Minister. He has
                            at all critical moments issued messages to the people affirming the
                            necessity of Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mosadeq</persName>’s
                            leadership in the vital oil nationalization issue.</p>
                        <p>Several months ago <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Ayatollah
                                Kashani</persName> decided not to appear in public. He has refused
                            to take his seat in the Majlis claiming that to do so would lower his
                            prestige. He never calls on anyone, but receives everybody in private
                            audience—in his own surroundings. His messages to public gatherings are
                            recorded and played back to the audience. With regard to his Majlis
                            seat, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> said that he
                            would go to the Majlis only in case of an emergency. Perhaps he is
                            waiting for a propitious occasion. In the prevailing tense atmosphere,
                            and over the oil nationalization issue, should <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> decide to make a public
                            appearance he would undoubtedly draw together an impressive mass of
                            people.</p>
                        <pb facs="0166" n="129" xml:id="pg_129"/>
                        <p>At the suggestion of Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mosadeq</persName>
                            two weeks ago, <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">W. Averell
                                Harriman</persName> called on <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d43fn3">The <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> Mission, composed of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">W. Averell Harriman</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RWM_1">William M. Rountree</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LW_1">Walter Levy</persName>, and General
                                Landry, traveled to Iran on July 13 in order to encourage a solution
                                to the oil dispute between Iran and the United Kingdom. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> left Tehran on August 25.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SRR_1">Richard Stokes</persName>, Lord
                                Privy Seal, led the British delegation to Iran that remained in
                                Tehran from August 4 to August 23 at which time talks between the
                                British and the Iranians were suspended. For extensive documentation
                                on the <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> Mission, see
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1952–1954, vol. X,
                                Iran, 1951–1954, pp. 88–173 (<ref target="frus1952-54v10#d39">Documents 39</ref>–<ref target="frus1952-54v10#d91">91</ref>).</note> As released to the press by <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>, the interview was
                            practically a <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>
                            monologue. A few pertinent remarks from the published version of the
                            interview follows:</p>
                        <p>“I must tell you plainly, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName>, that we have been oppressed and robbed by the
                            former oil company for fifty years” . . . . “Now four hundred Moslems
                            have pinned their hopes on our country. All the Moslem countries expect
                            us to break the chain put on our feet by British imperialist
                            exploitation . . .” “Should Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mosadeq</persName> compromise, he will lose the sincere support he
                            is now receiving from the people” . . . . “I am now working for the
                            union of the Moslem nations, and also for the union of the peoples of
                            the East. As I told you, I am trying my best to unite my four hundred
                            million Moslem brethren, who should be united and who should maintain
                            complete neutrality”.</p>
                        <p>Shortly after the <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName>
                            interview, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> was spurred
                            to more intense efforts. He spoke now with ever greater authority. He
                            addressed a message to the people of Khazistan expressing his
                            appreciation of their patriotism and assistance:</p>
                        <p>“I expect every effort will be exerted to maintain order . . . . and to
                            support the government of His Excellency Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mosadeq</persName>, and the appropriation committee which is
                            working for the benefit of the workers of Khazistan. I pray that God
                            Almighty will bestow health, happiness and tranquility upon my dear
                            brethren and that the hands of the merciless foreigners will be severed.
                            In conclusion, I should point out that the return to Tehran of His
                            Excellency Hosein Makki, honorable deputy from Tehran, is temporary and
                            only for medical treatment. He will return shortly.”</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> then addressed
                            messages to Prime Ministers <persName corresp="#p_NJ_1">Nehru</persName>
                            of India and <persName corresp="#p_AKL_1">Liaqat Ali Khan</persName> of
                            Pakistan calling upon them amicable to settle the Kashmir dispute. He
                            received a reply from both Prime Ministers.</p>
                        <p>To digress for a moment at this point, when <persName corresp="#p_PRS_1">Reza Shah</persName> decided to break the power of the clergy in
                            Iran one of his first acts was to strike at its finances. He confiscated
                            the ecclesiastical properties and the managers of the properties were
                            made civil functionaries of the Ministry of Education. In recent years,
                            despite the growing influence of the clergy no attempt has as yet been
                            put forth by that clergy to revise the funda<pb facs="0167" n="130" xml:id="pg_130"/>mental laws made by <persName corresp="#p_PRS_1">Reza Shah</persName> which stripped it of its power. It is to the
                            Minister of Education that <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> now addressed himself. In a letter to him
                                <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> urged the Minister
                            to make certain changes in order to conform to the regulations of Islam.
                            The letter closes:</p>
                        <p>“I seriously request your Excellency to issue prompt instructions
                            regarding the foregoing points and expect that you will advise us of any
                            decision you make to this effect.”</p>
                        <p>The next move was for The Right Honorable <persName corresp="#p_SRR_1">Richard Stokes</persName> to pay him a visit. He, like Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName>, was subjected to a
                            long harangue. His repeated requests for permission to leave were
                            ignored while <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> talked
                            on. It was during this interview that <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> made the following remark:</p>
                        <p>“Even Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mosadeq</persName>, who enjoys the
                            unanimous support of the people, if he deviated from the nine article
                            law, risks losing not only his prestige but also risks suffering the
                            same fate as <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName>”.</p>
                        <p>To <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> this means anyone
                            deviating from the path of nationalization as now laid down by <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> “risks suffering the same
                            fate as <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName>”.</p>
                        <p>After the satisfaction of his interview with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRR_1">Stokes</persName> another flow of “messages” may
                            be expected. The first has already appeared. It is <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>’s message to Pakistan on the
                            occasion of its fourth anniversary of independence. The message
                            ends:</p>
                        <p>“In conclusion I avail myself of the opportunity to strongly recommend to
                            the authorities, the nation and the press of Pakistan to continue its
                            previous policy of friendship with its Indian neighbor and not to take
                            any steps that would undermine the satisfactory solution of existing
                            differences.”</p>
                        <p>As evidence of his expanding activities the Tehran newspaper <hi rend="italic">Keyhan,</hi> of August 16 reports the following:</p>
                        <p>“The correspondent of the newspaper <hi rend="italic">Al Masri</hi> has
                            reported that Haji Amin-ol-Hoseini, the Grand Mufti of Palestine, is a
                            staunch supporter of <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Ayatollah
                                Kashani</persName>. His representative, Mr. Seyid Abdul Jalil Ankar
                            is now in Tehran to meet <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Ayatollah
                                Kashani</persName>, bringing letters from the Mufti addressed to him
                            . . .”</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Conclusion:</p>
                        <p>In <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>’s career there is a
                            thin thread of consistency. Throughout, he has opposed British
                            interference in Iranian affairs. The consistency ends there, except
                            perhaps for his opportunism. CAS reports that he can be bribed. He has
                            at least on one occasion made overtures to the American Embassy here for
                            financial support in return for which, presumably, he would support
                            United States policies.</p>
                        <pb facs="0168" n="131" xml:id="pg_131"/>
                        <p>He has fantastic delusions of grandeur which until recently had little
                            basis in fact. Events, however, have moved in his favor. His political
                            stature has been inflated by the publicity accorded him in the foreign
                            press and the prestige given him by the fact that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SRR_1">Stokes</persName> called on him. Their interviews
                            have been exploited to the maximum by <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Although his stature has grown over the last few months, <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> has not attained the
                            overwhelming influence which he believes he has and which he would have
                            others believe he has. Despite his present prominence in Iranian
                            political affairs, there is no doubt that his pretensions vastly exceed
                            his capabilities. As has been pointed out that prominence came about by
                            circumstances having but a fortuitous relationship with his character
                            and less with any personal political convictions. There is, therefore,
                            little basis for it. He would fall from his relatively influential
                            position as soon as its thin props were removed.</p>
                        <p>His reputation as a religious leader is not supported by his colleagues
                            whose influence in educated circles far exceed that of <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName>. While his bombast and
                            threats are effective in the current tense atmosphere, he probably would
                            fail to withstand a determined attack against him by any government with
                            the support of reputable religious leaders who would expose the
                            shallowness of the man and the exaggerated character of his
                            pretensions.</p>
                        <p rend="right">For the Ambassador:</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_RAL_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RAL_1">Arthur L. Richards</persName>
                                <affiliation>Counselor of Embassy</affiliation>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>