<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="8" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d8">
                        <head>8. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                            Eastern, South Asian, and African Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BBY_1">Berry</persName>) to the Deputy Under Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_MHF_1">Matthews</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d8fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1950–1954, 788.00/3–1551. Top
                                Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RWM_1">Rountree</persName>.
                                Attached is a handwritten note apparently written by <persName corresp="#p_BBY_1">Berry</persName>. In this note <persName corresp="#p_BBY_1">Berry</persName> poses a number of questions,
                                such as, “Is there the material from which to build ‘a strong
                                coalition government in Iran?’ (as suggested by <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>)”; “Is this the moment to bring
                                out ‘a rigorous overt U.S. program to strengthen Iran’ or is it the
                                moment to let the dust settle while we act correctly?”; and “It is
                                generally assumed that <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Ala</persName>
                                and his government are a temporary expedient. If so what do we
                                expect to follow, what groups and what leaders? Are we now working,
                                educationally and otherwise, on such?”</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-15">March 15, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> Proposals for the Iranian
                                Crisis</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Problem</p>
                        <p>To consider possible courses of covert action by <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> representatives in relation to the Iranian crisis.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Discussion</p>
                        <p>At the request of <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, and accompanied
                            by other representatives of <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss>, I
                            visited Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_DAW_1">Allen Dulles</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_WF_1">Frank Wisner</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Kermit Roosevelt</persName> on March 14 to discuss
                            the current Iranian crisis. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>,
                            concerned over the turn of events in that country, had prepared the
                            attached paper on the situation, setting forth possible courses of
                            action which might be carried out covertly.<note n="2" xml:id="d8fn2">
                                <ref target="#d5">Document 5</ref>.</note> It was emphasized that
                            the paper is no more than a draft hurriedly prepared and that the
                            program would be refined on the basis of subsequent discussions with the
                            Department.</p>
                        <p>I undertook to discuss in general terms the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> proposals with the appropriate Departmental officers
                            before pursuing the matter further with <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>. The real importance of the paper is, I think, that
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> is prepared to move ahead
                            rapidly with an action program requiring supplies, money, and personnel
                            if, in the opinion of the Department, it will be useful in the
                            attainment of our objectives in Iran.</p>
                        <p>I feel that we certainly must not under-estimate the dangers involved in
                            the Iranian situation, although <persName corresp="#p_RHA_1">Razmara</persName>’s assassination appears in fact to have been
                            accomplished by a representative of a small fanatical nationalist sect.
                            The lack of drastic subsequent developments <pb facs="0076" n="39" xml:id="pg_39"/> lends credence to the assumption that the
                            assassination was not brought about by Communist elements, although
                            Communism in Iran clearly has benefited greatly by the confusion and
                            turmoil which has been created. At the moment there is reason to hope
                            that by exercising a reasonably firm hand the Shah and Prime Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Ala</persName>, strongly pro-Western,
                            will be able to maintain order until tempers have cooled. There is
                            always the danger that every opportunity will be seized by subversive
                            elements and thus we should constantly be on guard; however, we must be
                            most careful in the conduct of our affairs in Iran to avoid any policies
                            or programs which might lower American prestige or encourage the
                            development of an anti-American attitude which unquestionably would
                            result from the disclosure of any “improper” intervention during this
                            critical period of emotional nationalism.</p>
                        <p>With this in mind, I believe that certain of the proposals set forth by
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> might involve great dangers,
                            while others, if carefully implemented, could be of considerable use. It
                            is difficult at this distance to evaluate fully in each instance the
                            propriety of our proceeding with given lines of action. Considerable
                            authority and responsibility for determining what courses of action
                            should be pursued must, in my opinion, be vested in the Ambassador in
                            Tehran, operating under broad lines set forth jointly by the Department
                            and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>With regard to <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>’s specific proposals
                            for action under the present situation, I have the following
                            comments:</p>
                        <p>(1) The suggestion concerning the development of an intensified
                            propaganda campaign by both overt and covert means in support of the
                            Shah and Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Ala</persName> is of
                            course generally desirable. However, any wide-scale United States
                            propaganda supporting the Shah and the Prime Minister at the present
                            moment would unquestionably embarrass them and leave them open to
                            criticism from the nationalist factions as American creatures. The
                            various propaganda points suggested by <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> are good.</p>
                        <p>(2) While a “strong coalition movement” along the proper lines would be
                            desirable, it is difficult to see how such a development could be
                            brought about by United States agencies at this time.</p>
                        <p>(3) Assistance in the form of money, personnel and technical aid to the
                            police and security forces in Iran is, of course, highly desirable. At
                            the moment I fear that it would be impossible for political reasons for
                            the Iranians to accept any American personnel in these fields other than
                            the present Gendarmérie Mission, but they probably would welcome
                            American assistance in the forms of arms, equipment, and the training in
                            the United States of Iranian security officials.</p>
                        <p>(4) I concur in the comment that this whole program would have a better
                            chance of success if it could be carried out in support of a vigorous
                            overt United States program to strengthen Iran, including loans, <pb facs="0077" n="40" xml:id="pg_40"/> increased military aid, medical
                            and public health programs and Point IV assistance. Every effort is
                            being made to increase as appropriate and expedite our Iranian aid
                            programs.</p>
                        <p>(5) I have serious reservations concerning the advisability of any
                            approach to Mullah Kashani, the leader of the ultra-nationalist
                            religious groups in Iran, who has a wide popular following. I doubt that
                                <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> could, in any
                            event, be bought for any appreciable length of time, and he might very
                            well use any approach of this sort as a further weapon in his current
                            attempts to stir up public hatred of all foreigners, particularly
                            Americans and British. It would be in character for him to use such an
                            approach as evidence of the intrigues of foreign powers against the
                            sovereignty of Iran; in this he could win more adherents and further
                            inflame those whom he already has. The alternate course proposed by
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, to discredit <persName corresp="#p_KSAAG_1">Kashani</persName> by means of printed
                            material, etc., has, I believe, merit but this program would have to be
                            carried out with the greatest caution.</p>
                        <p>(6) I concur with the opinion expressed by <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> that any approach to Dr. <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mohamad Mossadeq</persName>, the leader of the National Front
                            group, would be difficult, and believe it would be fruitless. The
                            suggested use of clandestine publications to expose the Soviet ties of
                            some of his followers appears a distinct possibility, but the possible
                            effectiveness of splitting off from his group his “more stable and
                            reasonable followers” appears questionable.</p>
                        <p>(7) The use of “black propaganda” weapons against the Tudeh Party is
                            attractive and might have useful results. However, the present
                            atmosphere in Iran is so tense and public opinion so emotionally aroused
                            that any revelation of a “plot” might further disturb the situation.
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> might, however, make plans for
                            activity of this sort with the understanding that it would not be
                            implemented until the situation is such that the results can be more
                            accurately estimated.</p>
                        <p>(8) The suggestion that an attempt be made to split the Tudeh Party,
                            particularly to exploit deviationist tendencies, appears to have merit
                            if practicable steps can be formulated. Perhaps precise courses of
                            action can be worked out by the representatives in the field as
                            opportunities present themselves.</p>
                        <p>In addition to the above courses of action suggested for immediate
                            implementation, the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> paper sets
                            forth programs assuming (a) a serious deterioration in the situation, or
                            (b) the imposition of a satellite government. Under either of these
                            contingencies it is recognized that our action must be far more drastic
                            than under present circumstances, and the suggestions set forth by
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> should be given careful
                            consideration. In this connection, the present <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> paper on Iran, which was approved by the Senior Staff
                            on March 13 and is going to the Council for <pb facs="0078" n="41" xml:id="pg_41"/> approval on March 21, provides broad latitude for
                            United States measures along these lines.<note n="3" xml:id="d8fn3">An
                                apparent reference to <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 107, <ref target="#d6">Document 6</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendations</p>
                        <p>(1) That <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss> pursue discussions with
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> along the foregoing lines and
                            urge that agency to proceed with appropriate aspects of its action
                            program, pointing out that the success of the program depends in very
                            large measure upon the caliber of the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> personnel assigned to the task.</p>
                        <p>(2) That instructions agreed to by the Department and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> be communicated to Tehran, authorizing
                            the implementation of such elements of the program as are fully approved
                            by the Ambassador.<note n="4" xml:id="d8fn4">In the left margin next to
                                these two recommendations, <persName corresp="#p_MHF_1">Matthews</persName> wrote: “I agree.” In <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Kermit Roosevelt</persName>’s account of the
                                same meeting, dated March 17, he wrote that “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BBY_1">Berry</persName> informed <gloss target="#t_CNE_1">CNE</gloss> that Deputy Under-Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MHF_1">Matthews</persName> had read and
                                approved in substance the reference memorandum. He said that this
                                approval was qualified in terms that had been understood fully by
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and State Department
                                representatives from the very beginning—namely, that the paper was
                                taken as an indication of general lines to be followed in an
                                accelerated <gloss target="#t_OPC_1">OPC</gloss> program, that the
                                specific illustrations included in the paper would require careful
                                evaluation in the field, and that the whole program would be subject
                                to coordination with and approval of the ambassador.” <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Roosevelt</persName> also discussed with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BBY_1">Berry</persName> the need to place
                                additional personnel and funding at the disposal of the <gloss target="#t_OPC_1">OPC</gloss> in Tehran to “assist the
                                Ambassador for the purposes of this program.” <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Roosevelt</persName> concluded by noting that
                                “It was agreed that a further meeting of State and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> representatives on this program
                                should be held as soon as possible, preferably on 19 March . . .
                                    <gloss target="#t_CNE_1">CNE</gloss> strongly recommends that
                                    <gloss target="#t_ADPC_1">ADPC</gloss> and, if possible, DD/P
                                should attend this meeting and should urge again the point that the
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> program can be effective to
                                any significant extent only as part of a vigorous national program.
                                It is feared that so far we have made this point to little avail.”
                                (Central Intelligence Agency, <gloss target="#t_DDO_1">DDO</gloss>
                                Files, Job 79–01228A, Box 11, Folder 14, Iran 1951–1953)</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>