<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-10-14T10:34:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-10-14T10:34:00-05:00" n="109" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d109">
                        <head>109. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the United
                                Kingdom</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d109fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy Files.
                                Confidential; Cherokee; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>London</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-10-14T15:34:00+00:00">October 14, 1975,
                                1534Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>15749. For Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and
                            Treasury Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWE1">Simon</persName>.
                            Subject: Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_YE1">Yeo</persName>’s
                            Report on Conversations with Germans.</p>
                        <p>Our discussions with Poehl were quite pleasant and frank. They centered
                            on the following points: <pb facs="0376" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Poehl indicated that he expected <persName corresp="#p_GEV1">Giscard</persName> to make a presentation on exchange
                                    rates. They anticipate that it will cover familiar territory,
                                    describing recent exchange rate fluctuations, attributing the
                                    current economic stagnation to exchange rate variability and
                                    calling for establishment of bands or zones within which rates
                                    should be kept.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>This view of the French position as insisting on zones was in
                                    no way congruent with the tone or specifics of our conversations
                                    in Paris with <persName corresp="#p_LJ1">de Larosiere</persName>
                                    or Clappier.<note n="2" xml:id="d109fn2">See <ref target="#d107">Document 107</ref>.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Interestingly, Poehl indicated that they thought an
                                    appropriate zone with the <gloss target="#t_DM1">DM</gloss>
                                    would be 2.50 to 2.70. This compares with the figures of 2.40 to
                                    2.60 mentioned by <persName corresp="#p_EO1">Emminger</persName>
                                    in a speech several weeks ago.<note n="3" xml:id="d109fn3">On
                                        September 15, the Embassy in Bonn reported on an August 26
                                        article written by Bundesbank Vice President <persName corresp="#p_EO1">Otmar Emminger</persName> in which he
                                        discussed the dollar’s strength vis-à-vis the mark and the
                                        implications of an exchange rate that hovered between <gloss target="#t_DM1">DM</gloss> 2.40 and <gloss target="#t_DM1">DM</gloss> 2.60 per dollar (a rate below
                                            <gloss target="#t_DM1">DM</gloss> 2.40 would mean
                                        trouble for West German exporters, while a rate above <gloss target="#t_DM1">DM</gloss> 2.60 would raise import
                                        prices and exacerbate inflation). (Telegram 15123 from Bonn,
                                        September 15; National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                        Policy Files)</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Either the Germans are not aware of the current French
                                    position as described by <persName corresp="#p_LJ1">de
                                        Larosiere</persName> or they themselves are pushing for
                                    zones by using the French.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Poehl apologized for their performance in re the <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss>/aid link at the U.N. He
                                    explained that the Chancellor, confronted late at night by the
                                    urgings of <persName corresp="#p_GHD1">Genscher</persName> and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bahr</persName>, had made the
                                    decision to withdraw their reservation on the link. Following
                                    the U.N. affair, the Chancellor had been criticized in the press
                                    for acquiescing to the link. As a result he issued an
                                    interpretation of their position which in substance stated that
                                    they are still opposed to the link.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>We agreed that the link would destroy the <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss> as originally conceived.
                                    Furthermore, the link lacked any semblance of conditionality,
                                    any consultation with a view to improving individual countries’
                                    economic performance and any political quid pro quo. We
                                    suggested that the private banking system’s ability to continue
                                    to finance that part of the <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>s
                                    deficits which could be described as structural is limited. The
                                    heavy debt burdens of many <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>s
                                    plus the banking system’s own limitations suggest that the flow
                                    of private credit might stagnate or decline somewhat. Improved
                                    world economic conditions might mitigate the <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>s earning problems but to the
                                    degree individual <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>s have
                                    structural concerns the positive effect would be only
                                    partial.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>It is clear that Poehl and perhaps others in the German
                                    Government are concerned about the liquidity issue. We indicated
                                    that the <pb facs="0377" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/> very sizeable
                                    amount of short-term economic expansion in recent years should
                                    not be confused with international liquidity. Existence of huge
                                    capital flows is not a symptom of too much liquidity or too
                                    little. We indicated that our own concern centered on the
                                    distribution of official liquidity and the related fundamental
                                    issue of individual countries’ comparative earning power.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Poehl indicated he personally feared an attempt by the British
                                    and Italians in conjunction with the <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>s to try for a new issue of <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss>s.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>We agreed this would be undesirable in the sense that it would
                                    represent an attempt to float everyone off the rocks without
                                    addressing underlying problems. We indicated at some point
                                    individual countries’ standards of living must be related to
                                    their earning capacities. Expansion of <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss>s would in effect transfer income from healthy
                                    developed countries to others. The mechanism would be through
                                    the process of inflation engendered by the broad issuance of
                                        <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss>s and this in turn would
                                    cripple our individual efforts to bring about price
                                    stability.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>We indicated that Germany’s ability to operate as an island of
                                    price stability in the future would be limited by other
                                    countries’ adoption of individual price stabilization programs
                                    and in any case meant that Germany would have to accept such low
                                    real rates of growth that they would have in effect embraced a
                                    policy of engineered stagnation.</item>
                                <label>11.</label>
                                <item>We discussed the New York City problem and gave them a full
                                    review of the situation.<note n="4" xml:id="d109fn4">The
                                        finances of New York City were in such disarray that the
                                        city was in danger of defaulting on its loans. On October 3,
                                        Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_SH1">Schmidt</persName>
                                        told President <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>:
                                        “I am also worried about <persName corresp="#p_SWE1">Simon</persName>’s attitude toward New York. If New
                                        York shouldn’t pay on the bonds, it could be looked on
                                        outside the United States as kind of a Black Friday. There
                                        are other cities, not like New York, but that are under some
                                        suspicion, and if New York collapsed they perhaps couldn’t
                                        sell bonds. I am sympathetic to the problem of New York’s
                                        mismanagement but there is a psychological problem
                                        involved.” (Memorandum of conversation, October 3; <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> Library, National
                                        Security Adviser, Memoranda of Conversation, Box 15)</note>
                                    It was apparent that they were not familiar with many of the
                                    pivotal factors in re the overall issue.</item>
                                <label>12.</label>
                                <item>We discussed the chairmanship of the Interim Committee. Poehl
                                    said he favored <persName corresp="#p_DWF1">Duisenberg</persName>. Impartiality and a steady and even
                                    hand were the most important criteria to us and we indicated
                                    some reservations <persName corresp="#p_DWF1">re
                                        Duisenberg</persName>. Poehl then mentioned <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Healey</persName> and
                                        <persName>Declerq</persName> and we indicated both were on
                                    our list but we were not prepared as of that moment to put
                                    forward a name.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_REL1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Richardson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>