<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-03-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="163" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                    <head>163. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for International Economic
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_FP1" type="from">Flanigan</persName>) to
                        President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d163fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 56, Records
                            of Secretary of the Treasury <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">George P.
                                Shultz</persName>, 1971–1974, Entry 166, Box 6, <gloss target="#t_GPS1">GPS</gloss> Trade—Volumes I &amp; II 1973/74. No
                            classification marking. A handwritten notation at the top of the
                            memorandum reads: “Be sure <persName corresp="#p_SWE1">Simon</persName>
                            &amp; <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> see this—” Attached
                            to a March 19 note from White House staff member Tod Hullin to <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> that reads: “<persName corresp="#p_EJ1">John Ehrlichman</persName> asked that the attached
                            be brought to your attention.”</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-03-16">March 16, 1973</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Wilbur Mills</persName> and the Trade
                            Bill</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>During a 1½ hour meeting with Chairman <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> in his office on Thursday, March 15, we discussed
                        (among endless non-related topics) the timing of Ways and Means
                        consideration of the Trade Bill, and the extension of <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> to the USSR.</p>
                    <p>Regarding timing, <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> said that he
                        had originally agreed to set aside tax hearings for trade legislation of an
                        emergency nature, such as the right to impose a surcharge on imports from a
                        single country. I pointed out that our trade negotiations were a major part,
                        but only a <pb facs="0655" n="624" xml:id="pg_624"/> part, of a broad
                        negotiating effort with our allies on both economic and non-economic
                        matters. The former includes negotiations for monetary reform and
                        discussions on investment rules as well as the trade negotiations. It was
                        essential that all parts of these discussions move forward together and that
                        the United States not be accused of “dragging its feet” in any single area,
                        particularly so important an area as trade. Given the <gloss target="#t_EC1">EC</gloss>’s public commitment to have a trade negotiating position by
                        June, and general agreement to begin trade negotiations in September, long
                        delay in consideration of the Administration’s Trade Bill would be a matter
                        of considerable concern.</p>
                    <p>I did indicate, however, some difficulty in declaring the Trade Bill to be
                        “emergency legislation.” <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> said
                        all he was looking for was a statement by you that there was some “urgency”
                        to Congressional consideration of the Trade Bill. If your message contained
                        a sense of immediacy, <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> would
                        respond by interrupting the tax hearings at the time of the Congressional
                        recess on April 19. He would further commit to begin hearings on trade
                        immediately on the Committee’s return on Monday, April 30 and continue with
                        the hearings and Executive Committee sessions, with the expectation that the
                        Bill would come to the floor in the first half of July. In order to do this,
                            <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> asks that the trade message
                        be sent to the Hill either during the week beginning Monday, April 2 or
                        early in the week beginning Monday, April 9.</p>
                    <p>In considering this timing, <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName>
                        indicated some regret that his first test of the new Rules Committee system,
                        which denies him the closed rule,<note n="2" xml:id="d163fn2">Before 1973,
                            the House Ways and Means Committee often sent legislation to the floor
                            of the House of Representatives under the closed rule, which prevented
                            the addition of amendments to a bill by the majority party; in 1973,
                            procedural changes were introduced that made it easier for majority
                            party House members to add amendments to bills coming out of the Ways
                            and Means Committee.</note> would come in connection with the Trade Bill
                        rather than the Tax Bill. He pointed out that the closed rule had been
                        instituted as a reform and that he “needed to teach these new reformers the
                        difference between good reform and bad reform.” His preference for using the
                        Tax Bill for this purpose is that he “considers trade more important.”
                        Presumably, he believes the new system could result in so bad a Bill that
                        you would veto it and he could then convince the Congress to revert to the
                        closed rule for Ways and Means bills. Since the prospect of vetoing a Trade
                        Bill is highly unattractive, one could make an argument for delaying trade
                        until after taxes. However, it is hard to believe that the Trade Bill would
                        get a closed rule even if the Tax Bill provided a lurid example of the
                        shortcomings of an open rule.</p>
                    <p>On <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> said he had had a long talk with Alkhimov<note n="3" xml:id="d163fn3">Vladimir S. Alkhimov.</note> (USSR Deputy Minister of
                        Trade) who had undertaken to get a relaxation of <pb facs="0656" n="625" xml:id="pg_625"/> the exit visa practices upon his return to Moscow. I
                        pointed out that this problem was considerably larger than
                            <persName>Alkhimov</persName> and that it might take quite some time to
                        arrive at a satisfactory solution. Therefore, I urged that <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> accept the <persName corresp="#p_JJK1">Javits</persName> proposal allowing you the right to grant <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> to countries behind the Iron Curtain,
                        subject to Congressional veto. I pointed out that this could remove <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> for the USSR from the Trade Bill
                        discussions, protect the détente to the extent of giving you the opportunity
                        of taking action on your commitment to <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Brezhnev</persName>,<note n="4" xml:id="d163fn4">The President made
                            this commitment during the U.S.-Soviet summit meeting in May 1972. See
                                <ref target="frus1969-76v14#d265">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume XIV,
                                Soviet Union, October 1971–May 1972, Document 265</ref>.</note> and
                        provide more time in which to work out a negotiation with the Soviets.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> said he did not find this
                        solution acceptable. He based his opposition entirely on the belief that a
                        Congressional veto violated the Constitutional right of the Executive to
                        act. I pointed out a similar veto existed with regard to reorganization
                        plans and that he had agreed to our proposal to a similar veto regarding
                        negotiations on non-tariff barriers. Nevertheless, he continued to express
                        opposition to the <persName corresp="#p_JJK1">Javits</persName> proposal.
                            (<persName>Jackson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RAA1">Ribicoff</persName> had expressed similar opposition though most
                        members of the Congress with whom it has been discussed find it an
                        acceptable compromise.) I agreed with <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> that further discussions of this provision of the
                        Trade Bill should await <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName>’
                        return and a review of his discussions in Moscow.<note n="5" xml:id="d163fn5">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> was in Moscow from March
                            11 to 14; reports on his talks are in the National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, NSC
                            Files, Box 953, VIP Visits, <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">George P.
                                Shultz</persName> (Europe &amp; USSR), March 8–22 1973 [&amp;
                            September–October] and ibid., Box 424, Backchannel Files, Backchannel
                            Messages—Europe—1973.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> will be on <hi rend="italic">Meet The Press</hi> on Sunday, March 18 and will be quizzed by Eileen
                        Shanahan on his schedule for trade hearings. In a phone conversation with me
                        today he agreed to state his intention of setting aside tax hearings if so
                        requested by the President. I recommend that prior to his television
                        appearance you call him and thank him for his willingness to take up trade
                        hearings immediately after the Easter recess and to continue them to
                        completion. This will assure his sticking to this commitment. If you are
                        successful in getting his agreement to the timing for the Trade Bill
                        outlined above, we will schedule the submission of the Message and the
                        legislation to Congress on Tuesday, April 10, as you are expected to be in
                        San Clemente during the previous week.</p>
                    <p>In your conversation you might wish to commiserate with him about his bad
                        back. Though he returned to Washington at the beginning of the week, he was
                        out two days and it is clear his back is still <pb facs="0657" n="626" xml:id="pg_626"/> hurting. However, he looks a great deal better than he
                        did during my recent visit with him in Arkansas.<note n="6" xml:id="d163fn6">See <ref target="#d161">Document 161</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TWE1">Timmons</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CR2">Cook</persName> concur in my recommendation that you
                        call <persName corresp="#p_MW1">Mills</persName> and confirm his agreement
                        to begin hearings on the Trade Bill on April 30.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>