<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>207. Memorandum From the Counselor of the Department of State (Sonnenfeldt)
                    to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State Kissinger</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v31</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d207</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">207</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-03-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recIW1xgHEanEAKPW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133192"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technology transfer</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recu3GH1ojKcJBA1c" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recFzikmNCJDCCGBL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade union</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Taxes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-03-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="207"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d207">
                <head>207. Memorandum From the Counselor of the Department of State (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SH2" type="from">Sonnenfeldt</persName>) to Secretary of State
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d207fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Records of Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry
                            Kissinger</persName>, Entry 5403, Box 5, <gloss target="#t_Nodis1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_memcon1">Memcons</gloss>, 1974. Confidential; Eyes Only.
                        Sent for action.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1974-03-12">March 12, 1974</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Discussions on Title IV of Trade Bill with Senator <persName
                            corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName>’s Staff</item>
                </list>
                <p>I have had two extended sessions, one with Bill Eberle present, the other with
                    Bill’s deputy <persName corresp="#p_JJ1">John Jackson</persName>.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d207fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_EW1">Eberle</persName>’s report to <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> on his meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_SH2">Sonnenfeldt</persName> and
                        <persName>Jackson</persName>’s staff members is ibid., <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, NSC Files,
                        Box 404, Subject Files, Special Assistant for Trade (Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_EW1">Eberle</persName>).</note> I cannot honestly say that
                    we <pb facs="0769" n="738" xml:id="pg_738"/> negotiated since Perle and Fosdick
                    essentially took the position that they have the votes to pass their amendment
                    and that they would agree to modify it only if certain very stringent conditions
                    were met. In fact, they would not agree to talk about modifications of the
                    amendment until they first had clear assurances that the demands on emigration
                    would actually be put to the Soviets. (This represented a slight advance over
                    their first position which was that they would talk about changing the amendment
                    only <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the Senator had received indications of a
                    positive Soviet reaction to the demands.)</p>
                <p>The <persName>Jackson</persName> demands are at Tab A. Originally,
                        <persName>Perle</persName> gave them to me orally but I urged him to reduce
                    them to paper in the form of generalized principles which would not have the
                    character of direct intervention into domestic Soviet procedures. This resulted
                    in the Basic Principles. But, in addition, there is the memorandum elaborating
                    on each principle.</p>
                <p>I pointed out that many of the points in the memorandum in fact described Soviet
                    practices not only toward potential emigrants but their population generally and
                    consequently the memorandum was tantamount to demanding the repeal of the Soviet
                    system. I suggested at one point that perhaps a proper way to formulate the
                    First Principle would be that any requestor for emigration and his family should
                    be treated the same as any normal non-requesting individual and family (Bill
                    Eberle’s idea). <persName>Perle</persName> and <persName>Fosdick</persName> were
                    reluctant, though not wholly negative.</p>
                <p>I repeatedly stressed my view that such a list of demands was non-negotiable with
                    the Soviets. They insisted that the Soviets have an incentive to let out all who
                    want to leave.</p>
                <p>After much back and forth, the principal propositions that emerged seemed to be
                    the following: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Jackson</persName> does not necessarily require a written
                            document by the Soviets.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>He does require an assurance from the President in fairly specific
                            terms that he has reason to believe the Soviets would permit an
                            increasing volume of emigration and that applicants would not be
                            subjected to discrimination, harassment and indignities.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Such a Presidential assurance would have to be in writing with some
                            oral assurance that it was based on explicit discussions with the
                            Soviets of the terms in the <persName>Jackson</persName> memorandum.
                            There could also be a legislative history indicating the performance
                            standards that would be employed to judge the Soviets.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Jackson</persName> feels strongly about hard-core cases; hence
                            the requirement to let out first those who applied first. He also feels
                            strongly about “good faith” acts.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>It is not wholly clear whether <persName>Jackson</persName>’s
                            agreement to a modified amendment and his support of the Bill will
                            depend on Soviet assurances <pb facs="0770" n="739" xml:id="pg_739"/>
                            (as conveyed by the President) alone or also require immediate Soviet
                            performance. (I pointed out repeatedly that in the unlikely event that
                            the Soviets accepted anything approaching the
                                <persName>Jackson</persName> list they clearly would condition it on
                            first getting <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> and retaining EXIM
                            credits.) <persName>Perle</persName> has agreed to set down on paper how
                            Soviet performance might be phased. I drew a careful distinction between
                            assurances as the condition for passage of an acceptable bill and
                            performance as the condition for continued granting of <gloss
                                target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> and credits after some specified period
                            of time written into the bill.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>While <persName>Jackson</persName> does not insist on an immediate
                            increase to a rate of 100,000 emigrants per year (he thinks there are
                            500,000 people of all kinds who want to leave and wants the process
                            completed in five years) he does insist on a rapid increase in the rate.
                            40–50,000 per year is not acceptable. 90,000 may be.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>A Presidential statement to <persName>Jackson</persName> that a
                            document similar to the <persName>Jackson</persName> principles and
                            memorandum has been handed to the Soviets and that the President
                            believes the Soviets understand that retention of <gloss
                                target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> and credits beyond a certain time
                            depends on their performance is <hi rend="italic">not acceptable to
                                    <persName>Jackson</persName>
                            </hi>.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>In any revised bill, the burden of determining Soviet nonperformance
                            must rest at least as much on the President as on the Congress.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>While <persName>Jackson</persName> would not raise the emigration
                            issue in other legislation if he were satisfied with respect to it for
                            the trade bill, he gives no assurance that he will not raise other
                            issues concerning trade and technology transfers to the USSR. On the
                            contrary, he insists on his right to question individual credit grants
                            on grounds of national security, etc.; and on his right to question such
                            projects as the gas deals and deals involving technology. (He plans
                            hearings on technology transfer to the USSR.)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>While I can continue, after my return from Europe, to try to whittle down the
                    performance standards to more generalized language, I do not think I can shake
                    the basic position without your having a further talk with
                        <persName>Jackson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RAA1"
                        >Ribicoff</persName>. I believe that in such a talk you should shoot for a
                    generalized formula that would be put to the Soviets and form the basis of
                    eventual Presidential assurances to <persName>Jackson</persName>: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>There will be no interference with the right to emigrate.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The flow of emigration shall be steadily increased.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Persons wishing to emigrate and their families shall not be subjected
                            to harassment, intimidation, discrimination and other indignities by
                            virtue of their desire to emigrate. In particular, there should be no
                            efforts to prevent applicants from complying with emigration
                            procedures.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>If it were possible for you to agree with the Senators that these are the
                    principles, you and they could then instruct me and their staffs to elaborate
                    these principles by about one paragraph each. In addition, you <pb facs="0771"
                        n="740" xml:id="pg_740"/> could agree to raise with <persName
                        corresp="#p_DA1">Dobrynin</persName> (not <persName corresp="#p_BL1"
                        >Brezhnev</persName>) some of the details in the
                        <persName>Jackson</persName> memorandum to make the Soviets aware of more
                    particular standards that we would apply in observing Soviet performance.</p>
                <p>While I understand that there may be differences between <persName
                        corresp="#p_RAA1">Ribicoff</persName> and <persName>Jackson</persName>,
                        <persName>Perle</persName> and <persName>Fosdick</persName> maintain that
                    the two Senators are totally in tandem. You may be able to form some judgment on
                    this point and on whether <persName corresp="#p_RAA1">Ribicoff</persName>’s man
                    could usefully be drawn into any future contacts.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That you indicate after my return from Europe whether, and if so, along what
                    lines you wish us to pursue this matter with <persName>Perle</persName> and
                        <persName>Fosdick</persName>.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="strong">Tab A</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">Basic Principles</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Principle I: Persons Wishing to Emigrate Must Not
                                    Be Subjected To Harassment or Intimidation</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Persons seeking to emigrate shall not suffer discrimination,
                                harassment or intimidation as a consequence of their desire to
                                emigrate.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Principle II: Assuring The Right And Opportunity
                                    To Emigrate</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Persons wishing to emigrate shall be able to comply with the
                                application procedures without interference.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Principle III: Visas Shall Be Granted In The Order
                                    In Which Applications Are Initiated And Without
                                    Discrimination</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>Applications should be processed and visas granted in the order in
                                which they are initiated without discrimination on the basis of
                                race, religion, national origin, place of residence, professional
                                status, etc.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Principle IV: A Good Faith Effort Must Be Made To
                                    Assure Freer Emigration</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In the spirit of détente and mutual accommodation there must be a
                                good faith effort to assure freer emigration accompanied by
                                immediate positive action.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Principle V: The Rate Of Flow Shall Be Increased
                                    To 100,000 Per Annum</hi>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">MEMORANDUM</p>
                    <p rend="center">Some Points in Elaboration of Principles I Through V</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Principle I:</hi> Persons seeking to emigrate shall
                            not suffer discrimination, harassment or intimidation as a consequence
                            of their desire to emigrate; for example: <pb facs="0772" n="741"
                                xml:id="pg_741"/>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Persons desiring to emigrate shall not be fired from their
                                    jobs nor demoted to tasks that do not reflect their professional
                                    qualifications.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Persons desiring to emigrate, or their children, shall not be
                                    expelled or suspended from their schools or universities.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Persons desiring to emigrate must not be subjected to
                                    harassment or intimidation by security authorities,
                                    interrogation, surveillance, etc.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Persons desiring to emigrate must not be subjected to public
                                    recrimination at their place of employment, residence, trade
                                    union, etc.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Principle II:</hi> Persons wishing to emigrate shall
                            be able to comply with the application procedures without interference;
                            for example: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>There shall be no interference with the communications
                                    necessary to obtain the documents required for filing an
                                    application to emigrate. Letters sent abroad for the purpose of
                                    obtaining a <hi rend="italic">Vysov</hi>
                                    <note n="3" xml:id="d207fn3">A vysov, or vyzov, was an
                                        invitation.</note> shall not be intercepted and incoming
                                    letters containing requisite documents shall not be withheld
                                    from the addressee.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Documents required from internal authorities shall not be
                                    withheld. There should be no administrative obstacle to the
                                    completion of the required application.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Travel for the purpose of completing application requirements
                                    shall not be prevented.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The necessary forms and information necessary to complete them
                                    shall be available upon demand.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Persons of adult age shall not be required to obtain the
                                    permission of parents, grandparents or other relatives in order
                                    to emigrate.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Persons desiring to emigrate shall not be required to submit
                                    character references from their places of employment.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Taxes and/or fees associated with applications to emigrate
                                    shall be nominal and shall not constitute a barrier to
                                    emigration.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Principle III:</hi> Applications should be processed
                            and visas granted in the order in which they are initiated without
                            discrimination on the basis of race, religion, national origin, place of
                            residence, professional status, etc. <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Those who have waited longest should be the first to receive
                                    visas. In assuring this, applications should be reviewed
                                    expeditiously.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Visas should be available equally without regard to race,
                                    religion or national origins.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Visas should be available equally without regard to place of
                                    residence or birth.</item>
                                <pb facs="0773" n="742" xml:id="pg_742"/>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Visas should be available equally without regard to
                                    professional status, job training, employment or
                                    education.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Persons wishing to emigrate who have been actively engaged in
                                    work of a secret nature should be notified upon application as
                                    to the earliest date on which they will become eligible to
                                    receive a visa.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Principle IV:</hi> In the spirit of détente and mutual
                            accommodation there must be a good faith effort to assure freer
                            emigration accompanied by immediate positive action. To this end: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>There shall be sympathetic and expeditious consideration of
                                    any individual case raised by the government of the United
                                    States.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Those persons presently imprisoned who, prior to their
                                        imprisonment, indicated an interest in emigration shall be
                                        granted visas upon the expiration of their present
                                        sentences;</p>
                                    <p>and</p>
                                    <p>Sympathetic and humanitarian consideration shall be given to
                                        the commutation of sentences and/or a general amnesty for
                                        those persons.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Persons whose applications to emigrate are denied shall be
                                    informed of the reason for such denial.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The government of the United States shall be supplied with
                                    such information as may be required to enable the President to
                                    assess the good faith of the implementation of these
                                    Principles.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Principle V:</hi> The rate of flow shall be increased
                            to 100,000 per annum.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The number of visas granted in recent years suggests that substantial growth
                        in the rate of flow is possible.</p>
                    <p>100,000 visas per annum would be consistent with a good faith effort to
                        permit substantially freer emigration.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
