<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>267. Memorandum From the Executive Director of the Council on International
                    Economic Policy (Eberle) to the Executive Committee of the Economic Policy
                    Board) to the Executive Committee of the Economic Policy Board</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v31</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d267</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">267</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006001993"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Interagency</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="267"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d267">
                <head>267. Memorandum From the Executive Director of the Council on International
                    Economic Policy (<persName corresp="#p_EW1">Eberle</persName>) to the Executive
                    Committee of the Economic Policy Board<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d267fn1"
                        >Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> Library, U.S. Council
                        of Economic Advisers Records, <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Alan
                            Greenspan</persName> Files, Box 57, Economic Policy Board Meetings,
                            <gloss target="#t_EPB1">EPB</gloss>—October 1974. Limited Official Use.
                        Printed from an unsigned copy. On October 29, <persName corresp="#p_MHB1"
                            >Malmgren</persName> gave a report on U.S. preparations for the World
                        Food Conference to the <gloss target="#t_EPB1">EPB</gloss> Executive
                        Committee that was based on this memorandum. (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1974-10-25">October 25, 1974</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Status of U.S. Policy Development for World Food Conference</item>
                </list>
                <p>The World Food Conference will be held in Rome, November 5–16, 1974. At the third
                    preparatory meeting of participating governments, ten draft resolutions were
                    prepared for consideration and adoption at the World Food Conference.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d267fn2">The third preparatory committee meeting was held in Rome
                        September 23–October 4. On October 24, <persName corresp="#p_EW1"
                            >Eberle</persName> circulated a <gloss target="#t_CIEP1">CIEP</gloss>
                        paper outlining the policy issues raised by the draft resolutions to the
                        participants in the October 25 <gloss target="#t_CIEP1">CIEP</gloss>–<gloss
                            target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> meeting. (National Archives, RG 429,
                        Records of the Council on International Economic Policy, 1971–1977, Box 255,
                        Senior Review Group Meetings, 1971–1974, 54234 <persName corresp="#p_EW1"
                            >Eberle</persName> Calls for <gloss target="#t_CIEP1"
                            >CIEP</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> Meeting on October 25
                        at 4 p.m., Rm 208, OEOB 10/23/74)</note> Position papers have been prepared
                    on each resolution, in consultation with selected agencies. These papers will be
                    presented by <gloss target="#t_COB1">COB</gloss> October 30 for <gloss
                        target="#t_EPB1">EPB</gloss> approval. It is anticipated that speeches to be
                    made by the principals (Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BE2">Butz</persName>) at the
                    World Food Conference may contain policy points not covered by the position
                    papers, so that the contents of the speeches may also need revision.</p>
                <p>The discussion in the <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> on Friday, October
                        25,<note n="3" xml:id="d267fn3">A summary of the October 25 <gloss
                            target="#t_CIEP1">CIEP</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss>
                        meeting is ibid.</note> revealed that there are some fundamental issues
                    which require resolution. Unfortunately, the final preparations have not been
                    timely. The interagency clearance process was handled in an ad hoc manner, with
                    the result that many issues have not previously been given full consideration by
                    key agencies. Consequently, the positions of some agencies are still
                    unclear.</p>
                <p>The October 25 <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> discussion reviewed the major
                    issues posed by the ten draft resolutions and the position papers, and certain
                    general conclusions emerged.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <item>It was agreed that there will be no commitments to any specific numerical
                        targets, including those involving <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>
                        expenditures, commodity levels, or program objectives.</item>
                    <pb facs="0978" n="947" xml:id="pg_947"/>
                    <label>II.</label>
                    <item>There is a fundamental disagreement as to whether U.S. willingness to
                        negotiate a grain reserve system should be linked to negotiating
                        multilateral trade agreements. Some agencies believe basic national
                        interests are involved with the issue, involving both commercial and foreign
                        policy interests. This poses a related issue on which there is also
                        disagreement concerning the appropriate forum in which to begin discussions
                        of an international grain reserve system.</item>
                    <label>III.</label>
                    <item>It was agreed that the U.S. would oppose any resolutions regarding grains
                        reserves which establish target levels, specific burden sharing criteria,
                        obligations of specific countries to hold reserves, sanctions, or other
                        specific elements of a grain reserves system. It was also agreed that the
                        language regarding burden-sharing criteria would be deleted from the
                        position paper.</item>
                    <label>IV.</label>
                    <item>It was agreed that the U.S. continues to favor national control of
                        reserves, and does not favor internationally held grain reserves.</item>
                    <label>V.</label>
                    <item>It was agreed that the U.S. will continue to reserve the right to
                        determine later how it will fulfill any reserves commitment. Agreement in
                        principle to a grain reserve system is not a commitment to hold reserve
                        stocks by the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> itself.</item>
                    <label>VI.</label>
                    <item>Given the tight supply situation for fertilizer and the high possibility
                        that domestic availabilities will fall short of domestic requirements, the
                        U.S. should not commit itself to assuring the availability of fertilizer to
                        other countries.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In the meeting of the <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss>, Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_MD2">Martin</persName> and the State Department representative
                    indicated that the speeches to be delivered by the principals might contain
                    numerical targets, which would commit the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> to
                    financial expenditures or to other specific objectives. Other agencies had not
                    seen the draft speeches, but expressed their concerns about the contents and
                    about this unusual clearance procedure in the economic-commercial area where
                    commitments affect other economic alternatives.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
