<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-11-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-11-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="55" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d55">
                        <head>55. Memorandum From <persName type="from">John Reynolds</persName> of
                            the Federal Reserve System Board of Governors Staff to the Chairman of
                            the Federal Reserve System Board of Governors (<persName corresp="#p_BA1" type="to">Burns</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d55fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_BA2">Arthur
                                    Burns</persName> Papers, Federal Reserve Board Subject Files,
                                Box B52, Gold–<gloss target="#t_BIS1">BIS</gloss> Meeting, Nov.
                                1973. Confidential (<gloss target="#t_FR1">FR</gloss>).</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-11-01">November 1, 1973</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Possible Consequences of Seeking a New Agreement on Gold</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The question has arisen whether it would be in the U.S. interest to seek
                            at this time to negotiate a termination of the gold agreement of March
                            17, 1968, together with a reaffirmation of Article 4, Section 2 of the
                                <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> Articles of Agreement which
                            provides that “no member shall buy gold at a price above par value plus
                            the prescribed margin.”<note n="2" xml:id="d55fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BA2">Burns</persName> had already proposed
                                this idea to Jelle Zijlstra, President of the Netherlands Bank, in
                                an October 26 letter. A handwritten notation on the letter reads:
                                “not actually sent”; however, another handwritten note indicates
                                that <persName corresp="#p_BA2">Burns</persName>’s proposal was
                                “Read to Zijlstra by phone, 10/26/73.” (Ibid.) The full text of
                                Article IV, Section 2 of the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>
                                Articles of Agreement reads: “The Fund shall prescribe a margin
                                above and below par value for transactions in gold by members, and
                                no member shall buy gold at a price above par value plus the
                                prescribed margin, or sell gold at a price below par value minus the
                                prescribed margin.” (de Vries, <hi rend="italic">The International
                                    Monetary Fund, 1966–1971</hi>, Volume II, p. 100)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>It appears likely that the several parties would enter such a negotiation
                            with very different objectives. The U.S. objectives would be (1) to
                            permit market sales of gold by central banks at times when this seemed
                            desirable in order to tranquilize foreign exchange markets, (2) <pb facs="0230" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/> to prevent official purchases
                            of gold at premium prices, and hence (3) to reduce further the role of
                            gold as an international monetary asset.</p>
                        <p>European countries might share the first objective. But their main
                            interest in gold at the moment is to make use of it in intra-European
                            settlements which, as a practical matter, they are prepared to do only
                            at a market-related price, well above the official price. Some of them,
                            in addition, wish to reserve the right to buy gold in the market as well
                            as to sell. In general, they wish to increase the usability of gold as
                            means of international settlement, and thus to enhance or at least
                            preserve the role of gold, rather than to reduce it.</p>
                        <p>Against this background, any negotiation to reach a new agreement on gold
                            seems likely to be difficult, and to precipitate decisions about gold
                            that it has so far been possible to postpone, and that might be contrary
                            to broader U.S. objectives in <gloss target="#t_C201">C–20</gloss>
                            negotiations.</p>
                        <p>Even if the European countries were to agree to the suggested communiqué,
                            some of them would wish to let it be known that they reserved the right
                            to conduct inter-central bank dealings in gold at negotiated prices.
                            Some countries not party to the new agreement would wish to stress that
                            they would not be bound by it. The result of such statements might well
                            be to enhance the role of gold as a monetary asset, to confirm market
                            expectations of at least a de facto rise in the official gold price, and
                            to exacerbate a dispute about gold between the United States and other
                            countries which might otherwise have been postponed and defused during a
                            later stage of the reform negotiations.</p>
                        <p>The U.S. interest in permitting central bank sales of gold to the market
                            is now much less acute than it was in July, when the gold price was
                            above $120 an ounce (vs. less than $100 now) and when the dollar was
                            weak because the U.S. balance of payments had not yet shown its recent
                            strength. It has never been clear that official market sales of small
                            amounts of gold would have useful lasting effects. Also, U.S. sales
                            might precipitate Congressional pressure to allow U.S. citizens to
                            purchase gold, which could add substantially to demand for gold.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> interest in undertaking official
                            gold transactions at market-related prices is much stronger now that
                            there are substantial intra-<gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> debts to
                            be settled. But such settlements could be postponed further, or made in
                            dollars, or made in gold-related assets with provision for later
                            revaluation in line with later <gloss target="#t_C201">C–20</gloss>
                            decisions. There is little logic in the present European position on
                            gold. On the one hand, European officials oppose small additional issues
                            of <gloss target="#t_SDR1">SDR</gloss>s as inflationary. On the other
                            hand, they propose to add billions to gold reserves through a de facto
                            increase in the official gold price.</p>
                        <p>On balance, it seems to me—and to my colleagues on the staff—undesirable
                            to seek a new gold agreement at this time because the result might be
                            contrary to the longer-run U.S. interest in constructing a <pb facs="0231" n="200" xml:id="pg_200"/> sound international monetary
                            system. It may be that ultimately we will have to compromise on gold
                            questions, but if so, it would be useful to save that card for a stage
                            in the reform negotiations when we can get something useful in
                            return.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>