<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>51. Telegram From the Embassy in Thailand to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-03-03T06:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-03-03T06:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="rec0252ZNz4fHrq9C" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="vietnam-conflict">Vietnamization</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="reccKWZw7wcZPbjV8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recNHstTN4mCmPSgR" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="missile-defense" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011305" lcsh-match="good_close">Air defense</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-03-03T06:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-03-03T06:40:00-05:00" n="51"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                <head>51. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Thailand</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d51fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 THAI–<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>.
                        Secret; Priority; <gloss target="#t_EXDIS1">Exdis</gloss>. Repeated to
                        Vientiane, CINCPAC, and COMUSMACTHAI.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bangkok</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-03-03T11:40:00+00:00">March 3, 1970, 1140Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2550. Subject: Meeting With Prime Minister. Ref: A. State 027316 (Joint
                    State/Def); B. State 030190; C. Bangkok 2522; D. State 023802.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d51fn2">Reftels A–<gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> are not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>During cordial meeting with <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss> at
                        Government House March 2 to discuss deployment of <gloss
                            target="#t_SIERRAROMEO1">Sierra Romeo</gloss> IX<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d51fn3">
                            <gloss target="#t_SIERRAROMEO1">Sierra Romeo</gloss> was the codename
                            for the Thai artillery unit which was periodically inserted into and
                            withdrawn from Laos in response to Communist pressure against the Lao
                            Government forces, mostly the Meo tribesmen on the mountain front; see
                                <ref target="#d29">Document 29</ref>.</note> (reported ref c), I
                        took the opportunity to inform him, in general terms (without divulging
                        specific or sensitive information), of items I considered would be pertinent
                        to his interests that were recently discussed at <gloss
                            target="#t_SEACOORD1">SEACOORD</gloss> meeting. I covered the military
                        situation in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>, status of pacification,
                        our views of Hanoi’s post-hostilities planning and the Vietnamization
                        program, including a word about its relation to third country forces.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss> was very interested and brought up
                        several points the most important of which concerned Vietnamization. He
                        pointedly asked whether the U.S. was training and equipping the <gloss
                            target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss> to replace U.S. forces only or whether
                        we also planned to replace Thai and other allied forces. I explained to him
                        that for the purposes of the Vietnamization program we were now discussing
                        the revitalized <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> forces were intended to
                        replace a substantial share of U.S. forces in <gloss target="#t_SVN1"
                            >SVN</gloss> but that in the longer run I assumed their eventually
                        replacing <gloss target="#t_FWF1">FWF</gloss> was also contemplated. (I had
                        already said that some U.S. troops which would be remaining in <gloss
                            target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> through the Vietnamization process would
                        continue to provide the Black Panthers with the various kinds of support
                        from U.S. forces they are receiving today; my comment was based on my
                        discussions last week in Saigon.) He responded that he had been under
                        considerable pressure from Parliament to withdraw Thai forces from <gloss
                            target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> in face of continued U.S. and allied
                        reductions. In response to my direct question on whether it was his feeling
                        that he would be obliged to carry our reductions, he did not say he intended
                        to reduce the Thai troop contributions in <gloss target="#t_SVN1"
                            >SVN</gloss>, but again stressed that he was under growing pressure from
                        the representatives in Parliament and said that “when the people feel very
                        strongly about a situation, the government must do something to ease that
                        situation.”</item>
                    <pb facs="0164" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>I replied that I was aware of and sympathetic to his problem. The <gloss
                            target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> had warmly appreciated his statement that
                        the <gloss target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss> intended to maintain the Thai forces
                        in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> as long as the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> needs them or until Thailand itself
                        requires those forces. I added that my government hoped the <gloss
                            target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss> would retain all of the Thai forces in
                            <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>, or at least a substantial part of
                        them, at least during the Vietnamization process. I had already emphasized,
                        however, that the Vietnamization program did not have a specific schedule
                        for completion but its rate depended upon intensity of enemy activity on the
                        battlefield, the capacity of the Vietnamese to take over the combat role and
                        progress in Paris, if any. I then pointed out the psychological and
                        political importance of having not only U.S. forces but Thai and other
                        allied forces as well to support the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                        during the period of its takeover of the combat responsibility. I also
                        pointed out the importance of the Thai forces in protecting the eastern and
                        southeastern approaches to Saigon and thus freeing <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss> forces, as Vietnamization proceeds to establish a stronger
                        Vietnamese military presence in remote areas along the Cambodian border. I
                        requested that, if at any time he felt he had to decide to withdraw some of
                        the Thai forces, I be given the opportunity to discuss his plans with him
                        before he takes any action. He said that he would discuss such plans with
                        the cabinet, <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>, and indicated that I would
                        also have an opportunity to talk with him.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In connection with Vietnamization I told the <gloss target="#t_PM1"
                            >PM</gloss> that the U.S. forces in Thailand might have some additional
                        functions to perform here because some of the combat support activities now
                        being con-ducted in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> such as air defense,
                        air interdiction and reconnaissance might, as Vietnamization proceeds, have
                        to be continued from outside <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>, e.g.,
                        Thailand and elsewhere. I added that while there appeared to be a continuing
                        need to have U.S. forces and personnel in Thailand to support the <gloss
                            target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> effort until Vietnamization is well down the
                        road, I did not believe this ruled out a continuation of the gradual
                        reduction of U.S. forces in Thailand which we and the <gloss
                            target="#t_RTG1">RTG</gloss> had jointly got underway last September. I
                        speculated that we might have a follow-on reduction to the present one in
                        the next fiscal year which would reduce our forces by about the same
                        magnitude and that I would consult with the <gloss target="#t_RTG1"
                            >RTG</gloss> as our plans developed. He acknowledged these points
                        without comment.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Comment. The <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss> carefully avoided saying
                        that he would at some point have to withdraw all or part of the Thai forces.
                        However, it was clear that he wished to register the point of Parliamentary
                        pres-sure and I did not press the matter beyond making clear our interest in
                        maintaining Thai forces and in being consulted about any reduction plans. I
                        believe that in sharing with the <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss> some of
                        our thinking on questions I know weigh heavily on his mind we have restored
                        some <pb facs="0165" n="116" xml:id="pg_116"/> substance to our dialogue. I
                        hope I will have made available to me timely information with which to
                        continue such exchanges of information on matters of importance to the Thai,
                        which also give us an opportunity to gain valuable insights into their
                        thinking.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_ULS1">Unger</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
