<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Report to the National Security Council by the Executive Secretary of the
                    National Security Council ( (Lay))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d192</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">192</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-04-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recu0jAoErrAESV42" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002775"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Airlift</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaty negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States policy</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-04-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="192"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d192">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">S/S–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot
                    63 D 351: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 38 Series</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Report to the National Security Council by the Executive
                        Secretary of the National Security Council</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Lay</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d192fn1">Attached to the source text were a
                        cover sheet and a note of transmission from Lay, stating that the report was
                        being submitted for consideration by the National Security Council at its
                        56th Meeting on May 4. The note further indicated that the Department of
                        State had set forth reasons in support of a request for a prompt decision.
                        Neither printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 38/5</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-04-27">April 27,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Draft</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Report by the National Security Council on Future Courses
                        of</hi> U.S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Action With Respect to Austria</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">the problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. To consider the nature and timing of future United States action with respect
                    to Austria in the light of recent developments of Soviet policy.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">analysis</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">United States objectives with respect to Austria</hi>.</p>
                <p>2. The major United States objective in Austria is the reestablishment of
                    Austrian sovereignty and independence as agreed in the Moscow Declaration of
                    1943. The conclusion of the Treaty reestablishing an independent and
                    Western-oriented Austria would go far to prevent: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Soviet domination of Austria, which would result in penetration of the
                            East-West “frontier” by a salient extending westward to the Swiss border
                            and permit Soviet control of the principal North-South lines of
                            communication in Central Europe.</item>
                        <pb facs="0404" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Partition, which would destroy the Austrian nation and increase the
                            instability of Central Europe.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>3. It was determined in October, 1949 to be governmental policy in the United
                    States interest to agree at an early date to an Austrian Treaty on the best
                    terms obtainable. At the same time, it was determined that United States policy
                    should insure, by all appropriate measures prior to the withdrawal of the
                    occupation forces, that the Austrian armed forces are reasonably adequate to
                    maintain internal security (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 38/4, “Future
                    Courses of United States Action with Respect to Austria,” approved by the
                    President on November 18, 1949<note n="2" xml:id="d192fn2">
                        <ref target="frus1949v03#pg_1190">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 1190</ref>.</note>). To date, the Four
                    Powers have been unable to reach agreement on the terms of the Treaty due to
                    Soviet intransigence. Soviet action in the most recent phase of the negotiations
                    are obviously designed to delay the conclusion of the Treaty, The United States
                    objective in Austria can be furthered by the conclusion of the Treaty and the
                    creation of an adequate security force prior to the withdrawal of the occupation
                    troops. The governments of Great Britain and France agree with these objectives.
                    The Soviet Union must be signatory to the Treaty in order that Soviet military
                    forces be withdrawn under the terms of the Treaty. Any action either by the
                    United States alone, or by the three Western Powers without Soviet participation
                    to negotiate an Austrian Treaty would not be desirable as it would lead to
                    partition of Austria, if not Soviet domination of all Austria, by failing to
                    secure the withdrawal of Soviet military forces.</p>
                <p>4. Pending the conclusion of the Treaty, the United States will seek to maintain
                    the authority of the Allied Council and insist on strict adherence to the New
                    Control Agreement of the Allied Commission for Austria (June 28, 1946)<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d192fn3">For the text of the New Control Agreement for
                        Austria, see <hi rend="italic">A Decade of American Foreign Policy, Basic
                            Documents, 1941–1949</hi> (Washington, Government Printing Office,
                        1950), pp. 614–620.</note> in order to prevent any unilateral action by the
                    Soviet element threatening the fulfillment of our objectives. It is in the
                    United States interest to strengthen the authority of the Austrian Government,
                    to encourage the present Western orientation of the Austrian Government and
                    people, and to lend all support to their resistance to Soviet pressure.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Soviet objectives and possible courses of action</hi>.</p>
                <p>5. The major Soviet objective in Austria is estimated to be Soviet-Communist
                    control of all Austria to be achieved by preventing establishment of a free,
                    democratic and Western-oriented Austria. A Western-oriented Austria would
                    penetrate the East-West frontier by a salient extending eastward to the
                    Hungarian border and permit denial to the Soviets of the Vienna communications
                    center. If the Soviets are unable to achieve their major objective they may <pb
                        facs="0405" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/> consider partition as a secondary
                    objective since it would maintain the East-West frontier substantially
                    unchanged. The aggressiveness with which the Soviets will seek to attain either
                    their major or secondary objective in Austria will be determined primarily by
                    their estimate of Western policy with respect to Europe as a whole and
                    secondarily by their estimate of the strength of Western policy with respect to
                    Austria.</p>
                <p>6. In terms of these objectives the Soviet authorities are most likely to pursue
                    one or more of the following courses of action: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To delay conclusion of the Treaty in order to obtain better terms or
                            to convince the present Austrian Government that it must conclude a
                            bilateral settlement with the Soviet Government granting a privileged
                            position to the latter as the price for the conclusion of the treaty and
                            withdrawal of occupation forces.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To intimidate the Austrian Government by kidnappings, recalcitrant
                            action in the Allied Council or other devices, with a view to weakening
                            its authority, or seeking its overthrow and replacement by a group
                            favorable to the Soviet Union.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To establish a rump government in the Eastern zone which would claim
                            authority over all Austria.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To take military or administrative action either to force the
                            withdrawal of Western forces from Vienna or to partition Austria. Such
                            action might take the following forms: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>A general move in Europe involving a simultaneous action in
                                    Vienna and Berlin to bar Western access in violation of existing
                                    agreements.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Local action in Austria involving a closing of the Eastern
                                    zone at the demarcation lines, thus barring the shipment both of
                                    supplies for the Western forces in Vienna and Austrian supplies
                                    originating outside the Eastern zone.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Prohibition of the shipment of supplies for the Western
                                    (forces in Vienna across the Eastern zone to Vienna.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>The barring of Western access to Vienna and the taking of such
                                    action in Vienna which would prevent the present unified control
                                    of all sectors of the city by the Austrian authorities.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To maintain the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in Austria, but
                            through political devices to attempt Communist infiltration of the
                            Government with a view to the ultimate imposition of a Soviet-controlled
                            government over the whole of Austria.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">United States and Soviet capabilities in Austria</hi>.</p>
                <p>7. By reason both of continued military occupation and their refusal to conclude
                    the Treaty, the Soviet Union is in a position to prevent the fulfillment of the
                    U.S. policy objective of reestablishing an independent Austria.</p>
                <p>8. If the Soviets continue for a long period to refuse to conclude the Treaty, it
                    will be increasingly difficult to prevent Soviet pressure on the Austrian
                    Government to sign a bilateral agreement with the Soviet Union as the ultimate
                    price for obtaining Soviet acceptance <pb facs="0406" n="390" xml:id="pg_390"/>
                    of the Treaty. Similarly, it will be increasingly difficult to convince the
                    Austrian Government that it should not sign a bilateral agreement as a desperate
                    gamble to secure the withdrawal of the Soviet military forces. Such an agreement
                    would in all probability nullify the guarantees of Austrian independence already
                    obtained in the agreed articles of the Treaty and would make Western support of
                    Austria difficult in the post-Treaty period.</p>
                <p>9. The United States cannot prevent Soviet attempts to intimidate the Austrian
                    Government or stop the threats against Government leaders in the Eastern zone as
                    long as Soviet military forces are present in Austria.</p>
                <p>10. The United States could not prevent the Soviet authorities establishing a
                    rump government in the Eastern zone. In the event it became impossible for the
                    Austrian Government to remain in Vienna, it would in all probability move to the
                    Western provinces and continue to claim authority over all Austria.</p>
                <p>11. While the United States could not prevent the Soviets taking administrative
                    or military action to close the Eastern zone at the demarcation lines (<gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 63/1, “United States Policy in the Event of a
                    Blockade of Vienna,” approved by the President on February 17, 1950) in order to
                    blockade Vienna completely the Soviet forces would be required to stop all
                    Austrian transportation of supplies to the city including those originating in
                    the Eastern zone or crossing the Eastern zone from the West and from overseas. A
                    complete blockade would, therefore, present the Soviets with formidable
                    political, economic and military problems. It is not likely that they will
                    attempt such action. It is in the United States interest to remain in Vienna in
                    the face of any threat of a Soviet blockade. The withdrawal of Western forces
                    would mean the abandonment of Vienna to the Soviet military forces, and would
                    constitute a partition of Austria, thus marking a significant political victory
                    for the Soviets. Withdrawal of Western forces in the face of a Soviet threat
                    would mark a major advance of Soviet military control in Europe and would
                    endanger our security interest in Central Europe as well as in Italy and
                    Yugoslavia. <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>In the event that the Eastern zone were completely blocked and
                            Austrian as well as Western supplies barred from Vienna, the United
                            States could not in all probability maintain United States forces at
                            their present level (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 63/1). If all
                            efforts fail to break this blockade, it may be impossible to remain in
                            Vienna, but the course of action of the United States should be
                            determined in the light of general U.S. policy designed to meet the
                            Soviet threat and of circumstances then prevailing.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>In the event that only Western supplies were barred from the city, our
                            forces in Vienna could be supplied by an airlift with great difficulty
                            for a short time in order to strengthen attempts to break the blockade
                            by diplomatic means.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0407" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/>
                <p>12. In view of the lack of success of the Communist Party in the Austrian
                    elections of 1945 and 1949, the Soviets would apparently have little opportunity
                    in the immediate future of increasing Communist strength in Austria by normal
                    political methods.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Courses of action open to the United States</hi>
                </p>
                <p>13. It is in the U.S. interest to continue to participate in the occupation of
                    Austria, pursuant to existing international agreements, and to bring all
                    possible pressure to bear on the Soviet Government to secure the conclusion and
                    implementation of the Treaty. Furthermore, it is in the U.S. interest to
                    preserve the authority of the Austrian Government against Soviet pressure, to
                    prevent a partition of the country, and to continue to seek a Four-Power formula
                    for the reestablishment of Austrian independence. <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>In the face, however, of Soviet policy in the Treaty negotiations and
                            the possible threat of Soviet action in Austria, it is urgent that the
                            Western powers maintain the initiative, both to make Soviet unilateral
                            action more difficult and to contribute to the progressive solution of
                            the Austrian question.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>It is necessary to focus upon the Soviet Union full blame for the
                            continuing failure to obtain a Treaty. The Western Powers must formulate
                            and carry out a policy which will progressively demonstrate that all
                            efforts are being made to secure Austrian independence, while at the
                            same time, no step is being taken which can be interpreted as weakening
                            the authority of the Allied Council. Measures in such a policy might
                            include: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Appointing civilian High Commissioners as authorized in the
                                    Control Machinery Agreement.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Relinquishing occupation controls which do not threaten either
                                    the security of the Austrian Government or the occupation
                                    forces.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Proposing a Four-Power Declaration, utilizing certain agreed
                                    articles of the Treaty, as a substitute for the Treaty. Any step
                                    taken should be based on firm tripartite agreement.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>14. The maintenance of Austrian unity is important to the United States. Soviet
                    action to destroy that unity or to prevent the maintenance of our forces in
                    Vienna must be carefully examined in the light of the political and military
                    threat to the security interests of the United States. Such a threat would
                    justify the United States taking strong diplomatic steps and effective
                    retaliatory measures, and urging other Western Powers to take parallel
                    action.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>15. The United States should continue to participate in the Treaty negotiations
                    and make every effort to bring them to a satisfactory conclusion.</p>
                <pb facs="0408" n="392" xml:id="pg_392"/>
                <p>16. The United States should continue the action currently being taken to
                    implement the conclusions of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 38/4, “Future
                    Courses of United States Action with Respect to Austria”, approved November 18,
                    1949, with respect to the Austrian security forces.</p>
                <p>17. Unless compelled by radically altered circumstances the United States should
                    not undertake to enter into a separate Treaty with Austria without Soviet
                    participation.</p>
                <p>18. The United States should make every effort to prevent a partition of Austria
                    and, in the absence of a Four-Power Treaty or agreement establishing Austrian
                    sovereignty, should continue to participate in the Allied Council with a view to
                    extending the authority and jurisdiction of the Austrian Government and reducing
                    unnecessary controls exercised by the occupation forces.</p>
                <p>19. The United States should make every effort to forestall and prevent
                    unilateral Soviet action either forcing a Western withdrawal from Vienna or
                    effecting a partition of Austria, should take all feasible measures to counter
                    any Soviet move designed to achieve these objectives, and urge other Western
                    Powers to take parallel action. Such measures might include, <hi rend="italic"
                        >inter alia:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Insist in the Allied Council on strict adherence to the Control
                            Machinery Agreement respecting the authority of the Austrian Government
                            and the rights of the occupying powers as established in existing
                            agreements.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>If the Soviets impose restrictions on Western access to the city, the
                            United States should, in cooperation with the British and French, supply
                            their personnel in Vienna, as well as such minimum requirements for the
                            city as possible, by an airlift as an emergency measure for a limited
                            period. Such action should be considered in the light of recommendations
                            by the Joint Chiefs of Staff at that time. (<gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss> 63/1 contains more detailed consideration of this
                            problem.)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>20. Conversations should be initiated at an early date with the British and
                    French to discuss the nature and timing of future action with respect to
                    Austria. In these conversations:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. The United States should propose: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The publication of a record of the Treaty negotiations to date. Such
                            publication should be appropriately timed in order not to disrupt any
                            current or prospective negotiations on the Treaty.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The preparation of a draft Four-Power Declaration reestablishing
                            Austrian independence which could be proposed if agreement cannot be
                            reached in the present Treaty negotiations. Soviet participation in the
                            proposed declaration would be required in order to provide for the
                            withdrawal of Soviet military forces and to avoid a partition of
                            Austria. A Declaration of this type might contain the following
                            provisions: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Reestablishment of Austria’s independence within her frontiers
                                    as they existed on January 1, 1938. (An agreed Article in the
                                    Treaty.)</item>
                                <pb facs="0409" n="393" xml:id="pg_393"/>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Withdrawal of all occupation forces within 90 days after the
                                    coming into force of the agreement. (An agreed Article in the
                                    Treaty.)</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>No reparations shall be exacted from Austria. (An agreed
                                    Article in the Treaty.)</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Each of the occupying Powers shall relinquish to Austria all
                                    German assets and war booty held or claimed by them in Austria.
                                    (Contrary to agreed Article 35 of the Treaty.)</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Four-Power agreement to respect the independence of Austria
                                    within her pre-1938 borders. (An agreed Article in the
                                    Treaty.)</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                <item>A declaration of the participating powers favoring the
                                    admission of Austria to the United Nations Organization. (An
                                    amplification of the agreed preamble of the Treaty.)</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>If the Soviets would not accept paragraph (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) in the
                    foregoing plan, the agreed text of Article 35 could form part of the declaration
                    as the settlement of the German assets question. Our position, however, would be
                    strengthened in terms of world opinion if such a proposal were not included.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>(3) The taking of immediate steps in Austria to relieve the burden of
                        occupation while retaining sufficient controls not only to assure security
                        of the Austrian Government and of U.S. occupation forces but also to prevent
                        additional advantage to USSR occupation forces.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>[The respective positions of the Departments of State and Defense on paragraph 20
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. (4) are as follows. The <gloss target="#t_NSRB1"
                        >NSRB</gloss> has reserved its position on this paragraph.]<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d192fn4">Brackets appear in the source text.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Department of State Position</hi>
                </p>
                <p>20<hi rend="italic">a</hi> (4) “To proceed at a date to be agreed with the
                    British and French and in a manner consistent with the requirements of Austrian
                    security with the appointment by each of the occupying powers of a civilian High
                    Commissioner without prejudice to the present control machinery. If Four-Power
                    agreement cannot be obtained, and consistent with the security requirements, the
                    Western Powers, in concert, should proceed with the appointment of civilian High
                    Commissioners. At the time of the appointment of a U.S. civilian High
                    Commissioner, responsibility for the execution and implementation of U.S. policy
                    in Austria in all fields except those pertaining to military matters will be
                    transferred from the Department of Defense to the Department of State.</p>
                <p>Agreement with the British and French should be obtained on the following
                    requirements respecting the appointment of civilian High Commissioners: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>No break should occur in continuity of authority and operations of the
                            High Commissioners in the present quadripartite Allied Council
                            organization during the transfer from military to civilian
                            authority.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>No situation should be created by the transfer of responsibility which
                            would prevent immediate military action by the <pb facs="0410" n="394"
                                xml:id="pg_394"/> United States or by British and French military
                            authorities, if and when required.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>No impression should be given to the Austrians that they are deprived
                            of military protection by the transfer of responsibility.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>United States implementation of any tripartite decision should be carried out
                    with the closest coordination between the Departments of State and Defense.”</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Department of Defense Position</hi>
                </p>
                <p>20<hi rend="italic">a</hi> (4) “To proceed at a date to be agreed and at a time
                    when the requirements of Austrian security permit with the appointment by each
                    of the occupying powers of a civilian High Commissioner without prejudice to the
                    present control machinery. Then if such Four-Power agreement cannot be obtained,
                    and the security situation permits, the Western Powers, in concert, should
                    proceed with the appointment of civilian High Commissioners. At the time of the
                    appointment of a U.S. civilian High Commissioner, responsibility for the
                    execution and implementation of U.S. policy in Austria in all fields except
                    those pertaining to military matters will be transferred from the Department of
                    Defense to the Department of State. Present security conditions do not permit
                    the change from a military to a civilian High Commissioner at this time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. The United States should further propose for
                    discussion, the formulation of a common tripartite policy on: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Action which can be taken to enable Western forces to remain in Vienna
                            in the event the Soviets prevent Western access to Vienna;</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Action which can be taken in the event the Soviets close the Eastern
                            zone at the demarcation lines to surface traffic;</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Action to be taken in event the Soviets force a partition of Austria
                            with a view to determining the future Western position with respect to
                            Austrian independence; and</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Determination of future action with respect to reference of the
                            Austrian question to the United Nations.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
