<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-01-21T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-01-21T13:00:00-05:00" n="221" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d221">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">663.00/1–1950: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the United States Deputy for Austria at the Council of Foreign
                                Ministers</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Reber</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d221fn1">Repeated to
                                Moscow as 58, Paris as 277, and Vienna as 114.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                                </gloss>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-01-21T13:00:00-05:00">January
                                    21, 1950—1 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>289. <gloss target="#t_Audel1">Audel</gloss> 230. Moscow’s 186 and 197
                            Jan 19<note n="2" xml:id="d221fn2">Not printed, but see footnote 4, <ref target="#pg_437">p. 437</ref>.</note> Although Moscow <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> may have negative results for this
                            immediate phase negots, we consider it to have served useful purpose in
                            crystallizing public opinion on Aust question. Gen reaction places blame
                            squarely on Sovs for delaying Treaty. <hi rend="italic">NY Times</hi>
                            editorial highlights contrast Sov attitude with their Peace Campaign,
                            but stresses necessity avoiding any partition Aust.</p>
                        <p>Our view is that completion Aust Treaty in order secure withdrawal Sov
                            forces shld remain major objective. Consequently no break shld occur in
                            continuity of negots. If it becomes clear Treaty cannot be concluded, we
                            shall consider possible alternative courses of action to supplement our
                            aims in Aust pending opportunity reach final settlement. Announcement
                            these steps will depend on clarification Sov position and developments
                            in Aust in following months.</p>
                        <p>In view these considerations Dept hesitates to endorse your third
                            proposal in <gloss target="#t_Delau1">Delau</gloss> 403, Jan 19.
                            Adjourning discussions without a fixed <pb facs="0457" n="441" xml:id="pg_441"/> date for resumption might leave us in less
                            favorable position than we are at present in negots by providing Sovs
                            opportunity to insist on further concessions on Arts 16 and 27 as price
                            for conclusion of Treaty. It is therefore recommended that alternative
                            two be accepted and that negots be resumed after appropriate interval at
                            fixed date on same basis as they now proceed. Such proposal for
                            adjournment to any date not later than Feb 15 shld be accepted with a
                            statement that interlude will provide Sovs time to conclude Vienna
                            negots and to proceed on previously agreed basis. All possible use shld
                            be made of Gromyko’s statements in this regard. No intimation shld be
                            given at Tues mtg that our action constitutes in any way a break in
                            negots, and maximum onus for necessity of delay shld be placed on
                            Sovs.</p>
                        <p>If at any time while impasse over 48 bis continues Zarubin raises Arts 16
                            or 27 you shld agree discuss them but limit your discussion to making
                            clear that our position on them stands and that we are unwilling to
                            consider further concessions in view of previous Sov assurances that no
                            difficulties wld be encountered on other arts if their position was met
                            on German assets. This is a negotiating position on which we might
                            reconsider our stand on Arts 16 and 27 in event agreement reached on
                            econ arts. Naturally no hint of this shld be given in present phase. We
                            assume Brit and Fr wld be prepared take similar firm position.<note n="3" xml:id="d221fn3">In telegram 107, January 20, not printed,
                                Legation Vienna expressed its opinion that the first alternative was
                                the best since it maintained the pressure on the Soviet Union better
                                than the other two choices (663.001/1–2050). This view was supported
                                by Embassy Moscow in telegram 210, January 21, not printed
                                (663.001/1–2150).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Besides consideration further action that may be taken in event no
                            further progress with Treaty, we are preparing record of negots, <gloss target="#t_Audel1">Audel</gloss> 225, and will inform you when ready
                            for publication.</p>
                        <p>If no further mtgs are held until Feb 15 subsequent <gloss target="#t_instrs1">instrs</gloss> will be sent re Del.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>