<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-04-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="228" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d228">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">663.001/4–650</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">British Secretary
                                    of State for Foreign Affairs</gloss>
                            </hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Bevin</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d228fn1">The source text was an attachment to a
                                memorandum of conversation between Thompson and Bernard A. B.
                                Burrows, Counselor of the British Embassy, dated April 6, not
                                printed (663.001/4–650).</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-04-06">April 6, 1950</date>.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>As Mr. Acheson will recall from the discussions I had with him
                                    and Monsieur Schuman in New York last autumn,<note n="2" xml:id="d228fn2">Regarding the Western Foreign Ministers
                                        discussion of the Austrian Treaty at New York during the
                                        autumn of 1949, see <ref target="frus1949v03#pg_1146">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1146</ref> ff.</note>
                                    I have for some time been concerned at what may happen in
                                    Austria if there is no Treaty. It was for that reason that I
                                    pressed Mr. Acheson and Monsieur Schuman last autumn to agree to
                                    make such concessions in the Treaty negotiations as might be
                                    hoped to secure agreement with the Russians.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Six months have now elapsed, and I am just as much convinced
                                    of the desirability of getting the Soviet out of Austria in the
                                    interest both of European pacification and of the maintenance of
                                    Austria’s will and capacity to survive as an independent State.
                                    I think that both Mr. Acheson and Monsieur Schuman are in
                                    agreement with me on this, and on the desirability of completing
                                    the Treaty as soon as possible. Unfortunately the Russians do
                                    not appear to be willing to conclude the Treaty at present. The
                                    result is that the efforts we made last year to reach agreement
                                    have so far proved vain.</item>
                                <pb facs="0467" n="451" xml:id="pg_451"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Five articles remain outstanding—16, 27, 42, 48 and 48–bis.
                                    The Soviet Deputy has repeatedly said that he cannot change his
                                    position on articles 42 and 48 until the questions falling under
                                    48–bis have been settled. Those questions were referred for
                                    study to the Soviet experts last October, and the Soviet
                                    authorities are making no attempt to settle them. So long as
                                    this remains the Soviet attitude there can be no settlement of
                                    Articles 42 and 48 on the basis of the Western texts. Moreover
                                    it is now by no means to be assumed that the Soviet would settle
                                    42 and 48 on our terms even when 48–bis is out of the way. The
                                    Soviet attitude in regard to Articles 16 and 27 is less clear.
                                    Last November Zarubin indicated that the Soviet might give way
                                    on Article 27 if they got satisfaction on 16 and 48–bis as well
                                    as 35. Since then the Soviet position seems to have hardened,
                                    and there is no certainty that our acceptance of their article
                                    16(5) would lead to withdrawal of their objectionable clause in
                                    Article 27.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>His Majesty’s Government’s position in regard to these four
                                    articles is as follows. We consider that the effect of accepting
                                    the Soviet 16(5) is less serious than has been suggested. We are
                                    prepared to agree to it. While we do not like the Soviet
                                    addition to Article 27 we would in the last resort be prepared
                                    to accept it as part of a final settlement. I cannot feel that
                                    the Russian addition to Article 27 is of intrinsic importance in
                                    regard to Austria’s future ability to protect herself within the
                                    Treaty limits. Austria can only be made able to protect herself
                                    against a putsch and local disorders, and not against invasion,
                                    and for this the assistance of foreign technicians in her
                                    aviation etc. is not indispensable. In any case Article 27 will
                                    not prevent Austria from sending her technicians to study
                                    abroad. On articles 42 and 48 we are examining whether
                                    agreements could be reached with the Austrian Government outside
                                    the Treaty which would make it possible for us, if necessary, to
                                    accept the Soviet texts. I am hopeful that it will prove
                                    possible to make such agreements.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>As I understand it, the attitude of the United States and the
                                    French Governments has hitherto been that, subject to
                                    satisfactory arrangements proving possible outside the Treaty
                                    for articles 42 and 48, they would be prepared to accept the
                                    Russian texts for the four articles if this was necessary in
                                    order to get agreement, and if such acceptance would in fact
                                    secure agreement on the whole Treaty text. (I appreciate that
                                    the United States Government are not themselves interested in
                                    Article 48 in which for us substantial sums are involved.) I
                                    understand this point of view and have not hitherto wished to
                                    press the United States and French Governments to make further
                                    concessions on the Treaty if these were unlikely to lead to
                                    agreement on the whole text. In the last three months I have,
                                    however, received repeated and strong representations from the
                                    Austrian Government to get these four articles settled, even
                                    though this would not lead to <pb facs="0468" n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/> full agreement. I have been bound to give
                                    consideration to these representations. The Austrians arguments
                                    are as follows:— <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>If the Russians were to decide to settle questions
                                            under Article 48-bis, the responsibility for holding up
                                            the Treaty would be thrown on the Western Powers if they
                                            were then unable to accept the Soviet texts of 42 and
                                            48. The Western Powers could be made to appear as
                                            blocking the Treaty for the sake of their restitution
                                            and financial claims on Austria.</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>So long as the Western Powers insist on including
                                            clauses in the Treaty for the restoration of their
                                            property and for the payment of pre-Anschluss loans, the
                                            Soviet are able to pose as protecting Austria from
                                            Western claims.</item>
                                        <label>(3)</label>
                                        <item>If there is to be no early Treaty Austrian morale must
                                            be fortified, and the best way for the Western Powers to
                                            do this is by making progress with the Treaty, by
                                            settling these four articles and so giving evidence of
                                            their determination to do everything that lies in their
                                            power to complete the Treaty.</item>
                                        <label>(4)</label>
                                        <item>If these four articles could be settled it would be
                                            clear to the whole world, as it is not at present, that
                                            it is the Soviet alone who are holding up the
                                            Treaty.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>I am impressed by these arguments and in particular by the
                                    argument about the effect on Austrian morale and by the
                                    awkwardness of the situation which would arise if the Soviet
                                    were to settle 48-bis while we were unready to settle 42 and 48.
                                    I agree that there is no certainty that the settlement of these
                                    four articles would lead to the completion of the Treaty, but
                                    their settlement would undoubtedly put the Russians on the spot,
                                    and it is at least conceivable that the Soviet Government might
                                    then be led to complete the Treaty, relying on delays in
                                    signature and ratification if they wished further to delay its
                                    early implementation. (In this connexion it may perhaps be
                                    significant that M. Gromyko recently informed the Austrian
                                    representative in Moscow that article 48-bis was quite
                                    unimportant in comparison with the issues involved in the other
                                    four outstanding articles and that while he could foresee no
                                    solution of article 48-bis so long as the deputies made no
                                    progress on the latter he anticipated no difficulty on it once
                                    the other four articles had been settled.) I recognise the
                                    importance of ensuring that outside arrangements can be made
                                    with the Austrians which will satisfactorily protect our claims
                                    and those of other United Nations nations for the restoration of
                                    their property and the payment of pre-Anschluss loans. It is
                                    perhaps arguable that the Soviet would make these outside
                                    arrangements an excuse for delaying the conclusion of the
                                    Treaty, but I feel that it would be difficult for them to hold
                                    up the Treaty just because the Austrian Government chose
                                    voluntarily to meet United Nations claims which they are already
                                    in principle prepared to settle. Such a course would make Soviet
                                    obstruction too obvious.</item>
                                <pb facs="0469" n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>I am therefore myself in favour of getting these four articles
                                    settled if we can, and my hope is that at our May meeting<note n="3" xml:id="d228fn3">Documentation on the London Foreign
                                        Ministers meeting, May 11–13, is in <ref target="frus1950v03#pg_828">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 828</ref> ff.</note> we shall be able
                                    to make progress on some of these matters which, like the
                                    Austrian Treaty negotiations, impede our plans for building up
                                    our position and for the consolidation of Western Europe. But I
                                    recognise the difficulties which some of these four articles
                                    represent for American and French opinion, and I do not want now
                                    to ask Mr. Acheson to make concessions which might cause
                                    difficulties for him with Congress. I would, however, ask him to
                                    reflect on this Austrian problem in the light of the
                                    considerations which I have mentioned above, in the hope that
                                    between now and May he may be able to make it possible for us to
                                    make progress with the Austrian Treaty at our meeting.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>