<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-08-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="24" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d24">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">S/S–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            Files: Lot 63 D 351: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 78 Series<note n="1" xml:id="d24fn1">Lot 63 D 351 is a serial master file of the
                                National Security Council documents and correspondence and related
                                Department of State memoranda for the years 1947–1961, as maintained
                                by the Executive Secretariat of the Department of State.</note>
                        </note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Legal Adviser</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Fisher</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="2" xml:id="d24fn2">This memorandum was drafted by Charles
                                E. Rogers of the Office of British Commonwealth and Northern
                                European Affairs and was concurred in by James C. H. Bonbright,
                                Acting Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs. The
                                ribbon-copy source text was attached to a memorandum of August 23
                                from Ambassador at Large Philip C. Jessup to the Secretary of State,
                                not printed, which suggested that the Secretary read this memorandum
                                and the attached Department of State paper in advance of the
                                National Security Council meeting of August 24. Jessup indicated
                                that he had in mind discussing the question of the treatment of
                                Finnish ships under proposed American port control measures at the
                                Secretary’s briefing meeting prior to the Council meeting. There is
                                no evidence that the Secretary actually saw this memorandum, but it
                                appears clear that it was used in the aforementioned briefing.
                                Regarding the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting of August
                                24, see footnote 8 below.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-08-22">August 22, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Treatment of Finnish Ships under United States
                            Port Control Measures.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 78<note n="3" xml:id="d24fn3">Reference to the Report prepared in the White House Office, <ref target="#pg_41">p. 41</ref>.</note> does not list Finland as a
                            Soviet satellite for purposes of the new Port Control measure. However,
                            a <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> memorandum of August 10 on this
                                subject<note n="4" xml:id="d24fn4">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> recommends that Finnish ships
                            “be restricted as are actual satellite ships or at least be rigorously
                            inspected before being allowed access to our ports”. The reason advanced
                            is that “the USSR is capable of subjecting Finnish ships to its control
                            for whatever purpose it desires”. Although the situation is not clear,
                            it is understood that in the light of this the President has agreed that
                            all Finnish ships shall be inspected.</p>
                        <p>As indicated in the attached memorandum to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, the Department does not agree that the USSR is capable
                            of subjecting Finnish ships to its control short of installing a
                            Communist government by <hi rend="italic">coup</hi> or using overt
                            military measures. Our Legation in Helsinki has analyzed in detail in
                            the attached telegrams<note n="5" xml:id="d24fn5">Under reference here
                                are telegrams 69, August 9; 70, August 10; 83, August 18; 86, August
                                19; and 89, August 22, all from Helsinki, none printed
                                (960e.536/8–950, 960e.536/8–1050, 960e.536/8–1850, 960e.536/8–1950,
                                and 960e.538/8–2250). Copies of these telegrams were subsequently
                                circulated to the National Security Council at the request of the
                                Department of State under cover of a memorandum of August 23 from
                                Council Executive Secretary Lay, not printed (<gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot 61 D
                                167: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 78 Series).</note> the
                            possibilities for the USSR covertly to utilize Finnish ships for
                            unconventional attack against the United States and has concluded, with
                            the concurrence <pb facs="0067" n="51" xml:id="pg_51"/> of the Service
                            Attachés, that there is no greater possibility in the case of Finnish
                            ships than of those of Scandinavian and West European countries. The
                            Legation has urged the danger in terms of undermining the Finnish
                            position of appearing to classify Finland as a satellite state. Such
                            action on our part seems to be contrary to the policy of support we
                            have, with successful results, followed toward Finland since the war.
                            Automatic inspection of Finnish ships would, in view of the contemplated
                            procedures, result in diversion of ships from harbors unsuited for
                            inspection, enforced lighterage, and other measures causing great
                            commercial hardship to the Finns and having the political implications
                            mentioned above.</p>
                        <p>The Finnish Government has already protested both here and in Helsinki
                            against the action of the Philadelphia Customs earlier this month in
                            holding up two Finnish ships fifty miles from port.<note n="6" xml:id="d24fn6">Finnish Chargé Otso Wartiovaara lodged his
                                government’s protest regarding the detention of Finnish ships in
                                meetings with Department of State officers on August 8 and 9 and
                                with Under Secretary of State James C. Webb on August 10. Memoranda
                                of these conversations are included in file 960e.536. Telegram 69,
                                August 9, from Helsinki (see footnote 5, above), reported that
                                Finnish Foreign Minister Ake Henrik Gartz had expressed to Chargé
                                Warren M. Chase in Helsinki the Finnish Government’s concern over
                                the examination of Finnish ships in American ports for the presence
                                of atomic bombs, and he requested the removal or at least the
                                alleviation of the new procedure. Foreign Minister Gartz described
                                Finland’s disappointment at being treated in the matter as a
                                satellite of the Soviet Union, and he also expressed the belief that
                                the new procedure would create difficulties for Finnish exports.
                                (960e.536/8–950)</note> The Finns pointed out the disruptive effects
                            on their trade and reserved their rights under our Treaty of Friendship,
                            Commerce and Consular Eights. The two ships were later released and in
                            view of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 78 we have in confidence
                            indicated to the Finns that our new Port Control measures would not
                            discriminate against Finnish ships.</p>
                        <p>We are presently examining with our Legation in Helsinki the
                            possibilities of obtaining with the help of the Finnish Government
                            advance information concerning future Finnish ship sailings to the
                            United States which would increase the effectiveness of our security
                                measures.<note n="7" xml:id="d24fn7">Telegram 63, August 21, to
                                Helsinki, not printed, indicated that the contemplated preclearance
                                procedures involved informal arrangements with the Finnish
                                Government allowing for the obtaining of information on ships
                                departing for the United States (960e.536/8–1950). Telegram 93,
                                August 23, from Helsinki, not printed, reported that a procedure
                                along the lines outlined above could probably be arranged with the
                                Finnish Government (960e.536/8–2350). At the request of the
                                Department of State, copies of these two telegrams were circulated
                                to the National Security Council under cover of a memorandum of
                                August 24 by the Council Executive Secretary Lay, not printed
                                    (<gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot 61 D 167: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 78 Series).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is recommended that you present the attached memorandum on this
                            subject at the National Security Council meeting on Thursday, <pb facs="0068" n="52" xml:id="pg_52"/> August 24 as a matter of urgency
                            with a view to having Finnish ships treated on a non-discriminatory
                            basis as among non-satellite countries.<note n="8" xml:id="d24fn8">At
                                its 66th Meeting on August 24, in which President Truman
                                participated, the National Security Council noted the President’s
                                decision, pursuant to the consideration of the problem of port
                                security at the Council’s 64th Meeting on August 10 (see footnote 1,
                                    <ref target="#pg_41">p. 41</ref>), that arrangements should be
                                made with the Finnish Government for preclearance control of Finnish
                                ships destined for U.S. ports, but that otherwise Finnish ships
                                should be treated as were the ships of all Other nations except the
                                U.S.S.R. and the Eastern European satellite states (National
                                Security Council Action 349: S/S–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                (Miscellaneous) Files: Lot 66 D 95: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records of Action).</note>
                        </p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Paper Prepared in the Department of
                                    State</hi><note n="9" xml:id="d24fn9">Another copy of this
                                    memorandum included in the <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot
                                    61 D 167: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 78 Series,
                                    indicated that it was drafted by Charles E. Rogers of the Office
                                    of British Commonwealth and Northern European Affairs.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-08-22">August 22,
                                        1950</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Problem</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>To clarify the treatment of Finland in proposed measures of United
                                States port control.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Analysis</hi>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>It has been suggested that Finnish ships be restricted in the
                                    same manner as satellite ships or at least be rigorously
                                    inspected before being allowed access to our ports with the
                                    result that Finnish ships would, in fact, be singled out. The
                                    reason given for this recommendation has been that the USSR is
                                    capable of subjecting Finnish ships to its control for whatever
                                    purpose it desires.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>In view of the difficulties of a foolproof inspection and the
                                    proposed procedures to carry out this inspection, automatic
                                    inspection of Finnish boats whether or not they have docked at
                                    satellite ports may involve their exclusion from harbors that do
                                    not have an area suited for inspection and in some instances the
                                    use of lighters for unloading in other harbors. This would be in
                                    violation of our Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Consular
                                    Rights with Finland<note n="10" xml:id="d24fn10">Reference is to
                                        the United States-Finnish Treaty of Friendship, Commerce,
                                        and Consular Rights, signed February 13, 1934 (49 Stat.
                                        2659; <gloss target="#t_TS1">TS</gloss> 868: 152 <gloss target="#t_UNTS1">UNTS</gloss> 45).</note> and would
                                    cause considerable hardship to Finland both politically and
                                    commercially.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>There is no evidence that there exists any control over
                                    Finnish ships by the USSR or that there exists such capability
                                    by the USSR short of overt measures. While Finland is prevented
                                    from aligning itself with the West due to Treaty obligations and
                                    proximity to the USSR, Finland is an independent country with a
                                    freely elected parliamentary government friendly to the free
                                    world. There are no Communists <pb facs="0069" n="53" xml:id="pg_53"/> in the cabinet and civil rights are
                                    safeguarded. The USSR exercises no control or surveillance over
                                    internal Finnish affairs and could not exercise control over
                                    Finnish shipping unless by internal <hi rend="italic">coup</hi>
                                    installing a Communist government or by direct military or naval
                                    action. A <hi rend="italic">coup</hi> is regarded as very
                                    unlikely, and Soviet military-naval action would probably occur
                                    only as a prelude to general war.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>This Government since the war has successfully endeavored to
                                    support Finnish independence and forestall encroachments by the
                                    Soviet Union. To that end we have assisted substantially in
                                    Finnish economic recovery. Finland has maintained a very stiff
                                    front toward the USSR as is indicated by the limited scope of
                                    the Soviet-Finnish Treaty of Mutual Aid<note n="11" xml:id="d24fn11">The reference here is to the Treaty of
                                        Friendship, Cooperation, and Mutual Assistance between the
                                        U.S.S.R. and Finland, signed April 30, 1948.</note> which is
                                    an example of successful resistance to Soviet demands by
                                    Finland. The treatment of Finland in this case as if it were a
                                    satellite would tend to undermine the strong Finnish will to
                                    resist and would have a very damaging effect on Finnish-American
                                    relations, as well as on our relations with other Scandinavian
                                    countries.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>While the top ranks of the Finnish Seamen’s Union are heavily
                                    penetrated by Communists, this is balanced by several other
                                    factors, including the facts that the Union leader is strongly
                                    independent and the rank and file in overseas shipping are
                                    believed mostly non-Communist. The Social Democrats are stronger
                                    among the dockworkers and there are no Communists among the
                                    masters or other ships officers on Finnish ships. An official of
                                    the dominant and tightly organized Social Democratic Party has
                                    told the American Legation in Helsinki that his organization can
                                    prevent sabotage materials from being smuggled aboard Finnish
                                        ships.<note n="12" xml:id="d24fn12">The incident referred to
                                        here was reported upon in telegram 70, August 10, from
                                        Helsinki, not printed (see footnote 5, above).</note> The
                                    Finnish Foreign Minister has offered to consider proposing to
                                    his Government that Finnish ships en route to the United States
                                    not be permitted to call at intervening ports. It is apparent
                                    that there is not any greater possibility for Soviet utilization
                                    of Finnish ships covertly for purposes harmful to the United
                                    States than for Soviet utilization of other Scandinavian or West
                                    European ships.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Finnish ships are not above suspicion. Special suspicion,
                                    however, does not attach to them by mere reason of their being
                                    Finnish or coming from Finnish ports.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Directives issued to implement Public Law 679 should refrain
                                    from making mandatory special treatment of Finnish ships; and
                                    these directives should call for non-discriminatory treatment of
                                    Finnish <pb facs="0070" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/> ships, on a
                                    basis similar to that applied to other non-satellite flag ships
                                    proceeding from European ports.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>The Department of State, through the American Legation,
                                    Helsinki, should devise, with the help of the Finnish Government
                                    and other appropriate groups in Finland, informal arrangements
                                    providing maximum possible security checks in Finnish
                                    ports.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>