<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-01-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="258" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">123 Heath, Donald R.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Bulgarian Legation</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d258fn1">At his meeting with President Truman
                                on the afternoon of January 19, Secretary of State Dean Acheson took
                                up the matter of the request contained in this communication: <p>“I
                                    reported this request to the President and told him that I
                                    assumed he would now wish us to carry out the procedure which he
                                    authorized at the time of our last communication to the
                                    Bulgarian Government. He thought we should do this.” (Memorandum
                                    by the Secretary of State, January 19, 1950: Secretary’s
                                    Memoranda, Lot 53 D 444, Secretary’s Memoranda—January 1950) Lot
                                    53 D 444 is a comprehensive chronological collection of the
                                    Secretary of State’s memoranda and memoranda of conversation for
                                    the years 1947–1953, as maintained by the Executive Secretariat
                                    of the Department of State.</p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 187</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Note Verbale</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Legation of the People’s Re public of Bulgaria in Washington, D.C has
                            been requested by the Bulgarian Government to notify the State
                            Department of the following:</p>
                        <p>The evidence from the trial of the criminal group of flagrant spies and
                            traitors led by Traicho Rostov, which was planning to overthrow the
                            legally established Powers in Bulgaria, proved before the court that His
                            Excellency, the Plenipotentiary Minister of the United States <pb facs="0521" n="505" xml:id="pg_505"/> in Sofia, Mr. Donald Read
                            Heath, had been in contact with Traicho Kostov and Tzonu Tzontchev,<note n="2" xml:id="d258fn2">Tsonyu Tsonchev, the Governor of the
                                Bulgarian National Bank until his arrest in 1949, was a principal
                                codefendant in the Kostov trial of December 1949.</note> convicted
                            by the Bulgarian Court for treason and espionage, and had allowed
                            himself to take action not in line with his diplomatic functions. By
                            this, he had shown abrupt interference in the interior affairs of the
                            People’s Republic of Bulgaria concerning its sovereignty as well as its
                            National Security.</p>
                        <p>In view of these circumstances, the Bulgarian Government announces to the
                            Government of the United States that it considers its Plenipotentiary
                            Minister in Sofia, Mr. Donald Re ad Heath, as <hi rend="italic">persona
                                non grata</hi> and requests the United States Government for his
                            immediate recall from Bulgaria.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-01-19">January 19,
                                1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>