<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-01T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-01T14:00:00-05:00" n="350" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d350">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">762.00/10–150: Telgram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfort</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-01T20:00:00+01:00">October 1,
                                    1950—8 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2722. <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss>. ReDeptel 2476, September
                            29, repeated Berlin 116.<note n="1" xml:id="d350fn1">Not printed; it
                                reported that the Department of State was inclined to favor the
                                course of action outlined in paragraphs 1–3 of telegram 2624 (same
                                as telegram 49, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>), but was concerned
                                that the letter of transmittal to Chuikov “be phrased in such manner
                                that its sense will not appear to conflict with recent <gloss target="#t_FM1">FM</gloss> decisions, thus giving Germans
                                impression we are trying ride off in two directions simultaneously.”
                                (762.00/9–2750)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Transmitted herein is proposed text letters to Chuikov by individual
                                <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>’s. In interest time and in
                            hope all clearances can be obtained to allow releases October 6 (in
                            order make important West German Saturday issues and Berlin Sunday press
                            and permit solid week of <pb facs="0677" n="661" xml:id="pg_661"/>
                            plugging which deemed especially important if way found to encourage
                            East Germans to register opposition to Soviet Zone elections). Hope
                            Department can approve by morning October 4, that Bonn liaison can
                            arrange for British and French similarly seek clearances, and that
                            Embassies Paris, London and Moscow can initiate talks soonest under this
                            time table.</p>
                        <p>Realize somewhat premature to draft proposed text in view non-receipt
                                <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> letter of transmission
                            (scheduled for October 2), but are proceeding on assumption that (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) transmittal of Bundestag resolution to <gloss target="#t_SCC1">SCC</gloss> will be requested as reported by Bonn
                            and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>
                            request to transmit resolution to UN need not at this stage be involved
                            in our letters to Chuikov (in fact we think it best not to mention or
                            raise UN issue in letter to Chuikov and, assuming we find it possible
                            comply with French and UK desires to forward resolution to UN, believe
                            it preferable to do so somewhat later in order that UN can consider
                            elections in light of event rather than indulge in polemics before
                            elections. Hence, suggest that Bonn liaison inform French and British,
                            as well as Germans, that we view issues as separate but will be prepared
                            discuss matter in package later in week if they will seek clearances on
                            letters to Chuikov and be prepared talk on October 4 or 5).</p>
                        <p>In event Bonn and Frankfort despatches forwarding Bundestag’s resolution
                            and Chancellor’s statement not as yet available in Department, next
                            numbered telegram (2723<note n="2" xml:id="d350fn2">Not printed.</note>)
                            transmits texts of both.</p>
                        <p>Believe proposed text, through somewhat longer than we had originally
                            anticipated, hits most important psychological points which should be
                            made at this time without necessarily reopening offer to discuss
                            all-German elections with <gloss target="#t_SCC1">SCC</gloss>. Perhaps
                            few preliminary observations appropriate.</p>
                        <p>We think it important and desirable to introduce Chancellor’s statement.
                            Similarly, we think it most important carry forward point that <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> only German government entitled
                            to speak for Germany: This intended beat Soviets to punch in event,
                            following elections, they seek through peace treaty or otherwise to
                            convert <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> into spokesman for German
                            people. This point when coupled with our anti-separate peace language in
                            letter of May 25, goes far in cutting ground from under Soviets on
                            separate peace and all-German character of <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> following “legitimation” by elections. Reference to
                            Hitler dictatorship, interjected in belief comparison Soviets with
                            Hitler strikes psychological chord with Germans and hits Soviets in
                            sensitive spot. We think it very important emphasize point that
                            elections will contribute to more definite partition of Germany.</p>
                        <p>Following is text of proposed letters.</p>
                        <pb facs="0678" n="662" xml:id="pg_662"/>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“At the request of the government of the German <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>, I transmit herewith the
                                German text of a resolution of the Bundestag which was adopted
                                September 14, 1950, by all political parties represented therein
                                except the <gloss target="#t_KPD1">KPD</gloss> (Communist Party of
                                West Germany).</p>
                            <p>The resolution represents the preponderant will of the Bundestag and
                                of the <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> which, as you will
                                have learned from the communiqué issued by the Foreign Ministers of
                                the UK, France and the US at New York City on September 19, 1950, is
                                considered by my government, pending the unification of Germany, as
                                the only German government freely and legitimately constituted and,
                                therefore, entitled to speak for Germany or to represent the German
                                people in international affairs.</p>
                            <p>Since its promulgation, the resolution has been extensively endorsed
                                by the free German press and radio as representative of the will of
                                the German people in respect of developments in the Soviet Zone of
                                occupation in Germany. I commend it to the attention of you and of
                                your government as a serious pronouncement by the German people in
                                respect of grave matters affecting their future and that of their
                                country.</p>
                            <p>The resolution should be considered in the context of the Federal
                                Chancellor’s declaration, made on behalf of the Federal Government,
                                on September 14 in connection with the promulgation of the
                                resolution. The declaration reads:</p>
                            <p>(Statement transmitted in our telegram 2723).</p>
                            <p>As in the case of the resolution, there is no question but what the
                                Chancellor’s declaration voices the predominant attitude of the
                                whole of the German people, including those now living in the Soviet
                                Zone.</p>
                            <p>In transmitting these documents to you, I wish to inform you that
                                they reflect the views of my government. In this connection, you
                                will have noted that the Foreign Ministers, in their communiqué of
                                September 19 under reference, noted that the Soviet Union continued
                                to ignore proposals for democratic all-German elections (of the type
                                proposed in my letter to you under date of May 25, 1950, as yet
                                unanswered by you) and that the ‘elections’ now scheduled in the
                                Soviet Zone for October 15 must be designated as both staged and
                                controlled.</p>
                            <p>I must now further inform you that if these ‘elections’ are conducted
                                in the manner which all information now available indicates they
                                will be, they will deny to East Germany the high principle of
                                democratic parliamentary government and ignore the democratic
                                processes under which German unification might become a reality,
                                both of which are objectives to which the Soviet Union is committed
                                under the Potsdam and other international agreements and for the
                                breaching of which the Soviet Union must bear full responsibility.
                                The [procedures] under which these ‘elections’ will be held, which
                                prevent the East German electorate from finding it possible to make
                                many choices between opposing policies and candidates, need only be
                                contrasted with the traditional requisites of free democratic
                                elections as enunciated in my letter of May 25, to establish why
                                neither my government, nor the <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>, nor the German people can recognize them for
                                any more than what they are; a devise to perpetuate in power, under
                                the semblance of legality and legitimacy, a small and unpopular
                                minority <pb facs="0679" n="663" xml:id="pg_663"/> dominated by the
                                Soviet Union. The free world will similarly view these ‘elections’
                                for what they are: a procedure which is reminiscent of the notorious
                                and rejected plebiscite and voting techniques once enforced by the
                                Hitler regime and now characteristic of all authoritarian regimes
                                which fear to trust to the free choice of the people.</p>
                            <p>Under the circumstances, my government cannot recognize these
                                ‘elections’ as capable of conferring on the East German regime
                                either legitimacy or any rightful capacity to represent the German
                                people now living in East Germany.</p>
                            <p>On behalf of my government, I, therefore, emphatically protest the
                                ‘elections’ now scheduled for October 15 in the Soviet Zone, and the
                                results they are intended to accomplish, because they will be
                                neither free nor democratic, because they are in violation of
                                international agreements applicable to the development of democratic
                                institutions in Germany, and because they are certain to contribute
                                to an even more definitive partition of Germany.</p>
                            <p>Because of the obvious interest of the German people in the subject
                                matter of this communication, I shall make a copy of it available to
                                the press following its receipt by you.”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>Bonn for Liaison Office, Berlin for Reber, Stone, Lightner, to be
                            delivered 08:30 a. m., October 2, 1950.</p>
                        <p>Department pass Moscow. Sent <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                            Department 2722, <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss> Bonn 53, <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss> Berlin 186; repeated info Paris
                            222, London 199, Moscow 32.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>