<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States High Commissioner for Germany ( (McCloy) ) to the Acting
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d351</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">351</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-10-03T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-10-03T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-03T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-03T13:00:00-05:00" n="351"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d351">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762A.00/10–350: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfort</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-03T19:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 3, 1950—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2791. For Byroade. <gloss target="#t_PEPCO1">PEPCO</gloss>. Inasmuch as Adenauer
                    letter (Bonn’s 183 October 2 repeated Frankfort 206, Paris 35, London 38, Moscow
                        5<note n="1" xml:id="d351fn1">Not printed; for the text of Adenauer’s
                        letter, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on German Unity</hi> (Frankfort,
                        Office of the U.S. High Commissioner for Germany, 1951), p. 156.</note>)
                    de-emphasizes Bundestag resolution on which proposed letter to Chuikov
                    transmitted <gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 2722 October 1 (repeated
                    Bonn 53, Berlin 186, Paris 222, London 199, Moscow 32) was based, and
                    specifically requests that Federal Republic conditions for all-German elections
                    be forwarded to <gloss target="#t_SCC1">SCC</gloss> via Chuikov, I think
                    Department will agree that we must comply in manner which will not involve US in
                    renewal offer to negotiate with <gloss target="#t_SCC1">SCC</gloss> and,
                    preferably, soonest and if possible before Soviet Zone elections.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, following text proposed in substitution former draft and Bonn
                    Liaison requested pass it to British and French with request <pb facs="0680"
                        n="664" xml:id="pg_664"/> they, if necessary, submit it for clearances in
                    effort adhere to original timetable of release this week-end:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“I refer to my letter of May 25, 1950<note n="2" xml:id="d351fn2">See
                            telegram 121, May 25, <ref target="#pg_641">p. 641</ref>.</note> as yet
                        unacknowledged by you, which informed you of conditions under which the
                        German Federal Republic and my Government would find it possible to join
                        with the Soviet Union in effecting the reunification of Germany through free
                        all-German elections, and transmit herein the translated texts of three
                        documents of recent date which bear on this subject and the relation of free
                        all-German elections to the ‘elections’ now scheduled for October 15, 1950,
                        in the Soviet Zone of occupation.</p>
                    <p>The first document is a resolution of the Bundestag, adopted September 14,
                        1950, by all political parties represented therein except the <gloss
                            target="#t_KPD1">KPD</gloss>, which, among other things, requests the
                        occupation powers to arrange for all-German elections. The second is
                        statement made on the same day by the Federal Chancellor on behalf of the
                        Federal Government, in which it is announced that the Federal Republic will
                        not recognize the validity of the October 15 ‘elections’ in the Soviet Zone.
                        The third is a letter addressed by the Federal Chancellor to the Chairman of
                        the Allied High Commission under date of October 2, 1950, which, with
                        reference to paragraph 2 of the Bundestag’s resolution of September 14 under
                        reference, enumerates the conditions on which the Federal Republic requests
                        the four powers now engaged in the occupation of Germany to agree to effect
                        German reunification through free all-German elections.</p>
                    <p>You will find upon examination that the procedures set forth in the
                        Chancellor’s letter are the same as those enunciated in the Bundestag’s
                        resolution of March 22, 1950, transmitted to you with my letter of May 25,
                        and that they are, therefore, within the context of my letter under
                        reference, procedures acceptable to my government.</p>
                    <p>The Federal Republic is, as you know, a freely elected Government and, as you
                        will have learned from the communiqué issued by the Foreign Ministers of the
                        UK, France and the US at New York City on September 19, 1950, is considered
                        by my government, pending the unification of Germany, as the only German
                        Government freely and legitimately constituted and, consequently, entitled
                        to speak for Germany. The documents transmitted to you with this letter
                        reflect the predominant will of the German people. I, therefore, commend
                        them to your attention and to your government as pronouncements of the
                        German people in respect of grave matters affecting their future and that of
                        their country.</p>
                    <p>You will have noted that the Foreign Ministers, in their communiqué of
                        September 19, stated that the staging of controlled elections of the type
                        now scheduled in the Soviet Zone for October 15 negated the principle of
                        effecting German unification through free all-German elections. The
                        single-list ‘elections’ will deny to East Germany democratic parliamentary
                        government and those democratic processes under which German unification can
                        become reality. The Soviet Union is committed under Potsdam and other
                        international agreements to these objectives and must bear full
                        responsibility for obstructing their accomplishment. The procedures under
                        which these ‘elections’ will be held are in direct contrast with the
                        traditional requisites of free <pb facs="0681" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/>
                        democratic elections as enunciated in the Bundestag’s resolutions of March
                        22 and September 14, and in my letter of May 25. For this reason I and my
                        government, nor the Federal Republic, nor the German people can recognize
                        them as capable of conferring on the East German regime either legitimacy or
                        any claim to represent the German people now living in East Germany.</p>
                    <p>On behalf of my government, I emphatically protest the ‘elections’ now
                        scheduled for October 15 in the Soviet Zone as neither free nor democratic,
                        as contravening international agreements relating to the development of
                        democratic institutions in Germany, and as designed to prevent the
                        unification of Germany.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Reasons for forwarding Adenauer formula bound up in simple logic that
                    Chancellor’s letter asks us to implement our announced position on Germany
                    unification, reiterated in Foreign Ministers communiqué of September 19, and
                    cannot in all probability be kept from press. Refusal to move forward with
                    Federal Republic initiative would thus undermine German faith in our <hi
                        rend="italic">bona fides</hi>, create doubt that propagandist motives rather
                    than political resolve motivated our approach to vital issue of reunification,
                    and leave impression of Allied weakness vis-à-vis Soviet Union. We feel that
                    risks of acceptance now are more minimal than was case with May 25 letter since
                    Soviet offensive not spent in Germany and momentum behind October 15 elections
                    and Sovietization East Germany too great to be brought to halt on this issue.
                    More convincing perhaps is fact that if Soviets want to propose negotiations on
                    this issue way is open under May 25 letter and will remain open under that
                    letter since draft submitted herewith does not make new offer.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d351fn3">The text of this letter was approved in telegram 2567,
                        October 5, to Frankfort, not printed (762A.00/10–350). It was discussed on
                        the same day, along with a British draft, at an informal meeting of the
                        Allied Council, which agreed that the Political Advisers should combine the
                        two versions. The final draft, incorporating the ideas but not the language
                        of the United States text, was cabled to Washington and approved on October
                        6, dated October 9, to be delivered October 10 and published on the 11th.
                        For its text, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on German Unity</hi>,
                        (Frankfort, Office of the U.S. High Commissioner for Germany, 1951), p. 157,
                        or Margaret Carlyle, ed., <hi rend="italic">Documents on International
                            Affairs, 1949–1950</hi> (London, Oxford University Press, 1953), pp.
                        165–166. The minutes of the informal Council meeting are in Bonn Embassy
                        Files, McCloy Project: Lot 311: Box 359: D(50) 2275e. Telegraphic reportage
                        on these discussions is in files 762.00 and 762A.00.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Department pass Moscow; sent Department 2791 Niact, Bonn 55, repeated information
                    Paris 229, London 203, Moscow 33.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
