<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-06T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-06T18:00:00-05:00" n="355" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d355">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">762A.00/12–750: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-07T00:00:00+01:00">December
                                    7, 1950—midnight.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>811. <gloss target="#t_AGSec1">AGSec</gloss> from Slater.<note n="1" xml:id="d355fn1">Joseph E. Slater, U.S. Secretary on the Secretariat
                                of the Allied High Commission for Germany.</note> For Acheson and
                            Byroade. Following summary report secret session <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> Council held Berlin with Poncet
                            (France) McCloy (US) and Kirkpatrick (UK) present re Grotewohl<note n="2" xml:id="d355fn2">Otto Grotewohl, Minister-President of the
                                “German Democratic Republic”.</note> letter to Adenauer proposing
                            all German constitutional assembly (text of which sent <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss> Berlin to Department 786, Frankfort
                            886, Bonn 183, London 90, Paris 166 and Moscow unnumbered <pb facs="0685" n="669" xml:id="pg_669"/> and <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss> Bonn sent Frankfort 397 repeated information
                            Department 354<note n="3" xml:id="d355fn3">Neither printed; for the text
                                of Grotewohl’s letter, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on German
                                    Unity</hi> (Frankfort, Office of the U.S. High Commissioner for
                                Germany, 1951), p. 166 or Margaret Carlyle, ed., <hi rend="italic">Documents on International Affairs, 1949–1950</hi> (London,
                                Oxford University Press, 1953), pp. 178–179.</note>).</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Grotewohl letter:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Kirkpatrick opened meeting with statement that UK intelligence had
                            concluded Grotewohl letter part determined attack “Anglo-US imperialism”
                            and attacks Adenauer would cease. Concentration this theme borne out
                            recent poster campaign throughout Germany.</p>
                        <p>Poncet expressed opinion Soviets serious their desire meeting four powers
                            in the hope such meeting would place them better moral position to
                            overcome feeling world public opinion they were aggressors. If West
                            Allies refused such meeting Soviet aim would be still furthered. In his
                            opinion primary Soviet objective to avoid rearmament in and
                            neutralization of Germany. Present feelings Germans follow Noack’s
                                line<note n="4" xml:id="d355fn4">Professor Ulrich Noack, head of the
                                so-called Nauheimer Circle, which advocated German
                                neutrality.</note> and desire avoid “scorched earth” situation
                            Germany, pleased and encouraged Soviets. Soviets were anxious extend
                            guarantee German neutrality and neutralization plus <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> re Oder Neisse border in order calm present worries
                            satellites. In view above Poncet believed necessary give greatest care
                            concerning Adenauer reply Grotewohl letter.</p>
                        <p>We took note of fact that Grotewohl addressed letter to “Federal
                            Government of <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> of Germany for
                            attention of Dr. Adenauer, Fed Chancellor” and signed letter as
                            “Minister-President of <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>”. Both Poncet
                            and Kirkpatrick inclined view it would be wise for Adenauer reply
                            directly Grotewohl and pointed out significance form of address. In
                            their opinion if <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> replied or
                            dictated terms of reply to Adenauer, Communists would claim in
                            propaganda campaign that Adenauer was puppet West Allies and would not
                            fail point out that Grotewohl wrote direct to Adenauer on his own.</p>
                        <p>I stressed that I would like give matter another 72 hours thought before
                            communicating any <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> advice to
                            Adenauer. I agreed that method, form and channel of reply was most
                            important in order avoid pitfalls inherent [in] the situation and that
                            it could serve as propaganda vehicle in support the case of West Allies.
                            (Personally I do not agree with Poncet that Grotewohl letter represented
                            serious Soviet move but rather feel it was merely part of propaganda
                            campaign.) I recommended that any reply should urge free elections
                            according West concept.</p>
                        <p>We all agreed since Chinese success in Korea there was general
                            disposition among certain elements in West Germany to examine the
                            Grotewohl letter most carefully rather than turn it down flat.</p>
                        <pb facs="0686" n="670" xml:id="pg_670"/>
                        <p>There seemed to be general agreement that the Germans to whom letter has
                            appeal do not fully comprehend that the reactivation Control Council
                            would again bring into operation Soviet veto which would involve
                            continuation Allied controls. Thus interim period to which Grotewohl
                            referred might be an indefinite extension control period.</p>
                        <p>Kirkpatrick informed us that Schumacher told him that he was “of two
                            minds” concerning note. He did not know whether outright refusal should
                            be given or more general approach be adopted.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion we agreed <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> political
                            advisors should commence at once formulation of proposed line which
                                <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> could communicate Adenauer.
                            Adenauer will be notified tomorrow by Poncet of Council’s first reaction
                            and that the Council would do its best consult with him and keep him up
                            to date with its thinking. In general we agreed that we should be in
                            position by next Thursday to give Adenauer our thoughts this matter. In
                            meantime I hope Reber can bring from Paris the thinking of group
                            drafting reply to Soviet note.<note n="5" xml:id="d355fn5">For further
                                documentation on the Soviet note of November 3, proposing the
                                convocation of the Council of Foreign Ministers, see <ref target="#pg_902">pp. 902</ref> ff.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Deteriorating German and European
                                morale:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I took occasion underline rapidly deteriorating German and European
                            morale resulting from the present period of indecision which was further
                            aggravated by Korean reverses. I stated it was <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss>’s responsibility come forward at once with
                            constructive solution whole German problem and not wait upon action of
                            the governments. I predicted the collapse of the Schuman Plan,
                            frustration all efforts build reasonable defense, greater success in the
                            Communist infiltration program and growth of “neutralism” unless
                            something done rapidly. I continued that if no other forum was presently
                            available deal effectively with these matters it was obviously my
                            responsibility to do so. (I had in mind that something along lines our
                            “package program” should be put forward by <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss>, although I did not refer to it specifically.)
                            Kirkpatrick enthusiastically agreed but Poncet’s attitude indicated he
                            was not disposed or in position to take such “free flight”.</p>
                        <p>Kirkpatrick urged me join him in recommendation that Spofford and Millar
                            (if not Alphand)<note n="6" xml:id="d355fn6">Charles M. Spofford, Sir
                                Frederick R. Hoyer-Millar, and Hervé Alphand, United States, United
                                Kingdom, and French Deputy Representatives on the North Atlantic
                                Council.</note> come Germany during December recess as he felt it
                            was essential they gain more direct impression the atmosphere here. He
                            continued that any group which could seriously entertain Dutch
                                proposal<note n="7" xml:id="d355fn7">For documentation on the Dutch
                                proposal for German participation in the European defense structure,
                                see <ref target="frus1950v03#pg_1">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff.</note> was far wide of mark and
                            therefore it was essential that they be reoriented.</p>
                        <pb facs="0687" n="671" xml:id="pg_671"/>
                        <p>Both Kirkpatrick and Poncet also extremely critical the announcement out
                            of London which stated the agreement reached re German rearmament took
                            form of series of restrictions to be imposed on German participation. It
                            is fatal in my judgment, to approach Germany with announcement of what
                            she can’t do. What must be done, if we are to be successful, is merely
                            to announce general understandings have been reached on range of German
                            contributions and that further decisions can only be made after
                            consultation with Germans. If the idea grows that all we do is transmit
                            through Germans a predetermined set of restrictions, Adenauer can never
                            be expected carry out affirmative program.</p>
                        <p>Department pass Moscow; sent Department 811, repeated priority
                            information Frankfort 915, Paris 175, London 95, Moscow 104.</p>
                        <p>Frankfort eyes only King (no distribution); Paris for Bruce, please pass
                            Reber; London for Holmes, please pass Colonel Gerhardt; Moscow for
                                Kirk.<note n="8" xml:id="d355fn8">James E. King, Jr., Executive
                                Secretary of the Office of the U.S. High Commissioner for Germany;
                                David K. E. Bruce, Ambassador to France; Samuel Reber, U.S. Deputy
                                for Austria at the Council of Foreign Ministers; Alan G. Kirk,
                                Ambassador to the Soviet Union.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>