<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting United States High Commissioner for Germany ( (Hays) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d381</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">381</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-09-01T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-09-01T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-01T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-01T10:00:00-05:00" n="381"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d381">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762A.00/9–150: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hays</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d381fn1">McCloy was in Washington for consultations on
                        Germany.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfort</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-09-01T16:00:00+01:00"
                            >September 1, 1950—4 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1864. High Commission met yesterday with Adenauer in executive session<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d381fn2">The executive session followed the 38th meeting of the
                        Council of the Allied High Commission for Germany at Bonn-Petersberg on
                        August 31, the minutes of which are in Bonn Embassy Files, McCloy Project:
                        Lot 311: Box 358: D(50) 2086b.</note> and asked him to clarify his memo in
                    regard to security measures. Adenauer stated that he was fearful of
                    possibilities after October election<note n="3" xml:id="d381fn3">For
                        documentation on the October 15 elections in the Soviet Zone, see <ref
                            target="#pg_942">pp. 942</ref> ff.</note> that Eastern Germany would be
                    set up as satellite country with fictitious independent powers, that <hi
                        rend="italic">Volkspolizei</hi> would be developed into an important combat
                    force and that East German Government would thereafter attack West Germany with
                    the object of unifying all Germany under East German regime. He asked whether
                    High Commission was able to give him positive assurances that in such a
                    situation Allied forces would oppose the <hi rend="italic">Volkspolizei</hi>. He
                    was informed that the Governments had already declared that their forces in
                    Germany would resist attack from whatever source, including attack by <hi
                        rend="italic">Volkspolizei</hi>. (It might be helpful in this connection if
                    Ministers at forthcoming meeting could reiterate clear statement of this
                    position to avoid any misunderstanding among Germans.)</p>
                <p>Adenauer then stressed importance of psychological effect upon <hi rend="italic"
                        >Volkspolizei</hi> if they were opposed by not only Allied forces but also
                    by Western German forces and stated that if adequate German forces were
                    established to counter <hi rend="italic">Volkspolizei</hi> he believed danger of
                    an attack from a satellite Eastern German Government might be averted. This was
                    the major basis of his demand for a Federal police force. He also stressed the
                    need for a Federal police force to combat Communism including <gloss
                        target="#t_FDJ1">FDJ</gloss> and Communist inspired strikes. In his opinion,
                    latter will increase. He cited Frankfort building strike as first example and
                    alleged that Frankfort police are not affording adequate protection to workers
                    who wish to remain on the job.</p>
                <p>Discussion developed that Adenauer desires Federal police force with sufficient
                    strength and type of equipment. He considered external security consisted of
                    defense against Soviet aggression but that internal security included protection
                    against any German threat, including that from East Zone. Consequently he was
                    unwilling to separate his police needs for internal security and his need for
                    force to oppose an attack from the <hi rend="italic">Volkspolizei</hi>.</p>
                <p>We inquired re political support for amendment to the constitution to permit the
                    establishment of the type and kind of Federal police <pb facs="0731" n="715"
                        xml:id="pg_715"/> force which he envisaged. The Chancellor claimed that he
                    had the support of three coalition parties and the <gloss target="#t_SPD1"
                        >SPD</gloss>. He hoped to gain support of other smaller parties later. He
                    admitted that minister presidents of the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> were
                    opposed at present to this concept but he hoped to be able to convince them that
                    such amendment was necessary and gain their support.<note n="4" xml:id="d381fn4"
                        >Initial planning by the Germans for the police force had begun on August 4
                        at a meeting attended by representatives of the Western occupation powers.
                        At this meeting a general proposal was made and subsequently discussed with
                        the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> Interior Ministers, who raised various
                        objections and the necessity to amend Article 91 of the Basic Law. By
                        September 1 agreement had been reached only that the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Laender</hi> police must be reorganized to strengthen the powers of the
                        Interior Ministers and to eliminate unreliable elements. Reports from Bonn
                        on these developments are in files 862A.501 and 862A.511.</note> When
                    informed by High Commission that it would be reluctant to use its reserve power
                    under paragraph 3 of occupation statute for purpose of authorizing establishment
                    of a Federal police force prior to the amendment to the constitution, Chancellor
                    then agreed that under his present authorization of 10,000 <hi rend="italic"
                        >Laender</hi> police, contingent measures should now be envisaged to set up
                    schools, establish central direction and start recruitment. These measures could
                    now be agreed without prejudice whether or not the force so recruited would
                    ultimately be transferred into a Federal force or remain as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Laender</hi> contingents available for Federal use in emergencies. In this
                    discussion, Francois Poncet indicated that he would be prepared to authorize a
                    major increase in the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> force over the 10,000 now
                    authorized.</p>
                <p>In support of his request for a Federal police force as a counterforce to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Volkspolizei</hi> and to offset any propaganda that this was
                    first step on the part of Federal Republic to establish national army,
                    Chancellor stated that he was prepared to accept any necessary Allied controls
                    over this force even to the appointment of Allied officers to positions within
                    this force.</p>
                <p>In concluding this phase of the discussion, the High Commissioners agreed to
                    forward to respective governments Chancellor’s security memo, copies of which
                    were taken to Washington by Mr. McCloy.<note n="5" xml:id="d381fn5">Regarding
                        Adenauer’s security memorandum, see footnote 3, <ref target="#pg_711">p.
                            711</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Discussion then turned to Chancellor’s memo on revision of the occupation
                        statute<note n="6" xml:id="d381fn6">For the full text of Adenauer’s
                        memorandum on the revision of the occupation statute, see Konrad Adenauer,
                            <hi rend="italic">Memoirs, 1945–1953</hi> (Chicago, Henry Regnery
                        Company, 1966), pp. 280–281; for a summary, see the first editorial note,
                            <ref target="#pg_765">p. 765</ref>.</note> and Adenauer was asked
                    whether the first two of the declarations envisaged for NY in paragraph III of
                    memo should precede the third which provides for progressive regulation of
                    relations between occupying powers and Federal Republic by agreements. He said
                    this was desire of Federal Republic since progressive regulations of these
                    relations would take some time and require considerable negotiations. He
                    explained that it would be extremely <pb facs="0732" n="716" xml:id="pg_716"/>
                    difficult to impose additional burdens on German people such as would be
                    required for defense or participation in European army if they had no assurance
                    that Germany was being received as equal partner by the western nations. He,
                    therefore, urged that a decision of the Foreign Ministers in September and an
                    announcement which could be understood clearly by the people were essential. As
                    an example of this frame of mind, he said he was horrified to learn from the
                    Ruhr that people were saying there that war between the US and USSR was
                    inevitable but that they should have no part in it.</p>
                <p>Kirkpatrick made considerable point of our rights to remain in Berlin which
                    should not be prejudiced if state of war between Allied powers and Germany is to
                    be terminated, pointing out our rights in Berlin grew out of the act of
                    surrender. He considered that this however could be handled by some formula
                    which would have practical effect of terminating war.</p>
                <p>High Commission likewise agreed to forward occupation memo to respective
                    governments (Mr. McCloy also has copies).</p>
                <p>Chancellor was obviously impressed by article in <hi rend="italic">Die Welt</hi>
                    which purports to give Soviets’ plans for peace with Eastern Germany (substance
                    of article being sent separate telegram<note n="7" xml:id="d381fn7">Telegram
                        1909, September 5, from Frankfort, not printed.</note>) and asked Allies to
                    pay particular attention to this program.</p>
                <p>Adenauer seemed even more discouraged than at last meeting. This may be due to
                    his concern over Communist-inspired strikes, continued reports of police
                    ineffectiveness, his difficulties with <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>, his fear
                    of what will happen in October and possible utilization by Soviets thereafter of
                    satellite status of East Germany to precipitate civil conflict leading
                    inevitably to third world war.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hays</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
