<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs (
                    (Perkins) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="4"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d4">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.69231/3–1350</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Perkins</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d4fn1">The source text is initialed by Deputy Assistant
                        Secretary of State for European Affairs Llewellyn E. Thompson.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-03-13">March 13,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Vesting of Hungarian, Rumanian and Bulgarian Government
                    Owned Assets now Held by the Office of Alien Property.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Treaties of Peace with Hungary, Rumania and Bulgaria<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d4fn2">For the texts of the Treaties of Peace with Hungary, Romania,
                        and Bulgaria, all signed in Paris, February 10, 1947, and entered into force
                        on September 15, 1947. see <gloss target="#t_TIAS1">TIAS</gloss> 1651, 61
                        Stat. 2065, or 41 <gloss target="#t_UNTS1">UNTS</gloss> 135 (for Hungary);
                            <gloss target="#t_TIAS1">TIAS</gloss> 1649, 61 Stat. (2) 1757, or 42
                            <gloss target="#t_UNTS1">UNTS</gloss> 3 (for Romania); <gloss
                            target="#t_TIAS1">TIAS</gloss> 1650, 61 Stat. 1915, or 41 <gloss
                            target="#t_UNTS1">UNTS</gloss> 21 (for Bulgaria).</note> give the United
                    States the right to seize, retain and liquidate all property, rights, and
                    interests in the United States on September 15, 1947 belonging to Hungary,
                    Rumania and Bulgaria or their nationals within the limits of United States
                    claims against those countries which have not been satisfied under other
                    articles of the Treaties of Peace. The three governments concerned have taken no
                    steps to honor their obligations to compensate American nationals’ losses
                    incurred as result of the war.</p>
                <p>In view of the rights given to the United States under the treaties and in view
                    of the present state of relations between the United States and the three
                    countries concerned, it is suggested that the Department request the Office of
                    Alien Property to proceed with vesting action against assets which are owned by
                    the three governments and which were blocked in the United States pursuant to
                    Executive Order 8389 as amended.<note n="3" xml:id="d4fn3">7 <hi rend="italic"
                            >Federal Register</hi> 2168.</note> There would be excluded from such
                    vesting diplomatic and consular property of these governments as provided by the
                    treaties. It is the view of the interested divisions that assets belonging to
                    private citizens of these governments should not be vested at the present
                    time.</p>
                <pb facs="0026" n="10" xml:id="pg_10"/>
                <p>It is understood that approximately the following government owned assets are
                    presently held by the Office of Alien Property: <table cols="2" rows="3">
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 7em">Rumania</cell>
                            <cell rend="padding-right: 7em" role="num">$19,256,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 7em">Hungary</cell>
                            <cell rend="padding-right: 7em" role="num">253,000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rend="padding-left: 7em">Bulgaria</cell>
                            <cell rend="padding-right: 7em" role="num">2,304,000</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>The attached letter is a request that the Office of Alien Property proceed with
                    vesting action against the assets concerned, the technical details and timing to
                    be worked out between the Department officers and officers of the Office of
                    Alien Property. The action will be held up pending the outcome of the Vogeler
                    appeal or until such time as it is determined that the action will have no
                    prejudicial effect on Vogeler’s situation.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that the attached letter be signed.<note n="4" xml:id="d4fn4"
                        >The proposed letter, signed by the Secretary of State, was sent to Attorney
                        General J. Howard McGrath on March 29, 1950; not printed (611.69231/3–2950).
                        Soon after the despatch of the letter a Nationalization Claims Policy
                        Committee was established to prepare recommendations on policy regarding
                        claims of American citizens for property nationalized or otherwise taken by
                        the Soviet Union or its Eastern European satellites.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
