<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-17T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-17T18:00:00-05:00" n="456" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d456">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">762A.00/5–1750: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Acting Secretary of State to the Berlin Element of
                                the Office of the United States High Commissioner for
                                Germany</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d456fn1">Repeated to Frankfort as
                                3494, London for <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> as 2366,
                                Moscow as 424, and Paris as 2251.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-17T19:00:00-04:00">May 17,
                                    1950—7 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>194. Berlin’s tel 699 May 9, sent Frankfort 839 rptd Paris 224, London
                            57, Moscow 44. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 185 May 12 to
                            Berlin, rptd Frankfort 3359, London 2259, Moscow 410.<note n="2" xml:id="d456fn2">Not printed, but see footnote 4, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> Dept suggests fol ideas to be discussed with
                            Brit, Fr and Berlin leaders in connection with reply Sov letter May 8 on
                            Berlin elections. Some of these points might be incorporated in City
                            Assembly res and/or Allied reply as you think best. Fol not to be
                            considered as rigid <gloss target="#t_instrs1">instrs</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Allied reply shld convey general tone of seeking clarify and resolve
                            differences between Western and Sov proposals rather than outright
                            rejection Sov proposals. It shld leave no doubt however that some of
                            proposals are entirely unacceptable as they stand. This method seems
                            desirable both indicate our sincerity in exploring whether genuine
                            agreement is possible on terms acceptable to West and achieve best
                            propaganda position if agrmt impossible. Our reply shld not invite
                            direct negots but shld give impression further clarifying correspondence
                            desired.</p>
                        <p>After initial remarks noting with pleasure Sov agrmt on free elections to
                            restore Berlin’s unity Commandants’ ltrs might comment on seven Sov
                            conditions somewhat along fol lines. It is disappointing Sovs again
                            suggest some conditions which were thoroughly discussed at Paris <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> in 1949 and rejected by Western Powers.
                            These conditions are no more acceptable now than then. As to individual
                            conditions: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Agreed</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>This proposal was made by Vyshinsky at Paris <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> in 1949 and was unacceptable
                                    US, Br and Fr then. It is still unacceptable, since Sov Sector
                                    is only one of four Sectors and contains only one-third of
                                    Berlin population. (We cld reiterate Western counter-proposal at
                                        <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>, that each commandant
                                    appoint same nr of Ger reps. We might also agree to a Ger comm
                                    chosen on basis relative pop in East and West Berlin.)</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Agreed provided denazification tribunals are included in
                                    definition of “court”.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>This proposal was also made by Vyshinsky at 1949 Paris <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> and was unacceptable Western
                                    Powers. It is still unacceptable. If a party decides it wants
                                    trade union or other representation in govt it can of course
                                    nominate representatives for such groups.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Proposals of Berlin City Assembly called for elections on
                                    basis of 1948 constitution. This reps a reasonable forward step
                                    since 1948 <pb facs="0874" n="858" xml:id="pg_858"/>
                                    constitution was passed in unified City Assembly with SovSec and
                                        <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss> participation. US (Br,
                                    Fr) Commandant ready to approve 1948 constitution and invites
                                    Sov Commandant to do likewise. (At Paris we were agreeable 1946
                                    constitution with deletion Art. 36 and substituion new US
                                    formula. See <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> Minutes, Vol
                                    VI, pp 70–71.<note n="3" xml:id="d456fn3">A copy of this volume
                                        of <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> minutes, prepared by
                                        the Division of Historical Policy Research in September
                                        1949, is in Box 234 of Lot M–88. The minutes of the 12th (2d
                                        Restricted) meeting of the 1949 <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>, under reference here, are also printed in
                                            <ref target="frus1949v03#pg_949">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 949</ref>.</note> We
                                    can retreat to this position later if exchanges proceed
                                    further.)</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item> What if anything wld Sovs substitute for May 1949 Occupation
                                    Statute? Sov proposal makes no mention of reestablishing
                                    quadripartite Allied Kommandatura. Does this omission mean that
                                    after possible withdrawal of garrisons Berlin City Govt wld not
                                    be under Allied Control? If it is to be under Allied control,
                                    what kind of control and to what extent shld the control
                                    mechanism have power over the democratically elected city Govt?
                                    The US (Br, Fr) Commandant cannot agree to return to former
                                    Kommandatura procedure under which one Commandant cld veto
                                    desires of other three and paralyze effective democratic Govt in
                                    City.</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>Does Sov proposal that “Ger dem orgs” be accorded freedom in
                                    Western Sectors mean Sovs are prepared grant right of
                                    unrestricted activity in their Sector to Polit parties and other
                                    orgs such as <gloss target="#t_UGO1">UGO</gloss> presently
                                    operating in West Sectors? (If Sovs wld agree to freedom for
                                    Western orgs there wld seem to be no serious objection
                                    permitting their orgs operate freely in West Berlin.) </item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item> This is new proposal not previously put forward. US (Br, Fr)
                                    Commandant wld like know why it is proposed withdraw occupation
                                    troops from Berlin in advance such withdrawal from all Ger. If
                                    withdrawal of troops considered necessary for free elections,
                                    does Sov Govt contemplate withdrawing its troops prior Oct 15
                                    elections in its Zone and Berlin Sec? (Of course we cld not
                                    agree withdrawal of troops from Berlin alone in view its
                                    location in heart of Sovzone.)</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>US (Br, Fr) Commandant considers it essential to free
                                    elections that genuine freedom of speech, press and assembly be
                                    guaranteed before, during and after elections and that no man be
                                    in fear of reprisals on account of opinions held or expressed in
                                    a peaceable manner. <hi rend="italic">End outline of suggested
                                        reply</hi>. </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Dept believes we must show our sincerity in seeking achieve agreement
                            with Sovs on elections. It is our understanding important Ger leaders
                            believe our moves for all-Berlin and All-German elections shld be more
                            than just propaganda maneuvers and feel one more real effort see whether
                            Sovs will agree unification on acceptable terms necessary at this time
                            before we recognize split of Berlin and Ger. Dept does not of course
                            have much hope this effort will succeed but is willing go through with
                            it, especially since Fr seem require positive evidence of Sov
                            unwillingness to reestablish Berlin as unified quadripartite city before
                            considering possibility Berlin’s becoming 12th <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> in Fed Rep. We believe negots shld be carried
                            considerable distance by exchange of notes, in which positions are
                            clearly stated and authenticated and polemic kept to minimum although
                            realities Sov conditions <pb facs="0875" n="859" xml:id="pg_859"/>
                            clearly revealed. If such, exchange shows narrowing of differences
                            indicating possible alteration previous firmly held Sov views, then it
                            might be worthwhile negotiate further across a table. Dept wld not agree
                            however resuming face-to-face negots in old atmosphere of recrimination
                            and sparring for propaganda advantage without some hope concrete
                            results.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>