<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé at Berlin ( (Page) ) to the Office of the United States High
                    Commissioner for Germany, at Frankfort</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">459</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-06-02T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-06-02T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-06-02T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-06-02T12:00:00-05:00" n="459"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d459">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762B.00/6–250: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Berlin</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Page</hi>) <hi
                        rend="italic">to the Office of the United States High Commissioner for
                        Germany, at Frankfort</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d459fn1">The source text was sent as 854 to the Department
                        of State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-06-02T18:00:00+01:00"
                            >June 2, 1950—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1046. Significance <hi rend="italic">Deutschlandtreffen</hi> from Berlin
                    standpoint may be summarized as follows:</p>
                <p>1. Vital importance Berlin for both West and East again emphasized. For West, it
                    constitutes most potent weapon against communism. For East, it represents
                    continuing menace which must be neutralized soon as possible. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Deutschlandtreffen</hi> a major political move to this end. Failure to
                    carry out original declared intention occupy West Berlin is tactical victory for
                    West and defeat for East, but renewed attempts certain. Unremitting vigilance
                    and continuing constructive effort essential to maintain Berlin as bastion of
                    democracy in Communist sea and to utilize unique opportunity for affirmative
                    counteraction. These conclusions underlined by <hi rend="italic"
                        >Deutschlandtreffen</hi> events as summarized Berlin’s 1019, May 30 to
                    Frankfort, repeated Department 836, Bonn 87, London 89, Paris 285, Moscow 70;
                    and Berlin’s 1036, June 1 to Frankfort, repeated Department 849, unnumbered
                    London, pouched Paris and Moscow.<note n="2" xml:id="d459fn2">Neither printed;
                        the former reported that Allied observers in Berlin felt that the
                        arrangements for the <hi rend="italic">Deutschlandtreffen</hi> (Whitsuntide
                        youth rally sponsored by the Soviet Zone Free German Youth) represented a
                        major achievement for the East Zone Communists, while the latter reviewed
                        press coverage for May 30–31. (762B.00/5–3050 and 962A.61/6–150)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0878" n="862" xml:id="pg_862"/>
                <p>2. Exceptional importance youth (reference last two paragraphs Berlin’s 1040,
                    June 1 to Frankfort, repeated Bonn 89, Department 851, Moscow 74, London 93,
                    Paris 94).<note n="3" xml:id="d459fn3">Not printed; it reported that the Kremlin
                        was “making substantial progress along well-known lines toward assimilation
                        of East Germany” but that the “Commie digestion process is far from
                        complete.” (762B.00/6–250)</note> Most effective counteraction Soviet effort
                    regiment and indoctrinate East German youth and appeal to West Berlin and German
                    youth, is effective West Berlin and West German youth action operating on truly
                    democratic basis.</p>
                <p>Youth groups here appreciate this fact and have contributed effectively to
                    maximum their resources in counterpropaganda effort during Whitsun period. Work
                    with <gloss target="#t_FDJ1">FDJ</gloss> boys and girls who have visited West
                    Berlin during past three days particularly significant. It is essential,
                    however, that West youth be encouraged and assisted in every feasible way to
                    strengthen democratic convictions and means of action. We propose to give this
                    problem preferred attention in Berlin.</p>
                <p>3. Effect of <hi rend="italic">Deutschlandtreffen</hi> on West Berlin population
                    can not yet be clearly appraised. It is evident that West Berliners view it with
                    mixed emotions: relief at failure of threat against West Berlin to materialize,
                    coupled with varying degree of realization ominous significance this mass
                    regimentation East German youth. Fact <hi rend="italic">Deutschlandtreffen</hi>
                    is not final episode, but merely one phase continuing Communist assault on
                    Berlin, emphasized by Reuter and other German spokesmen as well as in press
                    comment. On balance, safe to say West Berliners do not have false sense
                    security, but realize necessity continuous watchfulness and effort strengthen
                    democratic position and counter continuing Communist pressure.</p>
                <p>Sent Frankfort 1046; repeated information Bonn 92, Department 854, London 94,
                    Paris 297, Moscow 75.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Page</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
