<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Sweden ( (Matthews) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-05-17T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-05-17T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-17T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-17T11:00:00-05:00" n="56"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">450.6031/5–1750: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-17T17:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 17, 1950—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>659. Re <gloss target="#t_Depcirtel1">Depcirtel</gloss> April 28, 10 a. m.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d56fn1">Not printed, but see footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_105"
                            >p. 105</ref>.</note> We do not believe it desirable attempt Joint US–UK
                    assessment Swedish position this time. We have reported British views (<gloss
                        target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 442, April 4, repeated London 63, Paris
                    95 and <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 503, April 18, repeated Paris
                    109, London 76 and <gloss target="#t_Embdes1">Embdes</gloss> 430 April 20<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d56fn2">None printed.</note>).</p>
                <p>British have made only occasional inquiries to Foreign Office on certain special
                    aspects East-West trade. To our knowledge they have not stressed basic policies
                    nor desire for parallel Swedish action except in casual manner. Embassy has
                    requested that British Foreign Office be approached in effort obtain
                    instructions to British Ambassador Stockholm<note n="3" xml:id="d56fn3">Sir
                        Harold L. Farquhar.</note> to approach Swedish Foreign Office on high level
                    and to give firm assurance that British approach this problem is along same
                    lines. To date no such action has developed.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, while we are satisfied British Embassy officials individually
                    believe Swedish controls and information not satisfactory, we believe it
                    premature attempt joint assessment Swedish position before British have taken
                    more aggressive action.</p>
                <p>British recently requested Harris Chief <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>
                        Mission<note n="4" xml:id="d56fn4">Michael S. Harris, Chief of the Economic
                        Cooperation Administration Mission in Sweden.</note> to discuss history
                        <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> talks during 1948–1949 with Swedes on
                    East-West matters. Harris assumed British Ambassador wanted full story
                    negotiations, possibly for background before urging action on Swedes. He found
                    however that British Ambassador evidenced practically no interest in making
                    representations to Swedish Foreign Office and that his main concern was on
                    satisfactory solution Freja mines case (see <gloss target="#t_Embtel1"
                        >Embtel</gloss>s 508, April 19, and 492, April 17<note n="5" xml:id="d56fn5"
                        >Neither printed.</note>). British anxious obtain <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                        >ECA</gloss> Mission export for an agreement on Freja which would provide
                    satisfactory settlement British interests even though would result <pb
                        facs="0142" n="126" xml:id="pg_126"/> some expansion export strategic items,
                    including bearings to Czechoslovakia. Harris refused to be drawn into this
                    issue, but came away with strong impression lack of intention British Ambassador
                    make any vigorous move East-West trade in absence definite British Foreign
                    Office instructions.</p>
                <p>At present, we are only prepared to comment briefly some main factors Swedish
                    situation:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Reference Swedish production. As <gloss target="#t_OSR1">OSR</gloss>
                        reports have indicated, Sweden is one of few <gloss target="#t_OEEC1"
                            >OEEC</gloss> countries which has maintained trade with Eastern Europe
                        above prewar levels. Some of this trade and some of the expansion is in
                        strategic items, for example, ball and roller bearings. Thus, we are
                        concerned about tendency volume of trade to expand when strategic items
                        constitute an important part. Other items of importance, although possibly
                        not on American list; include for example, iron ore. Also, we do not have
                        sufficient official timely information on this trade with Eastern Europe. We
                        have been piecing the picture together bit by bit, and believe that
                        ultimately we should obtain Foreign Office agreement to current and complete
                        information.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>While we have of course Government decree of November 1949 we have only
                        vague assurances from Swedish officials as to how that decree will be
                        administered. We believe that we should work towards increased information
                        on the supplementary lists re the items listed in decree and should obtain
                        better current record of export controls in terms of American and
                        international lists.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Understand consultative group will determine whether international lists I
                        and II informal report progress <gloss target="#t_CoCom1">CoCom</gloss>
                        activity should be made available by Belgians to Swiss on informal basis. If
                            <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss> so determines believe US should
                        request permission transmit same information Swedish Government. Embassy
                        would take advantage such opportunity to reemphasize US concern absence more
                        adequate Swedish control.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Control of reexportation and in-transit shipments. The recent report of
                            <gloss target="#t_CoCom1">CoCom</gloss> to the <gloss target="#t_CG1"
                            >CG</gloss> on transit controls appears to represent marked progress
                        this area. If recommendations which appear to be applicable both to transit
                        control and reexportation are accepted by <gloss target="#t_CG1">CG</gloss>,
                        Embassy would propose; subject concurrence Department, approaching Swedish
                        Government to obtain its concurrence institute comparable control.
                        Application principles involved would likewise be sought for Swedish
                        freeports. While not optimistic, results such efforts, believe attempt worth
                            while.<note n="6" xml:id="d56fn6">Telegram 2561, May 26, to London,
                            repeated to Stockholm as 365, not printed, asked that the British
                            Foreign Office be approached on a high level with a view that more
                            affirmative British action was necessary to progress trade control
                            discussions with Sweden (450.6031/5–1750). In early June the British
                            Foreign Office agreed to make an approach to the Swedish Government, but
                            the initial action was delayed until early October 1950.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Sent Department 659; repeated information Paris 114 for <gloss target="#t_Excon1"
                        >Excon</gloss>, London 117, pouched Moscow.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
