<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Kirk) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d637</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">637</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-04-11T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-04-11T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-04-11T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-04-11T06:00:00-05:00" n="637"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d637">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.5622/4–1150: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d637fn1">This telegram, as well as telegram 1094, was also
                        sent for Lt. Gen. John Kenneth Cannon, Commander in Chief of United States
                        Air Forces in Europe. Copies of Doth telegrams were handed to a
                        representative of the United States Air Force in Washington at 10:55 a. m.
                        on April 11. G. Frederick Reinhardt, Officer in Charge of Soviet Union
                        Affairs and Acting Director of the Office of Eastern European Affairs, was
                        notified at 9:40 a. m. of the arrival of these telegrams.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-04-11T14:00:00+03:00"
                            >April 11, 1950—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1093. Responding to request I called on Vishinsky at Foreign Ministry at noon
                    today and he handed me note full translation in following telegram number
                        1094.<note n="2" xml:id="d637fn2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi>
                    </note> Note alleges violation territory at Libau on 8 April at 1739 hours
                    Moscow time (minus 3 Z<note n="3" xml:id="d637fn3">Three hours later than
                        Greenwich meridian mean time.</note>) by USA plane B–29, intercepted by
                    Soviet fighters, fire exchanged, no Soviet casualties, US plane disappeared to
                    seaward.</p>
                <p>Note was read by Vishinsky and translated by interpreter Pastoev<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d637fn4">Vsevolod Vladimirovich Pastoyev was an interpreter in the
                        Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union.</note> piecemeal.
                    Vishinsky’s manner serious but not aggressive nor antagonistic. I said note
                    would be transmitted at once to my government and matter would be
                    investigated.</p>
                <p>Then asked questions on various points as follows: (1) visibility, was told
                    adequate to read markings on incoming plane and to see signals (described as
                    rocking wings by fighters); (2) were plane numbers recorded, answer only
                    “markings”; (3) was plane clearly US <pb facs="1157" n="1141" xml:id="pg_1141"/>
                    and not British or French, reply plane clearly identified as US; (4) asked if
                    any casualties, reply “Soviets none, as far as Vishinsky knew”; (5) questioned
                    as to clock time in use by Soviet planes from Libau first reply was local Libau
                    time, but Pastoev phoned at 1230 to say time was identified as “Moscow time”
                    which is minus 3 Z.</p>
                <p>Evident Vishinsky was not completely familiar technical aviation aspects of
                    investigation, which terseness of note confirms. Note bears no notation
                    indicating “confidential” or otherwise and question publicity did not arise.
                    However, past record unreassuring this point, and by coincidence one Embassy
                    employee just received phone call from Stockholm newsman asking if Embassy has
                    news regarding Soviet plane down in Baltic (reply was of course negative).</p>
                <p>I recommend speediest investigation and I be kept informed promptest. Further
                    recommend publicity our side should be avoided or, if unavoidable, minimized. I
                    did not have impression Vishinsky was preparing create situation of real gravity
                    although his manner definitely serious and may mask something in propaganda
                    line. Suspect also possibility Soviet planes may have in fact attacked US plane
                    outside territorial waters and present <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> in nature
                    offensive defense.</p>
                <p>As regards foreign press correspondents Moscow I intend no comment for present,
                    but if story breaks will say all comments must come from Washington.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
