<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="728" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d728">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">761.56/5–2550</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the <gloss type="from">Acting Officer in Charge of Economic Affairs in the
                                    Office, of Eastern European Affairs</gloss>
                            </hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Truesdell</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-25">May 25, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Commander Davis<note n="1" xml:id="d728fn1">Commander Jack C. Davis was a
                                representative of the Navy Department, as an expert participating in
                                discussions about lend-lease naval vessels and arrangements for
                                their return by the Soviet Union.</note> called this morning to
                            inquire whether or not the Department had received a reply from the
                            Soviet Government to this Government’s note of May 8, 1950 in which we
                            requested the return of the icebreakers <hi rend="italic">North
                                Wind</hi> and <hi rend="italic">West Wind</hi> at Bremerhaven,
                            Germany by June 30, 1950 or this being impossible at Yokosuka, Japan by
                            that date. I advised Commander Davis that the reply had not yet been
                            received but that it was expected that the Soviet Chargé would be called
                            in early next week if a reply has not been received by that date.</p>
                        <p>I brought to Commander Davis’s attention the letter from the Secretary of
                            the Navy<note n="2" xml:id="d728fn2">Secretary of the Navy Francis P.
                                Matthews.</note> of October 10, 1949 in which he stated the “desire
                                <pb facs="1307" n="1291" xml:id="pg_1291"/> of the Department of the
                            Navy, which is concurred in by the Secretary of Defense,<note n="3" xml:id="d728fn3">Louis A. Johnson.</note> that the presently
                            anticipated resumption of negotiations on US–USSR lend-lease problems be
                            entered into with the intent of dispossessing the Soviet Government of
                            all operable U.S. Naval vessels in their custody”. I advised Commander
                            Davis that it is the present intention of the Department to proceed,
                            first by pressing for the return of the 186 Naval craft demanded with
                            the icebreakers and frigates in our note of October 12, 1948 at the same
                            time pressing as rapidly as possible for an over-all lend-lease
                            settlement carrying the matter to the highest level if necessary. I said
                            that to demand all of the craft at the present time, in the face of our
                            offer to sell, would undoubtedly not only jeopardize the return of any
                            further lend-lease naval craft but would also jeopardize the U.S.
                            position in the over-all settlement. After some discussion, Commander
                            Davis expressed his agreement to the course of action outlined above and
                            stated that he had recently submitted a comprehensive memorandum to
                            Admiral Sherman<note n="4" xml:id="d728fn4">Admiral Forrest P. Sherman,
                                Chief of Naval Operations.</note> on the present status of the
                            Soviet lend-lease matter in which he had advised that it was the Navy’s
                            expectations that the Department would attempt to obtain the return of
                            the 186 vessels prior to disclosing our intentions with respect to the
                            remaining 242. In this memorandum to Admiral Sherman, Commander Davis
                            pointed out that a request by the Department for the return of all of
                            these vessels at this time would undoubtedly jeopardize the
                            negotiations.</p>
                        <p>I advised Commander Davis that as result of the conversation and
                            clarification of the Navy views in the matter that unless he heard from
                            me to the contrary, the Department would proceed along the lines
                            indicated above.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>G[<hi rend="smallcaps">eorge</hi>] E. T[<hi rend="smallcaps">ruesdell</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>