<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="757" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d757">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">761.56/11–2150</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chargé of the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sokolov</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-28">December 28,
                                1950</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I refer to the question of two
                            icebreakers of the United States Navy, the <hi rend="italic">North
                                Wind</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">West Wind</hi>, leased to the
                            Government <pb facs="1352" n="1336" xml:id="pg_1336"/> of the Union of
                            Soviet Socialist Republics under the Lend-Lease Act which have not been
                            returned to the United States in accordance with the obligation of the
                            Soviet Government under Article V of the Master Lend-Lease Agreement and
                            as specifically provided for in the Agreement of September 27, 1949
                            between the Governments of the United States and the Union of Soviet
                            Socialist Republics.</p>
                        <p>You will recall that in a note of October 7, 1948, the Government of the
                            United States formally demanded the return of three icebreakers, the <hi rend="italic">North Wind</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">South Wind</hi>
                            and the <hi rend="italic">West Wind</hi>. On September 27, 1949 the
                            Governments of the United States and the Union of Soviet Socialist
                            Republics signed an agreement which provided for the return of the three
                            icebreakers to the United States at the port of Bremerhaven, Germany not
                            later than December 1, 1949. On November 12, 1949, the Soviet Chargé
                            d’Affaires informed this Government that only one icebreaker, the <hi rend="italic">South Wind</hi> could be returned by December 1, the
                            other two, the <hi rend="italic">North Wind</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">West Wind</hi> being unable to break through the
                            unusually heavy ice in the Arctic regions. The Soviet Government offered
                            to return the <hi rend="italic">South Wind</hi> before December 1, and
                            the <hi rend="italic">North Wind</hi> and <hi rend="italic">West
                                Wind</hi> at a port in northern Japan in May or June 1950, or
                            earlier if possible. In view of the original agreement, the Soviet
                            Government alternatively offered to return all three vessels at
                            Bremerhaven after piloting them through the Arctic from east to west
                            during the Arctic navigation season in 1950.</p>
                        <p>On November 29, 1949, the Soviet Chargé d’Affaires was informed that the
                            United States Government was prepared to accept the icebreaker <hi rend="italic">South Wind</hi> immediately in the port of Yokosuka,
                                Japan,<note n="1" xml:id="d757fn1">
                                <ref target="frus1949v05#pg_752">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1949, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, footnote 1, p. 752</ref>.</note>
                            and on December 27, 1949 the <hi rend="italic">South Wind</hi> was
                            returned to United States custody.</p>
                        <p>In its note of May 8, 1950 the United States Government expressed its
                            desire to accept delivery of the <hi rend="italic">North Wind</hi> and
                                <hi rend="italic">West Wind</hi> in Bremerhaven, Germany before June
                            30, 1950 or if that were not possible, it agreed to accept delivery in
                            Yokosuka, Japan. Mr. Bazykin, the Soviet Chargé d’Affaires replied to
                            the request of the United States Government on May 31, 1950 stating that
                            the icebreakers <hi rend="italic">North Wind</hi> and <hi rend="italic">West Wind</hi> could not be returned in the previously specified
                            time because they were caught in solid jammed Arctic ice and were
                            drifting westward. The Soviet Government therefore offered to deliver
                            the icebreakers in the port of Bremerhaven in November or December
                            1950.</p>
                        <p>On November 1, 1950 the Soviet Chargé d’Affaires again informed this
                            Government that the two icebreakers could not be delivered. Oil this
                            occasion the Soviet note stated that the icebreakers had not yet broken
                            into clear water because both vessels had damaged screws. <pb facs="1353" n="1337" xml:id="pg_1337"/> More than a year has passed
                            since the original delivery date agreed to by the Soviet Government. In
                            these circumstances the Government of the United States would appreciate
                            detailed information as to the whereabouts and condition of these two
                            vessels of the United States Navy in order that consideration may be
                            given to the possibility of accepting their return in their present
                            condition and location.</p>
                        <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                            </signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Under Secretary</hi>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>