<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-12T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-12T17:00:00-05:00" n="817" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d817">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">768.5 <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>/7–1250: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d817fn1">This telegram was repeated to Belgrade
                                as 26 and to Paris as 171.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-12T18:00:00-04:00">July 12,
                                    1950—6 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>186. Fol is summary substance of similar <hi rend="italic">Aides-Mémoire</hi> presented Jul 10 to Brit and Fr <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss>s Wash<note n="2" xml:id="d817fn2">Neither printed; filed separately under 768.00/7–1050.</note> on
                            joint planning of mil assistance to be rendered Yugo in eventuality
                            envisaged <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 18/4, para 27<hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Begin summary</hi> US Govt has studied with interest
                            Fr comments recd Feb 23<note n="3" xml:id="d817fn3">See telegram 579,
                                February 6, from Paris, <ref target="#pg_1363">p. 1363</ref>.</note>
                            and Brit comments recd May 2<note n="4" xml:id="d817fn4">See the
                                memorandum of conversation by Campbell, May 2, <ref target="#pg_1410">p. 1410</ref>, and telegram 2074, May 4, to
                                London, <ref target="#pg_1412">p. 1412</ref>.</note> in reply US <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> re mil assistance to Yugo in certain
                            contingencies and notes pleasurably similarity US, Fr and Brit approach.
                            For info ur govt there is attached US mil staff study analysis and
                            estimate Yugo mil situation.<note n="5" xml:id="d817fn5">The undated,
                                18–page, Department of State–Department of Defense staff study under
                                reference here, not printed, presented tentative estimates of the
                                probable Yugoslav requirements for military supplies under each of
                                the possible courses of Soviet action discussed in document <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 18/4, November 17, 1949, and the
                                extent and manner by which such supplies could best be made
                                available to Yugoslavia. The study concluded that should Yugoslavia
                                request military aid from the Western powers, the United States in
                                conjunction with other Western powers could provide and deliver
                                sufficient supplies to maintain current Yugoslav military strength
                                and equipment at a level sufficient to resist all but a Soviet
                                attack. However, in the case of an all-out Soviet attack only enough
                                supplies could be provided and delivered as would provide for a
                                defense of the mountainous region of Southwest Yugoslavia (S/ISA
                                Files, Lot 52–19, Policy–12.272–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>–Yugoslavia). The S/ISA files contain records of the
                                Office of the Director, International Security Affairs, Department
                                of State, covering the years 1949–1951. They form a part of FRC Acc.
                                No. 62 A 613.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>US Govt agrees deliveries equipment to <gloss target="#t_NAP1">NAP</gloss><note n="6" xml:id="d817fn6">North Atlantic Pact.</note>
                            countries shld have top priority, but as there is agreement polit and
                            strategic considerations may warrant acceding to a Yugo request for mil
                            aid there shld be on receipt such request tripartite discussions to
                            determine scope and nature mil supplies which shld be made
                            available.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Fol to Brit only:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>US Govt notes Brit study recd under cover Brit comments is in accord US
                            mil staff study referred to above.</p>
                        <pb facs="1449" n="1433" xml:id="pg_1433"/>
                        <p>Re Brit suggestion for joint mission to Yugo to study Yugo requirements
                            before any aid is advanced, US Govt of view that while final
                            recommendations for aid to Yugo shld be by qualified technical personnel
                            regular service atts at Belgrade of participating countries wld be
                            preferable channel for submission interim data to Govts concerned.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">End to Brit only.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In view present positions Brit, Fr and US Govts, US Govt suggests
                            advantageous for small group Brit, Fr and US officials meet immed in
                            Wash at technical working level at intervals whenever one participant
                            considers changing circumstances warrant, to discuss present views of
                            their govts and coordinate their planning in event future determination
                            that YuGovt shld be accorded certain mil assistance. Further suggested
                            this group cld be composed of several officials from US Depts State and
                            Defense and that Brit and Fr Govts might designate several counterpart
                            officials from among their respective Wash missions.</p>
                        <p>Similar communication as well as copy US mil staff study referred to
                            above being addressed Brit (Fr) <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss>
                            Wash. <hi rend="italic">End summary.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>