<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-09T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-09T16:00:00-05:00" n="869" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d869">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">768.56/11–1650: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-09T16:00:00-05:00">December
                                    9, 1950—4 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3184. Re <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 2776 Nov 16 rptd
                            Belgrade 38 London 660.<note n="1" xml:id="d869fn1">Not printed, but see
                                footnote 2, <ref target="#pg_1498">p. 1498</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Fr <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss> presented <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> Dec 5 stating: <quote rend="blockquote"> (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Report of tripartite comite on mil aid
                                    to Yugo (<gloss target="#t_reDeptel1">reDeptel</gloss> 2401 to
                                    Paris Nov 3<note n="2" xml:id="d869fn2">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1496">p.
                                            1496</ref>.</note> rptd Belgrade 335 London 2334) raises
                                    basic question whether three countries are prepared approach
                                    Yugo Govt with view to proceeding to practical steps; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Fr Govt considers Yugo negots with
                                    France for mil equipment provide opportunity to sound out
                                    Belgrade auths and to initiate deliveries of materiel in manner
                                    which would appear, from polit viewpoint, to take full acct of
                                    position of Yugo Govt; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) it would be
                                    desirable for three govts to settle questions which tripartite
                                    experts found beyond their competence, notably problem of
                                    financing; and (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) Fr <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> proposes tripartite
                                    discussions on these questions be opened in Paris at early date
                                    and desires know whether this procedure acceptable to Dept.
                                </quote>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Dept is of opinion Fr-Yugo negots, which have essentially
                                commercial character and involve peculiarly Fr interests such as
                                prewar debts and compensation for nationalized properties, should,
                                as suggested in para 2 of Belgrade’s 511 to Dept (rptd Paris 68
                                London 35),<note n="3" xml:id="d869fn3">November 17, <ref target="#pg_1501">p. 1501</ref>.</note> be held separate and
                                distinct from broader problem of developing general program of mil
                                assistance to Yugo. US (and presumably Brit) role in Fr-Yugo negots
                                should accordingly be confined to determination whether release of
                                any or all of mil items by Fr to Yugo would be prejudicial to
                                interests of gen rearmament program or of policies guiding program
                                of assistance to Yugo. Dept accordingly considers it appropriate
                                that all discussions concerning mil materiel involved in Fr-Yugo
                                negots for financial-commercial agreement be centered in Paris and
                                will undertake to provide you with necessary instructions for that
                                purpose at early date. With respect to broad policies of mil aid
                                program, however, Dept believes decisions can be taken only after
                                further consideration of tripartite comite report and reconciliation
                                of views of three govts thereon, and inclines to prefer in view of
                                work already done here that discussions on this program remain in
                                Wash. Views of Paris Belgrade and London <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss>s on this point urgently requested.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>As possibly providing insight into actual Yugo needs, Dept would
                                appreciate any info obtainable from Fr auths whether list given in
                                    <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> (and Paris despatch
                                1365 Nov 28 now received<note n="4" xml:id="d869fn4">Not printed,
                                    but see footnote 2, <ref target="#pg_1498">p.
                                1498</ref>.</note>) contains all items requested by Yugo or only
                                those which Fr feel they are in position to provide.</item>
                            <pb facs="1527" n="1511" xml:id="pg_1511"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Dept would appreciate as detailed as possible info re present
                                status of current Yugo-Fr debt settlement and credit negots and
                                nature of terms being discussed<note n="5" xml:id="d869fn5">Telegram
                                    3336, December 11, from Paris, not printed, reported that the
                                    Embassy had been informed by the French Foreign Ministry that
                                    the negotiations with Yugoslavia had been held up pending
                                    American comments on the military items to be provided and a
                                    determination by the French Government of the degree to which
                                    credit could be extended to Yugoslavia. The Yugoslav
                                    representatives appeared to be most impatient to complete the
                                    negotiations for arms already requested and had made tentative
                                    inquiries about additional items (768.56/12–1150).</note> (see
                                Belgrade’s 511 to Dept repeated Paris 68 London 35).</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Sent Paris, repeated London as 2973, Belgrade as 507.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>