<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>136. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Morocco</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d136</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">136</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-17T14:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-17T14:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-17T14:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-17T14:30:00-05:00" n="136"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d136">
                <head>136. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Morocco</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d136fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, DEF 19–8 US–MOR. Secret; Immediate; Limdis. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_RJF2">Root</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PJAII1"
                            >Palmer</persName> on June 16; cleared by Kitchen, Hoopes, Saunders, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>; and approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_REVD1">Eugene V. Rostow</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-06-17T15:30:00-04:00">June 17, 1967, 3:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>212261. Ref Rabat’s 5531 and 5532.<note n="2" xml:id="d136fn2">Telegrams 5531 and
                        5532 from Rabat, June 15, reported that Foreign Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_LA1">Laraki</persName> and General <persName
                            corresp="#p_OGM1">Oufkir</persName> informed the Embassy that recent
                        intelligence reports indicated that Algeria planned to attack Morocco July
                        8. <persName corresp="#p_LA1">Laraki</persName> said that Morocco would have
                        to obtain more arms very quickly, since its 3–4-day holding strategy was
                        invalid after the Arab-Israeli war when Israel won in 3 hours. (Ibid.,
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 32–1 ALG–MOR)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>You should assure <persName corresp="#p_LA1">Laraki</persName> and Oufkir
                        of our continuing deep concern for Moroccan security. We are giving urgent
                        attention to specific problem raised reftel and, while you are not in
                        position give specific response at this time, <gloss target="#t_GOM1"
                            >GOM</gloss> can be sure that we are carefully examining situation in
                        light of all prevailing circumstances in Maghreb and Near <pb facs="0252"
                            n="204" xml:id="pg_204"/> East. We will remain in closest contact at
                        both military and governmental levels on this matter.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>You should add that while we do not have any independent evidence
                        suggesting that Algerians readying attack against Morocco, we are taking all
                        steps available to us ascertain further information about Algerian
                        intentions. We obviously do not know Boumediene’s thoughts at this time, but
                        seems most illogical to us that he would contemplate attack against Arab
                        country at same moment he is trying to exert some leadership in reuniting
                        Arabs against Israel.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>We naturally hope to avoid new arms race throughout North Africa and
                        Middle East. We are closely following Soviet actions and intend to probe
                        their intentions in this respect. We consider it highly important in
                        interest of countries of the area and of the world to bring arms deliveries
                        to area under some kind of control.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>However, we certainly recognize Morocco’s right and desire to be in
                        position to defend itself. This is why, in light this latest request, we are
                        now urgently reexamining availability of resources, as well as how our
                        resources and influence can be brought to bear to insure that eventuality
                            <gloss target="#t_GOM1">GOM</gloss> fears does not materialize. Timing
                        of our response will have to take into consideration general situation in
                        Middle East as well as Maghreb.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. Apart from probable practical
                        impossibility of providing any substantial amount of equipment that
                        Moroccans could use effectively within time indicated, we are reluctant take
                        risk of action which might excuse Soviet increases arms supply at this
                        delicate juncture of Near East crisis. Moreover, we do not exclude
                        possibility that Moroccan request is essentially ploy by <persName
                            corresp="#p_OGM1">Oufkir</persName> to get US to react in a hurry. In
                        this connection we would be disturbed by possibility suggested in some [<hi
                            rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                        reports that <persName corresp="#p_OGM1">Oufkir</persName> might even be
                        considering preemptive strike against Algeria. We would hope of course you
                        could find means discourage any such possibility.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>While unable for present to give Moroccan request clear answer in
                        affirmative, we are also anxious that King does not take our reply as flat
                        turndown. We want to retain <gloss target="#t_GOM1">GOM</gloss>’s
                        confidence, especially in view of its potentially constructive role in
                        Arab-Israeli settlement, and to reassure King that we continue to follow
                        with close interest Morocco’s relations with its Algerian neighbor and would
                        be far from indifferent if there were serious danger of Algerian attack.
                        Your response to <persName corresp="#p_LA1">Laraki</persName>
                        <pb facs="0253" n="205" xml:id="pg_205"/> and Oufkir should therefore be
                        governed by various and to some degree conflicting considerations set out
                            above.<note n="3" xml:id="d136fn3">In telegram 5605 from Rabat, June 20,
                            the Embassy responded that the Department’s telegram did not answer the
                            question posed by the Moroccan Government, which was primarily
                            interested in how it could meet the serious security problem it faced on
                            its eastern border. Morocco wanted to know if the United States was
                            prepared to supply the arms it needed, so that, if necessary, it could
                            make other provisions over the next few months. (Ibid., DEF 19–8
                            US–MOR)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
