<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-03-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-03-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="147" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d147">
                        <head>147. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_KRW2" type="from">Robert W.
                                Komer</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            Deputy Administrator of the Agency for International Development
                                (<persName corresp="#p_GWS1" type="to">Gaud</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d147fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Files of <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Robert W.
                                    Komer</persName>, Tunisia, December 1963–March 1966. Secret.
                                Also sent to Hutchinson and Williams.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-03-25">March 25, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>My initial concern over how we handle our next aid round with the
                            Tunisians (my London 4561)<note n="2" xml:id="d147fn2">In telegram 4561
                                from London, March 22, <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName>
                                warned that <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>’s plan to advise
                                Tunisia that the U.S. Government was not prepared to make a
                                quantitative commitment to a new Tunisian long-term plan would be
                                “political folly” at a time when the United States wanted all the
                                moderate Arab support it could get. (Ibid.)</note> was to avoid
                            slapping Bourguiba just after he’s stuck to a responsible line on
                                Palestine.<note n="3" xml:id="d147fn3">Telegram 524 from Amman,
                                March 9, reported that President Bourguiba, who was on a visit to
                                Jordan, had declared at a March 6 press conference in Jerusalem that
                                Arabs could cooperate with Jews. (Department of State, Central
                                Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 TUN)</note> However,
                            entirely apart from this we face the problem of how to capitalize on
                            gains from past aid as we begin talking about their next plan.</p>
                        <p>There’s a special obligation to use tact because we made such a big thing
                            of our multi-year commitment three years ago. I realize multi-year deals
                            aren’t as appealing to us as they were in 1961–62. But if we’re going to
                            shift back to annual programming, it would be inexcusable not to do it
                            gently. After all, we’re the ones who sold the Tunisians on long-term
                            aid planning and multi-year commitments.</p>
                        <p>I’m not judging the merits of a multi-year pledge. What I’m worried about
                            is how to present whatever decision we make to the Tunisians without
                            jeopardizing the confidence we’ve built there.</p>
                        <p>So I think <hi rend="italic">we ought to be looking for a formula</hi>
                            for telling the Tunisians how far we’ll go in supporting their next
                            plan. Just to get us started, what about saying something like this to
                            Bourguiba and <persName corresp="#p_BSA2">Ben Salah</persName>: <pb facs="0272" n="224" xml:id="pg_224"/>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“We’ll continue aiding Tunisian development at substantial
                                    levels. Our interest is as great as ever. To improve the
                                    effectiveness of our aid, we would like to suggest some new
                                    techniques developed from our experience since 1961. For
                                    instance, one device we think offers promise is the annual
                                    development budget, which provides the most accurate guide to
                                    amounts and types of aid required. So we’d like to begin working
                                    with Ben Salah on such a budget and will gear our aid to that as
                                    soon as precise needs become clear.” This is much better than
                                    telling them right off we’re not going to make a quantitative
                                    commitment to the new plan.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The point is that this is both a political and an aid problem and we need
                            a formula that serves both needs. Above all, we can’t afford another
                            fiasco like the Title I blowup in December, especially on something as
                            important as this.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="strong">R.W. Komer</hi>
                                </persName><note n="4" xml:id="d147fn4">Printed from a copy that
                                    bears this typed signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>