<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-02-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="237" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d237">
                        <head>237. Memorandum From the Director of the Office of West African
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_TWC1" type="from">Trimble</persName>) to
                            the Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs (<persName type="to">Williams</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d237fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 GHANA–US. Secret. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TWC1">Trimble</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MWPJ1">Mahoney</persName>, and Deputy Director of
                                the Office of West African Affairs Leon G. Dorros.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-02-11">February 11, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Proposed Action Program for Ghana</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">A. Assumptions</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The course of action outlined below is based on the following
                            assumptions: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>By his present actions, <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> is daily rendering our position in Ghana
                                    more difficult. He sees us as an ideal scapegoat to cover his
                                    domestic shortcomings and a handy whipping boy to promote his
                                    extreme brand of Pan-Africanism. In contrast to his leftist
                                    advisors, it is doubtful, however, that he wishes us to leave.
                                    He probably desires to retain the Volta aid and also some
                                    connection with the West to give him a posture of neutrality.
                                    But his present conduct can only lead to circumstances under
                                    which our position could well become untenable.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>The U.S. should make a determined effort to remain in Ghana.
                                    Voluntary withdrawal of our representation would be interpreted
                                    both there and elsewhere in Africa as a defeat for the U.S. and
                                    a victory for the Communists. It also would encourage the
                                    Communists and leftist elements in other parts of Africa to
                                    adopt the same tactics they have been following in Ghana. The
                                    Soviet bloc desires us to leave Ghana and is actively engaged in
                                    promoting this end.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> is convinced that
                                    the U.S. is the principal obstacle to his program for African
                                    unity. He is also convinced that through the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> we are seeking to engineer his
                                    downfall. He is living in a state of fear induced by the several
                                    assassination attempts and an overriding sense of insecurity,
                                    and consequently is increasingly irrational and
                                    irresponsible.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>’s popularity has
                                    markedly declined in the past 18 months, especially among civil
                                    servants, police, businessmen, university students and the
                                    professions. Though he still enjoys a considerable following
                                    among the rural masses, the more politically-minded urban
                                    population has lost confidence in him.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Time is not on our side. The Parliament, judiciary and police
                                    have been emasculated; a purge of the universities is now under
                                    way and <pb facs="0462" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/> one of the
                                    civil service imminent. Although moderate elements still exert a
                                    slight influence on <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>, he increasingly depends for advice and
                                    counsel on the small group of leftists in his immediate
                                    entourage. <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> is
                                    consciously and deliberately creating a police state based on
                                    national Marxist principles.</item>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>Although <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>’s
                                    leftward progress cannot be checked or reversed, it could be
                                    slowed down by a well conceived and executed action program.
                                    Measures which we might take against <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> would have to be carefully selected in
                                    order not to weaken pro-Western elements in Ghana or adversely
                                    affect our prestige and influence elsewhere on the
                                    continent.</item>
                                <label>(7)</label>
                                <item>U.S. pressure, if appropriately applied, could induce a chain
                                    reaction eventually leading to <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>’s downfall. Chances of success would be
                                    greatly enhanced if the British could be induced to act in
                                    concert with us.</item>
                                <label>(8)</label>
                                <item>Failure to act can only result in a further deterioration of
                                    the situation to the point where we may feel compelled to leave
                                    Ghana, thereby facilitating the chance of Soviet success.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">B. Summary of Proposed Actions</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(1)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Postponement of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MWPJ1">Mahoney</persName>’s Return to
                                        Accra</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Ambassador Ribeiro should be called to the Department and
                                    informed by Governor Williams that in view of the Ghanaian
                                    Government’s expression of regret at the demonstrations before
                                    the American Embassy and the Foreign Minister’s assurance that
                                    they would not re-occur, it had been decided that Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MWPJ1">Mahoney</persName> would return
                                    to Accra on February 14. Because of the subsequent expulsion of
                                    American professors at the University of Ghana and vicious
                                    attacks on an officer of our Embassy, we now intend to postpone
                                    the Ambassador’s return. The same statement should also be made
                                    to Botsio by our Charge at Accra.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(2)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Award of Medal of Freedom to Adger E.
                                        Player</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Congressmen Oliver P. Bolton and Zablocki have proposed that the
                                    Medal of Freedom be awarded to Mr. <persName>Player</persName>
                                    for his action in preventing desecration of the American flag.
                                    The White House has asked for the Department’s views on the
                                    proposal. Our response should indicate that a decoration is
                                    fully justified, and suggest that it be either the Medal of
                                    Freedom or the Legion of Merit. Mr.
                                    <persName>Player</persName>’s valorous conduct has been widely
                                    reported in the American press, and the award would constitute
                                    tangible evidence of the country’s gratitude and admiration. It
                                    would also underscore our contempt for the controlled Ghanaian
                                    press in seeking to besmirch Mr. <persName>Player</persName>’s
                                    character.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(3)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Representations to <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MWPJ1">Mahoney</persName>
                                    </hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The Ambassador should see <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> as soon as possible after his return to
                                    Accra and make clear to him our concern at the course of
                                    developments <pb facs="0463" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/> in Ghana
                                    and their seriously adverse implications for U.S.-Ghanaian
                                    relations. He should indicate that as Ghana has failed to carry
                                    out the understandings set forth in the 1961 exchange of
                                    correspondence between President <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>, we may be forced to reexamine our
                                    commitments to Ghana. He should also express our shock that no
                                    action has been taken against the leaders of the demonstrations.
                                    The impact of the Ambassador’s remarks would obviously be
                                    enhanced if he were in a position to state that he had seen the
                                    President just before leaving Washington and had discussed the
                                    Ghanaian situation with him. It is felt that the Ambassador
                                    should not bring a letter from the President to <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> since it might (a) serve
                                    further to inflate <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>’s ego; (b) encourage him to initiate an
                                    exchange of correspondence with the President and (c) be quoted
                                    out of context by <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>
                                    to serve his own purposes.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(4)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Visit by Edgar Kaiser</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Mr. <persName>Edgar Kaiser</persName> should be encouraged to
                                    seek an interview with <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> in the near future at which he would
                                    stress the unfavorable reaction in the U.S. to recent events in
                                    Ghana and indicate that they are causing serious misgivings
                                    among the Directors of <persName corresp="#p_KPM2">Kaiser</persName> Industries on the desirability of
                                    proceeding with the <gloss target="#t_VALCO1">VALCO</gloss>
                                    project.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(5)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> Review of Its Support
                                        of Volta</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The recommendation should be made to the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss>, preferably through the Secretary of the
                                    Treasury, that it send a team to Ghana to study the desirability
                                    of continuing its support of the Volta project in the light of
                                    Ghana’s adverse financial situation.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(6)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Slow-down in Payments on the Volta Dam
                                        Project</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> and the Eximbank should
                                    delay action on pending and future requests for draw downs of
                                    loan funds by the Volta Dam. (This course of action is possible
                                    only until around July 1, 1964 when the lake starts to form and
                                    further delays in construction might cause serious flooding and
                                    loss of life.) Because of the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss>’s direct involvement in the project, it should
                                    be informed in advance of any such action.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(7)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Termination of NIH Facility</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The Bureau of the Budget is anxious to close down the NIH
                                    research facility at Accra as part of its program to reduce the
                                    balance of payments deficit. Although useful, the facility has
                                    been unable to fully realize its potential as a source of data
                                    on tropical diseases because of the uncooperative attitude of
                                    the leftist Director of the Ghanaian Institute of Health.
                                    Although of marginal value, early announcement of our intention
                                    to terminate the facility would be interpreted in Ghana as an
                                    indication of our displeasure at recent developments there but
                                    should not alienate pro-Western groups. If feasible, the
                                    operation possibly on a reduced scale, in deference to Budget’s
                                        B/<gloss target="#t_P1">P</gloss> concerns, should be
                                    shifted to Sierra Leone <pb facs="0464" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> thus making the point entirely clear to <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> and at the same time
                                    achieving a favorable impact with moderate African leaders.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(8)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Psychological Warfare</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Intensive efforts should be made through psychological warfare
                                    and other means to diminish support for <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> within Ghana and nurture
                                    the conviction among the Ghanaian people that their country’s
                                    welfare and independence necessitate his removal. Themes which
                                    might be exploited include: <list>
                                        <label>(a)</label>
                                        <item>The strong non-Ghanaian element among <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>’s closest
                                            advisors and their Communist backgrounds;</item>
                                        <label>(b)</label>
                                        <item>Suppression of civil liberties as exemplified by the
                                            Preventive Detention Act, purge of the judiciary,
                                            etc.;</item>
                                        <label>(c)</label>
                                        <item>Perversion of the trade union movement without regard
                                            to the interests of the working people;</item>
                                        <label>(d)</label>
                                        <item>Announced intention to destroy civil service
                                            leadership;</item>
                                        <label>(e)</label>
                                        <item>Parliament is no longer responsive to public
                                            opinion;</item>
                                        <label>(f)</label>
                                        <item>Threat to academic freedom as evidenced by expulsion
                                            of eight professors, invasion of the campus by the mob,
                                            campaign to place political commissars in institutions
                                            of higher learning, removal of the respected headmaster
                                            of Achimoto, etc.;</item>
                                        <label>(g)</label>
                                        <item>Decline in Ghana’s international prestige and
                                            increasing alienation of sister African nations;</item>
                                        <label>(h)</label>
                                        <item>Introduction of Soviet security agents among the
                                            President’s household;</item>
                                        <label>(i)</label>
                                        <item>Serious deterioration in Ghana’s financial position
                                            resulting from <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>’s irresponsible policies;</item>
                                        <label>(j)</label>
                                        <item>Creation of a police state;</item>
                                        <label>(k)</label>
                                        <item>Likelihood that <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName>’s policies will result in Soviet
                                            bloc domination of Ghana, thereby substituting one form
                                            of colonialism for another; and</item>
                                        <label>(l)</label>
                                        <item>Increasingly precarious position of the ordinary
                                            Ghanaian citizen.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">(9)</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> an African
                                        Problem</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>We must bring home to other African leaders that <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> is a problem which they
                                    must face up to in their own national interest.</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>