<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-04-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-04-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="262" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d262">
                        <head>262. Letter From President <persName type="from">Johnson</persName> to
                            Chairman of the National Liberation Council Lieutenant General <persName corresp="#p_ALGJA1" type="to">Ankrah</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d262fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Special Head of State Correspondence File, Ghana,
                                3/24/66–10/6/66. No classification marking.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-04-14">April 14, 1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Dear General <persName corresp="#p_ALGJA1">Ankrah</persName>:</p>
                        <p>Ambassador Williams has transmitted your kind letter of March 24 to
                                me.<note n="2" xml:id="d262fn2">
                                <ref target="#d261">Document 261</ref>.</note> Its honest,
                            straightforward account of the conditions which led to the change of
                            government in Ghana and its frank assessment of the problems to be
                            solved have left a deep impression upon me.</p>
                        <p>I was particularly encouraged to see that you are alert to the dangers of
                            subversion from alien sources. Indeed, we in the United States hail your
                            Government’s efforts to wipe out arbitrary rule in Ghana as you
                            reinstate the rule of law and re-establish those institutions essential
                            to democratic government. The swift diplomatic initiatives undertaken by
                            your Government were reassuring and I look forward to the role which an
                            effective and truly independent Ghana can play in the councils of Africa
                            and of the world.</p>
                        <p>You are to be praised for your immediate recognition of the economic
                            problems facing Ghana and the appointment of an able Economic Committee.
                            Praise is also well-deserved for the prompt actions you took at home and
                            abroad to deal with both your short-term and long-term economic
                            difficulties. The United States is acutely aware of the critical state
                            of Ghana’s economy and of the immediate needs of the Ghanaian people.
                            Our airlift of twenty-five tons of canned milk last week was tangible
                            recognition of your emergency food requirements. It represents a partial
                            delivery of five hundred tons of milk to help prevent the threatened
                            famine situation you described in your letter. It is our hope that the
                                <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>–480 food commodity agreement which
                            our two Governments recently signed<note n="3" xml:id="d262fn3">Signed
                                at Accra on April 1; 17 <gloss target="#t_UST1">UST</gloss>
                                484.</note> will help substantially to tide you over the critical
                            period ahead.</p>
                        <p>I greatly appreciate your expression of support for our common belief in
                            democratic principles and the democratic way of life. This is one of the
                            surest ways of achieving the world peace we so fervently desire.</p>
                        <p>It will be my pleasure to reinforce the ties of friendship which bind the
                            United States and Ghana. Therefore, I welcome this opportunity to
                            exchange views with you and I look forward to hearing from you
                            personally from time to time on developments in Ghana.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Lyndon B. Johnson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>