<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>289. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Ethiopia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d289</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">289</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-03-18T16:06:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-03-18T16:06:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec2qYX3T6ktEaSsg" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85087216"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Moratorium</term>
                    <term ref="recwKa2RCO7F6zrUd" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Overflight</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-03-18T16:06:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-03-18T16:06:00-05:00" n="289"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d289">
                <head>289. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Ethiopia</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d289fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL 32–1 ETH–SOMALI. Confidential. Drafted by Post; cleared by
                            <persName corresp="#p_GFJ1">Galanto</persName>, Officer in Charge of
                        Sudanese Affairs Robert N. Stookey, and <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                            >Newsom</persName>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_THJ1"
                            >Tasca</persName>. Also sent to Mogadiscio and Khartoum, and repeated to
                        Asmara.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-03-18T16:06:00-05:00">March 18, 1964, 4:06 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>793. Ref: Khartoum’s 388.<note n="2" xml:id="d289fn2">Telegram 388 from Khartoum,
                        March 16, reported that both Ethiopia and Somalia had agreed to begin
                        negotiations in Khartoum on or about March 24. (Ibid.)</note> Department has
                    welcomed reftel indications Ethio-Somali negotiations now scheduled proceed on
                    or about <pb facs="0551" n="503" xml:id="pg_503"/> March 24. Would appreciate
                    confirmation and comment Embassies Addis and Mogadiscio and, if confirmed,
                    conveyance to respective host governments our satisfaction that this further
                    step toward peaceful settlement their differences under OAU aegis has now been
                    taken.</p>
                <p>For Khartoum: Department desires do all it appropriately can both through parties
                    to dispute and through Sudanese to further successful outcome without becoming
                    involved in active good offices of in any way assuming basic African
                    responsibility for solution to present problem. In discussions of matter with
                    Sudanese, if it would seem appropriate within above context, you may indicate
                    our interest in successful talks and state we have studied problem for
                    considerable period, as have Sudanese. First step, in our opinion, should be to
                    get confirmation of willingness both sides preserve cease-fire and propaganda
                    moratorium. Beyond this you may express view that failure past efforts at talks
                    due in part to attempt at outset attack basic territorial/border problem and
                    that better prospects might result if effort were made find areas where
                    understanding and cooperation were possible, apart from basic issue. To extent
                    Sudanese have opportunity discuss conduct talks with the two participants, they
                    may find useful our own thoughts on problem. You may mention that some
                    possibilities which have been mentioned and to some extent explored in past are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Mutual agreement to pursue actively with international agencies (e.g.,
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Special Fund) and other interested
                            parties possibilities for joint development Webi Shebelli River
                            Basin.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Exchange of air rights (e.g., traffic rights at Mogadiscio for
                            Ethiopian Air Lines in exchange for overflight rights for Somali
                            civilian aircraft on direct Mogadiscio-Hargeisa run).</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Somali agreement permit Ethiopian use Somali ports (Chisimaio,
                            Mogadiscio, Berbera) on preferential basis.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Ethiopian agreement permit Somali civilian motor transport transit
                            Ethiopian territory via most direct route between Hargeisa and
                            Mogadiscio when Ogaden security situation permits.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Somali agreement permit pipeline construction across Somali Republic
                            territory should oil be discovered inside Ethiopian territory.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Should progress these matters establish proper atmosphere, it might then be
                    possible proceed to discuss: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>Agreement establish joint committee to study and make recommendations
                            for improvement liaison in border areas and for regularization
                            border-crossing arrangements.</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Agreement establish joint commission to demarcate on ground
                            provisional administrative line between Ethiopia and ex-Italian portion
                            Somalia.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0552" n="504" xml:id="pg_504"/>
                <p>Would appreciate further suggestions along above lines which Embassies Addis
                    Ababa and Mogadiscio might wish provide.<note n="3" xml:id="d289fn3">In
                        Khartoum, the two sides negotiated a cease-fire beginning April 1 and agreed
                        to establish a Joint Somali-Ethiopian Border Commission to control the
                        movement of troops displaced along both sides of the border. The Commission
                        began its work on April 8.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
