<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>360. National Intelligence Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d360</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">360</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recykDuvfC6iFH3Xe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7jSz4IPswgGKPB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic growth</term>
                    <term ref="rechWxPReovs7qx7u" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Urban</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec7XCpI38AIhVpLJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional issues</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="360"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d360">
                <head>360. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d360fn1"
                        >Source: Central Intelligence Agency: Job 79–R01012A, ODDI Registry of
                            <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SNIE1"
                            >SNIE</gloss> Files. Secret; Controlled Dissem. According to a note on
                        the cover sheet, the estimate was submitted by the Director of Central
                        Intelligence and concurred in by the U.S. Intelligence Board on August
                        26.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 64.2–65</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-08-26">August 26, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">PROSPECTS FOR NIGERIA</p>
                <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                <p>To estimate probable developments in Nigeria over the next two to three
                    years.</p>
                <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>The salient question for Nigeria is whether the federal structure can
                        survive in the face of the many internal strains and tensions. The facts <pb
                            facs="0662" n="614" xml:id="pg_614"/> of geography and population assure
                        that under the constitution, the federal government will continue to be
                        dominated by the party representing the tradition-bound Moslems of the
                        North, who are generally contemptuous of the South and unsympathetic to its
                        problems. The southern regions, which are deeply divided along tribal,
                        regional, and party lines, resent northern domination. Some southern leaders
                        cooperate with the North in federal affairs realizing that only thus can
                        they and their interest reap the benefits of participation in government.
                        (Paras. 1–7)</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>The economy is based upon agriculture, the beginnings of a modest
                        industrial sector, and a promising petroleum industry. Economic development
                        is hampered by regional and tribal parochialism, the dearth of essential
                        skills, and a high incidence of corruption. There is considerable
                        unemployment and underemployment. At mid-course in a six-year development
                        plan, domestic financial resources are inadequate, although foreign capital
                        is flowing in, particularly in the petroleum industry. Some modest overall
                        economic growth is expected, but the government will be beset by rising
                        pressures from discontented jobless and urban workers. (Paras. 8–16)</item>
                    <label>C.</label>
                    <item>We do not foresee any important lessening of the internal tensions and
                        resentments which threaten the unity of the federation. If northerners and
                        southerners continue to think and act in terms of narrow regional interests,
                        there will be serious danger of a critical North-South confrontation. We
                        estimate that the continuation of the federation and the growth of an
                        integrated nation cannot be taken as assured. Nevertheless, we believe that
                        the chances are considerably better than even that Nigeria will be able to
                        avoid a breakup during the next two or three years, through the
                        disappearance of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BSAT1"
                            >Balewa</persName> from the scene would reduce these odds significantly.
                        Over the longer run, we expect a rise of discontent and radical leaders in
                        the South who will challenge and probably replace present leaders and place
                        national unity in jeopardy. The security forces appear capable of dealing
                        with most disorders, but it is doubtful if they could cope with a national
                        crisis which involved interregional or federal versus regional issues.<note
                            n="2" xml:id="d360fn2">The Director of Intelligence and Research,
                            Department of State, agrees that Nigeria is not likely to break up
                            during the next 2 to 3 years. He believes, however, that the threat to
                            continuation of the federation is not so serious as the estimate
                            suggests. He considers that the estimate does not give due weight to the
                            accommodation to northern predominance effected by southern leaders in
                            the courses of major trials of strength over the past 3 years and that
                            consequently it misinterprets present north-south relations and
                            undervalues the southern commitment to maintenance of the federation.
                            While agreeing that social and economic grievances are becoming more
                            serious, he considers that the growth of southern opposition to northern
                            leadership will be slowed and limited by southern disunity, division
                            within the labor movement, and the weakness of radical organizations. On
                            the basis of these considerations, he also disagrees with a number of
                            related points of detail and presentation in the Estimate. [Footnote in
                            the source text.]</note> (Paras. 17–25)</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follows the body of the paper.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
