<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>393. Memorandum From Edward Hamilton of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Special Assistant ( of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Special Assistant (Rostow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-11-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-11-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-11-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-11-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="393"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d393">
                <head>393. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_HEK1" type="from">Edward
                        Hamilton</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                    President’s Special Assistant (<persName type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d393fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security
                        File, <persName corresp="#p_HEK1">Hamilton</persName> Files, Nigeria.
                        Confidential. A note in Rostow’s handwriting on the source text reads: “You
                        sound sensible, as usual. R.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-11-27">November 27, 1967</date>, p.m.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">WWR:</p>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Comments on State’s proposed itinerary for a Vice Presidential trip to
                        Africa</item>
                </list>
                <p>1. I think it is a very close question whether the Vice President should go to
                    Nigeria while the civil war is going on. Joe Palmer thinks he should go, and I
                    am not comfortable arguing against a man who has spent three years as Ambassador
                    to Nigeria. But I think we would have to realize that—however carefully the Vice
                    President’s speeches are drafted—his visit would be a clear and unmistakable
                    political signal that <pb facs="0718" n="670" xml:id="pg_670"/> we have moved
                    off the hands-off position in the civil war. At the very least, the rebels would
                    broadcast strong statements to the effect that we have abandoned our
                    peace-making role and lined up with the Russians and the British in support of
                    the “neo-colonialist puppet regime in Lagos.”</p>
                <p>Of course there is a case for doing just that. Our hands-off posture rests in
                    large part on a strong suspicion that the feds can’t lick the rebels, and that
                    we will have to deal with the sovereign state of “Biafra” in the years ahead.
                    The first few months of the war seemed to confirm this prediction. The last few
                    months—since the arrival of Soviet weapons in Lagos—suggest that <persName
                        corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName>’s forces will prevail. Thus, there is an
                    argument that now is the time to repair our relations with the winning side by a
                    gratuitous and newsworthy political gesture such as a Vice Presidential
                    visit.</p>
                <p>But, on balance, I still think it is more trouble than it is worth: <list>
                        <label>(i)</label>
                        <item>It still isn’t at all clear when or if the Ibo rebels will be put out
                            of business. They are in bad trouble, but they could bounce back fast in
                            the event of a number of plausible contingencies ranging from outside
                            military help (probably Portugal, South Africa and Rhodesia) to collapse
                            of the <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1">Gowon</persName> regime (which
                            always suffers some level of internecine strife).</item>
                        <label>(ii)</label>
                        <item>If we make this gesture and somehow <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1"
                                >Gowon</persName> does get into trouble, we will be in a more
                            difficult position to refuse him military help. (We will, of course, be
                            in a difficult position anyway if a Biafran revival is based on help
                            from the Portuguese and/or the white supremacists.)</item>
                        <label>(iii)</label>
                        <item>Even if the feds win, the Vice President’s visit would make us fair
                            game as negotiators and financiers of the sticky problems of peace—a
                            large group of refugees (perhaps in the millions) fleeing across the
                            border to Cameroon, arrangements for the safety of the conquered Ibos,
                            etc.</item>
                        <label>(iv)</label>
                        <item>There is an excellent chance that a <persName corresp="#p_GGYJ1"
                                >Gowon</persName> victory would bring bloody violence ranging from
                            tribal massacres of Ibos to summary trial and execution of the rebel
                            leaders. It may not be a pretty thing to be associated with.</item>
                        <label>(v)</label>
                        <item>There is the added danger that this violence may occur while the Vice
                            President is in Nigeria, or after his public itinerary had been
                            announced, making it politically difficult for him not to go.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>For these reasons—and recognizing that it is a 51–49 bet—I come out against a
                    Vice Presidential visit to Nigeria in January.<note n="2" xml:id="d393fn2"
                        >Nigeria was dropped from the Vice President’s proposed itinerary.</note>
                </p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of other aspects of the proposed itinerary.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">EH</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
