<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>407. Memorandum From Edward Hamilton of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Special Assistant ( of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Special Assistant (Rostow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d407</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">407</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="407"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d407">
                <head>407. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_HEK1" type="from">Edward
                        Hamilton</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                    President’s Special Assistant (<persName type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d407fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security
                        File, Country File, Malawi, Visit of President <persName corresp="#p_BHK1"
                            >Hastings K. Banda</persName>, 6/8–11/67. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-06-09">June 9, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">WWR:</p>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Visit of Dr. <persName>Hastings Banda</persName>, President of Malawi—June
                        8, 1967</item>
                </list>
                <p>This will be a short, largely ceremonial visit connected with <persName
                        corresp="#p_BHK1">Banda</persName>’s attendance at EXPO–67. I have talked
                    with his advance man; he has nothing in particular on his mind he wants to raise
                    with the President. He will undoubtedly want to hear about Vietnam (he is with
                    us), and to give the President his conception of the prospects for ameliorating
                    the black/white problems of South Africa. I do not think that he will have
                    anything specific to offer in the latter regard, however.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BHK1">Banda</persName> is a unique figure in Black Africa.
                    He is the only Black African leader—except for the Prime Ministers of
                    neighboring Botswana and Lesotho—who willingly does business with the Rhodesians
                    and the South Africans. He is much criticized for this, but it is also widely
                    recognized in both black and white camps that he has no choice. Malawi is
                    heavily dependent on Rhodesia for supplies. The Malawian economy is built around
                    the white expatriate community which is highly sensitive to the morale of expats
                    in Rhodesia and Zambia. Thus, <persName corresp="#p_BHK1">Banda</persName> is
                    given very little choice by the economic facts of life; still, he is so strident
                    about currying favor with Smith and Vorster that he draws a great deal of
                    unnecessary fire from his Black African comrades.</p>
                <p>In my view, the moral of this is to treat him with impeccable manners, but not
                    overwhelming warmth. We should be particularly careful that our toast and
                    welcoming speeches don’t portray him as a great Africa-wide figure. We certainly
                    lose nothing by being correct with him, but we risk difficulties with his many
                    African enemies if we go out of our way to embrace him.</p>
                <p>You may wish to make some of the following points this afternoon: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BHK1">Banda</persName> is U.S.-educated,
                            articulate, and very pro-American. If we can keep the visit casual and
                            keep public statements away from the problems of southern Africa, this
                            short stop should go off without a hitch.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BHK1">Banda</persName> does not have any
                            particular problem in mind in visiting the President. We should minimize
                            the business aspects of the meeting, both publicly and privately.</item>
                        <pb facs="0746" n="698" xml:id="pg_698"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We should be particularly careful in drafting toasts and statements to
                            avoid identifying <persName corresp="#p_BHK1">Banda</persName> as a
                            leading figure Continent-wide.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Ed Hamilton</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d407fn2">Printed from a copy that bears <persName
                                corresp="#p_HEK1">Hamilton</persName>’s typed signature below a
                            typed notation in parentheses that reads: “dictated—not read.”</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
