<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>417. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State (Ball) to Secretary of
                    State ) to Secretary of State Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d417</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">417</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-03-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbbfe5a445f57e45" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Cuban missile crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military balance</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="rec8PCbWGrkAaOOXZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001000124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developed countries</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="developing-countries" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341" lcsh-match="exact">Less-developed countries</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-03-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="417"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d417">
                <head>417. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_BGW1"
                        type="from">Ball</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d417fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss
                            target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/IL Historical Files, Special Group Files,
                        S.G. 121, May 21, 1964. Top Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-03-17">March 17, 1964</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Proposal Regarding Holden Roberto</item>
                </list>
                <p>I wish to register an emphatic dissent to the proposal to provide [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>] to
                    Holden Roberto [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                        declassified</hi>] of the Angolan Provisional Government (<gloss
                        target="#t_GRAE1">GRAE</gloss>).<note n="2" xml:id="d417fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d415fn2">footnote 2, Document 415</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In filing this dissent, let me make it clear that I do not admire the methods or
                    policies of the Portuguese Government in Angola. Their stewardship of this area
                    is obsolete, brutal—and probably has no long-term future. In fact, I told Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SAO1">Salazar</persName> that I did not think that,
                    without a drastic change of methods, Portugal could retain its influence in
                    Angola beyond a limited span of years.<note n="3" xml:id="d417fn3">As President
                            <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName>’s Personal
                        Representative, Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>
                        visited Lisbon and met with Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_SAO1"
                            >Antonio De Oliveira Salazar</persName> and Foreign Minister Franco
                        Nogueira August 29–30 and September 6–7, 1963. For a record of <persName
                            corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>’s meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_KRF1">Kennedy</persName> to debrief him on these
                        discussions, see <ref target="frus1961-63v21#pg_571">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations, 1961–1963, vol. XXI</hi>, p.
                            571</ref>. Records of <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>’s
                        mission are in the Department of State, Conference Files: Lot 66 D 110, CF
                        2301; ibid., Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7
                            US/<persName corresp="#p_BGW1">BALL</persName>, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 19 PORT, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> AFR–US, and
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> AFR–PORT; and Kennedy Library,
                        National Security Files, Countries Series, Portugal Subjects, Ball Mission.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>’s own account of his mission
                        to Portugal is in The Past Has Another Pattern: Memoirs (New York: W.W.
                        Norton &amp; Company, 1982), pp. 276–279.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0773" n="725" xml:id="pg_725"/>
                <p>I should perhaps point out, however, that I would estimate a longer span than
                    would many of my colleagues since I think the Portuguese are dug in and
                    determined to stay. The French stuck it out in Algeria during seven years of
                    fighting. While Portugal is not France, neither are the Bakongo Algerians.</p>
                <p>The core of my position is that, in developing an Angolan policy we should not be
                    over-persuaded either by sympathy for the underdog or abstract libertarian
                    principles. We should look at this question hard-headedly in terms of the United
                    States national interest. In those terms, I should like to set out my objections
                    to the current proposal.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">First, I object to this proposal as a destructive
                                moral precedent for the American Government.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The doling out of this money will constitute double-dealing on the part
                            of the United States Government. You have on at least two occasions (in
                            Lisbon and Athens in 1962) assured the Portuguese Foreign Minister that
                            we engaged in no activities with Holden Roberto that we could not
                            disclose to the Portuguese. You did tell the Foreign Minister that we
                            had had for some time an intelligence arrangement for Holden Roberto
                                [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                declassified</hi>]. Pursuant to my instructions, I categorically
                            assured Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SAO1">Salazar</persName> that we were
                            not providing assistance to Holden Roberto—and, by implication, that we
                            did not intend to do so.</p>
                        <p>To embark on a covert program of aid to Holden Roberto at this point
                            would be a direct violation of confidence. I cannot believe that it is
                            either good morals or good policy to put the United States Government in
                            that position.</p>
                        <p>We all recognized at the time of the Cuban missile crisis that the United
                            States could not act out of character without losing something of its
                            own self-respect. If it was true then, it is true now. And there are
                            practical considerations as well. The question of good faith cannot be
                            considered solely in the framework of United States-Portuguese
                            relations. If we break confidence with Portugal—an acknowledged ally—we
                            shall contribute to a general mistrust of our government that can cause
                            us irreparable damage in the whole area of our international
                            relations.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Second, I do not believe that the United States should
                                undertake a joint venture with the Communists to undermine a Western
                                ally.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Agency presentation states: “In January, 1964, <persName
                                corresp="#p_RH3">Roberto</persName> announced his willingness to
                            receive military aid from the Bloc but insisted that such aid be given
                            without commitments”. In arguing for the proposal, the presentation
                            states: “Nationalist leaders intend to seek Bloc arms in order to
                            satisfy the military wing of the movement, upon which their ability to
                            retain leadership ultimately depends. As long as Bloc military support
                            can be controlled by a friendly Congo move, and Bloc personnel excluded,
                            this presents no immediate danger to United States objectives.”</p>
                        <pb facs="0774" n="726" xml:id="pg_726"/>
                        <p>The United States role under the proposal would be to provide
                            “constructive” assistance, including the “administrative expenses
                            incurred by the” Provisional Government, “travel and representational
                            costs”, etc.</p>
                        <p>From this I take it that the proposal assumes that the Communists would
                            provide the military weapons while we—as the junior partner—would
                            provide the costs of administration of the Provisional Government. With
                            our combined help <persName corresp="#p_RH3">Roberto</persName> and his
                            colleagues would set about trying to undermine our ally.</p>
                        <p>I do not find this an attractive posture for my country.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Third, I believe it wrong to assume that we can
                                exercise “leverage over the direction of the Angolan nationalist
                                movement and … strengthen our relationship with its
                                    leadership,”<note n="4" xml:id="d417fn4">The omitted word in the
                                    quotation is “to.” The quotation is from the March 6 proposal
                                    cited in <ref target="#d2">footnote 2</ref> above.</note> by
                                providing money for administrative support on a covert basis.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The proposal assumes that United States involvement would not become
                            known except to <persName corresp="#p_RH3">Roberto</persName> and his
                            immediate associates. If this be the case, then the bulk of the Angolan
                            nationalists would be fighting with arms known to be provided by Bloc
                            sources, while only <persName corresp="#p_RH3">Roberto</persName> and
                            one or two of his colleagues would know that the United States had
                            helped at all. How would this give us effective leverage?</p>
                        <p>I doubt that the United States can build much influence in this manner.
                            At the moment, I understand that <persName corresp="#p_RH3"
                                >Roberto</persName>’s hold on the movement is precarious. He is, I
                            am told, a poor administrator and a rather indifferent leader. According
                            to a report received today, he may be ousted by his colleagues on the
                            grounds he is an “American tool”.</p>
                        <p>One accusation against <persName corresp="#p_RH3">Roberto</persName> is
                            that he has been unable to raise adequate funds. What would be the
                            result if he suddenly appeared with substantial funds? Against the
                            background of accusations already made wouldn’t it be evident that he
                            was getting money from the United States? If so, wouldn’t this become
                            promptly known to the Portuguese?</p>
                        <p>If, on the other hand, his followers assumed that he was getting money
                            from the Bloc, wouldn’t this strengthen the Communists?</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Fourth, I do not believe it in the United States
                                interest to encourage a state of terror in northern Angola.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>At the moment, the military situation in northern Angola is at a
                            stand-off, and the Portuguese are feeling increasingly confident. The
                            Agency presentation states: “The Portuguese military over the past year
                            has succeeded in containing the nationalist forces, but it has been
                            unable to put down the rebellion or put an end to rebel activities.”</p>
                        <pb facs="0775" n="727" xml:id="pg_727"/>
                        <p>Our administrative funds will not significantly alter the military
                            balance. Portugal has 40,000 troops in Angola. I think it is prepared to
                            fight to the finish (although it may withdraw from Mozambique and
                            concentrate in Angola). Under these circumstances, it is almost certain
                            that—without regard to whether or not we give him financial
                                help—<persName corresp="#p_RH3">Roberto</persName> will in time be
                            driven to terrorist methods. This happened in 1961. It will surely
                            happen again as the struggle grows more bitter—and, with increased
                            bitterness, becomes more racist in character.</p>
                        <p>I put, therefore, what I regard as a relevant question: All sentiment
                            aside, is it in the interest of the United States to become an accessory
                            to terrorizing Portuguese settlers in Angola? Isn’t it rather in our
                            interest to discourage such a state of affairs in the heart of Africa?
                            Or, if we cannot discourage it, shouldn’t we at least avoid associating
                            ourselves with it?</p>
                        <p>To put the question in larger terms, is there any hurry about Angola?
                            Left by themselves, the Portuguese will probably be able to sustain a
                            military stalemate for several years. While this may be a continuing
                            source of frustration to the other African states, I don’t see why it
                            need concern us except in the United Nations.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Fifth, is it in our interest to stimulate a Portuguese
                                invasion of the Congo?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Portuguese are known to have mobilized a substantial cadre of
                            Katanganese gendarmes. If nationalist activities grow more intense, I
                            think they will almost certainly move to destroy the nationalist camps
                            in the Congo—particularly if they feel we are helping the nationalists.
                            This can create major problems for us and the Adoula Government.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Sixth, I do not think that a payment to <persName
                                    corresp="#p_RH3">Roberto</persName> is either necessary or
                                useful.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I do not think we have to run and get ahead of each nationalist movement
                            in order to keep it out of Communist hands. Genuine nationalist
                            movements have shown themselves resistant to Communist domination, and
                            the test as to the direction of a regime is much more likely to occur
                            when the revolution is completed and the new nation is being
                            established.</p>
                        <p>For this reason, I question the thesis that underlies the present
                            proposal—that we must give covert financial aid to the Angolan
                            Nationalists if they are to be friendly with us after independence.</p>
                        <p>We have regularly supported the principle of self-determination in the
                            United Nations and in our continuing dialogue with the Portuguese. I
                            think we should persist in that course, which is in our great historic
                            tradition. It is because of our open adherence to this tradition that we
                            have won the leadership of the newly-emerging nations.</p>
                        <p>To assume, however, that there is any direct and inevitable relation
                            between financial help to revolutionaries and our relations with a
                            post-revolutionary regime is not borne out by the historical facts.
                            During the Second World War we helped Ho Chi Minh in Indochina and he is
                            no friend today. We have, for the most part, established useful working
                            rela tions <pb facs="0776" n="728" xml:id="pg_728"/> with the new
                            governments of Asia and Africa, yet we did not supply them covert
                            support during their revolutionary days. What we have done is to help
                            the new nations that have emerged from revolutionary struggles, and our
                            continuing help is to a considerable extent the basis of our
                            relationship.</p>
                        <p>One lesson can be clearly read in our recent experience: If the question,
                            “What have you done for me lately?” reflects political reality, it also
                            reflects the reality of our relations with the less-developed
                            countries.</p>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Finally, I think it unrealistic to assume that, over a period
                        of time, Portugal will remain unaware of our financial assistance to
                            <persName corresp="#p_RH3">Roberto</persName>.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The dossier prepared for you by the Portuguese Foreign Minister describing the
                    Angolan camps would indicate that their intelligence is competent. Once the
                    Portuguese are morally certain that we are providing financial help—even if they
                    cannot prove it—our credibility will be wholly destroyed. The question of
                    credibility again is not limited to US-Portuguese relations, since the
                    Portuguese will make it known throughout <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    circles that we have been treating them dishonestly.</p>
                <p>My conclusion from all this, therefore, is quite clear. I see no objection to
                    looking after Angolan refugees or even providing them with scholarship
                    grants—provided we tell the Portuguese. But I am against furtive aid directed at
                    undermining the interests of our ally.</p>
                <p>While the observations in this memorandum have been addressed to the proposal to
                    provide funds to Holden Roberto, [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines of source text not
                        declassified</hi>].</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">George W. Ball</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="5" xml:id="d417fn5">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
