<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-03-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="43" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                        <head>43. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG2" type="from">Bundy</persName>) and <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Robert W.
                                Komer</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to President
                                <persName type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d43fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File,
                                Country File, Libya, Vol. I, 11/63–6/64. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-03-17">March 17, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>There seems little alternative but to agree now to renegotiate our Libyan
                            base agreement, in hopes this will defuse the issue. Our best friends in
                            the Libyan Government (the King and <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>)
                            plead that we do so. They’ve panicked in the face of an outburst of
                            Libyan nationalism, and face an aroused Parliament demanding prompt
                            abrogation of the US/<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> treaties. Nasser
                            started off the parade by criticizing the bases, but clearly both his
                            action and Libyan popular hysteria were stimulated by the Arab-Israeli
                            issue.</p>
                        <p>Our ability to resist is undermined by <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                            agreement to renegotiate its base rights. Actually, the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> treaty had a renegotiation clause, while
                            ours is legally good till 1971. Yet if we stall now, we’ll almost
                            certainly face a Libyan parliamentary motion for abrogation which the
                            regime will be unwilling to block. We want to save this regime (the best
                            we could have), and also protect our oil investment, now $670 million.
                            So State, our Embassy, and our Libyan friends recommend we be
                            forthcoming now to sidetrack demands for abrogation. We would then hope
                            to spin out negotiations, and finally agree to a reduced tenure which
                            will buy us three-five more years. Much will depend on whether external
                            factors affecting US-Arab relations set the Libyans off again. But it’s
                            worth the try.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <list>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName>
                                            <hi rend="strong">McG. Bundy</hi>
                                        </persName>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">
                                            <hi rend="strong">R.W. Komer</hi>
                                        </persName>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>