<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>433. Circular Airgram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Portugal</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d433</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">433</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-08-23T17:37:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-08-23T17:37:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="recPjGjlVHIlHmzym" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112903"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Repatriation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-08-23T17:37:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-08-23T17:37:00-05:00" n="433"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d433">
                <head>433. Circular Airgram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Portugal</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d433fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> PORT–US. Secret. Drafted by
                        Funseth and Robert H. Edwards of <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>; cleared by George B. High of <gloss
                            target="#t_AFC1">AFC</gloss>, Fredericks, Assistant Secretary for
                        International Organization Affairs <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Joseph J.
                            Sisco</persName>, George L. Warren of <gloss target="#t_GPM1"
                            >G/PM</gloss>, Harry A. Quinn of <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>/BR,
                            <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> Deputy Assistant Administrator for
                        Africa Herman Kleine, Thomas Pape of <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss>/ITED,
                        and Col. Smyser, Lloyd, and Colonel Lardner of OASD/<gloss target="#t_ISA1"
                            >ISA</gloss>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_LJM2"
                            >Leddy</persName>. Repeated to Luanda and Lourenco Marques.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>-2167</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-08-23T18:37:00-04:00">August 23, 1965, 6:37 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Instructions to Lisbon to: (1) Reply to Foreign Minister’s Complaints of
                        U.S. Policy; (2) Reaffirm U.S. Interest in Azores Base and Loran-C
                        Negotiations; (3) Introduce New U.S. Proposal for a Peaceful Resolution of
                        the Portuguese African Question</item>
                </list>
                <p>With timing at your discretion, the Department would appreciate your seeking an
                    early occasion to continue the discussion with Foreign Minister Franco Nogueira
                    in the light of his meeting with the Secretary and the Under Secretary, June 18,
                    1965, and of your earlier conversations <pb facs="0803" n="755" xml:id="pg_755"
                    /> with him in Lisbon, January 11 and March 5, 1965. We see some advantage to
                    your conveying our oral responses to his catalogue of complaints at the same
                    time as you broach your plan for a peaceful resolution of the Portuguese African
                    problem. Additionally, because the Foreign Minister presented his complaints in
                    the context of a request for a clarification of U.S. policy and of our pending
                    requests for a renewal of the Azores bases agreement and the location of Loran-C
                    sites in Portugal, we would suggest you make reaffirmations of basic U.S. policy
                    objectives of maintaining friendly and constructive relations with Portugal and
                    of our interest in both the Azores bases and Loran-C.</p>
                <p>We recognize this presents you with a formidable agenda for one meeting but the
                    placing of your plan for Africa in the context of a continuation of earlier
                    meetings might provide a favorable context to introduce your new initiative.
                    However, if in your judgment it would be preferable to separate the response to
                    the complaints and the reaffirmation of our interests in the Azores and Loran-C
                    from your African proposal, you are authorized to request separate meetings.
                    Also, if you believe it desirable, in order to assure that the Prime Minister
                    has an accurate account of our responses to the complaints presented by the
                    Foreign Minister and of your proposal, you may make a similar oral presentation
                    to him—tailoring it for the occasion.</p>
                <p>There follows an outline of the points we would like you to make in your
                    presentation.</p>
                <p>[Here follow Sections I–III.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">IV. <persName corresp="#p_AGWJ1">Anderson</persName> Plan for
                        Resolving the Portuguese African Question.</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>In introducing your proposal for a peaceful solution of the Portuguese
                        African question, you may wish to set the stage by informing the Foreign
                        Minister that you have been instructed to pick up his conversation with the
                        Secretary at the point where the Secretary asked why Portugal did not hoist
                        a flag around which its friends could rally. You should reiterate the
                        remarks of the Under Secretary, June 18, that the U.S. has a good impression
                        of what Portugal is doing in Angola and Mozambique and that we do not
                        believe the Portuguese have as much to be afraid of as the Minister
                        suggested in his reluctance to endorse a public acceptance by Portugal of a
                        fixed date for self-determination. You should also state, that before
                        discussing the proposal, which the U.S. would like Portugal to consider, the
                        Foreign Minister should recall Secretary’s June 18 reaffirmation that the
                        U.S. would accept the results of a genuine plebiscite, notwithstanding a
                        possible rejection by certain other states, and that we noted with great
                        interest the Foreign Minister’s reply to the Secretary that the Portuguese
                        agreed to the U.S. concept of self-determination. Moreover, we would like to
                        reaffirm the Under Secretary’s observation that if there is a possibility of
                        the Portuguese and the Africans working out a mutually satisfactory
                        arrangement, the communists could be out <pb facs="0804" n="756"
                            xml:id="pg_756"/> and the security of the Portuguese African territories
                        protected. Finally, it is the U.S. hope, as stated by the Secretary June 18,
                        that Portugal would help itself in seeking a peaceful solution and a U.S.
                        fear that if Portugal hews to the status quo, its position in Africa will
                        steadily weaken. With these thoughts conveyed to the Foreign Minister, you
                        are authorized to orally introduce your proposal as outlined in Embassy
                        telegrams 652, April 13; 799, June 18; 38, July 23,<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d433fn2">None printed. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_AID1"
                                >AID</gloss> PORT)</note> and Department telegrams 671, June 9,<note
                            n="3" xml:id="d433fn3">Telegram 671 to Lisbon, June 9, stated that the
                            present juncture offered an opportunity for Portugal and the Africans to
                            reach agreement on a peaceful resolution of their differences, and noted
                            that the key elements of such a solution would have to be a transition
                            period leading to self-determination and cessation of
                            nationalist-inspired violence and subversion. (Ibid., <gloss
                                target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 10 PORT)</note> and 19, July 19.<note
                            n="4" xml:id="d433fn4">Not printed. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_AID1"
                                >AID</gloss> PORT)</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Summary of <persName corresp="#p_AGWJ1"
                                >Anderson</persName> Plan—In interest of clarity, there is
                            summarized below your plan as modified by above referenced
                            telegrams.</hi>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is proposed that the U.S. attempt to persuade the Portuguese Government to
                    publicly accept the principle of self-determination for its African territories
                    on the basis of a definite timetable. This action would be combined with a
                    suspension of African nationalist anti-Portuguese activities during that period
                    and carefully tailored political assurances and specified economic inducements
                    being offered to the Portuguese Government in order to forestall the inevitable
                    argument that any deadline would be bound to be telescoped drastically. The
                    proposal is based on the estimate that, at the present juncture when the
                    Portuguese are in a relatively strong position in both Angola and Mozambique,
                    there is an opportunity for Portugal and the Africans to reach agreement for a
                    peaceful resolution of their differences. Key elements of the solution would
                    have to be a transition period leading to self-determination and a cessation of
                    nationalist-inspired violence and subversion, as well as inspiration and support
                    for such actions by the African governments concerned. A full range of choice
                    would be left to the people, and would include maintenance of the <pb
                        facs="0805" n="757" xml:id="pg_757"/> present relationship with Portugal,
                    autonomy within a Portuguese commonwealth, or full independence. Aim of the U.S.
                    proposal would be a peaceful transition and creation of stable societies in the
                    Portuguese African territories no matter what political decisions are made by
                    the people.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Significant Points to Which the Portuguese would have to
                        agree:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Acceptance of a fixed date, for a broadly based plebiscite or
                                referendum in Portugal’s African territories. A full range of choice
                                would be given to all of the inhabitants, and would include
                                maintenance of the present relationship with Portugal, autonomy
                                within a Portuguese commonwealth, or full independence. Plebiscite
                                would have to be free and open and observed by U.N. and O.A.U.
                                representatives. In this initial approach, the U.S. would not
                                propose a specific number of years when the plebiscite should take
                                place but would state that an integral part of the plan would be a
                                Portuguese announcement of a specific time period. In the last
                                analysis, the U.S. would expect and prefer that this question be
                                worked out between the Portuguese and the Africans.</p>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_reftel1"
                                    >Reftel</gloss>s reflect Department’s views on the time period
                                which the Africans would seek and what might be a possible
                                compromise. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Accelerated interim Portuguese effort to improve the social, economic
                                and political status of all of the people of the provinces.</p>
                            <p>(See paragraph 4g, below, for possible assistance to Portugal by
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies.)</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>Granting of increasingly free political activity in the territories in
                            order to assure a meaningful plebiscite, as well as granting full
                            amnesty and repatriation of all refugees. <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                                >FYI</gloss>: Problem of amnesty for nationalist leaders would
                            probably be qualified as Portuguese may adamantly refuse to accept
                            certain such individuals whom they regard as “terrorists.” While we
                            recognize this qualification could be a major stumbling block, we would
                            not want the exclusion of a few individuals to impede the over-all
                            progress on this grave and important problem, affecting the millions of
                            inhabitants of these provinces. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                            >FYI</gloss>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">3. Significant Points to Which Neighboring African States
                        would have to agree:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>a.</label>
                    <item>Refusal to permit the use of their national territory as a training or
                        operating base for any anti-Portuguese forces during the interim period
                        preceding the plebiscite.</item>
                    <label>b.</label>
                    <item>Active support by African governments concerned for a cessation of all
                        nationalist-inspired violence and subversion.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">4. Significant Points to which other Selected Nations, most
                        especially the U.S. and other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> partners
                        would have to agree:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>a.</label>
                    <item>U.S. and other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies would
                        encourage Africans to accept and would urge fulfillment of terms of such an
                        agreement.</item>
                    <label>b.</label>
                    <item>Publicly come out in full support of the agreement once it is
                        adopted.</item>
                    <label>c.</label>
                    <item>Publicly condemn any violation of terms should such occur subsequently
                        from any quarter. We would make all parties concerned aware of our position
                        on this point from the outset.</item>
                    <label>d.</label>
                    <item>U.S. would sympathetically consider Portuguese requests for support for
                        any Portuguese complaint at the U.N. if we were satisfied that deliberate
                        and organized violations had taken place.</item>
                    <pb facs="0806" n="758" xml:id="pg_758"/>
                    <label>e.</label>
                    <item>U.S. would be responsive to Portuguese requests for arms purchases if we
                        were satisfied that deliberate and organized violations had taken place.
                            <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>: Likewise, if Portugal violated
                        terms of agreement, the U.S. would consider sympathetically African requests
                        for support. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>f.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>: U.S. would guarantee to maintain
                        maximum political pressure on Portugal so that rights of all concerned would
                        be protected within the Portuguese multi-racial communities, without
                        distinction or race, creed or color. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1"
                        >FYI</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>g.</label>
                    <item>During transition period, the U.S. would itself provide and would
                        encourage other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies to provide, if
                        Portugal so requests, economic and technical support for Portuguese efforts
                        to develop its African territories. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>:
                        Question of participation and observation by U.N. and its specialized
                        agencies in development programs and of possible invitation to <gloss
                            target="#t_OAU1">OAU</gloss> member states to provide economic and
                        technical assistance are considered to be second-echelon problems to be
                        worked out with Portugal only after broad agreement in principle had proven
                        to be possible. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>h.</label>
                    <item>At such time as Portugal agrees to U.S. proposal, we would propose to make
                        an initial approach to selected African leaders before Portugal would
                        undertake such discussions. We would hope that Portuguese talks with African
                        leaders would initiate a dialogue which might result in meaningful
                        negotiations.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Please confirm by telegram when you have met with the Foreign Minister as it is
                    the Department’s intention to convey the substance of the foregoing to the
                    Portuguese Ambassador following your meeting in Lisbon.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d433fn5">In telegram 93 from Lisbon, September 3, <persName
                            corresp="#p_AGWJ1">Anderson</persName> reported that he had conveyed the
                        U.S. proposal to Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_NF1"
                            >Nogueira</persName> on September 2. The Foreign Minister responded that
                        he could not comment immediately and officially upon a proposal of such
                        scope, which would require personal consideration by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SAO1">Salazar</persName> and other members of the
                        government. (Ibid., PORT–US)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
