<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-05-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-05-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="462" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d462">
                        <head>462. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                            African Affairs (<persName type="from">Williams</persName>) to the Under
                            Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_BGW1" type="to">Ball</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d462fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 19 RHOD. Secret. Drafted by Kinsey, and cleared by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_JTM1">Judd</persName> and Charles A.
                                Schmitz of <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>. Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName>, Harriman, L, <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-05-10">May 10, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>US Contingency Planning for Southern Rhodesian <gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>You have requested Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FJW4">Fredericks</persName>
                            to provide you with information concerning our planning for
                            contingencies arising from a possible unilateral declaration of
                            independence (<gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss>) in Southern Rhodesia.
                            The following information summarizes our preparations to the present
                            time.</p>
                        <p>The basic US Contingency Paper for Southern Rhodesia of July 2, 1964<note n="2" xml:id="d462fn2">A copy of the Southern Rhodesia Contingency
                                Paper of July 2, 1964, is ibid.</note> is still valid. The
                            Contingency Paper (copy attached) is based on the assumption of a
                            severance of constitutional relations with <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> by the Southern Rhodesian Government. This could occur
                            by a <gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss> of the <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> or by usurpation of Crown authority through “enacting”
                            independence by a two-thirds majority in the <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss> Parliament.</p>
                        <p>The Legal Adviser’s Office has prepared an addendum to the <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss> Contingency Paper which has now completed
                            Department clearance (copy attached).<note n="3" xml:id="d462fn3">Not
                                printed.</note> The addendum discusses the legal status of the
                            American Consulate General in Salisbury in the event of a <gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss>. It is based on our policies of
                            supporting the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> in our relationships
                            with a post-<gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss> Southern Rhodesia and of
                            retaining an official US presence in <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss>
                            for as long a time as feasible.</p>
                        <p>Our Emergency and Evacuation Plan is current and no major problems are
                            foreseen in evacuating the 1825 American citizens and their fireside
                            aliens resident in <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss> at the end of March
                            1965. The country is divided into seven areas; each area is the
                            responsibility of a “key man.” Seven telephone calls could alert the key
                            men who in turn would alert US citizens in their areas. In addition,
                            most missionary groups maintain radio contact with their outposts.</p>
                        <p>The US position in case of a severance of constitutional relations
                            between <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> would be largely dependent on the extent to which
                                <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and the Commonwealth would go in
                            imposing punitive action on Southern Rhodesia. US resources available
                            for use in case of <gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss> are limited, but
                            our national interest dictates support for <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and the Commonwealth <pb facs="0846" n="798" xml:id="pg_798"/> action. We are now engaged in informal
                            consultation with <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and the Government
                            of Zambia on a possible contingency operation to save Zambia, which is
                            dependent on its copper exports, from economic collapse in case normal
                            transportation, electricity and coal from <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss> are cut off for any reason following a <gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The current US planning position in case of a <gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss> is based on support for <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and Commonwealth punitive actions which were most
                            recently threatened by <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Prime Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName> on April 29. These
                            would be of an economic and financial nature primarily. Punitive
                            military action by <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> has been
                            eliminated from <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> planning, at least
                            for the present. Recognition of any minority <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> by the US soon after a <gloss target="#t_UDI1">UDI</gloss> would be politically impossible but we would attempt to
                            maintain a skeleton staff at our Consulate General as a symbol to <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss> Africans of US concern for them. We would
                            cooperate with Commonwealth and African nations working toward a
                            solution of the <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss> problem. While our
                            traditional policy does not favor recognition of Governments-in-Exile,
                            we would maintain friendly contact with major <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss> exile organizations. We would support the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> in its appeal to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Security Council immediately upon the
                            severance of constitutional relations between <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SRG1">SRG</gloss> and would
                            support <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> endeavors to mobilize <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and world support for economic and
                            financial action against the rebel colony. <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> has hinted guardedly that it might not oppose the entry
                            into <gloss target="#t_SR1">SR</gloss> of an international military
                            force under certain conditions and guarantees.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>