<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>565. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                    International Organization Affairs (Sisco) and the Deputy Assistant Secretary
                    for African Affairs () and the Deputy Assistant Secretary for African Affairs
                    (Quimby) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d565</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">565</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnar4LCjCtlPtXG" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">Free flow of
                        information</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recXuFW8WO1tqBrVK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="rec9yKWGNvCFmqmdD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="565"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d565">
                <head>565. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for International
                    Organization Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="from">Sisco</persName>)
                    and the Deputy Assistant Secretary for African Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_QTHE1">Quimby</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d565fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 16 RHOD. Confidential. Sent
                        through Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName>.
                        Drafted by Fain and Thomas J. Carolan of <gloss target="#t_IO1"
                            >IO</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> on March 6–7, and
                        cleared by Brown, Goldstein, and Edward W. Holmes of <gloss
                            target="#t_AFSE1">AFSE</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-06-10">June 10, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Security Council Recommendation for the
                        Withdrawal of all Consulates from Southern Rhodesia</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Security Council’s new Rhodesian resolution, adopted unanimously on May 29,
                    presents a special problem for us since it emphasizes “the need for the
                    withdrawal of all consular and trade representation in Southern Rhodesia . …” At
                    the time of the vote Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAJ1">Goldberg</persName>
                    explained that we would give careful consideration to this non-mandatory
                    provision but, in doing so, would have “to take into account our profound belief
                    in a free flow of information and communication throughout the world, which we
                    feel should apply to Rhodesia as well.” He pointed out that the US has no trade
                    representation in Southern Rhodesia.</p>
                <p>In terms of our public position as well as the Department’s own requirements, it
                    is essential that we decide promptly whether to remove or maintain our consular
                    establishment in Salisbury. After considering carefully all the factors
                    involved, we have concluded that it is in our interest to maintain the already
                    sharply reduced staff of the Consulate General, at least for the time being and
                    barring such developments as a mass exodus by other governments from the
                    territory. In any case, we propose to leave the question open so that should we
                    consider it proper we may withdraw the consular staff in the future. We
                    recognize that a decision to remain in Salisbury will draw some criticism from
                    the Afro-Asians and that, by virtue of being the biggest target, we can expect
                    to receive more than our share of criticism in the United Nations.</p>
                <p>The following considerations, however, argue in favor of maintaining our small
                    staff in Salisbury: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Reporting</hi>—Political and economic information
                            obtained at first hand in Salisbury has proved valuable. The Consulate
                            General’s reporting, particularly with respect to the effect of
                            sanctions on the Rhodesian economy, has helped us base our policy on our
                            own information.</item>
                        <pb facs="1001" n="953" xml:id="pg_953"/>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Protection for American Citizens—There are over 1,000 American
                            citizens in Southern Rhodesia, some three-fourths of whom are
                            missionaries and their families. Our Consular officials in Salisbury
                            perform a number of essential services for these people in passport and
                            citizenship matters and welfare activities.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Intentions of Other Governments</hi>—Ten foreign
                            consulates have remained in Salisbury since 1965. The Japanese have
                            announced the closing of theirs on June 5. (This action by Japan—which
                            claims no nationals resident in Southern Rhodesia—is an effort to regain
                            some favor with the Afro-Asians after being a prominent sanctions-buster
                            for some time.) We do not expect that many of the other governments
                            concerned (Belgium, France, West Germany, Italy, Netherlands, Portugal,
                            South Africa and Switzerland) will follow suit. The <gloss
                                target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> will maintain its residual mission
                            there.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>We believe the advantages of retaining our Consulate General at Salisbury
                    outweigh the disadvantages. We would propose, therefore, to make our intentions
                    on this subject known shortly after the President signs the Executive Order
                    implementing the mandatory provisions of the Security Council resolution. We
                    would say that, although the matter will remain under continuing review, we
                    intend to maintain our small staff in Salisbury for the time being. We would
                    emphasize our convictions about the free flow of information and communications
                    everywhere, and we would lean heavily on the rationale of providing essential
                    services for Americans residing in Southern Rhodesia. A draft statement for
                    press guidance is attached.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations<note n="2" xml:id="d565fn2">Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> initialed his approval of
                            both recommendations on June 17.</note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>That, subject to future developments, we continue to maintain our consular
                        office at Salisbury.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>That the decision be made public shortly after the issuance of the US
                        Executive Order, along the lines of the attached press guidance.<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d565fn3">The attachment is not printed.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
