<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-05-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="639" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d639">
                        <head>639. Briefing Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                            International Organization Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="from">Sisco</persName>) to the Under Secretary of State for
                            Political Affairs (<persName type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d639fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 19 SW AFR/<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. Confidential. Drafted by Elizabeth
                                Ann Brown.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-05-11">May 11, 1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>“Your Luncheon with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_THLT1">Taswell</persName> of South Africa</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Since I understand that you are lunching today with the South African
                            Ambassador, I thought it might be helpful for you to have a current
                            rundown of the situation in New York and of where we stand on our
                            efforts to initiate a dialogue with South Africa on South West
                            Africa.</p>
                        <p>You may recall my comments at a recent staff meeting to the effect that
                            there were indications the South Africans were trying to drive a wedge
                            between Washington and New York, or at least to see whether there are
                            not some differences in approach between Washington and New York, which
                            South Africa can exploit, on how to achieve the objectives of General
                            Assembly Resolution 2145 (attached)<note n="2" xml:id="d639fn2">See <ref target="#d636fn4">footnote 4, Document 636</ref>; not
                                printed.</note> for which we voted last October. I know you
                            recognize how important it is for all of us to speak with one voice at
                            this particular juncture when we are seeking to negotiate a satisfactory
                            resolution in New York which will keep all doors open.</p>
                        <p>The current situation in New York is very fluid. The Afro-Asians have
                            tabled an extreme resolution looking toward immediate <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> takeover in South West Africa and calling
                            for necessary implementing action by the Security Council in the event
                            South Africa defies the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. The Soviet
                            bloc have told them they cannot support this.</p>
                        <p>The Latin Americans have been discussing possible amendments with the
                            Afro-Asians which would stress the necessity for dialogue and which
                            would leave implicit the threat of possible enforcement action by the
                            Security Council. We have been working with Canada, Italy and the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> on a proposal of our own which would
                            provide for a <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Council and a <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> representative to continue the efforts to
                            find practical ways to achieve the objectives of Resolution 2145. The
                            Afro-Asians describe our proposal as involving new delays in the desired
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> take-over in South West Africa.
                            However, discussions are continuing since the Afro-Asians appreciate the
                            desirability of maintaining as much unanimity as possible in support of
                            the objectives of Resolution 2145. The Scandinavians also have been
                            working on a proposal setting up a <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            body to follow through on Resolution 2145.</p>
                        <pb facs="1128" n="1080" xml:id="pg_1080"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">A Possible Dialogue with South Africa on South West
                                Africa</hi>. Just before the Special Session convened the South
                            African Ambassador in Washington delivered an aide-memoire, which was
                            subsequently handed to all diplomatic representatives in Pretoria and
                            circulated at the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, which expressed
                            South Africa’s willingness “to discuss with any other genuinely
                            interested Government the problems of development in South West Africa
                            provided that Government is prepared in good faith to make a
                            constructive contribution to such discussion and is not solely looking
                            for ways and means of implementing the recent General Assembly
                            Resolution.”</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador confirmed that this language meant discussions without
                            preconditions and did not exclude discussion of the implementation of
                                <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Resolution 2145. Just before the
                            Special <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> convened Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAJ1">Goldberg</persName> suggested to <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Foreign Secretary Brown the possibility
                            of exploring prospects for a dialogue at a London meeting between the
                            two of them and South African Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MH2">Muller</persName>. Brown was favorably disposed but
                            believed any such effort should be deferred until after the Special UNGA
                            took action. Consequently we have deliberately not responded to the
                            aide-memoire since so much necessarily depends upon the outcome of the
                            Special Session.<note n="3" xml:id="d639fn3">On May 19, the U.N. General
                                Assembly adopted Resolution 2248 (S–V) by a vote of 85 to 2
                                (Portugal and South Africa), with 30 abstentions (including the
                                United States). It established an 11-member U.N. Council for South
                                West Africa, responsible to the General Assembly, to administer the
                                Territory until independence. The Council was to be based in South
                                West Africa and was requested to contact South Africa immediately to
                                arrange for transfer of the Territory. For text, see American
                                Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1967, pp. 264–266.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>