<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Chile ( (Bowers))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-10-29T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-10-29T22:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-29T22:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-29T22:00:00-05:00" n="146"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.74/547: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-29T23:00:00-04:00"
                            >October 29, 1942—11 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1302. Your 1808, October 24, noon. Please seek an early interview with President
                    Ríos for the purpose of bringing the following to his attention:</p>
                <p>Since the Axis missions in Santiago have been denied the use of secret code or
                    cipher on circuits extending directly out of the hemisphere, they have continued
                    to communicate in secret code or cipher with their Governments by way of the
                    Axis missions in Buenos Aires, resorting to the commercial circuits that connect
                    the two capitals. They are, consequently, still free to transmit to their
                    Governments by secret rapid communication, as they have in the past, information
                    that may lead to the loss of ships and lives of the American republics. This
                    Government is most anxious that means may be found for bringing under control
                    this last channel of secret rapid communication by Axis agents in Chile with
                    their Governments, and it feels that it can count on the sympathy and friendly
                    cooperation of the Chilean Government in achieving this objective.</p>
                <p>Having made the foregoing clear to President Ríos, you should ask for any
                    suggestions that he may have for remedying this situation, saying that you feel
                    free to make this request in view of the cordial relations that exist between
                    our two Governments and previous assurances that the Chilean Government will do
                    whatever is necessary to prevent Axis agents in Chilean territory from taking
                    any action <pb facs="0183" n="171" xml:id="pg_171"/> detrimental to the American
                    republics. You should point out to the President that, even if the private
                    companies were to refuse all messages in secret code or cipher over the lines to
                    Buenos Aires, the Axis missions would still be free to communicate secretly over
                    the national telegraph system to Argentina.</p>
                <p>You should indicate clearly that, in our view, the telecommunication situation
                    will not have been completely remedied while it is still possible for Axis
                    agents in Chile to make any use of Chile’s external telecommunication
                    facilities, whether for plain messages or code. You may say, however, that a
                    complete denial of secret code facilities to the Axis missions would be an
                    important step in this direction.</p>
                <p>Of course, if the Axis missions in Chile are denied the use of telecommunication
                    facilities, they will still be free to send confidential communications to
                    Buenos Aires by overland or air mail. However, the delay involved would have an
                    important effect in limiting the means by which Axis agents in Chile can do
                    damage to us and to the other American republics.</p>
                <p>You should, of course, be alert to guard against any action by the Chilean
                    Government that would impair our communications or those of your British
                    colleague.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
