<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Brazil ( (Caffery) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d188</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">188</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-04-28T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-04-28T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recHEnRX74raOryAY" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044893"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Espionage</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-04-28T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-04-28T14:00:00-05:00" n="188"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.20210/1360: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-04-28T16:00:00-03:00"
                            >April 28, 1942—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 7:08 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1435. Department’s 759, referred to its 738 which while it gave some discretion
                    in handling the source nevertheless made it clear that everything possible
                    should be done to prevent the source of the messages from being jeopardized or
                    destroyed.</p>
                <p>Department’s 937, April 11, clarified the question of giving this evidence to the
                    police here.</p>
                <p>The police as you know have arrested and have held these at our request. It was
                    necessary, the more so because as indicated in my 1413 April 25 their espionage
                    activities did not constitute a crime while Brazil is not at war, to show the
                    authorities here that we did in fact have “the goods” on them. The police have
                    therefore been given some of the messages in strict confidence, with the request
                    that they be used only to assist in questioning the prisoners, and under no
                    condition, to be published. The form in which the messages have been given to
                    the police to use has been either as a straight translation into Portuguese of
                    these messages when as in the case of the HTT group, they presented an
                    understandable record of the activities of the Hungarian ring, or as quotations
                    in interrogatories prepared for them by the Embassy as was necessary in order to
                    question Engels, von Heyer and Kempter. A selected group of Alfredo’s messages
                    was furnished to the President, to Aranha and to the police. Another group of
                    Alfredo messages dealing with leaks from the Air Ministry was given to Aranha to
                    show to General Eduardo Gomes.<note n="18" xml:id="d188fn18">General Gomes
                        represented Brazilian interests in the construction by United States
                        interests of air bases in northeast Brazil.</note> As an example of the
                    difficulty in holding these spies, Dr. Edmundo De Miranda Jordao, head of the
                    Brazilian Bar Association, today made energetic representations both to me and
                    to the police concerning the case of Rosa Debalas who is implicated in the HTT
                    ring and is under arrest.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
