<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Representative ( (Welles) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-01-16T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-01-16T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-01-16T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-01-16T15:00:00-05:00" n="28"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">710.Consultation (3)/344: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The American Representative</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-01-16T17:00:00-03:00"
                            >January 16, 1942—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received January 17—2:25 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>15. The situation remains approximately the same as indicated in my last
                    telegram.</p>
                <p>As you know, I completely share your own feeling that every effort should be made
                    to preserve unanimity, but that if the Argentine Government is unwilling to join
                    in a continental declaration for a severance of relations with the Axis Powers,
                    Argentina should be allowed to proceed alone.</p>
                <pb facs="0040" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/>
                <p>I had a very frank talk yesterday morning with Dr. Ruiz Guiñazú. I found him
                    wavering and vacillating, and obviously very much under the impression of the
                    strong line taken by the other delegations and by the general state of public
                    opinion in Brazil. Without making any commitment, he gave me to understand that
                    he was inclined to go along with a declaration for the severance of relations,
                    but he stated he would first have to cable President Castillo and get new
                    instructions.</p>
                <p>President Vargas<note n="64" xml:id="d28fn64">Getulio Vargas, President of
                        Brazil.</note> told me yesterday afternoon that the Argentines would come
                    along and that he himself had personally made it absolutely clear to Ruiz
                    Guiñazú that Brazil would support the United States 100%; that the final
                    decision of Brazil in this regard had been reached, and that he, Vargas, had the
                    support of practically every citizen of Brazil in following this policy.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Ministers of Mexico<note n="65" xml:id="d28fn65">Ezequiel
                        Padilla.</note> and Venezuela<note n="66" xml:id="d28fn66">Caracciolo
                        Parra-Pérez.</note> and the Chief of the delegation of Colombia,<note n="67"
                        xml:id="d28fn67">Gabriel Turbay.</note> are today jointly presenting to the
                    committee a project for the severance of relations with the Axis Powers. They
                    have been to see Ruiz Guiñazú, and have shown him the project. They have told
                    him that they will not agree to a compromise and that they will under no
                    conditions recede from the position they have taken, and that in this position
                    they have the support of every nation of the hemisphere, except Chile and
                    Argentina.</p>
                <p>The speech made yesterday by Dr. Guani was decidedly helpful as an indication to
                    the rest of the Continent that Argentina’s assumed control over the smaller
                    republics of South America is nonexistent.</p>
                <p>The general atmosphere of the Conference could not be more favorable from our
                    standpoint. I am now beginning to believe that the Argentine Government may
                    decide to come along largely because of the firm attitude taken by President
                    Vargas and Aranha. … Aranha feels and I agree, however, that if Argentina is
                    brought into line Chile will be forced without question to adhere to any joint
                    declaration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
