<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-07T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-07T15:00:00-05:00" n="369" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">835.34/577: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Armour</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                        Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-07T17:00:00-03:00">March 7, 1942—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6:18 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>446. For the Under Secretary. Department’s telegram 305, March 4,
                            midnight. I can well understand our Navy Department’s desire to maintain
                            friendly relations with the Argentine Navy and I recognize the value
                            inherent in an agreement providing for cooperation between our Navies
                            “in the event that Argentina enters the war against the Axis.” The
                            implication conveyed by such a clause, namely, the admission in writing
                            of the possibility of Argentina entering the war against the Axis would
                            in itself be of prime importance.</p>
                        <pb facs="0396" n="384" xml:id="pg_384"/>
                        <p>On the other hand there is little doubt that the Government here would
                            attempt to use the signing of any agreement to create the impression
                            that the position taken by the Argentine Government had not affected our
                            policy so far as the furnishing of war material is concerned. We would
                            have to anticipate I fear the impression for a time at least that we had
                            receded somewhat from our original position.</p>
                        <p>Referring to penultimate paragraph of your telegram effort should be made
                            to avoid creation of impression that we are making a distinction between
                            the Argentine Army and Navy, having in mind the existing jealousies
                            between these services. If this aspect is not carefully handled it might
                            have serious repercussions.</p>
                        <p>Not knowing the contents of the agreement, I am not in a position to
                            comment on whether the undoubted advantages would be compensation for
                            the aforementioned disadvantages. If the agreement is signed I would
                            suggest that a carefully worded statement be issued at the time of
                            signing to the effect that the actual furnishing of material is premised
                            upon the signing of a lend-lease agreement.</p>
                        <p>Regarding such a statement, the inclusion in the agreement of a specific
                            date 1942 when the furnishing of material is to commence would appear to
                            present a difficulty. This might be interpreted here as a commitment to
                            enter into a lease-lend agreement during the current year even though no
                            change in the present policy of the Argentine Government had occurred in
                            the meantime. If this point, provided it is well taken, could be cleared
                            up and the suggested explanatory statement issued, it would make it more
                            difficult for the Argentine Government to make capital out of the
                            signing of the agreement.</p>
                        <p>I do not know whether it would be the intention to publish the text or
                            summary of the agreement if and when signed. If this could be done, the
                            publication accompanied by the statement suggested should indicate that
                            there has been no fundamental change in our policy.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Armour</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>