<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="416" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d416">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">835.796/249</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Armour</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 4600</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                        Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-27">March 27, 1942</date>.<lb/>[Received April
                                6.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Department’s
                            strictly confidential telegram no. 428 of March 26, 10 p.m., I have the
                            honor to report two recent conversations with the Brazilian Ambassador,
                            Dr. Rodrigues Alves, regarding Argentine efforts to obtain the Lati
                            planes now in Brazil, and to outline further considerations with respect
                            to the Corporación Sudamericana de Servicios Aéreos.</p>
                        <p>On March 23 the Brazilian Ambassador told me of a recent talk he had had
                            with Dr. Castells, Undersecretary of Interior, who remarked that Dr.
                            Castillo’s elder son, Ramón, had considerable influence with his father;
                            in fact, the Acting President found it difficult to refuse his son
                            anything. Dr. Castells then referred to the desire of Ramón Castillo Jr.
                            to acquire the Lati planes now in Brazil, and said that the planes were
                            needed by Argentina for use on the airline from Buenos Aires to Esquel
                            (now being operated by the army air service), and to maintain
                            communications with isolated army posts along the Chilean frontier.</p>
                        <p>After his talk with Dr. Castells, the Brazilian Ambassador was approached
                            by Ramón Castillo Jr. for the purpose of enlisting the Ambassador’s
                            cooperation in arranging for the purchase of these Lati planes. Dr.
                            Rodrigues Alves replied that he thought all of these planes, with
                            perhaps one exception, were of flimsy wooden construction and hardly
                            suitable for the Argentine army. However, Castillo Jr. still seemed
                            anxious to acquire them, and said that he was also interested in getting
                            five or six transport planes from the United States.</p>
                        <p>The Brazilian Ambassador said young Castillo had told him that “a member
                            of the British Embassy” (he could not remember the name Castillo had
                            given him, and was unable to recognize it afterwards on consulting the
                            diplomatic list) had told him that if Argentina would grant
                            nonbelligerent treatment to Great Britain, the British would then use
                            their influence to get these American planes for Argentina. Dr.
                            Rodrigues Alves was very insistent that he had clearly understood young
                            Castillo on this point. However, I have since had the opportunity to
                            discuss this with the British Embassy, which states that the report is
                            “ridiculous”.</p>
                        <p>On March 241 had another talk with the Brazilian Ambassador, and asked
                            him specifically if he thought Argentina intended to use the Lati
                            planes, if they secured them, for a trans-Atlantic service. He replied
                            in the negative, saying that young Castillo had assured him the <pb facs="0446" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/> planes were intended for army
                            use and on the Esquel line. He also said that the local Fiat company had
                            endeavored to obtain the Lati planes by means of an ante-dated purchase
                            agreement, which Brazil refused to recognize.</p>
                        <p>The Brazilian Ambassador at first seemed favorably disposed to
                            recommending the sale of the Lati planes to Argentina; that they did not
                            amount to much anyway and the Argentine Government had after all
                            permitted the return of the Condor<note n="5" xml:id="d416fn5">For
                                correspondence on the removal of Axis influence in the operations of
                                Sindicato Condor, Ltda., see <ref target="#pg_441">pp.
                                    441</ref>–<ref target="#pg_453">453</ref>
                                <hi rend="italic">passim</hi> and <ref target="#pg_766">pp.
                                    766</ref> ff.</note> planes to Brazil (this point had also been
                            stressed by young Castillo). Furthermore, some reciprocal gesture by
                            Brazil, negotiated by the son of Dr. Castillo, would be highly
                            appreciated by the Acting President.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the American planes desired by young Castillo, Dr.
                            Rodrigues Alves admitted that it would be inconsistent under our
                            Government’s present policy to furnish such equipment to Argentina, but
                            suggested an ingenious solution whereby we might furnish such planes to
                            Brazil and Brazil in turn could release the Lati planes to
                            Argentina.</p>
                        <p>I said that I thought our Government would be against any such
                            arrangement permitting the release of the Lati planes to Argentina,
                            adding that I felt sure the Ambassador would agree that if our
                            Government scrupulously adhered, as it was doing, to the plan to furnish
                            all available supplies to Brazil and other republics which had broken
                            relations with or declared war on the Axis powers, it would seem
                            inconsistent for Brazil on its part to furnish planes to Argentina, even
                            though these were old Lati planes which happened to be within their
                            country.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Rodrigues Alves expressed hearty concurrence with this point of view
                            and said he would present it in this light to Dr. Aranha.</p>
                        <p>The above information furnished by the Brazilian Ambassador raises
                            several points for speculation. Bearing in mind that young Castillo is
                            affiliated with the Corporación Sudamericana de Servicios Aéreos, some
                            of the parts and motors from these Lati planes unquestionably would have
                            been used to replace worn out equipment on the company’s present fleet
                            of three Italian “Macchi” planes. Present operations are from Buenos
                            Aires to Montevideo and to Asunción, but there is a possibility of the
                            line being extended to Rio de Janeiro by the Corporación itself or by a
                            new Argentine company.</p>
                        <p>In such event, this extension might be a logical link for the rumored
                            airline between Buenos Aires and Europe. According to the local press,
                            one of the matters to be discussed during the forthcoming visit of the
                            Spanish trade mission is the possibility of an airline connecting <pb facs="0447" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/> Spain and Argentina. Col.
                            Francisco Iglesias, the Spanish aviator who made an extensive flight in
                            1929, arrived in Buenos Aires on March 24, on his way back to Spain from
                            Lima, where he represented his country at the Fourth Centenary of the
                            Discovery of the Amazon Region. <hi rend="italic">Pampero</hi> of March
                            24 comments as follows: “Although his visit does not have an official
                            character, it would not be surprising if he took advantage of the
                            opportunity to consider the possibility of establishing the projected
                            Madrid-Buenos Aires airline.”</p>
                        <p>The interest of Castillo Jr. in acquiring American transport planes is
                            also significant. There is a rumor to the effect that he would like to
                            merge the Corporación with Aerovias Argentinas, the latter company being
                            recently organized to obtain concessions and operate new air routes in
                            Argentina. As reported in the Embassy’s confidential despatch no. 3542
                            of November 21, 1941,<note n="6" xml:id="d416fn6">Not printed.</note>
                            this company has a strong board of directors, and while it had been
                            understood that most of them were partisans of ex-President Justo, it is
                            just possible that its directors would be willing to cooperate with the
                            Castillo faction, especially if they could make better progress. In this
                            event, the American planes would presumably be intended for domestic and
                            possibly international routes of the rumored Corporación Aerovias
                            consolidation. It is also reported that the Corporación intends to
                            change its name in the near future.</p>
                        <p>With specific reference to the Corporación, there is transmitted herewith
                            a translation of a report<note n="6" xml:id="d416fn8">Not
                                printed.</note> prepared by Sr. Antonio Biedma, the former manager
                            of this company, mentioned in the Embassy’s confidential despatch no.
                            4383 of March 11. Sr. Biedma is highly regarded in local aviation
                            circles, and he is believed to be a trustworthy source of information.
                            His report offers further evidence that the company is directly
                            controlled by Fiat and Ala Littoria, and that the Acting President’s
                            son, as well as his law partner, are closely affiliated with the
                            company.</p>
                        <p>As mentioned in the Embassy’s aforementioned despatch no. 4383, there
                            have been several factors which have restrained the Embassy from
                            recommending the Corporación for the Proclaimed List. To these may be
                            added the possibility of a lawsuit against Intava in the event it is no
                            longer able to supply gasoline, and the disruption of the pooling
                            arrangement between the Corporación and the Uruguayan company Causa<note n="7" xml:id="d416fn7">Compañía Aeronáutica Uruguaya, S.A.</note> on
                            the Buenos Aires–Montevideo daily service.</p>
                        <p>The refusal of Brazil to release the Lati planes materially reduces the
                            threat of expansion by the Corporación. The only other <pb facs="0448" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/> possibilities apparent at this time for
                            establishing new airlines from Argentina to Brazil and Europe are: 1)
                            utilization of the Air France planes for which Argentina has been
                            negotiating, which would first require considerable overhauling of the
                            planes and the probable employment of former Air France pilots, and 2)
                            the establishment of the proposed Spanish-Argentine line, with planes
                            furnished by Spain, which presumably could be discouraged by withholding
                            fuel.</p>
                        <p>Briefly, the inclusion of the Corporación on the Proclaimed List would
                            probably cause a cessation in operations, provided Intava stopped fuel
                            supplies. However, due to the considerations already mentioned, such
                            action on our part might well cause unpleasant repercussions.</p>
                        <p>The above factors have been outlined in some detail in order to give the
                            Department full background information, and in the event that future
                            developments require quick action with respect to placing the
                            Corporación on the Proclaimed List.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Norman Armour</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>