<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Secretary of State for President Roosevelt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d446</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">446</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXmtj6SyvT64JYD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic warfare</term>
                    <term ref="recc5wAbpL3cvsf8h" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="446"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d446">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.51 Frozen Credits/6701</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                            State</gloss> for President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="58" xml:id="d446fn58">Handed to President Roosevelt May 14, 1942. A
                        notation on the memorandum by the President reads: “C. H. Not in accord with
                        Good Neighbor Policy F. D. R.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content"
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1942-05-14">undated</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Proposal of the Treasury Department to the Board of
                        Economic Warfare That Argentine Funds in the United States Be Frozen</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">I. <hi rend="italic">The nature of the proposal</hi>.</p>
                <p>The proposal is that the funds of Argentina in the United States be frozen and
                    that a general license then be issued for purely Argentine transactions. The
                    purpose of the proposed action is twofold: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To coerce Argentina into greater collaboration with the war effort of
                            the United Nations.</item>
                        <pb facs="0484" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>To demonstrate to all the other American countries that the United
                            States Government “means business” and will wield its huge economic
                            power to force more effective collaboration. The Treasury
                                memorandum<note n="59" xml:id="d446fn59">Not found in Department
                                files.</note> states “it may be that the freezing of Argentine
                            assets should be accompanied by similar action against Chile and that
                            the policy (i.e. freezing) should be based on their continuance of
                            relations with the Axis.”</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">II. <hi rend="italic">The proposal is one of basic foreign
                        policy</hi>.</p>
                <p>Treasury and the Board of Economic Warfare frankly admit that they are not
                    concerned primarily with methods of improving Argentine administration of
                    foreign property but are attempting to force a change in the basic relationships
                    of Argentina and the United States. The technical inadequacy of the proposed
                    freezing order is admitted by all, but it is sponsored by Treasury and the Board
                    of Economic Warfare in the utterly mistaken view that it will coerce Argentina
                    into the line desired by us.</p>
                <p>The question raised is clearly one of foreign policy, namely, what is the best
                    way for this Government to bring about better collaboration in the war effort by
                    Argentina. The determination of such a fundamental matter of foreign relations
                    is obviously of proper concern only to the Department of State under the
                    instruction of the President.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">III. <hi rend="italic">Argentine policy regarding hemisphere
                        solidarity</hi>.</p>
                <p>The Treasury and the Board of Economic Warfare start from the premise that
                    Argentina is affirmatively working in the interests of the Axis. This is
                    definitely erroneous. The active collaboration of Argentina in some aspects of
                    our war effort is demonstrated by: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The offer by the Argentine Government of the use of its ports and
                            territorial waters by the armed vessels of the United States, just as
                            though the United States were not a belligerent.<note n="60"
                                xml:id="d446fn60">This offer was effected by decrees of December 9
                                and 13, 1941; see Embassy’s despatch No. 3740, December 24, 1941,
                                printed in <ref target="frus1941v06">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>
                                </ref>, section entitled “Reactions in the other American Republics
                                to the declarations of war between the United States and the Axis
                                Powers.”</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Argentine refusal to permit itself to become the haven of Axis
                            diplomats from the countries which had severed relations with the
                            Axis.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Refusal of Argentina to sell aviation gasoline to Axis-controlled
                            airlines.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Sale of its strategic materials to the United States.<note n="61"
                                xml:id="d446fn61">See <ref target="#pg_306">pp. 306</ref> ff.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Nevertheless, Argentina has not collaborated in the way hoped
                    for at the Rio Conference; primarily, it has not severed diplomatic relations
                    with the Axis.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">IV. <hi rend="italic">United States policy toward Argentina and
                        its results</hi>.</p>
                <p>In order to persuade Argentina of where its vital interests lie, the United
                    States, since Rio has withheld delivery of military and naval <pb facs="0485"
                        n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> supplies to Argentina unless Argentina agrees to
                    contribute substantially in some acceptable way to the security of the
                    hemisphere, and is furnishing scarce nonmilitary goods only after the needs of
                    the other American republics have been supplied. This policy is bearing fruit.
                    The powerful military and naval elements in Argentina, which really maintain the
                    present Government in power, are beginning to question the desirability of
                    Argentina’s present policy. Public opinion, carefully influenced by us, in
                    general is becoming more and more insistent upon a more effective collaboration
                    by Argentina with the democracies.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">V. <hi rend="italic">Effect of freezing Argentine funds in the
                        United States</hi>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>If in this situation Argentine funds here were to be frozen, not only
                        would commercial intercourse and the flow of trade, including strategic
                        materials, be hampered but of far greater importance, the Argentine
                        Government would be pushed toward the Axis. Our action would be considered
                        by most Argentineans, even our friends, as a demonstration of the thesis
                        which the Axis is subtly promoting, namely, that the United States, under
                        the guise of hemisphere solidarity, is actually embarked upon a policy of
                        ruthless economic imperialism. Indeed, this action would be received with
                        grisly satisfaction by the Axis, which would view it as a specific result of
                        its efforts to drive a wedge between Argentina and the other American
                        republics.</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>The contemplated measure would likewise produce serious repercussions in
                        the other American republics. The whole basis of our inter-American policy
                        over the past few years has been nonintervention, respect for individual
                        sovereignty, and the reaching of decisions through voluntary agreement. Far
                        from applauding the proposed freezing of Argentine funds as Treasury and the
                        Board of Economic Warfare believe, the other American republics would begin
                        to wonder whether we had repudiated our present policy and returned to the
                        days of the Big Stick. The spectacle of Argentina being beaten over the head
                        with an economic club would in no way advance the confidence in our aims and
                        purposes so painstakingly, but so successfully, built up in the other
                        American republics.</item>
                </list>
                <p>If those countries were to lose confidence in our ability to maintain a broad,
                    tolerant, and collaborative attitude, even in this time of stress, we might
                    well, by dramatic coercion, toss away the results of a decade of careful
                    development in relations and do harm inestimably greater to our war effort than
                    the difficulties flowing from Argentina’s lack of full collaboration.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">VI. <hi rend="italic">The problem of Argentine deficiencies of
                        administration of foreign property</hi>.</p>
                <p>Those deficiencies which have aroused the Treasury and the Board of Economic
                    Warfare no less than the Department, of course require <pb facs="0486" n="474"
                        xml:id="pg_474"/> continual attention and our best efforts to remedy them.
                    Effective control action can immediately be taken by this Government in
                    conjunction with the United Nations regarding some aspects, such as by more
                    thorough navicert control over shipments between Argentina and Spain, or by an
                    amendment to Treasury General Order No. 5<note n="63" xml:id="d446fn63">This
                        refers to General Ruling No. 5, amended May 19, 1942, and September 3, 1943.
                        See 5 <hi rend="italic">Federal Register</hi> 2159; 7 <hi rend="italic"
                            >Federal Register</hi> 3770; 8 <hi rend="italic">Federal Register</hi>
                        12286.</note> prohibiting the transfer of United States currency from any
                    foreign country to the United States. Other action can be taken through
                    implementation of our blacklist program, and some action can only be taken by
                    the Argentine Government itself. The Department has lost no opportunity to bring
                    to the attention of the Argentine Government the loopholes and weaknesses in its
                    administrative machinery.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
