<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Argentina ( (Armour))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d471</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">471</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-11-20T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-11-20T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-20T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-20T17:00:00-05:00" n="471"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d471">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">835.51/1525: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Armour</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-20T18:00:00-04:00"
                            >November 20, 1942—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1772. Your 2099, October 27, 11 p.m.; Department’s despatch no. 3388, October 28,
                        1942.<note n="27" xml:id="d471fn27">Neither printed.</note> Unless you
                    perceive some objection, please address a communication to the Foreign Office
                    protesting against the authorization of remittances to the head office of the
                    Banco Hipotecario in France and point out the following:</p>
                <p>Shortly after the collapse of France in June 1940, there was an accumulation of
                    three or four hundred million francs in the account of the Central Bank under
                    the Argentine-French Payments Agreement. Subsequently this Government was
                    informed that when this fund became exhausted, Argentina would not authorize
                    further transfers of payments to occupied or unoccupied France for the duration
                    of the war. On April 9, 1942 it was learned that authorization had been granted
                    for two substantial financial remittances to occupied France and that these
                    remittances were entirely outside the Argentine-French Payment Agreement. The
                    Foreign Office was informed that this Government considered these remittances a
                    violation of Rio Resolution V. The Foreign Office, under date of May 8, 1942,
                    submitted a memorandum to the effect that the remittances in question did not
                    constitute a violation of Resolution V. This Government, after giving careful
                    consideration to this memorandum, presented the reasons which, in its judgment,
                    made it necessary for it to continue to consider the transactions involved
                    inconsistent with Resolution V.</p>
                <p>This Government has recently learned that the Argentine authorities have
                    authorized further remittances of substantial amounts by the Banco Hipotecario
                    Franco-Argentina to its head office in France and that these remittances are to
                    be effected outside the French-Argentine Payments Agreement. For the reasons
                    which this Government has previously presented remittances made by the Banco
                    Hipotecario in the past have afforded facilities in France which might benefit
                    the aggressor nations. Accordingly, even before the recent developments in
                    France, it was the carefully considered view of this Government, that the
                    authorizations in question were inconsistent not only with Resolution V adopted
                    in Rio but also with resolutions adopted by <pb facs="0518" n="506"
                        xml:id="pg_506"/> the Washington Conference. As a result of recent
                    developments in France, it is now even clearer to this Government that such
                    remittances in the future would benefit the aggressor nations. Indeed such
                    remittances can no longer, in their practical effect, be distinguished from
                    remittances direct to Germany. Accordingly, their authorization would be viewed
                    with the greatest concern by this Government. It is hoped that the renewed
                    expression of this Government’s views, together with new developments in France,
                    will result in denial of authorizations for such transactions in the future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
