<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="539" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d539">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M) Bolivia/517</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Boal</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 784</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">La
                                    Paz</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-27">October 27, 1942</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                November 3.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose a copy of a
                                contract<note n="35" xml:id="d539fn35">Not printed.</note> which was
                            signed on October 19, 1942, between the authorized representatives in La
                            Paz of the Rubber Reserve Company and the Banco Agrícola of Bolivia
                            providing principally that the funds to be provided to rubber producers
                            in Bolivia to finance increased production will be loaned through the
                            Banco Agrícola, but that the Rubber Reserve Company shall be the sole
                            purchaser of rubber production in Bolivia.</p>
                        <p>The Banco Agrícola, according to the provisions of the contract, is to
                            receive all of the interest paid on the loans by the rubber producers,
                            in return for which the Banco Agrícola is required only to assume a
                            maximum risk of 25 percent of the loans and to perform the detailed
                            services of the collections and checking on the manner in which specific
                            amounts of funds are expended.</p>
                        <p>The Rubber Reserve Company considers this contract to be advantageous
                            principally because it includes the agreement of the Banco Agrícola that
                            the Rubber Reserve Company shall be the sole purchaser of Bolivian
                            rubber production. Also, it is definitely advantageous to the Rubber
                            Reserve Company to be relieved of the accounting details of handling the
                            large loans that are being made to producers. It is expected that these
                            loans to be handled by the Banco Agrícola may total between 50,000,000
                            Bolivianos and 100,000,000 Bolivianos (approximately between $1,000,000
                            and $2,000,000).</p>
                        <p>It will be noted that the contract provides that the Rubber Reserve
                            Company shall sell to the Banco Agrícola the 250 metric tons per annum
                            that is to be available for shipment from Bolivia to countries other
                            than the United States. It is expected that the Banco Agrícola will
                            realize a comparatively large profit on this amount of rubber.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre de L.
                            Boal</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>