<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-04-29T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-04-29T17:00:00-05:00" n="56" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">710. Consultation (3)A/49: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-04-29T19:00:00-03:00">April 29, 1942—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 7:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>327. For Chapin<note n="4" xml:id="d56fn4">Selden Chapin, Assistant
                                Chief, Division of the American Republics.</note> from Spaeth. No.
                            7. Brazilian member has introduced a resolution which recommends that
                            all of the Republics require nationals of the Tripartite Pact<note n="5" xml:id="d56fn5">Between Japan, Germany, and Italy, signed at Berlin,
                                September 27, 1940; for text, see League of Nations Treaty Series,
                                vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cciv</hi>, p. 386.</note> and states
                            subservient to them, as well as organizations of all kinds controlled by
                            such nationals, to file periodic reports as a condition precedent to
                            receiving a certificate of good conduct. The required reports would
                            include statements as to whether the Axis national or organization has
                            contributed funds or property in the interest of the Tripartite Pact,
                            participated <pb facs="0088" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/> in any manner in
                            any activity on behalf of the Tripartite Pact, or had knowledge of such
                            activity on the part of others. Substantial fines or imprisonment would
                            be imposed for failure to report, for falsification of the reports, and
                            for any repetition of pro-Axis activities actually disclosed. The
                            proposal is not only designed to put additional pressure upon enemy
                            groups, but would afford nationals of the Tripartite Pact who are
                            friendly to the democracies, an opportunity to establish their loyalty
                            and by so doing, to free themselves from prejudice or discrimination
                            under local laws. In addition, the proposal seems to have the merit of
                            hitting directly at a basic problem pending the preparation of more
                            comprehensive recommendations on the subject of registration and
                            identification. Full text of proposal will be sent airmail pouch.<note n="6" xml:id="d56fn6">Text of Brazilian proposal transmitted to
                                Department as Exhibit 0 of Report No. 2, May 1, by Mr. Spaeth (710.
                                Consultation (3) A/62).</note> [Spaeth.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dawson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>