<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">710. Consultation (3)A/197</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the Emergency Advisory Committee for
                                Political Defense</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Guani</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi><note n="31" xml:id="d72fn31">This document is translator’s summary of letter
                                dated October 16 from Mr. Guard to the Secretary of State,
                                transmitting a copy of the Final Act and the Secretary General’s
                                report of the Regional Meeting at Rivera concerning the entry and
                                departure of individuals and clandestine transit across
                                borders.</note></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-16">October 16, 1942</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>This meeting was held at the instance of Brazil and upon the decision of
                            the Advisory Committee. Five countries—Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil,
                            Paraguay and Uruguay—were represented and two members of the Committee
                            (from Brazil and the United States) attended. Brazil had proposed it
                            because of the problems arising in connection with its entry into the
                            war, particularly the presence of large numbers of people in its
                            territory whose interests were opposed to the defense and security of
                            the continent. The Committee felt it advisable that measures be taken so
                            as not to nullify Brazil’s efforts at control by the emigration of such
                            people to adjacent countries.</p>
                        <pb facs="0109" n="97" xml:id="pg_97"/>
                        <p>The general subject matter recommended by the Committee embraced three
                            matters: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Measures for the control of travel between the five Republics
                                    in order to adopt the necessary precautions in these times of
                                    emergency;</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Organization of effective patrols on the borders;</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Cooperative measures between the five Republics.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The meeting opened on September 22 and closed on September 26. Its
                            decisions were approved by the Emergency Advisory Committee’s Delegates
                            and their report to the Committee was unanimously approved by the
                            latter. At present the Committee is studying the recommendations
                            approved at the Rivera meeting to determine which of them may be used
                            and applied by the other American countries not represented thereat.
                            When it reaches a decision on this matter, it will immediately advise
                            the American Government.</p>
                        <p>The Final Act reports approval of recommendations on the following
                            subjects: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>A motion proposing the creation of political-social police
                                    agencies within the police organizations of the various
                                    countries to have charge of matters affecting the internal and
                                    external security of the State.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>A motion proposing that the Governments represented arrange to
                                    exchange information concerning certain aliens and measures
                                    adopted by the different countries to meet situations involving
                                    them.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>A motion recommending the adoption of regulations governing
                                    the entry and departure of nationals and naturalized or legal
                                    citizens, including special provisions for those living in
                                    “border zones”.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>A motion recommending the adoption of special regulations
                                    governing the entry and departure of aliens from non-continental
                                    States.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>A motion recommending that, in agreement with the authorities
                                    of a bordering State, each State determine points of entry into
                                    and departure from its territory.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>A motion recommending that international transportation
                                    companies be required to demand identifying documents of an
                                    individual before furnishing him with transportation.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>A motion recommending that hotels and lodging houses be
                                    required to demand presentation of identifying documents, make a
                                    record thereof and transmit the information to the
                                    authorities.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>A motion recommending the adoption of rules concerning the
                                    registration of aliens.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>A motion suggesting general lines to be followed in the
                                    guarding of borders between countries.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>A motion recommending the creation of Rural Police to protect
                                    rural frontier zones.</item>
                                <label>11.</label>
                                <item>A motion recommending the adoption of measures restricting the
                                    activities of immigrant farmers and experts in rural
                                    industries.</item>
                                <label>12.</label>
                                <item>A motion submitting to the Emergency Advisory Committee two
                                    resolutions, proposed by Brazil, concerning restrictions on the
                                        <pb facs="0110" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/> naturalization of
                                    aliens and the fixing of prohibited zones for the residence of
                                    Axis nationals.</item>
                                <label>13.</label>
                                <item>Vote of thanks to the presiding officer.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The second enclosure, the Secretary General’s report, lists the different
                            matters submitted for discussion, showing which were amalgamated, which
                            withdrawn, how they compared with the agenda suggested by the Emergency
                            Advisory Committee, etc.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>