<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-06-22T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-06-22T19:00:00-05:00" n="88" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d88">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/22389:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-22T19:00:00-05:00">June 22, 1942—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received June 23—3:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1021. For Welles. Barros Jarpa<note n="30" xml:id="d88fn30">Chilean
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note> this afternoon at my house set
                            forth a plan he mentioned to me Saturday at lunch that he is prepared to
                            inform the Missions of Germany, Italy and Japan that they no longer can
                            communicate with their Governments in code and he thinks this will lead
                            to a controversy eventuating in the breaking of relations. He wants to
                            know if we will take this as proof that a pretext is being sought and
                            with a certainty of finding it soon with the intention of breaking
                            relations.</p>
                        <p>It seems a big step forward. Sentiment here is changing so rapidly and is
                            becoming so strong for breaking relations that I dare entertain the
                            expectation that it is certain to come very soon.</p>
                        <p>In this connection he tells me he has just heard from his Ambassador in
                            Washington that you had told him Chile could expect nothing more from us
                            until relations are broken. He is to make an exposition on foreign
                            affairs before Congress tomorrow and would prefer not to mention this
                            ultimatum at that time since he says it would create an opposition in
                            quarters where it does not exist. I am persuaded that he now knows that
                            relations must be broken and that he is really searching for a pretext
                            on which he can break without imperiling his personal prestige. Since
                            outside this one phase he is strongly pro-American and pro-Ally this
                            would be satisfactory to me. Your plain statement to Michels<note n="31" xml:id="d88fn31">Rodolfo Michels, Chilean Ambassador in the United
                                States.</note> wipes out any false impressions that may have come
                            from Davila.</p>
                        <p>Last night 10,000 people attended a homage to Mexico because of the war
                            and with misgivings I agreed to attend on the stipulation that no
                            attacks be made on the Government directly. None were made and I
                            received a great ovation. The leaders of all parties that supported
                                Ríos<note n="32" xml:id="d88fn32">Juan Antonio Ríos, President of
                                Chile.</note> at the polls spoke in favor of Chile aligning herself
                            vigorously on the side of complete alignment with the Allies. Marcella
                            Mora, leader of the radicals, made a strong speech. It gives an impetus
                            to public opinion forming in our favor.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Bowers</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>