<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Motley to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-11-24T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPwjhmSWu0ZTtDD" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" subject="population-growth" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="capital-punishment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277" lcsh-match="exact">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="protocol" subject="protocol" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="financial-and-monetary-affairs" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" subject="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158" lcsh-match="exact">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="bilateral-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="summit-meeting" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991" lcsh-match="good_close">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-operations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Active measures</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="religious-freedom" subject="religious-freedom" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-11-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="106" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Motley</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 40.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the U. S. of America at Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-24">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi>24 1863</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi>There are symptoms that the German-Danish question
                    in the duchies of Schleswig and Holstein, now pressing for its solution, after
                    vain attempts for so many years to bury it, may lead to a European war.</p>
                <p>The condition of affairs was critical before the death of King Frederick VII,
                    which occurred on the 15th of this month.</p>
                <p>Denmark has a total population of about 2,700,000; of which the duchies of
                    Schleswig, Holstein, and Lauenburg are, in round numbers, a million, or
                    considerably more than one-third of the whole.</p>
                <p>Holstein is, actually and undoubtedly, German in population and in feeling; and
                    King Frederick, in his capacity of Duke of Holstein, was a member of the German
                    confederation.</p>
                <p>Schleswig is neither historically nor politically a constituent part of what is
                    commonly called Germany, and is not represented at the Frankfort Diet, but it
                    has a considerable German population, among whom the recent efforts on the part
                    of the government to consolidate its power, and give preponderance to the Danish
                    element in schools, churches, and the public service, has produced much
                    dissatisfaction, and called forth loud complaints of tyranny and ill usage. Born
                    German Schleswegers here, to my knowledge, complained that they were treated
                    more cruelly than the Poles in Russia, or than the slaves in the southern States
                    of America.</p>
                <p>This is doubtless a figure of speech, but it illustrates the exasperation of
                    feeling which exists. These outcries have awakened a universal sympathy
                    throughout Germany, where, to judge from the language of the press and of
                    conversation, there is no difference of opinion on this matter, every man, from
                    prince to peasant, feeling with equal keenness in regard to it.</p>
                <pb facs="0153" n="129" xml:id="pg_129"/>
                <p>On the other band, the government, feeling that its national existence was at
                    stake—for without the duchies Denmark could hardly rank as an independent
                    kingdom—and that the gravitation of this portion of its domain towards Germany
                    should be checked at all hazards, proceeded with stringent measures in regard
                    both to Schleswig and to Holstein, which called forth remonstrances from the
                    German Diet, and led to a sharp correspondence between that body and the Danish
                    government. The events, as they have developed themselves during the past year,
                    have doubtless attracted your attention; so that, without going into details, or
                    expressing any opinion as to the merits of the question, I need only remind you
                    that, at last, the Frankfort Diet formally notified the Danish government that
                    unless its decree of 30th March last should be revoked, which the Diet had
                    declared to be a violation of the laws of the German confederation and of treaty
                    stipulations, troops would be sent from Germany to occupy the duchy of Holstein,
                    in order to execute this declaration of the Diet, and keep possession until the
                    desired revocation. The Danish government replied that the decree itself was
                    provisional, but it proceeded to mature a constitution for Denmark-Schleswig,
                    incorporating that duchy with the kingdom, and to maintain in form certain
                    objectionable regulations in Holstein.</p>
                <p>This constitution, being ultra-Danish in its character, was considered as
                    embodying and perpetuating the principles of the 30th March decree, and as
                    violating engagements formally entered into by Denmark, and the Diet resolved to
                    proceed with the execution if the new constitution should be signed by the
                    king.</p>
                <p>That constitution was drawn up and ready to be signed on the 13th of the present
                    month, but the king, who had for some time been ailing, was unable to attend to
                    business. On the 15th the world was startled by the news of his death.</p>
                <p>The sensation was as great as that which a week before had been caused by the
                    speech from the French throne. At first, however, it was hoped by many that the
                    accession of the new king would produce a favorable change. It would obviously
                    be not only courteous but necessary to pause in the execution until Christian IX
                    should develop his policy. He might refuse to sign the constitution, which his
                    predecessor had been prevented by death from signing. He might remove his
                    ministers, dissolve his parliament, and exchange ultra-Danish proceedings for
                    more German measures. But should he incline to do this, it was at once evident
                    that he would forfeit his crown before he had time to put it on his head. After
                    a very brief interval of reflection, he yielded to the pressure of the Danes,
                    signed the constitution, and retained his ministers.</p>
                <p>There is no reason, therefore, why the execution should not be proceeded with at
                    once. And the news to-day is that the Saxon and Hanoverian contingents are about
                    to march towards Holstein, while the popular excitement throughout Germany is
                    very great. It is said and hoped that this measure will not be accepted by the
                    Danish government as an act of war; but I have it on excellent authority that it
                    will recall its legations from the German courts as soon as the execution shall
                    take place. Whether this be true or not, time will soon show. It will be seen,
                    too, whether England and France will take part with Denmark in resisting by
                    force of arms the execution, or whether they will counsel and compel her to
                    avoid war by prudent concessions. Denmark takes the ground that she has conceded
                    and parleyed and argued enough, and that if her existence be, as the great
                    powers have avowed, a political necessity, it is time that they help her to
                    maintain that existence by something stronger than words.</p>
                <p>The governments of Prussia and Austria are the more ready now to go on with the
                    execution, because the death of the last sovereign, whose claim was undisputed,
                    has opened a new question, which, it was hoped, had been settled by the protocol
                    of 1852; for it must not be forgotten that the execution question <pb facs="0154" n="130" xml:id="pg_130"/> is an entirely distinct one from the
                    question of succession, although both threaten a European war. I have no desire
                    to examine the merits of the succession question, and I shall only very briefly
                    recall to your remembrance one or two leading facts.</p>
                <p>The protocol of 1852, by which the Duke of Schleswig-Glucksburg was declared the
                    successor of the childless King Frederick VII, who has just died, was signed not
                    only by England, France, and Russia, but by Austria and Prussia. The protocol
                    was distinctly stated to have for its object the maintenance of the integrity of
                    the Danish monarchy, as a European necessity. It did not affect to untie the
                    legal knot of succession to the duchies of Schleswig, Lauenburg, and Holstein,
                    which centuries of intermarriages had made nearly insoluble, but it cut it in
                    pieces. A large number of claimants to the heritage of these provinces were at
                    once set aside, so far as the protocol could do it; and the most prominent of
                    them, the Duke of Schleswig-Augustenburg, renounced his pretensions in his own
                    name and in that of his descendants. He also received three millions of thalers,
                    but whether as compensation for his claims or for his private estates in the
                    duchies is, I believe, like everything else, a matter of dispute.</p>
                <p>The protocol, however, although signed by Austria and Prussia as European powers,
                    was never sanctioned by the estates of the provinces in question, nor by the
                    German Bund. Bavaria, indeed, and one or two other small powers, protested
                    against it at the time; and it has always been anticipated that the death of
                    Frederick VII would bring about the commotions in Germany which are now taking
                    place.</p>
                <p>Yet it has been rather the fashion in Europe to sneer at the Schleswig-Holstein
                    question, as the embodiment of all that was tedious and incomprehensible, and to
                    shove it aside for what were considered graver matters. It now rises again with
                    a more menacing aspect than ever out of the grave of the late king, and will not
                    be so easily exorcised. It may now cost thousands of lives before it will
                    consent to vanish.</p>
                <p>The Prince of Schleswig, Augustenburg, son of the duke who renounced his family
                    rights, has formally assumed the title of Duke of Schleswig-Holstein, announced
                    his accession to the estates, and summoned the Bund to recognize his
                    plenipotentiary at the Diet as the rightful representative of Holstein and
                    Lauenburg. Several of the lesser German sovereignties, as Baden, Coburg,
                    Altenburg, and others, have expressed their intention of supporting him; and the
                    question has already been put in the hands of a committee at a meeting of the
                    Diet.</p>
                <p>His supporters speak fluently of his legal claim to the duchies as
                    unuqestionable. I should say that all that was unquestionable was, that, if
                    German law prevails in the duchies, the female branch, and those claiming
                    through females, cannot succeed; and that, therefore, the right of Christian IX,
                    and with it the integrity of the Danish monarchy, rests entirely upon the
                    protocol, and upon the vigor with which it is defended by the sword of Denmark
                    and her allies. But to say, on the other hand, that the claims of the
                    Augustenburgs are unquestionable, is to speak specifically. There are many
                    claimants not only to each of the three duchies, but to separate portions of
                    each duchy, the most formidable among which heirs-at-law to a part at least of
                    the property is the Czar of Russia as chief of the house of
                    Holstein-Gottorp.</p>
                <p>Moreover, it is maintained that in Schleswig it was arranged centuries ago by
                    formal instruments, with every legal sanction, that the succession to that duchy
                    should follow the succession to the Danish crown. In short, any one who has ever
                    studied law or history must recognize at a glance that this is exactly one of
                    those questions which might occupy all the jurisconsults and genealogists of
                    Europe for the rest of this century, before it could be settled beyond
                    possibility of cavil, and which, if it regarded a private estate, would be sure
                    to be kept in <pb facs="0155" n="131" xml:id="pg_131"/> chancery until the whole
                    property was consumed, and two or three generations of claimants had died of
                    starvation.</p>
                <p>I have, therefore, not the faintest intention of examining the merits of the
                    case; and it would certainly be a marvellous spectacle if all Europe, in this
                    age of the world, were to be plunged into a sanguinary and protracted struggle
                    to settle such a lawsuit.</p>
                <p>One would have thought that the time had gone by for wars of succession; but they
                    must, perhaps, periodically recur, as results of the European principle, that
                    great countries, with all their inhabitants, are the private property of a small
                    number of privileged families.</p>
                <p>The probable attitude of the great powers on this question is far more important
                    than the legal aspects of the case. Austria and Prussia signed the protocol, but
                    it is contended that they did not sign it as members of the Bund, but only as
                    European powers. Moreover, Austria and Prussia might easily be outvoted in a
                    plenary sitting of the Diet. Practically, however, it is absurd to suppose that
                    the Bund could take active war measures, or active measures of any kind, without
                    the consent of these two great constituents. The Germanic Confederation, even
                    with Austria and Prussia, is but a political shadow. Without them it is not even
                    the shadow of a shade.</p>
                <p>As a matter of fact, the Austrian government is most anxious to recognize
                    Christian IX as Duke of Schleswig, Holstein, and Lauenburg, and to maintain the
                    Danish monarchy in its entirety. It also desires to act in concurrence with
                    Prussia on this question. Up to the moment of this writing, however, Prussia has
                    not yet answered a proposition of Austria to this effect, and has not yet shown
                    its hand.</p>
                <p>Meantime, to judge by the almost universal language of the German press, and by
                    excited speeches made by prominent members of the liberal party to the National
                    German Union League, and to enthusiastic mass meetings, embracing six to ten
                    thousand, (according to reports,) in Hamburg, Hanover, Frankfort, and other
                    places, the German feeling is rising to fever heat. It is loudly proclaimed that
                    the hour has at last struck for delivering a million of German brethren from
                    Danish oppression, and for reannexing to the fatherland these duchies, which are
                    once for all to be now separated forever from Denmark.</p>
                <p>The chronic rivalry between Austria and Prussia for the leadership of Germany
                    makes it difficult and dangerous for either power to balk this German enthusiasm
                    in its first effervescence, and to confront this strong manifestation in favor
                    of the Augustenburg as the legal proprietor and master of the duchies and all
                    their inhabitants—who thus, by an odd combination of circumstances, appears at
                    once as the standard-bearer of the most antiquated legitimacy, and the
                    representative of the great principle of German nationality and popular
                    rights.</p>
                <p>The moment is an anxious one. How can the Band make, or even contemplate, war
                    with Denmark, backed up certainly by England, and probably by France and Russia?
                    Yet how can all this Germanism be got to bubble quietly away, and subside
                    without any blood-letting?</p>
                <p>On the other hand, how, in case of the Bund’s proceeding to actual hostilities,
                    can England tolerate the immense damage to her commerce which would be caused by
                    the blockading by Denmark of Hamburg, Bremen, and other German ports in the
                    North sea? It is useless to deny the existence of a very widespread desire among
                    the inhabitants of Germany to sever the duchies from Denmark; and this desire is
                    encouraged and shared in by many of the less important sovereigns of the
                    country. Should this desire ripen into determination, it is possible that the
                    people may compel the leading German powers to place themselves at the head of
                    the movement. In this case Denmark must fight for the protocol, and be supported
                    in so doing by other powers, or it must cease to exist. The Austrian government
                    is anxious to stand by the protocol, and recognize <pb facs="0156" n="132" xml:id="pg_132"/> Christian IX as sovereign over all the realms of his
                    predecessor, but Prussia still hesitates.</p>
                <p>Meantime the supreme tribunal of Holstein has refused the oath of allegiance to
                    the new king, an expression of a legal opinion the gravity of which cannot be
                    gainsaid.</p>
                <p>I shall say no more to-day, except that Europe is likely to have enough on its
                    hands at home during the coming year, and that certain of the great powers are
                    likely to check that periodical and mischievous desire for intermeddling in our
                    affairs which is so apt to break out when the cisatlantic world is comparatively
                    tranquil.</p>
                <p>We have it on the high authority of the Emperor Napoleon that the political
                    fabric of Europe is dilapidated—that its foundations are crumbling in all
                    directions. Since those words were spoken a great war threatens to desolate
                    Europe in order to settle the comparative value of a protocol, signed a dozen
                    years ago, by the representatives of half a dozen kings, and a series of musty
                    parchments centuries old. A lawsuit about a meagre province of puny proportions
                    in the North sea is about to set Europe in flames, while already a congress has
                    been called to avert a war in another direction, and nobody believes in its
                    efficacy. In the last dozen years there have already been two great European
                    wars, besides lesser and more distant ones, which are chronic, carried on by the
                    leading powers. Not a great power of them all but holds in subjection by force
                    of arms millions of mankind, alien to their language, their race, or their
                    religion. One great monarchy bombards and burns populous cities at one end of
                    the earth, every inhabitant of which is innocent of any thought of offence
                    against the bombarding nation; another great monarchy carries fire and sword
                    into a republic at the other end of the world, and seeks to subjugate it by
                    force of arms and convert it into an empire; meantime the whole surface of
                    Europe conceals smouldering revolutionary fires, which are likely to find vent
                    at any moment and in any direction; while the fear of such outbreaks, combined
                    with the perpetual rivalries and international hatreds of hostile dynasties and
                    nations, necessitates enormous armaments by land and sea, even in times of
                    peace, which cripple the energies, exhaust the resources, and sicken the hearts
                    of the people. A contemplation of European politics leads us to the sincere
                    prayer that America may never be Europeanized.</p>
                <p>I may be oversanguine, but a doubt has not yet crossed my mind that the American
                    republic, based upon constitutional law, popular self-government, and the great
                    principles of reason and justice, will suppress an insurrection made for the
                    perpetuation and extension of African slavery, and for the abrogation of the
                    first principles of freedom. I expect as much to see the sun set at noonday as
                    to witness the destruction of our noble commonwealth and its dismemberment into
                    a jarring, warring Europe, without the historical excuses of Europe.</p>
                <p>The American people will carry on its righteous war of self-defence so long as a
                    single rebel remains in arms to threaten the national existence, or to extend
                    and perpetuate the accursed institution out of which all our misery has flowed.
                    When that blessed result, which cannot now be far off, is reached, America may
                    justly hope for centuries of peace, prosperity, and power; while if we fail our
                    future is endless war. Meantime Europe, occupied with its own dynastic wars, in
                    which the people have no part, will have less time just now to read us moral
                    lectures on the blessings of peace.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to remain, respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. LOTHROP MOTLEY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
