<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Motley to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d112</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">112</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1864-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1864-03-07T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="capital-punishment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85019949" lcsh-match="exact">Capital punishment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="bilateral-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recPwjhmSWu0ZTtDD" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" subject="population-growth" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="international-law" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081635" lcsh-match="exact">Martial law</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="water" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-operations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="invasion" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="quarantine-blockade" subject="blockade" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919" lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="sovereignty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="employment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236" lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="economic-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-03-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="112" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Motley</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 47.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Vienna,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-03-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 7, 1864</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I send you herewith a translation of the document
                    by which Austrian Poland is declared to be in a state of siege.</p>
                <p>This measure has taken few people in these regions by surprise, although it would
                    seem to have been unexpected in foreign countries.</p>
                <p>By a reference to many of my despatches, and especially to No. 39, of date
                    November 24, 1863, with the accompanying documents, you will observe that
                    something very like a state of siege has for a long time existed in Gallicia and
                    Cracow. The formal proclamation of this condition is not generally thought here
                    to be premature, nor is it connected, as I believe, with any secret political
                    combinations with other powers.</p>
                <p>It has been notorious that the “national government,” concerning whose doings I
                    have often spoken in this correspondence, had extended its net-work almost as
                    thoroughly over the Austrian as over the Russian portion of Poland. Taxes have
                    been levied, troops enlisted, tribunals erected, capital punishment decreed and
                    inflicted by secret and wonderfully constructed machinery, in defiance of the
                    legal authorities, with a precision almost without a parallel in history. An
                    organized assassination, directed by unseen authority, makes the whole
                    population shudder. In brief, although the religious strife which is so
                    envenomed in Russian Poland is absent in Gallicia—although the disaffected
                    portion of the population is supposed to be a minority of the whole, and
                    although the wrongs which have driven the Poles into revolt against the Russian
                    government have not been committed by the Austrian authorities, yet the
                    difference, after all, is only in the comparative intensity and extent of the
                    revolutionary fever in the one and the other territory.</p>
                <p>With so much of danger and of disaffection in its own domains, it may well be
                    supposed that the imperial royal government has not been proceeding very
                    cheerfully in the crusade against Denmark. To rescue one nationality in the
                    northwest of Europe from oppression by its sovereign does not seem the most
                    logical or congenial of tasks for an empire which is itself compounded of a
                    dozen different nationalities, many of them in a state of chronic discontent,
                    and one of. them in a state of rebellion, so far advanced as to require the
                    application of martial law. These reflections are so obvious as to suggest
                    themselves to every mind, and hardly require to be dwelt upon. Nevertheless,
                    Austria seems to be wading every day, but against its will, into deeper and
                    deeper water. If the military process now on foot, which is expressly declared
                    not to be war, although some thousands have already been killed and wounded,
                    foreign territory <pb facs="0172" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/> invaded, great
                    fortresses taken, and others besieged during its continuance, really be not war,
                    but a sensible series of measures taken to avert war, then a most hazardous
                    experiment will have been crowned with success. I hardly anticipate such a
                    result. What really lies at the bottom of the great German movement against
                    Denmark is, strange to say, the democratic element as it is understood in
                    Germany; and it is for the sake of apparently assimilating, but in reality
                    neutralizing, this dreaded ingredient in every European organization that
                    Prussia and Austria are now sending their troops to the North sea.</p>
                <p>The delay in the military operations since the retirement of the Danish armies
                    behind the forts of Duppel and the fortress Frederica will have engaged your
                    attention. I do not dwell on the military events as they succeed each other, but
                    it is well understood now that Jutland is to be occupied by the allied armies.
                    It is asserted, however, that this province is occupied not as a permanent
                    conquest, but for strategical reasons, with a view to operations against the
                    remaining portion of Schleswig.</p>
                <p>Thus Holstein was taken in “execution,” Schleswig was seized “as a pledge,” and
                    now Jutland is occupied “as a military basis,” but all without war. It remains
                    to be seen whether, if no foreign power interferes, Denmark, after being
                    entirely reduced to subjection, at an enormous expenditure of blood and
                    treasure, will be handed back again, in whole or in part, to the Danish
                    government.</p>
                <p>If so, an example of moderation after success will be afforded which will be a
                    refreshing phenomenon in European history. The object still avowed by the great
                    German powers is the enforcement of the stipulations of 1851, as they understand
                    them—a united Schleswig-Holstein, that is to say, dissevered from Denmark, but
                    placed in “personal union” under the present King of Denmark.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, the Danish government considers the term “personal union” as a
                    mere euphuism for national dismemberment, and refuses to hear of such an
                    arrangement. It has recently informed the British government, as is generally
                    believed, that it will go into no conference unless England will guarantee that
                    Denmark shall be called upon to concede nothing beyond the stipulations of
                    1851-‘52, which, as she declares, forbid a united Schleswig-Holstein, and any
                    separation of Schleswig from the Danish kingdom. In case this guarantee should
                    be given, Denmark would be willing to go into a conference on the ground of the
                        <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> before the invasion of Jutland and of an
                    armistice, pending negotiations for the revision and interpretation of those
                    stipulations. She declares that what England has hitherto urged upon her is
                    equivalent to that which her victorious antagonist could impose after her
                    complete subjugation. Under these circumstances she would prefer to die with
                    honor, sword in hand, to becoming a party to her own destruction.</p>
                <p>As it is perfectly obvious that these terms would not be listened to by Austria
                    and Prussia, to say nothing of the more violent portion of Germany, it is
                    believed that the English government has declined to come to the rescue, and
                    will permit the invasion of Jutland or any other portion of Denmark. I am not
                    aware that there is any organized party in England ready to go to war with
                    Germany in defence of Denmark, although the politicians out of office are
                    eloquent in their denunciations of the perfidy and the imbecility manifested on
                    this question by those who are in.</p>
                <p>Whether the sympathy of the governing classes in that country, which has been
                    exuberantly manifested for Denmark, as it was for the insurgent slaveholders of
                    America, will be more fruitful of armed intervention in behalf of the Danes than
                    it has hitherto been for the confederates, remains to be seen. The prevailing
                    opinion, but one which I do not share, is that England will look on while
                    Denmark is dismembered. In this case I do not see how the victorious powers
                    could resist the pressure upon them from the more advanced part of Germany in
                    favor of the Augustenburger. At present, however, the chances <pb facs="0173" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> of the pretender to the duchies seem to have
                    diminished. At any rate his claims are ostentatiously thrust into the background
                    by Austria and Prussia.</p>
                <p>But popular opinion in England is, after all, an important factor in the problem;
                    and there is a conviction spreading that England has been talking too long and
                    too loud against Germany, and in behalf of Denmark, to allow her to wash her
                    hands and fold her arms. The ridicule which is manifested towards the English
                    policy on continental questions may end in piercing the national stoicism; a
                    feeling of shame and generous indignation may break forth in action, and I
                    almost expect to find England taking the field for her slight but valorous ally
                    at the last moment.</p>
                <p>Meantime the delay in the military operations is thought, on the whole, to have
                    been rather beneficial than otherwise to Denmark. She has had time to strengthen
                    the fortifications of Duppel and Frederica. The advancing season enables her to
                    make use of her fleets. The blockade of the German ports, and the capture of
                    German trading vesssels, will inflict much damage on her enemy before the
                    Austrian squadron, which, as I understand, has just been ordered into the North
                    sea, comes to their protection; and, moreover, the confusion in the councils of
                    the German confederation has been growing almost hopeless. In the Diet at
                    Frankfort everybody seems to be in a minority on every question. Every motion is
                    negatived, every party is conquered without any conquerors, while puzzle and
                    perplexity reign supreme.</p>
                <p>One would think that the measures taken for shortening and localizing the war
                    really contemplated its perpetration and expansion; and I for one am not yet a
                    convert to the theory of preventing a great war by making a little one.</p>
                <p>“Has it come to this,” exclaims a leading journal of Vienna this morning, “that
                    no German merchant vessel can venture into the North sea; that the insignificant
                    Denmark is again blockading the mouth of the Elbe; that Germany is in a state of
                    bewilderment; that the Diet, reflecting the universal helplessness, is bringing
                    on itself the scorn and contempt of foreign nations; that, in fine, while we are
                    avoiding the Scylla of a general crisis, we are in danger of being sucked into
                    the Napoleon-Congress Charybdis? ”</p>
                <p>We had a telegraphic report this morning that a Danish cruiser is lying in wait
                    off the mouth of the Elbe for the Hamburg New York steam-packet Germania. I have
                    been informed, however, I know not with what accuracy, that these vessels have
                    been sold to a Russian company. At any rate the river’s mouth is considered to
                    be effectually blockaded.</p>
                <p>To resume in a single phrase what I have been dilating upon in this despatch,
                    there is a growing popular indignation in England that Austria and Prussia
                    should be allowed to crush little Denmark. There is a growing popular
                    indignation in Germany that they are not crushing her fast enough or thoroughly
                    enough. Whether such a widespread and antagonistic excitement between two such
                    mighty peoples as the English and the Germans is likely to be suppressed without
                    blood-letting, you can judge as well as I can.</p>
                <p>The prospects of peace in Europe do not seem to be very promising this year.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to remain, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. LOTHROP MOTLEY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Manifesto of the Emperor of Austria, of March</hi>1, 1864,
                            <hi rend="italic">addressed to the Provinces of Gallicia and
                            Cracow.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">[Document accompanying despatch No. 47.]</p>
                    <p>For many months the kingdom of Poland has been the scene of disastrous
                        occurrences. Gallicia is powerfully moved by sympathy for its neighbor, and
                            <pb facs="0174" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> that province, generally so
                        peaceful, and moving in the paths of law and order, is agitated to its
                        centre.</p>
                    <p>My government has conscientiously performed its international duties in the
                        face of this condition of things, put in force the existing laws, and given
                        that leniency and forbearance full sway which was thought fitted to calm the
                        excited minds and turn the misguided from their unhappy enterprises. The
                        results have not met expectation.</p>
                    <p>Treasonable associations have been organized within the limits of my empire;
                        enlistments and extortions for the support of the insurrection are
                        uninterruptedly continued; the personal safety and property of the
                        inhabitants of the land and the common weal are endangered, and the legal
                        order seriously threatened. A revolutionary power, secret in its action, the
                        end and aim of which are directed against the safety and integrity of
                        Austria, usurps a formal sovereignty in my realms; demands taxes and other
                        contributions; puts its organs under oath and allegiance; and seeks to
                        secure obedience to, and execution of, its decrees through terror and every
                        other means, not recoiling even from assassination. Numerous facts indicate
                        that the revolutionary parties are now preparing to make very soon my
                        kingdom of Gallicia and Cracow the scene of open hostilities.</p>
                    <p>Such a condition of things cannot be allowed. Conscious of my duty as ruler
                        towards a land which forms an integral part of my empire, the inhabitants of
                        which in the most decisive majority are among my most faithful subjects, I
                        have found myself, after the fruitless employment of all the means offered
                        by the existing laws, forced to decree such extraordinary measures for
                        Gallicia as may secure internal peace and increased protection to person and
                        property.</p>
                    <p>People of Gallicia: That these measures may very soon be dispensed with is my
                        lively wish. Its gratification depends essentially upon your
                        concurrence.</p>
                    <p>I cherish the firm faith that the efforts of my government to secure
                        obedience to the laws and calm the disturbed condition of the land will not
                        fail of your aid. My care is ever for your weal; and I am determined to
                        spare no effort again at the earliest possible moment to secure to your land
                        the blessings of legal order, and thereby the pledge of the general
                        welfare.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Given at my capital,
                                <placeName>Vienna</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-02-24">February 24, 1864</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>FRANCIS JOSEPH, M. P., <hi rend="italic">Archduke Rainer, Rechberg,
                                Mecsery, Schmerling, Lasser Plener, Forgach, Esterhazy, Burger,
                                Hein-Mertens.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
