<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-02-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="10" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                    <head>10. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d10fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 28 <gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss> B. Secret;
                            Exdis. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_TWR2">Tyler</persName>. Prime
                            Minister Home visited Washington February 12–14 for talks with President
                                <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>. Preparatory
                            documents, briefing papers, and memoranda of conversation from the visit
                            are ibid., Conference Files: Lot 66 D 110, CF 2368–2369.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1964-02-12">February 12,
                                1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Berlin and Germany</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>The Secretary</item>
                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TWR2">Tyler</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>Prime Minister Douglas-Home</item>
                        <item>Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BRA3">Butler</persName>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>After the Secretary’s dinner for the Prime Minister at Blair House, he
                        outlined to the Prime Minister and to the Foreign Secretary the three-phase
                        proposals on Berlin and Germany. He told them that he could not leave the
                            paper<note n="2" xml:id="d10fn2">No copy of the paper was found.</note>
                        with them because the proposals merely represented tentative ideas on a
                        bolder approach to the problem, and could not be considered as a US
                        Government position. The Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary expressed
                        interest in the idea, but the Prime Minister <pb facs="0049" n="19" xml:id="pg_19"/> said he strongly doubted whether the German Government
                        would ever be willing to move decisively on the major issues, such as the
                        boundaries question and security, which would be the condition for any
                        Soviet acceptance of proposals by the West.</p>
                    <p>There was some discussion of how it might be possible to talk to <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> about this kind of approach
                        without having the Germans go through the roof. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRA3">Butler</persName> said he thought his personal
                        relations with <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> were good and
                        getting better, and that he might be able to talk to him alone (and he
                        emphasized that this meant without anyone else being present) when they met
                        again in March for the next <gloss target="#t_WEU1">WEU</gloss> meeting.
                        Another possibility might be for <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> to come to Geneva from his skiing vacation in
                        Switzerland to see Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRA3">Butler</persName> when
                        the latter goes there in another ten days. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRA3">Butler</persName> said he would think the matter over.</p>
                    <p>The Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary both lamented the negative state
                        of mind of the Germans with regard to observation posts and said they hoped
                        that some way might be found to bring them around to a more positive
                        attitude. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TWR2">Tyler</persName> commented that
                        the Germans probably saw in the observation posts proposal the thin end of a
                        wedge which might lead to a reduction of forces and other types of “thinning
                        out” in Central Europe before an acceptable political solution had been
                        negotiated with the Soviet Union. He added that, in his view, any direct or
                        implicit linking of observation posts with “thinning out” would merely
                        confirm German suspicions and increase their opposition.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said we should persevere in our search for a possible
                        initiative on Germany. This should be done by the kind of discussion they
                        were now having and should be very tightly held. These matters should not be
                        dealt with in the Ambassadorial Group. The Secretary suggested that we go
                        back over the last three years and take a look at all the ideas and
                        suggestions which the Germans have floated at one time or another on the
                        Berlin and Germany question, and which have not been subsequently followed
                        up. He thought that proposals could be put together on such a basis, which
                        would contain many of the elements in the package which he had just
                        described to the Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>, who had joined the group
                        halfway through the talk, emphasized the desirability of examining every
                        possibility of coming up with a peace initiative in the course of this year
                        which would win widespread public support.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>