<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-06-04T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-06-04T10:00:00-05:00" n="115" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                    <head>115. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d115fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Germany,
                            vol. 8. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PA7">Puhan</persName> and approved in <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>
                            and <gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss> on July 8. The meeting was held in
                            the Under Secretary’s conference room. The source text is marked “Part 1
                            of 4”; memoranda of other portions of the conversation are ibid. A
                            memorandum of conversation of the portion of the discussion dealing with
                            France and <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is <ref target="#d116">Document 116</ref>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1965-06-04T11:00:00-04:00">June 4, 1965, 11 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Trade with Eastern Europe and the Zone</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Germans</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Ludwig Erhard</persName>,
                                    Chancellor of the Federal Republic of Germany</item>
                                <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Gerhard Schroeder</persName>,
                                    Federal Minister for Foreign Affairs</item>
                                <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KHK1">Heinrich
                                        Knappstein</persName>, German Embassy</item>
                                <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_HK3">Karl Hohmann</persName>,
                                    Assistant Secretary; Chief, Planning Staff, Federal
                                    Chancery</item>
                                <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_OH3">Horst Osterheld</persName>,
                                    Deputy Assistant Secretary, Office of the Chancellor</item>
                                <item>Dr. <persName>Dankmar Seibt</persName>, Deputy Assistant
                                    Secretary, Personal Aide to the Chancellor</item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LG3">Georg von
                                    Lilienfeld</persName>, Minister, German Embassy</item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HKG1">Karl-Guenther von
                                        Hase</persName>, State Secretary; Federal Press
                                    Spokesman</item>
                                <item>Dr. <persName>Klaus Simon</persName>, Aide to Foreign Minister
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHJ2">Jorg Kastl</persName>, Foreign
                                    Ministry Press Spokesman</item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName>Ulrich Bewerunge</persName>, Press Officer,
                                    Federal Press &amp;Information Agency</item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName>Hermann Kusterer</persName>, Interpreter</item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WH3">Heinz Weber</persName>,
                                    Interpreter</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Americans</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>The Secretary</item>
                                <item>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">George W.
                                        Ball</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">George C.
                                        McGhee</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Llewellyn E.
                                        Thompson</persName>, <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_AL1">AL</gloss>
                                </item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">John M. Leddy</persName>,
                                    Assistant Secretary,<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>
                                </item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CRC1">Robert C. Creel</persName>,
                                    Deputy Assistant Secretary, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>
                                </item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PA7">Alfred Puhan</persName>,
                                    Director, <gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss>
                                </item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FRB2">Richard B. Finn</persName>,
                                    Deputy Director,<gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss>
                                </item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName>Harry Obst</persName>, Interpreter</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The Chancellor spoke of his pleasure at being here. He said that he was
                        certain the Secretary knew how keenly he felt about the Alliance. He <pb facs="0315" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/> referred to his upcoming talks
                        with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> which he said would
                        not be easy. They would concern not only the problems of the Six, but the
                        problems of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. The Chancellor felt it
                        was not necessary this morning to mention the German problem in particular.
                        He was grateful, as the Secretary knew, for the recent statements by the
                        President and other American leaders on the German problem.</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor said he had one question he wished to explore with the
                        Secretary. He stated that one heard a great deal today about the relations
                        of the West with the countries of Eastern Europe. <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName>, according to the Chancellor, had
                        described the solution to the German problem in terms of a better
                        relationship between the East and West. The Chancellor said it was his view
                        that the Eastern European countries had their own identity, were national
                        states whether Communist or not and that they threatened the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> with giving equal treatment to the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>. In the US, Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> said one hears more and more that
                        commercial relations with these Eastern European countries are useful. He
                        referred to an article in Life by Professor Brzezinski.<note n="2" xml:id="d115fn2">Not found.</note> The Chancellor said the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> was not hostile toward the Eastern European
                        countries, but it was premature to speculate regarding diplomatic relations
                        between these countries and the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>. He felt
                        the time for such action was not opportune. He thought that in view of the
                        rupture of relations caused with the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> by
                        ten Arab states and the upcoming Algiers conference of Afro-Asian
                            countries,<note n="3" xml:id="d115fn3">The Conference was held October
                            28–November 2. It ended without any agreements.</note> any speculation
                        regarding the establishment of diplomatic relations between the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> and the Eastern European countries would
                        only create an atmosphere of uncertainty.</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor asked if all Western European countries grant long term
                        credits to the Eastern European states, what will be achieved? Are we not
                        basically deceiving ourselves into thinking that we may achieve German
                        reunification in this way? He felt it would be difficult to explain such
                        actions to the German people. He thought that even when viewed from a long
                        range point of view, it was necessary for us to proceed with great caution.
                        If everybody gives long term credits to the Eastern European states, what
                        will they do with these credits? Perhaps they will increase their
                        armaments.</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor asked if it was not to be expected that the Soviets would
                        increase the pressure on the Eastern European countries as we are trying to
                        develop better relations with them. The Chancellor asked, as an economist,
                        when and under what conditions would these Eastern European countries be
                        ready to repay the credits extended to them? He was concerned that the
                        position of the creditors would in the last analysis be <pb facs="0316" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/> worse than that of the debtors. We would be
                        forced to continue giving them credit in the hope of getting repayment. He
                        warned that we could not give them the impression that we are doing this as
                        a gift. He voiced the necessity for the development of an economic strategy
                        in this field, a strategy based on a study of the results achieved. He asked
                        if granting credits has resulted in greater readiness to move away from the
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Had the chances for German
                        reunification actually improved? Or are these Eastern European states making
                        use of these funds to undermine the Western position? Were they financing
                        armies of liberation in other parts of the world? He said he felt ill at
                        ease at these thoughts.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary replied we saw considerable advantage in more relaxed relations
                        between East and West Europe, including improved relations between the
                        Federal Republic of Germany and the Communist states of Eastern Europe. He
                        believed important developments were taking place in Eastern Europe. The
                        smaller Eastern European countries have achieved a considerable degree of
                        national autonomy. This is decidedly to our advantage. The Secretary felt
                        there was underlying nostalgia in Eastern Europe for greater association
                        with the West in the cultural, intellectual as well as other fields. The
                        Secretary said the role of the US in such a policy toward Eastern Europe is
                        fairly restricted. US trade with Eastern Europe is only a small fraction of
                        Western European trade with that part of the world. It was not easy for us
                        to change this situation. There was legislation governing our trade with
                        Communist states. Congress would want to look with great care into any
                        change of this situation. Moreover, the attitude of Eastern Europe toward us
                        cannot help but be affected by developments in other parts of the world—in
                        Viet-Nam and Cuba, for example. Some Eastern European countries, the
                        Secretary suggested, may stand aside in conflicts involving us with the
                        Communists in other parts of the world, but a crisis like that of Viet-Nam
                        imposes inevitably limitations on us to improve the atmosphere, the
                        relations between us and Eastern Europe.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary expressed his full agreement with the Chancellor on the problem
                        of credits to the Communist Bloc. He said that we and the Federal Republic
                        had tended to view the problem in the same light, but that we have often
                        been disappointed by the positions taken by other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> powers. He felt it would be unfortunate if there developed
                        in the West a policy of giving easy credit terms to Eastern Europe. He said
                        when credits became aid, we were making a mistake in our priorities. We
                        should obviously not increase the capacity of Communist strength until the
                        prospects for much better relations with the Bloc looked brighter. The
                        Secretary felt that the idea of a détente had gone far beyond the facts. He
                        cited the nuclear test ban treaty as a stimulus to the notion that a détente
                        had been reached. To prove that this was not so, he cited crises which had
                        arisen since that time. He said there were indications the Soviets may <pb facs="0317" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/> press us on Berlin again. He
                        reminded the Chancellor of <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s
                        suggestion that there be four-power talks on Berlin. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, he said, also tried to have
                        bilateral talks with us on Berlin and our position there. The Secretary said
                        he gathered <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> in Paris took up
                        the German and Berlin questions, hinting that the Soviets were growing
                        impatient. The Secretary added that we had intelligence reports concerning
                        very large military maneuvers in Eastern Germany, suggesting that we might
                        find ourselves again with very great pressure over Berlin. It was thus
                        important for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> to try to talk out in
                        some detail the wide range of questions affecting our relations with Eastern
                        Europe. He deplored the absence of a strong Western policy on this subject
                        and the tendency to create confusion.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said, in summary, we have noted a steady relaxation of tensions
                        in Eastern Europe which made for better East-West relations. He said our
                        role in increasing this better relationship would be somewhat restricted. He
                        believed this subject should be discussed further in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. The Secretary asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> to comment further on this
                        subject.</p>
                    <p>The Under Secretary referred to the difficulties which the Federal Republic
                        had encountered when it sought to take the lead with Belgium in restricting
                        credits to Eastern Europe to the Berne Union rules. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> said we made our support of this
                        position clear and tried to persuade our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> partners to agree. The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>,
                        however, would not make any distinction between credits to Eastern European
                        countries and to others. As a result, a split developed within <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> with the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> followed by the French and the Italians going beyond the
                        Berne rules. The result was that we had no common policy, which was a matter
                        of great regret to us. Our suggestion to have the Berne Union rules accepted
                        as a standard was taken up in the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss>. The
                        British showed little sympathy for this suggestion. Subsequently, Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">Leddy</persName> undertook to push this
                        further, but I am not very sanguine as to what might be accomplished.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">Leddy</persName> said the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> would go along with general rules applicable
                        to all, but was afraid they would want to grant credits for as much as ten
                        years. We feel it was appropriate to limit them to five years.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> added that as long as we have
                        members of the Alliance who believe in no discrimination, it would be very
                        difficult to develop a common policy.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said he wished to add that it was important to draw
                        distinctions between the smaller countries of Eastern Europe on the basis of
                        the role they played in Communist conspiracies in other parts of the world.
                        For instance, Rumania was quite inactive, whereas the Czechs were very
                        troublesome.</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor said he would like to speak about the Soviet Zone of
                        Occupation of Germany. He said we heard more and more about <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> trade with the Zone. In this connection, he
                        wished to make it clear that <pb facs="0318" n="288" xml:id="pg_288"/>
                        interzonal trade was not a matter of choice for the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>, was not engaged in for economic reasons. The <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> undertook originally to help Germans in the
                        Zone when the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> was literally the only
                        source for aid. Now, he said, the situation had changed and the Zone can buy
                        more from other countries which has altered zonal trade a considerable
                        degree. If the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> gets long term credits,
                        it will in turn be able to offer credits to countries like the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> (350 million marks) to Indonesia and
                        Tanzania. By enhancing the economic status of the Zone, the West will in
                        turn permit the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> to enhance its political
                        status with countries like those above by assisting them economically.</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor added he agreed with the Secretary in making a clear
                        distinction between the Zone and the Communist Eastern European states.
                        Referring back to trade with the Communist Bloc, <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> said that even viewed from a businessman’s point of
                        view, it was a bad bargain. He urged that we look at trade with the Bloc
                        from an economic point of view. He saw disaster ahead if developments in the
                        trade field in this area were not kept under control. He noted there was
                        already competition in Western European countries to grant credits to
                        Eastern Europe, a ridiculous situation.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said he did believe trade with the Zone represented a special
                        case. He thought that this affected us very little since the volume of trade
                        between us and the Zone was so small and so much less than that of Western
                        European countries with the Zone.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary asked the Chancellor how he saw the so-called co-production
                        schemes like those of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BB3">Beitz</persName> in
                        Poland. Would they involve long term credits?</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor thought the possibilities of anything coming of these schemes
                        were rather limited. He envisioned no great opportunities for Krupp. He
                        again suggested that it would be up to the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> to achieve better coordination in the general field of
                        trade with Eastern Europe. He suggested that these countries could offer
                        mainly agricultural products only. The <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>
                        was not in a position to expand its imports of agricultural products to any
                        substantial extent. How were they going to repay the credits?</p>
                    <p>The Secretary assured the Chancellor that we had no intention of relaxing our
                        limitations on credits to the Communist Bloc. The Chancellor warned that
                        German industry would try to emulate the actions of other countries. He
                        pointed to <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> trade with the Eastern Bloc
                        as representing only four per cent of the total German volume. Before
                        Hitler, German trade with the same area was twenty per cent of the total
                        volume.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">Leddy</persName> if there
                        were any possibility of getting neutral countries like Switzerland and
                        Sweden to agree on credit terms if there was no unanimity in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                    <pb facs="0319" n="289" xml:id="pg_289"/>
                    <p>The Chancellor interposed the suggestion he was skeptical that neutrals like
                        Switzerland and Sweden, who were so sensitive lest they be accused of being
                        drawn into Alliances, would be influenced by <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> decisions. He thought the most useful forum was the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> where the situation could be discussed in
                        sober commercial terms without openly mentioning the political angles.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">Leddy</persName> expressed complete agreement
                        with the Chancellor. He said that our efforts to achieve an agreed policy in
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> had made no progress. To get the
                        neutrals in, you would have to proceed on a commercial basis. He agreed
                        fully it was wise to pursue this in the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> and to see how far we could get.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>