<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-09-01T12:54:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-09-01T12:54:00-05:00" n="166" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                    <head>166. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Germany</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d166fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,<gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss> W–US. Confidential. Repeated to
                            London and Paris.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-09-01T17:54:00+00:00">September 1, 1966,
                            1754Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>2698. Subj: Conversation with <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName>.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>I had a meeting with Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> today which he expressed at length his views on
                            world affairs along familiar lines. I raised certain points which
                            emerged in some of his recent interviews and invited his comments on the
                            domestic situation.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> immediately launched into
                            an exposition of the Soviet threat and what the West should do about it.
                            His starting point was the proposed Senate resolution of the Democratic
                            Policy Committee. I drew his attention to the comments by the White
                            House spokesman on this resolution and assured him that we had no
                            intention to withdraw major combat units.<note n="2" xml:id="d166fn2">See <ref target="#d165fn2">footnotes 2</ref> and <ref target="#d165fn3">3, Document 165</ref>.</note> The substance of
                                <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName>’s exposition was that
                            the Soviet military threat toward West Europe had not diminished. It was
                            imperative for the West to maintain an effective military posture in
                            Western Europe. Although he felt that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName> was generally correct in his criticism of the
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> organization, he regretted
                            that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> had taken France
                            out of that organization. The Soviets were confronted with three major
                            tasks: to build up their military forces in competition with the US, to
                            tackle major problems of domestic economic development, and to ready
                            themselves for the Chinese threat. The Soviets could not accomplish all
                            these tasks simultaneously, but would have to choose. It was in the
                            interest of the West to steer the Soviets in a direction whereby they
                            would concentrate on domestic development and the Chinese threat in
                            order to do so, the West must not lower its guard in Europe. A major US
                            troop withdrawal would lead the Soviets to believe that Western defenses
                            are crumbling and encourage them to adopt an offensive posture in
                            Europe. The West, on the other hand, should not itself adopt a
                            threatening posture vis-à-vis the Soviets as this, in turn, would lead
                            the Soviets to concentrate their efforts in Europe. The proper Western
                            posture in Europe was one of patient waiting while maintaining current
                            defense levels. This would offer the best chance that the Soviets would
                            divert their attention from Europe to their own domestic problems and to
                            the threat posed by Communist China and the Far East. They would realize
                            that Europe offered no threat to them but that Communist China
                            did.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>I pointed out that our govt fully shared the view that a Soviet threat
                            remained serious. It seemed, however, that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> held a different <pb facs="0436" n="406" xml:id="pg_406"/> view. <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> said that he would gladly talk to <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> about this. He was confident
                            that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> would be in basic
                            agreement with his analysis. He said <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName> shared his belief that the fates of Germany and
                            France were closely interwoven. If Germany fell prey to the Soviets,
                            France would be next. French interest rather than a desire to be kind to
                            Germany was the reason for <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName>’s defense of the German case during his recent
                            Moscow visit. <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> recalled a
                            meeting with Eisenhower, Macmillan and <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName> during which there had been a frank discussion of
                            the German problem. While Eisenhower and Macmillan had been somewhat
                            cautious, <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> had taken the
                            position that he desired reunification because he did not wish to see
                            Soviet troops on the Rhine.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>I mentioned the interview which <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> had given to Sulzberger on August 10 in which
                            he had said that we should withdraw from Viet Nam.<note n="3" xml:id="d166fn3">The interview took place on August 2. For
                                Sulzberger’s account, see <hi rend="italic">Age of Mediocrity</hi>,
                                pp. 278–282.</note> I pointed out that in our opinion such a
                            withdrawal under present conditions would have extremely dangerous
                            consequences and that it might also be interpreted by the Soviets as
                            softness and in Europe and elsewhere as unwillingness on our part to
                            adhere to our commitments. I also said that we appreciated his views on
                            this as well as on any other problem but that we hoped he would give
                            them to us directly rather than through the press. <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> said he wanted to explain his
                            position to me very frankly. He had not asked for the interview but he
                            had welcomed it as an opportunity to draw attention to a situation which
                            he felt was very serious. What he really feared was that the question of
                            US obligations and commitments might become a serious issue in the US
                            Presidential campaign. He had given the interview in the hope of
                            provoking a statement from us reiterating the firmness of our commitment
                            in Europe.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Commenting on the current crisis in the Defense Ministry <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> said that in his opinion
                                <persName corresp="#p_HKU1">Von Hassel</persName> must go. He
                            thought this would happen fairly soon. A structural reform of the
                            Defense Ministry was also necessary—the tasks were too vast for one man
                            to handle. He said no decision had as yet been reached whether to
                            appoint an additional Minister or Political State Secretary to the
                            Defense Ministry, or whether to transfer some of the Defense Ministry’s
                            responsibilities to another Ministry.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>I asked <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> for his views
                            on the current prospects of the <gloss target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss>. He
                            said the situation was very bad. The voters were clearly dissatisfied
                            with the present govt. The problem was that under the German
                            Constitution a Chancellor was practically irremovable. Also, <gloss target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss> leaders had been dispersed during the
                            summer months and had made separate uncoordinated statements.
                            Nevertheless, unless the direction and style of operation of the govt
                            underwent a rapid change, the <gloss target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss> would
                                <pb facs="0437" n="407" xml:id="pg_407"/> surely lose the next
                            Federal elections. He said that he was greatly concerned about the
                            declining health of <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> leaders
                                <persName corresp="#p_EF4">Erler</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_WH6">Wehner</persName>. If they disappeared, the left
                            wing—those who had, among other things, advocated the speakers exchange
                            with the <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss> which he continued to
                            regard as a serious mistake—would take over. A dangerous situation would
                            arise in Europe if France, after <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de
                                Gaulle</persName>, had a popular front govt and Germany an <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> govt under left-wing leadership. I
                            asked <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> what kind of a
                            change of direction he considered necessary. He said “The government
                            must resume the course which I pursued as Chancellor. Coming from me,
                            this may sound vain; but it is not immodest if I consider myself a bit
                            more intelligent than certain others who are very stupid.”</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> looked pallid on the eve of
                        his departure for a vacation at Caddenabia. However he was alert and in good
                        spirits. I have reported his views on global problems in some detail even
                        though they represent little that is new. I was told today by Kingsbury
                        Smith of Hearst that the Chancellor expressed similar views in an interview
                        with him which he will be reporting. <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName>’s comments on domestic matters reflect his
                        undiminished disdain for <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> as
                        Chancellor, also <persName corresp="#p_HKU1">Von Hassel</persName> as Def
                        Min. <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> has recently been heard
                        recommending <persName corresp="#p_GE2">Gerstenmaier</persName> as <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName>’s successor. It is obvious that he
                        hopes that a combination of <gloss target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss> leaders can
                        soon be put together which could tackle the problem of <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName>’s succession.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">
                                <hi rend="strong">McGhee</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>