<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>239. Telegram From the Embassy in Germany to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d239</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">239</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-11-15T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-11-15T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJFd5tAUUdqBj9H" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">East-West relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recozOKDL3hzRM0mM" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-11-15T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-11-15T14:00:00-05:00" n="239"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                <head>239. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Germany</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d239fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                            Files,<gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> E–<gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss>.
                        Confidential; Priority; Limdis. Repeated to Paris, London, Moscow, <gloss
                            target="#t_USNATO1">USNATO</gloss>, Belgrade, and Warsaw.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-11-15T19:00:00+00:00">November 15, 1967,
                        1900Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5213. Subj: Meeting with Chancellor Kiesinger, East-West relations.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The present telegram summarizes the discussion of Germany’s relations with
                        the East which took place during the call I paid on Chancellor <persName
                            corresp="#p_KKG1">Kiesinger</persName> today at my request. Other
                        subjects discussed are reported in septels.<note n="2" xml:id="d239fn2">
                            <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">McGhee</persName> reported on their
                            discussion of <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> in telegram 5211 from
                            Bonn, November 15. (Ibid., DEF 18–6)</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I queried the Chancellor on his press statement made on Nov 3<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d239fn3">For text, see Meissner, <hi rend="italic">Die deutsche
                                Ostpolitik</hi>, pp. 230–231.</note> when he had, after repeating
                        the standard German line that there can be no final agreement on the
                        Oder-Neisse border except through a peace treaty, said: “That does not
                        exclude, for example, that joint discussions of such a solution acceptable
                        to both peoples could be arranged before such a peace treaty.” The
                        Chancellor replied that there was in his view nothing to prevent such
                        discussions, the purpose of which would be “just to build up a little more
                        trust.” He is aware that the Poles do not, at the present time, consider the
                        question a subject for discussion. The Poles are not willing even to accept
                        the German offer for mutual declarations against the use of force.
                        Apparently they feel that this would weaken their case in building Germany
                        up as a threat. In response to my question, he elaborated on what he had in
                        mind in making his statement—that he might tell the Poles that, although a
                        final decision could only be made by a united Germany, “We could imagine,
                        however, a solution along the lines of (blank).” <persName corresp="#p_KKG1"
                            >Kiesinger</persName> did not appear to be fully informed as to Polish
                            <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RA4">Rapacki</persName>’s reported statement in
                        Luxembourg on Nov 4<note n="4" xml:id="d239fn4">Not found.</note> to the
                        effect that Poland would be willing to normalize relations with Germany if
                        the Oder-Neisse issue could be settled. After discussion with his aides he
                        did not believe, however, that too much credence could be attached to this
                        report. The fact is, he said, that the Poles do not believe the Germans when
                        they offer assurances. He knows the Poles very well. They are suspicious by
                        nature as a result of their unhappy contacts with the Prussians over the
                        years (which was not the case in their contacts with southern Germans). The
                        Poles tend to react in the light of what they would do if they were in the
                        German position.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>According to Kiesinger, German East-West efforts must be directed not just
                        to the Communist countries. They must seek to convince <pb facs="0640"
                            n="610" xml:id="pg_610"/> the whole world that although they will
                        exercise their rights, they are seeking solutions in a responsible way on
                        the basis of justice for all. In doing so they recognize fully that the
                        first step must be the creation of a détente. Unification cannot be expected
                        to precede détente. In his judgement, they should have moved more quickly in
                        the beginning of his administration to establish relations with Hungary and
                        perhaps other countries before <persName corresp="#p_UW1"
                            >Ulbricht</persName> made his counter-attack. In response to my query
                        about the rumors that they might move toward establishing diplomatic
                        relations with Yugoslavia, he replied that the majority of the <gloss
                            target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CSU1">CSU</gloss> is not
                        yet prepared for such a step. He, himself, is not so worried at such an
                        apparent breach of the Hallstein Doctrine, although he admitted that it
                        would be a great defeat if India—for example—should as a result establish
                        relations with East Germany.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Kiesinger was pessimistic as to overall prospects for improvement of
                        East-West relations. However, he thought the Germans must continue to try.
                        Many changes will take place within the next 5–10 years which might be
                        favorable to their cause. The Chancellor spoke of his conversation of the
                        evening before with the Hannover industrialist Philipp von Bismarck, himself
                        a refugee from East Germany. Bismarck had advised him that for the first
                        time the refugee groups in Germany are taking Eastern policy seriously—and
                        on a realistic basis. There are those who argue that the govt’s Eastern
                        policy involves risk, <persName corresp="#p_KKG1">Kiesinger</persName>
                        continued—that there will be no immediate success and that in the end the
                        people will accuse the govt of having raised “illusions” and having ended up
                        in a “dead end.” He fully supported the policy which he and <gloss
                            target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWHF1">Brandt</persName> had developed, which was
                        based on the desire to move forward but without expectation of immediate
                        success. This policy, which had the official backing of the <gloss
                            target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CSU1">CSU</gloss>, was
                        not seriously contested within the party (this was confirmed by a group of
                            <gloss target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss> Parliamentarians at lunch-eon today,
                        as is being reported separately).</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>I advised the Chancellor that we had followed the efforts of his govt in
                        East-West relations closely, and that we had found nothing to take exception
                        to. His policy was consistent with that of our own in attempting to build
                        bridges to the East, although we were in the present circumstances
                        handicapped in our own efforts. The Chancellor commented that he did not
                        think there was much we could do under the circumstances. The Chancellor
                        assured me that Germany would of course not undertake any action with the
                            <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss>s which affected the US without first
                        consulting fully with us. I said that we appreciated this and that this was
                        particularly important where US forces were involved such as proposals for
                        mutual force reductions.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">
                            <hi rend="strong">McGhee</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
