<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>52. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d52</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">52</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-06-12T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-06-12T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec7MjCJlGL6L85Od" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Joint statement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recTNMFmPG15mKxJQ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-06-12T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-06-12T11:00:00-05:00" n="52"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d52">
                <head>52. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d52fn1"
                        >Source: Johnson library, National Security File, Country File: Germany,
                            <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> Visit, June 1964.
                        Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CRC1">Creel</persName> and
                        approved in <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss> on June 19. The meeting was held
                        at the White House. The source text is marked “Part 2 of 4.” Memoranda of
                        conversation dealing with the French attitude toward <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and internal German politics are ibid. A
                        memorandum of conversation covering the discussion of German-Chinese
                        relations is <ref target="#d51">Document 51</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1964-06-12T12:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 12, 1964, noon</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Soviet-<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> Treaty of Friendship and Mutual
                        Assistance</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>[Here follows the same list of participants as <ref target="#d51">Document
                            51</ref>.]</item>
                </list>
                <p>At Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName>’s request,
                    the interpreter read a report on the speech made by <persName corresp="#p_UW1"
                        >Ulbricht</persName> in Moscow today at the signing of the Soviet-<gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> Treaty of Friendship, Mutual Assistance and
                        Cooperation.<note n="2" xml:id="d52fn2">Not found with the source text.
                        Extracts of the joint communiqué are printed in <hi rend="italic">Documents
                            on Germany, 1944–1985</hi>, pp. 872–875.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> said he wished to draw
                    particular attention to the passage in which <persName corresp="#p_UW1"
                        >Ulbricht</persName> had stated that German unification was possible only
                    through negotiations between the two German states, but that in such a case the
                    treaty could be revised. <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName>
                    wondered whether this was part of the treaty itself or merely an interpretation
                    of it by <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName>. If it were the former,
                    then maybe it could be regarded as a sort of alibi on the part of <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> for not taking any action on German
                    reunification.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said we had just received a report from Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> in Moscow on the delivery of the oral
                    démarches to the Soviets about the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>-<gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> treaty that had been agreed on in Washington
                        yesterday.<note n="3" xml:id="d52fn3">Telegram 3740 from Moscow, June 12.
                        (Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 21
                            <gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss> E–<gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss>) For text of the U.S. statement on the Soviet-East German
                        agreement, see <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current Documents,
                            1964</hi>, p. 536.</note> The US, British and French démarches were
                    being delivered separately in Moscow today. The three démarches did not include
                    the sentence which had been suggested by the Secretary rejecting Soviet charges
                    of German revanchism. The British in Moscow had objected to this sentence on the
                    ground it was superfluous. The Secretary said that even so we could get this
                    sentence back in the picture in our oral statements on the matter.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that, with regard to <persName corresp="#p_UW1"
                        >Ulbricht</persName>’s statement about “the only path to reunification”, he
                    wondered to what extent this mention of reunification had been considered
                    necessary by <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> from the standpoint
                    of East German public opinion.</p>
                <pb facs="0152" n="122" xml:id="pg_122"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> said that in the past East Zone
                    leaders had for many years claimed to be the champions of German unity. It was
                    true the theme had been neglected for some time but they now seemed to be
                    reactivating it. Possibly this was being done for the benefit of the young
                    people in East Germany.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said we should be prepared for any follow-up on this assertion of
                        “<gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> sovereignty”. We should have the
                    Ambassadorial Group review the situation and check our intelligence as to
                    whether the agreement contemplates making any new difficulties on the Autobahn,
                    for example in connection with the scheduled July 1 meeting in Berlin of the
                    Bundesversammlung.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> said he felt that what was
                    needed at this moment was a demonstration of a common position by the Three
                    Powers. He pointed out that the démarches in Moscow had been delivered
                        separately<note n="4" xml:id="d52fn4">For text of the démarche, see <hi
                            rend="italic">Documents on Germany, 1944–1985</hi>, pp. 869–872.</note>
                    and that the Three could not agree on the admirable sentence suggested by the
                    Secretary. It was important that there be some sort of joint declaration by the
                    Three that no impairment of Berlin access could be accepted. It might be
                    desirable to move quickly since Pankow might wish to test Western resolution.
                    The Three Powers would have to make quite clear that no changes in the Berlin
                    situation could be accepted.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that after we had a chance to study the text of the treaty,
                    there should be consultation among all four of us very quickly to consider the
                    issuance of a joint statement. Such a statement might also be helpful in meeting
                    the German problem about support for reunification.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> said he felt such a statement
                    should be made on June 15 or 16. The Secretary agreed, but pointed out the
                    difficulty of transacting business over weekends.<note n="5" xml:id="d52fn5">For
                        text of the three-power statement, released on June 26, see Department of
                        State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, July 13, 1964, pp. 44–45.</note>
                </p>
                <p>State Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WL5">Westrick</persName> referred to the
                    passage in the <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> speech describing
                    West Berlin “as an independent political unit”. It would be a good idea for any
                    joint statement to take issue with that statement, which was always coming up
                    from the Communist side in the pass negotiations and other ways.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said we might have some problems with our Allies on this.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WL5">Westrick</persName> said he could not imagine any
                    real problem with the Allies, who had never said that West Berlin was an
                    independent unit. <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> said he
                    thought that we had already had formulas on this point that we could refer to.
                    He agreed with <persName corresp="#p_WL5">Westrick</persName> that we should
                    take a position on it. It would also be helpful for there to be a joint Allied
                    statement about reunification. There had not been such a statement for some
                    time.</p>
                <pb facs="0153" n="123" xml:id="pg_123"/>
                <p>The Secretary inquired if <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName>
                    attached any significance to the distinction between this treaty and a peace
                    treaty. <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> replied in the
                    affirmative. He said that a peace treaty would involve important arrangements in
                    the field of European security, and these could not be undertaken as long as
                    Germany was divided. The present treaty seemed to be a substitute, at least for
                    the time being, for a peace treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WL5">Westrick</persName> inquired whether <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> had stated to the Secretary that the
                    present treaty was not a peace treaty. The Secretary said that <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> had only read an oral démarche and had
                    added no comment.<note n="6" xml:id="d52fn6">A memorandum of their June 8
                        conversation is scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1964-68v14">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, volume
                        XIV</ref>.</note> He had not said that this was not a peace treaty or not to
                    take it seriously.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WL5">Westrick</persName> said he had been referring to the
                    report in this morning’s <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> said this was probably just
                    speculation. The Secretary said that maybe the Soviets had intimated something
                    of the sort to the press in Moscow, but <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> had intimated nothing at all to him beyond the oral
                    démarche.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
