<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-01-14T22:39:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-01-14T22:39:00-05:00" n="86" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d86">
                    <head>86. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Germany</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d86fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,<gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 32–4 <gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss>. Secret; Immediate; Nodis. Drafted in the White House
                            and approved by <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-01-14T22:39:00-05:00">January 14, 1965, 10:39 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>1980. To Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">McGhee</persName> from
                            <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName>. For your private
                        information, the President has read some but not all of your recent reports
                        and also what <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName> has reported of
                        the view that Fontaine of <hi rend="italic">Le Monde</hi> brought back from
                            Germany.<note n="2" xml:id="d86fn2">Telegram 3922 from Paris, January
                            11. (Ibid., INF 7 FR–<gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss> W)</note> He is
                        not troubled by what the French say, but he does want you to know of his
                        reaction to the German nervousness which you report. The President has made
                        his position on Germany most amply clear on many occasions. He remembers how
                        firm <pb facs="0240" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/> and clear he was with
                        Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> at the Ranch.<note n="3" xml:id="d86fn3">See <ref target="frus1961-63v15#d248">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1961–1963, vol. XV,
                                Document 248</ref>.</note> He recollects the extended assurance and
                        the full exposition in his Georgetown speech only a month ago. He recalls
                        that at the request of the Germans he made a further and explicit reference
                        to reunification in his State of the Union message. He recalls his own
                        recent conversations with you at the Ranch<note n="4" xml:id="d86fn4">See
                                <ref target="#d79fn2">footnote 2, Document 79</ref>.</note> in which
                        further reassurances were given and in which you explained your conviction
                        that the Germans would be greatly relieved by the President’s shift away
                        from pressure tactics on the <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss>. The
                        President does not now find it agreeable to have repeated and renewed German
                        questions about the firmness of his purpose or the direction of his
                        policy.</p>
                    <p>I have discussed with the President the psychological and electoral causes of
                        the reactions you have encountered as I understand it. He hears me but he
                        would like you to hear him.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                                <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>