<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="133" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">884.796/12</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-22">October 22,
                                1942</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: The attention of your Excellency
                            is invited to Article XI (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) of the Agreement
                            between the United Kingdom and Ethiopia, signed January 31, 1942,<note n="40" xml:id="d133fn40">Signed at Addis Ababa, <hi rend="italic">British and Foreign State Papers</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cxliv</hi>, p. 989.</note> in which it is
                            stated that the Emperor of Ethiopia will not permit foreign aircraft,
                            other than British aircraft, to fly to, in, or over Ethiopia without the
                            concurrence of the Government of the United Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>In an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> which this Department delivered
                            to your Embassy on May 27, 1942<note n="41" xml:id="d133fn41">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_21">p.
                                21</ref>.</note> in reply to one from your Embassy of April 15,
                                1942,<note n="42" xml:id="d133fn42">Unauthenticated copies in the
                                files of the Department are not printed.</note> this Department
                            referred to the air transport situation in the Near and Middle East and
                            Africa, and expressed the hope that neither the Government of the United
                            Kingdom nor the Government of the United States would set up
                            arrangements which would exclude in these areas air transport lines of
                            the other, except after consultation through diplomatic channels. In
                            your Embassy’s <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of July 28,
                                1942,<note n="43" xml:id="d133fn43">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_23">p.
                                23</ref>.</note> it was stated that His Majesty’s Government
                            concurred in this principle. In the circumstances it is assumed that
                            your Government has no intention of opposing the granting to United
                            States aviation interests of an equality of opportunity in Ethiopia.</p>
                        <p>I shall greatly appreciate it if you will inform me whether the provision
                            in the Agreement with Ethiopia referred to above is to be interpreted by
                            your Government in the manner indicated.</p>
                        <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                            <signed>A. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Berle, Jr</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>