<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Winant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d165</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">165</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-07-25T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-07-25T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-07-25T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-07-25T20:00:00-05:00" n="165"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d165">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.24/222a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-25T21:00:00-04:00"
                            >July 25, 1942—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3475. In recent months our Minister at Tehran and Iranian Minister here have
                    repeatedly called to our attention bitter dissatisfaction of Iranians with
                    exclusive control exercised by UKCC over importation and distribution in Iran of
                    tires, trucks and other essential articles. They have insisted that Iranian
                    transportation needs were not receiving due consideration and that entire
                    internal transportation system, which depends heavily upon trucks, was on the
                    verge of breakdown which would have disastrous results. General attitude of UKCC
                    toward Iranians was reported as overbearing and uncooperative. On July 20
                    Minister Dreyfus reported relations had reached breaking point over question of
                    tire distribution and recommended that Department make representations to
                    British Government looking toward modification of UKCC attitude.</p>
                <p>On July 22, however, Dreyfus cabled that Sir Frank Nixon, London head of UKCC,
                    was in Tehran and had intervened personally to direct adoption of a more
                    conciliatory policy. Nixon told Dreyfus that UKCC had made great mistakes in
                    Iran, especially in riding <pb facs="0161" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> rough shod
                    over Iranian susceptibilities, and that he planned to correct errors. He has
                    reorganized corporation’s staff in Iran and has apologized to Iranian Finance
                    Ministry for past attitude of UKCC employees. Nixon favors joint Allied-Iranian
                    supervision of tire and truck distribution, which it is understood Iranians will
                    accept and which is entirely acceptable to Department.</p>
                <p>Consequently, Department has decided to await developments before taking up the
                    question with the British Government. Please inform Foreign Office, however,
                    that we feel that a greater degree of American participation in the distribution
                    of supplies sent from the United States would tend to reassure the Iranians and
                    enlist their cooperation in solving the many delicate problems involved,
                    problems which are reported to have given rise to considerable friction between
                    the Iranians and the UKCC. You should add that we are gratified to learn that
                    very recently there have been indications of a UKCC policy of conciliation
                    toward the Iranians, which we believe will have a good effect upon the serious
                    economic and political situation. In view of its frequent suggestions that
                    American advisers of various kinds be sent to Iran, we assume the British
                    Government agrees with the viewpoint that American participation in supply
                    distribution would be helpful. Accordingly, we propose to send to Iran in the
                    immediate future an American representative to collaborate with the Iranian and
                    British authorities in directing the distribution of all civilian supplies sent
                    to Iran from this country in consequence of Iranian Government orders or
                    Lend-Lease requisitions made by or on behalf of the Iranian Government. It is
                    thought that it may be desirable to name a consignee other than the UKCC for
                    such orders, but such a change would in no way affect proper distribution in the
                    light of Allied and Iranian requirements. The American representative would, of
                    course, work closely with UKCC and other British agencies in accordance with
                    general policies determined by consultation between British, American and
                    Iranian authorities, and we should be glad to discuss his instructions with the
                    British Government.</p>
                <p>In accordance with Iranian request, supported by British Government, we also hope
                    to send a food and supply adviser for Iranian Government within next few
                    weeks.</p>
                <p>The procedure indicated above does not, of course, contemplate any modification
                    of existing arrangement whereby Iranian import requests are to be submitted to
                    Central Supplies Committee at Tehran and forwarded through Middle East Supply
                    Center.</p>
                <p>When discussing this with Foreign Office, please take occasion to mention
                    informally a recent instance in which British military in Iran requisitioned
                    3,000 tires ordered by Iranian Government from United States. We are informed
                    Iranians strongly resent this action <pb facs="0162" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/>
                    and that they plan formal protest. You should indicate that this Government
                    hopes that the Allied forces may find that, without jeopardizing their own
                    requirements, these tires, or at least a portion of them, can be returned to the
                    Iranians for distribution under Allied supervision. Such action, we feel, might
                    have a very beneficial effect in terms of good will.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
