<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Iran ( (Dreyfus) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d178</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">178</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-10-21T10:35:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-10-21T10:35:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recFe9iZmLH8fc4Ed" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103898"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Harvest</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recBTfVgprHsl1J9K" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85047074"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Famine</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-21T10:35:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-21T10:35:00-05:00" n="178"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d178">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/1925: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dreyfus</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-21T19:00:00+03:25"
                            >October 21, 1942—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 23—11:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>334. Section 1. Refer my 333, October 20. There is quoted in section 3 below text
                    of a draft prepared by British Legation of a proposed joint Anglo-American
                    declaration.</p>
                <p>Iran Government has prepared and telegraphed to its Legation in London a
                    counterdraft which differs from British draft in following main respects: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The joint declaration is changed to an agreement between Iranian,
                            British and American Governments.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Iran Government has struck out paragraph (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of
                            the engagement which British draft would have imposed on them and agrees
                            only to put into [effect food] and road transport measures recommended
                            by Sheridan.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Iranians have introduced new clause which British had stricken from an
                            earlier draft as objectionable. Clause states British and American
                            Governments are at once importing into Tehran 25,000 tons wheat to be
                            stored in silos as reserve to be supervised by Ministry of Food and
                            Sheridan and disposed of only case necessity and then only on consent of
                            majority of following: Minister of Food, Sheridan, American and British
                            Legations.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Section 2. Iranian draft should be changed to place responsibility for measures
                    regarding road transport on Anglo-Iranian-American Transport Committee which is
                    supreme in such matters.</p>
                <p>British state that Iranian allocation on railway is only 200 tons a day so that
                    it would take 125 days to move 25,000 tons of wheat to Tehran from the port to
                    the exclusion of other goods. This argument is hollow for if Iran’s pressing
                    need for essential goods is established it is the duty of the Allies to lend
                    their assistance. In view of length of time involved in shipping wheat and
                    transporting it to Tehran and considering great possibility of a wheat
                    deficiency I am of the <pb facs="0174" n="162" xml:id="pg_162"/> opinion that we
                    should approve the Iranian Government’s demand for a reserve of 25,000 tons.</p>
                <p>Section 3. Draft declaration dated October 19, 1942: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Governments of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern
                            Ireland and United States of America bearing in mind that the
                            responsibility for feeding the people of Iran rests primarily upon the
                            Imperial Iranian Government, and having in mind the economic distress
                            that war conditions may bring to the people of Iran, and the
                            desirability of ensuing [<hi rend="italic">ensuring</hi>] the supply of
                            bread for the people of Iran until the 1943 harvest, thereby declare as
                            follows:</p>
                        <p>In consideration of the undertaking given by the Imperial Iranian
                            Government to carry out, <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>All the measures recommended by the American adviser to the
                                    Ministry of Food, such as measures to prevent hoarding and the
                                    introduction of rationing of foodstuffs, and</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>All such recommendations of the Road Transport Committee as
                                    are certified to be essential for the regulation of the means of
                                    road transport in Iran by the majority vote of the following
                                    three members of the Committee, namely, the Iranian Chairman and
                                    the British and American members of the Committee respectively
                                    designated for the purpose by the British and American Ministers
                                    in Tehran.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Then, if the Iranian Minister of Food, with the concurrence of his
                            American adviser, and the American and British Legations in Tehran, by a
                            majority vote, are satisfied that all practicable steps have been taken
                            by Iranian Government in accordance with their undertaking referred to
                            above, and that nevertheless the supply of cereals (wheat and barley)
                            which has been or can be collected in and transported to the various
                            centers of consumption, or any one of them, is likely to prove
                            insufficient to feed the population of such center or centers, the
                            following procedure shall be observed: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>In the case of a deficiency in the total supply of cereals
                                    (wheat and barley) the Governments of the United States of
                                    America and United Kingdom undertake to arrange for the
                                    importation into Iran and delivery to the various centers of
                                    consumption of the quantity of cereals (wheat and barley)
                                    necessary to make good the deficiency until the following
                                    harvest, at such times as may be necessary to obviate the
                                    possibility of famine.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>In the case of a temporary deficiency in the supply of cereals
                                    (wheat and barley) at any particular center (whether there
                                    should simultaneously be a general deficiency) the Governments
                                    of the United States of America and the United Kingdom undertake
                                    to provide and deliver to the particular center of consumption
                                    the amount of the temporary deficiency at such times as may be
                                    necessary to obviate the possibility of famine.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dreyfus</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
