<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Egypt ( (Kirk) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d190</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">190</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-10-31T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-10-31T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-31T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-31T10:00:00-05:00" n="190"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d190">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/1934: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-31T17:00:00+02:00"
                            >October 31, 1942—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 8:59 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1908. Department’s 1304, October 26, 5 p.m. Following from feed Winant.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Further discussions with Middle East authorities in Cairo regarding crisis
                        in Iran bring out following points: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>In view extreme emergency due to November 2 expiration date for
                                further note issued [<hi rend="italic">issue?</hi>] it is felt that
                                it may be necessary to rely on notification to the Iranian
                                Government to be simultaneously presented by the United States,
                                United Kingdom and Soviet Governments requesting a continuance of
                                the expiring time limit.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>Currency note issue still main stumbling block. London feels
                                Iranian Government should observe terms of financial agreement
                                entered into for duration of war and questions efficacy of proposed
                                currency commission. Here there are suggestions of possible
                                concessions on rate of exchange and convertibility of balances into
                                gold. Unanimous British opinion that use of force is very much last
                                resort.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>Food declaration in form of agreement to which Iranian Government
                                would be party is fully agreed upon by British authorities. They
                                question however the physical facilities of providing any immediate
                                reserve of 25,000 tons of wheat in Tehran and also question location
                                of any such reserve when it might be accumulated. They prefer
                                location at ports to better service southern area and for reason
                                that reserve in Tehran might prove deterrent to uncovering hoarded
                                wheat. Also due to existing strained capacity of railroad Tehran
                                should normally be supplied from adjacent and northern area.</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>Fact that Russians seek to purchase from Iranian authorities some
                                20,000 tons wheat and barley is not understood here to mean that no
                                further supply of cereals will be available for Tehran from Russian
                                zone in Iran. Cooperation of Soviet Government is sought not only to
                                assist Iranians in wheat for Tehran but also to preserve operation
                                of railroad from South at maximum capacity for war supplies for
                                Russian front.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>To replace the 20,000 tons of cereals for which the Russians
                                negotiated it is proposed to import into Iran a like amount of
                                cereals as the shipping situation permits.</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>In spite of scarcity of wheat in Tehran it is still felt here that
                                motor transport is one of chief difficulties. Until appearance of
                                civilian trucks scheduled for Persian Gulf area it is planned to
                                provide lorries to assist temporarily Iranian Government in handling
                                wheat. It is hoped to release 150 lorries over 1 month’s period for
                                this work. Run from this area to Tehran requires about 17
                                days.</item>
                            <pb facs="0188" n="176" xml:id="pg_176"/>
                            <label>(6)</label>
                            <item>In all discussions to date and in most telegrams seen point has
                                been stressed of importance united and fully cooperative action on
                                part of United States and British Governments through their
                                Ministers in Tehran. The British here point out the necessary
                                concern of the United States Government in the matter of an adequate
                                supply of rials. They believe that the two Governments should
                                present a firm common front regarding financial aspects as well as
                                regarding material supplies covering cereal requirements. They
                                further believe that if the present pressing problem may be met that
                                it is unlikely that future situations will be as complicated
                                particularly in view of the expected increased efficiency of the
                                Iranian Government because of the additions of American
                                advisers.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <p>Not repeated to Tehran.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
