<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-10T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-10T16:00:00-05:00" n="230" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d230">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">891.00/1960: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-10T22:00:00+01:00">December 10, 1942—10 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received December 10—8:22 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>6999. Substance of Department’s 6232, December 9, 8 p.m. concerning
                                situation prevailing in Iran has been communicated to <pb facs="0225" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> Foreign Office. Foreign
                                Office states that it was informed of rioting in Tehran by British
                                Minister. With reference to present Cabinet, Foreign Office says
                                that it also feels that while this group is in some respects
                                unsatisfactory, a change at this time would be most inopportune.
                                Unfortunately, Foreign Office adds, the Shah himself apparently
                                wishes to dismiss Qavam. As Foreign Office, however, feels so
                                strongly about the advisability of retaining the present Cabinet in
                                power, it instructed the British Minister at Tehran on December 9 to
                                see the Shah and to emphasize how disruptive a change of Cabinet
                                would be at this particular time.</p>
                            <p>Foreign Office also states that it fully realizes that extreme
                                shortage of wheat, particularly in Tehran, is primary cause of
                                unrest and disorder. According to its information, which is
                                confirmed by the Soviet Ambassador at Tehran, some 35,000 tons of
                                wheat are available in the northern provinces of Iran, which are
                                under Soviet occupation. On two occasions recently the Soviet
                                Ambassador at Tehran assured the British Minister there that the
                                Soviet authorities would in no way impede the transportation of
                                wheat from this area to Tehran. As the food shortage may become much
                                more acute within the last few days, and as there is this supply of
                                wheat in the northern provinces immediately available, Foreign
                                Office also instructed the British Minister on December 9 to see the
                                Soviet Ambassador and urge him to do everything he can to enlist the
                                support of the Soviet authorities in those provinces in actually
                                transporting this wheat to Tehran. At the same time, the British
                                Minister at Tehran was instructed to report whether it has been
                                possible to obtain wheat in Iraq for Iran and, if so, whether any of
                                this has been shipped, and also to report how much, if any, barley
                                has been shipped to Iran from Iraq.</p>
                            <p>In connection with the possibility of obtaining some wheat and barley
                                in Iraq for immediate shipment to Iran see my Embassy’s 6518, of
                                November 19, 7 p.m.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>