<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of Near Eastern
                    Affairs ( (Alling))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-09-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-09-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="286"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d286">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.20/186⅓</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        Near Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Alling</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-09-15">September 15,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Hayter<note n="27" xml:id="d286fn27">W. G. Hayter, First Secretary of the
                        British Embassy.</note> said that the Foreign Office had instructed the
                    Embassy again to inform the State Department of the importance which the British
                    Government attached to the appointment of an American military mission to
                    Iran.</p>
                <p>I told Mr. Hayter that the War Department had recently decided that it could not
                    send a military mission at this time. However, the War Department did propose to
                    send to Iran General Ridley, who would take the place of General Greely. I said
                    that it was our understanding that General Ridley would be instructed to report
                    on the situation and that as a result of that report I thought the War
                    Department might give further consideration to the appointment of an American
                    military mission.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hayter said he hoped we could find an opportunity to let the Iranian Minister
                    here know that the British Government had fully supported on more than one
                    occasion the proposal for an American military mission to Iran. He said that if
                    such information could be conveyed to the Iranian Legation it would be helpful
                    to the British <pb facs="0267" n="255" xml:id="pg_255"/> in as much as the
                    Iranian Prime Minister apparently was under the impression that such a proposal
                    had met with British opposition. I told Mr. Hayter I would see what could be
                    done.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
