<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Frederick Winant of the Division of Exports and Defense Aid
                    to the Assistant Secretary of State ( (Acheson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d5</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">5</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="5"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.24/342½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Frederick
                            Winant</persName> of the Division of Exports and Defense Aid to the
                        Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Acheson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-04-17">April 17,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Civilian Supply Requirements of the Near East Countries and
                        The Middle East Supply Centre</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acheson</hi>: The procedure for handling the civilian
                    supply requirements of the countries comprising the Near East must be reexamined
                    in the light of the procedure now established for that area by the British, the
                    combined controls now existing in Washington and London, the effect on the
                    civilian population of present and potential military developments in that
                    theater of war, and the political influences that may be brought to bear on the
                    general situation.</p>
                <p>The present manner of handling Near East supplies from the United States sources
                    has evolved from a normal export practice through a period of ever increasing
                    regimentation, the consequence of growing war pressure. Foreign trade as a
                    private enterprise has changed so that today there is foreign trade of either
                    governmental undertakings or of private enterprise under strict governmental
                    controls. <pb facs="0017" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/> The shift has not eliminated the
                    general machinery of foreign trade; nor has it eliminated the private importer
                    or exporter, but it has very definitely curtailed his activities and has
                    subordinated his interests to those of the national governments. The practical
                    effect of the shift, therefore, is that our Government deals in fact with other
                    Governments. It is the procedure between governments that is under discussion at
                    this time.</p>
                <p>The controls in effect in the United States and the United Kingdom and in the
                    countries of the Near East do not mean an arbitrary assumption of power; rather
                    they reflect a realistic understanding of the present life and death struggle
                    for survival, with all the dislocations incidental to such a struggle. Strategic
                    and essential materials suddenly become surprisingly scarce, in some instances
                    to the point of non-availability, and their handling becomes further
                    circumscribed by a shortage in facilities for shipping, unloading and
                    distribution. The application of governmental controls indicates an effort to
                    bring order out of chaos to the end that the materials which are available may
                    be put to their optimum use.</p>
                <p>In the Near East there are at the moment two different systems of controls
                    governing civilian supplies required by the countries of that area. The British
                    have carried the controls of the individual countries into a broader control for
                    the entire area, embodied in the Middle East Supply Centre (“M. E. S. C.” or
                    “the Centre”). The Americans have been satisfied to leave the controls at the
                    country level. As the two systems have not been correlated there is a dual
                    administrative authority, accompanied by the inevitable complications of such a
                    situation.</p>
                <p>The Near East presents a peculiar problem in that, generally speaking, it is not
                    a theater of war of actual fighting but a theater of war of potential fighting,
                    and in the interim a service of supplies area on a grand scale. Materials of war
                    pass through here to the fighting fronts in Russia and Libya. The civilian
                    supply problems become acute as they become of secondary importance.</p>
                <p>Although this paper is concerned principally with the civilian supply problem, it
                    cannot ignore the logistical situation. Iran happens to combine both types of
                    supply problem to a marked degree and therefore deserves some special
                        consideration.<note n="9" xml:id="d5fn9">For correspondence regarding
                        supplies for Iran, see <ref target="#pg_120">pp. 120</ref> ff.</note> The
                    primary purpose is to get war materials on up to the Russians. To accomplish
                    this successfully, the civilian side of the equation must be kept in some sort
                    of reasonable balance. Add to this difficulty the British concept for control by
                    subordinating Iran to the broader aspects of the area as a whole and the problem
                    assumes challenging proportions. Whatever conclusions are reached for a joint or
                    combined authority for the administration of civilian supplies in each country
                    of the area, or for <pb facs="0018" n="6" xml:id="pg_6"/> the area in its
                    entirety, it is a matter of cardinal importance and fundamental necessity that
                    that portion of the area through which supplies travel to reach the Russian
                    front be kept intact and in complete independence of the surrounding territory.
                    The area might be termed a “Russian corridor.” For a clear cut segregation, Iran
                    and the necessary Persian Gulf ports and their facilities might be separated
                    from the Near East group and set up as a service of supply area for the Russian
                    theater of war in so far as United States supplies, their controls and their
                    administration are concerned.</p>
                <p>A neat case in support of this theory (and admittedly still trespassing on
                    military territory) is found in the dispute now going on between the British and
                    United States military authorities regarding the use of two cargoes of lumber
                    now awaiting unloading at the port of Basra. The lumber was sent out to increase
                    the berthing facilities across the river from Basra, that is for improving the
                    facilities for handling Russian supplies. The British authorities had, and
                    apparently still have, other ideas. Their plan is to erect some piers further
                    down the river to supplement the port facilities of Basra. To sum up the
                    dispute: The Americans wish to improve the facilities for handling supplies
                    through Iran; the British desire to enlarge the facilities for handling supplies
                    for Iraq. And in the meantime, the two vessels lie idle with only the prospect
                    ahead of three weeks’ time spent in unloading after the dispute is settled.</p>
                <p>The complications of a dual authority are manifest in most of the countries from
                    which the United States receives requests for civilian supplies. The British
                    have established a program for the individual countries through their control
                    system for the area. A good deal of programming has been done without
                    consultation with the United States authorities concerned. The Americans in turn
                    have acted upon requests of each given country without consultation with the
                    British authorities concerned. The inevitable result has been a collision of
                    ideas at some point in the process of procurement, generally at the final stage
                    of export clearance. The answer, of course, is simple. While joint or combined
                    boards and committees have been established at the two chief control centers,
                    Washington and London, application of the joint authority has not had time to
                    permeate the system to its peripheral points. The question for correct answer
                    is, of course, how best to install a joint authority for practical working
                    throughout the system. Before attempting to answer the question it might be well
                    to have a look at the organization set up by the British to exercise control
                    over the area as a whole—the Middle East Supply Centre.</p>
                <p>The M. E. S. C. was created in April 1941 to deal with civilian requirements. The
                    need for such an organization was primarily due to shipping difficulties which
                    followed the fall of France, with consequent <pb facs="0019" n="7" xml:id="pg_7"
                    /> loss of effective control in the Mediterranean. The main functions of the
                    Centre are: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <list>
                            <item>“(i) ‘to review and co-ordinate the joint resources and civilian
                                requirements in essential commodities of the territories (including
                                raw materials required for their war industries) in order to make
                                the Group as self-supporting as possible; and to exchange relevant
                                information with corresponding control organizations in each
                                territory;’ and</item>
                            <item>“(ii) ‘to estimate the balance of any essential requirements which
                                must be imported from outside the Group and make recommendations
                                accordingly to the authorities concerned, with a view specially to
                                the best possible use of available shipping …’.”<note n="10"
                                    xml:id="d5fn10">Omission indicated in the original
                                    memorandum.</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The organization consists of: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Director General.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Three Departments: <list>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Supplies:</hi> Sections dealing with areas and
                                    with groups of commodities.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Economics:</hi> Encourages self-sufficiency;
                                    research data sent to appropriate sections of Supplies
                                    Department.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Administrative:</hi> Executive action on
                                    imports, movements of ships, loading program.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Representatives in the several countries.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>M. E. S. C. maintains liaison with the war effort through the Supply and
                    Transportation Sub-Committee of the Middle East War Council, which is partly
                    civilian in membership and of which the Minister of State is chairman, and
                    through other smaller executive committees.</p>
                <p>The Centre is not authorized to perform commercial transactions, which are thus
                    reserved for established private companies or for the United Kingdom Commercial
                    Corporation (U. K. C. C.).</p>
                <p>The area of jurisdiction may be defined as all non-enemy territories bordering
                    the Mediterranean (from Malta eastward), Iraq and Iran. Turkey is included only
                    in the matter of cereals and like commodities.</p>
                <p>The Centre, as indicated under its functions, passes on essentialities and
                    assigns priorities to the approved material; it prepares programs for the
                    individual countries on a six month basis; and it studies local economies and
                    offers improved planned economies. A noteworthy example of this was the problem
                    of cotton versus wheat in Egypt. The M. E. S. C. was instrumental in curtailing
                    the planting of cotton and the partial replacement of this crop by heavier
                    plantings of wheat.</p>
                <p>All in all, the M. E. S. C. performs a very constructive service for the war
                    effort and the civilian population in the Near East area.</p>
                <pb facs="0020" n="8" xml:id="pg_8"/>
                <p>Having in mind this highly organized machinery on an area basis, it is easy to
                    visualize the difficulties which would be encountered if the United States were
                    to pursue an independent course of action through a loosely organized machinery
                    on a country basis. It is apparent that some adjustments must be made. The first
                    move, clearly indicated, is for closer collaboration at the point of origin of
                    the supply requirements. This step has no far-reaching implications; it is
                    nothing more than the application of common sense.</p>
                <p>For instance, in Baghdad there is a Central Supplies Committee, made up of local
                    British and Iraqians, and a British representative from the M. E. S. C. There
                    should be United States representation on this Committee.<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d5fn11">For correspondence on this subject, see <ref
                            target="#pg_343">pp. 343</ref> ff.</note> It would seem a simple and
                    safe proposition to arrange to have a group from our Legation participate in the
                    deliberations of the Committee. This would at least give the United States
                    authorities a clear picture of the original requirements, and undoubtedly any
                    revision or changes made by the M. E. S. C. Also the American Legation would in
                    this way be currently informed of any program worked out by the M. E. S. C. for
                    Iraq, and would inform the Department of the plan.</p>
                <p>In addition to the need for collaboration at distant points there is need for
                    better team-work in Washington. Eventually, some practical type sub-committee of
                    the Combined Raw Materials Board and perhaps of the Combined Shipping Adjustment
                    Board should be put into operation. Until that arrangement is developed further,
                    considerable benefit can be derived from informal and non-official meetings such
                    as those recently held in DE.<note n="12" xml:id="d5fn12">Division of Exports
                        and Defense Aid.</note> It is from, these latter meetings that a good deal
                    of the information in this paper has been garnered.</p>
                <p>The above provisions along with a continuance of the present practice for a
                    member, or members, of the United States Legation in Cairo to join informally
                    with the M. E. S. C. would result in a perfectly sound working arrangement. To
                    check this against the objectives set forth in paragraph one of this memorandum,
                    the suggested procedure would allow for the following: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Satisfactory integration with the existing British machinery for the
                            Near East.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Practical adaptation to existing combined controls and flexibility for
                            further adjustment if and when appropriate sub-committees are put into
                            effect.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Complete information on requirements.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Political strength, provided caution is exercised in
                            commitments.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0021" n="9" xml:id="pg_9"/>
                <p>The alternative course of action for the solution of the Near East supply problem
                    calls for partnership with the British. The action is simple—United States
                    representation on the M. E. S. C.—but the consequences are complex.</p>
                <p>Until the present time, it has been conceded that the British have primary
                    responsibility for the eastern Mediterranean area,<note n="12a" xml:id="d5fn12a"
                        >For a description of the negotiations between President Roosevelt and
                        British Prime Minister Churchill which in March 1942 resulted in agreement
                        for the division of the world into areas of strategic responsibility between
                        the United States and Great Britain, see Maurice Matloff and Edwin M. Snell,
                            <hi rend="italic">Strategic Planning for Coalition Warfare,
                            1941–1942</hi>, in the series <hi rend="italic">United States Army in
                            World War II: The War Department</hi> (Washington, Government Printing
                        Office, 1953), pp. 165 ff. The allocation of the Near and Middle East and
                        the Indian Ocean area as an area of British responsibility was in accord
                        with “United States-British Staff Conversations: Report” (short title,
                        ABC–1) of March 27, 1941, the joint strategic plan drawn up by American and
                        British military staff planners at meetings held in Washington during
                        January–March 1941. ABC–1 Report is reproduced in <hi rend="italic">Pearl
                            Harbor Attack:</hi> Hearings before the Joint Committee on the
                        Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack, 79th Cong., 1st sess., on S. Cong.
                        Res. 27 (Washington, Government Printing Office, 1946), pt 15, p.
                        1485.</note> and the treatment of that area has been tacitly left to their
                    general control both in military and civilian matters, and to a lesser degree in
                    political matters. With the increasing aid to that territory through Lend-Lease
                    shipments and the substitution of United States suppliers for the former
                    European suppliers, United States interests in the Near East have become of
                    increasing importance. As far as the future may be appraised, the present trend
                    will undoubtedly continue. From the point of self-interest, therefore, the
                    United States should consider the possibility of playing a more important role
                    in Near Eastern affairs.</p>
                <p>The British attitude toward American representation on the M. E. S. C. is one of
                    extreme cordiality. It was the British idea to begin with, and it is the British
                    who still strongly urge United States participation. The type of representation
                    has naturally been left to the American authorities, other than an informal and
                    general agreement that there should be one military and one civilian
                    representative. Whether the British envisage the participation as a full
                    partnership is not known, but the chances are that they think of the move as
                    considerably less.</p>
                <p>The British want United States representation on the M. E. S. C. to obtain
                    smoother functioning of the machinery of supplies; to get a unified
                    Anglo-American attitude toward questions of policy and administrative detail;
                    and to promote greater American responsibility in the Near East as a sphere of
                    influence and as a theater of war. The British believe particularly that “aid to
                    Egypt” or “aid to Tunis” should be raised to the broader plane of aid to the
                    Near East.</p>
                <p>There is little question that the British concept provides a broad and effective
                    theory. If the mechanics and the human equations can be brought together into an
                    orderly working scheme there would seem <pb facs="0022" n="10" xml:id="pg_10"/>
                    to be good reasons for formal participation by the United States in the broader
                    approach to the affairs of the Near East countries.</p>
                <p>According to the British file attached to this memorandum,<note n="13"
                        xml:id="d5fn13">Not attached to file copy.</note> the mechanics of the M. E.
                    S. C. are well thought out and well executed. The concrete results of the Centre
                    substantiate this statement.</p>
                <p>The matter of personnel is the one big problem of the undertaking. To have
                    American participation mean anything in a positive sense, this Government must
                    send out to the Centre a representative of the very highest type. He should be a
                    man well known publicly and in whom the public has confidence, and a man who has
                    some knowledge of Near Eastern affairs. The man must not only have strength by
                    himself but must be clothed with sufficient rank and authority to meet on equal
                    terms such men as the Honorable Richard G. Casey, Minister of State, Sir Oliver
                    Lyttelton, Minister of Supplies, other ranking diplomats, and the heads and
                    officers of all the countries of the area. The situation very clearly calls for
                    the rank of ambassador. A man who would fit these qualifications is Ambassador
                        Bullitt.<note n="14" xml:id="d5fn14">William C. Bullitt, former Ambassador
                        to the Soviet Union and to France. During November 1941–February 1942 he was
                        President Roosevelt’s personal representative on a mission to the Near East.
                        The latter commission was undertaken initially and primarily to investigate
                        and report on the matter of British “supply and similar problems” in the
                        area in light of the growing importance of military operations in that
                        theater of war, particularly Libya, although it was expanded subsequently to
                        include “a general survey of the areas concerned”. Ambassador Bullitt was in
                        the Near East from December 13, 1941, to January 23, 1942, and by direction
                        of President Roosevelt his reporting and recommendations were made
                        personally to the President. Originally the presidential plan called for
                        Ambassador Bullitt to proceed from the Near and Middle East to India, Burma,
                        the Straits Settlements, and the Dutch East Indies, returning to the United
                        States by way of the Pacific, although he was given discretion to return
                        immediately by the Atlantic if he considered this advisable after his study
                        of the Near Eastern situation; he did in fact return via the Atlantic,
                        presumably because of the war situation prevailing in the Pacific
                        theater.</note> In addition to this top flight type representative there
                    should be an equally able deputy who could take over during any absence of his
                    chief. Also there should be an able accountant and sufficient staff for keeping
                    adequate records.</p>
                <p>So far this memorandum has been principally concerned with the “requirements”
                    side of civilian supplies. A few words on the shipping and distribution side may
                    eliminate some earlier misconceptions.</p>
                <p>The M. E. S. C. does not contemplate a supply depot or a potential supply depot,
                    at or near its headquarters. Nor does it contemplate a general practice of
                    shipping materials to the M. E. S. C. for distribution to final destination
                    points. The M. E. S. C. would be consignee only on bulk cargoes, which are
                    listed as cereals, fertilizers, lubricants and wheat. Even here the ships are
                    directed at time of sailing to either Persian Gulf ports or Red Sea ports.</p>
                <p>With the Mediterranean closed for all practical purposes, waterborne freight must
                    reach the Near East by either the Persian Gulf or <pb facs="0023" n="11"
                        xml:id="pg_11"/> the Red Sea. The topography of the region divides it for
                    the distribution of supplies into two distinct parts, one comprising Iran, Iraq
                    and Arabia, and the other the balance of the Near Eastern states.</p>
                <p>If the United States authorities agree with the theory advanced herein that Iran
                    is complementary to the Russian theater of war rather than to the Middle East
                    theater of war and therefore should be set apart for special United States
                    control, then Iraq is the only country in this particular group for M. E. S. C.
                    handling, since Arabia has not yet been brought within that grouping. In other
                    words, Persian Gulf sailing orders would be tantamount to country
                    destinations.</p>
                <p>In the other group, there are so many British Mandates that Red Sea sailing
                    orders, so far as American interests are concerned, are likewise tantamount to
                    country destinations, excepting for possible confusion between Turkey and
                    Egypt.</p>
                <p>Thus upon analysis the question of consigning bulk cargoes to the M. E. S. C.
                    does not seem of such serious consequence.</p>
                <p>In considering the wisdom of full participation with the British, it might be of
                    comparative value to note the shortcomings of the more limited direct
                    arrangements between this Government and the governments of the several
                    countries of the Near East territory. Against the advantages of this approach
                    set forth earlier in this memorandum, certain disadvantages are apparent when it
                    is compared with the broader areal approach. The disadvantages are: <list>
                        <label>(i)</label>
                        <item>Inability in practice to fill the reasonable requests of any given
                            country because the United States had not participated in formulating
                            the general program.</item>
                        <label>(ii)</label>
                        <item>Inadequacy of integration with the British machinery in case of
                            adverse war developments in the Near East theater.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The disadvantages are simply the inherent weaknesses that are incidental to a
                    limited course of action in a potentially limitless field of endeavor.</p>
                <p>In contradistinction, full participation in the affairs of the M. E. S. C. would
                    allow for the following: <list>
                        <label>(i)</label>
                        <item>Complete integration with the existing British machinery in the Near
                            East.</item>
                        <label>(ii)</label>
                        <item>The optimum correlation between Near East controls and the combined
                            controls in Washington and London.</item>
                        <label>(iii)</label>
                        <item>Complete information on country and area requirements, and
                            participation in preparing and fulfilling programs for the countries and
                            the area.</item>
                        <label>(iv)</label>
                        <item>Strong political influence over the affairs of the Near East as a
                            sphere, in addition to the influence now exerted on the individual
                            countries.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Behind these known advantages are the unknown factors of war. It would seem the
                    course of wisdom to prepare the ground for any eventuality. It may be that the
                    Near East will become a focal point <pb facs="0024" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/> in
                    the present world conflict, and that United States forces will play an
                    increasingly prominent part in the probable campaigns of the future. Gaining
                    joint authority in the area for the current administration of civilian supplies
                    would pave the way for similar authority in the general affairs of the area in
                    the future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Frederick Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
