<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Afghanistan ( (Engert) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-07-30T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-07-30T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-07-30T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-07-30T03:00:00-05:00" n="50"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d50">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/23276: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Afghanistan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Engert</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kabul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-30T12:00:00+04:00"
                            >July 30, 1942—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received August 1—11:55
                        a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>40. I called upon the Prime Minister, Mohammed Hashim Khan, yesterday for the
                    first time. He is, the Department will recall, an uncle of the King and has for
                    the past 9 years been real ruler of Afghanistan. After a few minutes
                    conversation, it was quite evident to me that he is one of the outstanding
                    personalities not only of his country but of the political world today. We
                    talked for an hour and a quarter and as he understands English well and speaks
                    it fairly fluently conversation with him was easy. It is also a pleasure because
                    his mind is amazingly well balanced, he is extremely intelligent and he is
                    capable of an objective and impartial point of view which is quite unoriental.
                    In fact he reminds me more of Venizelos<note n="10" xml:id="d50fn10">Eleutherios
                        Venizelos, former Greek Premier and political leader; lie died in
                        1936.</note> or Smuts<note n="11" xml:id="d50fn11">Jan Christian Smuts,
                        Prime Minister of the Union of South Africa.</note> than anybody I have ever
                    met.</p>
                <p>The sequence of his remarks was that the democracies had made some fearful
                    mistakes and had lost many opportunities during the past 20 years, including our
                    failure to support the League of Nations. He then referred to the recent German
                    successes in Russia and said they might have far-reaching results for
                    Afghanistan whether the Afghans liked it or not. When the United States entered
                    the war he had hoped it would shorten it but now he was predicting it would be a
                    very long war and nobody could predict how it would affect Afghanistan before
                    the full strength of America could make itself felt especially if Japan should
                    attack Russia too. He said he was <pb facs="0065" n="53" xml:id="pg_53"/> not
                    pessimistic by nature and that deep in his heart he felt a better world would
                    emerge from this catastrophe, but as a practical man with heavy responsibilities
                    he had to face realities and he would welcome signs that the democracies would
                    not go on making mistakes indefinitely.</p>
                <p>I repeated to him what I had said to the King and to the Foreign Minister—see my
                    34, July 25, 4 p.m.<note n="12" xml:id="d50fn12">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_51">p. 51</ref>.</note> and my
                    35, July 27, 10 a.m.<note n="13" xml:id="d50fn13">Not printed.</note>—and also
                    gave him some recent figures of our related production. I expressed my firm
                    belief that the combination of the United States and the British Empire was
                    invincible and that he should not feel unduly alarmed by events on the Russian
                    front as the Germans still had a long way to go before they could menace Iran or
                    Afghanistan.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Engert</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
