<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs ( (Alling) )
                    to the Assistant Secretary of State ( (Berle))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d514</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">514</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="514"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d514">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">882.796/13</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Near Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Alling</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-03">November 3,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Berle</hi>: We have discussed with Colonel Johnson of
                    the Operations Division of the War Department the question raised by Sir Ronald
                        Campbell<note n="61" xml:id="d514fn61">British Minister in the United
                        States.</note> and Air Commodore Thornton regarding the use of Liberia as a
                    refueling station for the British BOAC land planes proceeding down the West
                    Coast of Africa. It was explained to Colonel Johnson that the British desired to
                    use Liberian territory for this purpose in order to conserve fuel by short hops
                    along the coast, so that a full load of vital military supplies could be flown
                    to the Egyptian front.</p>
                <p>Colonel Johnson said there was nothing new in this approach by the British,
                    except that it was now being made through the State Department instead of
                    directly to the War Department. In addition to the request for refueling
                    facilities, the British were asking permission to introduce their own petroleum
                    installations, their own ground crews and repair facilities, and that they were
                    obviously desirous of making Liberian territory a base for the BOAC commercial
                    traffic as distinct from military patrol work. The range of planes to be used on
                    this route, according to Colonel Johnson, was easily sufficient to fly the
                    distance between Freetown and Takoradi or Accra without coming down for
                    refueling.</p>
                <p>Colonel Johnson said that the War Department had been guided in its attitude on
                    this matter by the recommendations of Colonel Harry A. McBride who had recently
                    returned from a special visit to <pb facs="0428" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/>
                    Monrovia, and of Colonel Wood, the Commander of the American military forces in
                    Liberia. Both Colonel McBride and Colonel Wood felt that the use by these BOAC
                    planes of our airports in Liberia would be contrary to commitments given by the
                    American military authorities to the Liberian Government and would be deeply
                    resented by the Liberians. At present the British have the right to make
                    emergency stops in Liberia for refueling purposes when the planes are engaged in
                    coastwise patrol work, but this understanding does not extend to British
                    commercial planes used in ferrying supplies to the Middle East. Colonel Johnson
                    stated that the War Department was opposed to the BOAC proposals because of the
                    advice given by Colonel McBride and Colonel Wood, although this attitude might
                    change in the event that Liberia should declare war at some future date.</p>
                <p>Colonel Johnson further stated that a meeting has been arranged between
                    representatives of the War Department and the British Air Ministry, to be
                    attended also by Colonel McBride, in an effort to arrange an amicable solution
                    of the problem. Colonel McBride, however, is at present ill at his home and a
                    meeting will have to be postponed until he is well enough to attend, probably
                    within the next couple of days. It is our view that Colonel McBride is
                    particularly well qualified to discuss the situation, since he has just
                    investigated the air transport problem on the West Coast of Africa, and is fully
                    familiar with all questions relating to the various air services in that area.
                    Colonel Johnson suggested that the matter should be left in the hands of the
                    technical experts, particularly those who had firsthand acquaintance with the
                    Liberian problem. This view, it seems to us, is a reasonable one and as soon as
                    Mr. McBride is recovered I believe that we can expect a prompt handling of the
                    matter.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Alling</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
