<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to President Roosevelt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d583</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">583</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recXmtj6SyvT64JYD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic warfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Z9Aom0TY2rMGQ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85149842"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Zinc</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="583"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d583">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/22731</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to President
                            <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-30">June 30,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I refer to your telegram of
                    January 7, 1942 and my letter of January 17, 1942 regarding a suggestion made by
                    the American Chargé d’Affaires ad interim at Tangier to the effect that an
                    approach be made to the High Commissioner for Spanish Morocco, General Luis
                    Orgaz, looking toward the continued neutrality of Spanish Morocco and Tangier.
                    As you will recall, the Chargé d’Affaires indicated that General Orgaz might
                    agree to oppose Axis use of Spanish Morocco provided the United States should be
                    willing to guarantee him material support.</p>
                <p>In accordance with your request, the Department of State, in consultation with
                    the War Department, undertook to explore the possibilities of this suggestion.
                    An officer of the Department made a special trip by air to Bermuda in January to
                    discuss the matter orally with the newly-appointed Naval Attaché at Tangier,
                    then en route to his post. Subsequent developments, notably the checking of the
                    British offensive in Libya, made it appear that the moment had not yet arrived
                    for a direct political approach to General Orgaz, but it was felt that a
                    foundation for future action might be laid through an economic agreement which
                    would assist the High Commissioner in meeting the urgent supply problems of the
                    Spanish Zone of Morocco. General Orgaz had indicated on several occasions that
                    he would welcome such assistance, and it was believed desirable to strengthen
                    his position in order to facilitate any later independent action which he might
                    be disposed to take. (I believe you were informed, in a general way, of this
                    development.)</p>
                <p>Accordingly, the Department authorized the Chargé d’Affaires at Tangier to
                    ascertain the attitude General Orgaz would take if this Government should
                    propose an agreement along the lines of the economic understanding in effect for
                    French North Africa. The Chargé d’Affaires was instructed to suggest that
                    Spanish Morocco would be permitted to purchase in the United States, for export
                    on Spanish vessels, various foodstuffs and other non-military articles, under
                    guarantee that none of these commodities would be re-exported from Morocco. In
                    return, the United States would expect facilities in obtaining various products
                    of Spanish Morocco. It would be understood, of <pb facs="0482" n="470"
                        xml:id="pg_470"/> course, that the execution of any such arrangement would
                    depend upon the continued neutrality of the area.</p>
                <p>General Orgaz appeared to welcome this tentative approach, which he discussed
                    personally with the Spanish Government in Madrid. On April 30, 1942<note n="40"
                        xml:id="d583fn40">See telegram No. 195, May 5, 8 p.m., from the Chargé at
                        Tangier, <ref target="#pg_461">p. 461</ref>.</note> he informed our Chargé
                    d’Affaires at Tangier that he was able in principle to accept our suggestions as
                    a basis for negotiation.</p>
                <p>In the light of this reply, the Department, together with the Board of Economic
                    Warfare, has been considering certain specific proposals which might be made to
                    the High Commissioner and which may be summarized as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The United States would permit the purchase and export of a list of
                            essential, non-military commodities in quantities not exceeding the
                            normal import requirements of Spanish Morocco and under guarantee that
                            re-export of these or similar commodities from Spanish Morocco would be
                            prohibited.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The Spanish Moroccan authorities would make available to the United
                            States a number of products of the area, notably lead, zinc, manganese,
                            copper, cork and antimony, in amounts approximating the annual export
                            surplus of those articles. An American buying commission would be
                            admitted to Spanish Morocco to make purchases and explore the
                            possibilities of extending the program.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Spanish shipping would be provided for the transportation, in both
                            directions, of the commodities involved.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Although certain details of these propositions remain to be worked out, we
                    propose, if you approve,<note n="41" xml:id="d583fn41">Marginal note: “CH OK
                        FDR”.</note> to go ahead along these lines.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cordell Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
