<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-09-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-09-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="597" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d597">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/24313</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Childs</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1019</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-09-01">September 1,
                                1942</date>.<lb/>[Received September 16.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to present certain
                            general observations which may be of some possible interest in
                            evaluating the probable attitude of Spanish Morocco in the event of an
                            Allied landing in French North Africa.</p>
                        <p>In the event of such a landing, whether in French Morocco, in Algeria or
                            Tunisia, it may be expected that pressure would be exerted at once by
                            the Axis upon Spain for aid and assistance in repelling the Allied
                            forces. Such aid would comprise no doubt, in part, the granting of air
                            and submarine bases in Spanish Morocco and possibly the use of Spanish
                            troops for the purpose of creating a diversion in French Morocco, as
                            well as the use of Spanish vessels for employment between the Peninsula
                            and North Africa.</p>
                        <p>The attitude of Spanish Morocco toward such demands would depend, of
                            course, very largely on the international situation at the moment and
                            Spanish calculations concerning the respective chances for victory of
                            the United Nations and the Axis. Inasmuch as since about December, 1941,
                            Spanish sentiment, as reflected locally, has betrayed a loss of faith in
                            the possibility of a German or Axis victory, and for the reason that
                            since that time also Spanish disinclination to be involved in the war
                            has steadily declined, it may be assumed on the basis of the actual
                            present situation that, in the face of German demands such as those
                            outlined above, every reasonable effort would be made to avoid acceding
                            to them.</p>
                        <pb facs="0494" n="482" xml:id="pg_482"/>
                        <p>Spanish calculations in such an event would no doubt be based on the
                            assumption that a yielding to German demands for assistance which went
                            no farther even than the granting of air and submarine bases in Spanish
                            Morocco would probably entail inevitably the involvement of Spain and
                            Spanish Morocco in war against the United Nations. On the other hand,
                            the Spanish would probably calculate that a refusal to grant such aid
                            might not necessarily involve Spain in the war through the use of force
                            by Germany to obtain such bases. (In evaluating this factor of course
                            much would depend on the position at the moment of Germany and whether
                            it might have the land or air forces necessary to bring substantial
                            pressure against the Pyrenees frontier of Spain or against Spanish
                            Morocco.)</p>
                        <p>A distinction must be made between the probable attitude of Metropolitan
                            Spain and that of Spanish Morocco in the eventuality outlined above. It
                            is possible, though not altogether probable, that a decision on the part
                            of the Madrid Government to yield to Axis demands might be met with
                            refusal by the authorities of Spanish Morocco to execute orders of the
                            Central Government. It is known that General Orgaz, Spanish High
                            Commissioner, is strongly desirous of maintaining the neutral character
                            of Spanish Morocco and at a given moment it is by no means improbable
                            that General Orgaz might, under favorable circumstances, be induced to
                            decline to agree to the use by the Axis of Spanish Morocco as a base of
                            operations even if permission therefor might be granted by the Madrid
                            Government under pressure.</p>
                        <p>There is always the likelihood that as one strong inducement to persuade
                            the Spanish to create a diversion on behalf of the Axis in the event of
                            an Allied landing in French North Africa, the promise of Northern
                            Morocco and of the region around Oran would be held out by the Germans
                            to the Spanish as the price of their support. Northern Morocco,
                            particularly the region north of the so-called Sebou line and the region
                            in the vicinity of Oran, have been parts of French North Africa which
                            have figured in Spanish territorial aspirations for many years. One of
                            Spain’s territorial aspirations in Spanish North Africa, namely Tangier,
                            was acquired by it in 1940 following the collapse of France when the
                            troubled international situation made it possible for Spain to take at
                            least temporary possession of Tangier when other interested Powers were
                            too pre-occupied with other more important problems to interfere. There
                            can be little doubt that Spain’s hesitancy to embark upon other
                            territorial adventures in North Africa has been due to a consideration
                            of the risks involved. One very important consideration which might curb
                            the Spanish in undertaking a diversionary march into French Morocco from
                            the north or into Oran from Melilla would be the realization that no
                            single act would do more to solidify French sentiment <pb facs="0495" n="483" xml:id="pg_483"/> actively against the Axis and in favor of
                            the United Nations. It is on that account important that should an
                            Allied landing at any time be undertaken in the future in French North
                            Africa, the most explicit assurances should be given at once that the
                            Allies entertain no territorial aspirations in North Africa. Such a
                            declaration would do much to rally French assistance actively in behalf
                            of the Allied cause in the event Spain should choose the moment of an
                            Allied landing for an attempt to occupy any territory in French North
                            Africa.</p>
                        <p>In presenting the foregoing considerations it must be emphasized that
                            much, of course, will depend upon the complexion of the situation at the
                            given moment, and this involves so many unpredictable factors that it
                            would be idle to attempt to do more than sketch the possibilities in the
                            broadest outlines.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Rives Childs</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>