<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-02-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="603" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d603">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">881.512/164</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Childs</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 640</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-02-24">February 24,
                                1942</date>.<lb/>[Received June 5.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the
                            Legation’s despatch no. 258 of July 14, 1941,<note n="58" xml:id="d603fn58">
                                <ref target="frus1941v03#pg_559">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 559</ref>.</note> and in
                            particular to the note enclosed in that communication, <pb facs="0499" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/> addressed by the Legation to Colonel
                            Carvajal, at that time Civil Governor of Tangier, taking exception to
                            various taxes levied incident to the importation of goods through the
                            Tangier Customs.</p>
                        <p>On February 16, 1942, my Spanish colleague,<note n="59" xml:id="d603fn59">Rafael Soriano, Spanish Consul at Tangier.</note> acting presumably
                            in his capacity of Chief of the Diplomatic Cabinet of General Uriarte,
                            Delegate in Tangier of the Spanish High Commissioner,<note n="60" xml:id="d603fn60">Gen. Luis Orgaz.</note> called on me with
                            reference to the above mentioned note.</p>
                        <p>My Spanish colleague remarked that his Government did not think this was
                            the time to discuss with the United States the question of principle
                            raised in the note. He pointed out that the “Social Relief Tax”
                            mentioned in our note was in reality perhaps poorly defined. It was, he
                            stated, a fund used for social protection and was employed solely for
                            charitable purposes among all classes of the population.</p>
                        <p>He added that we have accepted a number of taxes not having a charitable
                            character, imposed by the former International Administration, and he
                            had been sent to inquire if we were not disposed to agree to the payment
                            by American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> of this particular tax
                            imposed for charitable purposes.</p>
                        <p>The Chief of the Diplomatic Cabinet remarked that if we were to accept
                            the payment of this tax, it would, he wished to emphasize, be without
                            any prejudice to our treaty position. If, on the other hand, we wished
                            to continue to insist on the exemption of American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> from this tax, I had only to inform him of this
                            and the High Commissioner would issue the necessary instructions
                            exempting American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> from its
                            payment.</p>
                        <p>My Spanish colleague spent some time with me during which we discussed at
                            some considerable length the American treaty position here in Morocco.
                            His attitude was extremely conciliatory and he appeared to have a
                            perfect comprehension of our position and showed no disposition to
                            question it. He remarked that after the war, at the Peace Conference,
                            the question of Tangier and Morocco would no doubt come before the
                            Conference, and we might safely leave until then the raising of
                            questions of principle, which the Spanish authorities wished now to
                            avoid.</p>
                        <p>I am at a loss to account for the raising by the Spanish authorities of
                            our possible acceptance of the five per cent ad valorem “Social Relief
                            Tax” by the Customs. In view of the absence of any apparent reason
                            therefor, I hesitate to speculate concerning the Spanish motives
                            involved. The collection of the tax is really for the moment one of
                            almost academic significance, in view of the fact that practically all
                            imports made by non-official Americans have virtually ceased.</p>
                        <pb facs="0500" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/>
                        <p>For several reasons, notwithstanding his assurances, I am disinclined to
                            suggest acquiescence in my Spanish colleague’s proposal.</p>
                        <p>The limitation of this proposal to the five per cent “Social Relief Tax”
                            alone among all the other taxes to which exception was taken in the
                            Legation’s note might lead us into an embarrassing dilemma. Our refusal
                            to grant a concession in regard to what my Spanish colleague termed a
                            charitable contribution might eventually be used as an item of
                            anti-American propaganda. On the other hand, our giving way in regard to
                            this particular illegal levy might be construed by the Spanish as a
                            recession from our position of principle on the other taxes. In as much
                            as the Legation’s note alluded to by Mr. Soriano recalled that the
                            Spanish Government had admitted the principle that these illegally
                            levied taxes are reimbursable, it may very well be that they are anxious
                            to find or to produce a flaw in our position in this respect, for the
                            reason that this is a strong point upon which we may hold up our
                            recognition of the Spanish position in Morocco, as long as it may suit
                            us to do so.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Soriano’s reference to our acceptance of taxes instituted by the
                            former International Administration of Tangier, notwithstanding our
                            failure to recognize that Administration, suggests an argument on the
                            part of the Spanish authorities that their own similarly unrecognized
                            position in Morocco ought not to debar our acceptance of taxation
                            imposed by them. They overlook the fact that the American Government’s
                            assent to taxes and other legislation emanating from the Tangier
                            International Administration was negotiated, not with that unrecognized
                            entity, but with the Resident General of France in his recognized
                            capacity of Minister for Foreign Affairs of the Sultan, which was
                            therefore entirely in keeping with our treaty position.</p>
                        <p>In view of the importance of the effect of custom and usage in this
                            country, prejudice to that position would depend upon the consistency of
                            our attitude and acts rather than upon assurances to the contrary by the
                            unrecognized Spanish authorities. Mr. Soriano’s suggestion that we
                            should mutually agree to eschew all reference to treaty principle at
                            this time, leaving this theme for discussion at the Peace Conference
                            after the war, and confining ourselves until then to the problem of
                            practical collaboration, appears to be an unacceptable inversion of the
                            situation. The Spanish can claim no authority, as Mr. Soriano hinted,
                            incidental to their presence or <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> control
                            in North Africa, to justify the suspension or overriding of established
                            principles on which American treaty rights repose. It is rather the
                            question of eventual reparation of Spanish disregard of American treaty
                            rights and interests which might be deferred for discussion at some
                            ulterior date.</p>
                        <p>In French Morocco we have been able to turn the difficulty by giving
                            temporary and withdrawable assent to certain taxation measures, <pb facs="0501" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/> but there we were dealing with
                            authorities whom we have formally recognized. It would not seem that
                            similar action could be properly adopted in regard to the unrecognized
                            Spanish Administration. It is suggested, moreover, that formal assent to
                            any of the enactments of the Spanish Administration might be construed
                            as tantamount to some measure of recognition.</p>
                        <p>In any event, it would seem to be a useful principle to follow not to
                            accept requests from the Spanish authorities for the application to
                            American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> of Spanish taxes as long
                            as we have not recognized either the Spanish Zone or the occupation of
                            Tangier by the Spanish. (See in this connection <ref target="#pg_5">pages 5</ref> and <ref target="#pg_6">6</ref> of the Legation’s
                            despatch no. 258 of July 14, 1941.)</p>
                        <p>In reply to the Spanish Consul’s suggestions under reference the Legation
                            believes that, while reiterating its desire to afford the Spanish all
                            practical cooperation in the general interests of the community in this
                            exceptional period, it is not deemed possible that any concession can be
                            made on the principles recalled in the Legation’s note to Colonel
                            Carvajal affecting any single item of taxation therein referred to. At
                            the same time it might be pointed out that the material object and the
                            present needs of the Spanish Administration, namely, the raising of
                            revenue for social relief purposes, is in fact being attained, in so far
                            as American <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> may be concerned. The
                            latter, albeit under protest, are actually paying this and other taxes
                            legally inapplicable to them, into the Customs to enable them to obtain
                            the clearance of their goods. In the present circumstances the Legation
                            is willing to refrain from disturbing this procedure pending more
                            opportune conditions for an ulterior adjustment of this situation. In
                            this sense, and subject to the Department’s approval, the Legation
                            proposes to leave with the Spanish Consul an <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> along the lines of the enclosed draft.<note n="61" xml:id="d603fn61">Not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Rives Childs</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>