<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé at Tangier ( (Childs) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d610</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">610</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="610"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d610">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.711/105</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Childs</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 928</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-29">July 29,
                            1942</date>.<lb/>[Received August 4.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my despatch no. 906
                    of July 20, 1942, transmitting a note addressed to the Spanish authorities<note
                        n="74" xml:id="d610fn74">See footnote 72, <ref target="#pg_497">p.
                        497</ref>.</note> concerning their attempt to open official packages
                    addressed to the American Legation, and to transmit herewith copy of a note
                    dated July 24, 1942 together with translation which I have received from my
                    Spanish colleague in answer to my note.</p>
                <p>I likewise enclose a copy of my rejoinder in which I have renewed the Legation’s
                    objections to the inspection by the Customs authorities in Tangier of the
                    contents of packages addressed to the Legation.</p>
                <p>My British colleague informs me that he has not yet replied to General Uriarte’s
                    note to him on the same general subject, which formed enclosure no. 3 to my
                    despatch no. 843 of June 18, 1942. My British colleague states that he proposes
                    to follow the same general lines in his reply to General Uriarte as I have taken
                    in my enclosed note of July 29, 1942 to the Spanish Consul.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Rives Childs</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Spanish Consul at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Soriano</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Chargé at Tangier</hi>
                            (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Childs</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 25</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-24">July 24,
                                1942</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Chargé d’Affaires and Dear Colleague</hi>: In reply
                        to your kind communication of July 20, 1942 concerning various cases lying
                        in the Customs house addressed to the Legation under your charge and which
                        are subject to inspection, I have the honor to inform you that such
                        inspection is effected solely for statistical purposes which imply
                        absolutely no diminution of the diplomatic privileges which our authorities
                        are obliged to observe. It is merely a measure of control now applied in the
                        Customs house following the assumption by Spain of the charge of that
                        administration under a special regime, and by analogy with the rules
                        established in Madrid in respect of any foreign representation, according to
                        which every Chief of Mission disposes of a fictitious credit in pesetas, of
                        a greater or lesser amount according to his rank, against which duties that
                        should otherwise have been applied, are debited on each parcel of goods
                        imported under franchise, without involving the payment of any amount. All
                        this <pb facs="0511" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/> procedure, as I have stated
                        above, is purely for statistical purposes, and parcels or packets
                        exclusively constituting the diplomatic pouch are alone exempted from this
                        measure of control.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rafael Soriano</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The American Chargé at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Childs</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Spanish Consul at Tangier</hi>
                            (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Soriano</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-07-29">July 29,
                                1942</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Consul and Dear Colleague</hi>: I have the honor to
                        acknowledge the receipt of your kind communication of July 24, 1942 in reply
                        to my note of July 20, 1942 which, on the grounds of treaty, custom and
                        usage, took exception to the intended inspection by the Customs authorities
                        in Tangier of the contents of certain packages addressed to the American
                        Legation.</p>
                    <p>You have been good enough to explain that such inspection measure now adopted
                        in respect of parcels imported into Tangier under diplomatic franchise
                        proceeds from the assumption by Spain of charge of the Customs
                        administration in Tangier, and follows the rules established in Madrid for
                        the Spanish Customs in this matter.</p>
                    <p>I note with pleasure your assurance that the inspection, which is required
                        solely for statistical purposes, implies no impairment of the diplomatic
                        privileges which the Spanish authorities are obliged to observe. The
                        Legation would recall, however, that in Morocco this obligation on the part
                        of the Spanish authorities implies observance of the privileges under
                        reference such as they are established by treaty, custom, and usage, and as
                        was pointed out in my note above mentioned in reference to Article 3 of the
                        British-Moroccan treaty of 1856, and Article 3 of the Spanish-Moroccan
                        treaty of 1861, have invariably been construed as granting to foreign
                        missions and consulates, not only immunity from payment of customs duties,
                        but also from inspection of the packages imported by them.</p>
                    <p>In the circumstances the Legation has no alternative but to confirm its
                        position in the premises as set forth in its note of July 20, 1942, and
                        consequently to renew its request that you will be good enough to take such
                        action as may be necessary to cause delivery to be made to the Legation of
                        the packages in question unexamined by the Customs authorities.</p>
                    <p>As stated in the Legation’s note above mentioned, its position on the point
                        of inspection has never been questioned, and the franchise passes issued by
                        the Legation, in accordance with the treaty provisions above cited,
                        indicated merely the number, without specification of their contents, of the
                        packages to be passed. However, a few years <pb facs="0512" n="500"
                            xml:id="pg_500"/> ago, the Chief of the Statistics Division of the
                        Tangier Customs made an informal request that the Legation include in its
                        franchise passes indications as to the nature, value, and if possible the
                        weight of the articles imported by it. He explained that this would be a
                        personal favor to him inasmuch as it would save him the time and trouble
                        otherwise required to search for such data in ships’ manifests and in the
                        parcel post returns of the various post offices in Tangier. Needless to say
                        the Legation gladly acceded to this request and will be happy to continue
                        this practice to facilitate the statistical work of the Spanish
                        administrators of the Moroccan Customs.</p>
                    <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Rives Childs</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
