<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-11-08T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-11-08T04:00:00-05:00" n="622" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d622">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/25321:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Childs</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-11-08T10:00:00+01:00">November
                                    8, 1942—10 a.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 10:15 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>560. My British colleague called on me a few moments ago to state that he
                            had been yesterday instructed to seek out General Orgaz at 2 a.m. this
                            morning in order to give him certain assurances concerning the peaceful
                            intentions of the British Government toward Spain in connection with the
                            American landing in French North Africa.</p>
                        <p>He showed me a copy of the statement he had been instructed to read to
                            Orgaz which he said had been drafted by the American and <pb facs="0523" n="511" xml:id="pg_511"/> British Government and British Embassy
                            Madrid. He added he had been specifically instructed not to disclose
                            purport of his message from his Government before it had been delivered
                            to anyone including myself.</p>
                        <p>My British colleague stated that in the absence of Orgaz in Madrid he had
                            delivered the message to General Mugica, Acting High Commissioner, with
                            whom he had succeeded in establishing contact at 2 a.m. as instructed.
                            Mugica evidenced great surprise and is stated to have remarked rather
                            plaintively that it was a pity Orgaz was not in Morocco. He asked where
                            the landings were taking place to which Gascoigne replied that he was
                            not informed. Gascoigne stated to me that in his journey to and from
                            Tetuán the zone appeared quite normal and that this was also the
                            impression of the British Consul in Tetuán.</p>
                        <p>Inasmuch as the absence of any specific assurance from the American
                            representatives in Spanish North Africa such as I was authorized to make
                            by the Department’s 201<note n="87" xml:id="d622fn87">Dated October 29,
                                11 a.m., <ref target="#pg_507">p. 507</ref>.</note> might be
                            misinterpreted in view of the assurances made by my British colleague, I
                            am proceeding at once to Tetuán to convey them to Mugica.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Childs</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>