<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Beirut ( (Engert) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d758</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">758</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-03-03T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-03-03T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-03T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-03T07:00:00-05:00" n="758"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d758">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890D.00/876: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Beirut</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Engert</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Beirut</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-03T14:00:00+02:00"
                            >March 3, 1942—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received March 4—10:22 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>64. Nationalists in Damascus have recently greatly intensified their activities.
                    One of their leaders Jamil Mardam called on me the <pb facs="0657" n="645"
                        xml:id="pg_645"/> other day and accused Syrian Government of being
                    unconstitutional, corrupt and inefficient. I advised him to tell this to the
                    British and French and he said he had already done so and that Damascus
                    newspapers too had called attention to the shortcomings of the Government. I
                    said I had observed that the press had rather freely criticised the Government
                    for its alleged failure to solve food problem and to prevent exorbitant rise in
                    prices but I had not seen any very constructive suggestions. He replied that
                    question of cost and distribution of food supplies was fundamental and that
                    unless Allied Powers especially Britain assumed complete control there might be
                    serious trouble. See also second paragraph of my 53, February 19, and my 63,
                    March 2.<note n="99" xml:id="d758fn99">Neither printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I pointed out that the British authorities had imported some 60,000 tons of wheat
                    since last July which would have been ample but for the cupidity and perhaps
                    even dishonesty of dealers who instead of selling to the hungry public were
                    hoarding most of it in the hope of still higher prices.</p>
                <p>German propaganda has taken fullest advantage of the situation by stating that
                    Allied promises of food and prosperity were worthless, that most of the wheat
                    has gone to the Jews in Palestine and that a corrupt clique was being kept in
                    office by Allied bayonets to enable British and French officials line their
                    pockets and to prevent the real patriots, i. e. Nationalists, from working for
                    Arab solidarity.</p>
                <p>Leader of Nationalist bloc, Shukri Kuwatly (see my telegram 365, September 15
                        [<hi rend="italic">16</hi>], 1941<note n="1" xml:id="d758fn1">Not
                        printed.</note>), has been away for several months ostensibly on pilgrimage
                    but chiefly to confer with Ibn Saud<note n="2" xml:id="d758fn2">King of Saudi
                        Arabia.</note> who is said to have advised him to cooperate with the
                    British. This report coupled with Jamil Mardam’s recent visit to Cairo has given
                    rise to the impression—which both Kuwatly and Mardam have always tried to convey
                    to me—that the Nationalists are really not pro-Nazi and are now ready to support
                    the Allies or at least the British. At the same time the Nationalists are
                    spreading reports that they are already enjoying the confidence of the British
                    Government.</p>
                <p>Catroux does not trust Nationalists and has requested British to prevent
                    Kuwatly’s return from Baghdad where he now is and large demonstrations were
                    being prepared for his reception. British have prevailed upon Kuwatly to
                    postpone his return few weeks but believe it would be great mistake to keep him
                    out altogether. I thoroughly concur that he should be allowed to return. He and
                    his followers may be given benefit of doubt while they behave themselves
                    provided they be closely watched. However, they should not be allowed to hold
                    office so long as an Axis threat of invasion exists for <pb facs="0658" n="646"
                        xml:id="pg_646"/> in that case they would be in a position to assist enemy
                    if they were so inclined. I have since last July been urging upon British and
                    French that the security problem is the paramount one and today more than ever.
                    I cannot be too emphatic that Syria must be defended not only to protect Suez
                    and Persian Gulf but because it is one of the few important potential bases for
                    an Allied offensive against Axis later on.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Engert</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
