<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs (
                    (Murray))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d790</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">790</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="790"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d790">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867.24/225</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Near Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>)<note n="2" xml:id="d790fn2"
                        >Addressed to the Secretary of State and the Under Secretary of
                        State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-02-07">February 7,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The attached letter<note n="3" xml:id="d790fn3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> to Mr. Stettinius<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d790fn4">Edward R. Stettinius, Lend-Lease Administrator.</note> was
                    suggested to us yesterday by Mr. Steinhardt,<note n="5" xml:id="d790fn5"
                        >Laurence A. Steinhardt, appointed Ambassador to Turkey; previously
                        Ambassador in the Soviet Union.</note> following his conference with the
                    President regarding Lend-Lease aid to Turkey. Mr. Steinhardt informs us that the
                    President desires some action on Turkish requests for Lend-Lease aid. Mr.
                    Steinhardt has consulted with Mr. Stettinius on the subject, who believes that
                    his position will be considerably strengthened if he can present to the
                    Munitions Allocation Board a recent letter from the Secretary of State renewing
                    the Department’s view that Turkey can be reasonably counted on to use the
                    material granted in resisting Germany.</p>
                <p>Although there is of course no basis for a categorical opinion regarding what
                    Turkey will do, this Division has been strengthened of late in its opinion that
                    Turkey will resist an Axis attack. The attached letter is consequently submitted
                    for your consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace Murray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
