<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-09T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-09T06:00:00-05:00" n="795" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d795">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">867.24/231: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-09T13:00:00+02:00">March 9,
                                    1942—1 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 10:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>135. For the President, Secretary and Under Secretary. In the course of a
                            conversation in Beirut with Rauf Orbay who is en route to London as the
                            new Turkish Ambassador he remarked that while Turkey would, of course,
                            adhere to its alliance with Britain, their will to resist a German
                            attack had been secretly shaken during recent weeks not so much as a
                            result of failure of Libyan campaign and recent events in Far East as of
                            steadily growing dissatisfaction in Turkish Government circles at
                            failure of promised and requisitioned war material to arrive from
                            Britain and United States. He referred with asperity to requirement that
                            Britain first approve delivery of American lease-lend material to Turkey
                            and remarked that this requirement and the physical handling of
                            shipments by various British agencies continued to entail inordinate
                            delays.</p>
                        <p>He cited delivery to Turkish Government of 50 American Howitzers which he
                            said had been received without the proper motive power, to the diversion
                            by British authorities in Near East of 190 out of 200 American
                            lend-lease trucks and to repeated failure of British mission in
                            Washington to take action in what he described as relatively unimportant
                            requisitions submitted by this Government and approved by American
                            authorities. He said that as a result of these and similar incidents his
                            Government was beginning to question whether Britain really wanted a
                            strong Turkey able to resist German aggression and that it was his
                            intention upon arrival in London to express the foregoing views to
                            British Government.</p>
                        <pb facs="0694" n="682" xml:id="pg_682"/>
                        <p>As I am informed Orbay is a confidante of President Inönü<note n="15" xml:id="d795fn15">Ismet Inönü, President of the Turkish
                                Republic.</note> and spent considerable time with him immediately
                            prior to his departure, he may well be considered to reflect Inönü’s
                            state of mind.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>