<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Turkey ( (Kelley) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d865</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">865</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-10-21T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-10-21T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-21T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-21T08:00:00-05:00" n="865"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d865">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M) Turkey/116: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kelley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-21T16:00:00+03:00"
                            >October 21, 1942—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 22—7:28 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1046. My 1029, October 16. Foreign Minister requested British Ambassador to call
                    upon him yesterday regarding chrome question apparently as result of
                    representations made to Turkish Ambassador in London.</p>
                <p>Numan repeated British would have all chrome mined or in stock up to January 8
                    and he made no reference to Turkish desire to obtain 5000 tons from British
                    stocks. He also stated definitely after 1944 British would have first option to
                    make an agreement and in any event he was prepared to let them have 50 percent
                    of output.</p>
                <p>Regarding 43 and 44 Numan declared it was not possible for Turks without breach
                    of faith to decline to deliver any chrome until whole of 18,000,000 Turkish
                    pounds of war material had been delivered and a further agreement signed. He
                    said that first 45,000 tons of chrome must be regarded as becoming due after
                    January 15 in proportion to actual deliveries of German goods under Schedule I.
                    He said that Turkish Government had now decided that no agreement with regard to
                    the delivery of remaining 135,000 tons of chrome would be signed with Germany
                    until the entire 18,000,000 Turkish pounds of war material had been delivered.
                    He said that instructions in this sense had already been sent to Berlin and that
                    he would attempt to maintain this position in the event that Germans raised
                    objections.</p>
                <p>Numan made it clear that Turkish Government regarded themselves as obliged by
                    Clodius agreement to furnish 135,000 tons of chrome to Germany if attendant
                    conditions were fulfilled and that consequently it was not possible to give
                    British <hi rend="italic">pari passu</hi> treatment in 1943 and 44. Provided
                    German deliveries of war material in Schedule I were made of corresponding value
                    45,000 tons of chrome must be regarded as a prior commitment to Germany. If
                    quantities above that amount were available before further agreement has been
                    concluded with Germany—that is, before Germany had delivered 18,000,000 Turkish
                    pounds of war material, British might obtain chrome, provided they did not ask
                    for quantity which would preclude <pb facs="0775" n="763" xml:id="pg_763"/>
                    Turks from delivering further 45,000 tons of chrome to Germany in 1943 if she on
                    her side fulfilled necessary conditions. If further agreement were concluded
                    with Germany, Numan would regard Germany as entitled to further priority up to
                    quantities specified for 1943 and 1944. On the other hand he promised that the
                    Turkish Government would do everything possible to increase production with a
                    view to British receiving quantity above 90,000 tons produced in 1943 and 1944.
                    Hugessen pressed very strongly for ton for ton treatment from January 8. Numan
                    would not agree to this arrangement and said that Germany must have priority
                    with regard to both the first 45,000 tons and the remainder.</p>
                <p>Numan informed Hugessen that no war material at all had as yet been delivered by
                    Germany under Clodius agreement. Total deliveries under the agreement amounted
                    to only 19,800,000 Turkish pounds, of which only 7,000,000 related to Schedule I
                    and therefore affected chrome. He said that delay in delivery of war material
                    was due to changes made by Turks in Clodius specifications. For this reason a
                    delay of about 9 months was inevitable before final deliveries of 18,000,000
                    Turkish pounds of war materials could take place. Hugessen was given to
                    understand it was out of question for Turkish Government to insist on full
                    delivery before March 31 and some further agreement would have to be drawn up.
                    Numan declared there was no question of facilitating German deliveries by
                    changes in war material specifications. He maintained war materials on original
                    list were of simplest kind and ones which were easiest for Germans to
                    deliver.</p>
                <p>Department will note new development in chrome negotiations is decision of Turks
                    not to sign agreement for delivery of 135,000 tons to Germany until entire
                    18,000,000 Turk pounds of war materials have been delivered. If Turks maintain
                    this position Turk deliveries to Germany in ’43 will probably not exceed 45,000
                    tons in view of fact Germany will not complete deliveries until end of that
                    year.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kelley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
