<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>219. Paper Prepared in the Central Intelligence Agency</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d219</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">219</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-08-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recebl4V1INuqlVGh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-08-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="219"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d219">
                <head>219. Paper Prepared in the Central Intelligence Agency<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d219fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency Files,
                        Job 82–00450R, Box 6, Folder 3, Willis’ Notes, Working Papers—Congo. Secret.
                        There is no drafting information on the original. A handwritten notation on
                        the paper reads: “Prepared for <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss>.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-08-13">August 13, 1964</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">CONGO</p>
                <p>1. Problem: How to restore order and some semblance of stability in the Congo
                    (Leopoldville).</p>
                <p>2. Situation: The so-called rebel forces of the <gloss target="#t_CNL_1"
                        >CNL</gloss> in the Congo have extended their control in a very brief period
                    from Uvira on the Burundi border to Albertville on Lake Tanganyika west to
                    Kabalo and up the Lualaba River and rail line to Stanleyville, the center of
                    Lumumbist dissidence in the Congo. They have done this through the relatively
                    simple tactic of exploiting whatever discontent there may be in each area by the
                    use of advance agitation agents followed by a relatively small but active armed
                    force. The rebel forces are currently in effective control of Stanleyville and
                    are planning to move on momentarily further west to Coquilhatville. Their
                    successes have been loudly broadcast by Stanleyville Radio and their
                    indominability is becoming accepted by both Congolese and Europeans alike. A
                    general attitude of defeatism has set in not only in the towns in their path but
                    even in Leopoldville. As of this date the key city of Bukavu on Lake Kivu in the
                    east is seriously threatened but has not yet fallen. In viewing the
                    extraordinary progress made by the dissident forces it becomes ever more
                    apparent that they are receiving both monetary and advisory support from outside
                    and that there are evidences of the Chinese Communist trademark.</p>
                <pb facs="0350" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/>
                <p>3. Faced with the above situation and the continued disintegration of Central
                    Government control in the Congo as well as the approaching evaporation of the
                    Central Government itself, the Embassy in Leopoldville is anticipating in the
                    near future the possible fall from within of Leopoldville itself. There has been
                    some speculation among informed Congolese leaders that it could come as early as
                    15 August 1964. With this in mind the Embassy has urgently recommended the
                    immediate dispatch of non-African troops to guarantee the security of
                    Leopoldville and the port area at the mouth of the Congo River. With this area
                    secured, planning could then proceed for the reacquisition by various means of
                    the territory already in rebel hands. There is a growing feeling that even
                        <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName>’s 8–900 paracommandos cannot
                    or will not hold even Leopoldville. Without first securing this critical area as
                    a base from which to operate, it will be more difficult to carry out a realistic
                    plan for reclaiming the rest of the Congo in the immediate future.</p>
                <p>4. Therefore, in simplest terms, the alternatives seem clear and are in
                    descending order or desirability:</p>
                <p>A. Dispatch of at least one battalion of Belgian paracommandos to secure and
                    garrison Leopoldville and the port area. These troops would be on the ground for
                    the stated, and not too implausible, purpose of protecting what is left of the
                    Congo from outside invasion. There is precedent for this in Congo (Brazzaville)
                    where a French garrison is still located. Further, there is precedent for
                    dispatch of metropole troops at the request of the government of a former
                    colony, i.e., Tanganyika.</p>
                <p>B. A second alternative is obtaining French willingness to provide troops for
                    this purpose.</p>
                <p>C. A third and probably unacceptable option is the dispatch of a U.S. force.</p>
                <p>5. In order to obtain the military intervention of any foreign power the Congo
                    Government must first make such a request and clearly on a most urgent basis.
                    The three operative elements in the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> today
                    are <persName corresp="#p_KEJ_1">Joseph Kasavubu</persName>, as President,
                    Defense Minister and Commander-in-Chief of the Congolese National Army (<gloss
                        target="#t_CNA_1">CNA</gloss>), Moise <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1"
                        >Tshombe</persName>, the Prime Minister, who claims the support of at least
                    4,000 ex-Katangan gendarmes (Katgens), and General <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1"
                        >Joseph Mobutu</persName>, the Commander of the <gloss target="#t_CNA_1"
                        >CNA</gloss>. Unless these three leaders work together there is little
                    prospect of accomplishing even the first step in a plan to reclaim the Congo,
                    i.e., securing full Belgian assistance. Thus, it is imperative that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>, presumably through its ambassador, establish
                    a close and confidential relationship with all three of these leaders. To date
                    this is not the case, but it must be developed without delay if we are to be
                    able to provide the necessary assistance. <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1"
                        >Tshombe</persName>, being the most active of the three, is perhaps the key
                    element and must be prepared to keep our Ambassador <pb facs="0351" n="318"
                        xml:id="pg_318"/> intimately informed in strictest confidence of his day to
                    day plans and problems.</p>
                <p>6. Assuming that the U.S. immediate objective in the Congo is as stated above to
                    take all possible action to restore order in the Congo and establish some
                    semblance of stability in the country after returning the disaffected areas to
                    Central Government control, the following actions can be and in some areas are
                    being undertaken by <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>:</p>
                <p>A. Military Action:</p>
                <p>(1) Air:</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> is presently providing air support to the
                    Congo Government. At present this support includes furnishing [<hi rend="italic"
                        >less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] pilots and ground personnel for six
                    T–28’s provided by <gloss target="#t_MAP_1">MAP</gloss> and six T–6 aircraft
                        [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]. There are at
                    this moment four of six T–28’s flying. One is undergoing repairs, one is being
                    replaced and is expected to be in operation within 14 days. The six T–6’s are in
                    flying condition but are currently in the process of being armed. Six additional
                    T–28’s provided by <gloss target="#t_MAP_1">MAP</gloss> have been promised for
                    the Congo and all are expected to be combat operational within 31 days. Seven
                    B–26 aircraft from <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> contingency force [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] have been ordered to
                    the Congo. The first two of these are to depart for the Congo within two days
                    and will arrive within one week. These planes will be ferried to Leopoldville by
                    U.S. contract personnel with <gloss target="#t_USAF_1">USAF</gloss> markings
                    with stops at Takhli, Ganis, and Aden. The [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line
                        not declassified</hi>] operational pilots and ground personnel will be
                    provided by <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> ostensibly under contract with
                    the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>. Experienced B–26 pilots are already on
                    the ground. More will be dispatched shortly. The longer-range B–26 as opposed to
                    T–28’s or T–6 are considered necessary to provide greater flexibility of
                    movement in the Congo where many alternate airfields are now in rebel hands. The
                    remaining aircraft will arrive in the Congo within 2–3 weeks.</p>
                <p>With the greatly augmented <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> Air Operations in
                    the Congo it will be necessary to procure two C–47’s for logistic support and
                    two helicopters for a rescue capability.</p>
                <p>Wherever possible qualified [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>] personnel will be used. However, it may be necessary to
                    have a minimum number of ground U.S. contract technicians where no [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] are available. In
                    addition, there will be a total of at least three U.S. contract or staff
                    officers [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]. The total
                    number of personnel in this program will reach a total of approximately 120
                    foreign and U.S. personnel.</p>
                <p>(2) Ground:</p>
                <p>Since it has now been graphically displayed that the Congolese Army is totally
                    ineffective and unreliable without leadership and it is <pb facs="0352" n="319"
                        xml:id="pg_319"/> clear that the army does not have qualified officers to
                    lead the troops, it is apparent that only with Belgian or other white officers
                    can an effective striking force be put in the field. Thus the Belgian Government
                    has been requested by State to assist and has agreed to provide Belgian officers
                    to lead these troops. Fifty such officers have or are being dispatched to the
                    Congo for this purpose. In addition the French Government has been requested
                    similar assistance. However, to date the French have not been forthcoming with
                    direct support. Nigerian troops have also been requested for garrison duty but
                    the response to this request has not yet been received. It is further understood
                    that <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> has asked the Government of
                    the Central African Republic (<gloss target="#t_CAR_1">CAR</gloss>) to provide
                    troop units. The army of the <gloss target="#t_CAR_1">CAR</gloss> is largely
                    officered by former French Foreign Legionnaires. As of this date it is not known
                    whether an agreement has been signed. At the same time <persName
                        corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> has made efforts to obtain the
                    services of white mercenaries from South Africa and Southern Rhodesia. According
                    to <persName corresp="#p_SMI_1">Michel Struelens</persName>, Belgian Publicist
                    for <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName>, there are 100 such
                    mercenaries ready to go. It is believed, however, that <persName
                        corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> is unable to pay their salaries and
                    has accordingly asked for financial assistance in this matter from both the
                    Belgian and U.S. Governments. In the interest of creating at the earliest
                    possible time an effective strike force it has been agreed that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> will support the immediate development of a
                    3000 man force with 200 white mercenaries. In order to avoid official <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> involvement with these mercenaries (Military
                    Technicians) <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> has been called upon to [<hi
                        rend="italic">1½ lines not declassified</hi>] determine what <persName
                        corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> needs to establish a force with the
                    least possible delay and to offer to help finance the salaries of these Military
                    Technicians if payment is causing the delay. (A paper has been submitted to the
                    303 Committee requesting policy approval for this action.)<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d219fn2">Not found.</note>
                </p>
                <p>[Omitted here is further discussion of military actions.]</p>
                <p>B. Political and Psychological:</p>
                <p>(1) Political:</p>
                <p>Recognizing that the tribal allegiances can be the final controlling factor in
                    stabilizing the Congo, it has been proposed that <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                        >CIA</gloss> provide [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>] selected key leaders financial support to reinforce
                    tribal loyalties.</p>
                <p>In the Swahili speaking section of the Congo, <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1"
                        >Tshombe</persName> has in the past maintained the support of tribal leaders
                    through periodic application of funds, gifts, and various items such as “Black
                    Powder” for their muskets (which is extremely hard for them to procure on their
                    own). Other political leaders in critical areas who would need support to <pb
                        facs="0353" n="320" xml:id="pg_320"/> maintain or reestablish control over
                    specific regions would include: (See map attached)<note n="3" xml:id="d219fn3"
                        >Not reproduced.</note>
                </p>
                <p>a) [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] in the Bakongo area in the
                    west. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>b) [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] in the Moyen Congo along the
                    Northern reaches of the Congo River. [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>c) [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] in the Mongo Tribal region of
                    Cuvette Centrale (just south of Moyen Congo). [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] who has in the past shown ability as an organizer is a
                    close friend of <persName corresp="#p_BJU_1">Bomboko</persName> with whom the
                    State keeps close contact.</p>
                <p>d) General <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Joseph Mobutu</persName> in Ubangi, the
                    northernmost province on the border of the Central African Republic. [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>e) [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] has support of the Bakongo who
                    make up approximately half of the native population in the Cite in Leopoldville.
                        [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>f) [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>], a <gloss target="#t_CNL_1"
                        >CNL</gloss> leftist presently in the <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1"
                        >Tshombe</persName> government who has good support in Luluabourg in Central
                    Kasai as well as Lualaba in the south and Kwilu Province to the west. Station
                    would establish contact.</p>
                <p>g) [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>], former Defense Minister, from
                    Lisala in Moyen Congo also has some support in the Kivu area.</p>
                <p>h) [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>i) [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>] Kibali-Ituri Province on the
                    Uganda border.</p>
                <p>j) [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>k) [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>l) [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>(3) [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] Psychological:</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> plans certain specific initiatives in the
                        <gloss target="#t_psywar_1">psywar</gloss> field which can supplement other
                    U.S. action programs. The basic, immediate, and overriding objectives of these
                    activities would be:</p>
                <p>(a) To counter and neutralize the highly effective rebel psychological offensive
                    which has succeeded to date in demoralizing the Congolese Army and
                    population.</p>
                <p>(b) To create a more favorable climate of opinion toward the Congolese Government
                    throughout Africa.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is further discussion of psychological actions.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
