<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>287. Telegram From the Embassy in the Congo to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d287</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">287</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-10-16T00:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003007715"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hostages</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-10-16T00:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="287"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d287">
                <head>287. Telegram From the Embassy in the Congo to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d287fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1964–66, POL 23–9 THE
                        CONGO. Top Secret; Flash; Limdis. Passed to the White House, <gloss
                            target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                        >CIA</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Leopoldville</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-10-16T06:00:00+01:00">October 16, 1964, 6 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1497. I will, of course, endeavor see <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1"
                        >Tshombe</persName> first thing this morning carry out instructions
                    contained Department telegram 958.<note n="2" xml:id="d287fn2">
                        <ref target="#d286">Document 286</ref>.</note> Sending appropriate [<hi
                        rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>] insure grounding T–28’s and
                    B–26’s. Also repeating information contained Department instructions <pb
                        facs="0449" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> Bukavu and Elisabethville re grounding
                    of planes, prohibition on overflights rebel-held territory by US planes, and am
                    reinforcing standing orders that every precaution will be taken insure no
                    additional US official personnel fall into rebel hands.</p>
                <p>Am deeply concerned, however, by starkness of message I have to deliver and fear
                    reactions of <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_NVI_1">Nendaka</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KEJ_1"
                        >Kasavubu</persName>. In fact <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1"
                        >Tshombe</persName> may well know of our decision even before I can see him
                    because of our action early this morning in standing down crucial air strikes
                    scheduled in Burma and Boende areas. Furthermore, while I will obviously not
                    tell <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> that US planes no longer
                    flying over rebel held area, Congolese will probably become aware of this during
                    course of day when <gloss target="#t_ANC_1">ANC</gloss> request for
                    reconnaissance around Bukavu and Uvira, point still under grave rebel threat, is
                    refused. Department will, of course, realize that grounding of planes will mean
                    complete stoppage of all military offensive operations against rebels, as all
                    current operations depend on air support by US furnished planes.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> is going to ask right away, or
                    at least ask himself, what <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> has in mind,
                    i.e., does this mean US proposing give in to rebel blackmail re hostages and
                    thus getting ready pull out military rug from under him, at least as far as
                    crucial support from US-furnished planes is concerned. Or, he will want to know,
                    does this mean <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> has something more positive
                    in mind. I can see reasons why we would not necessarily want to take <persName
                        corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> into our confidence at this stage if
                    latter is case. However, I believe it very much in our own interest give
                        <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> some additional thoughts
                    which would lead him conclude we not abandoning him and not panicking. This
                    would, I believe, keep him from having to consider possibility, which Department
                    has recognized, of reversing his decision re non use South African mercenary
                    pilots. Therefore, I request authorization make clear to <persName
                        corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName> that limitation on use of planes is
                    temporary measure and does not mean <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                    considering withdrawal of its aerial support. In other words, I would like be
                    able assure him that phrase “reviewing with him our aerial support” does not
                    mean give in to rebel blackmail.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Re_1">Re</gloss> Belgian reaction, I should think <persName
                        corresp="#p_SPH_1">Spaak</persName> would also have same concerns as
                    Congolese about what we have in mind. Would it not be better be somewhat more
                    frank with him? We will also need full support top Belgian military advisors in
                        <gloss target="#t_ANC_1">ANC</gloss>. Have, therefore, asked <persName
                        corresp="#p_WGM_1">Williams</persName> inform <gloss target="#t_VDW_1"
                        >VDW</gloss> and Marliere of grounding of planes as we will need their
                    support keep impulsive <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> in line.
                    Am asking them say nothing to Congolese until I have had opportunity approach
                        <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1">Tshombe</persName>. Foregoing drafted at 0500
                    local. At 0700 Marliere was scheduled depart for Coquilhatville in B–26 and I
                    have accordingly told <persName corresp="#p_WGM_1">Williams</persName> send
                    Marliere at once. Thus in matter of hour our decision will be known here to
                    Belgians.</p>
                <pb facs="0450" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/>
                <p>We must face fact that 72-hour stand down, even though not immediately known to
                    rebels, could result in some substantial rebel victories. For example, last time
                    reconnaissance around Bukavu stopped, rebels quickly took occasion launch major
                    attack on that city which nearly fell. Unless Belgians undertake reconnaissance,
                    US could be in position of being blamed for fall of key city which fell under
                    fear rebel threats.<note n="3" xml:id="d287fn3">Telegram 968 to Leopoldville,
                        October 16, instructed the Embassy to assure <persName corresp="#p_TMK_1"
                            >Tshombe</persName> that the stand down was temporary and did not
                        indicate a decision to withdraw U.S. air support. This was to provide a
                        breathing space so both governments could consider how to minimize the risk
                        of reprisals. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Files 1964–66, POL 23–9 THE CONGO) In telegram 1524 from
                        Leopoldville, October 18, <persName corresp="#p_GGM_1">Godley</persName>
                        pointed out that <gloss target="#t_ANC_1">ANC</gloss> attacks on Boende and
                        Kindu were being held up indefinitely pending release of air support, and
                        that Belgian pressure would build up if <gloss target="#t_ANC_1">ANC</gloss>
                        troops suffered counterattacks, since the <gloss target="#t_VDW_1"
                            >VDW</gloss> plans were based on air support. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GGM_1">Godley</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
