<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>338. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Belgium</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d338</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">338</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-11-19T20:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-11-19T20:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003007715"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hostages</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-11-19T20:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-11-19T20:15:00-05:00" n="338"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d338">
                <head>338. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Belgium<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d338fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1964–66, POL 23–9 THE
                        CONGO. Secret; Immediate; Exdis. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PJI_1"
                            >Palmer</persName>, cleared by <persName corresp="#p_BWH_1"
                            >Brubeck</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CRC_1">Creel</persName>,
                        and approved by <persName corresp="#p_BGW_1">Ball</persName>. Repeated to
                        Leopoldville, Nairobi, Addis Ababa, Dar es Salaam, and London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-11-19T20:15:00-05:00">November 19, 1964, 8:15 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1107. Following are tentative rationale and guidelines for <persName
                        corresp="#p_FJW_1">Fredericks</persName> talks with Kanza and/or <gloss
                        target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss>, subject to Belgian concurrence. When final
                    version agreed, including any changes Belgians may propose, Dept will transmit
                    guidelines as basis and framework for all discussions, including exploratory
                    talks authorized <gloss target="#t_Deptel_1">Deptel</gloss> 1303 (to
                        Leopoldville).<note n="2" xml:id="d338fn2">Dated November 19. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For Brussels:</hi>
                    <persName corresp="#p_FJW_1">Fredericks</persName> will be prepared discuss this
                    text urgently with you and <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> on Friday
                    morning with goal of getting agreed guidelines in time proceed Nairobi Friday
                    evening.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Begin text of guidelines</hi>. First objective of <persName
                        corresp="#p_GGM_1">Godley</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_GCH_1"
                        >Gbenye</persName> message emphasizing willingness to negotiate is to avoid
                    accusation in US and Africa that US unwilling respond initiative which could
                    affect life US citizen. Second objective, equally important, is to use
                    confrontation with rebels, if it can be arranged, to test whether rebels are
                    ready to accept restoration of <gloss target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> authority
                    under terms which 1) would make unnecessary invasion Stanleyville, 2) would
                    offer prospect of extracting hostages at minimal risk, 3) could be imposed on
                        <gloss target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> by concerted US-Belgian pressures,
                    and 4) would help rehabilitate US–<gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss>
                    relations.</p>
                <p>While our primary effort is to try to bring about rebel acceptance restoration
                        <gloss target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> authority Stanleyville which would
                    make military solution unnecessary, we do not envisage this initiative as
                    replacing present military efforts. We believe it is only credible threat of
                        <gloss target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> capability and will to decapitate
                    rebellion by military means which might predispose rebels to end hostilities
                    under acceptable terms. Further, this initiative does not presuppose any delay
                    of military thrust. We recognize, however, rebels will seek delaying action in
                    order renew build-up of rebel confidence, increase possibility of external
                    military support to rebel forces. These factors make it imperative adopt hard
                    line with rebels, stressing tight deadlines and, if necessary, a
                    take-it-or-leave-it approach with consequences clearly spelled out of rebel
                    refusal to sign-on.</p>
                <p>Political deal we would propose picks up themes from aborted <persName
                        corresp="#p_KEJ_1">Kasavubu</persName> declaration as agreed by <persName
                        corresp="#p_SPH_1">Spaak</persName> during his visit to US: <gloss
                        target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> guarantee of personal safety to all rebels
                    who lay down their arms, <pb facs="0522" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/> public offer
                    of political amnesty, no prosecution of political crimes, full freedom to engage
                    in political activity in preparation for forthcoming early elections, and right
                    of all to hold office if elected. If rebels indicate any interest, we are
                    prepared to offer, in concert with Belgians and possibly <gloss
                        target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss>, a major effort to win <gloss
                        target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> acceptance and to examine possibility of
                    arranging some sort of neutral presence (e.g. US-Belgian-<gloss
                        target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss>) in Stan to assure physical safety and order
                    during transfer to <gloss target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> control and further
                    presence (e.g., <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> observers) to assure other
                    undertakings are fulfilled. This might even include token forces—hopefully from
                        <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss>, though possibly even US-Belgian with
                        <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> blessing.</p>
                <p>Precise terms and modalities of course might be made to conform in some degree to
                    specific, perhaps even personal, rebel demands. Therefore, would be most
                    helpful, if talks with rebels materialize for Belgium to position an officer in
                    whom <persName corresp="#p_SPH_1">Spaak</persName> has full confidence to
                    consult with our negotiator on the spot. Hennequiau would be a possibility.</p>
                <p>We recognize that keystone to whole enterprise would be US–<gloss
                        target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> concerted démarche to <gloss
                        target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> in event rebels seem forthcoming in
                    meaningful and realistic sense. The US and <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss>
                    must be prepared clearly indicate that present and future relations with Congo
                    in jeopardy unless <gloss target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss> is willing to end
                    hostilities under settlement terms outlined above. Our objective, therefore, is
                    to gain <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> go-ahead with clear understanding
                    that negotiations are ad referendum but that both governments prepared to
                    consider such a deal seriously, including potential heavy pressure on <gloss
                        target="#t_GDRC_1">GDRC</gloss>, if our exploration with rebels so
                    warrants.</p>
                <p>We believe this final effort absolutely essential to build irrefutable record of
                        US–<gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> attempts to gain political
                    settlement as well as being one final effort to secure safety of hostages short
                    of perilous military solution.</p>
                <p>Nor do we entirely discount possibility that even at this late date such a
                    maneuver might work. We have never had any illusions that political deal could
                    be consummated except at point when all possible alternatives to rebels had been
                    slammed shut. That time has now arrived. It is crucial we try to test rebel
                    response. <hi rend="italic">End of guidelines text</hi>.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d338fn3">In telegram 1011 from Brussels, November 20, MacArthur
                        reported that <persName corresp="#p_SPH_1">Spaak</persName> considered the
                        proposed negotiations with the rebels dangerous. Kanza would immediately
                        request a cease-fire as quid pro quo for evacuation of the hostages, but the
                        Congo could not be forced to accept a cease-fire, and refusal to accept a
                        cease-fire would be exploited internationally. (Ibid.) In a telephone
                        conversation with <persName corresp="#p_BGW_1">Ball</persName> on November
                        20, <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1">Harriman</persName> said he had just talked
                        with MacArthur, who told him the Belgians thought it would be a great
                        mistake to send <persName corresp="#p_FJW_1">Fredericks</persName> to
                        Nairobi for negotiations, which should be conducted locally. If the United
                        States made too much of this, it would be more difficult to handle. (Library
                        of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_HWA_1"
                            >Harriman</persName> Papers, <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1"
                            >Kennedy</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName>
                        Administrations, Subject Files, Box 448, Congo (1))</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RDE_1">Rusk</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
