<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-11-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="486" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d486">
                    <head>486. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d486fn1">Source: National Security Council, Intelligence Files, 303 Committee,
                            Minutes 1966. Secret; Eyes Only.Prepared on November 10.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-11-04">November 4,
                            1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Minutes of the Meeting of the 303 Committee, 4 November 1966</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PRESENT</head>
                        <item>Mr. Rostow, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_THB_1">Thompson</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HRI_1">Helms</persName></item>
                        <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GGM_1">Godley</persName> and Mr. John
                            Waller were also present</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0745" n="712" xml:id="pg_712"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">1.</hi> Congo—Air and Maritime
                        Program</p>
                    <p>a. The long-standing desire to turn over the U.S.-operated Congolese Air
                        Force and pocket Navy to the host government came under discussion on
                        Friday, 4 November. Tabled were two papers from the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss>, one from <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, and two
                        draft cables from State Department to Kinshasa.</p>
                    <p>b. Without a paragraph by paragraph overhaul, it was abundantly clear that
                        the Committee was in agreement that a turnover be effected with all
                        convenient speed but with minimum sacrifice to efficiency and order.</p>
                    <p>c. All agreed that the key to the question was to find an airline executive
                        or experienced operations officer to manage the air force for <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName>. The candidates, of course, would
                        have to be satisfactory to <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName>.
                        It was also agreed that a non-American would be preferable and that <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> would undertake the “talent scouting.”</p>
                    <p>d. Declining to be bound by any deadlines, the Committee principals pointed
                        out that with the Congolese penchant for failing to meet payrolls, the
                        Agency might be some time in getting out from under. The pocket Navy was
                        believed to present a somewhat less complicated problem in transfer.</p>
                    <p>e. Following the meeting, State drafted four <gloss target="#t_Roger_1">Roger</gloss> channel cables to Kinshasa (Nos. 81702, 81703, 81709, and
                            81710)<note n="2" xml:id="d486fn2">None found.</note> offering general
                        guidance on the intent of the Committee. The Executive Secretary believes
                        that these messages contain an umbrella of accurate guidance under which the
                        parties concerned can proceed to search for solutions.</p>
                    <p>f. It was further agreed that the steps envisaged would, when necessary, be
                        discussed in confidence with both the Belgian and Italian governments.</p>
                    <p>(References: Minutes of 303 Committee meetings held on 28 October 1965, Item
                        3; 17 February 1966, Item 1; 28 March 1966, Item 1; 22 April 1966, Item 9; 9
                        June 1966, Item 2; 8 July 1966, Item 4; and 5 August 1966, Item 8.)<note n="3" xml:id="d486fn3">For text or summaries of the minutes for the
                            first six meetings, see <ref target="#d440fn2">footnote 2 to Document
                                440</ref>, <ref target="#d464">Document 464</ref>, <ref target="#d467">Document 467</ref> and <ref target="#d467fn3">footnote 3</ref> thereto, <ref target="#d472fn3">footnote 3 to
                                Document 472</ref>, and <ref target="#d473">Document 473</ref>. The
                            minutes for the August 5 meeting are in National Security Council,
                            Intelligence Files, 303 Committee, Minutes 1966.</note></p>
                    <p>[Omitted here is discussion of another subject.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName corresp="#p_JPE_1">Peter Jessup</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>