<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-11-18T06:11:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-11-18T06:11:00-05:00" n="563" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d563">
                    <head>563. Telegram From the Embassy in the Congo to the Department of
                            State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d563fn1">Source: National
                            Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                            POL 23–9 THE CONGO. Secret; Exdis. Repeated to Brussels, Kigali, the
                            Mission in Geneva, and <gloss target="#t_CINCSTRIKE_1">CINCSTRIKE</gloss>.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Kinshasa</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-11-18T11:11:00+00:00">November 18,
                                1967, 1111Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>5723. For Under Secretary from <persName corresp="#p_MRH_1">McBride</persName>:</p>
                    <p>1. <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> received me Saturday
                        morning on board boat. I outlined in full Dept’s instructions as contained
                        in State 70801.<note n="2" xml:id="d563fn2"><ref target="#d562">Document
                                562</ref>.</note> I stressed Dept’s view about public outcry in US
                        in event Katangese harmed after their return to Congo. I made all six
                        numbered points contained in paragraph five.</p>
                    <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> said he was deeply shocked
                        and disappointed in Dept’s refusal to help him. He said <gloss target="#t_ICRC_1">ICRC</gloss> had withdrawn from operation and there
                        was no possibility of calling them back into game. I said that under my
                        instructions, I was therefore forced to tell him US could not furnish any
                        aircraft assistance whatever in connection with resettlement of Katangese.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> replied simply in that
                        event, Congo would have to take care of transport problem herself by other
                        means.</p>
                    <p>3. With regard to Katangese, <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName>
                        gave me lengthy description of his plans for handling them. He insisted that
                        they had all decided to return to Congo and that <persName corresp="#p_BJU_1">Bomboko</persName> had held personal conversation
                        with Monga who wished to be reintegrated into life of Congo. He said he had
                        decided to place Katangese for a period of a few months in Iberu near
                        Mbandaka and he wanted to start movement by air from Kigali as soon as
                        possible. He said he felt Katangese might be in some danger if they went to
                        Katanga while so many <gloss target="#t_ANC_1">ANC</gloss> units were still
                        in Kamina area and it was for reason of guaranteeing their protection that
                        he was sending them to Iberu where only soldiers were a few Katangese.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> added that if Dept was so
                        worried about future of these men, he was willing to establish an
                        international commission that could visit them every two weeks to see they
                        were not being harmed.</p>
                    <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> added that furthermore full
                        prestige of <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> was behind this
                        resettlement of Katangese. He said they would be permitted to resettle
                        elsewhere in Congo after brief period. <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> stated he was going on radio later today to read his
                        full declaration on this subject and to explain to Congolese people why it
                        was essential these Katangese be peacefully reintegrated into life of
                        country even though they had borne arms against <gloss target="#t_ANC_1">ANC</gloss>. He said he felt very deeply about this.</p>
                    <pb facs="0850" n="817" xml:id="pg_817"/>
                    <p>5. With regard to para 5(A) of Dept’s instruction, <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> said he could give most categoric
                        assurances on this point. He said full weight of Africa was behind this
                        solution and effective implementation of amnesty. Reverting to <gloss target="#t_ICRC_1">ICRC</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> said they had withdrawn and it was not possible to
                        consider having them again interrogate Katangese after <gloss target="#t_OAU_1">OAU</gloss> had already done so, and important point
                        was to get Katangese resettled in Congo. <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> insisted that he was satisfied pressure had not been
                        used on Katangese. I said we had reports to contrary, but he denied
                        these.</p>
                    <p>6. I reiterated Dept’s concern at reaction in US both publicly and in
                        government circles if Katangese were mistreated. <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> said he was profoundly hurt Dept
                        doubted his word as to their safety. He said amnesty decree was a law of the
                        nation and must be observed. <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName>
                        continued saying that, far from adding to his difficulties, Dept should be
                        helping him with problem of resettling Katangese. He said he simply failed
                        to understand Dept’s attitude regarding an internal Congolese problem which
                        he thought could achieve a satisfactory solution especially if Congo’s
                        friends could help. I repeated Dept’s refusal to assist with aircraft in any
                        way under circumstances he outlined. He repeated Congo would simply have to
                        proceed with her own resources (“se debrouiller”).</p>
                    <p>7. <persName corresp="#p_MJD_1">Mobutu</persName> concluded with fairly
                        impassioned statement about his surprise that his word as Chief of State was
                        being doubted by Dept, and expressed regret US was not helping in this
                        operation. He said apparently Dept did not trust him, and this of course was
                        blow to him.</p>
                    <p>8. Comments follow.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName corresp="#p_MRH_1">McBride</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>