<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Poland ( (Stetson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1014</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1014</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-05-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaty negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-05-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="1014"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1014">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">660c. 11212/34</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Poland</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stetson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Warsaw</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-24">May 24,
                            1928</date>.<lb/>[Received June 16.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1752</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Adverting to the Department’s telegraphic
                    Instruction No. 29 of April 17, 7 P.M.,<note n="1" xml:id="d1014fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> relative to American indirect shipments into Poland, I now
                    have the honor to transmit herewith a memorandum of a conversation between
                    myself and Mr. Allen on the one hand, and Mr. Kwiatkowski, Minister of Industry
                    and Commerce, and Mr. Dolezal, Vice Minister, on the other. The Department will
                    find the memorandum in question self-explanatory.</p>
                <p>I shall have the honor to keep the Department informed of the results of any
                    future conversations which I may have with Mr. Kwiatkowski on the subject.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John B. Stetson, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of a Conversation Between the American Minister
                            in Poland</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Stetson</hi>), <hi rend="italic">the
                            American Commercial Attaché</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Allen</hi>), <hi
                            rend="italic">and Certain Officials of the Polish Ministry of Industry
                            and Commerce, May 17, 1928</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Mr. Stetson announced his desire to open the old question of a trade treaty
                        with the United States, sketching the course the negotiations had taken
                        during the past two years.<note n="2" xml:id="d1014fn2">On August 31, 1925,
                            the Department submitted to the Polish Legation a draft commercial
                            treaty similar to the treaty between the United States and Germany
                            signed December 8, 1923, <ref target="frus1923v02#pg_29">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 29</ref>. The records of the
                            intermittent negotiations following the submission of the draft are not
                            printed.</note> He explained that the American Legation in Warsaw had
                        for some time refrained from any initiative in the matter, at the express
                        request of Mr. Ciechanowski, the Polish Minister in Washington. A recent
                        visit to the United States had, however, given Mr. Stetson an opportunity of
                        talking with Mr. Ciechanowski and of conferring with the Department of
                        State, <pb facs="1045" n="925" xml:id="pg_925"/> whereupon it was deemed
                        advisable for Mr. Stetson to solicit an opinion from the competent Polish
                        officials in Warsaw as to whether the present might not be a favorable time
                        to define and discuss any differences in point of view which it may be
                        necessary to resolve before a commercial treaty between the United States
                        and Poland can be concluded.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Kwiatkowski replied that far from looking upon the question as old, he
                        was inclined to view it as a new one, because the Poland of today was far
                        different from the Poland of the time when the subject first came up. He
                        expressed himself as most cordial to the suggestion of the American Minister
                        and eager to facilitate discussions in whatever way he could. He emphasized
                        his hope that practical aspects would characterize any discussions which
                        might take place to the exclusion of academic or theoretical
                        considerations.</p>
                    <p>After acknowledging his pleasure at meeting an attitude of mind so receptive,
                        Mr. Stetson took occasion to allude to the Polish-German commercial treaty
                        negotiations. He had observed an opinion during his trip abroad, doubtless
                        deliberately inspired, that failure of the two parties to agree in spite of
                        repeated attempts was an incurable disposition on the part of the Poles
                        which rendered reasonable dealing with them impossible. If, in the face of
                        such propaganda, Poland might now speedily negotiate a trade treaty with the
                        United States, she would furnish a most effective denial to these damaging
                        insinuations of third parties, and at the same time, further fortify the
                        country’s good reputation abroad.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Kwiatkowski’s reply showed that he was deeply impressed by this
                        thought.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Stetson continued that he would be glad to begin work as early as
                        officials from the Polish side might find it convenient and wondered whether
                        the Polish Government was ready to discuss objections it found to American
                        proposals already advanced.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Kwiatkowski said that the matter would first be considered by a special
                        commission who could make a report to him in about two weeks. After studying
                        the report, he would be pleased to confer again with Mr. Stetson with a view
                        to arranging for appropriate exchange of opinions and full consideration of
                        the problem. Here Mr. Kwiatkowski digressed into some affable but sincere
                        remarks about American co-operation with Poland, the substance of which was
                        that in effective benefits and absence of friction, the results already
                        visible of American participation in Polish affairs was truly astounding and
                        exceeded anything that could possibly have been imagined a few years ago.
                        Digressing even further, Mr. Kwiatkowski referred to his joy and pride, the
                        harbor of Gdynia, and asked whether Mr. Stetson had seen it lately. It so
                        happened that Mr. Stetson had just returned from a <pb facs="1046" n="926"
                            xml:id="pg_926"/> trip which included a visit to Gdynia and was able to
                        make several remarks concerning the accomplishment of the project which were
                        highly pleasing to Mr. Kwiatkowski.</p>
                    <p>In taking leave, Mr. Stetson offered any assistance to the Commission he
                        could render which might ease their immediate task.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
