<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to Diplomatic and Consular Officers</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1054</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1054</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-07-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-07-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="1054"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1054">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">150.01/1843a</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                            <gloss type="to">Diplomatic and Consular Officers</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Application of the Act of October</hi> 16, 1918, <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">As Amended by the Act of June</hi> 5, 1920</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-07-18">July 18,
                            1931</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">Diplomatic Serial</seg>
                    <lb/>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2023</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sirs</hi>: With reference to Note 70, Section 361, Consular
                    Regulations, as amended by the Department’s circular instruction of July 18,
                    1931 entitled “Changes in Consular Regulations and Notes No. 73,” there have
                    been prepared for your guidance the following explanatory notes on the Act of
                    October 16, 1918, as amended by the <pb facs="1101" n="981" xml:id="pg_981"/>
                    Act of June 5, 1920, which are applicable in the case of all aliens desiring to
                    come to the United States.</p>
                <p>I. Subdivisions (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of
                    Section 1 of the Act debar from the United States “aliens who are anarchists”
                    and “aliens who advise, advocate, or teach, or who are members of or affiliated
                    with any organization, association, society, or group, that advises, advocates,
                    or teaches, opposition to all organized government.”</p>
                <p>II. That portion of Subdivision (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) which debars from the
                    United States “aliens who believe in, advise, advocate, or teach, … (1) the
                    overthrow by force or violence of the Government of the United States or of all
                    forms of law, or (2) the duty, necessity, or propriety of the unlawful
                    assaulting or killing of any officer or officers (either of specific individuals
                    or of officers generally) of the Government of the United States, or of any
                    other organized government, because of his or their official character, or (3)
                    the unlawful damage, injury, or destruction of property, or (4) sabotage,” may
                    be taken to refer, among others, to the following categories of persons: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Members of Communist Parties which are sections of the Communist
                            International.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Members of Communist Unions of Youth which are sections of the
                            Communist International of Youth.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Persons who believe in, advise, advocate, or teach, the doctrines
                            mentioned but who are not actual members of the two organizations
                            mentioned in (1) and (2).</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>III. That portion of Subdivision (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) which debars from the
                    United States “aliens … who are members of or affiliated with any organization,
                    association, society, or group, that believes in, advises, advocates, or
                    teaches, … (1) the overthrow by force or violence of the Government of the
                    United States or of all forms of law, or (2) the duty, necessity, or propriety
                    of the unlawful assaulting or killing of any officer or officers (either of
                    specific individuals or of officers generally) of the Government of the United
                    States, or of any other organized government, because of his or their official
                    character, or (3) the unlawful damage, injury, or destruction of property, or
                    (4) sabotage,” may be taken to include, among others, the following categories
                    of persons: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Members of the following organizations: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Communist Parties which are sections of the Communist
                                    International.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Communist Unions of Youth which are sections of the Communist
                                    International of Youth.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Other organizations which believe in, advise, advocate or
                                    teach the overthrow by force or violence of the Government of
                                    the United States.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Persons affiliated with the following organizations (including <pb
                                facs="1102" n="982" xml:id="pg_982"/> subsidiary organizations),
                            that is to say, persons who have taken part in meetings of these
                            organizations (Congresses, Conferences, et cetera), who have been or are
                            members of the executive organs (Executive Committees, Departments or
                            Sections of Executive Committees, Central Committees, Presidia,
                            Secretariats, et cetera), of these organizations, or who have
                            participated or are participating in any capacity in the work of these
                            organizations, and so forth: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Communist International.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Communist International of Youth.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Red International Labor Unions. <list>
                                        <item>Subsidiary and affiliated organizations: <list>
                                                <item>Pan-Pacific Secretariat of Labor
                                                  Unions.</item>
                                                <item>Latin-American Federation of Labor
                                                  Unions.</item>
                                                <item>International Propaganda and Action
                                                  Committees, such as: <list>
                                                  <item>Miners International Committee for
                                                  Propaganda and Action.</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>International Associations of Separate Trades
                                                  and Industries, such as: <list>
                                                  <item>International of Educational Workers.</item>
                                                  <item>International of Seamen and Harbor
                                                  Workers.</item>
                                                  </list>
                                                </item>
                                            </list>
                                        </item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Peasant International.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Red Sport International.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                <item>International Organization for Aid to Fighters for the
                                    Revolution (MOPR).</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                                <item>International Organization of Workers Relief
                                    (MEZHRABPROM).</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Communist University of National Minorities of the West in the
                                    Name of Markhlevsky at Moscow.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">i</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Communist University of the Workers of the East in the Name of
                                    Stalin at Moscow.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">j</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Communist University of Workers of China in the Name of Sun
                                    Yat Sen at Moscow.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">k</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Lenin School at Moscow.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">l</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Other organizations which believe in, advise, advocate, or
                                    teach … the overthrow by force or violence of the Government of
                                    the United States, et cetera.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>IV. Subdivision (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) debars from the United States “Aliens
                    who write, publish, or cause to be written or published, or who knowingly
                    circulate, distribute, print, or display, or knowingly cause to be circulated,
                    distributed, printed, published, or displayed, or who knowingly have in their
                    possession for the purpose of circulation, distribution, publication, or
                    display, any written or printed matter, advising, advocating, or teaching,
                    opposition to all organized government, or advising, advocating, or teaching:
                    (1) The overthrow by force or violence of the Government of the United States or
                    of all forms of law, or (2) the duty, necessity or propriety of the unlawful
                    assaulting or killing of any officer or officers (either of specific individuals
                    or of officers generally) of the Government of the United States or of any <pb
                        facs="1103" n="983" xml:id="pg_983"/> other organized government, or (3) the
                    unlawful damage, injury or destruction of property, or (4) sabotage.”</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Note</hi>.] The terms of the statute are
                    self-explanatory.</p>
                <p>V. Subdivision (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) which debars from the United States
                    “Aliens who are members of or affiliated with any organization, association,
                    society, or group, that writes, circulates, distributes, prints, publishes, or
                    displays, or causes to be written, circulated, distributed, printed, published,
                    or displayed, or that has in its possession for the purpose of circulation,
                    distribution, publication, issue, or display, any written or printed matter of
                    the character described in subdivision (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>),” may be taken
                    to refer, among others, to the following category of persons: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Persons who are members of or affiliated with the organizations listed
                            in III above.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Persons who are members of or affiliated with, any other organization,
                            association, society, or group, that may be involved in one of the acts
                            enumerated.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>VI. Subdivision (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) defines “advising”, “advocacy”,
                    “teaching” or “affiliation” as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“For the purpose of this section: (1) the giving, loaning, or promising
                            of money or anything of value to be used for the advising, advocacy, or
                            teaching of any doctrine above enumerated shall constitute the advising,
                            advocacy, or teaching of such doctrine; and (2) the giving, loaning, or
                            promising of money or anything of value to any organization,
                            association, society, or group of the character above described shall
                            constitute affiliation therewith; but nothing in this paragraph shall be
                            taken as an exclusive definition of advising, advocacy, teaching, or
                            affiliation.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Note</hi>.] For a further definition of affiliation see
                    Note 70, Section 361, Consular Regulations.</p>
                <p>The list of organizations named in this instruction while believed to contain the
                    names of the principal organizations membership in or affiliation with which
                    renders an alien inadmissible to the United States, is not to be taken, however,
                    as an inclusive list of such organizations and may be added to from time to
                    time.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. R. Castle, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
