<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State ( (White))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d142</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">142</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-10-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-10-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="142"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">839.51/3568</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">White</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-10-27">October 27,
                            1931</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Dominican Minister, Señor Despradel, came in at my request and I pointed out
                    to him that there was a paragraph in his note of October 22 which did not
                    conform with the statement in the penultimate paragraph of his note of October
                    20. The latter recognizes that the action of the Dominican Government is
                    contrary to the Convention of 1924 and contracts with the bankers, whereas the
                    paragraph in the note of October 22 states that the changes made in the law are
                    to bring it within the terms of the Convention.</p>
                <p>I suggested to him that all that would be necessary would be to hand us a new
                    copy of the enclosure to the note of October 20, giving the text of the proposed
                    law as recently modified in substitution of the text enclosed in that note. We
                    would then give him back the text originally included in the note and there
                    would then be no necessity for the note of October 22, which I would also give
                    back to him.</p>
                <p>Señor Despradel said that he was surprised at the wording also, but he had put it
                    in the note under instructions from his Government and he would have to consult
                    them first. He later called up and asked <pb facs="0254" n="134" xml:id="pg_134"
                    /> to come in to see me and said that on returning to his Legation he had
                    received the text of the proposed law as finally submitted to the Congress,<note
                        n="40" xml:id="d142fn40">For the official texts of Laws No. 205 and No. 206,
                        see <hi rend="italic">Gaceta Oficial</hi>, No. 4404, October 24,
                        1931.</note> and he had brought it along to substitute for the one
                    originally enclosed in his note of October 20. He made the substitution, and I
                    gave him back the original text. He also took back with him the note of October
                    22.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>F[<hi rend="smallcaps">rancis</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >hite</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
