<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Egypt ( (Jardine))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d160</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">160</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-02-03T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-02-03T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-02-03T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-02-03T16:00:00-05:00" n="160"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d160">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">883.05/375: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jardine</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-02-03T16:00:00-05:00"
                            >February 3, 1931—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>15. Your 13, January 27, noon.<note n="2" xml:id="d160fn2">Not printed.</note> At
                    the time of the official announcement of the appointment of an additional French
                    judge to the Mixed Court judiciary, please present a note to the Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs substantially as follows:<note n="3" xml:id="d160fn3">The note
                        was presented under date of March 3, 1931 (883.05/382).</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“On several occasions during recent years my Government has had occasion
                            to express to the Royal Egyptian Government its interest in favor of a
                            return to the principle of equality of representation as among the
                            principal capitulatory Powers on the Mixed Court judiciary. The last of
                            these occasions was on April 18, 1929, when my predecessor, in a note to
                            the Egyptian Minister for Foreign Affairs,<note n="4" xml:id="d160fn4">
                                <ref target="frus1929v02#pg_942">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1929, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 942</ref>.</note> set forth in
                            considerable detail my Government’s viewpoint on this question.</p>
                        <p>The subsequent action of the Egyptian Government in appointing an
                            additional American judge to the Mixed Court of First Instance at Cairo
                            was particularly gratifying to my Government, which interpreted this
                            appointment as indicative of the Egyptian Government’s intention to
                            bring about an early realization of the principle of equality of
                            representation among the principal capitulatory Powers.</p>
                        <p>That it is the intention of the Egyptian Government to bring about a
                            return to this principle is now further indicated by the recent
                            announcement of the appointment of an additional judge from among the
                            nationals of one of the principal capitulatory Powers which in recent
                            years has not been equally represented on the Mixed Courts.</p>
                        <p>In reaffirming my Government’s position with respect to the principle of
                            equality of representation, I have been instructed to express my
                            Government’s confidence that the Egyptian Government will continue to
                            apply this principle in future appointments in order that American
                            representation on the Mixed Court judiciary may soon be brought to a
                            parity with that of the other principal capitulatory Powers.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0263" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/>
                <p>After the note has been presented you may, if you perceive no objection, show a
                    copy thereof in strict confidence to your French colleague.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
