<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in El Salvador ( (Curtis) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-12-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-12-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-12-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-12-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="223"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">816.00 Revolutions/48</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in El Salvador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Curtis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">San Salvador</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-12-15">December 15,
                            1931</date>.<lb/>[Received December 21.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 26</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my telegrams regarding the events of
                    the revolution which took place in this country during the first days of the
                    month, I have the honor to make the following corrections of statements
                    contained therein.</p>
                <p>In my telegram No. 97 of December 3—7 AM, I stated that the President was
                    bringing troops from Santa Tecla. This statement was based on information given
                    me by telephone from Santa Tecla by Mr. Salvador Godoy, the private secretary of
                    President Araujo. As a matter of fact armed men were sent as outposts
                    approximately onethird of the distance from Santa Tecla to the capital and no
                    advance against the capital was attempted.</p>
                <p>My telegram of December 3, 9 [<hi rend="italic">11</hi>] a.m., No. 98, stated
                    that the civilian population was apparently decidedly in favor of President
                    Araujo. Even allowing for the fact that in such a country as this nothing
                    succeeds like success and that therefore the vast majority of the people are now
                    more or less enthusiastically on the side of the government of General Martínez,
                    I believe that the loyalty to President Araujo was limited to appearances due to
                    the fact that there was still a possibility that he would be able to reestablish
                    himself as President.</p>
                <pb facs="0318" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/>
                <p>The statement in my telegram No. 100 of December 3—4 p.m., that Messrs. Gomez
                    Zarate and Enrique Cordova and General Claramount were probably back of the
                    revolution and that the last was probably one of the leaders, has been partly
                    contradicted by my telegram No. 105 of December 4—10 a.m. [<hi rend="italic">1
                        p.m.</hi>] I should add, however, that there is now every indication that
                    General Claramount was not concerned in this revolution. A definite statement
                    was made to me by one of President Araujo’s intimates to the effect that General
                    Claramount was the organizer and leader of the revolution and, although it soon
                    became clear to me that this statement was inaccurate, I believed at the time of
                    sending my telegram that he had participated in it. Since then I have learned
                    that he has been completely ignored by the leaders of the revolution. I am
                    unreliably informed that he was organizing a revolution of his own and that he
                    is now seeking to place himself in a position to overthrow the Government of
                    General Martínez.</p>
                <p>In my telegram No. 105 of December 4—10 AM [<hi rend="italic">1 p.m.</hi>], I
                    stated that Generals Martínez and Claramount and other higher officers were
                    assisting actively in the revolution. The statement concerning General
                    Claramount has been dealt with in the preceding paragraph; that concerning
                    General Martínez has been dealt with in some detail in later telegrams. As
                    nearly as I can now learn the only higher officers actively assisting in the
                    revolution were Colonels Joaquín Valdes and Osmin Aguirre, concerning whose
                    activities I have reported in some detail.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">C. B. Curtis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
