<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-10-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-10-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="404" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d404">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">368.117/296</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Fisher</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-10-26">October 26, 1931</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                November 13.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1899</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to despatch No.
                            1840, dated August 28, 1931, in which the Department was informed that
                            reduced military service would be required from those Greeks that have
                            resided continuously abroad for a period of ten years. The Division of
                            Near Eastern Affairs, in its informal comment upon despatches received
                            during the month of September, stated that it did not have a clear
                            understanding of one part of the despatch. The obscure sentence read as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“For those who belong to classes already called to the colors,
                                    the ten-year period terminates with the date of publication of
                                    this Act; while for those who belong to classes which have not
                                    yet been called to the colors this period terminates with the
                                    date upon which they shall be called upon for
                                enlistment.”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>The significance of the above is the following: To secure the benefits of
                            the law, those persons who have already been called upon for military
                            service must have resided abroad for a period of ten years prior to
                            August 14, 1931; those persons that are called to the colors in the
                            future, must have resided abroad continuously for ten years immediately
                            preceding the time that their military obligation accrues,—that is, at
                            the time they are summoned to serve.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Carl A. Fisher</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>[On February 12, 1932, the Department issued to the press the
                                following statement:<note n="21" xml:id="d404fn21">Department of
                                    State, <hi rend="italic">Press Releases</hi>, February 13, 1982,
                                    p. 155.</note>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Department is informed that the exemption from alleged
                                        military obligations accorded by the Greek Government to
                                        American citizens of Greek origin who visited Greece during
                                        1930 and 1931 has not been extended to cover the year
                                        1932.</p>
                                    <p>“It is understood that the persons affected by this ruling
                                        are American citizens of Greek origin and naturalized
                                        American citizens born in territory now forming part of
                                        Greece. It is accordingly suggested that any American
                                        citizens in these categories who contemplate visiting Greece
                                        in 1932 should apply, before departure from this country, to
                                        a Greek consular officer in the United States for
                                        information as to their exact status with respect to alleged
                                        Greek military obligations.”]</p>
                                </quote></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>