<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the American Missions in Costa Rica, El Salvador,
                    Honduras, and Nicaragua</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-01-03T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-01-03T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-01-03T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-01-03T15:00:00-05:00" n="412"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d412">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">814.01/32b: Circular telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">American Missions in Costa Rica, El Salvador, Honduras,
                            and Nicaragua</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-01-03T15:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 3, 1931—3 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Department is advised by the Legation in Guatemala that the Assembly met at 4
                    p.m. on December 31, and accepted the resignations of Palma and Luis Chacon as
                    Second and Third Designates, respectively. (The ex-First Designate Leon was
                    killed in the fighting on December 16.) The Assembly then elected Reina Andrade
                    First Vice President by 50 votes to 11 for General Ariza and 3 for Chief Justice
                    Midrano. General Reyes was elected Second Vice President and General Solorzano
                    Third Designate. The first reading was then given to President Chacon’s
                    resignation. On January 2, the Assembly met for the third reading of the
                    resignation of Chacon after which Reina Andrade assumed the provisional
                    presidency.</p>
                <pb facs="0517" n="397" xml:id="pg_397"/>
                <p>After the publication of the call for new elections to be held within 6 months
                    the Department is disposed to extend recognition to Señor Andrade as its
                    information would seem to indicate that he has come into office as Provisional
                    President in a constitutional manner. Please discuss the matter at once with the
                    Government to which you are accredited in an endeavor to find out the attitude
                    which it will take in the premises and whether it would be disposed to recognize
                    Andrade also.</p>
                <p>I am taking this step because I feel it appropriate and highly desirable that we
                    act in harmony in this matter with the signatories of the General Treaty of
                    Peace and Amity of 1923 in as much as we took a position opposed to General
                    Orellana in order to support the action initiated and the policy laid down by
                    the five Republics of Central America in that treaty.</p>
                <p>Reply by cable as soon as possible.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
