<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Haiti ( (Munro) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d432</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">432</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recez5uVgqvmr6Nwm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006268"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Irrigation</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="432"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d432">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">838.105/365</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Munro</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-02-07">February 7,
                            1931</date>.<lb/>[Received February 10.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 59</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith a copy of a
                    note which I addressed to the Minister for Foreign Affairs on February 6th, and
                    also a copy of a note addressed to him on January 23rd, containing a tentative
                    schedule for the promotion of Haitian officers in the Garde.<note n="17"
                        xml:id="d432fn17">Note of January 23 and its enclosure not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dana G. Munro</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The American Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Munro</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Haitian Minister for Foreign
                            Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Sannon</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Port au Prince</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-02-06">February 6,
                                1931</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 24</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        receipt of Your Excellency’s note of January 14, 1931,<note n="18"
                            xml:id="d432fn18">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_408">p. 408</ref>.</note>
                        and to say that I have given careful study to the proposals therein
                        contained.</p>
                    <pb facs="0536" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/>
                    <p>The Government of the United States desires to replace as rapidly as
                        practicable the Americans now serving in the Treaty Services by the Haitian
                        citizens who have been receiving training and experience in these Services,
                        in order that it may be possible not later than 1936 to withdraw entirely
                        the American personnel. If this process is to be carried out in such a way
                        as to provide for the efficient operation of the Services during the
                        intervening period, the necessary changes in personnel must of course be
                        made in an orderly manner, taking into consideration in each instance not
                        only the capacity and the practical experience of the individual to be
                        appointed, but also the desirability of avoiding the impairment of the
                        efficiency of the Service as a working organization by too abrupt and
                        sweeping changes. I am confident, however, that the replacement of American
                        by Haitian personnel can be effected with a maximum of efficiency and
                        rapidity if the two Governments work in harmony toward this end.</p>
                    <p>I have already advised Your Excellency informally of the measures of
                        Haitianization which my Government is prepared to adopt in the near future
                        if a satisfactory accord on points under discussion between the two
                        Governments can be reached. In my personal letter of December 20, 1930,<note
                            n="19" xml:id="d432fn19">
                            <ref target="frus1930v03#pg_273">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1930, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 273</ref>.</note> I discussed the
                        matter in some detail. On January 21, 1931, I handed Your Excellency an
                        informal Memorandum regarding the Service Technique,<note n="20"
                            xml:id="d432fn20">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_413">p. 413</ref>.</note>
                        the contents of which I hereby confirm, and on January 23, 1931, I
                        transmitted a plan which this Legation would be prepared to put into
                        execution for the promotion of Haitian officers in the Garde d’Haiti.<note
                            n="21" xml:id="d432fn21">Not printed.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>With regard to the other matters discussed in Your Excellency’s note and
                        memorandum of January 14th., I have the honor to reply as follows:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Public Works Service</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Your Excellency proposes the immediate appointment of a Haitian engineer as
                        Assistant Engineer in Chief. M. Jeannot is now acting as principal assistant
                        to the Executive Officer of the Public Works Service. In this position, he
                        is kept in direct contact with all business which is transacted and every
                        opportunity is given to him to study and participate in the work of the
                        Service so that he may receive training which would make him capable of
                        assuming the entire direction of the Service upon the expiration of the
                        Treaty. I believe that this arrangement will achieve the purpose which Your
                        Excellency has in mind.</p>
                    <pb facs="0537" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/>
                    <p>With respect to the other proposals which Your Excellency makes regarding
                        specific appointments, I am prepared to adopt the following program if a
                        satisfactory accord on other points under discussion can be reached:</p>
                    <p>Engineer Ethéart to be appointed Director of Irrigation and Engineer Maignan
                        Director of Public Buildings immediately; Engineer Ménos to be appointed
                        Director of Telegraphs and Telephones, and Engineer Péreira, Director of
                        Roads within one year; and a Haitian Engineer as Director of Municipal
                        Engineering within two years. The execution of this program must of course
                        be dependent upon the continued satisfactory performance of their present
                        duties by the Engineers referred to during the remainder of their
                        training.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the District Engineers, I understand that M. Cauvin is now
                        serving in this capacity at Jacmel. M. Martin could be appointed
                        Departmental Engineer at Aux Cayes immediately upon the conclusion of an
                        accord on other questions. The Engineer in Chief is not prepared to appoint
                        M. Sales immediately as District Engineer at Jérémie for reasons which have
                        been fully explained to M. Sales himself.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the proposal that the present inspectors be recalled from the
                        Department of the North and Artibonite Northwest, I regret to say that I
                        cannot assume any commitment which would restrict the full liberty of the
                        Engineer in Chief to make use of such inspectors as he may deem necessary so
                        long as he has the responsibility for the direction and the control of the
                        Service.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Public Health Service</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>While it is essential that the American Administrator of the Haitian General
                        Hospital should have full responsibility and authority in the management of
                        that Institution until its complete Haitianization, the Director General of
                        the Public Health Service is prepared immediately upon the conclusion of a
                        general accord to appoint a Haitian Codirector to be associated with the
                        American Director in the latter’s work, with a view to training him to take
                        full control of the Institution upon the withdrawal of the American
                        personnel.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the proposal that a Haitian Co-director be appointed for the
                        National Public Health Service as a whole, I may say that Dr. Torchon is
                        already occupying the position of Executive Officer and principal Assistant
                        of the Director General and in this position is being given every
                        opportunity for training in the work of directing the Service as a
                        whole.</p>
                    <p>With further reference to this Service, I may point out that five out of the
                        ten sanitary districts have already been placed under Haitian <pb
                            facs="0538" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/> officials, and that according to
                        present plans the district of Jacmel will be turned over during the coming
                        year and the districts of Gonaives and Cayes during 1932 or 1933.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Office of the Financial Adviser-General
                            Receiver</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Government of the United States considers that any further extensive
                        Haitianization of this Service would be inadvisable and impracticable at the
                        present time. As I have stated in my informal letter of December 20, 1930,
                        the situation of this office is different from that of the other Treaty
                        Services because its major activities will continue after the expiration of
                        the Treaty, until the amortization of the existing debt, under the
                        provisions of the Protocol of 1919 and the loan contracts. Furthermore, in
                        view of the world wide financial depression and the very difficult present
                        financial situation of the Haitian Government, it is necessary to proceed
                        with the greatest caution in taking any steps which might result in a
                        reduction of revenue or which might make more difficult the problem of
                        keeping expenditures within the revenue available. For these reasons, I am
                        unable to accede to the proposal that a Haitian Director of the Bureau of
                        Contributions be appointed at present, or to agree with Your Excellency that
                        the time has arrived to withdraw all American personnel from the Customs
                        Service. I take due note, however, of Your Excellency’s statement that the
                        Haitian Government is prepared to negotiate with the Government of the
                        United States a special accord on the basis of the Protocol of 1919, to
                        cover the situation existing after the expiration of the Treaty, and I have
                        the honor to suggest that the discussion of questions relating to the
                        financial services be postponed until they can be considered in connection
                        with these proposed negotiations. It is obviously far, more urgent to deal
                        at the present time with the other Treaty Services from which all American
                        personnel will presumably be withdrawn during the next five years, in order
                        that adequate provision may be made now for the sweeping changes which it
                        will be necessary to make during this rather short period.</p>
                    <p>In discussing the question of Haitianization as a whole, I wish to assure
                        Your Excellency that the steps which the Government of the United States is
                        now prepared to take or commit itself to take in the future do not represent
                        a maximum but rather a minimum to be achieved in the process of
                        Haitianization. The Government of the United States desires that the
                        functions now exercised by American officials in the Treaty Services be
                        turned over to Haitian citizens as rapidly as practicable, and it will
                        always stand ready to expedite the process of Haitianization if the
                        conditions existing in the Treaty Services make it seem proper and possible
                        to proceed faster than is now contemplated.</p>
                    <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>[File copy not signed]</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
