<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Liberia ( (Mitchell) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d735</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">735</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="735"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d735">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">882.01/28</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Liberia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Mitchell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Monrovia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-10-31">October 31,
                            1931</date>.<lb/>[Received December 3.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 104</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to confirm the Legation’s
                    telegram No. 79, October 3, 9 p.m. with reference to the desire of the present
                    administration <pb facs="0815" n="695" xml:id="pg_695"/> to send an envoy to the
                    United States who would be especially instructed to lay before the Department
                    the policy which will be adopted and put into effect after the inauguration of
                    Mr. Edwin Barclay as President of Liberia on January 5, 1932.</p>
                <p>At an informal meeting, a discussion of Liberia and its future development came
                    up and Mr. Barclay repeatedly stated that propaganda circulated as to his being
                    anti-American was without foundation; that it was his intention to give Liberia
                    an administration that would reflect credit upon those entrusted with official
                    duties; that none but those highly qualified educationally and of acknowledged
                    strict integrity would be given positions of trust.</p>
                <p>He seemed at a loss to know just what representation could be made to insure the
                    American Government that the reforms as recommended by the International
                    Committee of Inquiry would be speedily and satisfactorily put into
                    operation.</p>
                <p>It was finally decided that a cable be sent asking if a special envoy, clothed
                    with the authority to speak for the Government would be given a sympathetic
                    hearing. The Department’s reply (No. 52, Oct. 6, 2 p.m.) was repeated to the
                    Honorable Louis A. Grimes, Attorney General, recently returned representative
                    from the League meeting at Geneva where he was in collaboration with Liberia’s
                    representative, Signor Sottile.</p>
                <p>A few days thereafter Mr. Grimes called at the Legation and after expressing the
                    great regret of the Liberian Government at the continued reluctance on the part
                    of the American Government to signify its intention of renewing the friendly
                    relations which had for so many years existed, placed in my hands the enclosed
                        Memorandum.<note n="53" xml:id="d735fn53">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Legation does not presume to offer any comment on this memorandum in view of
                    the Department’s reply contained in the cablegram referred to above and the fact
                    that the text of this document has been to some measure the subject of
                    discussion and review on previous occasions.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles E. Mitchell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
