<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-06-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-06-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="788" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d788">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.51/1734</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Mexican Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Téllez</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-06-29">June 29, 1931</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your Note No. 0268 [<hi rend="italic">02628</hi>] of June 26,
                            1931, in relation to litigation pending in the courts in the State of
                            New York which Gustavo Gallopin instituted against Thomas W. Lamont and
                            others constituting the so-called International Committee of Bankers on
                            Mexico. You state that you are informed that an appeal taken by the
                            defendants from an order issued by a Justice of the Supreme Court of the
                            State of New York will be heard before the Appellate division of that
                            Court on Friday, July 3, at 10:30 o’clock in the morning, and you ask
                            that the Supreme Court of the State of New York be informed: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <list>
                                    <item>“First: That the government of Mexico declines to appear
                                        in the suit instituted by Mr. Gustavo Gallopin against
                                        Thomas Lamont and others:</item>
                                    <item>“Second: That the funds which are in the possession of the
                                        Lamont firm and in connection with which Mr. Gallopin filed
                                        suit, are property of the Government of Mexico and therefore
                                        not subject to seizure since they belong to a foreign
                                        Government.”</item>
                                </list></quote></p>
                        <p>I have requested the Attorney General to instruct the appropriate United
                            States attorney to appear before the Appellate division at the time
                            mentioned and state to that Court the position of this Government as
                            above outlined.</p>
                        <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. R. Castle,
                            Jr.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>