<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-07-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="91" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d91">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/3118</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Guggenheim</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-07-31">July 31, 1931</date>.<lb/>[Received August
                                4.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 804</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Supplementing my despatch No. 722 of June
                            8, 1931, I have the honor to transmit herewith additional memoranda of
                            my conversations with various prominent Cubans, in order that the
                            Department’s records may be complete.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Harry F.
                            Guggenheim</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Extract]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Guggenheim</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a
                                    Conversation With the President of Cuba</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Machado</hi>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-06-08">June 8, 1931</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                            <p>In the morning of June 8th, I asked for an audience with the
                                President. The President, as usual, spent about an hour or an hour
                                and a half discussing many subjects. I told him that I had advised
                                my Government in regard to his decision to carry out the reforms and
                                that I had called to inquire from him what the present situation
                                was. He said that the House would consider this week the various <pb facs="0187" n="67" xml:id="pg_67"/> proposals; that he would
                                back the <hi rend="italic">ponente’s</hi> plan, but was willing to
                                listen to certain modifications. I reiterated my advice—that in
                                order to effect the desired results he must carry out the plan in
                                some manner that would appeal to the public and the newspapers, even
                                if the opposition could not be satisfied. I pointed out that
                                expeditious action was necessary; the political, economic and
                                financial matters had reached a “low-water” mark, and that the
                                political situation had better be rectified immediately so that the
                                financial situation might be taken in hand. I told the President
                                that I did not think the country could stand a $60,000,000 budget;
                                that $50,000,000 was, in my opinion, the limit. He said he realized
                                this, but was confronted with an impossible situation. He gave me a
                                copy of the <hi rend="italic">ponente’s</hi> plan which I told him I
                                would study.</p>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>