<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Nicaragua ( (Beaulac) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d941</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">941</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1930-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1930-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recu8CRwmmn30dF6G" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081635"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Martial law</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="941"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d941">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">817.1051/353</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Beaulac</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Managua</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-01-21">January 21,
                            1930</date>.<lb/>[Received January 25.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1290</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Department’s telegraphic
                    instruction No. 4 of January 16, 1930, concerning the trial of Nicaraguan
                    civilians by extraordinary courts martial under the Articles for the Government
                    of the Guardia Nacional de Nicaragua, I have the honor to report that I had
                    discussed this subject at length with President Moncada, the Commanding General
                    Second Brigade and the Jefe Director of the Guardia Nacional.</p>
                <p>President Moncada agrees thoroughly with the Department that the weakness of the
                    present system is the inefficiency of the courts and that every effort should be
                    made by his government to improve them. While he stated that his efforts in the
                    past to do this had been unsuccessful, he promised to call a meeting of the
                    Supreme Court to discuss the matter and determine what steps could be taken
                    under the Constitution or, if necessary, in what way the Constitution must be
                    amended to permit the various civil courts to function in cases of banditry in
                    districts where martial law has been declared.</p>
                <p>He said that he had been informed by members of the Supreme Court that the trial
                    of bandits by civil courts under martial law was not possible. He had therefore
                    given that idea up long ago. For several months he tried to handle a large
                    number of bandit cases in the Northern Area through military courts composed of
                    civilians sitting under authority of Nicaraguan military law and having no
                    connection with the Guardia. This system broke down utterly and had to be
                    abandoned.</p>
                <p>General Williams and General McDougal likewise agreed that the procedure outlined
                    by the Department, if it can be successfully worked out, is preferable to the
                    trial of bandits by Guardia courts martial. Both however expressed doubt as to
                    the possibility of its success under the plan outlined. General McDougal in
                    particular stressed the urgent necessity which he feels exists to dispose in one
                    way or another of bandits now in the custody of the Guardia. There is
                    transmitted a copy of a memorandum prepared by him on the subject.</p>
                <p>President Moncada said that a great deal of pressure was being exerted on him to
                    turn Sergeant Larios over to the civil courts (Legation’s <pb facs="0984"
                        n="864" xml:id="pg_864"/> telegram No. 9 of January 15). The Legation
                    likewise has received a number of petitions from various groups of citizens in
                    the same sense. A copy and translation of one dated January 15 are transmitted
                        herewith.<note n="49" xml:id="d941fn49">Not printed.</note> President
                    Moncada expressed the hope that the Department would stand behind him in this
                    case which he considers extremely important to the future discipline and success
                    of the Guardia. The court martial which will judge Larios will meet for the
                    first time today. Instead of three Americans and four Nicaraguans as I
                    previously informed the Department, it has now been decided that the court will
                    consist of one American who will act as President and six Nicaraguans.</p>
                <p>I shall communicate further with the Department on the subject of courts martial
                    as soon as President Moncada informs me of the results of his meeting with the
                    Supreme Court.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Willard L. Beaulac</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Jefe Director of the Guardia Nacional</hi> (<persName
                            type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">McDougal</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Chargé</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Beaulac</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Managua</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-01-18">January 18,
                                1930</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Prior to the declaration of martial law by the President, 9 April, 1929, and
                        7 October, 1929, no bandits had been tried by any courts except court
                        martials convened by chiefs of <hi rend="italic">Voluntaries</hi> of which
                        no reports have been received by the Guardia; but as a matter of common
                        knowledge these courts tried and sentenced prisoners captured in the field
                        and others who were apprehended on information. The one case I have
                        cognizance of is the case of Jiron, who was tried by Escamilla and three or
                        four of his colonels, all of whom being Mexican and one Costa Rican. Jiron
                        was tried and sentenced to death and executed by this court without
                        reference to higher authority.</p>
                    <p>The Government appointed two <hi rend="italic">Fiscals de Guerra</hi>, one
                        who was sent to Ocotal and the other to the Jinotega area, it being the
                        intention of the Government to send a commission of civilians to try cases
                        prepared by these <hi rend="italic">Fiscals</hi>, presumably under the
                        military code or customs of the country of previous times. I have no
                        information of the activities of the <hi rend="italic">Fiscal</hi> in
                        Jinotega, but the <hi rend="italic">Fiscal</hi> who went to Ocotal became
                        very active in preparing different lists of Conservatives, who he listed as
                        bandit suspects, and also lists of Guardia who had been formerly <pb
                            facs="0985" n="865" xml:id="pg_865"/> Conservatives and whom he wished
                        to classify as ex-bandits. He took little interest in the bandit prisoners
                        being held by Guardia and Marines for trial, beyond ascertaining which
                        political party they belonged to. Requests were made to the President to
                        send up the commission of civilians to clear up these cases, and to handle
                        cases that would occur from time to time in the future, but no commission
                        was ever appointed for either place. I was informed that the difficulty was
                        in finding reputable persons who were willing to go up into the bandit areas
                        to serve on these courts, and finally the <hi rend="italic">Fiscals</hi>
                        were recalled and were discharged.</p>
                    <p>Upon the discontinuance of the <hi rend="italic">Voluntarios</hi> there
                        ceased to be any military tribunal before which bandits could be brought to
                        trial in the Segovias. In Matagalpa, which borders the bandit country, a
                        number of cases were put to the order of the court in that place, and all
                        were either placed on bond or were released summarily. Several notorious
                        criminals were thus set at large, and protests by the Jefe Politico and
                        other civilians were made to the President with representations that the
                        courts were in sympathy with the bandits, and that no further cases should
                        be sent to these courts. On verbal instructions of the President all cases
                        of a bandit nature occurring in that locality have been held waiting the
                        formation of some tribunal which could dispose of them. I have repeatedly
                        urged that a Military Commission formed of civilians be created by the
                        President, under such laws as authorized him so to do, to clear up these
                        cases; but nothing has been done due I believe to the fact that no one could
                        be found who was willing to serve, and thereby incur the enmity and the risk
                        of retaliation which seems to be well founded.</p>
                    <p>We have the names of a great many of the known bandits and many could be
                        located, but without means of bringing them to trial prestige would be lost
                        by catching them and then having to release them for lack of machinery for
                        handling the cases.</p>
                    <p>We are facing a situation which exists in the present, which must be met in
                        some way shortly if banditry is to be kept from increasing. At present
                        Martial Law where it exists is in name only. Its only effect is to prevent
                        captured bandits from being released by the courts immediately after
                        capture.</p>
                    <p>The following courts are in the areas where Martial Law has been proclaimed: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>District Criminal Courts, Matagalpa, Esteli, Ciudad de Dario,
                                Jinotega, Ocotal, Somoto, Juigalpa, Boaco and Acoyapa.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Court or Appeals, Matagalpa.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">D. C. McDougal</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
