<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>261. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Haig) to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs () to
                    the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d261</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">261</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rechWxPReovs7qx7u" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Urban</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recbqzzF4Eebaylpi" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="border-administration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006006662"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Cross-border</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="261"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                <head>261. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HAM1" type="from">Haig</persName>) to the
                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d261fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 157,
                        Vietnam Country Files, Viet Sept 1971. Top Secret; Sensitive; Eyes
                        Only.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-09-27">September 27, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Southeast Asia Trip, September 20–26, 1971</item>
                </list>
                <p>On September 20, a team composed of three representatives of the National
                    Security Council and one representative of the Department of State departed
                    Washington to conduct a survey of the situation in Southeast Asia, with emphasis
                    on the security situation in South Vietnam. The team returned to Washington via
                        <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>, arriving the evening of
                    September 26. At Tab A<note n="2" xml:id="d261fn2">Tabs A–D, attached but not
                        printed.</note> is the team composition and a detailed itinerary.</p>
                <p>The following is a summary of the findings concerning the political, economic,
                    and security situations in the Republic of Vietnam.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Political Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Despite a deep sense of disappointment within our mission in Saigon with respect
                    to the current political situation, <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">President
                        Thieu</persName>’s decision to proceed with the October 3 referendum has
                    caused: <list>
                        <item>—little controversy in the countryside where most voters live;</item>
                        <item>—vocal opposition among urban political groupings;</item>
                        <item>—a policy of violent confrontation in a very small minority of city
                            dwellers with some leadership from the Vice President. Despite
                            exaggerated press reporting, the violence thus far has stirred hardly a
                            ripple in Saigon or elsewhere;</item>
                        <item>—no known serious coup planning;</item>
                        <item>—no serious threat to <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>’s
                            prospects for a “victory” in the referendum.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>However, it is apparent that during the post referendum period, there is serious
                    risk of an erosion of <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>’s control and
                    support if he does not institute positive reforms designed to broaden the base
                    of his new government and move, at least ostensibly, against the more flagrant
                    kinds of corruption.<note n="3" xml:id="d261fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HAM1">Haig</persName> met with <persName
                            corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> on September 23. See <ref
                            target="#d268">Document 268</ref>.</note> A detailed report is at Tab
                    B.</p>
                <pb facs="0988" n="949" xml:id="pg_949"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Economic Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This economic stabilization program continues to be very successful. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PR1">Price</persName> increases in 1971 should be in the 10% to
                    15% range, well below the past levels of 30% to 40%.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> is planning another set of
                    far-reaching reforms for October. They include a major devaluation. This
                    devaluation will be the key step toward limiting inflation in 1972 to 10% to
                    15%.</p>
                <p>There is a slight political risk within South Vietnam if import prices rise
                    sharply as they will when the reforms are executed. One-third of South Vietnam’s
                    goods are imported. But <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">President Thieu</persName>
                    appears confident he can bear these risks; and the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> appears determined to lessen its dependence on U.S.
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>The best way to insure that U.S. assistance is not cut by our critics in the
                    Congress is to launch an economic development program. One has now been designed
                    by our Mission and the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> wants to implement
                    it. Plans now are to launch this program on January 1, 1972, but it could be
                    implemented earlier by President <persName corresp="#p_NVT1"
                    >Thieu</persName>.</p>
                <p>You will be informed later of the decisions required, and it may be appropriate
                    for you to take a personal role in launching the program.</p>
                <p>A detailed report is at Tab C.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Security Assessment</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The latest reports on the pacification situation show that <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> control of the rural population is 69%
                    countrywide. Of more importance, <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> control in
                    southern South Vietnam (<gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>’s III and IV) is about
                    75%; in areas in the northern part of the country (<gloss target="#t_MR1"
                        >MR</gloss>’s I and II), it is around 50%.</p>
                <p>The resources and plans for pacification in the Delta and Saigon areas
                    practically guarantee continued pacification progress against likely enemy
                    threats through 1972. In the northern part of the country, there is a serious
                    question whether pacification progress can be sustained in the face of the
                    likely enemy threats.</p>
                <p>The potential problem results from U.S. redeployments and the incentives they
                    could create for a North Vietnamese offensive. While there is practically no
                    solid evidence on enemy intentions and capabilities for the upcoming 1971–72 dry
                    season, analysis shows that if the enemy mounts an effort similar to last
                    year’s, he could set back the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s pacification
                    effort at least temporarily in northern South Vietnam and perhaps temporarily
                    occupy a highland city like Pleiku or Kontum. Of course, if one optimistically
                    assumes the enemy will not infiltrate resources at a level approaching last
                    year’s level, the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s prospects are very
                    good.</p>
                <p>Vietnamese forces have the capability to pre-empt to some degree even the enemy’s
                    best efforts. They can do this if they take actions to strengthen their forces
                    and execute cross-border operations to pre-empt enemy attacks.</p>
                <pb facs="0989" n="950" xml:id="pg_950"/>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> must mobilize additional forces in the
                    northern part of the country, increase the pay of combat soldiers countrywide,
                    modify its draft and personnel allocation policies to raise the manning levels
                    of its combat units to 90%, and remove selected division and regimental
                    commanders who by all accounts border on the incompetent.</p>
                <p>At your direction, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> and
                    General <persName corresp="#p_ACW1">Abrams</persName> have sought these changes.
                    But President <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>’s response has been
                    slow. This trip provided me with an opportunity to impress again on <persName
                        corresp="#p_NVT1">President Thieu</persName> the need for decisive action in
                    these areas. He seemed to understand what was called for and intends to act.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> is planning to execute
                    cross-border operations toward Kratie in Cambodia and on a limited quick-stroke
                    basis into southern Laos. These will play a key role in limiting Hanoi’s
                    options.</p>
                <p>With regard to U.S. forces, the political and security situations in South
                    Vietnam justify some acceleration in U.S. redeployments, beginning on December
                    1st.</p>
                <p>Assuming no negotiated settlement, residual U.S. functions of helicopter,
                    tactical air, and limited advisory, logistics, and intelligence efforts can be
                    adequately maintained at a U.S. force level of approximately 50,000, provided it
                    is correctly designed.</p>
                <p>A detailed report is at Tab D.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
