<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>56. Memorandum for the President’s File by the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (Haig))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recXXj74deZExVTOj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace plan</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026944"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Clergy</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="rec3sLRKjD3pOGyzL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100445"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum products</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-10-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="56"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                <head>56. Memorandum for the President’s File by the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HAM1">Haig</persName>)<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d56fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White House
                        Special Files, President’s Office Files, Box 82, Memoranda for the
                        President, Beginning October 18, 1970. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>. According to a briefing memorandum from <persName
                            corresp="#p_IJN1">Irwin</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName>, October 20, <persName corresp="#p_SP1"
                            >Souvanna</persName> arrived in the United States on October 15,
                        addressed the UN General Assembly on October 19, spoke with <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> in New York on October 19, and also
                        met there with <persName corresp="#p_IJN1">Irwin</persName> on October 17
                        and <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName> on October 16. He planned to
                        return to Laos on October 22. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 7 LAOS)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-10-21">October 21, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>RE</head>
                    <item>Meeting in the President’s Office with <persName corresp="#p_SP1">Souvanna
                            Phouma</persName>, Prime Minister of Laos (11:05–11:45 a.m.) (Mrs.
                        Porson, State Department interpreter)</item>
                </list>
                <p>While the press photographers were in the President’s office at the outset of the
                    meeting, the Prime Minister mentioned to the President that he had met Senator
                        <persName corresp="#p_FJW2">Fulbright</persName> in St. Louis yesterday,
                    where he had delivered a speech; he added that the Senator had not reacted at
                    all to the speech.</p>
                <p>When the photographers left, the Prime Minister started by thanking the President
                    for his decision to grant the <gloss target="#t_RLG1">RLG</gloss> the funds
                    necessary to defend Sam Thong and Long Thien at a very critical time. As the
                    Prime Minister had cabled the President, if these positions had been lost, it
                    would have had a disastrous psychological effect on Laos. Now, thanks to that
                    aid, the Lao have overcome their difficulties and resumed the offensive.
                    Apparently, the current offensive against the Plain of Jars and Ban Na is going
                    well, and the Prime Minister hoped that all the <gloss target="#t_RLG1"
                        >RLG</gloss>’s objectives would soon be attained.</p>
                <p>The President asked the Prime Minister for his view of the cease-fire proposals
                    that had been made.<note n="2" xml:id="d56fn2">See <ref target="#d46">Document
                            46</ref>.</note> He asked whether he thought the North Vietnamese might
                    respond favorably or whether they might instead try to separate out Laos as a
                    special case.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister said they were trying to separate the Laos question from the
                    over-all Vietnamese question. His reasons for that view were that neither Peking
                    nor Hanoi had expressed any objections to the opening of contacts between the
                        <gloss target="#t_RLG1">RLG</gloss> and the Pathet Lao. Moreover, the
                    Cambodian front is creating additional difficulties for the North Vietnamese, in
                    that they find themselves unable to fight on three fronts: Cambodia, Laos, and
                    South Vietnam. It is possible that they may want to step down the level of
                    activity in Laos and accept, in a distorted way, the Prime Minister’s proposals
                    to Hanoi of some two or <pb facs="0179" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/> three years
                    ago, to the effect that if the North Vietnamese would withdraw their troops from
                    Laos, the bombing would be stopped and the North Vietnamese would be allowed by
                    the <gloss target="#t_RLG1">RLG</gloss> to use the <persName corresp="#p_HCM1"
                        >Ho Chi Minh</persName> Trail, over which the <gloss target="#t_RLG1"
                        >RLG</gloss> had no control and which was the affair of the United States
                    and the North Vietnamese. It is possible, concluded the Prime Minister, that it
                    is along those lines that the other side would like to see the Laos problem
                    resolved.</p>
                <p>The President asked the Prime Minister for his estimate of the Cambodian
                    operation—whether he thought it had been helpful to the general situation in
                    Indochina.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister’s reply was twofold: First, the operations in Cambodia had
                    created some difficulties for the Lao, represented by the North Vietnamese
                    offensive and the taking of Attopeu and Saravane. The North Vietnamese object is
                    to create a second supply route to Cambodia and South Vietnam, parallel to the
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi Minh</persName> Trail. The second point
                    was that the destruction of the military potential in Cambodia of the North
                    Vietnamese and Viet Cong and the elimination of their main supply route via
                    Sihanoukville had weakened the enemy’s strength. The supplies destroyed in
                    Cambodia can never be built back up because the capacity of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi Minh</persName> Trail is substantially less than
                    that of Sihanoukville.</p>
                <p>The President then asked the Prime Minister for his opinion of why the American
                    casualty rate in South Vietnam is so low—last week we took 40 casualties
                    compared to 200 for the same week in 1969 and 300 for the same week in 1968. Did
                    he think that was due to a lessening of the enemy’s capability or rather were
                    they deliberately trying to break contact and thus reduce the number of
                    casualties?</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister said “Both.” On the one hand, the enemy’s manpower potential
                    was clearly weaker—they had lost at least 40,000 men in Cambodia. Additional
                    evidence was the discovery by <gloss target="#t_RLG1">RLG</gloss> troops on the
                    battlefields in Laos of the bodies of North Vietnamese women soldiers. It was
                    also important to note that the renowned main strength units of the <gloss
                        target="#t_VietMinh1">Viet Minh</gloss>, those who fought against the
                    French, have by now been decimated, and the new soldiers are less combative. For
                    example, prior to 1963, the <gloss target="#t_RLG1">RLG</gloss> forces had never
                    been able to take any North Vietnamese prisoners; since 1963–64, they have taken
                    over 100. Also, there are many pure Vietnamese who have rallied to the <gloss
                        target="#t_RLG1">RLG</gloss> side. Therefore, the Prime Minister thought the
                    enemy was running out of strength.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister then commented that he thought that the President’s ceasefire
                    proposal had been rejected by Hanoi and the Liberation Front for propaganda
                    purposes and that basically they want to seek the way to peace.</p>
                <p>The President asked what we should do—should we continue to press for a ceasefire
                    or assume that there was no hope? Is there a chance that the other side might
                    nibble?</p>
                <pb facs="0180" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/>
                <p>The Prime Minister said we should back them up to the wall. It is necessary to
                    study the question of the withdrawal of United States forces and to determine
                    roughly when that withdrawal could take place under the conditions the enemy
                    desires. Then we can see how the other side reacts and if, when the date draws
                    nigh, there has been nothing positive from them, it would not be too late to act
                    accordingly.</p>
                <p>The President asked whether he meant taking stronger measures?</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister said yes, if necessary. He thought that the fact of setting a
                    date would show the United States’ strength and have a definite favorable impact
                    on domestic and foreign public opinion.</p>
                <p>He suggested that the measures envisaged might include strengthening the United
                    States forces in Thailand, which Thailand would welcome.</p>
                <p>The President then expressed our gratitude for the Prime Minister’s strong
                    support of our peace plan. He assured him that he should not be concerned about
                    Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW2">Fulbright</persName>’s reaction.
                    Unfortunately, there are men like <persName corresp="#p_FJW2"
                        >Fulbright</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SWS1">Symington</persName>, and
                    others who never miss a chance to attack United States assistance to Laos and
                    Cambodia, especially Laos. As the Prime Minister knew from previous meetings,
                    the President said, he was strongly with him in his efforts to obtain a
                    cease-fire and an independent Laos. We have difficulties with public opinion in
                    the United States, but he, the President, would personally do all he could to
                    resist the efforts of men like <persName corresp="#p_FJW2">Fulbright</persName>
                    and <persName corresp="#p_SWS1">Symington</persName> who would let Laos go down
                    the drain.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister thought his St. Louis speech of yesterday had made an
                    impression on Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW2">Fulbright</persName>. In it,
                    he had talked of Laos’ 25-year fight for survival, its desire for peace, its
                    satisfaction with the United States’ decision to help it after Chairman
                    Khrushchev had turned down its request for arms, and its total approval of the
                    President’s proposal. He had also stated that there was no agreement signed
                    between the United States and Laos.</p>
                <p>The President remarked that that was a very strong case, which it would be hard
                    for Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW2">Fulbright</persName> to attack. He added
                    that, as the Prime Minister knows, we have to do some things in private that we
                    do not admit publicly, and we shall continue to do so.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister thanked the President, saying that the <gloss target="#t_RLG1"
                        >RLG</gloss> is counting absolutely on United States assistance to bring
                    peace as soon as possible, but peace in justice and independence.</p>
                <p>In sum, the President asked, compared to his views expressed at their last
                    meeting at the White House a few months ago,<note n="3" xml:id="d56fn3">The two
                        met on October 7, 1969; see <ref target="frus1969-76v06#d132">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume VI, Vietnam,
                            January 1969–July 1970, Documents 132</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v06#d133">133</ref>.</note> was the Prime <pb
                        facs="0181" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/> Minister more optimistic about the
                    prospects for peace and did he think the enemy was weaker?</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister’s answer was yes to both. Besides the signs of enemy weakness
                    that he had already indicated, there was an even more important sign. After the
                    publication of the joint communiqué following the meeting between <persName
                        corresp="#p_SN1">Sihanouk</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_S1"
                        >Souphanouvong</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Pham Van
                        Dong</persName>, et al., <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao Tse Tung</persName>
                    had come out strongly urging the Liberation Fronts of Indochina to wage all-out
                    war. Yet, there was no reaction when the Pathet Lao contacted the Prime
                    Minister. If there was no agreement between the Pathet Lao, Hanoi, and Peking,
                    then Peking would not let the Pathet Lao resolve the Laos problem outside of the
                    over-all Indochina problem.</p>
                <p>The President then asked whether the Prime Minister was surprised that the new
                    Cambodian Government has survived as long as it has.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister said no, because he knew the Cambodians. In Cambodia, as in
                    Laos, there is anti-Vietnamese feeling, which is even stronger in Cambodia than
                    in Laos, as was evidenced by the massacres immediately after the coup d’etat.
                    Additionally, the Cambodians have always been better fighters than the Lao or
                    the Vietnamese. For example, during the Indochina war whenever a major strike
                    was called for, it was the Cambodians who handled it. Now that the government of
                    Cambodia has had enough respite to consolidate its armed forces and is
                    continuing to receive outside assistance, the Prime Minister was not surprised
                    that General <persName corresp="#p_LN1">Lon Nol</persName> had been able to take
                    things in hand. He did, however, regret that the new government had not heeded
                    his advice, sent via a Lao dignitary to Phnom Penh, to retain the monarchy and
                    keep the Queen as a symbol, and not to rush things. This was because the
                    peasants and the clergy, as in Laos, are respectful of the monarchy.</p>
                <p>He feared that the creation of the republic would create a new opposition
                    faction, that of the monarchists, drawn essentially from the peasants and the
                    clergy. He thought that opposition group would feed the guerrilla forces of the
                    other side. He hoped he was wrong, but that was his view.</p>
                <p>The President then expressed his good wishes to the Prime Minister on his return
                    to Laos, saying that we would continue to keep in close touch with him and to
                    work with him. For our part, we shall continue to keep public opinion in the
                    United States informed, so that those Senators who create problems for our aid
                    to Laos will have no base to destroy the program.</p>
                <p>Before taking his leave, the Prime Minister wished to bring up one last question,
                    which he had already discussed with Assistant Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_GM1">Marshall Green</persName>, namely, the cancellation by
                        <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> effective November 1 of the funds for
                    importation of petroleum products used to fuel the <pb facs="0182" n="143"
                        xml:id="pg_143"/> power plants.<note n="4" xml:id="d56fn4">In a memorandum
                        to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, October 22, <persName
                            corresp="#p_ETL1">Eliot</persName> indicated that <gloss
                            target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> had worked out a plan to continue financing
                        the petroleum imports needed by the Lao Electric Company until December 31
                        and would devise a solution to the exchange rate problem for imports
                        thereafter. <persName corresp="#p_HAM1">Haig</persName> sent a memorandum to
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, October 24, with this
                        information. (Both in National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> Files, Box 548, Country Files, Far East, Laos, Vol.
                        VI)</note> He said the cancellation would have an extremely serious impact
                    on the cost of living and therefore he asked whether it could be put off until
                    the end of 1971, by which time the Nam Ngum hydroelectric plant would be
                    operational, thus causing a 90 percent drop in the requirement for diesel and
                    the like. That was the only request he had to make.</p>
                <p>The President said we would have it in mind in reviewing our budget, adding that
                    perhaps there was a Congressional problem regarding funds. He asked General
                        <persName corresp="#p_HAM1">Haig</persName> to look into the matter.</p>
                <p>In closing, the Prime Minister warmly thanked the President for his help and for
                    seeing him today. The President wished him well and expressed good wishes to the
                    Lao people, whom he liked and remembered well from his visit in 1953. He also
                    asked the Prime Minister to convey his best regards to Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_GGM1">Godley</persName>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
