<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>58. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-10-22T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-10-22T12:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077241"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Linkage</term>
                    <term ref="rec0252ZNz4fHrq9C" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="vietnam-conflict">Vietnamization</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-10-22T12:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-10-22T10:00:00-05:00" n="58"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                <head>58. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d58fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 71, Country
                        Files, Europe, USSR, <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> 1970.
                        Top Secret; Sensitive. The meeting was held in the Oval Office. The full
                        text of the memorandum of conversation is printed in <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v13#d23">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, Soviet Union,
                            volume XIII, October 1970–October 1971, Document 23</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1970-10-22T11:00:00-04:00" to="1970-10-22T13:30:00-04:00"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date">October 22, 1970, 11 a.m.–1:30
                            p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>US <list>
                            <item>The President</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">William P. Rogers</persName>, Secretary
                                of State</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, Assistant
                                to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                            <item>William D. Krimer, Interpreter, Department of State</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>USSR <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">A. A. Gromyko</persName>, Soviet Foreign
                                Minister</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">A. F. Dobrynin</persName>, Soviet
                                Ambassador</item>
                            <item>Viktor Sukhodrev, Interpreter, Soviet Ministry of Foreign
                                Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The President welcomed <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Foreign Minister
                        Gromyko</persName> to Washington and said that he appreciated the
                    opportunity to have a talk with him. He had been informed that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> had held <pb facs="0185" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/>
                    useful conversations in New York.<note n="2" xml:id="d58fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d57">Document 57</ref>.</note> It would be helpful if today
                    they could discuss the questions of the general relationship between their two
                    countries. The President said he was prepared to take up any items that the
                    Minister wanted to bring up. Specific problem areas, in his view, which could be
                    usefully discussed concern the Middle East, the Berlin negotiations between the
                    Four Powers, SALT, a most important issue, Western Hemisphere problems,
                    specifically Cuba, and problems in Asia, specifically Vietnam.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d58fn3">In an October 19 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName> briefing him for the meeting, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted that while the Soviets had
                        been accurately reporting the administration’s views to Hanoi, they had been
                        unwilling to do more. So that the Soviets did not become merely
                        intermediaries, he advised <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> to
                        be tough and say the following: A stable settlement was possible based on
                        his October 7 proposals, but if Hanoi was not forthcoming then the United
                        States would continue with Vietnamization, which was working; Hanoi’s
                        political proposals were unrealistic; and it would be a mistake for Hanoi to
                        increase its military activity because it would not prompt a precipitate
                        U.S. withdrawal or disguised defeat. The memorandum is printed in <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v13#d18">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, Soviet Union,
                            volume XIII, October 1970–October 1971, Document 18</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to Vietnam.]</p>
                <p>The President said that there were possibilities in this field. He thought one
                    would have to be realistic and say that some of the other problems come into
                    play when it comes to considering the possibility of increasing trade between
                    the two countries. For example, the Vietnam war, which involved our primary and
                    basic interests, was bound to have an inhibiting influence upon trade. It was a
                    fact that under our legislative arrangements some items which could be used to
                    aid North Vietnam could not be exported to the Soviet Union. We were indeed
                    prepared to explore ways in which trade between our two countries could be
                    increased. He did not like to use the word “linkage”, but it was true
                    nevertheless that a settlement of these other matters would lead to increasing
                    economic exchanges between us. He therefore felt that if our political relations
                    improved, increased trade would follow naturally. This was in our interest as
                    well as in the interest of the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to Vietnam.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Vietnam</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The President said that he would raise the subject of Vietnam only in passing, in
                    view of the fact that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> and
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> had already discussed it
                    in New York, and that it had been reported to him that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> saw no prospects of North Vietnam or
                    the Provisional Revolutionary Government engaging in a discussion of our
                    proposal. Our position in this matter was as follows: we have made a <pb
                        facs="0186" n="147" xml:id="pg_147"/> proposal<note n="4" xml:id="d58fn4"
                        >The President is referring to his October 7 speech; see <ref target="#d46"
                            >Document 46</ref>.</note> and this is as far as we would go. It had
                    been suggested, for example, that unilateral withdrawals be made without
                    discussion with the other side. This was completely out of the question. The
                    President said he had carefully considered the recent proposal advanced by the
                    United States and if North Vietnam and the <gloss target="#t_PRG1">PRG</gloss>
                    declined to discuss our proposal in Paris, we would simply have to proceed down
                    the other road, our program of Vietnamization. That program also would end the
                    war, although the road would be longer. We would much prefer to shorten the war
                    by meaningful discussions with the other side. The problem of Vietnam, of
                    course, involved the United States to a far greater degree than the Soviet
                    Union, for the simple reason that so many U.S. soldiers had been killed there.
                    If, in the future, we should have to undertake forceful moves to protect the
                    interests of our men, we would do so resolutely, but would also inform the
                    Soviet side as we had done at the time of Cambodia. The President hoped that Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would understand our
                    position, by putting himself in our place. Since we were in this area we must
                    protect our interests. We had made our proposal and hoped that it would be a
                    basis for negotiation. If this failed to stimulate an interested reaction on the
                    other side, we would proceed down the other track as forcefully as we considered
                    necessary.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said that in his view there
                    was no prospect of the other side engaging in discussions unless the United
                    States was willing to work out the timing for withdrawal of its troops, and
                    agreed to the establishment of a coalition government for South Vietnam. His
                    statement was based upon his knowledge of the position of North Vietnam. The
                    President had spoken of the possibilities open to the United States and had said
                    that the recent proposals were as far as we could go. Of course, we would be
                    able to judge the situation better than he, but it was his impression that if we
                    were serious about wanting to put an end to the war, we would have to go along
                    with the two conditions he had mentioned. He would be less than frank if he did
                    not tell the President the same thing he had said to Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>.</p>
                <p>The President appreciated Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s
                    candor and said he knew that we disagreed on this subject. Regarding a date for
                    withdrawal of U.S. troops, we were willing to negotiate a mutual withdrawal of
                    forces. We were not going to indicate any date in advance on unilateral
                    withdrawal, however, since to do so would mean to destroy our negotiating
                    position. In regard to the coalition government, the opposition spoke of a
                    coalition government as one that would be set up after removing all elected
                    people in the present government.</p>
                <pb facs="0187" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/>
                <p>This was totally unacceptable to us. As he had said earlier, and as Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> had told Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> in New York, whatever the leaders of
                    North Vietnam and the <gloss target="#t_PRG1">PRG</gloss> could arrange with
                    South Vietnam would be acceptable to us.</p>
                <p>If North Vietnam tried to step up military operations we would take strong
                    actions. In that case, we would inform the Soviet leaders in advance. We had our
                    interests in the area and we had our plan which was succeeding. We were
                    confident that our plan would succeed. Time was now on our side, even though we
                    regretted that it would take longer than the negotiating route. The President
                    emphasized that we would do our best not to permit the Vietnam situation to
                    interfere with our bilateral relations with the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to Vietnam.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
