<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-05-18T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-05-18T23:00:00-05:00" n="126" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d126">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A4/1904: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-05-19T13:00:00+09:00">May 19,
                                    1933—1 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received May 19—5:52 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>103. 1. The Departments of Foreign Affairs, Army and Navy are carefully
                            considering all implications of the President’s appeal for <pb facs="0254" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/> disarmament and universal
                            nonaggression and it will probably be several days before an official
                                reply<note n="10" xml:id="d126fn10">See telegram No. 351, June 6, 6
                                p.m., to the Chairman of the American delegation, <ref target="#pg_184">p. 184</ref>.</note> is forthcoming. The
                            general reaction in Japan has not been favorable to the proposal as a
                            whole, but the impression is gaining ground in Japan that the past
                            tendency to ignore the opinions and wishes of other nations is in part
                            the cause of economic reprisals such as the recent abrogation of trade
                            agreements by parts of the British Empire and that therefore the
                            President’s proposal should not be refused in toto. Nevertheless, the
                            consensus of opinion among observers here is that Japan, while agreeing
                            in principle, will add such conditions and reservations as practically
                            to nullify the effect of the agreement as far as Japan and the Far East
                            are concerned.</p>
                        <p>2. The Tass representative in Tokyo stated to a member of my staff that
                            he believes that the Soviets will accept the proposal with the condition
                            that all other nations accept in good faith, this condition being aimed
                            particularly at Japan. If Japan does not accept unconditionally,
                            therefore, he believes that the Soviets will be unable to accept the
                            President’s proposal and that this will undoubtedly influence the
                            decisions of European powers bordering on the Soviet.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>