<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-08-23T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-08-23T04:00:00-05:00" n="318" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d318">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">762.63/91: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Long</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-08-23T10:00:00+01:00">August 23,
                                1933—10 a.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received August 23—8:45 a.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>93. My 92, August 21, 7 p.m.<note n="10" xml:id="d318fn10">Not
                            printed.</note> All high officials still absent from Rome but I learn
                        from official Foreign Office source that Italy will <pb facs="0538" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/> definitely consider a Nazi Austria as analogous to <hi rend="italic">Anschluss</hi>. In this connection Suvich<note n="11" xml:id="d318fn11">Italian Under Secretary of State for Foreign
                            Affairs.</note> told me August 7th “Germany must not be permitted to
                        control Austria.” The general opinion here is that this movement of
                        Mussolini is intended as a pointed but indirect notice to Germany that she
                        must cease her anti-Dollfuss activities or provoke a united European
                        opposition which might assume more than diplomatic character.</p>
                    <p>New economic proposals for Austria and Hungary each to use Trieste more
                        freely as their port and agreements between Italy and each of those
                        countries for reciprocal commodity purchases are the basis for rumors that
                        there is contemplated a political association between Italy and Austria but
                        it is believed Italy would rely on the Four Power Pact and the Paris
                        treaties rather than assume any separate responsibility in that regard
                        except to help the economic situation and foster trade and friendly
                        relations between the three countries.</p>
                    <p>The Nazi <hi rend="italic">putsch</hi> in Austria is scheduled for September
                        6th and it may lead to some definite difficulty.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Long</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>