<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-05-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="373" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d373">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">550.S1 Washington/535</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Joint Statement by President <persName type="from">Roosevelt</persName> and the Argentine
                                        Ambassador to France</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Le Breton</hi></persName>)<note n="84" xml:id="d373fn84">Issued by the White House as a press
                                        release, May 6, 1933; reprinted from Department of State,
                                            <hi rend="italic">Press Releases</hi>, May 13, 1933, p.
                                        327.</note>
                                </head>
                                <dateline>
                                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1933-05-06">May 6, 1933</date>
                                </dateline>
                                <p>The conversations<note n="85" xml:id="d373fn85">Further
                                        conversations between American and Argentine representatives
                                        were held May 2 and 3; see Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Press Releases</hi>, May 6, 1933, p.
                                        306.</note> in which we have been engaged had as purpose the
                                    fullest possible exchange of views and ideas between our two
                                    countries upon the tasks that confront all countries at the
                                    coming Economic Conference. They were inspired by the wish to
                                    examine all possible phases of economic and monetary policy
                                    which by international action might restore employment, improve
                                    prices and the turnover of trade, and aid in the solution of
                                    financial and monetary difficulties. The exchange of views was
                                    to prepare the way for action between all countries, and not to
                                    lead at the moment to definite agreements.</p>
                                <p>The conversations have been characterized by the spirit of warm
                                    friendship that has long existed between these two countries,
                                    and by the quick and friendly understanding of each other’s
                                    minds and spirit which has grown up between the two countries
                                    whose history has made us neighbors in mind and feeling.</p>
                                <p>We have joined in the realization that the gradual and
                                    simultaneous economic disarmament of the world is imperative,
                                    and the restoration of stable monetary conditions. We have
                                    surveyed with a close similarity of views and judgments the ways
                                    and means of bringing about an increased movement of trade
                                    between the two countries and throughout the world. We have
                                    entered into related questions of trade policy<note n="86" xml:id="d373fn86">For correspondence relating to trade
                                        policies concerning the United States and Argentina, see
                                            <ref target="frus1933v04#pg_642">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 642</ref> ff.</note>
                                    in which the two Governments have an important and immediate
                                    concern.</p>
                                <p>These conversations, we believe, will greatly help to forward the
                                    common purposes that we have, and to prepare the way for
                                    undertakings at the Economic Conference and the development of
                                    the mutual interests of the two countries. In warm friendship we
                                    will continue to carry forward this work.</p>
                            </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>