<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs ( (Hornbeck) )
                    of a Conversation Between American and Japanese Representatives</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d395</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">395</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1933-05-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1933-05-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recLVtmipNOLIF0A1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-05-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-05-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="395"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d395">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">550.S1 Washington/586½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a
                        Conversation Between American and Japanese Representatives</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-05-25">May 25,
                            1933</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table rend="width: 50%" rendition="#center-block">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Present:</cell>
                        <cell>The Secretary of State,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Viscount Ishii,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Fukai,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Japanese Ambassador<note n="38" xml:id="d395fn38">Katsuji
                                Debuchi.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Tsushima,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Taketomi,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Iida,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Warburg,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Bullitt,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Tugwell,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Wylie,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Livesey,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Sussdorff,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Hornbeck.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The conversation was opened by the Secretary of State, who made a statement with
                    regard to the purposes of the conference and certain views of the American
                    Government in connection with procedure related thereto.</p>
                <p>Viscount Ishii said that his delegation would be content with any order of
                    procedure in regard to the conversation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg gave an account of the suggestions which the American Government has
                    laid before other delegations and of the views which we entertain and of some
                    points in which other delegations, by name, have been in accord or in disaccord
                    with our views.</p>
                <p>When the conversation had reached a certain point Viscount Ishii asked what
                    agreements had been arrived at.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg replied that we had avoided making any agreements; we had merely
                    discussed matters—”just as we are doing with you”. Mr. Taketomi said that he had
                    seen in the newspaper that six points had been agreed on; he understood that
                    this is a statement which Senator Pittman had given out.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tugwell said that we must not believe anything that we see in the papers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bullitt said that we had made no agreements; we had simply held conversations
                    and kept everything in suspense.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that the things which we are talking over are simply things
                    which we are going to suggest at the conference. We <pb facs="0640" n="538"
                        xml:id="pg_538"/> realize that each country has its own domestic problems
                    which necessarily have a bearing on its views.</p>
                <p>At this point the Japanese group held some discussion in Japanese.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai then stated that Mr. Tsushima would ask some questions.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima said that, as to monetary policies, in particular, under the heading
                    “capital movement” what is meant is “international investment”. He understood
                    that the International Labor Office at Geneva was going to propose some
                    international program of international public works.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that we felt that each nation must raise its own funds. We would
                    oppose without any ambiguity a proposal that we finance someone else’s
                    program.</p>
                <p>There followed some discussion of the purport of proposals for stabilization,
                    toward the end of which Mr. Warburg asked what would be the Japanese attitude
                    toward a <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> stabilization.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai replied that as he saw it exchange rates are not in their nature
                    subjectable to control of governments.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that the only thing we could do would be to reduce
                    speculation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that to undertake to fix a rate at a certain point was a different
                    thing from trying to prevent its going lower.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg asked whether he should outline how we think it might be done:
                    whether we should have a little exploration of the idea. Suppose that some of
                    the countries are going to attempt stabilization. They could give notice of the
                    rate at which each expected to stabilize; each could act independently, but they
                    would notify the others of any change. This does not suit us from the point of
                    view of our domestic policy; but we think that the work of the conference would
                    be greatly facilitated by having stability while the conference is going on.
                    Suppose we agree to accept the exchange of other countries at a given price.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that he was not speaking in an abstract and general way. Japan had
                    lost a lot of gold. She could not afford to let gold go out. She had almost no
                    hoarded funds abroad. From exports she paid for imports. In addition she had
                    been sending out newly produced gold. She had practically no funds to be used
                    for stabilization of exchange. The United States had plenty of gold. England had
                    a hoard. France has much gold.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg inquired whether it was the Japanese feeling that it would not be
                    helpful to them unless the stabilizing were at so low a figure that the effect
                    would be to put the yen up.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that he would begin again. So far as the Japanese Government and
                    Bank of Japan were concerned they had done everything possible to prevent the
                    going down of Japanese currency. Since <pb facs="0641" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/>
                    last November they had been able to maintain exchange at somewhere between 20
                    and 23 cents. Before that there had been fluctuations downward from 49 to 20
                    cents. They did not like the low exchange. They are anxious to maintain the yen
                    at the present level. So far they have been successful. He hoped they would be
                    so for some time to come. If there are no unexpected developments they would be
                    able to prevent further depreciation. So—their desire and hope coincided with
                    our point of view; but as to entering into an undertaking, they must either let
                    their gold go to a certain extent or must have difficulties [?] which we have
                    not. In order to envisage an ultimate return to the gold standard they must hold
                    their present stock of gold.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that if he were in their place he would say the same. It was
                    valuable to us to have that point defined. We are willing that those who are
                    able to do this do it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima said that Japan had invisible exports amounting to $75,000,000. He
                    thought that the yen was not subject to any undue fluctuation. But if they made
                    undertakings to stabilize at a particular point it would lead to fluctuation.
                    Therefore they would try to prevent fluctuation of the yen but they did not
                    desire to make any definite engagement.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg inquired: Is not the chief threat to your exchange a budgetary threat
                    rather than an international threat?</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima replied that there would be no further occasion to depreciate the
                    yen. As to <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> stabilization, Japan’s budget was
                    unbalanced. He thought that this would continue for a year or two. We could not
                    know how long. The international commodities price is not adjusted. We must have
                    internal readjustment before there will be a chance for international
                    readjustment.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that we had seriously considered with the British and French the
                    idea of stabilization—in order to facilitate the work of the conference.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that he could say definitely that the Japanese did not want to let
                    their exchange go lower. They would do everything possible to prevent it and he
                    hoped that they would be successful. This would be to their conscious interest
                    and he thought that it would contribute to world interest. What he did not see
                    was how any engagement could be made. In the present condition of Japan an
                    undertaking would be impossible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg asked whether, in regard to movement of capital they were in
                    agreement with our view.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima said that they could not admit the necessity of an international
                    public works program. Japan had her own internal problems: her own people were
                    demanding more public works.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg made a statement on the subject of loans to debtor nations and gave
                    some account of the British view.</p>
                <pb facs="0642" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/>
                <p>Mr. Warburg stated that we have no desire to have an unbalanced amount of the
                    world’s gold in this country.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that the Japanese Government had had to issue bonds to meet its
                    expenditures. It had not been able to issue these to the public. The Bank of
                    Japan had taken them up. But so far they had been able to sell them to other
                    banks and subscribers. In the future their budgetary system might affect their
                    international exchange; but they were trying to prohibit the flight of capital
                    and speculation of exchange operations since last November. (Mr. Warburg
                    remarked that they had done this very effectively).</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima said that with regard to cooperation among central banks the
                    Japanese were quite in accord with the American view. They wanted to pursue an
                    easy money policy. The Bank of Japan was ready to help.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that he would add—and he would come to a wider field—: the
                    Japanese agreed that a policy of free credit and cheap credit was desirable to
                    meet the situation of the world in general and of Japan; but that there was a
                    limit: if the policy went too far it might interfere with the Japanese objective
                    of a return to the gold standard. So, it was not an immaterial question whether
                    we were going on the theory of cheap money without limit.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that there would be stages.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima suggested that there be a limit.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that the general tendency must be taken advantage of to start
                    our machinery. We did not advocate that everybody do it regardless of internal
                    situations.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that if the policy went too far it would lead to unbridled
                    inflation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that easy money should not be pursued by countries that could
                    not afford it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that he agreed that to meet the present situation cheap money was
                    desirable. To a certain extent an increase in the amount of currency was
                    inevitable; but that the Japanese could not agree in principle to unlimited
                    cheap money.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that we concurred.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima said that the Japanese were anxious to remove trade barriers. The
                    Japanese Government had no thought of intervening in the normal transactions of
                    foreign trade. They were anxious to prevent the flight of capital. Japanese
                    bonds issued abroad and those at home had a big difference in yield.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that so far as exchange transactions were trade barriers, what
                    Japan wanted was to restrict the flight of capital. Here was one of the means by
                    which they maintained exchange. They did not like to use exchange restrictions
                    such as Germany is using.</p>
                <pb facs="0643" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that they differentiated between exchange restrictions which
                    obstruct trade and those which …<note n="39" xml:id="d395fn39">Omission
                        indicated in the original.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima said that with regard to the question of a 25 per cent reserve, the
                    Bank of Japan, like the Bank of England, had no fixed rate. It was advisable for
                    Japan to maintain her existing system.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg inquired whether the Japanese would as a matter of practice agree
                    that 25 per cent was a practicable rate.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that Japan’s position was quite clear: as to the general world
                    question they might be lighthearted, for the reason that they have no definite
                    connection with that problem; therefore, if the general tendency is in that
                    direction he saw no reason why Japan should obstruct; but he personally did not
                    favor this; he did not believe in a legal reserve system; that was his personal
                    opinion; but if the majority thought it good, Japan would not take exception to
                    it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg inquired whether, assuming that there was a legal reserve system, the
                    Japanese felt that 25 per cent was enough for such a system.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that it was his personal opinion that a wise administrator would
                    not lay great emphasis on this; Keynes<note n="40" xml:id="d395fn40">John
                        Maynard Keynes, British economist.</note> was of the same opinion. The
                    inclusion of a percentage in silver was of no interest to Japan.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that they would not have to do it; they had an option.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that he thought that putting up the price of silver would be a
                    good thing for the world.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima inquired what had been the view of the French delegation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg replied that they had said that silver was not of interest to them;
                    we had contended that it was—because of world trade—and had convinced them. They
                    probably would not exercise the option but they would not obstruct.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima said that with regard to silver the Japanese had no particular views
                    regarding the understanding to be arrived at between silver producing and silver
                    using countries. If it would help stabilization of silver prices it would be a
                    good thing for the world. As to debasement, the Japanese Government had taken no
                    action. As to increase of content of silver, that question would involve the
                    question of the budget. He wished to make a reservation: Japan could not afford
                    to increase the silver content.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that our suggestion was to remonetize when, as, and if budgets
                    permitted.</p>
                <pb facs="0644" n="542" xml:id="pg_542"/>
                <p>A Japanese member asked whether we had any information on the position of
                    India.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that we had not talked the question over with them as yet.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fukai said that with regard to public works in various countries the Japanese
                    thought this should be left to the countries concerned. “Synchronization” seemed
                    to them to be going too far.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tsushima said that Japan considered it essential to adjust the undue burdens
                    on debtors occasioned by fall of commodity prices.</p>
                <p>Viscount Ishii asked what points would be considered at tomorrow’s meeting.</p>
                <p>Mr. Warburg said that among the questions would be: tariff truce; treaties,
                    bilateral and multilateral; and the most-favored-nation clause.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned until 10:00 a.m., May 26.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanusy</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
