<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-05-05T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-05-05T18:00:00-05:00" n="420" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d420">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">550.S1/729: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chargé in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Atherton</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-05-05T19:00:00-04:00">May 5,
                                    1933—7 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>92. For Norman Davis. In regard to the tariff truce proposals. In the
                            light of the circumstances and difficulties you are facing, it seems to
                            the Department wise that you recall to the British Government that all
                            that was contemplated for the period between now and the Conference was
                            the promulgation by the Organizing Committee of a strong recommendation
                            that all governments live up to the general purpose and aims of
                            international economic cooperation which the Economic Conference is
                            designed to forward. As to the exact wording of this recommendation, the
                            Department authorizes you to agree to any wording that is feasible and
                            which is not so weak or does not contain so much leeway for special
                            action as to defeat itself. It also leaves to your judgment whether this
                            recommendation should be issued by the Organizing Committee or as a
                            joint statement of the governments represented on the Organizing
                            Committee.</p>
                        <p>As for the tariff truce proposal which is to be brought forward at the
                            Conference, the exact wording of that will no doubt be discussed at the
                            Conference itself. If it proves possible, the American Government will
                            endeavor to hold conversations with various other governments before the
                            Conference.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>