<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-11-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="700" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d700">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51W89 Finland/65</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-11-13">November 13, 1933</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Finnish Minister, having received the necessary instructions from his
                            Government, the President received him at the White House on November
                            13th together with Mr. Acheson and myself. The President opened the
                            conversation by expressing his appreciation of the attitude of the
                            Finnish Government towards its obligations and pointed out that Finland
                            was the only one of foreign debtors to the United States which had
                            carried out to date in full its obligations to this country. He wished,
                            he said, to show his full appreciation of this situation by proposing a
                            settlement which would radically reduce the Finnish debt.</p>
                        <p>He reminded the Minister that Finland had been paying interest at the
                            rate of 3½ per cent. He would like, he said, to reduce this interest to
                            a purely nominal one and to apply the payments on account of interest to
                            payments on account of capital. If, therefore, payments from Finland
                            since the original debt refunding agreement were applied to capital, the
                            capital debt would be materially reduced. The President asked Mr.
                            Acheson and me to work out the details of such an undertaking. The
                            Minister expressed deep appreciation of the President’s proposal.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">William Phillips</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>