<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-06-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="715" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d715">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51W89 France/913</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-06-15">June 15, 1933</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The French Ambassador left with me this morning the accompanying
                                note,<note n="6a" xml:id="d715fn6a">
                                <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> in which his Government states
                            that it is compelled to postpone payment on its debt. The important
                            point in the note is the statement that “it by no means intends to
                            break, unilaterally, engagements freely entered into and desires to
                            renew to the Federal Government the assurance that it is always ready to
                            bring in all appropriate ways its most active cooperation in seeking a
                            satisfactory solution.”</p>
                        <p>M. de Laboulaye called attention to this phraseology and felt that it was
                            “something at least.”</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador asked me to explain to the President the genuine efforts
                            which he made to elicit part payment. He had, he said, some <pb facs="0981" n="879" xml:id="pg_879"/> days ago urged upon his
                            Government the idea of part payment to cover the December and June
                            instalments due; he had received a reply saying that the proposal was an
                            interesting one and was being carefully studied; he had, therefore, for
                            several days hopes that the French Government would reconsider its
                            former position, but apparently, after sounding out the leading members
                            of the Chamber, his Government had come to the conclusion that it could
                            not face the Chamber with such a proposal.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said he would be glad to make this explanation to the
                            President personally. I explained that the President was getting ready
                            to leave town, that he was overwhelmed with various matters to be
                            disposed of and that, in the circumstances, I would ask M. de Laboulaye
                            to allow me to carry forward his message. The Ambassador said he
                            understood perfectly.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">William Phillips</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>