<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-06-19T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-06-19T07:00:00-05:00" n="718" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d718">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51W89 France/916: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Straus</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-06-19T13:00:00+01:00">June 19,
                                    1933—1 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received June 19—12:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>286. When Monsieur Paul-Boncour returned my call this morning he brought
                            up the question of the nonpayment of debt installment on June 15 saying
                            that he wanted to emphasize to me as had already been done by Ambassador
                            Laboulaye in Washington that this however did not in any way change the
                            French point of view with respect to their recognition of their
                            obligations and their intentions of settling them in connection with a
                            discussion of the entire debt question. He said that the fact that the
                            reply from the White House to the French note on this subject had stated
                            that the nonpayment of the installment of December 15th and June 15th
                            had not even as yet been discussed, made him feel that now was the time
                            to undertake such discussion and that if certain principles of payment
                            of the debt question could be agreed on these principles would enable
                            the Government to go to Parliament with some hope of obtaining a
                            reversal of their previous attitude on the former installment. It was
                            his belief that before some discussions of this character and before
                            some agreements in principle there would be no possibility of changing
                            the French parliamentary attitude which he said was even more opposed to
                            payment now than at the time of the December 15 nonpayment when the
                            Radical Socialists Party had supported Herriot out of personal loyalty
                            but at present he was convinced that for the most part they would vote
                            against payment.</p>
                        <p>I outlined to him the bad effects on American public opinion of these
                            nonpayments and the difficulties with our Congress and he said <pb facs="0983" n="881" xml:id="pg_881"/> that we were of course each
                            faced with parliamentary difficulties and the necessity for obtaining
                            parliamentary authorizations for regulation of the question. He said
                            that to his mind the worst thing that could take place at the moment
                            would be another refusal by the French Parliament to make payments and
                            therefore that new facts and in particular some indications of the
                            general line of an ultimate agreement on the whole debt question would
                            be necessary. He touched upon the old arguments that the moratorium had
                            put a new factor into the debt situation of the world which would have
                            to be taken into account in any form of regulation. He expressed his own
                            good will and that of his Government to make earnest efforts to find a
                            solution.</p>
                        <p>Repeated American delegation, London.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Straus</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>