<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 551The Commander in Chief, Far East (Ridgway) to the Department of the
                    Army</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v14p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d551</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">551</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-04-09T01:37:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-04-09T01:37:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-04-09T01:37:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-04-09T01:37:00-05:00" n="551"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d551">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/4–2952: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 551<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, Far East (<persName corresp="#p_RGMB1"
                            type="from">Ridgway</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            the Army</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>routine</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-04-09T15:37:00+09:00"
                            >April 9, 1952—3:37 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss> 66619. 1. With the early coming into force of
                    the Peace Treaty and the changing status of Japan from that of an occupied
                    country to that of a sovereign nation, I feel it incumbent upon me to present
                    for your consideration my views on certain matters relating to US military
                    policy in the Far East.</p>
                <p>2. A. The most vital factor in the achievement of US objectives in the Orient is
                    the continued maintenance of Japanese faith in our commitment to guarantee the
                    essential security of Japan, until it is capable of assuming that responsibility
                    of a sovereign state. During my service as <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>
                    I have several times heard influential Japanese express such deep concern over
                    the possible lack of continuity of US intentions to protect Japan as to amount
                    almost to fear. On each such occasion I have sought to impress upon the
                    individuals concerned, and later upon the highest Japanese governmental
                    authorities, the firm intention of the US to provide essential protection to
                    Japan during that period when Japan is creating the essential forces to permit
                    her to assume responsibility for her own defense. With the effectuation of the
                    treaties it will, I think, become more than ever important to US interests that
                    our long range intentions be made positive and clear, and that this be done from
                    time to time so as to preclude the building up in the Japanese mind of any idea,
                    however weakly founded, that we do not in fact intend to continue our protective
                    shield over them until they can substitute one of their own. The factor of
                    possible political pressure for economic advantage, in this expressed concern by
                    Japanese, is of course recognized.</p>
                <p>The Japanese, in common with other Oriental peoples outside the Soviet orbit,
                    will be subject to steadily mounting internal and external pressures directed
                    from the Kremlin. They will be ever mindful of their close proximity to a
                    Communist dominated Asiatic mainland and ever alert to any indication of a
                    weakening in our political or military policies toward them. Japanese response
                    to US leadership will be predicated upon a constant realistic appraisal of US
                    intentions and commitments on a positive and long range basis. What they think
                    our intentions are, may be even more important than what these intentions
                    actually are.</p>
                <pb facs="0181" n="1237" xml:id="pg_1237"/>
                <p>Therefore I suggest that at an appropriate time shortly after the coming into
                    effect of the Security Pact, the Japanese be publicly and authoritatively
                    reassured of our firm intentions. While such a statement should go far toward
                    allaying any trepidation on the part of the Japanese, there must necessarily be
                    continued concrete assistance toward the development of essential Japanese
                    Security Forces, and continued insistence that Japan shall make proper and
                    timely contribution thereto.</p>
                <p>B. The programs for development of the security forces of Japan and Korea are
                    closely interrelated and a proper and controlled balance must be maintained. US
                    support and maintenance of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Military Forces,
                    if unrelated to similar assistance to Japan, could have serious adverse effects
                    on our relations with both governments, and consequently upon our Far East
                    position. It may be that a bilateral security pact between Japan and the <gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>, however infeasible at this time, could later
                    eventuate, and even perhaps, at a still more distant date, be a prelude to a
                    more encompassing Pacific security pact embracing the other free nations of the
                    Orient. If so, then the interrelation of US programs for arming Chinese
                    Nationalist and Southeast Asian forces likewise has important bearing, political
                    as well as military, on our Japanese and <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                    programs.</p>
                <p>C. In due time Japan may be expected to seek membership in the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.<note n="1" xml:id="d551fn1">For documentation on
                        this question, see <ref target="frus1952-54v03#pg_802">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 802</ref> ff.</note> That her people
                    have an awareness of the responsibilities which such membership entails, and a
                    desire to meet these responsibilities, has been adequately demonstrated both
                    spiritually and materially. Despite subversive efforts intended to spread
                    disunity in Japan there has been conspicuous accord if [<hi rend="italic"
                        >in</hi>?] the manner in which the great majority of Japan’s agricultural
                    and industrial workers have thrown themselves behind the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss>’s war effort in Korea. Her churches and charitable institutions,
                    from their own meager resources, responded immediately to alleviate conditions
                    among war ravaged Korean families, and thousands of Japanese have given their
                    blood for the care of our wounded. Japan’s request for membership in the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> organization should, I think, be provided full US
                    support. While realizing the objections to be overcome, our support would
                    further provide positive proof to the Japanese as to which nations were friends
                    and which enemies.</p>
                <p>3. These views are submitted because of the imminent and unlamented demise of
                        <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>. Summarizing: <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>I consider it of signal importance that our government, as often as
                            may be necessary, seek to reassure the Japanese people <pb facs="0182"
                                n="1238" xml:id="pg_1238"/> that our policy toward Japan will remain
                            constant, and that our security interests in the Pacific are inseparable
                            from their own.</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>We must be ever alert to the intimate relationship between the
                            development of the Japanese and <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                            security forces and the need for their joint alignment against a common
                            foe. Moreover, the development of Chinese Nationalist and Southeast
                            Asian military forces is in turn a closely related problem.</item>
                        <label>C.</label>
                        <item>We must continue to press vigorously for completion of the desired
                            expansion of Japanese security forces, and at substantially the rate now
                            programmed.</item>
                        <label>D.</label>
                        <item>Japan should receive strong US support in her endeavor to secure
                            membership in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, including, I
                            believe, an authoritative US government statement to that effect,
                            published shortly following the effective date of the treaties. Even
                            though membership should be long delayed, our support would emphasize
                            the integrity of US intentions toward the Japanese people.</item>
                        <label>E.</label>
                        <item>Finally, we must by word and deed do everything within our power to
                            overcome any feeling in the Oriental mind that our interest in Asia is
                            casual, temporary or overshadowed by our interests in other
                            regions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
