<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 639The Ambassador in Japan (Murphy) to the Director of the Office of
                    Northeast Asian Affairs (Young)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v14p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d639</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">639</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recYmlCrc3Fe9WvIx" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="639"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d639">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.94/4–2853</note>
                <head>No. 639<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan (<persName corresp="#p_MRD1"
                            type="from">Murphy</persName>) to the Director of the Office of
                        Northeast Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_YKT1" type="to"
                            >Young</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d639fn1">Filed as an attachment to a covering note dated
                        Apr. 28, not printed, from <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName> to
                            <persName corresp="#p_SCA1">Charles A. Sullivan</persName>, Deputy for
                        American, South Asian, and Far Eastern Affairs in the Office of Foreign
                        Military Affairs, Department of Defense.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential<lb/>official–informal</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-02">April 2,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Ken</persName>
                    </hi>: You will recall that during your recent visit to Japan you had an
                    opportunity to discuss with some of my officers the over-all problem of criminal
                    jurisdiction, to speak to Japanese Government officials about this matter, and
                    to observe one of our frequent meetings with the Commonwealth Chiefs of Missions
                    in Tokyo, where the subject was also discussed in connection with the current
                    negotiations for an agreement to cover the United Nations forces in Japan. As a
                    result of your talks with those persons in the <pb facs="0345" n="1401"
                        xml:id="pg_1401"/> field intimately concerned with this problem, I feel sure
                    you left Tokyo with a greater understanding of the seriousness of the situation
                    and its possible significance on future United States–Japanese relations. You
                    will undoubtedly be kept informed of the situation as it develops, particularly
                    with regard to Japanese reactions which should make themselves known during the
                    election campaign in Japan. I wish, however, on the eve of my departure to set
                    forth several considerations which have occurred to me in the hope that they may
                    serve some useful purpose in dealing with the problem as we approach the April
                    28 deadline,<note n="2" xml:id="d639fn2">Article XVII provided that if the
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Status of Forces Agreement had not
                        gone into effect within one year of the effective date of the Administrative
                        Agreement, the United States would at the request of Japan reconsider the
                        question of criminal jurisdiction over U.S. official personnel and their
                        dependents. Documents in file 611.94 for 1953 indicate that the Japanese
                        Government instead chose to await the entry into force of the <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Agreement, which took place on Aug. 23,
                        1953.</note> when the Japanese are certain to request reconsideration of
                    Article 17 of the Administrative Agreement.</p>
                <p>In the first place we are faced with the Japanese emotional factor. The Japanese,
                    and I refer to various levels of responsible Japanese opinion in and out of
                    government, do not always approach the problem realistically. They will admit
                    quite frankly that the jurisdiction issue is a question of “national sentiment,”
                    and do not appear able to face the issue on a practical basis. Persons who
                    should know better talk in terms of extra-territoriality and loss of sovereignty
                    even though we have repeatedly pointed out that these concepts are not involved.
                    Nevertheless, the press and Diet members are disinclined to re-orient their
                    thinking.</p>
                <p>Second, the Japanese are convinced that the present state of international law
                    supports their position for split jurisdiction along the lines of the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> formula, and they refer constantly to the
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Agreement as their authority for this
                    view. Even though the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Agreement may never
                    come into force, they contend that it still represents the prevailing views and
                    considered judgments of those statesmen who signed that treaty. They feel that
                    they can accept this internationally-approved formula without loss of prestige
                    and without injury to their “national sentiment”. They are familiar with the
                    fact that the <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> Administration
                    supported the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> formula and that the present
                    Administration on February 27 also urged Senate ratification. This situation
                    makes it difficult for us to discuss with the Japanese the international law on
                    the subject, which is by no means uniform.</p>
                <p>Third, criminal jurisdiction in Japan is a political football, with the Japanese
                    apparently more interested in kicking the ball than in running with it. If there
                    is any one thing that all political parties <pb facs="0346" n="1402"
                        xml:id="pg_1402"/> are agreed upon it is the desire for the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> split jurisdiction arrangement. I would
                    venture to say that if a Japanese in political affairs should undertake to
                    espouse United States exclusive jurisdiction, his career would be in jeopardy.
                    Thus, at a time when <persName corresp="#p_YS1">Yoshida</persName> appeared to
                    have complete control of a majority in the Diet, he did not dare to take to the
                    Diet the issue of exclusive jurisdiction for the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >U.N.</gloss> forces in Japan; and I have yet to see any evidence that any
                    political or governmental group is prepared to sponsor such jurisdiction at this
                    time or in the future. It is my impression also that many important Japanese
                    bureaucrats, including those dealing with the Administrative Agreement, feel
                    strongly that Japan should fight for the split jurisdiction formula.</p>
                <p>As a final consideration, I need not remind you that the die was cast in the
                    Administrative Agreement negotiations when we promised to give the Japanese
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> treatment upon Senate ratification or
                    else to reconsider the subject after April 28 of this year. This they consider
                    an implied promise to turn over some jurisdiction to them, and they would
                    undoubtedly consider a refusal to give way as a breach of good faith.</p>
                <p>There may be a number of explanations for these Japanese attitudes. I would
                    explain them by saying that they are the reaction to the many years of
                    occupation, and also a reassertion of the national pride of a sensitive people.
                        <persName corresp="#p_OK1">Okazaki</persName> recognizes this, and I am sure
                    others in government office have the same feelings. Last fall <persName
                        corresp="#p_OK1">Okazaki</persName> told me, with reference to the question
                    of jurisdiction, that the Japanese are a people suffering from an inferiority
                    complex which is reflected in their strong desire to exercise jurisdiction in
                    the present instance.</p>
                <p>What then is the solution—what should we do? Obviously the simplest answer is
                    U.S. ratification of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Agreement. In the
                    event, however, that the Senate does not ratify <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>, or else tables the treaty indefinitely, we will be faced with
                    a decision which will have to be measured in terms of the relative merits of
                    military exigence versus political prudence. At this point, I don’t believe that
                    the Japanese will give up easily, and I think it would be dangerous for us to
                    apply such pressure on them as might conceivably obtain our objectives on
                    criminal jurisdiction at the expense of alienating the friendly Japanese
                    relationships and popular support, which are so essential for the successful
                    mission of our forces in Japan. I can think of nothing short of re-enactment of
                    the Asiatic exclusion law that would be more calculated to arouse the resentment
                    of all classes of Japanese.</p>
                <p>In the event the Senate ratifies <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, the
                    Japanese will most certainly ask for similar treatment, and, under the terms of
                    the Administrative Agreement, apparently are entitled to get it. This <pb
                        facs="0347" n="1403" xml:id="pg_1403"/> does not mean, however, that the
                    Japanese may not be willing in certain situations to waive jurisdiction in our
                    favor. Last September we had indications in the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >U.N.</gloss> Agreement negotiations that the Japanese were interested in
                    exercising jurisdiction only in a limited category of major offenses—five in
                    all. Whether the Japanese would be so inclined if they had the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> formula is hard to say. If the Japanese are
                    given jurisdiction over our troops in Japan, they may make use of it for an
                    initial period to assert their authority and satisfy their so-called inferiority
                    complex. Nevertheless, I should expect that we would be in a position at the
                    same time to arrive at some working arrangement with the Japanese whereby they
                    would relinquish more and more of their jurisdiction on an informal basis, other
                    than by means of a written commitment, perhaps on the Provost Marshal-Japanese
                    police level.</p>
                <p>Should the Senate disapprove of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> or
                    pigeon-hole it, we can no longer use the argument with the Japanese that the <hi
                        rend="italic">status quo</hi> must be maintained so as not to affect the
                    chances of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>’s ratification. The question
                    then becomes wide open, and since the Japanese know that the President and the
                    Secretary are behind the split jurisdiction formula, which can be granted in
                    Japan without Senate approval, our position becomes even more untenable. I
                    realize of course that a Senate rejection of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> formula would make it difficult to undertake any arrangements
                    contrary to the Senate’s policy, but the Japanese may not see it that way,
                    particularly when they learn that the United Kingdom will put into effect the
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> jurisdictional formula on April 30, as
                    part of its internal legislation, whether or not <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> comes into force. I don’t think the Japanese will ever
                    willingly continue to grant exclusive foreign jurisdiction if the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> formula is in force in Europe. The most we
                    can hope for is a watered-down version of the split jurisdiction, and I believe
                    we can get it provided Europe takes it as well. At least we ought to try for
                    it.</p>
                <p>Apparently, there has been some thought given to taking the position that the
                    existence of hostilities in Korea is cause for the retention of exclusive
                    jurisdiction by one means or another. This position would have a great deal of
                    merit if it were not for the fact that the Japanese would consider it as an
                    obvious attempt to circumvent the provisions of the Administrative Agreement.
                    These hostilities were in existence when the U.S. committed itself either to
                    grant <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> treatment or to reconsider criminal
                    jurisdiction after April 28, and although I was not present at the negotiations,
                    I am reliably informed that the “hostilities” concept was never considered or
                    discussed with the Japanese. Since the situation today is substantially what it
                    was last year in this respect, I do not believe that the Korean hostilities
                    offer us a sound basis for seeking retention <pb facs="0348" n="1404"
                        xml:id="pg_1404"/> of exclusive jurisdiction. I doubt the Japanese would
                    concede that the hostilities in Korea justify continued United States exclusive
                    jurisdiction because of the implication that Japan would be admitting a status
                    of belligerency. Under these circumstances, therefore, any attempt to hold on to
                    exclusive jurisdiction on the basis of hostilities in Korea presents a situation
                    of compounded difficulty.</p>
                <p>In this discussion I wish to make my own position clear. Under the Administrative
                    Agreement the Japanese owed us at least one year of exclusive jurisdiction
                    without recrimination or regret in order that our forces could readjust to the
                    changed situation resulting from the Peace Treaty. To this extent at least they
                    had paid their debt although at times with evident distaste on the part of the
                    press and politicians. However, in view of our present position and policy, both
                    in Japan and in Europe, it is difficult to see how we can withdraw from our
                    implied promise to split our jurisdiction with Japan. We might have obtained
                    more favorable treatment last year when the Japanese were willing to give us a
                    better version than <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. We may even be able
                    to do it now, but with less possibility of success. The Japanese consider
                    criminal jurisdiction as one of the foremost problems between the U.S. and
                    Japan. There seems little doubt that if we press for better treatment than we
                    receive in Europe, we are in for trouble.</p>
                <p>We were delighted to have you visit with us, and I hope you enjoyed your stay in
                    Japan as much as we enjoyed having you. I look forward to our next visit.</p>
                <p>With warm personal regards, I am</p>
                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Murphy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
