<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-10-20T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-10-20T05:00:00-05:00" n="703" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d703">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">794C.0221/10–2053: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 703<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan (<persName corresp="#p_AJM1" type="from">Allison</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-10-20T19:00:00+09:00">October 20, 1953—7
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1001. <persName corresp="#p_OK1">Okazaki</persName> spoke to me this
                            morning regarding timing of return of Amami-Oshima group. He said
                            special Diet session would convene about October 29 or 30 and it would
                            be necessary to present budget for coming year’s expenses in
                            Amami-Oshima, as well as legislation governing those islands. While it
                            would not be necessary to include definite date of going into effect on
                            legislation, it would be necessary to explain to Diet probabilities in
                            this connection and government hoped it would be able to say islands
                            would be returned on or about December 1. I told him I could give <pb facs="0478" n="1534" xml:id="pg_1534"/> him no definite information
                            in this connection, but hoped it would be possible to meet his
                            desires.</p>
                        <p>I referred to necessity of reaching agreement on military facilities to
                            be retained and I told him frankly that one of difficulties was close
                            relationship which Amami group bears to security of Okinawa and
                            necessity of devising some method of insuring that future developments
                            would not menace that security. <persName corresp="#p_OK1">Okazaki</persName> appeared most understanding and said he was
                            certain Japanese Government would go to great lengths to meet American
                            desires. He asked whether or not it was possible for United States
                            military to list type of rights or facilities it might need in future
                            and said that if this could be done, he felt definite agreement could be
                            reached; that Japanese Government would at any time be willing to
                            negotiate with United States Government arrangement for such rights or
                            facilities. I said I hoped this could be done and that we were earnestly
                            looking into matter.</p>
                        <p>I believe <persName corresp="#p_OK1">Okazaki</persName> reflects true
                            cooperative attitude of Japanese Government toward this question and
                            that if we approach them on reasonable basis, we can obtain all
                            legitimate needs. However, if we demand everything in writing in first
                            instance, thereby indicating to Japanese our distrust of their good
                            will, I seriously doubt that present cooperative attitude will be
                            maintained.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AJM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Allison</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>