<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="720" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d720">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">794.5/12–1054</note>
                        <head>No. 720<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss> to the Secretary of Defense
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_WCE1" type="to">Wilson</persName>)</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d720fn1">Attached to the
                                letter from Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>
                                to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> dated
                                Dec. 10, 1954, <ref target="#d836">Document 836</ref>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-12-21">21 December 1953</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Japanese Defense Forces</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>This memorandum is in reply to your memorandums of 18 May 1953 and
                                23 May 1953,<note n="2" xml:id="d720fn2">Neither found in Department
                                    of State files.</note> on the above subject, which requested the
                                views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff on the following matters relating
                                to development of Japanese defense forces: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>Japanese force levels which should be established and
                                        maintained.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>Possibility of an early agreement by the Japanese to a
                                        buildup of forces beyond 4 divisions.</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>Estimated schedule in the event such a build-up is
                                        believed probable.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>Data as to the probable annual yen requirements of U.S.
                                        forces in Japan over a 10-year period.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>This memorandum also contains the views of the Joint Chiefs of
                                Staff on a message No. 1415, dated 7 December 1953, from Ambassador
                                    <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName> in Tokyo to the
                                Department of State on this subject.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>With regard to Japanese force levels, the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                                believe that the revised force goals for the Japanese National
                                Safety Agency (<gloss target="#t_JNSA1">JNSA</gloss>), as enumerated
                                in the Appendix hereto, represent the minimum forces necessary for
                                the adequate defense of Japan when U.S. forces have been withdrawn.
                                The revised force goals recommended herein should supersede the
                                previous Japanese force levels indicated in the memorandum for the
                                Secretary of Defense dated 13 December 1951,<note n="3" xml:id="d720fn3">The correct date is Dec. 12, 1951. For text,
                                    see <ref target="frus1951v06p1#pg_1432"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1951, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, Part 1, p. 1432</ref>.</note> subject:
                                “High-level State–Defense Mission on Japanese Defense
                                Forces”.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>, with
                                the concurrence of the Commander in Chief, Far East, (<gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss>), has recommended a U.S.
                                position for negotiations on the build-up of Japanese forces. Based
                                on discussions with Japanese officials, it is the Ambassador’s view
                                that the Japanese are likely to agree to an early build-up of their
                                defense forces, but they are unlikely to deviate substantially from
                                the 5-year program previously proposed by them in Washington, i.e.,
                                a <pb facs="0505" n="1561" xml:id="pg_1561"/> ground force of
                                180,000, a navy of 150,000 tons, and an air force of 1500 planes.
                                The Ambassador believes that these goals represent the most the
                                Japanese Government can attempt at this time. Therefore, he
                                considers the immediate objective in negotiations should be to
                                obtain agreement on a reasonable build-up of forces at once, with
                                the understanding that the schedules proposed represent a minimum
                                phasing and will not reduce the ultimate requirements.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Although the Ambassador has proposed as a negotiating position a
                                ground force of 210,000 by April 1956, he has submitted an
                                alternative proposal which he considers politically more palatable,
                                i.e., a ground force of 180,000 (excluding civilians) by April 1956
                                in exchange for certain commitments on the part of the Japanese
                                Government. Acceptance of this alternative proposal would permit the
                                Ambassador to press for a higher budget for naval and air forces
                                thereby emphasizing the build-up of these forces and tending toward
                                a more balanced force structure.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item><p>Although the Japanese have been informed that the U.S. is
                                    willing to consider supplying destroyers and destroyer escorts
                                    on a loan basis, the Joint Chiefs of Staff are of the opinion
                                    that it would be to the best interests of both the United States
                                    and Japan, if Japan, with appropriate financial assistance,
                                    constructed the majority of the ships for the Coastal Safety
                                    Force. However, in order that the Japanese will have sufficient
                                    experience and training to operate naval units effectively, the
                                    U.S. is willing to provide on a loan basis, the following ships,
                                    to be programmed during the first year of military assistance
                                    (estimated <gloss target="#t_JFY1">JFY</gloss> 54): <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>2 Destroyers (1600 Ton type)</p>
                                        <p>2 Destroyer Escorts (<gloss target="#t_DE1">DE</gloss>)</p>
                                        <p>1 Submarine (<gloss target="#t_SS2">SS</gloss>)</p>
                                        <p>2 Minesweepers (<gloss target="#t_AMS1">AMS</gloss>)</p>
                                        <p>1 Minesweeping Craft (<gloss target="#t_MSB1">MSB</gloss>)</p></quote></p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">in addition, naval air squadrons (Patrol or
                                        <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> attack aircraft) will be
                                    provided, with one squadron programmed in <gloss target="#t_JFY1">JFY</gloss> 54.</p></item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>In the air force build-up proposed by the Ambassador and <gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss>, the number of training
                                aircraft is far in excess of that previously recommended to <gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss> by the Commander, Far East
                                Air Forces (<gloss target="#t_COMFEAF1">COMFEAF</gloss>), but there
                                is no provision for combat aircraft during <gloss target="#t_JFY1">JFY</gloss> 1954. A message from <gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss> has indicated a requirement which makes it
                                essential that combat aircraft be introduced into the program at the
                                earliest practicable stage in the development of the Japanese air
                                force. To achieve the most effective defense program within budget
                                limitations, <gloss target="#t_COMFEAF1">COMFEAF</gloss>’s
                                recommendations should be used as a guide in resumed
                                negotiations.</item>
                            <pb facs="0506" n="1562" xml:id="pg_1562"/>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>The Joint Chiefs of Staff realize that the negotiating position
                                proposed by the Ambassador is only a basis upon which to resume
                                negotiations with a view toward getting a build-up started as soon
                                as possible. Further appraisal of the over-all program will be made
                                as the negotiations proceed and upon receipt of detailed information
                                concerning the proposed build-up schedule covering the entire 5-year
                                period.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>As to the estimated schedules referred to in subparagraph 1 c
                                above the Joint Chiefs of Staff do not consider it possible to
                                predict the schedule of build-up, at this time, to which the
                                Japanese Government might be expected to agree.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>With regard to the probable yen requirements of U.S. forces in
                                Japan, mentioned in subparagraph 1 d above, the Joint Chiefs of
                                Staff do not consider it possible at this time to prepare the data
                                you have requested. This data is contingent upon the phase-out of
                                U.S. forces from Japan which in turn depends upon (1) the adequate
                                buildup of Japanese forces, and, (2) the final U.S. policies and
                                objectives which may be adopted with respect to Korea affecting the
                                deployment of U.S. forces in the Far East.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>In light of the foregoing it is recommended: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>That the revised force goals for the Japanese National
                                        Safety Agency (<gloss target="#t_JNSA1">JNSA</gloss>) as
                                        enumerated in the Appendix hereto be approved for planning
                                        purposes.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>That, subject to the comments in paragraphs 5, 6, 7, and
                                        8, above, the Department of Defense concur with Ambassador
                                            <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>’s
                                        proposal for resumption of negotiations with the
                                        Japanese.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>Upon your concurrence with the foregoing recommendations, <gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss> will be informed
                                accordingly.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>For the Joint Chiefs of Staff:<lb/><signed><persName corresp="#p_CARB1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Robt</hi>. B. <hi rend="smallcaps">Carney</hi></persName></signed><lb/><hi rend="italic">Chief of Naval Operations</hi></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">[Enclosure]</note>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Appendix</hi></head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Revised Force Goals for the
                                    Japanese National Safety Agency</hi> (<gloss target="#t_JNSA1">JNSA</gloss>)</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">i. revised force goals for the
                                    japanese national safety force</hi> (<gloss target="#t_JNSF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">jnsf</hi></gloss>)</p>
                            <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Size</hi>. Under this Revised Final Force Plan
                                the Japanese National Safety Force would be expanded to a balanced
                                fifteen-division ground defense force of 348,000. Divisional
                                organization will be <pb facs="0507" n="1563" xml:id="pg_1563"/> of
                                a reduced type U.S. Army infantry division of 12,022 men each. The
                                Plan also includes a Reserve Force, a Labor Service Corps, and
                                provisions for a Civil Defense Organization. It does not
                                substantially increase the requirements for personnel or major items
                                of equipment over the presently approved 10-division plan.</p>
                            <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Composition</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">The Active Force</hi> (348,000) <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>National Headquarters</p>
                                        <p>Field Army Headquarters</p>
                                        <p>15 divisions organized into 5 Army Corps</p>
                                        <p>19 <gloss target="#t_AAA1">AAA</gloss>
                                            <gloss target="#t_AW1">AW</gloss> Battalions</p>
                                        <p>21 <gloss target="#t_AAA1">AAA</gloss> Gun Battalions</p>
                                        <p>Other combat battalions (field artillery, tank, engineer,
                                            and chemical) and technical service units as required
                                            for support.</p></quote></item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">The Reserve Force</hi> (57,400
                                        combat—15,456 service)</p>
                                    <p>The formation of an initial reserve of civilian component
                                        type combat and service units will add flexibility to
                                        emergency mobilization plans. Reserve combat units and guard
                                        units could augment the active force and assume the
                                        responsibility of internal security. The formation of these
                                        reserve units decreases the requirements for many types of
                                        active units which would otherwise be on a “standby” status.
                                        The reserve will include Combat Prefectural Guard units and
                                        a mobilization reserve to supplement the active and reserve
                                        forces in event of a general emergency.</p></item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Labor Service Corps</hi></p>
                                    <p>A Labor Service Corps is included to provide unskilled labor,
                                        in lieu of military personnel, in periods of emergency. A
                                        small agency in National Headquarters would formulate plans
                                        for the establishment of the Labor Service Corps during
                                        periods of emergency only.</p></item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Civil Defense Organization</hi></p>
                                    <p>In view of the vulnerability of Japan to air attacks a civil
                                        defense organization is essential. This organization is
                                        included in the revised Final Force Plan in order to present
                                        complete defense organizational requirements to the Japanese
                                        Government. It should be handled as a separate matter from
                                        final military force planning.</p></item>
                            </list>
                            <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Disposition of Active Force (<gloss target="#t_JNSF1">JNSF</gloss>)</hi></p>
                            <table cols="3" rows="6">
                                <row>
                                    <cell>a.</cell>
                                    <cell>Hokkaido Corps</cell>
                                    <cell>3 Inf Divs</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>b.</cell>
                                    <cell>Honshu</cell>
                                    <cell/>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>(1) North Corps</cell>
                                    <cell>3 Inf Divs</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>(2) Central Corps</cell>
                                    <cell>4 Inf Divs</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>(3) South Corps</cell>
                                    <cell>3 Inf Divs</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>c.</cell>
                                    <cell>Kyushu Corps</cell>
                                    <cell>2 Inf Divs</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">ii. revised force goals for the
                                    japanese national coastal safety force</hi> (<gloss target="#t_JCSF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">jcsf</hi></gloss>)</p>
                            <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Size and Composition</hi>. The planned ultimate
                                composition (Revised Force Goals) of the Japanese Coastal Safety
                                Force is as follows, <pb facs="0508" n="1564" xml:id="pg_1564"/>
                                except that inclusion of carriers and cruisers will not be
                                recommended to the Japanese Government at this time: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>4 light carriers (defensive type) with supporting
                                        squadrons</p>
                                    <p>3 antiaircraft cruiser types</p>
                                    <p>30 destroyer types<note n="*" xml:id="d720fn4">Number of each
                                            may vary between types. [Footnote in the source
                                            text.]</note></p>
                                    <p>75 destroyer escort types<note n="*" xml:id="d720fn5">Number
                                            of each may vary between types. [Footnote in the source
                                            text.]</note></p>
                                    <p>50 large minesweepers <list>
                                            <item>—large number of small <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss>, minesweeping and patrol craft</item>
                                            <item>—small number of coastal submarines for training
                                                purposes</item>
                                        </list></p>
                                    <p>4 minelayers</p>
                                    <p>2 <gloss target="#t_LST1">LST</gloss>s</p>
                                    <p>3 Supply Mother Ships</p>
                                    <p>10 patrol squadrons (<gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss>)
                                        (U.E.12a/c)</p>
                                    <p>18 patrol frigates (already on hand)</p>
                                    <p>50 large support landing ships (already on
                                hand)</p></quote></p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">iii. revised force goals for the
                                    japanese air safety force</hi> (<gloss target="#t_JASF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">jasf</hi></gloss>)</p>
                            <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Size and Composition</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The planned ultimate composition (Revised Force Goals) of the
                                Japanese Air Safety Force is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>A Japanese Air Force headquarters</p>
                                    <p>Pilot and Technical Training Schools</p>
                                    <p>9 Fighter-interceptor squadrons (U.E.25a/c)</p>
                                    <p>6 Interceptor (all-weather) squadrons (U.E.25a/c)</p>
                                    <p>6 Fighter-bomber squadrons (U.E.25a/c)</p>
                                    <p>6 Light-bomber squadrons (Jet) (U.E.16a/c)</p>
                                    <p>3 Tactical reconnaissance squadrons (U.E.18a/c)</p>
                                    <p>6 Transport Squadrons (Medium) (U.E.16a/c)</p>
                                    <p>1 Fixed radar surveillance and control system covering the
                                        home islands (3 <gloss target="#t_ADCC1">ADCC</gloss>,<note n="†" xml:id="d720fn6">Air Defense Control Center.
                                            [Footnote in the source text.]</note> 6 <gloss target="#t_GCI1">GCI</gloss>,<note n="‡" xml:id="d720fn7">Ground Control Intercept. [Footnote in
                                            the source text.]</note> 17 <gloss target="#t_EWGCI1">EW/GCI</gloss>)<note n="§" xml:id="d720fn8">Early
                                            Warning Ground Control Intercept. [Footnote in the
                                            source text.]</note></p>
                                    <p>Essential Service and Support Units (as
                                required)</p></quote></p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>