<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-02-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="734" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d734">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">794.5/2–1554</note>
                        <head>No. 734<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief
                                of the Japanese Finance and Trade Section, Office of Northeast Asian
                                Affairs (<persName>Cronk</persName>)</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-02-15">February
                                    15, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Discussions of Japanese Rearmament with other governments.</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>Participants:</head>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>J.L. Allen</persName>, Second Secretary, Australian
                                Embassy</item>
                            <item>Mr. [<persName>Michael Joy</persName>, First Secretary, British
                                Embassy</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Peter Campbell</persName>, First Secretary, Canadian
                                Embassy</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Hunter Wade</persName>, First Secretary, New Zealand
                                Embassy</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">Robert J.G.
                                    McClurkin</persName>—<gloss target="#t_NA1">NA</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Hamilton</persName>—<gloss target="#t_BNA1">BNA</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mrs. <persName>Alice L. Dunning</persName>—<gloss target="#t_NA1">NA</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Edwin M. Cronk</persName>—<gloss target="#t_NA1">NA</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName> had asked the above
                            representatives of the British, Canadian, Australian and New Zealand
                            Embassies to come in for the purpose of reviewing the Japanese defense
                            program. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName>
                            summarized recent developments and future plans with respect to the
                            buildup of Japan’s defense forces using as reference the information
                            contained in the memorandum attached hereto. (The attached memorandum
                            had been previously cleared by the State–Defense Military Information
                            Control Committee by Mr. [<persName>Michael H.] Styles</persName>,
                                <gloss target="#t_MC1">MC</gloss>, for release, on a classified
                            basis, to the above mentioned governments. Copies of the table attached
                            to the memorandum were distributed but the memorandum itself was not
                                released.)<note n="1" xml:id="d734fn1">Neither document found
                                attached.</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0545" n="1601" xml:id="pg_1601"/>
                        <p>The New Zealand and Australian representatives indicated a particular
                            interest in the development of Japan’s naval forces and asked if any
                            carriers or cruisers would be provided the Japanese. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName> replied that the United
                            States had no plans at this point of providing Japan with any naval
                            vessels larger than a destroyer. He mentioned that in addition to naval
                            vessels, consideration was being given to the possibility of providing
                            an auxiliary supply vessel. He also stated that the Japanese had
                            requested two coastal submarines for use in anti-submarine training and
                            that this request was under consideration. The New Zealand and
                            Australian representatives indicated that this might cause their
                            governments some concern and urged that information on this be handled
                            carefully. They requested specific information regarding the size and
                            range of the submarines which might be provided which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName> agreed to make available
                            when definite plans had been developed. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName> stressed the classified nature of information
                            which had been provided.<note n="2" xml:id="d734fn2">In a memorandum of
                                a conversation held with <persName>J.L. Allen</persName> on Feb. 23,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName> quoted an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> handed him by
                                    <persName>Allen</persName>, which stated the Australian
                                Government’s view that submarines should not be given or lent to
                                Japan even for training in antisubmarine warfare. “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName> said that there was no
                                likelihood that a submarine would be transferred to the Japanese in
                                the near future in any event, and that perhaps something could be
                                worked out to avoid any possibility that this issue would be
                                injected into the Australian election campaign.” (U/<gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> files, lot 57 D 567)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>