<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-02-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-02-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="739" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d739">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">794.5/2–2454</note>
                        <head>No. 739<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Director of the
                                Office of Northeast Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MRJG1" type="from">McClurkin</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of
                                State for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWS1" type="to">Robertson</persName>)</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-02-24">February 24, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Meeting by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName> with Officers of the Department of
                                Defense</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>On February 18 Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>
                            addressed a large group of military and civilian personnel in the
                            Department of Defense who are interested in Japanese affairs. The
                            following general officers were present: Lt. Gen. <persName>Walter
                                Weible</persName>, Deputy Chief of Staff (Army); Lt. Gen.
                                <persName>G.H. Decker</persName>, Comptroller (Army); Maj. Gen.
                                <persName>A.P. Fox</persName>, Office of <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>; Maj. Gen. <persName>R.F. Tate</persName>, Office of
                                <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>; Rear Adm. <persName>W.F.
                                Boone</persName>, Office of <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>;
                            Brig. Gen. <persName>B. Hamlett</persName>, Office Chief of Staff
                            (Army); Brig. Gen. <persName>J.M. Willems</persName>, <gloss target="#t_G21">G–2</gloss>; Brig. Gen. <persName>Mark
                                McClure</persName>, <gloss target="#t_G21">G–2</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName> described the
                            current status of Japanese defense plans and the difficulties which they
                            face. He stressed the fact that the present Government had crossed a
                            major stream in the presentation of current defense plans to the
                            Japanese Diet and in recommending a change, in the assigned mission of
                            the Japanese forces. He pointed out that while the steps which the
                            Japanese were taking were slower than we would like, and there was every
                            reason to maintain a continued pressure upon the Japanese in private
                            interviews with Japanese leaders, it could he adverse to our interests
                            publicly to criticize the pace of their rearmament.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>’s talk was well
                            received and should prove useful in our continuing dealings with the
                            Department of Defense.</p>
                        <p>In a conversation with the general officers enumerated above following
                            his talk, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>
                            pointed out that any increase in the United States forces in Japan above
                            the 2 1/3 divisions now there could create serious political
                            difficulties.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>