<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 753The Secretary of State to the Embassy in Japan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v14p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d753</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">753</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-04-08T12:38:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-04-08T12:38:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recgAskQzr2OrtpaG" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade control</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-04-08T12:38:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-04-08T12:38:00-05:00" n="753"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d753">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">493.949/4–154: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 753<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Japan</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d753fn1">Drafted in <gloss target="#t_EDS1">EDS</gloss> and
                            <gloss target="#t_NA1">NA</gloss> and cleared in <gloss target="#t_CA1"
                            >CA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, the Foreign Operations
                        Administration, the Departments of Defense and Commerce, and, in substance
                        by the Department of the Treasury. Repeated for information to London and to
                        Paris marked <gloss target="#t_Topol1">Topol</gloss>; airpouched to Hong
                        Kong.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-04-08T12:38:00-05:00"
                            >April 8, 1954—12:38 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2229. <gloss target="#t_EXCON1">Excon</gloss>. Your 2410<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d753fn2">Dated Apr. 3; in this telegram the Embassy reported in part
                        that it had received from the Japanese Government a note accompanied by a
                        list of 383 items which Japan embargoed from its China trade, but which were
                        not on the China Committee embargo list. “Of these, Japanese Government
                        proposes 127 items be removed from bilateral understanding.… Note expresses
                        appreciation of previous lifting ban on over 100 items, but observes
                        proposed step can be taken without jeopardizing objectives security export
                        controls.” (493.949/4–354)</note> and 2378.<note n="3" xml:id="d753fn3">
                        <ref target="#d751">Document 751</ref>.</note> Embassy requested inform
                    Japanese that US prepared cancel bilateral on basis assurances providing gradual
                    reduction and designed prevent serious harmful effect Geneva Conference.
                    Specific assurances would cover following: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Japan would agree relax controls at rate no faster than 30 items per
                            week against list 383 items representing extent Japanese study indicates
                            controls presently above multilateral level. Initial releases to be
                            taken from list 127 mentioned your 2410. However release any US IA, IIB
                            or <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> items would be withheld until after
                            May 1 permit time review here whether covered whole or part by existing
                            multilateral embargo. Re such items US would reserve right request
                            clarification <gloss target="#t_CHINCOM1">CHINCOM</gloss> where
                            difference view found re existing multilateral coverage and might also
                            wish propose for adoption <gloss target="#t_CHINCOM1">CHINCOM</gloss>
                            few additional items which clearly related existing embargo.</item>
                        <pb facs="0575" n="1631" xml:id="pg_1631"/>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Japan would agree limit public announcements to routine statements
                            preferably by <gloss target="#t_MITI1">MITI</gloss> officials at time
                            removal of items to general effect that Japanese Government is engaged
                            intensive reexamination items on which Japanese controls are higher than
                            multilateral level and intends release from control at accelerated rate
                            those items which Japanese do not consider to be of strategic
                            importance.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Purpose US proposal is (a) enable Japan meet political pressures for reduction
                    controls to multilateral level by accelerating rate of decontrol but (b) avoid
                    any sudden removal large bloc of items from control which would imply that
                    substantial relaxation China controls underway. While necessary for Japanese
                    Government indicate that another step has been taken in direction bringing
                    Japanese controls into conformity with multilateral controls, highly desirable
                    no attempt be made by Japanese Government dramatize accelerated removal of items
                    from embargo as new policy or as indication Japan no longer recognizes need for
                    multilateral cooperation in maintenance controls on China trade. Our hope is
                    that Japanese handling of decontrol would so closely resemble disciplined
                    decontrol procedure followed in past six months that could not be regarded by
                    Chinese Communists as evidence inability countries of free world continue
                    maintain high level controls on strategic trade with China.</p>
                <p>Department defers to Embassy judgment that it is unwise to condition proposal for
                    cancellation bilateral upon Japanese undertakings support US other trade control
                    matters. But US proposals will demonstrate willingness US to cooperate with
                    Japan on realignment Japanese controls and will enable Japanese ease political
                    pressures for reduction Japanese controls to multilateral level. Consequently
                    Embassy requested coincident with presentation US proposal on bilateral to seek
                    Japanese cooperation in (1) withholding request to <gloss target="#t_CHINCOM1"
                        >CHINCOM</gloss> for exception on GI sheets and automotive parts and (2)
                    supporting maintenance <gloss target="#t_CHINCOM1">CHINCOM</gloss> controls
                    during Geneva conference.</p>
                <p>Embassy should caution Japanese that in event Far East situation deteriorates US
                    will depend on Japan and other free world countries cooperate imposition tighter
                    controls on trade with Communist China.<note n="4" xml:id="d753fn4">Documents in
                        file 493.949 for 1954 indicate that gradual release of items from Japan’s
                        separate China trade embargo list continued through spring and summer
                        1954.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
