<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 781U.S. Summary Minutes of the Third Meeting of United States Republic of
                    Korea Talks, Washington, July 29, 1954, 2:30 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v14p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d781</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">781</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-29T13:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-29T13:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7MjCJlGL6L85Od" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Joint statement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec1ldfvh0EmC9PyC" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="rec3U9TKkW5rS0s3i" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="law-of-the-sea" subject="freedom-of-navigation" lcsh-match="no_match">Freedom of the seas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-29T13:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-29T13:30:00-05:00" n="781"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d781">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation, lot 64 D
                    199</note>
                <head>No. 781<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">U.S. Summary Minutes of the Third Meeting of United States
                        Republic of Korea Talks, Washington, July 29, 1954, 2:30 p.m.</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d781fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1"
                            >McClurkin</persName> on Aug. 2. Participants listed below include:
                        (United States) <persName>C. Tyler Wood</persName>, Economic Coordinator in
                        Korea, <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss>; (<gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                            >ROK</gloss>) <persName>Ben C. Limb</persName>, Ambassador at Large and
                            <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Observer at the United Nations; Adm.
                            <persName>Sohn Won II</persName>, Minister of Defense; and
                            <persName>Paik Tu Chin</persName>, Economic Coordinator. For additional
                        documentation on President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s
                        visit to the United States in late July 1954, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v15p2#pg_1829">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xv</hi>,
                            Part 2, pp. 1829</ref> ff.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-29T14:30:00-04:00"
                            >July 29, 1954, 2:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName>Briggs</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DEF1">Drumright</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRJG1">McClurkin</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Secretary of Defense</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1">General Hull</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Vice Admiral <persName>Davis</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Wood</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Hagerty</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Republic of Korea</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName>Yang</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName>Limb</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Admiral <persName>Sohn Won-il</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName>Paek Tu-chin</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName>Choe Sun-chu</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>General <persName>Chong Il-kwon</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>General <persName>Kim Chong-yol</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>General <persName>Choe Tok-sin</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of a joint statement, a draft of agreed minutes, and
                    President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s plan for the unification
                    of Korea. For this portion of the minutes, see <ref
                        target="frus1952-54v15p2#pg_1849">volume XV, Part 2, page 1849</ref>.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">3. Relations between the Republic of Korea and Japan</hi>
                </p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> said that he understood the
                    United States representatives wished to talk about this question.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> said that there are
                    clearly a number of difficult problems to be solved but he believes Japan will
                    make a real effort to put relations with Korea on a fair and honorable basis.
                    Our <pb facs="0632" n="1688" xml:id="pg_1688"/> working hypothesis in the Far
                    East must be that Japan will become a reliable member of the Free World.
                    Otherwise the whole balance in the Pacific could turn against us.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> said that it is correct for
                    the United States to desire peaceful relations between Japan and Korea, but he
                    hoped the United States Government would try to find out which party is right
                    and which wrong. In a quarrel one party is wrong.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> suggested that perhaps
                    both might be wrong to some extent.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> rehearsed a number of his
                    long-standing complaints against Japan. He said that Japan claims 85% of Korean
                    property, and that Japan is insisting on regarding Korea as one of its former
                    possessions despite the Peace Treaty.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> said that he was not
                    himself aware of any claim by Japan to 85% of the territory of Korea. Clearly
                    that would be an outrageous violation of the Peace Treaty.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName>Yang</persName> reported some of Kubota’s remarks of October
                    16, 1953<note n="2" xml:id="d781fn2">See <ref target="#d689fn6">footnote 6,
                            Document 689</ref>.</note> in the course of negotiations between the
                    Koreans and the Japanese.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> said that the United
                    States sent its men through the United Nations to protect Korea. He could not
                    conceive how we can be accused of trying to make Koreans bow their necks to the
                    Japanese. A clause in the Japanese Peace Treaty which Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> negotiated specifically protects Korea.
                    We will talk to the Japanese just as frankly as we do to the Koreans. He asked
                    whether President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> would like us to
                    begin an exploration of the whole tangled problem, perhaps leading to eventual
                    adjudication. He thought we could produce people who would be completely fair.
                    He concluded by referring to the desirability of good relations among Japan,
                    Korea and Formosa.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> then brought up the question
                    of the fishing line and detailed the history of this question, beginning with
                    the <persName corresp="#p_MDII1">MacArthur</persName> Line. He said it is
                    necessary to have such a line if Korea is to live in peace with Japan.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> said that this is a very
                    difficult question. In a situation where there is the tension which exists
                    between Korea and Japan something of the sort would seem to make sense. On the
                    other hand, there is the problem of the traditional United States position with
                    respect to freedom of the seas. Perhaps it would be possible to work out a sort
                    of self-denying ordinance in which the Japanese would agree that they would not
                    send any fishing boats into certain areas, but without doing violation to the
                    general principle of freedom of access to the high seas.</p>
                <pb facs="0633" n="1689" xml:id="pg_1689"/>
                <p>He then went on to ask whether the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> had any
                    concrete suggestion. He said that we would be glad to do anything we can to
                    help. He wondered whether the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> would like to
                    have some form of arbitration or to set up a panel of some kind or to refer the
                    question to the World Court. Another possibility would be that we provide an
                    individual to observe and to mediate if the Japanese also agreed to have such a
                    person.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> said that the United States
                    must tell <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> first whether we believe the
                    Koreans are right or the Japanese are right.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> said that we cannot
                    give such answers now because we have not explored these questions sufficiently.
                    However, we will try to find out where justice lies.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName>Yang</persName> referred to his discussions in Washington
                    with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_IS1">Iguchi</persName> and emphasized that
                    the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> is willing and anxious to settle these
                    questions.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> read the statement which
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_IS1">Iguchi</persName> had proposed the
                    Japanese make publicly.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName>Yang</persName> said that if the Japanese will consent to
                    make that statement publicly, the Koreans would resume negotiations.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> said that if we are
                    going to support our friends we cannot have them fighting each other. We have a
                    great deal of sympathy for the Korean position with respect to Japan, but we do
                    feel that friendly relations between the two countries are essential to the
                    security of the whole area. If the Koreans and the Japanese can improve their
                    relations by direct negotiations, so much the better. If it is necessary for us
                    to participate, we will be glad to do it.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> emphasized that the
                    Koreans should not think that United States sympathies lie with Japan rather
                    than with Korea, because they do not. We have not forgotten that Japan was our
                    enemy, whereas Korea has been our ally. What has been said by the United States
                    representatives in this discussion is the policy of the United States Government
                    regardless of any isolated remarks by individuals on any other occasion. He
                    added that he believes the Japanese have made a serious mistake by clinging to a
                    rather tenuous legal claim in order to attempt to buttress their bargaining
                    position. We can and will exert influence on the Japanese to deal with these
                    problems in a statesmanlike way instead of on the basis of sharp trading.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
