<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-12-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="116" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                    <head>116. Memorandum of Discussion at the 390th <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d116fn1">Source:
                            Agenda item 1: Measures To Carry Out the Concept of Shelter. Top Secret;
                            Eyes Only. Extracts—5 pp. Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Records.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-12-11">December 11,
                            1958</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <pb facs="d116-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d116-1"/>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Discussion at the 390th Meeting of the National Security Council
                            Thursday, December 11, 1958</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Present at the 390th Meeting of the National Security Council were the
                        President of the United States presiding, the Vice President of the United
                        States; the Acting Secretary of State; the Acting Secretary of Defense; the
                        Director, Office of Civil and Defense Mobilization. Also present were the
                        Secretary of the Treasury and the Director, Bureau of the Budget. Also
                        present and participating in Council action on Item 1 were the Attorney
                        General; the Chairman, Atomic Energy Commission; the Chairman, Council of
                        Economic Advisers; the Special Assistants to the President for Science and
                        Technology and for Public Works Planning. Also attending were the Acting
                        Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff; the Director of Central Intelligence; the
                        Acting Director, U.S. Information Agency; the Director, International
                        Cooperation Administration; the Under Secretary of State for Economic
                        Affairs; Assistant Secretaries of State <persName corresp="#p_SGC_1">Gerard
                            C. Smith</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MLT_1">Livingston T.
                            Merchant</persName>; the Deputy Director, Office of Civil and Defense
                        Mobilization, The Assistant to the President; the Deputy Assistant to the
                        President for Congressional Affairs; the Special Assistants to the President
                        for National Security Affairs and for Security Operations Coordination; the
                        White House Staff Secretary; the Assistant White House Staff Secretary; the
                        Naval Aide to the President; the Executive Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>; and the Deputy Executive, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>There follows a summary of the discussion at the meeting and the main points
                        taken.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">1. MEASURES TO CARRY OUT THE CONCEPT OF SHELTER</p>
                    <p>(<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5807; <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5807/1; <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Actions Nos.
                        1882 and 1948–<hi rend="italic">b</hi>; Memos for <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> from Executive Secretary, same subject, dated November 5
                        and 18, and December 4, 1958)</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG_1">Gordon Gray</persName> explained briefly the
                        nature of this item and called on Governor Hoegh to summarize the main
                        points in his report. (A copy of Mr. Gray’s briefing note is filed in the
                        Minutes of the Meeting.)</p>
                    <pb facs="d116-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d116-2"/>
                    <p>After describing in general the status of measures to carry out the concept
                        of shelter, Governor Hoegh went to the main point which was his specific
                        recommendation for one additional measure to carry out <pb facs="0498" n="393" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_393"/> the concept of shelter, namely,
                        to provide fall-out shelters by modification of existing Federal buildings
                        on a selected basis. Governor Hoegh’s recommendation envisaged a cost of
                        this procedure of approximately $5 million during the next fiscal year.</p>
                    <p>After Governor Hoegh had explained the reasons for making this recommendation
                        and the great need for a Federal example, he pointed out that the Joint
                        Chiefs of Staff had signified their approval of the recommendation.
                            <persName corresp="#p_TGMD_1">General Taylor</persName>, the Acting
                        Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff, indicated that the approval of the Joint
                        Chiefs was to be interpreted in terms of the principle but not the dollar
                        costs.</p>
                    <p>The President referred to the fact that in the course of his remarks earlier,
                        Governor Hoegh had referred to an individual who had built an extremely
                        confortable, commodious, and safe blast shelter at a cost of only $15,000.
                        The President inquired how deep this shelter was and how it was possible to
                        build one for as little as $15,000. Governor Hoegh replied by pointing out
                        that the shelter in question was built only to withstand blast pressures of
                        30 psi. although it did qualify as a blast shelter.</p>
                    <p>The President said that the reason he had asked this question was that he
                        himself had long been undecided as to whether or not it would be a good
                        thing for the President to build such a shelter and thus set an example to
                        other people or whether if he went ahead and built such a shelter, the
                        effect would be to scare other people to death. But all his calculations had
                        added up to a cost much larger than $15,000. Governor Hoegh said he would
                        undertake to get plans for the $15,000 shelter to which he had referred for
                        the President and the President said that he would very much like to see
                        them.</p>
                    <p>The President then asked if there were any other comments. The Director,
                        Bureau of the Budget said that he would like to make four points regarding
                        Governor Hoegh’s recommendation for a $5 million appropriation to provide
                        fall-out shelters on a selected basis in existing Federal buildings. The
                        first point, said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMH_1">Stans</persName>, was to
                        warn that the proposed $5 million program might end up by becoming only the
                        down payment on a much larger program. He reminded the members of the
                        Council of an earlier $90 million estimate for providing fall-out shelter in
                        U.S. post offices over the country. He therefore doubted whether this
                        program would stop with an expenditure of $5 million.</p>
                    <pb facs="d116-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d116-3"/>
                    <p>Secondly, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMH_1">Stans</persName> said, he wished
                        to raise a question as to timing. He pointed out that Governor Hoegh had
                        already referred to research prototype programs which were being undertaken
                        in order to determine the best type of shelter. Five million dollars had
                        been allocated to this program. Would it not be premature to proceed to
                        build shelters in existing Federal buildings until the results of the
                        research and prototype programs had come in?</p>
                    <p>Mr. Stans’ third point related to the nation-wide survey now underway to
                        determine what existed by way of shelter in existing buildings. <pb facs="0499" n="394" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_394"/> Should not this
                        survey likewise be completed and analyzed before Governor Hoegh’s new
                        recommendation was adopted?</p>
                    <p>His further and final point, said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMH_1">Stans</persName>, was to suggest that some of the $5 million which had
                        been allocated to the above-mentioned prototype shelter program might also
                        be used to provide for shelters in existing Federal buildings and thus serve
                        a dual purpose of building prototypes and setting an example of shelters in
                        Federal buildings. Accordingly, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMH_1">Stans</persName> recommended that action on Governor Hoegh’s
                        recommendation be deferred for six months or a year until the results of the
                        various surveys had come in.</p>
                    <p>The President expressed relief at being confronted with a figure of $5
                        million which was low in comparison with the estimated costs of some of the
                        shelter programs which the Council had considered in the past. He added that
                        he did not wish to argue the matter of the $5 million for Governor Hoegh’s
                        recommendation and said that the two or three officials most concerned
                        should meet with him in the next few days and decide how to act on this
                        recommendation. On the other hand, he did not believe that those in charge
                        of the shelter program should cease in their efforts to determine what it is
                        best for the country to do in this field. We are, of course, now discounting
                        the likelihood of a worldwide holocaust as a result of nuclear war.
                        Nevertheless, we are also anxious to give our people a feeling of confidence
                        so we were on a kind of knife edge between providing some degree of
                        confidence through the medium of a shelter program while at the same time
                        not scaring our citizens to death by too elaborate a program. It was not,
                        said the President, that he felt he knew exactly what to do about it and he
                        therefore wanted to ponder the problem before adding anything more.</p>
                    <p>The President also commented on the fact that we were trying to prevent the
                        General Services Administration from building any more new Federal
                        buildings.</p>
                    <p>Governor Hoegh agreed that this latter statement was correct and explained
                        that it was because we were unlikely to have examples of shelters in newly
                        built Federal buildings that made it seem important to him for the Federal
                        Government to set an example through <pb facs="d116-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d116-4"/> the means of providing shelter in
                        modified existing Federal buildings.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Anderson expressed the opinion that it might be wise to select and
                        concentrate on one example of shelter in an existing Federal building. We
                        would thus be doing something by way of setting an example for the people of
                        the U.S. and would also in the course of so doing learn what is the best
                        kind of shelter to build. Governor Hoegh replied to Secretary Anderson that
                        the <gloss target="#t_OCDM_1">OCDM</gloss> believed that we already knew
                        pretty well what was needed in the way of building fall-out shelters.</p>
                    <p>The President concluded the discussion by stating that we should wait a day
                        or two and then make our decision.</p>
                    <pb facs="0500" n="395" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_395"/>
                    <p>The National Security Council: <list>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Noted and discussed the report on the subject by the Director,
                                Office of Civil and Defense Mobilization, contained in the
                                enclosures to the reference memoranda of November 5 and 18; in the
                                light of the views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff thereon, transmitted
                                by the reference memorandum of December 4, 1958, and the views of
                                the Director, Bureau of the Budget as presented orally at the
                                meeting.</item>
                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Noted the President’s statement deferring action for a short
                                period on the recommendations presented in <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                                above, pending further consideration of these recommendations by the
                                President and the other officials most directly concerned.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>[Omitted here is the remainder of the memorandum.]</p>
                    <pb facs="d116-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d116-5"/>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_GSE_1"><hi rend="strong">S. Everett
                                Gleason</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>