<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>290. Letter From Stassen to Eisenhower to Eisenhower</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v03mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d290</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">290</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-02-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-02-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="290"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d290">
                <head>290. Letter From <persName corresp="#p_SHE_2">Stassen</persName> to
                        Eisenhower<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d290fn1">Source: Letter of
                        resignation. No classification marking. 1 p. Eisenhower Library, Whitman
                        File, Administration Series, Stassen, Harold E., 1957.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1958-02-14">February 14, 1958</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. President:</salute>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d290-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d290-1"/>
                <p>On March 19, 1955 you requested that I make the studies and submit the
                    recommendations for the policies of the United States in the <pb facs="1341"
                        n="1236" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1236"/> field of control and regulation
                    of armaments, for consideration by you and by the National Security Council.</p>
                <p>With the assistance of an able, experienced, and devoted group of men from
                    without and within the government these studies have now been completed and a
                    comprehensive set of recommendations have been made, some of which have already
                    been adopted as the policy of the United States and the others of which are well
                    understood within the Administration. It has been an honor, inspiration, and
                    privilege to work with you in this task.</p>
                <p>It is my highest hope and my fervent prayer that our endeavors in this assignment
                    are confirmed in the years ahead as having made a contribution to a lasting
                    peace with freedom and justice.</p>
                <p>It is my belief that I may now make a larger contribution to your objective of a
                    durable peace, which I share, by reentering the active political field in the
                    Pennsylvania Governorship campaign and by discussing with the people of our
                    country the issues and problems of the worldwide competition of ways of life and
                    the tasks of building peace and safeguarding against war.</p>
                <p>I write with deep appreciation and commendation for your life time of service to
                    our country, with an especial heartfelt thanks for your leadership as President
                    these five years, and with best wishes for the years ahead.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHE_2">
                            <hi rend="strong">Harold E. Stassen</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Special Assistant to the President</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
