<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-05-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="329" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                    <head>329. Memorandum of Conversation between <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">John
                            Foster Dulles</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Strauss</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d329fn1">Source:
                            Suspension of testing and reducing fallout from tests; includes report
                            of Strauss’ General Advisory Committee. Top Secret; Personal and
                            Private. 5 pp. Eisenhower Library, Dulles Papers, General Memoranda of
                            Conversation.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-05-16">May 16,
                            1958</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <pb facs="d329-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d329-1"/>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Admiral Strauss</persName> discussed with me
                        the question of suspension of testing. He indicated that if we thought it
                        politically important it might be possible to announce before the end of the
                        HARDTACK series that future testing would only be done under conditions
                        which would assure no fallout. He gave me in this connection the report of
                        his General Advisory Committee, copy attached.</p>
                    <p>I reported on Lloyd’s desire to extend the period for the testing of the
                        smaller, e.g., less than one megaton, weapons, and my reply to <persName corresp="#p_LJSB_1">Lloyd</persName> that it might be possible to deal
                        first with detection machinery covering the big explosions with a second
                        phase which would be introduced only later dealing with the smaller tests.
                            <persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Admiral Strauss</persName> seemed to think
                        this might be possible.</p>
                    <p>I spoke of the composition of the experts who might function if this was
                        agreed on with the Soviet Union. He suggested that there should be experts
                        designated as jointly agreed between <gloss target="#t_AEC_1">AEC</gloss>,
                        Defense, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJR_1">Killian</persName>. I said I thought we should have a
                        meeting on this subject in the near future and I would try to set it up for
                        next week.</p>
                    <p>I said we were not clear as to whether the Soviets would accept <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> experts or merely wanted U.S. and Soviet
                        experts. <persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Strauss</persName> suggested that in
                        the latter case we might keep in touch with the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> and perhaps have the meetings in London.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Admiral Strauss</persName> spoke very highly of
                        General Norstad’s testimony before the Joint Congressional Committee and
                        suggested I should thank him. <persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Admiral
                            Strauss</persName> thought that the amendments could be put <pb facs="1459" n="1354" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1354"/> through,
                        particularly if we would accept the formula for disapproving agreements with
                        other governments by a concurrent resolution. I asked how it would be if we
                        accepted it by a two-third’s vote. <persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Admiral
                            Strauss</persName> said he thought this might squeeze through and he
                        would talk to Pastore about it if we wished.</p>
                    <p>I recalled my conversation with the President yesterday, in which <pb facs="d329-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d329-2"/> the President
                        indicated that there was doubt whether <persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Admiral
                            Strauss</persName> would continue to serve beyond his present term. The
                        Admiral expounded on his reasons for this. I said that if he should not
                        continue to serve, I felt that his services should be kept available to the
                        Government and that he might, for example, be a consultant in the State
                        Department with a mention to be a sort of “ambassador-at-large” for atomic
                        peace matters, having in this respect the personal rank of ambassador, if
                        and as he went abroad. <persName corresp="#p_SALL_1">Admiral
                            Strauss</persName> indicated that something like this would be agreeable
                        to him.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName><hi rend="strong">JFD</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline"><hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi></note>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-05-07">May 7, 1958</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d329-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d329-3"/>
                        <p>The General Advisory Committee feels that the country is approaching a
                            crisis with regard to the continuation of atomic tests on anything like
                            the present scale. While most of the widely disseminated arguments
                            against further tests are exaggerated and unsound, there is widespread
                            uneasiness in the country over the prospect of constantly increasing
                            radioactive fallout, and even many sincere scientists share this
                            feeling. The statements of the President regarding a possible change of
                            policy after the completion of the present series of tests make it
                            important in our unanimous opinion that a statement should be issued
                            before the end of this series, indicating that hereafter we are willing
                            to restrict tests so that future fallout will be deeply reduced.</p>
                        <p>In our opinion the least concession which the Commission could offer with
                            prospect of winning over a substantial part of the sincere opposition
                            would be to say that hereafter the great bulk of our tests would be
                            carried out underground, with no fallout production, and that tests in
                            the atmosphere would be limited so that the maximum fission yield from
                            the tests of the free nations in any year would not exceed a megaton
                            providing the Russians agreed to a similar limitation. If they did so,
                            and our allies cooperated, we would reduce the addition to potential
                            fallout to between 10 and 20% of the average annual addition resulting
                            from the tests made during the past <pb facs="d329-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d329-4"/> four years. What is more
                            important, in view of the rate of radioactive decay, etc., we would <hi rend="italic">actually not increase the total amount of potential
                                radioactive fallout beyond that prevailing this summer</hi>.</p>
                        <pb facs="1460" n="1355" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1355"/>
                        <p>Admittedly the policing of this agreement would not be easy but an
                            international inspection agency could be created which could determine
                            compliance fairly accurately for each side. And, as a matter of fact,
                            such a policy would penalize us so little that we might continue it for
                            some time even if Russia did not cooperate. Actually, the only tests of
                            any size and importance which now appear could not be carried out
                            underground, would be in connection with the development of anti-missile
                            missiles and some “plowshare” tests.</p>
                        <p>While a majority of the Committee recommends that the first proposal be
                            the one made, it would be possible to go still further if necessary and
                            eliminate all above-ground testing for a period of, say, two years. This
                            would make it much harder to develop anti-missile missiles. It would
                            also prevent tests on some peaceful uses such as “ditch-digger” unless
                            special exceptions were made for them, possibly under international
                            inspection. Such an agreement could not be readily policed, especially
                            on small weapons, and would probably be evaded by the Russians unless
                            there were extensive policing inside Russia, but it would practically
                            eliminate any addition to fallout during the period the agreement was
                            effective.</p>
                        <pb facs="d329-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d329-5"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">The Committee is unanimously agreed that to go any
                                farther than this in the restriction of testing would seriously
                                endanger the security of the United States.</hi></p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>