<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>354. Letter From Kistiakowsky to to Killian</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v03mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d354</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">354</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-08-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-08-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-08-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="354"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                <head>354. Letter From <persName corresp="#p_KGB_1">Kistiakowsky</persName> to
                        <persName corresp="#p_KJR_1">Killian</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d354fn1">Source: Conveys report of
                        Inter-Agency Group on Surprise Attack (not included). Top Secret. 1 p.
                        Eisenhower Library, Records of the Office of the Special Assistant for
                        Science and Technology, Disarmament, Surprise Attack.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1958-08-15">August 15, 1958</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJR_1">Killian</persName>:</salute>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d354-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d354-1"/>
                <p>On July 14 the President sent a memorandum to the Secretary of State suggesting
                    that he join with the Secretary of Defense and yourself in having a careful
                    study made “to further our preparations for possible negotiations on measures to
                    detect and discourage surprise attack.” He further directed that this study
                    should be made after appropriate consultation with other government agencies and
                    officials, that the Working Group actually charged with the study be kept quite
                    small, and that it take “full advantage of the analyses and studies of a
                    technical nature bearing on this matter that are being developed within Dr.
                    Killian’s scientific and technical group.”</p>
                <p>The Inter-Agency Group that was brought together in accordance with these
                    instructions to the Secretary of State herewith presents its report with
                    Appendices I to IV attached. In addition there is included a J.C.S. document
                    referred to in the report and a memorandum from the Chairman of the Watch
                    Committee.</p>
                <pb facs="1515" n="1410" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1410"/>
                <p>The Working Group functioned as individuals, rather than as representatives of
                    their agencies. The Group confined itself to an analysis of the problem and to
                    conclusions about what further studies could most effectively be undertaken in
                    order to prepare adequately in the time available for discussions with the
                    Soviets which may open during the first week in October. The Working Group
                    wishes to stress the fact that it is not making any recommendations in regard to
                    positions which should be taken by the United States in these proposed
                    discussions.</p>
                <p>We do venture, however, to add to the conclusions and comments in our report our
                    conviction that the U.S. Government faces a task of great complexity and
                    difficulty in preparing adequately for the discussions, and that the time
                    available is very short.</p>
                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KGB_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">G.B. Kistiakowsky</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Inter-Agency Group on Surprise Attack</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
