<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-11-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-11-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="390" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d390">
                    <head>390. Telegram Supnu 45 From Geneva<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d390fn1">Source: Summary of first 10 days of nuclear test
                            conference. Confidential; Priority. 2 pp. NARA, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files, 700.5611/11–1158.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-11-11">November 11, 1958,
                                noon</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <pb facs="d390-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d390-1"/>
                    <p>Supnu 45. Following summary appraisal first ten days nuclear weapons test
                        conference.</p>
                    <p>1. Soviet position. Soviet delegation after quickly coming terms on minor
                        points such as private rather than public sessions, and use of
                        “discontinuance” in conference title, immediately assumed rigid position on
                        agenda. Soviet position on agenda has remained consistent that first act of
                        conference be “conclusion” agreement on “cessation” weapons tests. This p.m.
                        informal meeting three delegations proved inconclusive in changing Soviet
                        position. Soviets have indicated wish continue informal discussions on
                        agenda.</p>
                    <p>In spite of Soviet delegation rigidity on agenda Soviet position in meetings
                        has not been one of complete avoidance substance. They have, of course,
                        focused on their own draft treaty, but from time to time have engaged brief
                        discussions on controls. Soviet challenge to U.S. <pb facs="1580" n="1475" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1475"/> and U.K. delegations to table own
                        versions draft agreement obviously calculated further center attention
                        conference on first item of Soviet agenda, i.e., conclusion of agreement.
                        Nevertheless may have had some element of attempt get substantive discussion
                        going without formal adoption agenda. Moreover, generally low key at which
                        Soviets have conducted conversations and meetings, even in face of
                        occasional fairly stern lectures from Western delegations seems indicate <pb facs="d390-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d390-2"/> Soviet delegation
                        interested in prolongation of conference rather than early break, at least
                        prior arrival Kuznetsov, and probably for some time.</p>
                    <p>2. U.K. position. U.K. delegation reflects preoccupation U.K. Government with
                        securing treaty even if this means corners have to be cut. U.S. delegation
                        gets general impression U.K. delegation will from time to time try to act as
                        “honest broker”. However, to date, cooperation of U.K. delegation has been
                        good. Agreed tactics have been carried out with minimum of free-wheeling,
                        and agreed positions maintained. U.K. delegation is noticably silent in
                        defending link with disarmament leaving this to U.S. delegation but we were
                        on notice as to U.K. attitude before we reached Geneva.</p>
                    <p>3. U.S. position. Heaviest Soviet attack has been on “year-by-year” element
                        of U.S. position, link with disarmament, and link with effective performance
                        of controls. We expect attack on “year-by-year” and disarmament link to
                        continue without let-up. One element of U.S. position already made public in
                        President’s August 22 statement has drawn no fire, namely reference to
                        peaceful uses. Agreement by Soviets that conference should deal “weapons
                        tests” and use of same term in Soviet draft treaty have made it possible
                        consider peaceful uses item as means plugging loophole in commitment stop
                        weapons tests rather than exception. Tactical position on this item
                        therefore improved although U.S. delegation has yet to discuss it.</p>
                    <p>4. Conclusions. It is far from clear this stage whether Soviets have come
                        under instructions find best propaganda method avoiding treaty and
                        inspection or whether they are under instructions seek some sort of
                        agreement with minimum of controls and these preferably more or less left to
                        wither on vine after agreement actually signed. Actions Soviet delegation
                        thus far seem indicate only that Russians did not come here looking for
                        immediate break. Agenda deadlock does not give completely accurate picture
                        of conference in which there has been some give and take on matters of
                        substance. Our best guess on outlook is for protracted negotiations with or
                        without adoption final agenda and with outcome very much in doubt.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName><hi rend="strong">Villard</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>