<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-05-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="50" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d50">
                    <head>50. Letter from Cutler to <persName corresp="#p_MNH_1">McElroy</persName>.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d50fn1">Source:
                            President’s comments on <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5810. Top
                            Secret. 2 pp. Eisenhower Library, White House Office Files, Office of
                            the Special Assistant for National Security Affairs.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-05-05">May 5, 1958</date></dateline>
                        <salute>Dear Neil:</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <pb facs="d50-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d50-1"/>
                    <p>The President has just approved the Record of Action of the Meeting of the
                        National Security Council for May 1, relative to <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5810—the revision of Basic National Security Policy—and it
                        is being transmitted to you formally. In addition, I thought it might be
                        useful for me informally to summarize the points made by the President at
                        the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Meeting which affect the Department
                        of Defense (the following statement of which he has checked): <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>He doubted the validity of the concept that “mutual deterrence”
                                provides an umbrella under which “small wars” could be waged in
                                areas such as <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> without
                                expanding into general nuclear war. Accordingly, he thought this
                                concept required further study.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>He asked for further study and debate on the view that it would be
                                possible to withhold involving our massive nuclear retaliatory
                                capability in the event that the Soviet Union attacked in the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> area.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>He thought there were various alternative courses of action, if we
                                were to strengthen our forces and our capabilities for limited war.
                                One alternative might be at the expense of our nuclear deterrent
                                capability. If such an alternative were adopted, we would need a
                                detailed accounting by the Joint Chiefs of Staff as to precisely
                                what would constitute a satisfactory deterrent. Another alternative
                                could involve a massive increase in resources allocated to defense.
                                If such a course were adopted, it would be necessary to study what
                                methods might be found <pb facs="0293" n="188" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_188"/> to maintain much greater forces, without
                                resorting to a controlled society or becoming a garrison
                                state.</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>He thought there should be provided to the National Security
                                Council more definitive information as to the exact size of the
                                deterrent forces which the U.S. requires in this calendar year and
                                will require over the next two or three calendar years.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>As you will see from the Record of Action, we have included in <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5810/1 the exact language for pars. 13 and
                        14 of the existing basic policy (<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                        5707/8) without change.</p>
                    <pb facs="d50-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d50-2"/>
                    <p>You will note in the approved Record of Action that the President revised the
                        June 2 date for receiving from the Department of Defense (perhaps in the
                        form of a limited-distribution-supplement) recommendations for any revision
                        of the military strategy outlined in <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                        5810/1, after Defense shall have given further consideration in the light of
                        the Council discussion at the May 1 Meeting. The President has authorized an
                        extension of this date to June 16, because he wants these important matters
                        brought up for further discussion and final approval, while the significant
                        issues raised are still fresh in our minds, without there being requested
                        any further postponement.</p>
                    <p>Accordingly, he has approved a Council Meeting on June 26 to hear the Defense
                        recommendation. This schedule will permit advance circulation of the Defense
                        recommendation due June 16 (on such limited basis as may be deemed
                        necessary) to Council Members, in plenty of time to be fully prepared for
                        the Council Meeting on June 26.</p>
                    <p>It would obviously be very desirable to receive the joint study on limited
                        war capabilities pursuant to <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Action No.
                        1881 on or before June 16, so that its consideration could be coordinated
                        with the above Defense recommendations.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CR_1"><hi rend="strong">Robert
                                Cutler</hi></persName>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Special Assistant to the President</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>cc: The Deputy Secretary of Defense</p>
                        <p>The Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff</p>
                        <p>The Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security Affairs</p>
                        <p>The Special Assistant to <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> for
                            National Security Council Affairs</p>
                        <p>Lay</p>
                        <p>Asst. Sec. of Def (Sprague)</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>