<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-05-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-05-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="51" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                    <head>51. Letter from <persName corresp="#p_MNH_1">McElroy</persName> to
                            Eisenhower.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d51fn1">Source: Transmits
                            report on military reconnaissance satellite program. Secret. 2 pp.
                            Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, DDE Diaries.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-05-07">May 7, 1958</date></dateline>
                        <salute>Dear Mr. President:</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <pb facs="d51-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d51-1"/>
                    <p>I am forwarding herewith the first quarterly report of progress in the
                        Military Reconnaissance Satellite Program undertaken by the Advanced
                        Research Projects Agency, Department of Defense.</p>
                    <p>The Military Reconnaissance Satellite Program is the initial satellite
                        program (other than VANGUARD and JUPITER C) which I have this far
                        determined, in accordance with National Security Council Action No. 1846,
                        “to have objectives having key political, scientific, psychological or
                        military import.”</p>
                    <p>This initial report covers historical background and program plans for the
                        development of Weapons System 117L which consists of the satellite vehicle,
                        its information sensing, storage and transmission devices, and the ground
                        receiving equipment and facilities. A financial plan for this project
                        through Fiscal Year 1959 is also included.</p>
                    <p>Weapons System 117L is the culmination of extensive research and
                        investigation since 1946 to determine the feasibility and operational
                        capability of a satellite as a military reconnaissance vehicle. These
                        studies have concluded that a Satellite Intelligence System is feasible and
                        has potential operational capability of providing current and reliable
                        intelligence information. Need for this information will continue to become
                        more critical as technological advances enable a potential enemy to bring
                        into being offensive weapons with constantly increasing range and greater
                        destructive power.</p>
                    <p>Contracts for development and test of Weapons System 117L were let in October
                        and November 1956. The first test flight of the Weapons System 117L
                        satellite vehicle is planned to be conducted in late 1958. Successive tests
                        of orbital capability of the vehicle and performance of the reconnaissance
                        equipment are planned to continue through 1960.</p>
                    <pb facs="d51-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d51-2"/>
                    <p>Expected useful life for pioneer versions of the Military Satellite Vehicle
                        equipment is 10 to 30 days and for later versions one year. The satellite
                        vehicles are planned to be equipped with sensing devices which will relay
                        reconnaissance information to the earth at a rate which would permit
                        coverage of the entire Soviet Bloc by a single vehicle as frequently as once
                        every eight days.</p>
                    <p>Successive progress reports will be provided to you each quarter showing
                        highlights and significant accomplishments in the execution <pb facs="0295" n="190" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_190"/> of the Military Reconnaissance
                        Satellite Program. Additional interim reports will be submitted in event of
                        breakthrough or other occurrence which would rapidly modify the schedules or
                        objectives of the program.</p>
                    <p>In accordance with National Security Council Action No. 1846, the “scope of
                        operational capability” of Weapons System 117L will be promptly raised for
                        your approval when such approval becomes necessary in carrying forward the
                        program.</p>
                    <p>With great respect, I am</p>
                    <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MNH_1"><hi rend="strong">Neil H.
                                McElroy</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>1 Incl</p>
                        <p>Report, subject</p>
                        <p>as above</p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>