<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-10-07T12:10:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-10-07T12:10:00-05:00" n="602" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d602">
                    <head>602. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d602fn1">Source: Disarmament at the United Nations. Secret. 2 pp. NARA, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Secretary’s Memoranda of
                            Conversation: Lot 64 D 199.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">SecDel MC/110</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1960-10-07T13:10:00-04:00">October 7, 1960, 1:10
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <pb facs="d602-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d602-1"/>
                    <p rend="center">SECRETARY’S DELEGATION TO THE FIFTEENTH SESSION OF THE UNITED
                        NATIONS GENERAL ASSEMBLY<lb/>New York, October 3–7, 1960</p>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item><list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">United States</hi></item>
                                <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                                <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KMV_1">Max V.
                                    Krebs</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">United Kingdom</hi></item>
                                <item>Lord Alexander Home</item>
                                <item>Mr. I. A. Samuel (Private Secretary)</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Disarmament</hi></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The Secretary opened the conversation by asking Lord Home how Prime Minister
                        Macmillan’s second conversation with <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> had gone. The Foreign Secretary said almost the
                        entire conversation had been devoted to disarmament with <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> adding a new element in
                        suggesting a special session of the General Assembly in February or March
                        1961 to take up only disarmament. <persName corresp="#p_MH_1">Macmillan</persName> countered that he thought some progress could be
                        made in Committee I during the General Assembly. He made no commitment
                        regarding Khrushchev’s suggestion. Lord Home went on to say that <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> is expected to speak tomorrow
                        when the Assembly discusses adoption of the agenda, and may advance his line
                        regarding disarmament at that time.</p>
                    <p>Lord Home said that British tactic will be to refuse to be drawn into any
                        general discussion of disarmament in the plenary. He questioned how long
                        Boland would allow <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> to go
                        on with any statement on disarmament noting that the <pb facs="d602-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d602-2"/> vote in the Committee on referral of
                        disarmament to Committee had been better than a two-thirds majority. The
                        Secretary said that in several of his talks with representatives of smaller
                        nations he found them all in agreement with the idea of taking up
                        disarmament in Committee first. As far as he was concerned Lord Home said he
                        planned to leave on the morning of the 8th and would come back to New York
                        only if the General Assembly got involved in the disarmament item and then
                        only for a few days. He did indicate he might return to take part if the
                        item came under serious consideration in Committee I.</p>
                    <pb facs="2286" n="2181" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_2181"/>
                    <p>Continuing, Lord Home said <persName corresp="#p_MH_1">Macmillan</persName>
                        had tried to get <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> into
                        discussion of controls and inspection, but that <persName corresp="#p_KNS_1">Khrushchev</persName> had shied away. The Foreign Secretary said that
                        in a talk with <persName corresp="#p_MJ_1">Moch</persName> yesterday he had
                        raised the question of DeGaulle’s proposals on control of means of delivery.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MJ_1">Moch</persName> had said there had been a
                        misunderstanding of French intentions in this regard and that they had
                        intended only inspection of the means of delivery in the first stage.</p>
                    <p>In reply to Lord Home’s question the Secretary said the only other item which
                        had been under consideration by the U.S. for possible advancement into the
                        first stage was the matter of nuclear missiles. The Secretary added,
                        however, that we had run into difficulty since this would involve submarines
                        and other naval vessels as well as any aircraft capable of delivering
                        nuclear weapons.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>