<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-07-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="68" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d68">
                    <head>68. <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Report<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d68fn1">Source: “Directive on Net Evaluation Subcommittee.” Top
                            Secret; Special Limited Distribution. 4 pp. NARA, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot 63 D
                            351, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5816 Series.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5816</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-07-01">July 1,
                            1958</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <pb facs="d68-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d68-1"/>
                    <p rend="center">NOTE BY THE EXECUTIVE SECRETARY</p>
                    <p rend="center">to the</p>
                    <p rend="center">NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL</p>
                    <p rend="center">on</p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">A NET EVALUATION SUBCOMMITTEE</hi></p>
                    <list type="references">
                        <head>REFERENCE</head>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5728</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The President, on the recommendation of the Chairman, Net Evaluation
                        Subcommittee, approved on June 25, 1958, the withdrawal of <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5728 and the issuance, on a special
                        limited-distribution basis, of the amended Directive enclosed herewith as
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5816. The amendment consists of the
                        deletion of the last two sentences of paragraph 3 and of subparagraphs 3–<hi rend="italic">a, b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> of <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5728, and the substitution therefore of a
                        new paragraph 3.</p>
                    <p>The enclosed Directive has also been revised in paragraph 5, to include on
                        the membership of the Subcommittee the Director of the Office <pb facs="0345" n="240" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_240"/> of Defense and
                        Civilian Mobilization in place of the Director of the Office of Defense
                        Mobilization and the Federal Civil Defense Administration, in accordance
                        with Reorganization Plan No. 1 of 1958, effective July 1, 1958.</p>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5816, as approved by the President is
                        transmitted herewith for the information of the National Security Council,
                        and is being referred to the members of the Subcommittee for appropriate
                        implementation.</p>
                    <p>The enclosed Directive supersedes <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                        5728.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Special security precautions should be observed in the
                            handling of the enclosure, with access thereto limited to those
                            individuals having a strict “need to know” in the performance of their
                            official duties.</hi></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_LJS_1"><hi rend="strong">James S. Lay,
                                Jr.</hi></persName>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Executive Secretary</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>cc: The Secretary of the Treasury</p>
                        <p>The Attorney General</p>
                        <p>The Director, Bureau of the Budget</p>
                        <p>The Chairman, Atomic Energy Commission</p>
                        <p>The Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff</p>
                        <p>The Director of Central Intelligence</p>
                        <p>The Chairman, Interdepartmental Intelligence Conference</p>
                        <p>The Chairman, Interdepartmental Committee on Internal Security</p>
                    </postscript>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline"><hi rend="strong">Enclosure</hi></note>
                        <pb facs="d68-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d68-2"/>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">DIRECTIVE</hi></p>
                        <p rend="center">on</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">A NET EVALUATION SUBCOMMITTEE</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Pursuant to the recommendations of the National Security Council
                                in <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1260–<hi rend="italic">b</hi> (November 4, 1954) and my subsequent
                                approval thereof, I hereby establish the following permanent
                                procedure (superseding <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5605) to
                                provide integrated evaluations of the net capabilities of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, in the event of general war, to
                                inflict direct injury upon the continental United States and to
                                provide a continual watch for changes which would significantly
                                alter those net capabilities.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Each integrated evaluation should: <list>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Cover all types of attack, overt or clandestine;</item>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Include consideration of the several courses of action
                                        which the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is capable
                                        of executing; and</item>
                                    <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Take into account the estimated future status of approved
                                        military and non-military U.S. defense programs.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Each integrated evaluation report should estimate, from the
                                practical standpoint, the extent and effect of direct injury,
                                including radioactive fall-out, upon the continental United States,
                                resulting from the most probable types and weights of attacks which
                                the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is capable <pb facs="0346" n="241" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_241"/> of
                                delivering during the nuclear phase of a general war (i.e., the
                                period during which the Soviet nuclear weapon stockpile or means of
                                delivery of nuclear weapons on the United States would be
                                substantially expended). Military operations overseas should be
                                considered only in so far as they (a) require a diversion of Soviet
                                resources from attack on the continental United States, or (b)
                                affect U.S. capabilities to execute the Bravo mission and
                                consequently the Soviet capability to attack the continental United
                                States. Each report should consider, in so far as damage to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is concerned, the effects
                                of U.S. attacks on the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> which
                                would affect their capability to damage the United States. In
                                addition, a general estimate should be made of the over-all effects
                                of the U.S. attacks against the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> which would show the general order of magnitude of
                                destruction, disruption of communications and government, and loss
                                of life in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. In arriving
                                at this general estimate, it is not expected or anticipated that
                                detailed analyses will be undertaken. An evaluation will be made
                                annually on the basis of an assumption or assumptions of <pb facs="d68-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d68-3"/> conditions
                                under which a general nuclear war might be initiated. Such
                                assumption(s) should be developed by the Subcommittee after careful
                                consideration of the implication of the world situation, and
                                submitted for my approval.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Integrated evaluations should be submitted to the Council on or
                                before November 15 of each year, and relate to the situation on a
                                critical date normally about three years in the future. In addition
                                to these annual integrated evaluations, an integrated evaluation
                                should be submitted to the Council at such times as the Subcommittee
                                feels that a change has become apparent that would significantly
                                alter the net capabilities of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> to inflict direct injury upon the continental
                                United States.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>In order to prepare these integrated evaluations I hereby
                                establish a Net Evaluation Subcommittee of the National Security
                                Council, composed of the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, who
                                will serve as Chairman, the Director of the Office of Defense and
                                Civilian Mobilization, the Chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission,
                                the Director of Central Intelligence, the Chairman of the
                                Interdepartmental Intelligence Conference, and the Chairman of the
                                Interdepartmental Committee on Internal Security. Each Subcommittee
                                member shall be consulted regarding and given ample opportunity to
                                review the following prior to adoption by the Subcommittee: (a)
                                subsidiary terms of reference, (b) the assumptions to be used as a
                                basis for each evaluation report, (c) the complete evaluation report
                                (less background material, which shall be made available only on a
                                “need-to-know” basis), and (d) any recommendations which the
                                Subcommittee may choose to submit. If the Director of the
                                Subcommittee Staff, after adoption of the evaluation report by the
                                Subcommittee, has any additional comments which he believes should
                                be presented to the <pb facs="0347" n="242" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_242"/>
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>, such comments may be submitted
                                to the President, through the Chairman of the Subcommittee, for
                                consideration. The Chairman of the Subcommittee, in consultation
                                with the Director of the Subcommittee Staff, will prepare
                                regulations and establish procedures for the handling of highly
                                sensitive information<note n="2" xml:id="d68fn2">Information such as
                                    that relating to war plans, new weapons and equipment,
                                    techniques and tactics for their employment, the vulnerability
                                    of U.S. defenses, and domestic and foreign intelligence sources
                                    and methods. [Footnote is in the original.]</note> required in
                                the preparation of an evaluation report so as to safeguard its
                                security on a strict “need-to-know” basis and to preclude the
                                assembly of an unwarranted amount of sensitive information in one
                                document. Such <pb facs="d68-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d68-4"/> regulations and procedures shall not be finally
                                adopted until the other members of the Subcommittee have been
                                consulted concerning them.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Subcommittee members are designated to act as individuals, but
                                each shall have the right to consult, at his discretion and under
                                appropriate security safeguards, with his agency or committee prior
                                to Subcommittee action on matters normally within the cognizance of
                                his committee or agency. In subscribing to the reports and
                                recommendations of the Subcommittee the individual members shall not
                                be expected to assume responsibility for technical matters or
                                conclusions not normally within the cognizance of his own parent
                                committee or agency. Reports as submitted to the Council should
                                show, so far as possible by textual footnotes, any dissents by
                                Subcommittee members.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>The Subcommittee will have a Staff, composed of individuals
                                assigned by member agencies, as required by the Director, and under
                                the direction of a Director whom I shall designate. The Director may
                                be compensated through the National Security Council from
                                contributions by the member agencies. Individuals assigned to the
                                Staff from each military service and by the Central Intelligence
                                Agency should normally serve for two years and be so appointed that,
                                to insure continuity, not more than fifty per cent will vacate each
                                year.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>The Net Evaluation Subcommittee hereby established is empowered
                                under the terms of this Directive to call on any agency of the
                                Government for relevant information, evaluations, and estimates,
                                subject only to establishment of appropriate security regulations
                                and procedures for the handling of highly sensitive information as
                                provided under paragraph 5 above.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Distribution of each completed Subcommittee report will be
                                determined at the time by me.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_EDD_1"><hi rend="strong">Dwight D.
                                        Eisenhower</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>