<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>98. Memorandum of Discussion at 380th NSC Meeting Meeting</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v03mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-09-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Science and technology</term>
                    <term ref="recyvYvKBWCiz1E8g" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026326"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil defense</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recXmtj6SyvT64JYD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic warfare</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127" lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear war</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-09-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="98"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                <head>98. Memorandum of Discussion at 380th <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                        Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d98fn1">Source: Agenda item 2:
                        Status of National Security Programs on June 30, 1958: The Mobilization
                        Program and the Civil Defense Program. Top Secret; Eyes Only. Extracts—4 pp.
                        Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                        Records.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1958-09-25">September 25, 1958</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d98-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d98-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Discussion at the 380th Meeting of the National Security Council Thursday,
                        September 25, 1958</item>
                </list>
                <p>Present at the 380th <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Meeting were the
                    President of the United States, presiding; the Secretary of State; the Secretary
                    of Defense; and the Director, Office of Civil and Defense Mobilization. Also
                    present were Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SFC_1">Fred C. Scribner, Jr.</persName>
                    for the Secretary of the Treasury; the Acting Director, Bureau of the Budget;
                    the Acting Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff; the Acting Director of Central
                    Intelligence; the Assistant to the President; the Deputy Assistant to the
                    President; the Director, U.S. Information Agency; the Director, International
                    Cooperation Administration; the Special Assistants to the President for National
                    Security Affairs, for Science and Technology, for Security Operations
                    Coordination; the White House Staff Secretary; the U.S. Ambassador to <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>; the Deputy Secretary of Defense; Assistant
                    Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGC_1">Gerard C. Smith</persName>; the
                    Executive Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>; and the Deputy
                    Executive Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>There follows a summary of the discussion and the main points taken.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is agenda item 1.]</p>
                <pb facs="d98-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d98-2"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">2. STATUS OF NATIONAL SECURITY PROGRAMS ON JUNE 30, 1958:
                    THE MOBILIZATION PROGRAM AND THE CIVIL DEFENSE PROGRAM</p>
                <p>(<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5819)</p>
                <p>Mr. Gray introduced Governor Hoegh and provided a short briefing to the Council
                    on certain policy questions which seemed to emerge from the Status Report on the
                    Mobilization Program (A copy of Mr. Gray’s briefing note is filed in the Minutes
                    of the Meeting and another is attached to this Memorandum).</p>
                <p>Governor Hoegh said that he would first report on the status of the mobilization
                    program and thereafter on the status of the civil defense program inasmuch as
                    the status reports covered the period <pb facs="0432" n="327" type="typeset"
                        xml:id="pg_327"/> to June 30, 1958 and that the Office of Defense
                    Mobilization and the Federal Civil Defense Administration had not been merged
                    until July 1, 1958. Next year these two Status Reports would be combined.
                    Continuing, <pb facs="d98-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d98-3"/> Governor
                    Hoegh pointed out that the emergency agencies, proposed to be set up in event of
                    war or national emergency, were being evaluated in the light of the findings of
                    OPERATION ALERT 1958. Recommendations as to the emergency agencies would be made
                    to the President on October 10, 1958.</p>
                <p>Likewise, Mobilization Plans C and D-Minus were being reviewed. The results of
                    the review of these plans would be ready by November 1, 1958 at which time all
                    the President’s Emergency Action Documents would be completed.</p>
                <p>As to the program to strengthen the U.S. Mobilization Base, Governor Hoegh
                    pointed out that it had been agreed that while we could fight a World War II
                    type of war with our present mobilization base, further study was being
                    undertaken with respect to the adequacy of the mobilization base in the event of
                    general nuclear war.</p>
                <p>The program for the relocation of federal agencies, said Governor Hoegh, was
                    likewise being re-evaluated in the light of OPERATION ALERT 1958.
                    Recommendations on this subject would be made to the President and the Cabinet
                    on October 10. As Mr. Gray had pointed out, warning times were of the very
                    greatest importance and the relocation plans needed a complete new look and
                    evaluation. <hi rend="italic">We did have, however, at the present time a
                        continuing operatio</hi>nal capability for nineteen agencies in the event of
                    war.</p>
                <p>Finally, Governor Hoegh pointed out that the results of the plan to disperse
                    federal facilities had practically negligible results. The one exception was the
                    Atomic Energy Commission which had relocated out of Washington.</p>
                <p>Turning to the status of the federal civil defense program as of June 30, 1958
                    Governor Hoegh stated that the situation described in the Status Report was
                    still far from satisfactory despite marked improvement in the course of the last
                    fiscal year. Governor Hoegh illustrated this point by providing certain
                    highlights of developments in that fiscal year. He stated that the passage of
                    the Durham Bill on August 8 was a landmark in the development of the national
                    civil defense program. No funds, however, had yet been provided for the shelter
                    program and it would be necessary to go back to the Congress with a presentation
                    on this program early in January 1959.</p>
                <p>At this point Secretary Dulles interrupted and indicated that he would have to
                    leave the meeting at 10 o’clock and wanted to raise one issue before being
                    obliged to leave. He said he wished to deal with the statement on Page 18 of the
                    Report on the Mobilization Program <pb facs="0433" n="328" type="typeset"
                        xml:id="pg_328"/>
                    <pb facs="d98-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d98-4"/> which called for the
                    creation of an economic warfare agency in the event of war or national
                    emergency. The Secretary of State added that he did not think that the proposal
                    to create such an emergency agency was wise. The Department of State and other
                    agencies were already carrying out a considerable amount of activity related to
                    economic warfare and would be able to carry on this activity in the event of
                    war. While Secretary Dulles said he sought no decision on this matter at this
                    time, he did wish to raise the question of the desirability of planning to
                    create an emergency agency for the conduction of economic warfare.</p>
                <p>In reply Governor Hoegh said that he and his people had come to much the same
                    conclusion as the Secretary of State. Having reevaluated this proposal, he had
                    come to feel that such an agency would not be necessary in the event of a
                    general nuclear war.</p>
                <p>Secretary Dulles left the meeting at 10 a.m. after which Governor Hoegh concluded
                    his report on the status of the key elements of the civil defense program.</p>
                <p>The National Security Council: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Noted and discussed the reports on the status of the Mobilization
                            Program and the Civil Defense Program on June 30, 1958, prepared by the
                            Office of Civil and Defense Mobilization (transmitted as parts 4 and 5
                            of <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5819), as summarized at the
                            meeting by the Director, Office of Civil and Defense
                            Mobilization.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Noted that the Secretary of State and the Director, Office of Civil
                            and Defense Mobilization, were in agreement that the concept of an
                            emergency organization for economic warfare will not be adopted at this
                            time.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>NOTE: The action in <hi rend="italic">b</hi> above as approved by the President
                    subsequently transmitted to the Director, Office of Civil and Defense
                    Mobilization.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">3. U.S. POLICY TOWARD GERMANY</p>
                <p>(<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> 5803; <gloss target="#t_OCB_1">OCB</gloss>
                    Reports, dated September 3, 1958, on <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                    5803)</p>
                <p>The National Security Council:</p>
                <p>Noted the reference Reports on the subject by the Operations Coordinating
                    Board.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GSE_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">S. Everett Gleason</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
