<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-07-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="242" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00R296/4821</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Declaration of the London Conference,
                                    1931</hi><note n="12" xml:id="d242fn12">Approved at the final
                                    session, July 23; copy transmitted to the Department by the
                                    Chargé in Great Britain as an enclosure to his despatch No.
                                    2141, July 28; received August 5.</note></head>
                            <dateline>
                                <placeName>London</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1931-07-23">July 23, 1931</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p>The recent excessive withdrawals of capital from Germany have created
                                an acute financial crisis. These withdrawals have been caused by a
                                lack of confidence, which is not justified by the economic and
                                budgetary situation of the country.</p>
                            <p>In order to ensure the maintenance of the financial stability of
                                Germany, which is essential in the interests of the whole world, the
                                Governments represented at the Conference are ready to co-operate so
                                far as lies within their power, to restore confidence.</p>
                            <p>The Governments represented at the Conference are ready to recommend
                                for the consideration of the financial institutions in their
                                respective countries the following proposals for relieving the
                                immediate situation:— <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>that the Central Bank credit of $100 million recently
                                        granted to the Reichsbank under the auspices of the Bank for
                                        International Settlements, be renewed at maturity for a
                                        period of three months:</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>that concerted measures should be taken by the financial
                                        institutions in the different countries with a view to
                                        maintaining the volume of the credits they have already
                                        extended to Germany.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>The Conference recommend that the Bank for International Settlements
                                should be invited to set up without delay a Committee of
                                representatives nominated by the Governors of the Central Banks
                                interested to inquire into the immediate further credit needs of
                                Germany and to study the possibilities of converting a portion of
                                the short-term credits into long-term credits.</p>
                            <p>The Conference noted with interest a communication from Dr. Brüning
                                relative to the joint guarantee recently placed by German Industry
                                at the disposal of the Gold Discount Bank. The Conference are of the
                                opinion that a guarantee of this description should make it possible
                                to provide a sound basis for the resumption of the normal operations
                                of international credit.</p>
                            <p>The Conference consider that, if these measures are carried through,
                                they will form a basis for more permanent action to follow.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. Ramsay
                                    MacDonald</hi></signed>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">President of the
                                    Conference.</hi><lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">M. P. A.
                                        Hankey</hi></signed>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretary-General.</hi></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">July</hi> 23, 1931.</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>