<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Italy ( (Kirk) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="316"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d316">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15a3/1652</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-10-09">October 9,
                            1931</date>.<lb/>[Received October 21.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1080</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my telegram No. 198 of October
                    9, 11 a.m.<note n="35" xml:id="d316fn35">Not printed.</note> regarding the
                    Franco-Italian negotiations for a Naval Accord, I have the honor to transmit
                    herewith a copy and translation of the Italian memorandum submitted by Signor
                    Rosso to M. Massigli on September 26, 1931, which is referred to therein.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexander Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation<note n="36"
                                xml:id="d316fn36">File translation revised.</note>]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum From the Italian Government to the French
                            Government</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>(1) In his letter of August 21, 1931, M. Massigli communicated to M. Rosso a
                        memorandum giving the general lines for a provisional agreement which the
                        French Government would be disposed to consider for the settlement of the
                        naval question between France and Italy.</p>
                    <p>After setting forth the reasons which led the French Government to submit a
                        proposal radically deviating from the Bases of Agreement of March 1, 1931,
                        the memorandum suggests that the building programs which have been voted
                        respectively in France and in Italy between the signing of the Washington
                        Treaty and 1930 be taken as the basis for establishing the building programs
                        for the 6 following years. According to the figures indicated in the
                        memorandum, the average annual construction for France would be 32, 510
                        tons, and for Italy 22, 359 tons. The memorandum proposes that for the
                        period January 1, 1931, to December 31, 1936, the annual average of
                        construction of light surface craft and submarines be set in the proportion
                        resulting from a 25 percent reduction of the above-mentioned figures. On the
                        other hand, the agreement would not affect the construction of battleships
                        and airplane carriers, which would continue to be governed exclusively by
                        the provisions of the Washington Treaty and by article I of the London
                        Treaty.</p>
                    <pb facs="0547" n="433" xml:id="pg_433"/>
                    <p>Furthermore: (1) the tonnage of submarines in service would not exceed 81,
                        989 tons for France and 52, 700 tons for Italy; (2) no cruiser with guns
                        exceeding 155 mm. in calibre would be put into service by France or by Italy
                        prior to December 31, 1936.</p>
                    <p>(2) With regard to the proposals contained in the French Memorandum of August
                        21, it should be pointed out in the first place that after all the work and
                        all the efforts which have been put forth to reach the agreement in
                        principle consecrated in the Bases of Agreement of March 1, the Italian
                        Government could not regard with favor, nor without a certain scepticism,
                        the opening of new negotiations deviating in so marked a fashion from the
                        above-mentioned bases.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, in the same conciliatory spirit in which the Italian
                        negotiators have unfailingly approached the study of the naval question, the
                        Italian Government did not neglect a careful examination of the new French
                        proposals, and it arrived at the following conclusions, showing the very
                        serious difficulties which oppose the application of these proposals on the
                        part of Italy;</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) According to the Bases of Agreement France and
                        Italy were authorized to construct, during the 6 years of the agreement, an
                        annual tonnage which was approximately equal (this in the case that the 12
                        French torpedo boats of the <hi rend="italic">Algériens</hi> type should be
                        considered as exempt, in conformity with article 8 (<hi rend="italic"
                        >a</hi>) of the Treaty of London and the displacements indicated in Document
                        L. N. C. 6 of the London Conference). If, on the contrary, it should be
                        admitted that the question of the <hi rend="italic">Algériens</hi> might be
                        construed in conformity to the French viewpoint, France would have been
                        authorized to build during the course of the 6 years 6, 800 tons more than
                        Italy.</p>
                    <p>According to the new proposals, this difference of 6, 800 tons would be
                        changed into a difference of 45, 680 tons, which would mean that the
                        comparative strengths of the French and the Italian navies would be
                        radically altered in favor of France. This result would be in open
                        contradiction to the principle which had been established by common accord
                        prior to undertaking the negotiations which led to the Bases of Agreement of
                        March 1, since it was understood that the agreement to be concluded was not
                        to affect questions of principle nor to modify the comparative situations of
                        the naval forces of the two countries. While the Bases of Agreement of March
                        1, through the interplay of reciprocal concessions, on the whole respected
                        these two conditions, the project contained in the French memorandum would
                        imply a disavowal of the above-mentioned principle, marking at the same time
                        a very considerable advantage in favor of France.</p>
                    <p>It is true that according to the French interpretation of the Bases of
                        Agreement the superiority of 6, 800 tons would have been applicable only to
                        the first 4 years of the agreement. But even if this period <pb facs="0548"
                            n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/> of time alone is considered, the difference in
                        construction envisaged by the new French proposals would reach the still
                        very outstanding figure of 30, 450 tons. Thus, while on March 1 the French
                        Government declared itself satisfied with an agreement giving it a
                        superiority in construction of 6, 800 tons during the first 4 years, in its
                        new proposals it asks of the Italian Government an agreement giving France,
                        during the same period of time, a superiority in construction approximately
                        four and a half times greater.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The figure of 10,151 tons which the French
                        memorandum gives as the difference between the annual averages of French and
                        Italian constructions during the last few years was obtained by including in
                        the basis for calculation the years 1922–1924 during which time Italy, who
                        was going through a period of political crisis and economic reorganization,
                        had laid down only 8,563 tons as against 75,225 tons laid down during the
                        same period by France. If the starting point for the calculation of the
                        constructions of the last few years was really such as to show—according to
                        the words of the French memorandum—“the efforts which the two countries have
                        considered necessary to put forth in view of the reconstruction of their
                        navies”, it would seem much more equitable to calculate the average of
                        constructions upon the basis of the last 6 years.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) According to the Italian interpretation of the
                        Bases of Agreement, the annual average tonnage of all categories which
                        France could lay down was 26, 350 tons (not including the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Algériens</hi>) or 27, 550 tons (including the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Algériens</hi>). According to the new proposals the annual average of
                        French constructions would be 24, 383 tons for light surface craft and
                        submarines alone. In view of the fact that according to the Washington and
                        London Treaties France is authorized to construct during the next 6 years an
                        annual average of 17, 975 tons of battleships and airplane carriers, the
                        total of French constructions in all categories would amount to about 42,
                        358 tons annually, or more than the tonnage envisaged by the proposals which
                        had been made by France last April and which Italy was not in a position to
                        accept.</p>
                    <p>Thus the French plan, although at first glance apparently contemplating a 25
                        percent reduction in the construction of the last 9 years, in reality
                        involves a potential increase of about 30 percent in this same construction.
                        In the category of light surface craft alone there would be an increase of
                        about 85,000 tons in French constructions during the period 1931–1936, in
                        comparison with the constructions envisaged by the Bases of Agreement as
                        interpreted by Italy.</p>
                    <p>(3) In paragraph 2 of the French memorandum mention is made of two specific
                        difficulties in putting into execution the provisions of the Bases of
                        Agreement concerning battleships. The Italian Government recognizes these
                        difficulties, but it does not consider them insurmountable.</p>
                    <pb facs="0549" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/>
                    <p>The French memorandum is entirely correct when it observes that the Italian
                        Government regretted that the problem of battleships should be connected
                        with that of the limitation of tonnage which is not governed by the
                        Washington and London Treaties. During the course of the negotiations which
                        led to the Bases of Agreement of March 1 it had, however, been led to accept
                        the provisions concerning battleships because they appeared to be a
                        necessary condition to an understanding among the three powers directly
                        interested in the agreement. Having at that time renounced, in a spirit of
                        conciliation, the attempt to have its viewpoint accepted, the Italian
                        Government prefers not to revert to this question now and not to run the
                        risk of destroying an agreement which, taken as a whole, represents a fair
                        compromise resulting from reciprocal concessions made by the three
                        interested powers.</p>
                    <p>(4) For all the foregoing reasons and as a result of consultations which it
                        has had occasion to exchange with the British Government, the Italian
                        Government is of the opinion that it would be deeply regrettable to abandon
                        the Bases of Agreement of March 1, thanks to which the very divergent
                        viewpoints of the three Governments upon a particularly complex problem
                        could have been to a great extent reconciled. It is, on the other hand,
                        persuaded that the best chance for further progress lies, not in the
                        abandonment of the results already attained with such great difficulty, but
                        rather in the effort which can still be made to eliminate the remaining
                        difficulties in the way of a complete agreement.</p>
                    <p>If the French Government and the British Government should see the utility of
                        resuming the negotiations broken off at London at the end of last April, in
                        order to seek a means of reconciling the Bases of Agreement of March 1 with
                        the difficulties which have arisen since that date, the Italian Government,
                        ever desirous of arriving at a complete understanding with the other two
                        powers on the settlement of the naval question in harmony with the London
                        Treaty, declares that it is ready for its part to lend to this last effort
                        of conciliation its most cordial and solicitous collaboration.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
