<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-08-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="389" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d389">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15a4/337⅔</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Atherton</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-08-05">August 5, 1931</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I am informed by Count
                            Bernsdorff that when you were in Berlin Dieckhoff gave you a memorandum
                            on disarmament. It has been discovered that certain figures in
                            Dieckhoff’s memorandum were incorrect and accordingly Bernsdorff has
                            asked that I forward you the enclosed corrected copy, with the new
                            figures underlined in red on page 2. Also Bernsdorff asks that you
                            return to me, for delivery to him, the copy of the memorandum which
                            Dieckhoff gave you, for which this is a substitute.</p>
                        <pb facs="0632" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/>
                        <p>You may notice that sterling exchange broke today. The City rumors are
                            that the Bank of France has stated it cannot do business with the Bank
                            of England while Norman remains its head. There follow, of course, other
                            rumors that Norman’s resignation is contemplated, but apparently without
                            foundation.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Ray Atherton</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum on the Question of Replacing
                                    Battleships</hi></head>
                            <p>1) According to Article 190 of the Treaty of Versailles the life of
                                German battleships is 20 years. The 8 battleships (2 of these were
                                reserve ships) which were left us by the Treaty of Versailles and
                                after the negotiations with the Interallied Naval Commission, have
                                reached the following age resp.: one 29 years, three 28 years, one
                                27 years, one 26 years and two 25 years. Some of the ships are so
                                used up in parts that the safety of the crew would probably be
                                endangered if the ships were still used for many years.</p>
                            <p>According to the building programme for replacing old ships covering
                                the years until 1936, only 3 “Ersatz” battleships are to be put into
                                service and the building of a fourth battleship is to be begun.
                                According to this plan there would be replaced: the battleship <hi rend="italic">Preussen</hi> (age 29 years)—(by the battleship
                                    <hi rend="italic">Deutschland</hi>), the battleship <hi rend="italic">Lothringen</hi> (age 30 years), the battleship <hi rend="italic">Braunschweig</hi> (age 34 years); the battleship
                                    <hi rend="italic">Elsass</hi> would not be replaced before 1938,
                                at which time this ship will have reached the age of 35 years.</p>
                            <p>Of the 8 cruisers allowed to Germany (2 of which are reserve
                                cruisers) we have replaced 4 cruisers by new ships. These 4 cruisers
                                had already by far surpassed the age limit of 20 years prescribed by
                                the Treaty of Versailles. A fifth “Ersatz” cruiser <hi rend="italic">Leipzig</hi>, which is to replace a ship that has surpassed the
                                age limit by 11 years, has been completed and will shortly be put
                                into commission.</p>
                            <p>2) Our replacement programme is necessarily regulated by the fact
                                that, according to the Treaty of Versailles, our ships had to be
                                delivered to the Allies. At the end of the war we possessed 28<note n="28" xml:id="d389fn1">Underlined in red in the original
                                    document.</note> modern capital ships (dreadnoughts and battle
                                cruisers), some of which had only been completed during the war.
                                Apart from this we had 3<note n="28" xml:id="d389fn2">Underlined in
                                    red in the original document.</note> modern cruisers. All these
                                ships had to be delivered according to the Treaty of Versailles
                                (articl. 185). We were merely allowed to keep 8 old battleships
                                dating from the pre-dreadnought time, which were launched between
                                1902 and 1906. Apart from these ships 8 small cruisers were left to
                                us most of which, at the time that the Treaty of <pb facs="0633" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/> Versailles became valid, had already
                                attained the age limit of 20 years (apart from this all our
                                submarines, 42 modern destroyers and 50 modern torpedo boats were
                                taken from us).</p>
                            <p>Had we been allowed to keep modern battleships instead of the old
                                ones which can hardly put in sea without endangering the crew, it
                                would have been unnecessary for us to build new ships for a long
                                time. Owing to the fact that they were of high technical standard,
                                we could even have kept in service for a long time the oldest of our
                                capital ships which were put into service in the years 1910 and
                                1911, in spite of the fact that they had attained the prescribed age
                                limit.</p>
                            <p>3) The battle cruiser <hi rend="italic">Deutschland</hi> was launched
                                in May last, and its construction has already been completed: the
                                work on the ships armaments is at present proceeding; it is to be
                                completed in September 1932.</p>
                            <p>4) The budget for 1931 provides for a first instalment of RM
                                10.830,000.—for the battle cruiser “B” (Ersatz <hi rend="italic">Lothringen</hi>). Of this sum the costs of building are 6,1
                                million marks, the costs of artillery armaments 4,63 million marks,
                                the costs for torpedo armaments a 100 000 marks. The keel of the
                                ship has already been set. The building yard works are proceeding
                                for several months. The amounts provided for by the budget for 1931
                                have already been completely spent on orders placed with the
                                building yards and the industry.</p>
                            <p>It is intended to put the ships in commission by the end of 1934.</p>
                            <p>5) For the battle cruiser “C” the construction of which is provided
                                for in the building programme for the middle of 1932 until the
                                middle of 1936, no budgetary means have been provided for so far.
                                The period for construction of the battle cruiser “D” is to be the
                                middle of 1934 until the middle of 1938. Also for this ship no
                                dispositions have of course been made.</p>
                            <p>6) The tonnage conceded to Germany under the Treaty of Versailles for
                                battleships (in total 60,000 tons) and for small cruisers (36,000
                                tons) to which 2 battleships and 2 cruisers without ammunition and
                                crew must be added as reserves, compares with the following French
                                total, taking into account the present strength of the French navy
                                plus ships under construction: <table cols="8" rows="3">
                                    <row>
                                        <cell role="num">9</cell>
                                        <cell cols="6">battleships with a total tonnage of</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">194.544</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell role="num">2</cell>
                                        <cell cols="6">aircraft carriers with a total tonnage
                                            of</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">32.046</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell role="num">21</cell>
                                        <cell>cruisers</cell>
                                        <cell>“</cell>
                                        <cell>“</cell>
                                        <cell>“</cell>
                                        <cell>“</cell>
                                        <cell>“</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">178.154</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table></p>
                            <p>Whereas Germany is allowed 24 destroyers and torpedo boats (plus 8
                                vessels in reserve) France possesses 92 destroyers and torpedo boats
                                and, in addition, at the time being 110 submarines with a tonnage of
                                97.111 which are completely forbidden to Germany.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>