<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Address by the Chancellor of the German Reich ( (Bruening))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-06-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-06-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recykDuvfC6iFH3Xe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recfIX2Uumy8inHEq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85144526"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wages</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-06-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-06-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="39"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d39">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00R296/4444</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Address by the Chancellor of the German Reich</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Bruening</hi>)<note n="53" xml:id="d39fn53">Delivered over the
                        German radio, June 23, 1931. Text and translation transmitted to the
                        Department by the Ambassador in Germany as enclosures to his despatch No.
                        1003 of July 1; received July 14.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1931-06-23">June 23, 1931</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ladies and Gentlemen</hi>: All the peoples of the earth are
                    deeply impressed by the historical step taken by the President of the United
                    States on Sunday to check the tremendous crisis which has overtaken almost all
                    nations and to bring aid to those who threaten to succumb beneath it. The German
                    people and the German Government accepted President Hoover’s proposal with
                    heartfelt gratitude. We see a new hope for Europe and for Germany proceeding
                    from this proposal. It brings Germany aid at a critical moment in her history
                    when difficulties have accumulated to the utmost limit. The first effectual
                    initiative has been taken toward a better future; but the German Government must
                    warn against the belief that through this proposal, if it is accepted by all the
                    nations in question, we will have surmounted all the troubles confronting
                    us.</p>
                <p>While the German Government has attempted to gain control of threatening dangers
                    by repeated rigorous measures in the form of the Emergency Decree of December
                    and the last Emergency Decree and while it was forced to impose upon the German
                    people the extreme of burdens and privations in order to get through the coming
                    months and, above all, next winter, it was well aware that the climax of
                    financial difficulties would, in all probability, be reached in 1932. Although
                    the German Government has balanced the budget of the Reich for the current
                    fiscal year, in the event that no further worsening of the economic situation
                    occurs, and although it has even made a considerable amount available for the
                    municipalities in order to alleviate the growing exactions for those unemployed
                    who are supported neither by unemployment insurance nor by the Reich, the
                    situation of the states and municipalities is still unsettled in 1931. According
                    to the estimates of the German Government, the taxes transferred by the Reich
                    will fall off by hundreds of millions. In addition there are the great losses in
                    taxes on trading profits, real estate and rents which must be expected as a
                    result of the bad economic situation. The result of the decline in incomes and
                    wages in <pb facs="0166" n="52" xml:id="pg_52"/> 1931 will be that the full
                    weight of the tax deficit will only be felt in the 1932 budgets of the Reich,
                    states and municipalities.</p>
                <p>An additional factor was the acute danger, which we have experienced repeatedly
                    during the past two years, that great anxiety manifested itself following a
                    series of economic events and that this anxiety resulted in the sudden
                    withdrawal of tremendous numbers of short-term credits by other countries. At
                    one blow the danger which had long since been predicted, namely, that during the
                    years of seeming prosperity German business had been largely built up on
                    domestic and foreign money which was either loaned for a short time only or
                    invested in undertakings from which it could not be withdrawn from one day to
                    the next, became manifest to its full extent. The attempt now made for the third
                    time to withdraw a large part of these short-term credits from Germany brought
                    on a storm, which may now be regarded as calmed. At the same time, however, this
                    storm clearly and drastically brought before the eyes of all discerning people
                    the fact that the economy of the whole world is interwoven, positively and
                    negatively. It transformed the plight of individual nations, especially Germany,
                    into a plight involving the whole world. It showed that the living standard of
                    one nation is conditioned by the living standard of other nations. If one nation
                    suffers severely, other nations that have business relations with it cannot in
                    the long run maintain their prosperity.</p>
                <p>To believe that all Germany’s troubles will be at an end when President Hoover’s
                    proposal is accepted, would be the most dangerous illusion to which the German
                    people could surrender. The German Government was obliged to adopt the rigorous
                    measures in question to save the financial situation and must adhere to them,
                    because even without reparation payments extraordinary exactions will be
                    necessary in order to hold out for the next year and a half. The Government has
                    declared that it is prepared to mitigate the hardships and especially oppressive
                    measures of the Emergency Decree, and it adheres to its statement. But it is not
                    in a position to allow the general financial results of the Emergency Decree to
                    be undermined in any way. Only under guarantee of these general financial
                    results will it be possible to balance the above-mentioned additional losses in
                    1932, if President Hoover’s proposal is accepted.</p>
                <p>The German people would jeopardize all the sympathetic appreciation of the world
                    and all confidence if it did not adhere to the principle of absolute
                    recuperation of our state finances, even if sacrifices are required to carry it
                    out. The restoration of finances is one of the most important premises for the
                    establishment of confidence. The proof of confidence, embodied in President
                    Hoover’s initiative, important to the history of the world, can only bear fruit
                    if the German <pb facs="0167" n="53" xml:id="pg_53"/> people are determined to
                    proceed by their own strength along the road of greatest economy in every
                    field.</p>
                <p>According to the proclamation of the President of the United States, the proposed
                    holiday year is intended to serve not only to restore international business
                    confidence, and consequently the economic reconstruction of the world, but its
                    purpose is, at the same time, to free the political relations between the
                    countries of disturbing tension and to promote and fortify a peaceful
                    development based on determined cooperation between the states. This is
                    necessarily a reciprocal relationship. Unless the economic and financial
                    relations become sound, the political situation cannot become quiet, and without
                    political pacification there can be no end to economic distress. The well-being
                    of Europe and the world is contingent upon the resolute and far-sighted
                    determination on both sides that those who by a tragic fate became enemies in
                    the world war will now energetically make such resolutions as are demanded of
                    all governments and nations by the extreme stringency of the moment. The
                    American proposal will prepare the way to this magnificent goal, if it is
                    accepted by the countries concerned in the same high-minded spirit in which it
                    was offered by its author.</p>
                <p>The German Government is prepared to cooperate with all its power in striving for
                    this goal of the American proposal. It is sincerely determined to collaborate,
                    on the political side as well, with all the governments in order to solve the
                    questions which are of importance to the pacification of Europe. The greater the
                    alleviation of the severe economic and social distress from which the German
                    people are suffering, the more firmly and unanimously will they be prepared and
                    competent to form a bulwark of quiet and order in Europe.</p>
                <p>The solemnity of this hour and the responsibility resulting from it impel me to
                    voice the hope and expectation that all those who are influential in forming
                    public opinion will keep in mind the importance to Germany and Europe, at this
                    moment, of moderation and self-discipline in all utterances and demonstrations
                    of all our compatriots.</p>
                <p>The German Government is aware that in all this the future shaping of the
                    relations between Germany and France will be assigned a particularly important
                    role. Though many difficulties and obstacles have shown themselves in the
                    development of these relations, though there have been animated disputes in the
                    press on both sides of the border, I nevertheless hold fast to the conviction
                    that all this is not insurmountable, that, on the contrary, if there is mutual
                    good will, ways and means can be found to bring to the fore what is of common
                    interest to both countries and to fasten it so securely in <pb facs="0168"
                        n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/> the minds of both nations that it will provide a
                    guarantee of durability. For the reason that I am convinced that a really
                    well-balanced and fruitful cooperation among the peoples of Europe and the
                    stabilization of peace in Europe, which is necessary for an active business
                    exchange with the New World, will only seem secure on the day that in the souls
                    of the two great neighboring nations the past will have been overcome and their
                    joint vision directed toward the future and its mental, economic and political
                    shaping, for that very reason it is the aim of the Government which I lead to
                    look ahead beyond the gloomy mood of the moment and to do everything feasible
                    that it can answer for to help President Hoover’s generous action succeed as it
                    deserves to do and as it should do in the interest of Europe and the whole
                    world.</p>
                <p>The German Government for its part will not spare good will. When once agreement
                    has been reached regarding the holiday year, all the more easily will it be
                    possible to pave the way for peaceful collaboration of both countries by means
                    of a straightforward discussion. I would welcome it if an opportunity presented
                    itself for such a preliminary discussion, as the recent meeting in Chequers
                    paved the way for a discussion between Germany and England. The tasks
                    confronting Germany and France are too big and too urgent for both countries
                    that it should not be possible to find a common ground, in confidential and
                    unreserved exchange of views, from which the solution of these tasks could be
                    attacked with prospects of success.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
