<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Great Britain ( (Atherton) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="505"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d505">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">561.311D1/73</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Atherton</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-05-27">May 27,
                            1931</date>.<lb/>[Received June 5.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1976</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the Department’s cable No. 118 of
                    May 6, 6 p.m., I have the honor to transmit five copies of a report dated May
                    26, 1931, prepared by Mr. Raymond E. Cox, First Secretary of this Embassy, on
                    the Conference of Wheat Exporting Countries held in London, May 18–23, 1931. Mr.
                    Cox was Secretary of the American Delegation to this Conference. The enclosures
                    to the report are being forwarded to the Department under separate cover with a
                    cross reference to this despatch.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ray Atherton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of the American Delegation</hi> (<persName
                            type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Cox</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in Great Britain</hi>
                            (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Dawes</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-05-26">May 26,
                                1931</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to submit the following
                        report on the Conference of Wheat Exporting Countries held at Canada House,
                        Trafalgar Square, London, May 18–23, 1931.</p>
                    <p>The Conference of Wheat Exporting Countries was convened in London at the
                        invitation of the Canadian Government. The following <pb facs="0754" n="640"
                            xml:id="pg_640"/> countries sent delegations: United States, Argentina,
                        Australia, Bulgaria, Canada, Hungary, India, Poland, Roumania, Soviet Russia
                        and Jugoslavia.</p>
                    <p>The Canadian High Commissioner in London, the Honorable G. Howard Ferguson,
                        was elected Chairman of the Conference. The meetings were private.</p>
                    <p>The purpose of the Conference, as expressed by Mr. Ferguson at the first
                        Plenary Session on May 18, was to discuss (1) the disposition of present
                        accumulated wheat stocks in various countries; (2) improving the methods for
                        handling and distributing the wheat surplus of the future.</p>
                    <p>Early in the proceedings clarification was given to the views on these two
                        items held by the American delegation, the Russian delegation, and the
                        delegations from Poland, Bulgaria, Hungary, Roumania and Jugoslavia, the
                        latter five acting together as a group. The delegations from Poland and the
                        four Danubian countries desired the formation of an International Wheat
                        Board with headquarters in London to determine wheat export quotas for each
                        wheat exporting country. Practically identical proposals to this effect were
                        presented by the Polish, Roumanian and Hungarian delegations.</p>
                    <p>In the opinion of the American delegation, economic adjustment of production
                        in keeping with the changed economic outlook was the best method of solving
                        the problem of present wheat surpluses, without resort to quotas or anything
                        to disturb the freedom of trade on international wheat markets. The American
                        delegation made it clear that the United States would not participate in any
                        International Wheat Board to fix export quotas. It gave to the Conference
                        the reassuring statement that the supplies accumulated by the Federal Farm
                        Board would not be dumped on European markets and thus demoralize them. It
                        also stressed the desirability of capitalizing on present low wheat prices
                        to extend wheat consumption in Oriental and tropical countries.</p>
                    <p>The Soviet delegation refused to accept acreage reduction as a solution of
                        the problem as Russia aimed at increasing her present production rather than
                        diminishing it. The Soviet delegation, however, was prepared to discuss the
                        limitation of wheat exports on a quota basis subject to the following
                        provisos: (1) The quota for Soviet Russia to be based on the quantity of
                        wheat exported by Russia before the war; (2) the largest wheat exporting
                        countries to participate in the scheme; (3) States adhering to the quota
                        scheme should not conclude any separate agreements between themselves or
                        with a wheat importing country or group of wheat importing countries.</p>
                    <pb facs="0755" n="641" xml:id="pg_641"/>
                    <p>At the outset, the Canadian, Australian and Indian delegations appeared to
                        favor some quota plan, but the Canadian delegation held itself in reserve,
                        never fully declaring its position. At the same time the Canadian
                        delegation, together with the Argentine and Australian delegations, showed a
                        receptive frame of mind to the attitude on the questions at issue adopted by
                        the American delegation.</p>
                    <p>The points of view enumerated above proving to be irreconcilable, the
                        delegates, in order to produce something tangible from the Conference
                        proceedings, agreed to establish a Conference Committee consisting of one
                        representative from each State participating in the Conference to— <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <list>
                                <item>“(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Submit to the Governments of the
                                    countries participating in this Conference a definite proposal
                                    for establishing, under the supervision of the Committee of the
                                    Conference, a Clearing House of information to serve the wheat
                                    exporting countries. For this purpose, the Committee shall be
                                    empowered to secure from the States represented on the Committee
                                    full information as to the unloadings and stocks of wheat at all
                                    importing points, the areas sown to wheat, and the crop
                                    prospects, thereby assisting the orderly distribution of wheat
                                    in world markets. This information should be provided as far as
                                    possible in the form prescribed and at the times fixed by the
                                    Committee.</item>
                                <item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) To explore carefully all possible
                                    avenues for the greater utilisation of this important
                                    cereal.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>This Committee would also prepare and recommend a draft agenda for a further
                        meeting of the Conference at such time as is considered desirable. Mr. N. A.
                        Olsen of the Department of Agriculture, one of the American delegates, was
                        named the American representative on this Committee. The text of the
                        resolution providing for the Committee, adopted at the final session of the
                        Conference on May 23, was sent to the Department of State in the American
                        Embassy’s telegram No. 163 of May 23, 1 p.m.</p>
                    <p>There are transmitted under separate cover one copy each, in English and in
                        French, of the documents distributed by the Secretary General of the
                            Conference<note n="67" xml:id="d505fn67">None printed.</note> (the
                        yellow and white colored documents being the Minutes of the meetings, the
                        gray folder and pink colored documents being general documentation. Of the
                        latter pink group, possibly the most interesting are document No. 9, the
                        statement of Honorable S. R. McKelvie, of the American delegation; documents
                        Nos. 17, 18 and 19, the Polish, Roumanian and Hungarian proposals,
                        respectively; and document No. 26, the statement of Mr. I. E. Lubimoff of
                        the Soviet delegation.)</p>
                    <p>Documents Nos. 13 and 16, entitled “The Chadbourne Agreement” and “Effects of
                        Protective Measures adopted by European Wheat <pb facs="0756" n="642"
                            xml:id="pg_642"/> Importing Countries”, are, at the request of the
                        Chairman, to be considered strictly confidential.</p>
                    <p>There are also transmitted under separate cover a copy of the “Final Act of
                        the Conference” (white paper), giving the text of the agreement finally
                        reached by the delegates on May 23 as outlined above, and the Directory of
                        the Conference, containing the names and titles of the various delegates and
                        advisers. A copy of the “Final Act” is attached to this report, together
                        with single copies of editorials from the London press commenting on the
                        results of the Conference.<note n="68" xml:id="d505fn68">Enclosures not
                            printed.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Raymond E. Cox</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
