<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1930-12-23T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1930-12-23T18:00:00-05:00" n="513" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d513">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">511.4A6/194: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1930-12-23T18:00:00-05:00">December 23, 1930—6
                                p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>Your December 20, 9 a.m.<note n="77" xml:id="d513fn77">Not
                                printed.</note> Since London Preliminary Conference was called
                            merely to prepare certain material for the May Conference, which this
                            Government has not yet agreed to attend and since the American
                                representative<note n="78" xml:id="d513fn78">J. K. Caldwell.</note>
                            had not formally accepted on behalf of this-Government any of the
                            results of the Preliminary Conference, he did not consider it necessary
                            or advisable to have any formal reservation of the position of this
                            Government appear in the report issued by the Conference. However, when
                            formal reservations were made by certain delegates the American
                            representative stated that his failure to make any formal reservation
                            for incorporation in the report of the conference should not be
                            understood as committing the Government of the United States in any way
                            in regard to the measures which had been discussed by the Conference. In
                            reply, the President of the Conference stated that all delegates were in
                            the same position; that none of the delegates were plenipotentiaries and
                            no Government would be bound by any decision of the Conference; that all
                            that the Conference could do was to make recommendations and submit
                            proposals for the consideration of the various Governments and for the
                            consideration of the Advisory Committee and the May Conference; and that
                            all of the Governments represented at the London Conference were at
                            liberty to start quite a different scheme if they saw fit. No delegate
                            disagreed with this view.</p>
                        <pb facs="0764" n="650" xml:id="pg_650"/>
                        <p>You are at liberty to make such use of the above information as you see
                            fit.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Stimson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>