<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Bolivia ( (Trueblood) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d572</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">572</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-06-25T15:32:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-06-25T15:32:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-06-25T15:32:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-06-25T15:32:00-05:00" n="572"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d572">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/1239: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Trueblood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">La Paz</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-06-25T16:00:00-04:32"
                            >June 25, 1931—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 10:37 p.m.<note n="68" xml:id="d572fn68">Telegram in three
                            sections.</note>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>59. With reference to Department’s 24, June 24, 1 p.m., I have to report that I
                    have just had an interview with the Foreign Minister, in which he said that he
                    was drafting a reply to the Paraguayan note refusing satisfaction, and that the
                    reply would probably be delivered tomorrow. I was unable to learn any details
                    concerning the reply <pb facs="0847" n="733" xml:id="pg_733"/> but was promised
                    a copy later today, at which time I will send another telegram. The Minister
                    read to me the Bolivian note which asked for a repudiation of Ynsfran’s remarks
                    and stated that if the same were not forthcoming the Government of Bolivia could
                    only believe that the Government of Paraguay approved them, and consequently
                    would be obliged to suspend diplomatic relations. The Minister insisted that the
                    note contained no threat but simply a warning, and that Bolivia did not have the
                    slightest desire to break diplomatic relations but was compelled to protect its
                    national honor.</p>
                <p>[I?] then made a personal suggestion that with the renewal of the offer of the
                    neutral nations the present difficulty perhaps could be settled through those
                    channels. The Minister said that the Papal Nuncio had already tendered his good
                    offices to that end and that it would be appropriate to consider the
                    advisability of having recourse to the neutral nations only in case the impasse
                    continued and his efforts failed.…</p>
                <p>It is reported that there is a distinct cleavage in high Government circles, one
                    group being aggressive and the Qther conciliatory, so, unless the aggressive
                    group takes control of the situation, it is likely that the Bolivian reply,
                    which is scheduled to be delivered tomorrow, may be of a nature to render it
                    possible for Paraguay to give satisfaction for the Ynsfran statements. Public
                    opinion is indifferent and there are no demonstrations. Except for <hi
                        rend="italic">La Nation</hi> and <hi rend="italic">La Republica</hi> this
                    morning’s press did not comment editorially. Yesterday <hi rend="italic">El
                        Diario</hi> criticized the Government’s policy. <hi rend="italic">La
                        Nation</hi>, which is close to the Foreign Office, stated that it [thought?]
                    the Government of Bolivia had no other recourse but to withdraw its Minister
                    from Paraguay. Should that be the case it is believed that a Chargé will be left
                    so as to prevent a rupture of diplomatic relations.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Trueblood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
