<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-06-27T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-06-27T15:00:00-05:00" n="58" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00R296/4179: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Edge</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-06-27T21:00:00+01:00">June 27, 1931—9
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received June 28—12:37 a.m.<note n="81" xml:id="d58fn81">Telegram in five
                                    sections.</note>]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>365. It was not possible to obtain an interview before our meeting at
                                3 o’clock owing to the fact that the Cabinet did not get away from
                                    <pb facs="0200" n="86" xml:id="pg_86"/> the Chamber of Deputies
                                until this morning at 6 o’clock. We opened the discussion with a
                                strong presentation of the points set forth in sections 1 to 5 of
                                your telegram No. 289 of June 26, 6 p.m. We met with the
                                unsatisfactory responses which have been previously outlined and
                                some added comments which were evoked by last night’s attacks in
                                Parliament.</p>
                            <p>When it was found that we had reached an impasse so far as accepting
                                either President Hoover’s original proposal or the French reply as a
                                whole, we attempted to find some way out. The French representatives
                                expressed clearly their view that we could find a way out. The
                                proposal which follows emerged after 2 hours of discussion. We
                                agreed to submit it to you for comment before the meeting which we
                                will hold at 10:30 on Monday, June 29. The understanding is that the
                                suggestion is completely confidential and does not bind either
                                Government as to a final decision.</p>
                            <p>The proposal in substance is that France will place at the disposal
                                of the Bank for International Settlements, as the monthly
                                unconditional payments are made by Germany for 1931–32, a sum equal
                                to the French share of the unconditional annuities. The Bank, in
                                accordance with its statutes, will then apply this sum to loans made
                                available to Germany. France, however, wants to have one-fifth of
                                this money applied to loans to other countries of Central Europe,
                                with those countries which will suffer hardships from the
                                postponement of the Young Plan receiving priority.</p>
                            <p>On July 1, 1932, the money loaned by the Bank will be repayable, but
                                for 4 years the complete repayment will be adjourned. Repayment will
                                be made gradually by monthly payments in the last 3 years amounting
                                to one-third of the total annually and drawing interest as of July
                                1, 1932. This postponement of payment is made on the assumption that
                                Germany before this date will not have declared a moratorium. If
                                Germany declares a moratorium between July 1, 1932, and July 1,
                                1936, then the loans in question will be called, but France will use
                                the money thus called in to establish the guarantee fund for which
                                the Young Plan provides.<note n="82" xml:id="d58fn82">See Great
                                    Britain, Cmd. 3343 (1929), Annex VIII, p. 65.</note> According
                                to an understanding with Flandin the interest rate should not be
                                greater than 5 percent.</p>
                            <p>This proposal involves a series of compromises by the French. The
                                French originally asked for the commencement of monthly payments in
                                the second year to be completed by the end of the third year and for
                                interest to begin at the end of the first year. The proposal which I
                                have outlined above was drawn up by Flandin at the end of the
                                meeting when we made it clear that we could neither accept nor
                                recommend the original French suggestions. We agreed to submit the
                                new <pb facs="0201" n="87" xml:id="pg_87"/> proposal confidentially.
                                It will be noted by the Department that there is reference to the
                                fact that the money loaned by the Bank for International Settlements
                                is to be loaned in accordance with the Bank’s statutes. This means
                                that the loans will not be-for the aid of the German Government
                                budget but must be for the benefit of the German economy. The French
                                demand is likewise expressed that one-fifth of the unconditional
                                payments which are turned over by France to the Bank should be
                                loaned to Central European countries other than Germany and with a
                                special priority for those countries which the temporary suspension
                                of the Young Plan will embarrass financially. Laval particularly
                                insisted upon this point in the way of his [omission] in Parliament
                                and also because he believed that it was not wise to allow Germany
                                to continue payments to those countries or to allow the use of any
                                of this money to finance dumping or armaments. The Government of
                                France is most anxious to reach agreement with Germany on these
                                matters. Therefore the French are particularly anxious to have
                                Bruening visit Paris as soon as possible. It was pointed out for our
                                part that our Government could not take part in these political
                                matters nor in any circumstances be expected to pass on them. Our
                                position was completely understood, and if and when the German
                                Chancellor comes to Paris there will be no tripartite meetings of
                                our three nations. Any conversations that might take place would be
                                between two Powers at a time. Thus there would be avoided both the
                                criticism of the French Parliament that our Government was dictating
                                to France and the criticism that our Government was entering into
                                political spheres in Europe in addition to purely economic matters.
                                It is our understanding that the French are willing to credit
                                payments in kind against the unconditional annuities. Payments in
                                kind, in other words, would bring about a reduction of the
                                unconditional payments.</p>
                            <p>A communiqué was prepared at the end of the meeting and, since it was
                                believed that the whole of the proceedings should remain
                                confidential, the communiqué merely stated that a discussion had
                                taken place and that some progress had been made although no
                                conclusions had been reached.</p>
                            <p>It was only when the meeting had neared a breaking point that we were
                                able to secure a definite understanding from the French that only
                                one-fifth of the unconditional payments going to France would be
                                made available as loans to countries other than Germany. This
                                amounts to about one-sixth of the total of the unconditional
                                annuities arising from the loans to [<hi rend="italic">payments
                                    from?</hi>] Germany during the Hoover year.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Edge</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>