<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-07-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-07-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="643" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d643">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">738.3915/429</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in the Dominican Republic</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Curtis</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-07-13">July 13,
                                    1931</date>.<lb/>[Received July 22.]</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 436</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my despatch No. 412 of
                                June 8, 1931,<note n="6" xml:id="d643fn6">Not printed.</note>
                                regarding friction between the Dominican and Haitian Governments due
                                to frontier incidents, I have the honor to transmit herewith a copy
                                and <pb facs="0890" n="776" xml:id="pg_776"/> translation of the
                                memorandum which I stated had been promised me by the Dominican
                                Secretary for Foreign Affairs.</p>
                            <p>The contents of this memorandum and its enclosures serve to indicate
                                that the Dominican Government has endeavored sincerely to obtain a
                                final demarcation of the frontier line at the point where the most
                                recent friction has arisen and that the Haitian Government has
                                steadily refused to proceed with the further work of demarcation,
                                giving no valid reason for this refusal.</p>
                            <p>In this connection, it may be mentioned that the local newspapers
                                report an interview obtained by one of the subordinate editors of
                                    <hi rend="italic">La Opinion</hi> with President Vincent of
                                Haiti. In the course of this interview, President Vincent is
                                reported to have said that Haiti would welcome the negotiation of an
                                agreement to arbitrate, as provided in Article 18 of the
                                Dominican-Haitian Frontier Treaty of January 21, 1929. The Dominican
                                Secretary for Foreign Affairs, discussing the matter with me
                                informally, has indicated that the position of the Dominican
                                Government is that recourse should first be had to the Mixed
                                Commission of five members provided in Article 7.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">C. B. Curtis</hi></signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation<note n="7" xml:id="d643fn7">File translation
                                    revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Dominican Ministry
                                            for Foreign Affairs</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American Legation</gloss></hi></head>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi></p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>On January 21, 1929, there was signed in Santo Domingo the
                                        Dominican-Haitian frontier treaty for the purpose of
                                        “putting a definitive end to the differences” which have in
                                        the past separated the Dominican Republic and Haiti
                                        “regarding the demarcation of the frontier line which
                                        separates their respective territories”. (See annex No.
                                            1.)<note n="8" xml:id="d643fn8">None of the annexes
                                            mentioned in this memorandum are printed; for text of
                                            the treaty of January 21, 1929, see League of Nations
                                            Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cv</hi>, p.
                                            193.</note></item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>This treaty was approved by the National Congress of the
                                        Dominican Republic on February 7, and by the Haitian Council
                                        of State on February 15, 1929; it was ratified by the
                                        President of the Dominican Republic on February 25, 1929,
                                        and by the President of the Republic of Haiti on February
                                        11. The exchange of ratifications took place in the city of
                                        Santo Domingo on April 29, 1929.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>In accordance with the provisions of the third article of
                                        the treaty, the Dominican-Haitian Boundary Delimitation
                                        Commission <pb facs="0891" n="777" xml:id="pg_777"/> was
                                        established by means of two decrees, one issued on May 14 by
                                        the President of the Dominican Republic to designate the
                                        members of the Dominican Section, and the other issued May
                                        15 by the President of the Republic of Haiti to designate
                                        the members of the Haitian Section.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>In July the Department of Foreign Affairs of the Dominican
                                        Republic notified the Departments of Foreign Affairs of the
                                        United States of America, of Venezuela, and of Brazil, that
                                        the seventh article of the treaty provided for the creation
                                        of a mixed commission to decide finally all difficulties
                                        which might arise in the execution of the treaty and upon
                                        which the High Contracting Parties should be unable to
                                            agree.<note n="9" xml:id="d643fn9">See note No. 295,
                                            July 9, 1929, from the Dominican Minister for Foreign
                                            Affairs, <ref target="frus1929v01#pg_945"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1929, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 945</ref>.</note>
                                        The Chancelleries of those three countries notified the
                                        Department of Foreign Affairs that their governments
                                        accepted the charge which this article of the treaty
                                        attributed to them.<note n="10" xml:id="d643fn10">See note
                                            of August 21, 1929, to the Dominican Minister for
                                            Foreign Affairs, <ref target="frus1929v01#pg_946"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p.
                                        946</ref>.</note></item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>By action of the Dominican Government, the treaty was
                                        registered with the Secretary General of the League of
                                        Nations on August 7, 1930, in accordance with the provisions
                                        of article 18 of the Pact of the League of Nations.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>From all the foregoing, it is seen in an incontrovertible
                                        manner that the Dominican Government performed with
                                        painstaking diligence all the acts necessary to insure the
                                        execution and validity of the treaty.</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>The Dominican-Haitian Frontier Delimitation Commission
                                        held its preliminary sessions, all the members of both
                                        sections being present, in Comendador and Veladero on May 16
                                        and 17, 1929, to decide upon the plan of action by which the
                                        work of demarcation should be carried out, and as a result
                                        of these deliberations there was drafted and signed on May
                                        17 an instrument called the Protocol of Comendador-Veladero
                                        which, with the approval of both Governments, has been in
                                        force without modification during all the process of the
                                        execution of the provisions of the treaty. (See annex No.
                                        2.)</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>On June 1, 1929, the Delimitation Commission held a full
                                        meeting at Dajabón to verify the full powers of its members,
                                        and on June 2, to approve the Comendador-Veladero Protocol
                                        and begin the work of demarcation. Minutes of these meetings
                                        were made in the form established by the third article of
                                        the treaty, and the minutes of the later meetings were also
                                        kept in similar form up to the minute numbered 91, of
                                        December 2, 1930, which is the last.</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>An examination of these minutes shows: <list>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>That for the work of demarcation the frontier line
                                                was divided into six zones; that the work of three
                                                zones was to be carried out by the Haitian Section
                                                under the inspection of a Dominican Commissioner,
                                                  <pb facs="0892" n="778" xml:id="pg_778"/> and that
                                                the work of the other three zones was to be carried
                                                out by the Dominican Section under the inspection of
                                                a Haitian Commissioner;</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>That in the course of the work five difficulties
                                                have arisen, as enumerated in minute No. 89 of
                                                October 28, 1930. (See annex No. 3.)</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>That the Dominican Section has completed entirely,
                                                including the erection of boundary posts, all the
                                                work assigned to it in the sectors where there has
                                                been agreement; and,</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>That the Haitian Section stopped its work in the
                                                sectors where there was agreement and which were
                                                assigned to it in accordance with the distribution
                                                made of the work.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>10.</label>
                                    <item>As to this last point (the stoppage of the work of the
                                        Haitian Section in the sectors where there was agreement),
                                        we must insist upon making the following explanations. As
                                        can be seen in minute No. 91 (annex No. 4), the Delimitation
                                        Commission, at its meeting in San Juan on December 2, signed
                                        seven plans made by the Haitian Section covering the sectors
                                        between Tête-à-l’Eau and the mouth of the Pédernales River
                                        and between Mare Citron and Gros Mare, and agreed that the
                                        Haitian Section should finish the work which it had pending
                                        in the sectors where there was agreement. The foregoing
                                        notwithstanding, on December 27 the President of the Haitian
                                        Section sent written notice to the President of the
                                        Dominican Section that, in spite of what was established in
                                        minute No. 91, the Haitian Section could not continue the
                                        construction of the boundary posts because such was the
                                        decision of its Government. (See annex No. 5.)</item>
                                    <label>11.</label>
                                    <item>Due to this, in compliance with orders of the Dominican
                                        Government, the Dominican Legation in Port-au-Prince
                                        addressed to the Department of Foreign Relations of Haiti a
                                        note setting forth substantially the following: That the
                                        Dominican Government had received with profound surprise the
                                        notice of the stoppage of this work, a surprise which had
                                        been accentuated by the consideration that the stoppage,
                                        according to the statement of the President of the Haitian
                                        Section, was due to orders of the Haitian Government; that
                                        the Dominican Government not only desired an explanation of
                                        the motives for this grave decision but invited the Haitian
                                        Government to order that this and other work pending with
                                        the Haitian Section be resumed at the earliest possible
                                        moment.</item>
                                    <label>12.</label>
                                    <item>This note was deposited on January 22, 1931, with the
                                        Haitian Department of Foreign Affairs, which answered it on
                                        March 5, stating that the order to suspend this work had not
                                        been given by the Haitian Government, which was most
                                        favorably disposed toward the conclusion of the work. (See
                                        annexes 6 and 7.)</item>
                                    <label>13.</label>
                                    <item>Although it is difficult to believe that a step of such
                                        importance could have been taken freely by the President of
                                        the Haitian Section in contradiction of the agreements which
                                        he, acting within his powers, had signed in minute No. 91,
                                        it is a fact that the Haitian <pb facs="0893" n="779" xml:id="pg_779"/> Government denied having given such an
                                        order to Engineer L. Roy, whose statement it contradicted;
                                        but, on the other hand, the Haitian Government did not state
                                        when the work would be resumed nor, up to the present time,
                                        has it ordered its resumption, notwithstanding the cordial
                                        requests which the Dominican Government has subsequently
                                        made.</item>
                                    <label>14.</label>
                                    <item>From all of the foregoing, it is seen in an
                                        incontrovertible manner that the Dominican Government has
                                        shown permanent and vigorous good will in the execution of
                                        the frontier treaty, faithfully complying with all its
                                        obligations and encouraging the Haitian Government, by all
                                        the means at its disposal, to behave in the same way.</item>
                                    <label>15.</label>
                                    <item>After making this categorical statement, based on facts
                                        truly set forth in this Memorandum, we must call attention
                                        to the fact that, in order to avoid prolixity, we have
                                        omitted the relation of an endless number of facts and
                                        circumstances which arose in the course of the work of
                                        demarcation, in all of which the Dominican Government not
                                        only complied with its obligations but also amply assisted
                                        the Haitian Government in complying with its
                                        obligations.</item>
                                    <label>16.</label>
                                    <item>Nevertheless, it will be well to mention a declaration of
                                        Engineer Roy, that in which he states that, owing to the
                                        excitement noticed among the inhabitants of Tête-à-l’Eau due
                                        to the course which the line was to follow, he had stopped
                                        the work of demarcation assigned to the Haitian Section in
                                        that region. In fact, as can be seen in annex No. 8 (note of
                                        August 26, 1930, of the Haitian Legation in Santo Domingo to
                                        the Department of Foreign Affairs of the Dominican
                                        Government), Engineer Roy, President of the Haitian Section
                                        of the Frontier Delimitation Commission, stopped during that
                                        month the demarcation work assigned to the Haitian Section
                                        and so notified his Government, which, in its turn, so
                                        informed the Dominican Government by means of the note
                                        referred to. It is important to note that the motives
                                        adduced for the stoppage of the work did not really exist
                                        (see annex No. 9), and that the excitement of the Haitian
                                        residents of those sections must have been due to other
                                        causes which have nothing to do with the Dominican
                                        authorities; and, moreover, that if these things had taken
                                        place, they should not have caused the stoppage of the work
                                        of demarcation. From that note, it is clearly seen also
                                        that, contrary to what the Haitian Chancellery declares in
                                        its note of March 5 (annex No. 6), the Haitian Government
                                        knew as early as August 1930 that the work of its section
                                        had been stopped, a step which, if it was not ordered by the
                                        Haitian Government, at least has been continued by it in
                                        spite of the insistence with which it has been invited to
                                        resume and finish that work.</item>
                                    <label>17.</label>
                                    <item>Similar excitement was produced among Dominican citizens
                                        in the Bánica region but, nevertheless, the Dominican
                                        Government did not stop the work assigned to its section,
                                        because it knew that the line <pb facs="0894" n="780" xml:id="pg_780"/> of January 21, 1929, would deviate at
                                        times to the west and at other times to the east of the
                                        existing frontier line, and because it was confident that
                                        the Dominican proprietors whose fields passed into Haitian
                                        territory would enjoy in the Haitian State all the
                                        protection of the law, in the same manner as all those
                                        proprietors whose fields passed into Dominican territory, by
                                        virtue of the new frontier line, would enjoy the protection
                                        of the law in the Dominican Republic.</item>
                                    <label>18.</label>
                                    <item>But if the Haitian Government has shown little diligence
                                        in the execution of the provisions of the treaty of January
                                        21, it has, on the other hand, thought itself authorized to
                                        go and occupy lands which have been and are Dominican, and
                                        which will continue to be such by virtue of the stipulations
                                        of the treaty. And it has gone and occupied, moreover, lands
                                        which are now Dominican but will change and become Haitian
                                        by virtue of the treaty, without taking into account, as has
                                        been shown by the Dominican Government, that until the work
                                        of demarcation is finished and accepted by both governments,
                                        the armed forces and the civil authorities must not act
                                        beyond the limits fixed for them respectively by the present
                                        frontier line.</item>
                                    <label>19.</label>
                                    <item>These extra-limitations, encouraged or tolerated by the
                                        Haitian Government, which in this case means the same thing,
                                        have been the cause of endless frontier incidents which
                                        occurred mostly in 1930 and up to the present in 1931, and,
                                        although it has not been shown that the Dominican
                                        authorities have indulged in those extra-limitations, the
                                        Dominican Government has wished to attribute them to the
                                        confusion which may have arisen on the part of Haitian and
                                        Dominican officials as to what is the line that they must
                                        take into consideration as regards their duties; and, in
                                        order to put an end to these difficulties, it has invited
                                        the Haitian Government (annex No. 9), to order its troops
                                        and its authorities to abstain from acting in places other
                                        than those where they did so prior to January 21,
                                        1929.</item>
                                    <label>20.</label>
                                    <item>That invitation has been unproductive, for not only have
                                        the Haitian forces continued to dispatch patrols into
                                        Dominican territory and the Haitian civil authorities
                                        continued to carry on various activities within our
                                        territory, but they have also established sentry posts in
                                        certain Dominican points such as Tierra Fría de Mallín,
                                        Banano, etc., and have occupied Dominican sections such as
                                        those of Federico, Masogoy, etc.</item>
                                    <label>21.</label>
                                    <item>After many months of useless requests made by the
                                        Dominican Government to the Haitian Government that the
                                        latter order the completion of the work of demarcation
                                        assigned to it and that, meanwhile, it abstain from
                                        performing acts of sovereignty in Dominican territory, the
                                        Dominican Government has found that the Haitian Government,
                                        ignoring these just requests, has established those sentry
                                        posts <pb facs="0895" n="781" xml:id="pg_781"/> which are
                                        mentioned in the previous paragraph, and has occupied
                                        various Dominican sections.</item>
                                    <label>22.</label>
                                    <item>In view of these grave circumstances, the Dominican
                                        Government gave orders to the Dominican Legation at
                                        Port-au-Prince to address to the Department of Foreign
                                        Affairs a note containing the following: That the Dominican
                                        Government is informed that in the Dominican section of
                                        Tierra Fría de Mallín, a Haitian sentry post is operating;
                                        that the Garde d’Haiti, making use of plans and reports
                                        furnished to its headquarters by Engineer L. Roy, has tried
                                        to take possession of Dominican points such as Tierra Fría
                                        de Mallín, Federico, and yet others, and the Haitian
                                        authorities are frequently penetrating into Dominican
                                        territory to patrol it, reconnoiter, etc.; that, in view of
                                        this, the Dominican Government calls the attention of the
                                        Haitian Government to the fact that these acts constitute
                                        grave violations of the respect due to the existing frontier
                                        line and invites it to issue immediately the orders
                                        necessary for the withdrawal from Tierra Fría de Mallín of
                                        the sentry post which is there and for the abstention of the
                                        Haitian authorities from penetrating into Dominican
                                        territory; that the Dominican Government informs the Haitian
                                        Government that it has ordered the National Army to oppose
                                        every violation of the frontier line which may be attempted
                                        by the Haitians, leaving to the Haitian Government the
                                        responsibility for the unfortunate events which may take
                                        place if the latter does not pay attention to this request;
                                        that the Dominican Government sincerely laments that it is
                                        compelled to insist to the Haitian Government upon the
                                        necessity that the latter maintain its forces within the
                                        limits set by the existing frontier line; that the Dominican
                                        Government, in view of the fact that the work of the Haitian
                                        Section has been officially stopped, has notified the Chargé
                                        d’Affaires a. i. to oppose the activities in which said
                                        Section desires to engage in Dominican territory until he
                                        receives information from the Dominican Government that such
                                        work may be permitted; that the Dominican Government again
                                        invites the Haitian Government to order the conclusion of
                                        the work which the Haitian Section has pending;
                                        and—finally—that the Dominican Government reiterates to the
                                        Haitian Government the assurances of its firm friendship and
                                        unvarying disposition to seek that the harmonious relations
                                        between both peoples be daily intensified. (See annex No.
                                        10.)</item>
                                    <label>23.</label>
                                    <item>This note was presented to the Haitian Chancellery on May
                                        19, and, when the Dominican Government expected that the
                                        Haitian Government, recognizing the absolute justice and
                                        truth of everything requested and stated in it, would order
                                        withdrawal from the territory improperly occupied and would
                                        hasten to renew the fulfillment of the obligations imposed
                                        by the treaty of January 21, it received confidential <pb facs="0896" n="782" xml:id="pg_782"/> advice that 200
                                        Haitian soldiers were marching toward the frontier on May
                                        29, 1931.</item>
                                    <label>24.</label>
                                    <item>The attitude of the Dominican Government toward this news
                                        was that which is shown by the following telegram addressed
                                        to our Legation in Port-au-Prince: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                            <p>“Dominican Legation, Port-au-Prince. Dominican
                                                Government surprised attitude Haitian Government
                                                sending troops frontiers, the Frontier Treaty being
                                                in execution and the Treaty Peace, Amity of February
                                                  20<note n="11" xml:id="d643fn11">Signed February
                                                  20, 1929, League of Nations Treaty Series, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">cv</hi>, p. 215.</note> being
                                                in force, since Dominican Government assures
                                                categorically not having committed any act
                                                justifying such despatch troops. Dominican
                                                Government is disposed to defend integrity national
                                                territory, but hopes that all the difficulties can
                                                be solved by pacific and cordial means by both
                                                Governments. Ask explanations Haitian Chancellery
                                                and transmit them urgently”.</p>
                                        </quote></item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>When our Chargé d’Affaires a. i. in Port-au-Prince
                                        requested these explanations, the Secretary of State for
                                        Foreign Affairs of Haiti answered that he knew nothing about
                                        the matter. Nevertheless, it is true that those 200 soldiers
                                        marched to reinforce the frontier.</item>
                                    <label>25.</label>
                                    <item>It is significant that the same day that these troops were
                                        mobilized, the Haitian Chancellery, in answer to the note of
                                        the 19th, delivered to our Legation in Port-au-Prince a note
                                        containing the following: That the note of the 19th had
                                        disagreeably surprised the Haitian Government in view of the
                                        efforts which it had been making to increase cordiality
                                        between the two countries; that the new Secretary of State
                                        for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Au. Leger), had assumed the
                                        portfolio only a few days before but would examine the
                                        frontier dossier in order to inform the Dominican Legation
                                        in Port-au-Prince of the point of view of the Haitian
                                        Government concerning the question which is the subject of
                                        the note under reply; and that the Haitian Government hopes
                                        that the Dominican Government will not permit the acts of
                                        hostility announced in that note, which would be contrary to
                                        the amity which the Dominican Government affirms.</item>
                                    <label>26.</label>
                                    <item>It is clear that the Haitian Government has avoided
                                        reference to the concrete points enumerated in the note of
                                        May 19, that it has not ordered its forces to retire from
                                        the points improperly occupied, and that it considers as an
                                        announcement of acts of hostility the statement that the
                                        Dominican Government has ordered the army to prevent any new
                                        violation of the frontier line and any unauthorized act of
                                        the Haitian Section of the Delimitation Commission.</item>
                                    <label>27.</label>
                                    <item>To summarize, the Haitian Government has received
                                        notification from the Dominican Government inviting it to
                                        withdraw from land improperly occupied, not to permit its
                                        armed forces and its civil <pb facs="0897" n="783" xml:id="pg_783"/> authorities to continue violating the
                                        frontier line, to resume compliance with the obligations
                                        imposed by the treaty of January 21, and to take note of the
                                        fact that the Dominican Government has given orders to its
                                        army to prevent any violation of the frontier line; and, in
                                        the face of this notification, the Haitian Government has
                                        not withdrawn its forces from the points improperly
                                        occupied, has offered no explanation regarding the basic
                                        points of the matter, and has considered as an announcement
                                        of acts of hostility the fact that the Dominican Government
                                        has ordered its army to oppose every new violation of the
                                        frontier line.</item>
                                    <label>28.</label>
                                    <item>From all the foregoing it appears, likewise in an
                                        incontrovertible manner, that while the Dominican Government
                                        has complied with all the obligations which it assumed by
                                        the treaty of January 21, and has sought to preserve and
                                        promote, on the basis of reciprocal respect, the existing
                                        Dominican-Haitian relations,—the Haitian Government has
                                        abandoned compliance with the obligations which it assumed
                                        by that treaty, has committed and is committing grave
                                        violations of the frontier line to the prejudice of the
                                        Dominicans, and has revealed ostensibly its design to
                                        persist in such an attitude, without any indication that it
                                        has given any heed to the just demands of the Dominican
                                        Government or the solemnity of international treaties which
                                        it has signed with this Republic for the purpose of putting
                                        a definitive end to the frontier question and for
                                        maintaining with it loyal amity.</item>
                                    <label>29.</label>
                                    <item>Just now, while the present memorandum is being drafted,
                                        the Dominican Government receives notice that the Haitian
                                        forces have continued to occupy Dominican territory in the
                                        frontier region. Therefore, nothing can be more grave than
                                        the situation created by the Haitian Government for the
                                        Dominican Government, whose obligation to preserve,
                                        conserve, and retain the national territory, is a supreme
                                        obligation which cannot be abandoned for any reason and in
                                        defense of which it has the unavoidable duty of making every
                                        sacrifice.</item>
                                    <label>30.</label>
                                    <item>Consequently, the Dominican Government considers that the
                                        only method of avoiding the occurrence of the friction which
                                        the Haitian Government is provoking is compliance by the
                                        latter with the request which has been made to it that it
                                        withdraw from the land of which it has improperly taken
                                        possession.</item>
                                    <label>31.</label>
                                    <item>For the Dominican Government, which has given and is
                                        giving the highest evidence of its desires to maintain peace
                                        with the Republic of Haiti, it will be painful to be obliged
                                        to resort to extremes to defend and retain its territory in
                                        compliance with the most sacred of its duties. And it will
                                        be yet more so that the United States should become involved
                                        in this friction, as is to be deduced from the text of the
                                        telegram sent by the State Department to the Legation in
                                        Santo Domingo, <pb facs="0898" n="784" xml:id="pg_784"/> in
                                        accordance with which “any act of aggression against the
                                        (Haitian) Garde would consequently be a matter of immediate
                                        and grave interest” to the American Government.<note n="12" xml:id="d643fn12">See telegram No. 20, May 29, 2 p.m.,
                                            to the Minister in the Dominican Republic, <ref target="#pg_771">p. 771</ref>.</note></item>
                                    <label>32.</label>
                                    <item>Consequently, if the mediation initiated by the American
                                        Government does not result in the Haitian Government paying
                                        attention to the just requests which have been made to it to
                                        abandon the lands of which it has improperly taken
                                        possession, the Dominican Government hopes that the American
                                        Government will not permit officers of the American Army to
                                        oppose the action which the Dominican Army may take in favor
                                        of national integrity, in compliance with an unwaivable
                                        patriotic mandate.</item>
                                    <label>33.</label>
                                    <item>This is the proper moment to call attention to the fact
                                        that high officers of the Army and Navy of the United States
                                        of America have had occasion to proclaim the justice of the
                                        Dominican view of the frontier question, and especially of
                                        the effort which it has made to have Haiti respect the line
                                        of the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi>, marked in 1912, by
                                        the 2nd Division of the General Staff of the War Department
                                        in Washington,<note n="13" xml:id="d643fn13">See <ref target="frus1912#pg_368"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                                  Relations</hi>, 1912, p. 368</ref>.</note> by
                                        virtue of the mediation solicited by Haiti and accepted by
                                        the Dominican Republic. (See Annexes 11 and 12, Memorandum
                                        of August 11, 1919, of Colonel Rufus H. Lane to the Military
                                        Governor, and note of Colonel A. T. Marix, in charge of the
                                        Department for Foreign Affairs of the Dominican Republic, to
                                        the Minister of Haiti in Santo Domingo, on April 12,
                                        1921.)</item>
                                    <label>34.</label>
                                    <item>Finally, the Dominican Government expresses the wish that
                                        the mediation of the American Government be directed to the
                                        end that the Haitian Government resume compliance with the
                                        obligations which it assumed by the treaty of January 21,
                                        1929, to the end that the execution thereof be terminated,
                                        and that the old and troublesome frontier controversy be
                                        ended.</item>
                                </list>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>