<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-03-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="677" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d677">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">150.071 Control/32</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State of a
                                Conversation With the British Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lindsay</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-03-03">March 3, 1931</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>During the call of the British Ambassador this morning, he brought up the
                            subject of the pending shipping bill (S. 202) about which he was very
                            much troubled. He told me that one of its provisions permitted ships to
                            be searched and if any sailors were found who were aliens not qualified
                            to become citizens of this country they must be <pb facs="0933" n="819" xml:id="pg_819"/> seized and deported. He said that this provision
                            would prevent every British ship from touching at our Pacific Coast
                            ports, because these ships always had among their crews many Lascars and
                            Chinese.</p>
                        <p>I then told him that the Secretary of Labor had brought up this question
                            at the last Cabinet meeting and the President had expressed himself in
                            favor of the bill, and pursuant to his direction I had told the
                            Committee so; that after a talk with Mr. Johnson<note n="33" xml:id="d677fn33">Senator Hiram W. Johnson, of California.</note> of
                            the Committee who had pointed out what I believed to be the same section
                            of the bill (Section 7) which the Ambassador referred to as affecting
                            our Pacific Coast ports, I had directed Mr. Flournoy<note n="34" xml:id="d677fn34">Richard W. Flournoy, Jr., Assistant to the
                                Solicitor.</note> to try to amend this bill so as to be
                            unobjectionable in that way. I tried to get Mr. Flournoy on the
                            telephone but he was at the Capitol and could not be reached. I called
                            up the Secretary of Labor while the Ambassador was still here and he
                            told me he believed the bill had been amended so as to reach this
                            provision. I reported this to the Ambassador and he went away.</p>
                        <closer><signed>H[<hi rend="smallcaps">enry</hi>] L. S[<hi rend="smallcaps">timson</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>