<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Austria ( (Washburn) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d706</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">706</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-02-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-02-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-02-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-02-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="706"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d706">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.632/54</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Austria</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Washburn</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-02-26">February 26,
                            1929</date>.<lb/>[Received March 16.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2122</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my telegram No. 1 of February 7th,
                    11 a.m., and to the Department’s telegrams No. 2 of February 8th, 1 p.m.,<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d706fn3">Neither printed.</note> and No. 3 of February 12th, 6
                    p.m., I have the honor to report that the news that the Senate had given its
                    advice and consent to the ratification of the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and
                    Consular Rights with Austria subject to a reservation caused a visible, if
                    temporary, annoyance in the Austrian Foreign Office. The proposal to limit the
                    term of the sixth paragraph of Article VII in a manner similar to that in the
                    Commercial Treaty with Germany was not at first understood here, especially as
                    it was immediately recalled that Article XXV in the draft form as agreed upon
                    provided for the special termination of the sixth paragraph of Article VII in
                    accordance with the German Treaty precedent. The amendment to Article XXV was
                    made at the last moment, it will be remembered, at my suggestion pursuant to
                    instructions received in the Department’s telegram No. 29 of June 5th, 1928, 4
                        p.m.,<note n="4" xml:id="d706fn4">
                        <ref target="frus1928v01#pg_994">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1928, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 994</ref>.</note> where, <hi
                        rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, it was said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Department has altered policy toward Senate reservation to Article VII
                            of German Treaty and is signing treaty with another country including
                            provision for the national treatment of shipping obligatory for full
                            term of treaty. Department would prefer to have all treaties submitted
                            to the Senate the next session uniform in this respect.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The Foreign Office here, including the Chancellor, with whom I talked yesterday,
                    now understand and appreciate the situation fully.</p>
                <p>There were two factors that contributed to the Government’s discomfort: (1) the
                    necessity of laying this matter <hi rend="italic">de novo</hi> before a Cabinet
                    Council and going to Parliament again to receive sanction for the alteration,
                    inasmuch as under the Austrian constitutional system no change can be made in a
                    treaty without parliamentary sanction, just as with us the advice and consent of
                    the Senate are required; (2) there has been some apprehension that the
                    Opposition may criticise the Government for not having anticipated this
                    difficulty. This fear still exists and if it proves to be well founded, the
                    Government can only answer that the difficulty was foreseen and provided for;
                    that the Treaty was altered at the last moment at our suggestion; and that
                    apparently the State Department and the Senate were not in full accord on this
                    matter. The point is not overlooked here that one-third of the Senate can defeat
                    ratification and that <pb facs="0963" n="849" xml:id="pg_849"/> concessions must
                    be made to a very considerable minority. It has been pointed out to me that if
                    the original provision had been retained it would probably have passed through
                    Parliament without attracting the slightest attention or comment. Now attention
                    must be focused upon this exception and there may be some unpleasantness. It is
                    hoped however that the ways may be smoothed before hand, but much will depend
                    upon the parliamentary temper at the moment. At all events there is likely to be
                    a delay of some weeks which the Government would have preferred to have avoided.
                    I fear the disposition may be in future to await action by the Senate before
                    taking parliamentary action here. In any case the necessity of embroidering the
                    Treaty effected through an exchange of notes is deplored here. It was referred
                    to by one of the Ministers at the Foreign Office as a “Schönheitsfehler”—in
                    other words, a blemish.</p>
                <p>Awaiting the more definite instructions forecasted in the final paragraph of the
                    Department’s before-mentioned telegram No. 3,</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert H. Washburn</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
